All right, looks like we can begin, so welcome.
And I will tell you about my project which is called Chimera Linux.
But first let me introduce myself a bit.
I'm a software developer from the Czech Republic.
I've been contributing to open source software since 2007.
And currently I'm on a break from work, so I'm kind of working on the distro full time.
When I'm not on a break for work, I work in the WebKit team in Iglia.
Previously I also used to work for Samsung in the open source group where I worked on
the Enlightenment Foundation libraries and the Window Manager.
Since 2009 I've been using FreeBSD, also on desktop for about ten years.
But I've not been using that on desktop since about 2018 because I've been mostly using
power architecture computers these days which FreeBSD doesn't have the greatest support
for.
So for example, my GPU wouldn't work.
I'm also a former developer of the Void Linux distribution which has served as a huge inspiration
for this project, especially in the design of the packaging system.
And I sort of do all sorts of things besides distribution development.
I also do, for example, game development, compiler stuff.
I did some kernel bits as well.
But now what's Chimera Linux?
It's a new Linux distribution which I started in 2021.
And it's a general purpose distribution created from scratch.
It utilizes core tools from FreeBSD which is one of the big differences from standard
distributions which is GNU tools for this or Busybox for example.
It uses the LLVM toolchain to compile all the packages.
As a matter of fact, there's currently no GCC in the distribution other than for some
variants of U-Boot for specific ARM devices.
It uses the muscle Lipsi and it's a rolling release distribution so there are no releases.
It sort of updates continuously.
And it's also highly portable to many architectures.
Right now we are supporting Arch 64, Power, Little Indian, soon there will be PowerBigIndian,
X8664 as well as complete full support for RISC-5 64-bit.
I started this project in early mid-2021 and it started with C-Build which is sort of a
meta-build system for packages.
You create your packaging templates and these basically describe the package and how to
build it and C-Build builds it.
I also void Linux developer at this time and I started C-Build as a way to investigate
if I can fix many of the shortcomings of void Linux's Xbps SRC system.
So I've created a quick distribution around C-Build which consisted of GCC and GNU user
runs as well as the Xbps package manager which you avoid to use this.
At this point it was only about 50 packaging templates.
So it was very tiny.
It couldn't boot definitely because it had no kernel and no bootloader or init system
even or anything.
So it was just like a little container which was capable of building itself when hosted
on another distribution.
And as I said I was trying to fix many of the issues and main focuses of C-Build have
been performance as well as correctness.
This was when I first managed to make Kaimira boot in VM.
Shortly after those 50 packages switched to LLVM and removal of GCC followed as well as
the switch to FreeBSD tools, removal of the GNU stuff and so on and as well as gradual
expansion of all the packages.
I've been sort of iteratively enhancing the distribution ever since and until it got to
the current state.
In late 2021 it was possible to boot the system and it's capable of bootstrapping itself.
In early 2022 there was a full GNOME desktop already.
This was when I got a Wayland Compositor running and of course everything needs to be able
to run Doom so we got Doom working as a terminal and some other basic stuff but this was I
believe around late 2021.
I had a talk about the distro at FOSDAM 2022 and many things happened during 2022 so last
year I did the talk as a sort of chronological thing.
I'm not going to do that this year because there have been too many things and I couldn't
fit it into a 50 minute slot.
Which focus has been in last year on security hardening and on development of different
new solutions for things which we've been missing.
I'm currently aiming for an alpha release which will be sort of early adapter release
where things will mostly work on desktop.
In late February or early March I plan to make it coincide with one of the betas of
FreeBSD 13.2 in order to be able to rebase the tooling.
Now for some motivations why did I create this project?
I've been unhappy with existing systems.
There are many great things that existing systems have but there's always at least
one thing which has been annoying me so I sort of wanted to create a thing which would
actually suit me in every single way.
I wanted to make a well rounded practical operating system that wouldn't be just a toy
but something people could actually use.
At the same time I would like to improve software in general that is mainly in terms of portability
as well as security when it comes to things like usage of sanitizers and so on.
I would like to make full use of LLVM not just to replace GCC compiler but actually
utilize the unique strengths of LLVM which includes great sanitizer infrastructure, things
like finLTO which GCC still doesn't have and so on.
Of course proving Linux is an under-gnew Linux is also a major thing.
While doing all this I wanted to have some fun and some people on the internet said I
couldn't do this so of course it's important to prove them wrong.
I wanted to build a nice community which would be fun to hang around with and make a good
system for both myself and for other people.
Now for some general principles of the project.
I strongly believe that projects which basically are centered around a single goal are eventually
doomed to fail because once you reach this goal you have nothing else to do but at the
same time it creates dogmatic things which you are not allowed to cross and it really
restricts you with the development.
On the other side of the problem there's scope creep if you have too many things to do and
you keep expanding on it eventually you get to the point where you never get anything
done.
It's important to balance these things.
I think opinion development is overall a good thing because it gives you a sense of direction
which is always nice to have.
I think obviously quality of the code matters but quality of the community matters even
more so.
I think fun is good so I would like to try to keep it that way and not to get too technical
in the process.
I think free and open source software projects are social spaces and that's why if you let
toxic people into your community it's eventually going to become a job for everybody else.
So I try hard to keep them out but at the same time I try to make sure it does not get
overly elitist because it should be an open inclusive project for everybody.
As for technical principles I try to make sure things are strict by default and try
to avoid technical debt at all costs.
There should usually be just one way to do things.
That doesn't mean there only has to be one way but more like a good default that people
are supposed to follow and that's sort of intuitive and easy to follow.
This should remain as simple as possible but not too simple.
There are many people who overly focus on things like minimalist systems and in the
process they end up forgetting what's actually practical.
I think security and hardening is also very important and in many Linux distributions
it's sort of overlooked so that's another thing.
And I think portability is also extremely important.
There are many kinds of hardware and people like using many different kinds of hardware.
Of course most people have their x86 computers but there's more of it than you may think
and things like RISC-V are taking off and there's of course power workstations and there's
ARM and so on so it's good to have all these things.
Now good tooling is also very important and related to that is self-sustainability.
That basically means whatever infrastructure you have should be self-contained and easy
to get going and easy to replicate on any new computer.
Related to that is being able to bootstrap the system from a source code.
I think that's sort of a double-edged sword because some people don't care about bootstrapability
at all and things are massive binaries downloaded from the internet.
On the other side of the coin there's people who insist on complete bootstrapability from
source code for everything even if it involves doing completely cursed things such as ever
seen how to bootstrap the Haskell compiler from a source completely.
It's like if you want to do it and you have to go through an ancient unmaintained Haskell
compiler which only targets 32-bit x86 computers and compile some stuff on NAND and it's from
2004 and then you have to iterate through newer versions.
Eventually you get to GHC and then you can cross-compile a partial distribution for architecture
and then go from that and eventually you reach your goal.
I think it's a means to an end and it's important but not that important.
Another thing is that I've seen over the years many things and I think it's something is
written in shell and it's a complicated program and it probably shouldn't be.
It should be easy to do the right thing but tooling should also make it difficult to do
the bad thing, kind of steer people towards doing what's right and doing so out of the
box.
Documentation is obviously also important and many people avoid writing documentation.
I understand them because I'm also guilty of this in many cases but yeah we should strive
for a good documentation.
There's also the question of systemd.
I believe systemd is in many aspects not great but also it brought necessary change
to Linux and there are basically many people and distributions who just stick their head
into the sand and just avoid even considering that systemd might have brought some useful
things and that it might kind of be also their fault that it has become so widely adopted.
So we should develop good solutions to counter whatever systemd has come up with and basically
always try to improve.
Now let's take a look at how a bsd system is developed.
Usually you have your entire system in a single tree and a single repository typically sbn
and so on and you have lots of different components in this repository.
It's a complete system capable of boot so if you invoke the central makefile and compile
the system you generally compile your kernel and compile your user lines and if you put
it together you will get a system which is capable of booting.
And third party software which is not required for the base system is distributed through
some kind of port system.
Of course this doesn't mean that there are no third party components in a base of the
bsd system because I'm not aware of any bsd system which is developing a complete replacement
for the toolchain for example.
You have your lvm or whatever in base and usually it has its own built system integrated
with the existing makefiles but it's a single tree.
Now let's contrast it to a linux distribution.
In a linux distribution it's a collection of software from many different parties which
are separate packages.
And you have linux kernel as the base layer that's always the case otherwise it wouldn't
be a linux distribution.
You have your user line tooling which is often supplied by GNU and you have the libc which
is also often supplied by GNU glpc.
And you have the toolchain to build all this so it's also from GNU because while client
is used for some distributions not too many of them.
And you have the service manager and also some auxiliary tooling around to the service
manager so that's often system D nowadays.
This is tied together with a package manager which handles installing and removing and
so on.
And sometimes you have some of the components always and then you can install or remove
whatever you want.
And linux plus gcc plus glpc plus corutals find utils if utils so on.
It makes GNU linux or what is called GNU linux.
This exists to make sure that all these components work together and they combine well because
many different distributions combine them in different ways and they have different
versions of these components and they all have to play nice.
So the linux kernel has a rule of never breaking user space if a new version of linux kernel
results in a binary not working.
It means it's a bug in the kernel even if it was for example originally an unintended
behavior so this can be kind of a pain.
But let's get back to chimera.
So starting out the toolchain.
LLVM and linux is pretty seamless nowadays most of the time.
You have it available on most linux systems but on most linux systems it's sort of a different
arrangement because you do not have LLVM provide the runtime.
Gcc provides this and it's called libGcc.
It's mostly ABI compatible with libunwind from LLVM but it also includes some of these
built ins which are provided via a separate library in LLVM.
LLVM comes with its own runtime called compiler RT and this is used in chimera instead of
libGcc.
For the C library we use muscle because it's a proven good implementation of a C library
which is used by several distributions already and you can make most software work on it
just fine with maybe with a few patches but better than other libcs.
When you have GNU toolchain you usually have GNU Benu tools to complement Gcc as well as
Lv tools to provide lib else.
Benu tools provides things like linker because Gcc does not come with its own linker.
It also provides different tools which are used together with the compiler things like
erkiver and read else and this kind of stuff.
In chimera this is the LLD from LLVM is used as a linker and it's used everywhere.
As for the other tooling which is provided by Benu tools, Lv toolchain provides this
tooling and this is also used on FreeBSD to provide these tools.
Lv toolchain also provides libelse implementation which replaces the one provided by Lv tools.
Libelse is used in many places but for example the kernel requires it.
LLVM also provides most of these tools which are provided by libutils.
They have a prefix LLVM so for example LLVM read else.
We do not use those in the core system most of the time.
So now to sort out the core user want you have many GNU components as well as non GNU
components things like core utils, find utils, defutils and so on.
You have util linux also which is used by pretty much all distributions and provides sort of
a mixture of tools for all sorts of stuff.
In non GNU distros existing ones such as Alpine you often have Busybox which is a sort of
single binary which can be configured to include many different tools which are otherwise provided
by core utils and so on as well as by util linux.
The main strength of Busybox is that it's a single binary so you can put it in embedded
environments and we can have things mostly work.
But the other side of the coin is that it's very Spartan when it comes to functionality
and the code is also not very good.
But the other alternatives are usually even worse in terms of available functionality.
So FreeBSD tools are the answer here and that's what we've done.
I found this third party port of FreeBSD's tools called BSD utils.
It was a sort of incomplete experimental thing which was not quite ready for an actual system.
So I helped complete it and reach parity with core utils.
I fixed many bugs which were created during porting in the process.
I also ported many other tools to expand coverage and the result is Karmira utils which the
distro currently manages and it's sort of a single easy to build package which includes
all of the tooling you want.
And this replaced not just GNU tooling but also for example a portion of util linux which
makes things much easier for the distribution especially in terms of bootstrapping because
for example in void linux a nxb-psrc which is the build system which is similar to C
build you have stripped down version of util linux in the base build container and you
need this because some of these tools are necessary.
But this means bootstrap problem because when you build a full version of util linux you
have many dependencies which you do not want during bootstrapping of your system.
For example udef or that kind of stuff which you really don't want to pull in.
So it has a stripped down version of util linux for that and then it has a full version
which is built separately and it's kind of a mess.
If we have a single package for the user run all of this can be avoided and then only a
partial build of util linux can be built if needed.
Karmira tools is lean enough for better environments things like init ramfs or even embedded things.
But at the same time it's fully featured enough to be used as interactive tooling so it's
a nice all in one thing.
And of course it helps break up the current monoculture of tooling as well as it's easy
to harden.
For example Karmira tool utilizes client control flow integrity hardening which can be enabled
on Karmira tools very easily and it just works.
Now to get the kernel sorted out.
These two photos one is Karmira running on the MNT reform laptop and the other is running
on Raspberry Pi 3.
The kernel is mostly compatible with client these days and some patches are needed to
support BSD utilities as well as the lip else from L-Toolchain.
I would like to eventually upstream these things and make sure things work out of box.
Until recently there was an issue with the option to use client's internal assembler.
It did not work on some architectures notably 64 bit power because of some legacy debugging
for nonsense.
So GNU binutils was used for that until sometime but nowadays it's not a problem and the client
assembler just works for every architecture.
CKMS.
What is CKMS?
distros usually use a DKMS which stands for dynamic kernel module system to build out
of three kernel modules and it's a massive 5K inline bash script and it has functionality
which seemed like a good idea at the time and nobody uses it and it no longer seems
like a good idea for example.
DKMS can package kernel modules and you can distribute them and of course this doesn't
work because every distro has its own kernel and it can result in slight differences in
ABI and so on so you cannot really do that.
I created CKMS which stands for chimeric kernel module system and it's kind of similar to
DKMS but it's much more lightweight, more robust, it's implemented in Python.
It has privilege separation so when you have your package manager build a kernel module
in a hook during installation and you run your package manager through it, it will properly
drop privileges so it does not run the whole compilation of the module through it which
also happens with DKMS and most setups.
Now for the package manager that's an important thing in a distro.
I considered the FreeBSD package manager at some point but it was not in quite the shape
I would like for production.
I did contribute back some patches to fix a bunch of things with muscle because that
was the main thing which was really problematic and I got it working but there are things
such as version expressions and the version string stuff which is a work in progress and
it's quite obvious that it's mainly all geared towards FreeBSD issues right now.
Eventually I ended up investigating APK from Alpine Linux which ended up proving to be
a great fit.
For one it's lightweight but it's also fairly powerful and I really like its virtual package
system.
It handles things like shared libraries very seamlessly where shared libraries in packages
are provided basically as virtual packages and this makes it easily searchable, easy
for the solver and so on.
I eventually transitioned to APK tools version 3 which is the next generation of APK which
is currently not used by Alpine and it does not have a stable roof yet but it works great.
The main difference in APK 3 is that it no longer uses starballs as packages.
It has a new custom sort of structured format which should help with avoiding vulnerabilities
in the package manager.
By summer 2021 it was fully integrated in C-built and it just worked.
Service management is another big thing you need to boot Linux distribution.
Many options were evaluated in the process for example Runit which is used by Void Linux,
S6 which is a new kid on the block, OpenRC which is classic and built on the same principles
as classic RC systems.
In the end I ended up choosing Dynit which is a new service manager.
I chose it because it's both powerful and lean.
It's implemented in modern C++ so it's also safer than most other service managers.
Most importantly it took me about one afternoon to get it fully working and get the system
from not booting at all to having it completely booting.
It's supervising which means most demons are supervised by the service manager by running
on the foreground and being basically child processes of the service manager.
But you can have background processes as well.
It's less robust so it should be avoided most of the time.
It's dependency based so it can ensure that your services start in correct order.
It has support for things like one shots which help immensely during early boot because most
things you need to do during early boot is basically things you run once and they do
not have any sort of persistent process.
So the early boot process is full of one shots.
For example, void Linux solves it by making these one shots a bunch of sequential shell
scripts which are run before the actual services are running.
It's not a great solution because it's not very flexible.
In any case it's a good base for a solid service infrastructure.
We have a custom suite of core services for Dynit written from scratch.
It has full support for fine grained targets.
Basically a target is a logical service which does not do anything by itself except act
as some sort of sentinel.
You can for example have networked as target and then you can have other things say I want
to start before this and then you can make sure that or I want to start after this.
You can make sure that your services start only after network is up for example.
It also has first class support for user services which is very important and I'll get to that
later.
The eventual goal is to have all long running processes be services.
And there's also the matter of session tracking which I'll describe in a bit.
Now this is a new project that I came up with.
It's called turnstile and it's an answer to the login part of system D.
Let's mostly use this system D login D for session tracking.
What that does is basically know when a user has logged in or when a user has logged in
on another console and it also knows when the user has logged out and it can be used
by say desktop environments in many different ways.
This E login D which exists as a standalone version which is basically just ripped away
from system D and the dependencies are stopped out and it's sort of dirty and not great.
This is done by basically running a daemon which is called login D and a module in the
PAM infrastructure which is obviously used for authentication.
The PAM module basically lets the daemon know when a new session has started and it also
lets it know when a session has ended.
This plus seed management which E login D also does but this is not widely used because
usually you only have one seed.
This is used by desktop environments especially things like Wayland compositors.
With system D most importantly also have login D also spawn a user session of system D basically
which acts as just like normal service manager but it runs as your user and it runs Caesar
services.
E login D cannot do this because it has no idea what other init system or what user service
manager you might be running.
So this functionality is removed and there's no way to access it.
This is one of the reasons why I developed this.
It aims to eventually replace E login D and it was originally created just to manage those
user instances of init.
The issue with that when running this in parallel with E login D was that sometimes it needs
to know something which E login D knows but sometimes E login D also needs to know something
the user service manager knows.
It especially affects things like lingering for example.
You can enable specific user to linger which means those user services will stay up even
after you have fully logged out.
E login D manages your runtime directory for you which is used by many services and upon
log out it removes this runtime directory.
If you have still some user services running and E login D has removed your service directory
then things go wrong.
So it needs to be integrated and I plan to eventually fully replace login D.
It turns out does not manage seats because there's already a project called libseat and
CTD which can do this satisfactorily.
But libseat does not do the session tracking so they can be used together and I plan to
provide a library alongside the daemon.
This library will provide agnostic API.
This API will have multiple back ends and it will have a back end for login D, it will
have a back end for turn style D as well as potentially other solutions and then things
like desktops will be able to use this and be actually portable because for example right
now to have GNOME for on free BSD for example it needs many patches to replace this functionality
and it's just not great.
Having an agnostic API which is not provided by system D would be much nicer solution.
Of course I also have to convince up frames to adopt it.
One thing which you do if turn style is managing the bus session, bus as a user service, this
has an advantage because you have a single session bus per user just like is done when
you have system D. Well why have a single session bus?
This session bus has a socket.
The socket is somewhere on the file system and the socket is used to identify other things
on the bus.
The way to locate this session bus is provided via environment variable.
So if you have the environment variable in your environment then things can use this
to read the path and actually locate the socket.
Traditionally you had the session bus started by for example your X11 script, Xinit RC which
would run something like D bus run session something.
That means the session bus was only available within your single graphical DTY.
This is not great because when you switch console and log in there and you want to run
something which needs to access the session bus it doesn't know about it.
System D solves this.
We also solve this by running the session bus as a user service.
So when you first log in it automatically spawns the session bus.
When you last log out it stops the session bus and it's available on every single Vt.
This has also limitless potential for other user services.
We can do things like D bus activation without having D bus spawn the services themselves.
It's currently also used for the sound server for example with pipewire.
Now let's move on to C build.
C build is basically a build system for seaports as I already know.
This is what a template might look like.
This is the template to build Doom game.
As you can see it's mostly metadata.
There's one hook in there which runs W
which has no other way to do this.
There's a build style for configure script which basically strips away all the non-decorative
things you would otherwise need.
How C build works is that it builds all the software in a simple container called the
build root in our terminology.
It's minimized chimera system.
There's some packages which provide a baseline and your build dependencies which are specified
by the template are also installed into this container.
This container is fully unprivileged so you don't need to run anything as root and it's
fully sandboxed.
This is done by with Linux namespaces.
The container is also read only after the build dependencies are installed which means
no package built can actually change anything in the container otherwise other than in its
own build directory.
It also has no network access after all the fetch stage things are done.
It has no access to the outside system.
Templates are also declarative.
As I said, ideally just metadata and it has fully transparent support for cross compiling
with most build systems which means in most templates you don't need to do anything and
it will be able to cross compiling without any additional effort.
It has a clean handling of common build systems.
This includes configure script, mass and CMake and so on.
It's strict.
It has mandatory linting hooks for many things and unit tests where possible will run out
of box.
I strongly believe that being strict by default is good because you can always make things
more loose if you need it but if you have things loose by default and then you need
to strengthen them and you have many hundreds to thousands of packages and you need to adjust
every single one of them it becomes effort which cannot be done because it's just too
much.
It has support for things like bulk builds where it can properly order things in the
batch to build without having dependency ordering issues.
It can check upstream projects for new versions and so on.
Build flags.
All the basic stuff for hardening which Linux and service typically use like Fortify, position
independent executables, stack entries and so on are used.
On top of that we use system wide LTO for practically every package.
I think there's only about 30 templates out of close to a thousand which have LTO disabled
for different reasons.
In some cases it could be enabled but it's not worth it.
We do utilize a system wide subset of undefined behavior sanitizer.
It deals with things like trapping signed integer overflows in order to avoid potential
problems.
Also CFI or control flow integrity is used for many packages.
It cannot be used for all because it breaks on a lot of stuff.
It's very strict when it comes to typing of functions but it's still used on a couple
hundred packages.
The allocator.
We now use the scudo allocator from LLVM which is also used for example on Google Android.
It replaces the allocator in muscle.
This is not because of hardening because muscle allocator is already hardened but scudo is
also hardened allocator.
But it has significantly better multi-threaded performance because muscle malloc ng uses
a single global lock.
This is a trade-off but it also means that the stock allocator in muscle performs poorly
in many things and it's something people commonly complain about so we now rely on scudo.
This is also the advantage of being able to eventually deploy GWP asan which is sort of
sampling runtime version of address sanitizers which can catch many memory errors at runtime
with minimal performance overhead.
This is not enabled yet but it will be at some point.
Other core things for this row.
Some tooling is taken from Debian.
For example we use initramfs tools to generate initramfs images because other solutions were
generally found to be unsatisfactory.
For example requiring bash for the hooks and so on.
Initramfs tools is very clean and simple and nice to work with.
We also use console setup from Debian to do console and keyboard configuration as well
as the script for handling encrypted drives.
I also had to add some other things like the GRAP bootloader support for ZFS.
We now support root on ZFS very easily and so on.
This is Kaimira desktop on RISC-V.
You can see it runs things like Firefox for example which it does not build out of books
but I made it work.
This is on the high-five unmatched board from C5.
When I was starting to add to the desktop, the first thing I added was the Western Wayland
Composter as well as GTK.
This sort of provided a baseline set of dependencies which are also used by pretty much everything
else.
Then I expanded with Exodorq stack, things like the Enlightenment Window Manager as well
as PEGWM for a simple X11 Window Manager.
I added the multimedia stack including FFmpeg, Gstreamer, media players and so on.
In Spring 2022 I added GNOME desktop which is the default choice but of course you can
use anything else you want.
I also added web browsers, this includes Epiphany which comes with GNOME and is built on WebKit
and Firefox which is alternative choice.
And of course some games.
As I said before I would like to release an alpha version in late February or early March.
I'm not sure if this will happen but I hope it will.
Before doing this I would like to perform a complete world rebuild of all the packages
because I have introduced some things in C-Bilt which I would like to propagate it into existing
packages and it's not.
So just to be clean I would like to build everything with LVM 15 as it is right now
and basically then release the alpha.
I will need to launch automatic built infrastructure.
I currently have a server in Kolo in my city but it's not on public network yet so I need
to set up the public network and launch things like this as well as CI.
I would like to clean up the remaining fallout from the recent hardening stuff as well as
update every template to its latest version.
And after alpha which is the alpha cycle is expected to take about half a year to one
year I would like to add libGCC compatibility shim so we can run existing binaries because
right now you cannot run existing binaries because the system runtime is different.
I would like to add support for the bus activation so the bus does not run demons by itself through
the bus service files but instead delegate it to the service manager.
I would like to investigate additional hardening things like LVM save stack and I would like
to improve the documentation.
Right now there's the beginning of Chimera handbook which includes some handy basic information
like installation and how to set up encrypted writes and so on but it can always use more
documentation and local support is also another thing I would like to expand to this is the
problem in pretty much all muscle distros with the local support being sort of limited
and you can have translations but things like formats and so on.
So the conclusion we are currently nearing usability and it should be suitable for early
adapters by March.
I would like to get all the major changes done by beta and continue packaging more software
as well as cooperate with upstreams including the free BSD upstream on sensing fixes and
tooling and so on.
In any case thank you for listening and if you have any questions you can ask them out
of course we also have stickers so come pick them up.
Yeah.
Yeah, as I said it's supported.
I recently introduced it and I recently tested it.
Oh yeah.
Sure.
So it's only thing if ZFS on the root is supported.
Yeah, it's supported.
It uses the upstream scripts for any time of tools just patched to support the user
and because we don't use busy box and it just works.
We also provide ZFS packages with precompiled binary modules so it's not necessarily compiled
from source during installation.
And CKMS can handle things in a non-conflicting way so if you have the package installed for
the stock kernel which provides the binary ZFS modules, CKMS will not try to build the
modules again.
Yeah.
What are the target user segments for this distribution?
For example at home I use gel, I have to use Ubuntu and...
Okay.
Well, the question was if...
What's the target audience basically?
Well, I would say the primary audience is basically the same people who would use things
like Gen 2 and so on.
Basically power users who can find their way around things because there's no insistence
on providing graphical clickable stuff for everything because it just wouldn't be possible.
I just do not have the manpower to do all this.
So yeah, it's for power users who can find their way around a simple system.
Yeah.
Where does the name come from?
He was asking where does the name come from?
Well, Chimera is basically like a mythical monster made up of three different animals
so it should be fairly obvious where it comes from.
We have Linux kernel and FreeBSD stuff and other stuff.
Yeah.
How do you work with upstream in particular against FreeBSD to provide a change in path
to the...
Okay.
...change in some way might be useful?
Yeah, the question was if I'm working with FreeBSD.
I know the project has taken back some of the changes.
I have some patches in Chimera tools which I do believe would be useful for upstream
and yes, I do want to submit to them upstream.
For example, I have a fix in the sort tool which fixes a crash with control flow integrity
hardening so this would be nice to include for example.
Yeah.
Turns out the...
How did you solve the problem of the PAM service program?
The problem was the PAM service crashing before it can run the...
Oh.
...use C groups?
Sorry, can you repeat?
Those turnstile use C groups.
Question is if turnstile uses C groups.
No, it doesn't.
It uses...
It does the same thing as Log-in-D basically.
This is a PAM module to report things and it keeps a persistent socket connection to
the daemon as long as the session is active and then when the socket is closed and when
the daemon receives basically a notification pulse on the socket and once it knows the
connection has been closed then it closes the session inside of the daemon.
Yeah.
Follow up question.
So you open a socket from the PAM service module?
The question is if I open the socket from the PAM module.
Yes, the PAM module opens a connection to the socket which is provided by the daemon
and the daemon basically opens the socket in the system as a Unix domain socket and
it's only accessible by root obviously so the PAM module access it.
Yeah.
Follow this is the last question.
So if you open a socket from the PAM module that socket obviously ends up appearing as
a file descriptor inside the program that ran the PAM.
Does that not interfere with anything?
Have you not found anything that closes for like...
Because I have to try to do the same thing.
The question is if the PAM module with the socket actually interferes with anything?
No, I found it doesn't interfere with anything and in fact as far as I know Log-in-D does
basically the same thing and other solutions for handling for example there are several
solutions for handling for the runtime directory which is basically run user your UID and they
basically did the same thing as far as I know but yeah as far as I can tell it works okay.
Yeah.
So first of all text to the job must be like really difficult to maintain all this dependence.
Thank you.
So my question is are you planning to integrate like in a specific SSL library like for example
LibraSSL or like OpenSSL?
Okay the question was about integrating SSL library.
We do use OpenSSL version 3.
This was actually a pretty big transition when it happened because many things do not
or did not work well with OpenSSL 3.
Unfortunately the amount of packages right now is not that huge.
There are still some which do not work with OpenSSL 3 and which we do rely on.
For example the Heimdall implementation of Kerberos which we use instead of MIT, GAR-B
does not work with OpenSSL 3 yet but it has its own built-in crypto which can be used
instead so we fall back on that for now.
Anyone else?
Looks like that's it then and thank you again.
Thank you.