Good afternoon, everyone. I'm Mamda.
I work as a software engineer at Leica GeoSystems,
and I work mostly in embedded domain.
So this is the outline of my talk.
So just to keep everyone on the same page,
I'll be giving a brief introduction about LLVM and Clang,
and so that the terminology is next I'm using are clear.
Then I'll talk about compiler RT sanitizers,
what they are, how you can build them,
and how exactly they work,
and then my final thoughts about sanitizers.
So this is a typical compiler pipeline,
which most of you are aware of,
and they call it as a textbook diagram as well.
So whenever you write a source or a code in any language
to produce a binary executable for your machine,
it has to go through multiple stages.
So mostly, most important ones are the front end,
middle end, and the back end.
And the front end actually does all the lexical analysis,
semantic analysis, it checks the syntax,
and then it generates an intermediate representation.
Then it is passed to the middle end,
which does optimizations independent of the target.
And then it is passed to the back end,
which generates much executable,
and it has more optimizations depending on the target
you are building it for.
And sometimes if there are multiple object files,
then comes in the picture linker.
So how does LLVM fits in our pipeline?
So basically, the same, it's LLVM,
it's a modular and reusable compiler framework,
and it provides front end, back end, and LLVM core,
which is the LLVM optimizer.
So if we map it to our compiling pipeline,
so for depending on the language you are trying to build
or use this compiling tool chain,
you have LLVM front end,
that is the Clang for C languages and Rust,
Rust C for Rust,
and then depending upon the target,
it will use the target as x86, 32-bit or 64.
And the main part, which is most reusable
from the LLVM perspective,
it's the LLVM optimizer and the core.
So if I have to develop a new compiler tool chain,
I can easily reuse LLVM.
I just have to write my own front end,
and if there is a new hardware, back end maybe.
So in short, I can say LLVM is like a Lego
of compiler tool chains.
Next, focusing a bit more on one of the LLVM front end Clang,
which is built for targeting mostly C, C++,
and C-like languages.
And here, whenever you provide your source code,
it performs some lexical analysis,
it generates tokens for parsing,
then it does semantic analysis
and generates abstract syntax tree,
and the end goal should be LLVM intermediate representation.
So just to summarize, LLVM is a collection of all modular
and reusable compiler technologies,
and there is much more to it because it provides now
with static analyzers, sanitizers, and more libraries.
So it comes under an umbrella project as LLVM.org.
And Clang is a compiler front end,
which is mostly for C, C++ and C-like languages.
But when we say Clang executable,
it's more than a front end.
So when you build LLVM, you have Clang executable as well.
And it's like a compiler driver.
So for example, if you have a static compiler,
and we have to tell it which directives to use
or to use this hyphen I option,
where is the standard library path,
for example, for C, C++.
So Clang as a driver does most of the housekeeping
for all this task, and it helps this compiling pipeline
to tell you where to look for the libraries
and also provide some OS related features
and how your OS is.
So that was just a brief introduction about Clang and LLVM.
So now I'll talk about compiler RT sanitizers.
It's one of the sub projects in LLVM.
But before that, I'll highlight about the run times.
So LLVM comes with compiler RT run times.
It's pretty much equivalent of lib GCC for LLVM pipeline.
And it provides target specific support
for some low level functionalities,
which hardware itself cannot do.
So it consists of three main components,
built-ins, sanitizer, run times and profilers.
So built-ins provide implementation
for target specific hooks, which hardware itself cannot do.
So just to simplify it a bit more,
for example, if the 32 bit system cannot do 64 bit division.
So here you can see a code snippet.
And if I try to compile it using Clang,
so first we do a normal compilation on x86 machine,
which is a 64 bit.
And here on left, you can see it directly calls this diff Q,
which means it performs the division itself.
But when I use hyphen M32,
which is I'm forcing it to compile for 32 bit machine,
it depends on another call.
It actually calls this U-diff I3,
which is basically a built-in implementation in compiler RT.
So this is an overall picture of compiler RT run times.
So talking about the sanitizers,
sanitizers are like runtime checks,
which it's like adding a code probe in your code
to verify if there are any memory bugs
or to sanitize the code or to find any security flaws.
So in case of LLVM, it's provided by compiler RT,
compiler RT and called as compiler RT sanitizers.
And there are multiple kind of sanitizers available.
First is address sanitizer,
which you can use to detect use after free buffer overflow
and memory leaks as well.
Then you have undefined behavior sanitizers,
memory sanitizers to identify
if there is some uninitialized memory.
And threat sanitizer to detect some race conditions
and deadlocks.
So here it's just an example of how sanitizer looks.
So here is a very simple code
where I'm allocating some memory in heap.
And then I'm trying to, I'm freeing it
and then I'm trying to access it after free.
So if you build this code with your sanitizer flag on
and try to run it, immediately it will complain
that you are trying to access a memory after free.
So that's how it looks like
when it's built with address sanitizer.
And I will talk in more detail
about what goes behind the scene.
But before that, how to build compiler RT sanitizers.
So there are a lot of documentation around as well.
And it's very easy to follow as well,
but sometimes it works, sometimes it doesn't.
So you can build first compiler RT with LLVM, it's easy.
You can directly enable it with LLVM enabled projects
when you're building your complete LLVM tool chain.
And you can do a separate build as well
if you have your LLVM config
and use generator of your choice.
To enable the sanitizers,
so if I'm doing a build along with the complete LLVM tool
chain, I just have to use this flag,
compiler RT build sanitizers to on.
And when you do this, and here I'm using Ninja
as a generator, you can see we get a config out of CMake
and you can see it is enabling different sanitizers
as address sanitizer, leak sanitizers,
memory sanitizer, thread and undefined behavior.
And same you can do for, and after, sorry,
after the installation and build,
you can get these set of libraries.
You can do the same for the standalone build as well
with the similar flag.
And this is the config generated
when I'm doing a compiler RT standalone build.
And then it's also possible to cross compile RT sanitizers.
You have to provide a lot of flags
and you need to have your arms as well.
And I personally don't prefer this way,
but there is a talk today in the end from Peter
about building embedded tool chain using LLVM.
So to make it a bit easier for all the embedded developers,
there is a, in Yocto project,
there is an open embedded layer called meta-clang.
It makes it a bit easy because it provides everything
for building your tool chain
and you just have to include this layer
if people are aware of Yocto builds.
And just few configurations are needed.
Like you have to enable the SDK,
you have to use LLVM run times
and then either you can write in your package groups
or in local conf to include compiler RT
and compiler RT sanitizers.
And this actually generates a SDK
and it's very easy to distribute this SDK
to other developers or like in our case,
I used to send it to the application team
so that they can use this
and the people who are developing C++ code,
they can run their code,
they can compile their code and run sanitizers on it.
So this was actually while contributing to meta-clang,
I became more aware about compiler RT sanitizers
and also now it's available for ARM32 bit
and ARM64 bit and x86 of course.
And you can easily test it also on KMU ARM as well,
just specifying your sysroot and running your test code
to see how it behaves on your actual target.
So that was all about what is compiler RT sanitizers,
how we build it, but what exactly goes behind the scene.
So here I'm using an example of address sanitizer to use
and here is a very basic code
where we are taking some arguments
and converting into integer.
But here you can see we are using argument counter
and the value for this can be very large as well.
So first time when I try to compile it with clang,
it compiles and when you run it,
after like as you can see easily
and it's very easy to spot here,
I have defined the size of buffer to be just two.
And if I provide input more than two,
it should fail actually, that's the case.
But it's very, the crooks here is like, it's difficult
for some machine it will fail for three
and for some machine it will fail with the four input
and leads to the segmentation fault
and we don't know what happened exactly behind the scene.
Second, when you try to build it
with address sanitizer enabled
or link it with compiler RT
and with your address sanitizer flag as well.
And the output is actually a bit large,
this is the first part of it.
So it can easily spot that there was a stack overflow,
stack buffer overflow and it also points out
if you build it with hyphen G option,
it also points out at what line it is failing.
But what exactly led to generation of this kind of error.
So in very simple term, when address sanitizers,
adding sanitizer is like adding an additional code
to your actual code to just check
when it is going to fail and report the error.
So here it looks very easy.
Okay, if my buffer size is more than two
or sorry, if the input size for the buffer is more than two,
just notify it's an error.
But behind the scene for address sanitizer,
it's much more and it can adopt multiple strategies
to implement it.
So here address sanitizer uses memory mapping.
So memory that should not be accessed
is called as poisoned memory.
So behind the scene, it's implemented like to check
whether this is getting poisoned or not.
So here poisoned means either it is referring
to some deallocated memory or some already allocated memory
or there is getting some overflow or not
and just report the error.
But there is much more how this memory is mapped.
So for any code, any application that you build,
the virtual address space is divided
into two kind of memories.
One is shadow memory and one is application memory.
So for address sanitizer, it is more important
to implement this is poisoned and report error
in a very compact and fast way.
Then talking about shadow memory and the application memory.
So application memory is the main memory of the code
and shadow memory is a copy of application memory,
but here eight bytes of your application map memory
is mapped as one byte in shadow memory.
And when the sanitizer checks,
whether this memory is poisoned or not,
it is mapped to either zero or one.
So here it's a small portion of shadow memory
above of our example.
And you can see the memory which is accessible
and which is in good condition is marked as zero.
But here when we are checking the buffer here,
you can see after it's marked as the memory
which is like more when we are trying to access more
than the allocated buffer size, it's marked as one.
And these, and here you can see in the square brackets,
it is it's marking that hello,
this here you are supposed not to access this,
it's getting out of the range of the buffer.
So that's how this application memory
and shadow memory is used.
And then you can see here we restrict it as the red zones.
So if you have anything greater than these,
than the allocated one.
So that one gets marked as one
and you can see F1, F3 around.
And so that's how the address sanitizer works
by using this shadow memory and application memory
and knowing about your shadow memory.
And whenever it spots it's one,
then it says, okay, there is a problem.
So that's all about the address sanitizer and how it works.
So here are my final thoughts about using sanitizers.
It's a very great tool to find bugs and memory issues
and in a very run in runtime for complex applications.
So by using sanitizers, you can improve your development
and you can spot the errors very quickly.
And since we had a very simple example,
but when the code gets more complex,
it's more difficult to find what is the problem.
And though with the sanitizers,
it's more like a tool to check
not to be used in your production.
It increases the code size,
but the sanitizers are comparatively more faster
than Valcrant, the existing one.
And still there are not all the architectures
are supported uniformly.
Like for example, for ARM32, we don't have threat sanitizer
completely implemented.
So I hope we see a better implementation later
and it supports threat sanitization
on 32-bit machines as well.
Questions?
Yes, sorry, the question here is like,
I'm using the optimization flag
for building with address sanitizer enabled.
Yes, it can be enabled to up to three as well
and you get a similar kind of log.
So the question is, where I'm placing the instrumentation
to identify whether my buffer is overflowing or not,
to use assertion here.
I'm not sure I can answer that well,
but it's more, the strategy of this one is using more
with this memory mapping one.
And also here, since this buffer size is very small,
so maybe assertion might work here.
Okay, thanks.
This I'm also not much aware of.
So the question is like, if I can sanitize it
for a very specific portion of the code, right?
Yeah, you can, no, I'm sorry, I'm not much aware of.
You can reverse it, you can prevent some specific code
from being instrumented, either by annotating the code
or by using the blacklist.
Hi, yeah, there is this blacklist address sanitizer options
as well, yeah.
Have you, you say that sanitizers are primarily
a development tool, and yes, they mostly are,
but have you ever looked into using some of them
for actual production executables for hardening?
For example, UBSan has a fairly minimal overhead,
so it can be used in production,
especially if you make it a trap,
or if you make it, if you use the minimal runtime,
or also there's GWB-asan,
which is like a lightweight sampling version
of other sanitizers, which can be used in runtime.
I think Android is using it actually easily.
Okay, so does it support some of the embedded platforms
as well, like ARM32 or 64?
It supports, I believe it does,
well, UBSan works pretty much everywhere, almost everywhere.
GWB-asan works, I think, almost everywhere,
but it's also dependent on external function
for unwinding, so it might not be great in all scenarios.
It's really dependent.
Okay.
But we have to show the first preview.
Yes.
I was wondering if you can use this for kernel
and ring zero code as well.
Yeah, you can, but like there's like,
But there's a,
Why there are, if you provide it in the kernel,
you don't have like the runtime is not in the MPM,
it's actually open by the kernel and it's in binary.
You insert the checks,
but the hooks themselves are implemented in the kernel.
Well, some sanitizers don't require any runtime, so.
So, for instance, you need this implementation.
Yeah, but there's a KA center.
Yeah, you can use kernel address sanitizer for it, maybe.
But like, it's on the phone for it, like the,
it's on best point, like the,
I think it's just a level implementation of the stuff.
There's other sanitizers in kernel which are implemented
this way, I think that it's KCFI and,
yeah.
Yes.
All right.
Do you know where the code lives currently
that does the hooking to malloc and free,
like the C library?
Like how does the interaction with the C library work?
Do you know?
Because like I could have, for example,
have a muscle instead of a chili C library
and I guess the code has to be adapted somehow
or there must be some book infrastructure.
So do you know how that works and where the code lives
that books malloc and free, for example?
Is it in this compiler RT library?
It's in compiler RT built-ins, if I'm right.
It's a great point.
So if you change the version of library you have,
you need a different kind of sanitizer
to support all of these things.
It's horrible.
It's essentially a shared library.
So it's basically just intercepting using.
Yeah, the FM runtime, I have to input
that for malloc and free.
Okay, that's just so it acts outside of the C library.
Yeah.
So I could write my own C of library
and it would still work.
As long as it's dynamically,
I mean this is one of the problems
that sanitizers have at the moment.
Well, for ASAN, yes, but for example,
for L-san, for leak sanitizer,
which is enabled by ASAN,
you need to actually, you need to be aware of things
like the TLS layout and so on,
which needs to have some support.
But the runtime in LLVM definitely
implements both GLF2 and malloc.
Oh, good.
Yes.
Are the sanitizers shared between GCC and LLVM
or does it have its own implementation?
They are.
They have.
They are shared.
Sorry.
Yeah, they're shared, yes.
I noticed that one shadow byte corresponds
to eight actual bytes.
However, considering that there are special values for it,
does it mean that there could be situations
where there could be some byte
which are not protected necessarily by this?
Yeah, there can be some cases
where you can call it as a false, positive kind of thing
or sometimes it is checking very much in the end.
So it was a very small example,
but it can happen that you get these square brackets
at the very end and it's an overrun case.
So that can happen, yes.
Okay, so there are the situations
where the address sanitizer is just getting it wrong
because of the fact is actually valid code,
but there are just limitations to the parallel byte system.
Yes.
Good, okay.
Thanks.
Yes.
So could you get a false negative in some sense
in the sense that if you have two almost adjacent blocks
of allocated application memory
and you access a pointer from one to the other,
could you get a false negative in this sense?
So because that would not be a point
and it would still be part of the application,
but for example, what an address sanitizer has there?
Yeah, it can be, like it can be a false positive case,
maybe.
I think the valid negative is like if A-Fam
will not catch it.
The other case puts red zone.
Yes.
It makes it harder to dig up.
Okay.
Yeah, it's one question,
I think it was already partially answered before,
but I'm not sure, so I'm just gonna ask it.
So for example, I'm also working on embeddits
in an embedded scenario and we don't use,
I think we don't use gilets or muscle,
like we have our own set of proteins for malochic free.
Yes.
Would it also work in that case
or is that then something that you would need to,
are there any more requirements
before you can use these sanitizers on both devices?
For my experience,
I have been just using this meta clang layer included.
And for testing with like for just doing on the SDKs
and emulator, it was perfectly fine.
So not on the actual devices
because it's just meant for testing.
Because you need virtual memory
at the moment to set up the shuttle.
So you can in theory do a bit of fixed offset,
but not in a full point.
Is the kernel address the driver
that hard codes to you?
I don't know.
You have to write your own
set of memory allocation.
All right.
Thank you, Manja.
Thank you.