So, the start. Oh yes, I put a who am I, so I'm Rodrigo Soryos, so I'm free BSD port
committer since 2014. What else? So yes, what speak it provides? I don't know if how many
of you knows package provides? A few ones, okay. So, sorry? Oh yes, so this part of,
so as you know we have package, pkg, which is a free BSD command used to manage
packages and the package was designed to be extended with plugins, so you can
route your own plugins to run special commands, handle hooks, replace existing
commands or access the package database just for statistics or have numbers or
whatever. So package provide basically is a plugin you can use with packages. We
extend package to do a special thing as matching a found the package for
a specific file. Basically you have, you are looking for which package I need to
install to have this file in my computer and usually is you start looking on the
internet, you Google a little bit to know exactly what the package you need and
because sometimes the packages doesn't provide the name of the files we have
inside the command or so on. So basically it's a way to found, is a
reverse way to find with package correspond to a specific file. It could
be a library, an executable or just a header like a.h file. So this is an
example, so you just type package provides and libmpg123.iso and give
you the list of packages who provide this. Sorry for the contrast, it's not
really good. So you have a for this lib you have two packages, we
have the mpg123 which is probably the main project who provides the file but
you see that zoom video conferencing also provide this library in another
version probably for my own and basically it's a Linux compat library. So
as you can guess package provide is a client so you have in your computer but
it's also a database who contains the full list of files you can install if
you install all the packages existing in FreeBSD and this is a lot for just one
release and one architectures we have one nine million files installable so
this is a huge database we have to build. So just I put here this is
the numbers for the the latest version so the 13 and if you look at the
different versions of FreeBSD and different architectures you see how many
how many files are and basically this is based on the packages you can build on
FreeBSD for this architecture and version. So you can probably see which are the
the good architectures the architecture works and you have a lot of applications
and those architectures you who are a little bit not really use or we are
missing a lot of tools who doesn't be out for those architectures.
You have the also the the new ones like the ARMv7 who appears suddenly and it has
a big big number and you have the ARMv6 who is declining a little bit it's
still still things still works but as the numbers shows it's it's not that
that popular than ARMv7. So this is basically how everything works. I have
here because I host the database server myself so I have the the package provide
server here you have the clients who connects to upload the database and I
use the package FreeBSD servers to sync and have the list of files because this
is the best and most efficient way to have the full list of files in a minimum
of time because of course you you can guess it's it's not always possible to
build all the packages just to have the list. It's kind of a nightmare. So
basically yes I put some some things about these three so I start it on 2017.
I have multiple motivations the first one was to stop doing grip on ports when I'm
looking for a file is nothing more terrible than you try to compile a new
a new project and say oh I'm missing this something H file and you start
draping around and it takes hours just to have the full list of dependencies so
this this way you you you can found it easily and and have the exact number and
also you can have a full list so you the of the of the the package is providing
the same file so you can choose the right one who match for you usually it's
not it's not the first one because some some some packages bring a lot of
dependencies so you can choose the right one and my second motivation was to write
a package plugin at this time package just was a new thing this we had this
plugin feature and as much as I know probably the first plugin available for
package and probably the one of the works who's still working I have really
real users but yes so so yes package provide was introduced at the FOSDEM
the one year late when you're after in 2018 and this is where the story start
this is the daily connections of people who access the server to upload the
database looks not that much but I consider a package provide like consider
package provide developer tool so I don't expect regular people use it that
much because it doesn't too much sense and and also we have only people access
only when they perform our package update I don't upload the database every
time so when you are doing an update we you have update is at this time the
plugin looks if we have a new database so it don't it downloads it it's right to
be oh so oh yes yes this is what happens when you host your own server from time
to time you have a breakages and in this case was some kind of certificate issues
the some some numbers new questions from where people come from and as you can
see it's much a lot the free BSD developers based so you have people
mostly USA Canada some people in South America mostly in Europe we have some
people as yeah Australia and unfortunately we now have too much
to be upon Africa who don't use people not like BSD there so if you take the
numbers yes we have the big the big chunk of users are in United States and
you have a Germany and France we are quite the same numbers and yes and after
that you have a lot of countries around the world sometimes yes you have a what
funny is we have a Russian Federation and Ukraine and both have the same number I
have the same number of people coming from both countries so strange and from
time to time you have some special guests so for a couple of months I have
people from st. Kitties and Nevis and food if you don't know st. Kitties is a
small island here just just close to Cuba and it's basically just a place to
put money and register your companies when you have things to hide so okay we
have developers there just yes a quick look about the database as I say the
database so we have a at this time we have a 58 thousand of ports if you
consider we have a three major releases and six architectures that brings you a
lot of ports so as I say it's something you can build by your own because I
don't have enough space or CPU also to obtain the list of files it's not
possible to trust big G list because those files are not totally fully
complete sometimes you have replacements we don't during the build and I can just
download as is the packages because it needs time and space to download the
full list of packages and also having impact on mirror performances so I found
a simple way is I try to abuse the the package file format as you know packages
are just archived who contains two two times the manifest of the package and
the second manifest which is a full manifest has the list of files provide
for the package then comes all the files and the thing is you can just use the
head HTTP request to only download the first part of the package and let's say
we took we can extract the manifest because it works and if the JSON file is
valid you're wrong you're good if you if you have an error you just increase a
little bit of size just remember it for the next time so this way you can just
download the only the manifest part of the files and the good thing is the HTTP
head is a totally standard method so we are not trying to abuse the HTTP server
and we are not producing or breakages in connections we are saving people bandwidth
because we are we are not we are not using the the package to mirror just for
us and we save our also everybody's time yes so talking about the database
itself at the beginning I designed it as a just a full text file just because it's
easy to read and search but it I have I have this problem is was too large is
was 36 megabytes even compress okay
so in 2018 I do is busy con I talk with talking with mark SP about the thing he
suggests me I can use to locate file format locate is a Unix standard tool
who store all the is try to store all the files you have in your computer so
it's easy to found a place and use a nagoreen called bigram to store the
datas and this this file format is pretty efficient because if we once once
generated and compressed it I reduced by two to not the size of the file so it's
it's pretty convenient because instead of downloading for a couple of minutes
the database we can have a just in one one minute and something we it's pretty
similar with the package itself in time so the package provide usages as I saw
yes I show you you can just perform reverse searches you're looking for a file
give you the name of the package but you can also use it to identify unexpected
files in the packages like core dams things happen sometimes people commit
and then the commit comes with binary files or dams because of this happens
and also you can use it to search for duplicate files when you have two
packages installed the same file and conflicting for a long time I report this
this information to to the developers and I try to track exactly how much
conflict we have and someone decide or Stefan Stefan is a decides to start
looking at it and use the database the database I provide to to search for
file conflicts and try to fix it to to to avoid conflict during a package
install because package the tool can handle conflicts but the handle the
conflict the worst way it's a okay you have a conflict so or you can't install
the new package or you have to remove the old one so there's no way to and
sometimes you you have a and that there's a lot of funny things because you have a
binaries who have to say exactly the same name doing completely different
things sometimes is the game and the network manager and Wow so yes so oh yeah
and I still having six minutes so if you have questions please yeah oh the
options no I am what I take is the real files available in in package servers
so is the real thing you have if you install a package it's not something I'm
sorry the question was if I scan for options and the the answer is no I just
try to track what's on the package servers and the real files installed if
you install it's not it's not used the custom yeah if you have a custom package
server it doesn't bring you the files you are installing yes it's just for
standard instant free BSD packages the way we build it yeah oh the first
okay how long is to how long is take to scan the packages and build the index
allow so the first the first con it can take about I think is I so I didn't do
for a long time but I think it's like half an hour 30 minutes something like
that and once once I build it I can I can just update in a couple of seconds
from one minute so it's that the good thing is if I consider because I we have
a file a manifesto with all the packages on the version so I can see which package
change so I'm cons I just look at the package who changed the version and
based on that and just recovering the the manifesto it takes yes it takes a
cup I think the maximum is like a five minutes for for for an architecture and
the version oh yes do that I use the locate so it's the yes is the locate
format so because because it's really it's really convenient for this kind of
usage yes yes I storied that and yeah
oh yes I I include because the the way big RAM works it take just a line and
just to line is it is a path so it's considered a path and there's no extra
data around so you can you can use so I just include the the the package name
inside inside the path and use a special character yes also separator I think in
this case I used the star character because I don't expect people to put it
put a star in the package name yes absolutely and and I use
I use a regular expression for search but the the result is quite
acceptable in bytes compressed it's 17 exact compressed it's 70 megabytes yes
around because it depends on which version you're looking at but it's
basically yes it's around this this size yeah yes could be could be yeah oh sorry
the question aha this was a trick just to see if I can repeat yes the question
was was why not use a slash instead of star because a slash a slash made more
sense probably yes so but I am yes we can we can probably oh good question no I
just see happy people