a tool called Parkoach and how they've been using
a logarithm for one time and they've kept it well.
I think.
Yeah. We'll see.
All right. Up to you, Philippe.
Thank you very much. So yes,
my name is Philippe. I work at Tenerife in France.
And so the talk today is not so much about Parkoach itself.
I'm sorry for the wrong title,
but naming is hard,
so I had to put something.
But today I want to talk to you about
my experience with dealing with out of
three plug-in and tools for LLVM.
Parkoach is just one example and I will give some others.
So first of all, I will try to explain you why and for whom
am I doing this talk so that you know the audience.
I'm going to talk about three different things.
The first one is keeping up with LLVM.
So we will see some code,
CMake, C++ and stuff.
The other point, the second point is usability,
both from a developer to developer point of view and the user point of view.
And the final point will be dealing with
packaging when you're actually targeting some system.
So why am I doing this talk?
First of all, it's to provide some feedback
and maybe provide you with some stuff I wish I knew beforehand,
before coming into this.
I'm doing this also because I've learned a couple of out of three projects
and I faced the same issues.
So maybe you've faced them too and it will be helpful.
So it's not so much about the tool Parkoach itself,
it's rather about the approach.
And for whom it's basically anyone with a vote or who is involved in
an out of three project for LLVM.
This is my own point of view on this topic.
If you have IDs, comments,
improvements that you think may be helpful to me, don't hesitate.
I will welcome them.
So Parkoach is a tool for HPC application.
It's basically an instrumentation analysis and instrumentation tool
for OpenMP and MPI application.
Basically checks that the user is using
the APIs appropriately that there are no deadlock or data racism.
The developers, this is where it gets interesting
because they are not LLVM engineers, right?
They are interns, students, PhD students, researchers.
They have a whole job which is not LLVM.
The users of the tool,
they are scientific application developers.
So you cannot ask them to compile LLVM from source.
It's not going to work. They are not going to use your tool.
The last part which is interesting with this project,
it started like a long time ago when it was LLVM 3.7,
and now it's based on LLVM 15.
So there has been a lot of history in the tool.
I'm working on it right now.
It's my main job. So they have an LLVM engineer now,
and I can do stuff.
I provided the link for reference if you want to take a look.
There are two other motivating projects that I can talk about.
One, I'm actually not going to talk about
much because it's not free.
It's a commercial compiler which is based on LLVM,
and basically the developers are LLVM engineers.
So we have more flexibility when doing developments,
and the users are clients who are paying for the compiler.
So we needed to provide something good.
The other point is a student LLVM exercises.
I do LLVM courses for security students,
and I want them to be able to do
some code transformation with LLVM.
So the developers are just a friend of mine and me,
and the users are students.
We are expecting them to code into the project.
So we need to make it easy for them to get into,
and we have 16 hours to this project,
and they cannot spend two hours installing LLVM.
It's not going to work either.
So in all this projects,
I'm going to talk pretty much the same issues.
So I'm going to talk about them now.
The first one is keeping up with LLVM.
So I'm not sure if it was intentional in the schedule,
but having a talk for you about CMake and stuff,
it's quite helpful because I don't have to
go too deep in the details.
You already know them.
So let's go back like maybe eight years ago.
You wanted to do some LLVM tools,
as there was no CMake integration.
The first approach that you had as a developer was
either do stuff manually,
maybe using LLVM config to get
the flags and the libraries and so on.
But basically, you had no easy way to
integrate with LLVM. It was quite manual.
Then came CMake, and you could use
the standard add library, target link libraries,
but you had to know what to feed these macros with.
Some stuff I've encountered in this project is
some people who were developing this project,
were not comfortable with CMake,
and they would perform some changes where they would
actually do CMake integration with
our coded passes in the CMake, so it would be a quad.
Basically, now it's, I think,
at least from the examples we have, it's way better.
So using the LLVM CMake integration
simplifies a lot of stuff.
You just have basically to know which component of LLVM you want to use,
how you want to build your library,
like is it static or shared basically,
and you have dedicated macros to just construct
whatever stuff you want to construct for LLVM.
So let's take an example code.
So you don't have to understand everything.
It's just to give an example of how it works.
You basically say, okay,
I want to find LLVM, provide a version, sometimes,
include the LLVM CMake helper,
and include some definition,
and then this is interesting part because you can say, okay,
I want these components in my tool.
Call the CMake helper with your plugin source, and that's it.
I mean, the CMake helper will take care of saying, okay,
depending on how LLVM is installed,
like is it just the big dial-up or are there individual libraries?
It will set up the target link libraries
appropriately and you don't have to think about it.
It's just automatic.
If you want to do some tools or pass plugin,
there are macros to do these two.
So basically, you just have to figure out which kind of build you want,
and CMake LLVM will configure everything for you.
There are some useful examples.
For pass plugins, there is a by example,
which is basically a new pass plugin,
very simple, it's a kind of a hello world.
LLVM tutorials are some out of three passes to get you started with,
and actually quite helpful if you are looking into this.
Now, let's talk about some code.
So let's say you're new to LLVM,
pretty new to C++.
Your students, for instance,
and you want to perform some LLVM transformation.
So you go on your search engine and you look for,
how do I iterate over instructions of LLVM function?
Pretty much all of your resources like StackOverflow or even
some presentations that will give you the code on the left.
So it's fine, it works. I mean, you are iterating over
all the iteration instruction of the function.
But if you know a bit better C++,
you know that you can put runge instead of row iterators.
If you know the instruction iterators from LLVM,
you know that you can use instruction of F to just get all the instruction of F.
All the code works, but arguably,
the codes on the right are easier to read and in the end,
easier to maintain especially if you consider that there are a lot of examples like this in the code.
It adds up and so simplifying stuff is nice sometimes.
So it's not a problem of StackOverflow or anything.
It's just that the answer in StackOverflow on the slides are old like from 2015.
Like if you would update the answer,
it would just be the option on the right.
Another thing I want to talk about and that I've seen a lot in
Parkout is iterating over something,
but putting a predicate like I want to iterate through this stuff,
but only if this stuff is true for some predicate.
So you can do stuff like that,
early continues or nested if.
But if you know the STL extra from LLVM,
you know that you can create filtered range for any range actually.
So you pass a range,
you pass a predicate and inside the loop,
you just get the object you're looking for.
Again, it's a simple predicate,
so it doesn't matter much as is,
but if you add some more stuff,
it starts growing up and maintenance became a bit harder,
readability is impacted too.
So this is something to consider.
Now, something more like a critical,
it's advanced data types.
There are a lot of data types in LLVM.
If you are not familiar with LLVM,
and I've seen a lot of color exists,
you will just use whatever data types is available in the STL,
and you will get a map for instance,
use some helper, and the actual issue starts when input,
the map of instruction,
you want to map an instruction to something.
If you go through the input and
change an instruction like if you delete it,
or if you replace all the uses with some other value,
what happens to the instruction in the map?
So with row map from the STL,
there is no mechanism,
so nothing happened and you end up iterating
of trying to find something which is not valid anymore.
Whereas if you are aware of the data types from LLVM,
you are able to use some kind of value map which has
specific handle to remove the value or
update the value if it is changed during the life of the value.
So some other helpers that are quite nice,
I mean it's not a big deal,
but for instance, instead of using std-fanif,
you can use LLVM-fanif and just put a range
instead of just the individual character.
In this case, it's not a big deal,
but it's actually quite nice.
But basically, every stuff like that,
I've encountered this for a lot of code where
you would be able to replace most of
the occurrences with any vector from
the LLVM advanced data types or a array for string graph.
There are a lot of stuff in LLVM that you may not be aware of,
and that makes your code quite nicer if you use them.
So yeah, dealing with it.
So you may think, okay,
this guy is just being picky with
people who are writing the code. It may be true.
I would argue that it depends on
actually who makes the contribution because you cannot
expect the same level of contribution from
a student or from an LLVM engineer.
Especially when you're a PhD student,
you have a, I don't know, a deadline,
you just want a tool who does something.
You're not going to spend times and times on how you do stuff,
as long as it works.
At least that's my experience dealing with that.
But in my opinion, the accumulation of small details matters,
and it was very explicit in the case of
Barcoach because I came after maybe five,
six years where the accumulation of researchers and PhD students
led to a lot of technical depth.
If there was some advice that were given
to the PhD students or the researcher,
it would have been a way nicer code to read or to maintain.
It's quite obvious, but doing code reviews helps a lot.
Sometimes you cannot do them if there is no one
able to actually provide some useful feedback on this.
Like in the case when people don't know LLVM,
you cannot expect them to review code and
provide some a lot of feedback.
But what I do know is I
redirect every time to the LLVM programmers manual.
It's not like the first thing you do.
Usually, you just go to a search engine and search for what you want.
But I will argue that actually reading
the programmer manual is more helpful in that specific case.
Some things that I know people don't want to
do when they are starting LLVM is just
read the code from the past using LLVM.
There are a lot of good stuff in there.
Obviously, if you're not familiar with C++ and LLVM,
it's not the easiest,
but I think it's still worth it.
So the next topic is updating the LLVM versions.
So far when I've developed out of two tools,
I've always set the version to one specific number.
Let's say LLVM 9.
Then when LLVM 10 comes out,
you rebase your plugin and check if any API broke.
Either was some changes in the IR.
Most recently, I am thinking about Opac pointers.
It was quite a big change when updating the LLVM version.
Something to consider when doing this is that it may be time consuming.
A lot of time can be spent in,
it may be just a day if there were no changes in the API.
But it could also be very time consuming.
For instance, if you have to change all your passes because it's been
three years that the new pass manager was out and you still didn't do the migration,
and now suddenly it's deprecated and it's going to be removed.
So you need to migrate your passes.
So you have to do it.
In my experience, it's quite obvious too,
but skipping versions makes it worse.
Sorry. Something that I've seen,
and I know sometimes it cannot be avoided,
but in that case it was avoidable.
But basically trying to support multiple LLVM versions at once.
Like say support from LLVM 9 through 12,
it's actually what was done.
Don't do it. If you can, just don't do it.
It's a pick a version and stay like this because otherwise,
it's just multiple if-def and everyone
is going to code and it's a unmaintainable, I think.
So now, let's talk about passes.
If you look for a Hello World pass on the Internet,
you will get a Hello World pass which is a transformation pass.
So in LLVM, you have two kinds of passes.
One was the first kind is analysis,
and basically they don't touch the IR.
You just look at the IR and maybe provide some result,
which is a result of the analysis and that can be
used by transformation passes or other analysis.
There are the transformation passes
which may or may not change the IR.
Obviously, when you get your Hello World pass,
you want to do everything in it.
I'm not talking about LLVM developers,
but I'm talking about students and researchers that have
the pass and they put everything in it.
So it's fine when it's just
one shot or something like that,
but in the time at some point,
both the analysis and the transformations
are semantically different and LLVM has some mechanism
to make it easy for you to have
the analysis run only when it's needed.
There is a caching mechanism.
You can say, okay, I want this analysis for this object,
and if it exists, it will give it back to you.
Also, it avoids the passing structure around
because when you are in a transformation pass,
you can request any analysis from basically anywhere
as long as you have the analysis manager.
So this is something that have cost me quite some time,
like just untangling the analysis code from the transformation code,
and overall, it's improved the performances
because some analysis were requested more than once for the same object.
So yes, it leads me to
investigating performance issues because it was something too.
So what happens when you don't know LLVM and you want to debug your code?
You put LLVM errors everywhere and you
come on them out when your code is ready.
Okay. So it's a nightmare.
I mean, it works, but you're not supposed to do it like this.
So specifically for like a printf-like debug stuff,
you have some LLVM helper.
It's actually quite handy.
You just put a debug type somewhere and you dot CPP.
You wrap everything in LLVM debug because it does all the thing for you.
If you don't include the debug information,
it doesn't even appear in the binary.
When you're running your path with ops,
you can say, okay, I want to show
the big information for this kind of path.
Basically, provide the same feature and you don't have to come out LLVM errors.
The other thing is timing your code,
being able to tell, okay,
this part of the transformation is costing me time.
So what I've seen was some manual attempt to do timers,
and basically, you declare all the timers,
you start them manually and it start being a mess really quick.
Hopefully, now we have a time trace scope.
It was, I think it's what's used when you use F-time trace when starting Clang.
So basically, it's just one line.
You put one variable and when it's constructed,
it starts a scope and it starts a timer and when it's disrupted,
it stops the timer.
LLVM has a whole system for this and it emits a GZON.
If you put this GZON in a speed scope,
you get something like that.
You can see basically everything in your code without having to do anything.
You get the entry points,
you get the analysis, and here it was quite obvious for us,
was the changes, what the changes were,
because this analysis for instance was called multiple times.
But it was for the same objects.
So for instance, it would appear here too.
But because of the caching mechanism and the untangling,
it basically just was just called once.
So this is something nice that you get basically for free.
So now, some conclusion on the tool developments.
So it's a fairly basic conclusion.
Try to invest in maintenance.
I know it's not always possible,
especially in a scientific project, but it's worth it.
Don't remember the wheel. If you want to do something in LLVM,
it likely has already something in LLVM for this.
Keep the dish minimal.
One of the main weakness of Power Coach right now is that we
use some passes which exist already in LLVM.
I'm thinking about memory SSA, for instance,
we use some copy of this and from a maintenance point of view,
it's not quite nice so we need to migrate this away.
If your passes can be useful to others,
just try to upstream them.
If you don't use them, you don't have to pay for them.
Then let's talk a bit about usability,
because it's quite a big deal for a tool,
because you want it to be usable.
So first, from a developer point of view,
if your developers are going to be non-LVM folks,
you don't want them to go into the LLVM install and stuff.
So I've had good experience with using Docker
and basically provide a Docker image with
the LLVM compiled install somewhere
or just install using the app repositories.
Have some clear CI like how to build your tool,
like just looking at the CI should be enough to know how to
build your tool from a developer point of view.
The other great thing is when you use LLVM,
you get LLVM tools with it.
So you get the lead and fight check.
So instead of going through some manual testing and stuff,
you can just use them and it's actually quite nice.
Yes, of course, I could talk about coding standards,
but basically since you're making a plug-in or a tool for LLVM,
it makes sense to follow the same standard and you have
already clung format and clung tidy configuration for this.
Now as a user,
you obviously don't want
scientific application developer to compile your code from source.
You want them to just have the plug-in and use it or have the tool and use it.
If you look at Hello World passes,
you see a lot of times that you have to first get the IR.
So in our case, it's either from clung or from flung.
You have to call up,
load the path manually and call the path manually.
So I would argue this is not nice enough for researchers and students.
Since Barcoach is a verification tool,
we cannot expect users to call it on every single file.
So we actually had to do some more tooling to create some wrapper,
which takes original compiler invocation,
runs the original compiler invocation,
generates a temporary IR and then runs a tool over it.
It makes it much more easy for the users to just integrate with the other tools or to make.
So that makes the tool more user friendly than I would say is unusual.
The other part is how do you get the tool?
So again, I've had good experience with Docker,
especially for students because it's easy for them.
Sometimes, obviously, we also provide some package for major distributions,
but you actually have to worry about how is LLVM packaged on the target system,
because depending on what is available,
how easy chair libraries, dialyman stuff,
it's not the same thing.
And yeah, Docker, it's not something you can quite use on shared HPC clusters.
You're more looking at stuff like Geeks,
for instance, when targeting such platforms.
So for this, you need some packaging.
And packaging is my last pointer.
So obviously, we used to do it yourself approach,
basically just create a shared library and hope for the best.
It doesn't work because you depend on how opt is installed and compiled,
because you're loading dynamically a library into opt.
So if you have not used the same like C++ libraries,
you're going to run into issues.
You don't know for sure which path manager is enabled by default in opt.
So there's also this.
So we've moved to doing some proper packages for APT,
the dev and for Geeks and for Red Hat too,
because we have some users using some custom version of Red Hat.
And for this, we actually have quite an interesting issue,
because we are sure that the LL version in their image is not available.
So we made the choice of shipping just one single static tool.
And for this, it was actually quite easy, because as I said when I talked about CMake,
you just say, okay, I want this to be statically or as a shared library and
the LLVM CMake handles it for you.
And it was quite a nice experience for us to package for so
many distribution without having to worry too much about CMake option and stuff.
So some takeaways for the whole talk.
In my opinion, the LLVM integration has evolved a lot and in a good direction.
It's way easier to integrate with LLVM now than it was 10 years ago.
It's nice, but it's nice to say it because when nice stuff happens, you have to say it too.
Be prepared for maintenance.
If you want to create a note of tool, you have to invest in maintenance both for LLVM rebases,
basically reviews and make sure that your contributors,
if you are able to provide some LLVM guidance to your contributors, do it and it's worth it.
Investing in CI is worth it, obviously.
And LLVM documentation, I would definitely every day recommend
going to the LLVM documentation rather than Google for understanding what is available in LLVM.
And yeah, I'm encouraged by students to read the LLVM source code, but it's sometimes a bit hard.
So if you have questions or comments, feel free and I will be happy to answer them.
Yeah.
Yes.
So the question is for the wrapper we created, what do we use to create this wrapper, right?
So basically it's a very, very small LLVM tool.
Maybe you are familiar with not in LLVM.
There is a very small utility in LLVM which just does not on the return of a program.
And it's a very small LLVM tool based on LLVM.
And we use a similar approach.
Basically we say, okay, I created basically an empty main where I just use the LLVM support
library to get the benefit from like argument parsing and the data types and so on.
And I just pass the command line and call successfully clone the original compiler line.
And then I just generate the intermediate representation for it by adding the appropriate
flag and filtering out the other object generation flags.
And then I just run the tool over it.
Yes.
Yes, because you can just, for instance, with CMake you can use the CMake C launcher.
Basically just like C cache work for LLVM, you just change the launcher and you can use
the tool to launch the compiler.
And for all two tools you can actually, actually in our project we use MPICC,
but we are able to change the compiler used for MPICC and say, okay, use instead of
a package clone instead of GDC, for instance.
And the first point was,
so the question is, when you ship your tool, do you link statically or dynamically?
Basically, yeah. So both, actually both.
When shipping for Radatz, because we don't have a control over what package are in their custom
image, we ship statically because we are not sure which LLVM we are going to have.
So we just, the binary is 100 megabytes, but we don't have a much choice.
And when shipping for system like Ubuntu or Debian, we just ship that with the dependence on the shared libraries.
Yes?
So the question is, when we're basing the tool from one LL version to the next one,
do you use the change log developers put their love into?
And if yes, is it helpful?
Unfortunately, the answer is no.
But that's because I look at the LLVM weakles, so I kind of know what happens.
This is just my way of doing stuff.
Yeah, so no, but if I would look into the change log, I would find helpful information, I'm sure.
So the question is, am I trying to rebase as LLVM progresses,
or am I just rebasing every version when it's released? And it's only when a release
comes out, I do the rebase. It's easier because otherwise, you know, some, yeah, I mean,
you know the stuff, depending on what kind of target you ship for, it's hard.
And it's just simpler to say, okay, we know and then, like, we know we need to rebase a version, and it's fine.
Thank you.