Next up we have Peter Smith who will talk about using LLVM to create embedded toolchains.
Hello, my name is Peter and thank you all very much for staying up so late. It's almost
bedtime. So I'll be here to talk about embedded toolchains using LLVM. So first thing I want
to clarify is what do I actually mean by an embedded toolchain. Now as some of the people
here earlier on were talking about sanitizers and we mentioned Yocto and embedded Linux.
That's way too high level. This is basically for bare metal embedded systems. So yeah,
so typical this is for those of you already know this, I'm sorry, but for those of you
aren't necessarily familiar about what some of the differences are. So typically when
you're developing on say Linux or Mac or Windows, whatever you're developing with the knowledge
of an operating system. So when you implement your C library, you already know you can use
system calls. You know, if you want to get some more memory, you ask the operating system,
that type of thing. So by contrast on the embedded system, you don't have an operating
system. You can ask for memory. So you basically have to roll part of that into the C library,
that type of thing. So also when you're actually programming, you're programming on the device,
you're actually running the program on embedded systems, you're cross compiling. That is one
thing that is likely shared with Yocto and embedded Linux because quite often you're
cross compile for speed on that one there. Typically you'll be static linking only because
your either your your RTOS probably doesn't have a dynamic linker at that particular point.
And your RTOS might actually just be a library that you link into your program, that type
of thing. So yeah, so platform when you if you're on on the Linux, you might be using
glib C that type of thing and that will be platform. And then you just use you when you
have a tool chain, you might just need to provide a compiler and everything's there
for you. Embedded systems, everything's just you have to do everything or yourself. I will
mention one word there freestanding. So there is a definition in the C plus standard of
what freestanding means. It's a little loose. It kind of says this is basically what the
minimum you have to supply, but that's practically useless unless you want to write a full C
plus plus stand implementation yourself. So in effect, what happens is that most embedded
C libraries tend to roll half of an operating system into themselves, at least basically
the minimum from there. So that's what we're sort of talking about by an embedded tool
chain.
OK, so this is the thing we already have embedded tool chains. What why do we need LLVM essentially
at this particular point? So this is some of the reasons why you might actually want
to use LLVM over say something like GCC. So first of all, clang is kind of a natural cross
compiler. So you don't actually have to say, gather GCC for arm GCC for S5 GCC for a out
of 64. You just have one clang. Now that is quite useful if you're a team where you don't
want to use different compilers, different installations. That's I guess more administrative
more than anything, but it can be a benefit on some places. So code generation can also
be more mature. And I will say be safe of fairness, sometimes less mature than GCC,
for example. So when my is it obviously for somebody who works for arm or my examples
of a mom just because that's what I know. But I'm sure there are similar sort of things
on other architectures as well. So an example here, V8.1n, which is one of arms most recent
sort of CPUs for embedded systems, has got a vector extension. And basically, clang has
got better support for auto vectorization for this than GCC, just simply because the
work was done earlier, that type of thing. But that's just one of the examples where
if you've got that particular target, you might want to use that. Whereas if you've
got a different target, GCC might be better at the moment. Other thing is taking advantage
of some of the tooling that clang provides. So I'm going to go into in the next few slides
how you might be able to use some of the sanitizers. I know we kind of said in the early bit this
morning that we were talking particularly about MSAN and ASAN, that type of thing. And
those typically have quite a high runtime component. But there are sanitizers that you
can use without that. And I'll just go through a few of those here. And finally, you've got
diversity of implementation. Running more compilers is almost always good. Compilers
find different sets of bugs. And sometimes programs find different sets of compilers.
Sorry? Yeah. I was working recently on safety critical application for train. Yeah. You
actually have to implement several processes doing different things. Yeah. So having two
different compilers is a good thing in that application. Yes, definitely. Yes. And certainly
you can different programs find different compiler bugs as well. That sort of thing.
So yeah. OK. So do you think sanitizers are embedded systems? So we kind of run through
some of this earlier on today. So the main restriction of sanitizers is that it's not
actually the code generation. It's actually the run times. So if you look at the runtime
for ASAN, it's basically using a dynamic shared object to intercept the C library. It's got
all sorts of bits that are kind of operating system dependent. But of course, in embedded,
you don't have an operating system. So it's very hard as a tool chain vendor to provide
a kind of bare metal thing that doesn't depend on one very specific example. But some of
the sanitizers have a very minimal runtime. And some of these things you can use here.
So I'm just going to go through some of these here right now. So the first one to use is
the undefined behavior sanitizer. So by default, that does have a runtime. But all that runtime
effectively doing is pretty printing a nice error. But if you don't care about pretty
printing a nice error, you might not even have a printer. So at this particular case,
then you can just say, OK, well, if there's undefined behavior in my program and someone's
trying to attack me, maybe that's a bad thing. So maybe I just want to abort, say, for example,
if I've gotten an out of range runtime. This particular example is just using a very standard
integer overflow detection. And basically, look on there, all it's really doing is just
saying check for overflow. If I overflow, branch to an undefined instruction that just
happens to cause an abort on the processor, that type of thing. So yes, crash your program.
There's also a minimal runtime. So there is a default implementation to the minimal runtime
in compiler RT. You can't use that directly on an embedded system. But you can basically
write your own. So instead of actually calling, well, going branching to an undefined instruction,
it just calls a user defined function. And you can basically make that do whatever you
want. There are ones for log and continue, and there's ones for log and terminate, that
type of thing. But basically, the choice is yours. But those functions have got extremely
trivial implementations that you can make work for an embedded system.
Next one here is the kernel control flow integrity. And it's called KFCI. And I keep calling it
KFC. I've even got this to write right around it. And it's actually, I think I've even got
it wrong on the slide, which is embarrassing. I should actually be KCFI at that particular
point. So there is a control flow sanitizer that can work with embedded systems right
now. That's the sort of the full facts. I'll call it sanitizer. But that requires link
time optimization. So the advantage of the kernel control flow integrity sanitizer is
it doesn't need LTO, which makes which if anyone's tried to use LTO on embedded systems,
it works until you've got a linker script. Certainly, we're a linker script that depends
on placing things in different places. So yeah, so here's just a very trivial example
of something that's just calling a floating point. And this just shows some of the code
that's generated. So what we essentially have is this function pointer has a type. And you
can basically make that into a signature. So what happens is we prefix at the top of
the function with the signature. And then we basically load when we're sort of saying,
well, let's load from this arbitrary function pointer. Well, let's check its signature.
And then we'll check to see if it matches what we want. And if it doesn't, boom. So
this doesn't, as far as I know, work on C++ tables at the moment. Obviously, this is implemented
for the Linux kernel. So they don't care about C++. But if you're using C with function
pointers, this is a relatively low cost way to get control flow integrity checking. So
this is just some of the things that the components have embedded toolchain. I'm kind of jumping
around here at the moment. So these are sort of things you would expect in a GCC embedded
toolchain. And as you can see, Clang's actually, well, LLVM project. We've got pretty much
all that we need in one place. We're only really missing a C library at the moment.
So yeah, as we can go through some of the, I won't go through each individual thing in
those titles, but you've got Clang, the compiler, you've got LLD, the linker, you've got implementations
of Obsdump, read-elf, you've got implementations of the C++ runtime library. Yes, say what
we're missing is a C library. So technically, GCC doesn't have a C library either. But there
are hooks in the build system to basically build new lib in sort of multi-lib configurations
at that point. LLVM is developing a C library. I would say at the moment, currently, it's
sort of focused on what you would probably call desktop use cases. But they are planning
to have sort of scalable implementations. So I think the end goal is that it will be
able to cope with embedded systems, but I expect that to be some years down the line
at the moment. So how would you actually assemble one of these building, basically assemble
an LLVM toolchain from the LLVM project? And the honest answer is it's not as easy as it
could be. Certainly when you're building a sort of a hosted toolchain, it's just, it's
fairly easy. You just go to LLVM, CMake, Ninja, done. So actually building the tools is not
difficult because they're all cross compilers. They're just all part of the default build.
So if you want to get all the tools, very, very simple. Building the run times is a bit
more difficult because you've got to cross compile the run times and you've got to do
them in a particular order. Not all of them build in all of the things. So one of the
big problems if you say try and buy a compiler, sorry, if you try and compile compiler RT,
it'll fail because you've not got all of the, you know, it's kind of, if you try, it'll
end up building the sanitizers and the sanitizers obviously have got dependencies on POSIX operating
systems, which of course won't work. But you can say, for example, build the built-ins,
which are kind of like the libGCC equivalent. So what we've done at Arm is to put together
an embedded toolchain for Cortex-M, which is the sort of Arm's microcontroller range.
And this is essentially a set of build scripts. It's all open source. And we're using the
Pico libc at the moment as our C library. We did start with new lib, but we sort of moved
on to Pico lib at that point, but you can make it work with new lib if you want to.
So we've got, it's primarily just build scripts. It's not like got an LLVM project embedded
on that. It will just go fetch LLVM from the actual source code. And yes, it's got a few
samples for building some programs, that type of thing. So as I say, it's by Arm for Arm,
but I'm sure if anybody wanted to apply it to a different microprocessor, they pretty
much could, because it's essentially just a bit of CMake that you can adapt.
So what's the usability of an LLVM toolchain like next to, say, the GNU-embedded toolchain,
that type of thing? So one of the main things we're missing at the moment is multi-lib support.
Now there are some multi-lib support for certain targets. So for example, I think there are
some RISC-V multi-libs that are already in the bare metal driver, but that's not the
case for Arm at the moment. I'll go on to what we're doing about that in a few slides
time. Clang also doesn't have a direct equivalent of GCC specs files. So specs files are basically
just fragments of command line, but they're not just raw command lines. They have got
some intelligence and they can talk to each other and override defaults. So as an example
here, that nano.spec and rdimon.spec, that says, give me newlib nano, which is the really
small version of newlib. And rdimon is the semi-hosted version, which is easier to run
on emulators, that type of thing. So for the LLVM-embedded toolchain, we basically, because
we don't have the information for the specs file to say, ah, someone has someone added
this other specs file, so I'm going to modify my behaviors. We have to basically have multiple
config files that just blow up for all of the possible combinations. So as you see there,
we've got an Arm V6M, which ideally would be handled by multi-lib in DMD semi-host version.
And yeah, there's just more configuration files than you really ought to have. And I
would say there's probably a small, well, there's a long tail of small incompatibilities.
You might find that LLD doesn't do orphan placement exactly the same way as GNU-LD does,
that type of thing. But normally these sort of small incompatibilities, you can kind of
code around it. There's normally a way you can make it work. So that's what we found
so far anyway. So this is just, again, another jumping around, just showing you how Clang
might do some of this sort of stuff. So if any of you have played around with Clang drivers,
whenever you give them the target triple, so normally if you're using Clang on your
Linux, your target triple is native, I guess, at this particular point. Or you're using
the default triple that's there. But if you're doing cross compilation, you have to give
it a sort of architecture environment. So you've got the Linux-GnU there. So this is
actually one if you were targeting something like the Octo, that type of thing. And that
will, Clang driver will then tell you where all of your header files are, what your target
features are. So it's like a much low level using sort of private command line options
at that particular one. So for what we find for embedded systems is that Clang has added
something probably a few years ago, but it's sort of only recently sort of getting a bit
more development onto it. In particular, the multi-lib support for RISC-V came in fairly
recently. And that's when you have a target that the bare metal handles. So far, that's
only ARM-A out 64 and RISC-V at the moment. But this, in theory, could be added for any
other target, that type of thing. If you happen to be doing bare metal development on an X86
and you don't match, say, a Linux operating system or BSD or whatever, you end up getting
forwarded to the generic GCC driver, which basically throws everything at GCC, which
generally knows what to do about things. So as long as you've got a GCC toolchain, if
you give an object file to GCC, GCC will say, oh, I'll just fire that at the linker, that
type of thing. So it will work itself out. OK, yeah. So I've just basically repeated
what I've just said there. It will default to the LLVM tools at that particular point.
So as for the last part of the talk, I just want to go to some of the ongoing work that's
happening in Clang and some of the community involvement that's going on here. So one of
the first and probably the major bit of work that we're doing at the moment is what I'm
going to call data-driven multi-lib at the moment. So currently, multi-lib support in
Clang is hard-coded. It's basically a C++ class where you basically describe what the
multi-lib will do for that. Now, that works pretty well if you're doing things like 32
or 64-bit x86 in, say, Debian or Red Hat, because the structures are well-known at that particular
point and they are stable. Whereas there's no way every possible embedded toolchain with
every possible library variant that you might want to do could get that hard-coded in upstream
Clang. So typically what you find is that every toolchain based on LLVM has its own
downstream patch if it wants to support multi-lib. So GCC allows you to set this up at configure
time and the GCC way basically maps command line options onto directories. So for Clang,
we can do a bit better because the Clang driver has a bit more scope to, say, do things like
target parser and find out more about what the CPU can do. So at the moment, we're kind
of proposing that you kind of have a stacked tower of multi-libs where you can kind of
– almost like a Docker container file where you get each sort of can override the next
so that you can basically describe what your multi-lib configuration is and then Clang will
be able to take this configuration file. So it will basically allow people to have multi-lib
toolchains without having to hard-code them in downstream patches, that type of thing.
So this is still in active development. There's an RFC that went up probably a few weeks ago.
Recently there's some links to the patches and that sort of thing. So please do, if you're
interested in data-driven multi-lib and how it develops, please do comment on those patches
and the RFC.
So future work. So we'd ideally like to get some upstream build bots for some of the compiler
RT runtimes. So whilst there are build bots for AART64 and ARM Linux, we haven't got
build bots for, say, the built-ins for, say, the V6M, V7M, the very low-level embedded
sort of targets. And we think that would be good to – well, obviously more build bots
the better, I think, at that particular point. There is some work going on at TI, and that
link to YouTube is to a presentation from the – at the last LLVM developer meeting,
basically adding attributes from the linker script so that you can tell – you can basically
say things like, this section must go in this place, this output section, this one must
go in this other one. Please do not cross module inline across these boundaries because
these things might not be in memory at the same time, that type of thing. So – and
also I need this section to have this particular name, so please don't give it a different
name or merge it, that type of thing. So that should be able to make LTO much more usable
with linker scripts. And what we tend to find with Clang is that if you get it right, LTO
is very aggressive at removing code that's not needed. So that's actually very good
for code size if you can make it work. Certainly we've seen – you know, for benchmarks,
LTO is great, but then we say to customers, hey, use LTO, and he goes, ah, but we can't
because of the linker script, that type of thing. Next one is not strictly embedded,
but it is very important for the safety critical industry, which often is, you know, by definition
embedded because you're controlling some kind of hardware. And this is something called
MCDC code coverage. And that is kind of a special form of code coverage where you're
kind of – if you can imagine something like IF and then A, B, C, D, E, E, it's a way
of sort of deriving test cases so that – so it's not quite exhaustive, but it covers
more than just did this branch go this way or this way. It's like did it go this way
because this condition held that type of thing. Hopefully that's not going to show up too
much there. And, yes, so there's a patch in for generating that in the code coverage
thing. And obviously, LRVM libc developing, and we would like that to support embedded
systems. Okay. I'll skip through this very quickly. There's some patches up for big
endian support. If anyone actually uses big endian, I don't know. I'll be rude there.
There's an armed person in the way. Almost all arms a little endian. And then there's
the Cortex-M security extensions, which are, you know, that's very useful if you're trying
to sort of have secure state and non-secure state. So that supports an LLD. Again, if
anyone wants to comment on those patches, please do. Okay. Okay. So finally, if you
do want to contribute to this, and this is not just as a developer, we're perfectly happy
to have contributions from users as well, or just in some ways just telling us what's
important. So Clang has pretty much come out of what I call the hosted community. You know,
it's generally, at least as now, I would say there's a lot fewer people in the embedded
system, embedded systems area than there is on GCC. So if you, you know, there are certain
features that are useful in embedded tool chains, but not necessarily in say, say, hosted
tool chains. So just telling the community that you need these features is often helpful
because quite often it will say, why do we need all this complexity for this thing? No
one's going to use it. And it's like, well, and you can only get people who only get used
to features if they're there, but then you can't get them in, you know, chicken and egg
situation there. So yeah, so there is a full weekly call that goes on, unfortunately, at
a time slot that's not great for Europeans, but this is the only sort of time slot you
can kind of get across US and Europe together at that particular point. So that's probably
about I'd say about 20 people turn up. And that's really just about the various people
are working on embedded systems. And if they want to sort of highlight patches that want
to be reviewed, discuss new features. Last time we were talking about how we might improve
LLDs and observability of diagnostics, that type of thing. Obviously bug reports welcome
those links. And obviously, if you attend the developer meetings, there's often a round
table on embed systems at that point. And with that, that's my last slide. So hopefully
we've got a few minutes for questions.
I'm trying to understand something I know of some people who say that they're using
LLVM for embedded already. Yeah.
Does this mean that they're using the other definition of embedded?
So there's two, well, you can do it. There'll be three ways they can do it. One of them
is they're kind of using an LLVM based tool chain from a vendor. So that vendor will have
done all of that packaging up. Or it will be, like for example, Arm will sell you a commercial
tool chain that is a derivative of Clang. That type of thing. That's one way of doing
it, that sort of thing. Or they might be using embedded Linux. That type of thing. Yeah.
The question was, sorry, I've been holding up a picture all day saying, please repeat
the question. I didn't. And that's the question was that some people say they're already using
LLVM. Does that mean they were using a hosted system or not? Okay. Yes. Sorry. Go to the
back. Yes. So one of the things I noticed is LLVM ships, it's on the Sember. Yeah. We've
noticed for some embedded projects that they have trouble with some of the newer Sember
macros. So we have to use, have to fall back to the inter-tool changes for some targets.
Is there some plans for work on this?
So there was, with the latest LLVM, I know, sorry, repeat the question. Yeah. So the question
was the LLVM has an integrated Sember, GNU has GNU AS. And there are some directives
or macro support that might be in the GNU Sember but not LLVM. So I think it's generally
done on demand. So there was a big effort to get the Linux kernel compiled with Clang.
And that added quite a lot of features that were basically needed for the Linux kernel.
So the best thing to do is have a really important project that's a big company, wants to get
compiled with the integrated Sember. Yes. And then, yes. That is a very good way of
doing it.
As macros were in the Linux kernel and they asked us to support them and say, no, screw
this, the kernel changed away from macros. And they changed away from macros.
Yeah. But there certainly was support. I think there is a directive where you can switch
the GNU Sember into advanced macro mode or something like that. I can't remember.
No, that's not that. That's an inline assembly thing. There is an, yes, there is a highness
GNU extensions option. But no, there was a patch that probably landed a few years ago.
So depending on how long ago you tried, then there was some support done for more macros.
But whether it's got all of it or not, I don't know.
Well, I forgot what the problem was a while ago.
Right. So you may find that someone has already fixed that already. Yes. Thank you.
Yeah. So my question is about like we, for example, try to deploy machine learning models
on tiny bare metal devices.
Yeah.
And then there we are also looking into, for example, TVM as a tool chain, but also MLIR
now, like the EV project from Google.
Yeah.
And they're basically what they do is they use this entire tool chain and then they use
the MHC dialect, for example, in EV to MHC code again.
Okay.
To then put it into an embedded tool chain to actually do the final compilation stuff.
Do you think that there is, or what is basically needed to omit this last going back to C
or is this a good idea or not?
Oh, well, I mean, I suppose I'm just trying to think, think how, not very familiar.
The question was about people deploying machine learning models on small devices and they're
currently outputting to a C back end and then recompiling that C back end.
And do I think this is a good idea or not?
I mean, I guess the C back ends are often the how do I get this up and running as quickly
as possible.
I do know that there are, I guess, machine learning compilers that have got, I guess,
code generation out.
I mean, I guess if you're using LLVM itself, it's probably not too difficult to just lower
to LLVM and get most, and you then get the code generation for free.
I guess the bit that you might not get is, have you got all of the, the runtime and intrinsics
that you might have that the C compiler might insert, but you might find someone else in
this way.
So maybe just in addition, it does not compile the whole machine learning models to C, so
they are still a static library linked in which is generated via LLVM.
It's just some parts around.
So it's not that there is a pure C in the end.
That's not done in the approach.
Okay.
Yes.
I was one of those unfortunate uses of a big ambient arm.
We were running several compilers in the safety critical application.
Everyone had a problem with one thing, and that's the linker.
We're trying to generate the header.
And the linker, you called insert the text string in the linker.
It's very difficult to insert static data.
We want to insert information about how large is the section.
Right.
With great difficulty, I think, I think there isn't really a, there isn't, I think the,
yeah, I think Christophe has nailed it in that what I would probably do myself is reserve
some space in the binary, name a section out of it, and then use objdump to poke it in
that particular part.
Yes.
No, but.
You see my problem?
No.
Yes.
I mean, there are some.
Putting a string in the linker command file.
Well, it's a bit, well, it's a bit more difficult.
It's the, I think the linker needs to know the lengths.
I mean, I suppose you could do it with horrifying things.
You could use data statements in the linker script.
But that sounds, it's really what you would want it.
You really.
Yes.
I really, I think, yeah, because you get a number.
But really, yeah, I suppose, yeah, found an extension request of a linker script.
Yeah.
I think we do have the problem.
We do have a problem with things like build ID.
I think at that particular point where you're generating the build ID string, which, which
it needs to know everything all at once.
But yeah, I get, I, yeah, unfortunately there's nothing in the LLD linker.
I think someone should try to generate the header for a binary, put in the interesting
information.
But you quickly realize all the problems.
Oh, yeah, sure.
But no assembler has the ink bin.
Yes, it does.
The assembler does have ink bin, but I think the idea is for the header, you want the linker
to generate something based on the properties of something.
You want to generate the information about the link time, not when you assembled it
two weeks ago.
You can, you can assemble just before the link step, assemble something that's generated.
It's an, it's an double file and then link that in using a link script.
I know there are workarounds, but a good workaround would have to have a good link.
Yeah.
I mean, I think, I think, I mean, there's a lot of times with linkers, it's the, because
one of the, one of the perennial things you get asked is how do I embed some kind of custom
checksum that I've written at link time, you know, that type of thing.
And it's just which one and do you then have a linker Python script extension or plugin?
It just tends to build.
Yeah.
Check some afterwards.
And that's also something that should be supported in linker.
Yeah.
And it could be done just say, run this application afterwards on the section.
So, so it's.
I mean, I guess.
I mean, I guess it's, I mean, to, I mean, to paraphrase, I guess it's the tools are
supposed to make users life easier, I suppose, at that particular point.
So if it's a common enough thing to do, then it should be, they should be able to find
a way of doing it.
And if this is security, then you don't want to generate the checksum in one process and
then use it the other process.
You want to use all in one because I know who generated this.
They didn't come from outside.
We actually have to have two different programs in this application.
Yeah.
So, I wait, so I better go for.
So, I, I'm not in all the other.
Yeah.
I deal with a lot of built-in stuff.
Is anyone working on stuff to make things better?
Essentially, like, you're talking about communicating between the mild stage and the line stage,
and introducing dependencies to what you've accomplished, and then you have to link with
that to that stage.
Right.
And now, like, it seems like you need like a schema, a data format, and a dependency
specification for that.
And then, you have to use it and spare the users who have to deal with all this crap.
Nice.
The, the incentive.
I mean, I, I, I think the, the, the, the, the, I say it's mostly a, what I would call
almost a coordination problem between getting the right people on board at that particular
point and it's, so it's quite.
I need the question.
Sorry.
Yes.
Okay.
So, the question, question was about, is anybody working on build systems?
And things that able to be able to communicate the, of the linker to be able to communicate
to the build system and automate things like the checksum sort of handling and that type
of thing.
I mean, I think the, the major difficulty is just, LLVM's an open source project and
there's often, as soon as you open something like that up, it ends up in lots and lots
of discussions about what the right way, and you can easily find a way that works for one,
a small number of people, but completely doesn't work for someone else.
So it's one of those.
It first of all needs someone brave enough to actually try it rather than just implementing
it downstream.
So I think it's, what it really needs in this case is, because this is sort of things that,
this is not, it really needs people to go on the LLVM mailing list and say, yes, we
really need this.
Because typically this sort of thing is to silent people who say, oh, this stuff's all
rubbish, but we don't, as developers, we don't get to hear about it.
Or at least we don't get to hear it, hear about it loud enough for the people who pay
our wages to say, go and work on it.
Yeah.
Right.
Okay.
I probably ought to hold it there to let everyone go.
Thank you very much for staying.
I'll tell you after.
Thank you very much.