Yeah, I hope you had a great Fostem so far.
I'm happy to talk about how to build your own MLIR dialect.
So just as a first question, who is aware of what MLIR actually is?
Who have heard of the MLIR subproject?
Awesome.
So it's not the whole audience, so I'm going to talk a little bit more about what MLIR
is.
So my outline is, yeah, what is MLIR actually, but I only have a really short slide on that.
I will show you the standalone example which exists in the MLIR or in the LLVM repository
as part of the MLIR project.
And I will tell you a little bit more about how you can extend it, how you can build your
own dialect, because following the discussions on discourse and discord, it always seems
like people hitting the same pain points, at least we did several times.
So that's why I set up this kind of tutorial to show you some of the tricks behind, mainly
from the CMake perspective, which is some kind of tricky sometimes.
So beside that, how to build it, I show you how you can combine it with other dialects.
And last but not least, how to extend your dialect with types or attributes.
And just as a side note, all code snippets are, of course, licensed under Apache 2 with
LLVM exceptions.
So what is MLIR?
MLIR is actually a reusable compiler infrastructure that was introduced by Google in 2019, early
2019, and at the end of 2019, Google donated it to the LLVM Foundation, so it's officially
part of the LLVM project, and there it lives in the main, in the monorepo MLIR.
And what it allows you is to define operations, attributes, and types which are grouped in
so-called dialects, and that lets you define your own intermediate representation.
Later on in the session, we will also have an update about the flank compiler, which
also uses MLIR to define its own intermediate representation.
And these dialects can be part either of MLIR core, meaning they are in upstream, like the
funk dialect, which gives you the ability to define what a function is, or there's also
an LLVM IR dialect, which actually mirrors what LLVM IR is, but it is modeled in MLIR
– sorry, what LLVM IR is, but it is modeled in MLIR.
There are tons of other dialects, like a GPU dialect, a TOSR dialect, which is the Tensor
Operate Set Architecture, or a MTC, which I am one of the developers behind.
There are also many, many out-of-tree dialects, like the SOC project is using it, or Torch
MLIR, which is actually modeling PyTorch in MLIR, many, many more, and these are considered
as out-of-tree.
So when we look at the standalone example, which is really a brilliant starter when you
want to create your own dialect, you find it as part of the LLVM MonoRepository, and
you can just build it against an installed LLVM, you can just run CMake, configure it
accordingly, you just need a path where you find your installed MLIR and where the LLVM
external lit is present, and actually then you can just build your target, which is here
– check standalone, it builds all the tools, and further runs some tests.
This actually assumes, as I have mentioned, that LLVM and MLIR are built here and built
here, and then they are installed to prefix.
And that corresponds to out-of-tree somehow, and for me, when I began with LLVM or MLIR,
I was not a compiler developer, but I had some experience in CMake, and how these terms
out-of-tree are used in LLVM and MLIR and the outer world are sometimes confusing, so
I want to give at least a short definition.
So in the LLVM world, Intree also often or nearly every time refers to a monolithic build.
That means you build LLVM or your LLVM subproject, plus your dialects or whatever.
Intree can refer to the source location.
So here we have an out-of-tree dialect, which is however part of the LLVM MonoRepo, but
it's considered out-of-tree because you can pull it out and you don't need to have it
in the MonoRepo.
So out-of-tree normally refers to work with a separate repository.
However, there is also a mechanism which you can use to build your project with this LLVM
external projects mechanism, and projects using this, and if you look into their CMake
configuration or into other tutorials, either they call it out-of-tree monolithic build,
so it's not a component build like you have against an installed MLIR or LLVM, or they
even call it Intree, which is somehow confusing because when you look to CMake, normally Intree
just means you're building where your source code lives, which is actually a bad practice.
You shouldn't do this.
Normally you do out-of-tree builds.
It just means you create a separate directory where you set up a configuration and where
you do your build.
This can also be a subdirectory in the source tree, but it's a separate directory not checked
into your Git later on.
So within this talk, I just call it the external project mechanism.
For me, it's always an out-of-tree build.
Regardless of what I do, even if I build LLVM, I wouldn't call it personally Intree because
I'm using the CMake notation normally.
It's to make it clear when you look into some of the projects and don't get confused.
What we can do is we can extend the standalone project by the LLVM external project mechanism,
and the question is why should we do this?
Stephen Neuendeuer gave a great tutorial about how to architecture LLVM projects at the LLVM
Dev Meeting 2021, which is available on YouTube.
I also have the link in my references.
Here we are referring to a monolithic build, and historically he says use the component
builds.
That is what the standalone project already gives you.
But there are some benefits when you maybe want to use the LLVM external projects.
So what we actually do is when we developed the MHC dialect, we developed this as an out-of-tree
dialect, completely independent or buildable against an installed MLIR version.
MHC is now part of the MLIR core, so it's upstreamed.
What we normally do is, or what's quite nice is, sometimes we want to look into when we
change our dialect upstream or when we extend it, how does it behave together with our out-of-tree
source, which we still have, all our conversions, all our transformations are not upstreamed
yet.
It's quite nice to build it as run project because you can easily debug into, you don't
have to keep your installation and what you're building out of source, you don't have to
keep this in sync, you just have a monolithic build.
There are some benefits, and we just want to look into what do we need to do to build
it with the LLVM external project mechanism.
So we are creating our build directory again, then we have to define the LLVM targets to
build, so here you need to specify for which architecture you want to build LLVM, so here
it's just host or x86, which is also an option.
You must specify the build type, either release, debug, min source with rel info, whatever,
and we need to enable our project MLIR, otherwise it's not built.
And in addition to that, as we want to build our standalone project, we use LL, or we specify
LLVM external projects, standalone dialect, which is our project name, and furthermore
we specify LLVM external standalone dialect source tree to specify where do we find our
source, that are the two additional parameters you need to pass, and here LLVM source tree,
actually we assume that it points to the root of our mono repo checked out.
So that is what we want to have later on, right now the standalone example can't do
this, what do we need to change to make this possible?
So right now it's looking like the following, looking to the main CMake configuration, and
what is important here is we have find package, we call find package MLIR, and find package
in general imports information which we exported by a project.
So here find package imports information from the installed MLIR version, and furthermore
the find package MLIR also calls find package LLVM for us, so we don't need to care about
this, so we can then just, well the MLIR config CMake is actually parsed as well as the LLVM
config CMake parsed, and we can gladly just do our includes which adds some further code
for us.
So for the external project mechanism build we don't need to do this, so what we need
to change is we only need to call find package if there is an installed MLIR, otherwise there
won't be one because we're just building it as part of our build process.
So in that case CMake sourced here normally is equal to CMake current sourced here.
If it's not the case we have a different build type and we're just adding this if else block
and we don't have the need no longer for our other project to load the CMake modules with
include.
And the code we're adding is we're just setting the variables which are not available as exported
project settings by ourselves, so MLIR main source here, main include here, and that's
actually it.
So that are the few lines we need to make it buildable.
However your lit tests will fail.
So there is a little bit more code that we need to modify.
Here we just define a standalone source here and standalone binary variables which are
then later on used also for our include directories.
And we adjust our lit side cfg.py accordingly.
So here we actually need to change CMake binary D or CMake source here by our newly set variable
otherwise the lit tests are the location of lit cfg is assumed in the wrong place.
So we just fix that here.
That's nearly it.
So when you now want to use a dialect with other dialects and you have these in several
repositories or with several projects at least, you can either use LLVM external projects
to build multiple dialects.
Torch MLIR for example is doing exactly this.
Another option is to use CMake's external project add which is considered as the cleanest
way as it really keeps the projects enclosed and doesn't transfer reliability between the
projects.
However what I normally do is I use add subdirectory but in addition with the exclude from all
so no only the build targets I really use are exported or transferred to the other project.
And we do this in our MLIR MHC repository and to do this we actually have an option
just embedded which changes our source code a little bit so only when we want to call
it embedded then we check is it the case or not because the find package is already done
by the other project we don't need to call this.
We only do the includes which we don't need for the external project mechanism.
So getting to types.
This is how the standalone dialect is currently structured or at least most of it there are
also some tools standalone ops standalone translate which I would consider here and
you see we have multiple finds and types could be specified in standalone ops dot TD in our
tablegen definition file.
However it's quite nice to not put it in all into one file but to use separate files.
So what we are doing is we are adding new files we are adding a tablegen file standalone
types we are adding a header file and we are adding the CPP for our implementation and
what you need to put into those are actually the following.
Let's start with the tablegen file.
First of all we include the attribute type base and the dialect itself because the dialect
has some definitions and then we can define our standalone types class which is the base
class for types and in addition to that we can define a custom type actually this is
a simple copy of a mid-seas or park type quite straightforward but here we use a standard
assembly format so no custom parser and printer and it just holds a string referometer so
nothing special just to illustrate the example.
So that is how the tablegen file could look like.
Getting to standalone ops we can just replace the include of standalone dialect by standalone
types and this is because the types already includes the tablegen TD file so that's as
fine and that's it.
Regarding the CMAK list we don't need anything to change why is that?
Actually at MLIR dialect already calls MLIR tablegen for you with gen type def decals
and type def definitions so that's fine we don't need to change anything here.
Remember for attributes that would be different because for attributes the atMLIR dialect
doesn't call MLIR tablegen for you so just set the algorithm target definitions by yourself
call MLIR tablegen by yourself add a public tablegen target and that's it so attributes
are quite close related to or quite similar except for that you need to adjust your CMAK
configuration by yourself.
For the header file just include the auto generated type def classes in the header that's
it add the define the include nothing more to do.
For our implementation we need to make sure that the types can actually be registered
by the parent dialect so what we do is we have a define here get type def classes we
include then our generated code generated by tablegen and then we write a function register
types which actually calls the method add types plus some of the auto generated code
and this needs to be called in our standalone dialect.cpp so we just add the register types
here and that's nearly the role trick you can do the same not with add operands or add
types but with add attributes for attributes and to register your attributes.
For the CMAK list itself just add this to your MLIR standard library dialect library
target that's it nothing more to do.
For attributes you can also just add your source code or you must add your source file
here of course but in addition you also need a dependency on MLIR standalone attributes
inkgen the target we generate or we create it by hand because it's not auto generated
just to make sure that tablegen generates the code before CMAK tries to or before the
MLIR standalone target is built you might be lucky otherwise you might have a race condition
in your build system I experienced that several times try to fix it or just keep it in mind
and that's mainly it.
For the standalone dialect here we use the default printer and parser just let us tell
tablegen to generate those and for register types actually we need of course a declaration
we have the implementation but we also need the extra cast declaration generated by tablegen
otherwise yeah we cannot use it in our standard ops.cpp.
So all the examples are available in my fork of the LLVM project I couldn't make it to
send these via fabricated to be reviewed through App Serum Inclusion prior to my talk but I
will do so I will add some more documentation to this that's at least my goal.
So when I planned this talk I thought that's what maybe some hints which could have one
or the other and hopefully it's even more helpful if you not only find it in the slides
below it's in the upstream example and there are many good resources out there so the talk
given by media mini and River Riddle the MLIR primer the MLIR tutorial at the 2020 LLVM
staff meeting we have some great talks at MLIR LLVM.org here how to create a dialect
the toy example for example how to combine it how to add attribute and types if you want
to get more into the details what you can do all in the tablegen world and last but
not least the tutorial given by Stephen Neuendeuer at the LLVM 2021 staff meeting yeah so that's
it from my side so if you have questions please let me know and I try to answer them.
I just recently got into learning how to develop compilers even less how to create languages
and I'm going to talk about how to use LLVM as a backend for a really abstracted C-type
language which I'm working on and use LLVM as a backend to generate machine code for
x86 and my understanding was that I only had to use or generate an IR for LLVM the LLVM
IR and now you mentioned that LLVM IR can be described or is somehow related with the
LLVM or sorry the MLIR right so I was wondering if I'm still on the correct track to try to
generate the parse tree and use LLVM and try to generate the standard LLVM IR and target
the x86 or an x86 platform or do I need to learn something about the MLIR?
So to trying to summarize your question the question is when as a compiler starter you
are mostly focusing on parsing an abstract C-type like language and want to know if you
can just go through the ordinary LLVM IR way or if you need to plug in switch over to MLIR
to do what you want so in real short so you can do this definitely you can you can go
the way you're right now doing so MLIR actually is a little bit yeah different so if you if
we are looking to clang I don't if you're talking about an abstract C language looking
into clang there is clang AST and then we directly more or less go to LLVM IR and that
is one of the things which yeah isn't that nice or if you look into other compilers they
introduce more intermediate representations in between like we will see later on in the
session the flang app that for example or even Swift has two intermediate representations
for example so MLIR just gives you the ability to define additional intermediate representations
so you can you can also write a front end for for your for your language pass it into
MLIR trans yeah convert it to LL to the LLVM IR dialect and then translate it to LLVM IR
so that would be identical it really depends on what you want to do what kind of infrastructure
you want to use but you can the way you can go the way you're already going so hopefully
that somehow at least answers your question okay the question is not directly related
to the talk but as I'm one of the developers behind MHC why we developed MHC sometimes
you cannot compile with clang or directly or with LLVM at all to your to your target
so the idea was to get to to get something independent of the compiler and if we when
we actually yeah generate C code with MHC you can have have send a freedom to choose
which compiler you want to use to translate for your for your final target so we are in
the domain of compilers for machine learning and sometimes we have some very exotic targets
where clang unfortunately is not the option to to use it as a compiler so that's the simple
reason I was looking to doing some sort of log
I was looking into doing some sort of just in time compilation.
But I also wanted to define my own types and my own, let's say, things.
My question is, would MLIR be a good fit for that?
Or would possibly just see with some sort of, I don't know,
dynamic library, you can argue with it.
So the question is, when coming from the other side, so for
JIT, essentially, if MLIR might be a good fit to define your own types and attributes.
And well, I'm not an expert regarding JIT, but MLIR provides you,
I think most of the codes are upstream, provides you the possibility to
register types and attributes, I'm quite sure at least, at runtime.
So you can extend your dialect after you compiled MLIR.
So that is maybe, yeah, depending on what you wanna do,
if you really want to modify it during runtime.
Just to instantiate new types during runtime.
That should be possible with MLIR.
So I'm not 100% sure, but at least worth a look, I think.
Yeah, I also have a question, last question.
So I've been interacting with some people that define a new language to define
dialects, or a dialect to define dialects, called IRDL.
I'm not sure if you know that.
I was wondering, this would probably change the entire flow of building a dialect,
right, or?
Well, I'm partly aware of IRDL, but I don't know,
you mean how you compose it via CMake in the targets or what?
Yes, you mean this, yeah.
Yeah, probably as you, with IRDL, as far as I know,
as you do most of the time at runtime, you wouldn't need to build it in advance.
So yeah, the CMake stuff would be somehow obsolete, yeah.
I think so.
All right, if we're out of questions, thank you, Maurice.
Thank you.
And we'll see you next time.