All right. Thanks everyone for coming so early. I admire your... I'm very impressed to tee
up this early in the morning. I'm David Llewelyn-Jones. I work for a company called Yolo O in Finland.
We make an operating system called Selfish OS for mobile phones like this one. And today
I'm going to talk to you about COVID exposure notification. It's actually a project that
was done... It was a personal project rather than something related to the company. But
it was something that relates to Selfish OS. So hopefully it all kind of comes together
in some kind of sensible way. Okay. So exposure notification. It's almost certainly something
that you've all come across individually. Essentially it's the apps that people ran on their phones
that did contact tracing. They would give you an alert if you had been in contact with
someone who had a COVID diagnosis. And I guess they were a big deal during COVID. I guess
probably they're less of a big deal now. Although I track the numbers on my phone while I'm
at FOSDEM and there's still a lot of people at FOSDEM using them. I can tell that. And
the idea about this talk is that I want to talk about a very particular implementation
of it. And that's the Google Apple Exposure Notification Protocol, which was released
I guess in April 2020. And it was an implementation that went out to Android devices and iPhones
in order to basically provide the services needed in order to allow countries or medical
organisations to build apps on top of it in order to perform this contact tracing process.
And initially when it was released it was called, as you can see here, the contact tracing
API. Later on I guess that name was a little bit ambiguous, a little bit confusing. They
changed it to the Google and Apple Exposure Notification API. I guess when people think
about contact tracing they think about maybe people phoning them up and asking them who
they've been close to. But it is all the same thing. And this was the original specification.
Like I say, the original one was released in April 2020. And it's made up of these three
documents. It was initially, this was version 1.1. I think they're up to version 1.4 or
later now. There's been several versions that have come out since. So they've refined the
protocol. And I guess it's worth putting it in a little bit of context. Back then when
this was released there was no vaccine. So at that point in time people thought that
the World Health Organisation predicted that vaccine was about 16 months away but no one
was entirely sure. In practice the first vaccine was actually approved about nine months after
this. But you can imagine that at this point in time people were very worried about COVID.
They were concerned about how it was going to be dealt with. And this was seen as kind
of like a kind of one really quite exciting way to address the problem given that there
were so few tools at that time to deal with things. So let me just talk about these three
documents. The first one on the left here is the Bluetooth specification. So it's made
up of three parts. The Bluetooth specification, I'll talk about how it works in practice in
a second or two. But it's sending beacons using Bluetooth from your phone. So the Bluetooth
specification tells you essentially how to pack the data into a Bluetooth beacon and
also other details like for example for privacy reasons the information in the beacon changes
periodically and you have to change the MAC address of your phone in sequence with that
in order to avoid privacy problems coming up. So that's that part. There's a cryptography
specification because the data that is sent in the beacons is cryptographically I guess
hidden in order for privacy reasons. And then finally there's the framework documentation
which is the API which is really describing how organizations can make use of these tools.
And I guess another important point about it is that there are two parts to the process.
So Google and Apple released this API for all phones but that's actually only half of
it. That sends out the beacons. But as those beacons go around eventually you have to do
something with that data that's being sent. And for that you needed an app that was going
to be written by a government organization, a government level organization, like it could
be a health organization. And Google and Apple had nothing to do with that. They said you
know you've got to write that part. We'll just give you this piece here. And the project
that I'm essentially talking about is about a reimplementation of this for Salesforce OS.
And so of course we had to also deal with those two parts separately. So this is only
one part of it. All right. So one of the nice things about this protocol is it's actually
heavily privacy focused. So you can imagine also at that time there was a lot of concern
about the fact that you're sending beacons out on your mobile phone. There are privacy
concerns about that. And the protocol tries to address that in a very careful way. And
that's actually rather a nice feature about it. All right. So when it was released this
is actually a slide from Google and Apple. I did not draw these pictures. And this basically
describes how it works. So very briefly, Alice and Bob wandering around the world, they have
the app installed on their device sending out beacons. When they get into close contact
with each other, their phones are communicating via Bluetooth. Well, they're not exactly communicating.
They're listening for these beacons and they're storing the beacons that they hear. OK. So
that's that's step one. So when they get close to each other, Bob's beacons get stored on
Alice's phone. Later on, Bob turns out to have COVID and he gets a positive diagnosis.
And he basically goes to his doctor. He gets an official diagnosis. And he puts that information
into the app. And he voluntarily uploads data about his beacons to some cloud server that's
run by a government or health authority. And he uploads 14 days worth of his beacons. So
in practice, these beacons are actually generated using a cryptographic process. So you don't
have to store on your phone 14 days worth. You just store essentially the seed that generates
them. But they change frequently. So they change between every 10 and 20 minutes. It's
actually a random interval somewhere between those two. In order to prevent people from
tracking you, they are unlinkable. So when they change, you can't link one from the other.
And that means that there's a limit to how far you can track people. But Bob can regenerate
those keys to upload to the server. Alice just gets random, essentially random numbers.
She can't tell what those numbers are essentially or what they mean. So then later on, so I
guess the next day. So this happens later. But then the next day or later on that day,
the keys get uploaded to the server and the server then dumps all of the keys that it's
received, received back to every single device out there. It downloads these keys to all of
their phones, to everyone's phones. So it downloads them to Alice's phone. Alice then
Alice's phone then matches them up with the keys that she captured along the way. And
she then knows that she was in contact with someone who has a positive diagnosis for COVID.
She gets an alert on her app and then her life is held for two weeks. That's basically
the process. She has to isolate and go through all of the steps that you have to go through.
We don't know whether Alice has COVID or not, the idea is she might have. So at the time
it was a kind of a big deal, like I said, because it was seen as a kind of a white horse
to get us out of the problem of COVID. At that time, everyone was focused on this thing
called the R number, where the idea being that the R number was the number of people
you essentially go on to reinfect after you have COVID. And the objective was to keep
that down. If the R number was above one, there was an exponential growth in the number
of people that would have COVID. If it was below one, then it would be reducing numbers.
And the aim of all of this process was to keep people isolated if they might have COVID
in order to reduce that R number and prevent it from spreading. Google and Apple came out
with this protocol because they immediately identified that there were going to be serious
risks involved in tracking people with their mobile phone to do this stuff. So they knew,
for example, that there were privacy risks associated with it. They knew that if they
let governments go ahead and just do it, they would just collect everyone's data, was the
concern. Or some of them might do. Maybe not all of them, but some of them might. They
also knew that sending out Bluetooth beacons... Sorry, you have a question.
Sorry, if Alice receives keys from infected people, can she not match back with the time,
relative time she got the re-elected key? So she knows that the key is the one that she
found two days ago, and two days ago was the time she met Bob. So is there a problem?
So I guess I should make clear. So I mean, there are privacy controls in this, but they're
not complete. And the idea is that essentially at the point when you upload your keys, you've
got your diagnosis, that's essentially when some of your privacy is lost. But you voluntarily
choose to do that. That doesn't happen automatically. Does that make sense? Okay. But it's a good
point. So yes, but Google and Apple were concerned about the privacy implications because it
reflects badly on their systems, if their phones are doing this stuff. Also, the power
consumption is a problem, so they didn't want organizations to deploy apps that would have
problems in terms of battery on their phone. And they also wanted it to be effective, because
if it's not effective, that also reflects badly on them. So they identified that there
were all these risks that they wanted to avoid. And even at that time, the APIs that Google
and Apple provide prevented people from doing this kind of stuff for precisely those reasons.
I mean, it was nothing to do with COVID. I mean, they've always just prevented you from
sending out beacons and collecting beacons like this in a sensible way. Primarily for
power consumption reasons, right? They don't want people draining the battery of the phone
to do that. So my concern as a YOLO employee was that, well, Google and Apple have released
this stuff. It's probably going to get quite popular. And I didn't want selfish users who
are using an alternative operating system, which is not Android or iOS, to essentially
get sidelined by this process and be left in a situation where they can't basically
participate in this scheme. So the objective then was to create an open source implementation
that could be used on other sorts of phones. So this is selfish. Selfish OS is a version
of Linux, it's a Linux distribution that has a Qt UI layer on top of it. And it is sold
by, well, it's released by YOLO. And then there is also a paid for license that you
can get for it to get additions on top of that. So yeah, the idea was to write an application
that essentially mimicked that functionality. And so this was the app that myself and Oscar
Roseler, I don't know if Oscar is here. Is Oscar in there? I guess not. He said he might
turn up, but I guess he's not here at the moment. So we developed this together as a
kind of a personal project. And you can see here's the process. This was like the first
time that we actually got beacons appearing on the device. So that was kind of an exciting
moment. And there are, I guess, several steps. There's the collecting beacons, there's sending
beacons, and there's also uploading your data if you get a positive diagnosis. So we implemented
all those parts. And we tried to implement it in the same way that the Google and Apple
did in terms of structure. So you have a service underneath that sends out these beacons. And
we had a separate app, which was the app that was the equivalent to the app that had to
be developed by governments. And in theory, other people could have developed other apps
on top of the service. I don't think that ever happened. We only implemented one version.
And the version we implemented was the COVID warn app, which was Germany's implementation.
And the reason we did that was because it was both very early in the process in terms
of being deployed. But it was also incredibly open. It was an open source deployment. And
they were really committed to doing it as an open source project. Not just an open source
chunk of code, but the development model was also supposed to be open. It was actually
developed by SAP and Deutsche Telekom. I think my understanding is that SAP did all the code
development. Deutsche Telekom provided the infrastructure for it, the back end service
infrastructure. So like I say, we did this independently of Yola. For those interested,
it was Qt based. It used Bluetooth for the Bluetooth stack and open SSL for the crypto
stuff. And this was the timeline, essentially, that we worked to. We didn't work to that
we ended up with, I guess. So on the 10th of April, that's when the Google Apple specs
first came out. We released our first version implementation of those specs on the 19th.
So that was quite soon afterwards. Then the COVID warn app from Germany came out on the
16th of June. And then on the 30th of June, so quite a few weeks later, but we got out
our first app that had equivalent functionality. So we were pretty happy with that. We thought
that was kind of could be considered a success. But it was only possible because the specifications
that Google and Apple rolled out were very good. They were clear specifications that
you could re implement. And the COVID warn app team also did a lot of good work in releasing
source code very early. They had a huge amount of documentation that was all on GitHub. They
even had a, I guess, a CCC evaluation of the project in terms of its privacy. So they were
really quite committed to being open with their stuff. In practice, what we found was,
so they released some reference versions of the servers. And we found that really helpful.
That was really important. They also released the source code for their app that we re implemented.
We actually ultimately found that that was not so useful. It was useful for some edge
cases, but really it was a server deployment that was really helpful for us. So I guess
the real reason that I wanted to talk today was to talk about our experience working with
these companies as small developers, as independent developers. And I guess it was very much as
you might expect in terms of Google and Apple. They produce, I mean, they re phenomenal at
producing good specifications and good APIs. That s what they do. That s their bread and
butter. They re absolutely phenomenal at it. But zero engagement. So we tried to contact
them and talk to them about their stuff to try and get information or to get help. Nothing
at all. Which is, I guess, not surprising, right? They re a massive company. There s
no reason why particularly they would. They promised test data to test stuff against and
that never materialized. So there were also some bumps in the road for us. And although
they did release the source code, they released the source code for an app, for a reference
app quite early, but they didn t release the source code for the underlying system, the
Bluetooth system, until somewhat later. Until I guess that was late in July. So for us that
was already too late. So working with them, like I say, there were good points, but they
were not really having an open source development model. For SAP, working with the SAP code was
a little bit different. So this is essentially the SAP implementation that they developed
on top of the Google Apple notification protocol. So this is the app and this is the server
backend on the left-hand side. And the main parts of it are this verification server and
from our point of view, in the Corona Warn app server. So essentially what they do, you
have to have a download server to download all of these keys that are going to Alice
s phone and to everybody s phone. That happened in the Corona Warn app server. You have to
have a verification server so that when you get a positive diagnosis, you can upload it
in a secure way with your identity, essentially proving that, not with your identity, but
proving that you ve got a positive diagnosis from your doctor. And then you need an upload
server to upload your keys to. And that happened also in the Corona Warn app server. So in
practice this was actually two servers, not one. So those were the two bits we were interested
in. And we had to deploy them to test against. We couldn t deploy the whole lot. That was
going to be impossible. That was not really a plausible thing to do. But they did have
a reference implementation of these two servers. And so we tried to deploy, we tried to deploy,
well, so we did end up deploying those to an AWS server and testing our code against
those. And what we found was that the download server implementation was a little bit broken.
We had to fix it. But it was otherwise pretty good. There were just some glitches. Whereas
the verification server and the upload server were pretty minimal. So we actually essentially
had to re-implement parts of those based on the specification in order to do our testing.
But they did release a lot of code with this stuff. And the fact that they had these reference
servers was absolutely key in allowing us to re-implement the protocol. So our overall
experience was that they produced lots of code and lots of documentation, which was
really good. They were one of the earliest teams to get this stuff out into the wild,
in terms of source code, which was also phenomenally good. They worked through GitHub issues. So
when we found problems, we would submit pull requests to try and fix the code. And it was
clear that they were trying to engage with that process. But in practice, they were just
taking way too long. So by the time, so for example, we would fix a bit of a, we would
fix something in one of the reference servers. And people would be using our PR code to deploy
elsewhere. But by the time they got to actually thinking about integrating it, it was already
too stale. It was no longer useful. So they were clearly trying to do that. But I guess
it was just a question of time. So as a consequence, some of the code was left broken for quite
a long time, even though there were fixes that they could have just integrated. Some
of the reference implementations differed quite significantly from reality in terms of
the servers. But there was something to work with, and that was really helpful. And so
our overall impression was that they had this real commitment to openness. They were genuinely
committed to doing this well. They had an open development process. But the team were
just a bit overwhelmed with the amount of effort involved in doing it. That was the
impression we got from the outside. So we were very impressed by this. But obviously,
there's obviously scope for learning there in terms of how to do it better. So my overall
reflections on how things went were that at the time, I think, again, you have to put
this into context. There was huge pressure on governments all over the world to get this
stuff deployed. So the first deployment in South Korea was, I think, the COVID 100-meter
app. And that went out really early. And as soon as that went out, and that used a GPS
position in GNSS so that it uploaded people's locations to the cloud. I mean, essentially,
zero privacy in that situation. But as soon as that was out, all other governments, there
was a lot of pressure for them to do something similar. There was a huge rush to deploy this
stuff. And so there was a lot of pressure. And there was a lot of competing requirements.
There were a lot of competing requirements. The requirements for openness was just one
requirement. There was also requirements for efficacy, requirements for speed, requirements
in terms of privacy. All of these things combined are actually quite challenging to get right.
And both Google and Apple and the CWA team, the SAP team, the impression I got was they
really got that. They really understood these competing impressions, but they also understood
the need for openness. They understood that in order for people, not just for them to
do it well, but for people to trust the apps that they were running, they also needed to
be open about it. And that's one of the reasons they did it. And in that sense, I think they
were pretty successful. Like I say, there was scope for improvement. There was, as I
said, with Google and Apple, there was zero inward flow of information. With SAP, there
was, and so with both teams, there was a lot of outward flow of information that was excellent.
With SAP, there was some inward flow, but not as much as perhaps we as independent developers
would have liked. And I guess more generally, what we kind of felt was that there was a,
there was this commitment to openness, but not necessarily a full appreciation of how
much effort was involved in that process, in getting that process to work really well
and effectively for the companies involved. So for example, and I guess I should say that
YOLA also works with a lot of open source code. So we also have an open development
process for a lot of our stuff and we have the same challenges, right? So people provide
PRs for us to integrate into the system and knowing what is good to integrate and what
is bad to integrate takes a lot of time and effort, right? It sounds like you're getting
free implementation, which I guess in some sense you are, but there's still a lot of
effort involved in that process. And like I said, I guess with this process that we
as independent developers experienced from the outside, it felt like that perhaps these
other competing things were impacting on the effort that they could put into that process.
So yeah, so overall, given that these organizations had absolutely no duty towards us as independent
developers, we were kind of very happy that we could work with the things that they've
given us and that they were actually high quality. So we were very pleased with how
it went, but like I say, we felt that there was definitely some room for improvement.
Okay, so that's my summary of how things went. Thanks for taking the time to listen. There's
some links in case you're interested in more. We are actually on the Linux on mobile stand
in Building K at the top of the stairs. So if you want to talk more about it later, please
come and visit us and we'd be happy to do that. Thanks very much. Is there time for
questions?
Okay, especially for the live stream. Right. Understood.
Right. So your question is, what's my experience with the Bluetooth parts, the Bluetooth notifications?
Because as you were saying, at the time there was a lot of discussion about whether it was
going to give enough accuracy in terms of proximity detection. So the key thing, the
key thing with the COVID notifications, of course, is that there was this two meter,
there was always this like, or some distance that you were supposed to stay away from people.
And so in terms of the Bluetooth, you wanted to try and mimic that process. You wanted
to actually distinguish that someone was within two meters or some distance or outside that
distance. Right. That's essentially what you're talking about in terms of proximity. So it's
interesting actually. So when we started out the process, the protocol didn't specify greatly
how to tackle that. So what happened, what actually Google and Apple did is they set
a bunch of risk parameters in their implementation that you could tweak, that you could change.
And they came from the download server. They were set by the government organizations,
not by Google and Apple. And they basically said, you know, how much risk do you, they
gave weightings, how much risk do you associate with a power level of this for the Bluetooth?
And how much risk association do you put with how long that association went on for? Like,
is it five minutes or 10 minutes that they're within range of this, of this distance? So
you could tweak those parameters. And later on in the process, Google actually released
a lot of information that provided essentially weightings for some of the parameters that
almost every phone on the market. So they had a process where they would basically put
two phones on stands next to each other and measure the power consumption that came through.
And then based on which phone was communicating with it, which other phone, they would then
tweak the parameters to try and make that proximity more effective. So we, so we, we
use those parameters, but I have to say we didn't really, we were not in a position to
check whether or not they were working effectively because what's happening behind the scene
is quite opaque, right? We're sending data upload up to a server. And the whole point
is that you then know nothing about what happens after that because of the privacy aspects.
So, so it's actually very hard for us to judge whether or not it was working well or working
badly. But it was clear that there was a lot of work going on to get it to work well in
the background. My, my, my more general experience with Bluetooth is it's not great at this stuff.
You know, if there's a person between you and another person, then water is a big problem
for signal propagation. So stuff that's in between causes a lot of dampening of the,
of the signal. So it's quite tough. It was the impression I got. Yeah, but I'm not an
expert in that. I have to say.
Okay.
So I'm just going to come a bit closer so I can hear from you.
Right.
Right. Okay. So, so the question, the question was, is, was there any evidence that all of
this open source release of code resulted in reuse of code by other governments? That's
essentially your question, right? And I think there was, so I can't think of specific instances,
but my understanding was that, that people did take the COVID war nap code and use it
in their implementations or perhaps more generally, I think people definitely took the Google
reference implementation and use that in their code, which was open source. And of course
was a, was a yes. I'm sorry. Which was, which I guess was an example of open source being
reused. Perhaps more specifically with the COVID war nap because the Google and Apple
notification protocol was the foundation for it. It was used really quite widely across
Europe. Not all countries used it, but a lot of countries did. And at this point in time,
I think there's 11 countries that all use the same backend. So they're all uploading
their keys to servers. So now if you use the COVID war nap, you or contract our version
of it, you actually get keys from countries across Europe, half of Europe, essentially
is quite a large, large area. So I mean, you could argue that's not perhaps a con that's
more a consequence of having a common API than it is open source, but, but there definitely
was benefit in, in, you know, sharing of information, sharing of code. It did happen. I think it
did happen, but perhaps it's not, it's not as, not as clear that it happened as it might
otherwise seem. Yeah. All right. I'm being told my time's up. So.