Today, I'm going to be talking about public money, public code in Europe and basically
try to do a very brief overview of what has happened in terms of public money, public
code in the EU institutions.
Because of time and also because of the topic, I just want to focus on public money, public
code because I know that at the moment there are a lot of legislation going on that is
worrying a lot of the community but I'm just going to exclude those.
If you want to talk about those later, we'll be mainly in the booth or you can just shoot
me an email and we can exchange some ideas.
So I always like to start with the basics and always to put everybody on the same page,
maybe this is very familiar for you but I think it is super important now more than
ever to always remember that free software guarantees the four freedoms to use, start
each year and improve the software and whenever one of those freedoms is excluded then we're
talking about a non-free software project.
How are you going to name it?
We are the free software foundation in Europe so we empower users to control technology
and we do this with free software and among different activities that we have, we have
the public money, public code campaign.
Maybe this is also very familiar for you and also mainly in this deaf room but also briefly
overview of our campaign.
We started this four, five years ago, 2017 and we are basically requiring legislation
that demands that public procurement or public software that is procured for the public sector
should be public code.
And for this then we have different reasons, we use different arguments whenever we are
talking with public administrations, with decision makers.
So one of those is definitely tax saving because then the public money should be spent in the
most efficient way.
So there is no point to spend public money on proprietary licenses if you can reuse software.
Then the collaboration part is also super important because we all know free software
enhances interoperability and collaboration so administrations can collaborate with each
other because it's open, because it's there and there is no need to reinvent the wheel
again.
And then it's also serving the public because then the public money given by the public,
the people will know what the money is being spent and then I think we all agree if the
money is spending a good way, we like that.
And of course to foster innovation because then we have to start from scratch again but
we can just reuse the solutions that already exist.
So we have in our open letter, we have an open letter that you can sign as individual
organizations, but also public administrations.
We have more than 10,000 signatures and now at the moment we have seven public administrations.
There are some from Germany, from Sweden, from Spain, I think three of them.
And then recently one from Luxembourg has also signed our open letter.
So it is not so many but it is nice to see some administrations supporting our campaign.
But yeah, so now that was a very brief overview of the public money public code campaign and
within this we have different activities and we also actively try to advocate in the EU
level in this regard.
So today I want to talk about two EU institutions.
I'm going to first start with the European Commission, what has happened in there over
the last three, four years and also I will talk a little bit about the European Parliament,
more specifically about the AI resolution, a little bit of the AI, ongoing AI act and
then I will also talk very briefly about the declaration of digital rights because these
are some of the files or legal documents where we have been active.
And yeah, so let's start with the Commission.
I think in order to talk about the Commission we have to talk about these two pilot projects,
the EU FOSA and the EU FOSA2.
So basically these were projects that were given to the European Commission by the European
Parliament.
So basically the European Parliament or the Commission get those pilot projects ready
because we need to improve the security of the free software tools that have been or
are used on the European institutions.
So they did that, they did their best.
Within those two pilot projects they did 15 Bantys, three Hackathons to actually audit
the code of these free software tools within the institutions.
However there was not budget allocated to these projects and therefore they could not
run any longer.
So this was basically like the European Parliament told them how to do it and what to do it but
there was not budget allocated.
And I think through my talk you will see that this is a, unfortunately this is a pattern,
there is a lot of nice warnings and a lot of nice initiatives but fortunately there
is not budget.
So they stopped doing these projects and in 2020 the European Commission released the
open source strategy.
And this strategy is super interesting because this is as you can read there it's a communication
from the Commission to the Commission.
So basically this is, I mean this is not a legal binding document so it's basically the
Commission telling themselves how they should work with open source, what they should do.
It's like a plan, it's not legal binding.
So in this regard, I mean we still have to say that we acknowledge that the Commission
has the will, has the initiative to set up these kind of things and then they are already
realizing that open source has been used in the EU institutions and they need to do something
about this.
However as a strategy by itself it's rather weak because it doesn't have any real indicator
or anything that we can, you know you can actually follow up what's happening and see
the progress of such plans so far.
So if you go to the text then you can see word in search of like whatever it makes sense
to do so, the Commission will share the source code and again here is like when whatever
makes sense or whenever it makes sense what does that even mean?
Like it is not clear when the Commission should share the source code and then also in some
apart there is a section that talks about that the Commission has the freedom to choose
a non-open source tool if there are good reasons to do so and again like what is a good reason,
what is not.
So all this wording it's a little bit biased and not biased like ambiguous so to say so
it is very unclear and therefore our analysis of this strategy is like okay nice you want
to do something but there is still some, I don't know, we're not quite happy with the
wording and the way it was done.
However in 2021 then the European Commission also realized about this and then they had
a decision.
So this is a decision then we saw this transition between a project, a strategy, a communication
to more like a legally binding paper.
So in this paper they want to define the conditions under what the European Commission is going
to share open source.
And within this decision then we can see that they are trying now to implement, all that
is already happening, the European Commission open source program office.
So basically this is kind of like the office that will be in charge of taking care of all
these plans or all these decisions from the past documents I already talked about.
So this is a step, I mean now there is an open source program office that is actually
trying to act as a facilitator so they also do some backbond days, they also do hackathons
and I have to say that they're really trying to do something about this, they're trying
to implement all these projects and all these plans and all these strategies but again there
is not budget allocated to this ESIP OSBO.
So for them it's really hard to do what they have to do because there is not human capacity
because basically there is no budget so it's really difficult.
So here we find ourselves again with a very nice wording, there is like the will and the
initiative to do something about this but there is no budget allocated to these initiatives.
Within this decision then in the Article 6 a public repository is also included and this
is definitely something good, I mean we have been advocating for public repository for
all the open source tools that the European institutions used and this is publicly available.
So this is again another step here, from here we can see not only the European institutions
are sharing what they're using but this is also trying to include member states so they're
also trying to see, you know, to build this interoperable network among member states.
So in terms of public code this is again a step and I feel like this is going on the
right path but I can really say enough that there are some things that need to be worked
and work such as the wording has to be more clear and again there should be more budget
allocated to free software in general and this is not happening at the moment.
So this is basically what is happening in the European Commission, I know that at the
moment the European Commission is proposing a lot of legislation and initiatives towards
open source, they are realizing that open source free software it needs a special regulation,
it is important, in my point of view they are noticing that but yeah within the European
Commission this is what's happening, we can see there is will, there is something the
OSBO is trying to do whatever they can but not budget at all allocated in this.
So now let's talk a little bit about the European Parliament.
So as I mentioned very briefly I want to talk about mainly the EU AI resolution, this was
a resolution that was led by the special committee that was created in the European Parliament
to take care of, to do this resolution and this resolution is again not legally binding
it's just an opinion like a guideline for the ongoing AI act and the AI act is going
to be a regulation so this is going to be legally binding but the European Parliament
decide to create this committee to exchange views to talk with experts, to with stakeholders
and yeah they come up with this resolution.
So of course we also try to advocate there although we knew it was not legally binding
but again these are guidelines and the decision makers really this is a good argument for
us you know if there are guidelines we can always bring them to these guidelines because
that's why they are using them for right because they need to be used, you always need to go
and look back to these guidelines.
So in this regard it's hard to say if it was completely successful or not but there was
a huge step, there is a recital that talks about public procurement on AI, again we see
this pattern from the EU institutions to have this very ambiguous wording of whatever it's
appropriate whenever it makes sense, whatever there are good reasons and in this recital
we see again as you can see I just caught this recital.
So nice I mean this is step and I guess in this regard we can always use it to benefit
the community but it's still super ambiguous.
So this recital was voted especially like the specific recital and the good thing is
that it found a huge majority within the European Parliament so that tells something as well
that tells also the will that the European Parliament has but the downside as I already
mentioned is it's not legally binding it's just a guideline but at least we have something
right so in this regard then we would say that decision makers understood the importance
of open source on AI.
So to briefly talk a little bit about our FSP demands for the AI legislation we basically
we are it's very straightforward we say like AI should be fair transparent accessible
and this is only possible if it's open source and then of course we have an argument on
public research and public AI so whenever there is public money invested on research
on AI then it should be also public AI.
At the moment the AI act has been still discussed at the European Parliament so nobody knows
how the final text would look like we don't know if the European Parliament is going to
go back and see these guidelines from the AI resolution it is not clear but I feel like
we step in in the moment that we could we're still going to try to monitor what's happening
there but so far it's really difficult to see how that's going to develop from now on
until I don't know I think the last this is going to be vote by the end of the year and
the last plenary I don't know.
And finally I want to talk a little bit about the declaration of digital rights so this
was also an initiative of course from the Commission they just want to have this guidelines
I guess as well as a reference point for the digital transformation of Europe so we decide
to also step in because as well as like with the Berlin Declaration and the Tallinn Declaration
these are always guidelines that we use to talk to decision makers to public administrations
because they are there and they talk about public procurement and free software so we
said like let's try to also influence the way the wording is going to happen in this
declaration again I mean this is just like you know it's a it's a guideline document
for their ongoing legislation so a lot of people didn't really like see the point to
work on this paper but I personally I saw that it was like the baseline to discuss further
legislation so we went for it and this was super interesting because we also try to we
approach decision makers on the European Parliament then they had an opinion as a European Parliament
I win this opinion before going into the inter institutional negotiations the European position
the European Parliament position was open source or free software was included on AI
system so there was a nice a article there that was in which open source was included
however once the three institutions sat down to discuss then this wording was completely
gone and then at the moment like the final text that was signed by the three institutions
remove completely the part on open source on AI and then we just have a reference to
promoting interoperability open technologies and standards that's the final text it's super
unclear I mean is it open standards is it on the standards it is for us it was like
our it was not the ideal outcome because we were quite happy yeah quite happy with the
with the opinion from the European Parliament but then this was completely changed and that's
what usually most of the times happens whenever the three institutions sit down to to discuss
however again I mean let's look at the bright side as well we saw that the European Parliament
in its position a included open source free software so again this shows that there is
a will or there is a there is an understanding from the European Parliament as well on this
on the importance of open source free software on AI or on public procurement so yeah unfortunately
this is how this end up not the best outcome but yeah I mean this is this is what you get
when you try to advocate this European institution sometimes so just to maybe talk a little bit
what's ahead of us we see and I think you already got it we have very ambiguous wording
on the documents that we have so far so we just really trying to advocate for a clear
and consistent wording about free software in ongoing legislation so we cannot change
what's done already but we want to I mean now that this is being included we want to
make sure that the wording is more clear and also consistent so again the European Commission
doesn't have to come up with a new wording with a new inclusion with something different
but they can just reuse what it's already there and we want to make sure that if we
get to this point then this wording is clear and of course that it benefits the free software
ecosystem in general and then of course there is a problem with implementation because not
yeah we have nice wording documents but there to practice it's a it's a little bit different
so we want to keep monitoring you know like how much of this a a legally binding documents
have been properly implemented so we basically with this we just have to keep advocating
for public money public code and then trying to make sure that there is a proper implementation
implementation of such documents and last but not least I think that's one of the most
important one is that we really want to keep demanding that is governmental budget allocated
to free software because as we can see there is there is will there is some text but if
there is not budget then that becomes very difficult so that's that's what we have ahead
of us it's not quite easy but at least we have seen what's like the the transition and
not the whole process we have already pinpoint what we need to focus on and yeah we're just
going to try to do our best to to do so so and for this we also need our community we
are I mean it is important to talk to decision makers but it's also important that the free
software ecosystem the free software community also approaches administration's you know
raise awareness of this matter as well so you can convince your local administration
and for these if you might be interested I also invite you to see the talk from my one
of my colleagues in the community that room he's going to explain more how you can actually
get active on our the framework of our public money public code because there is this sometimes
people don't really see the power that use that you guys have to reach out your local
administrations and also you know like we're not talking about the European Parliament
European Commission we're talking about the library of your town that's also a public
administration so I invite you also if you are interested to check that talk you can
sign or open letter of course as individuals organizations or if also you want to convince
your local administration to sign the open letter well that's pretty nice and of course
I mean donations are always working we're a charity and we are really trying to work
as much as we can for to to come up with legislation that benefits the whole free software community
and of course spreading the word I know that this public money public code campaign is
quite well known but it's you know there is always people that don't know or people that
don't really know what free software is so all these things are super important we also
have a I mean we have a brochure on public money public code but then we also have a
brochure that we have prepared for AI that we use also to reach out to decision makers
it's also on our website so if you also want to take a look at this position paper and
distribute it feel free to do so and yeah with this just to close up I don't want to
I don't want you to leave this room feeling a little bit upset or like you know sad I
feel like personally I feel quite positive for what's happening at the moment with other
files as well it is just a matter to you know we that's why I really like these spaces and
these events where we can talk to each other we can you know discuss and then we can actually
bring all these positions and all these concerns to decision makers because there is a gap
between the community and decision makers and we're trying to close that gap or build
a bridge so the future legislation that is happening it's yeah it really benefits free
software so yeah thank you very much and now very happy to take questions okay yeah yeah
I wonder why I don't hear anything about the cases compared to five years ago open source
did not exist in any enterprise at European Commission and any organization nowadays anyone
can use mainly or 100% 90% open source software and I hear you only complain that it's not
a free software the software that is graduated by CNCF it is vetted it is supported by many
organizations there's a rigorous process to get it through and to get a new release and
I I don't hear anything about what happened how much of a change we had the last five
years and how much much much better the world is since five years ago then we had only Windows
and VMware and IBM and now we have large large organization for the huge amount of
code and I need to complain I would say it's a different whole topic yeah I mean can you
please repeat the question for the livestream well okay why am I complaining that it's not
like free software although we have seen some changes on inclusion of open source in the EU
institutions over the last five years right that's basically well but I mean it was not available
very like the open source solutions that have been using in the European Commission are not
publicly available until they just released this public repository before they were not
publicly available so they were using inner source they were using open source within the institutions
but that was not open to the public and that's what we are demanding but is it available to
the public yeah but it that was yeah exactly and that's not available to the public and that's our
demand I mean nice they're using open source but is it available to us no until now and that's why
I mean I I'm sorry but I was not really trying to complain at all I mean not only complaining I also
was highlighting their will that this you institutions having because I can't see it as well I mean there
has been a huge shift and a huge change and there is will now now we have a public repository of the
free software using the public in the EU institutions that's something but I'm sorry this is not good
enough yeah yeah yeah I mean we die it's a little bit tricky oh yeah yeah we
know that what what do we mean with AI being accessible I mean I also have to say I'm not an
AI expert here but I mean AI needs a lot of data to be trained and then if you're using open data
then the results of research of AI to build something it should be at least available to
people I'm not saying all the AI should be open I mean this is another discussion but if there is
public money involved in the research then it should be open and people should be able to see
how these AI systems are being trained are and what kind of data has been used and yeah what not
yeah yeah I mean yeah yeah this is a question I regarding this year
a and that maybe it's a huge threat for the free software community in the beginning of this talk
I mentioned that I wanted to focus on the public money public code so basically public procurement
on an open source I would be very happy to chat with you about this because we have also been
meeting decision makers on this file as well and so far it is still a little bit unclear how we're
gonna move forward from our side and also from their side this is just starting so I cannot
really let me tell you more but if for this for this topic I would prefer to keep this out and
then I will be very happy to stay with you after after this talk and then we can chat a little bit
yeah I mean yesterday yesterday at 11 there you can see the recordings there was the European
Commission was here was a with Red Hat they did a panel on this year a there was it was super
interesting so I also invite you if you couldn't attend to see the recordings of this panel
yeah this is my time's up yeah I'm gonna reply to this yeah so if this is in line with the
research community as well and this is something we have noticed and we are really trying to focus
more now on research because I feel like this is a community that we have left a little bit apart
and behind and with AI we know we notice the importance of including all this research
communities so this is definitely something we want to keep working on and keep I don't know try to
do it better in a better way because it is definitely a community that can contribute a lot
to us and I think they're quite open to this to to be open to be free software and so on so yeah
this is on our agenda yeah thank you very much you you