Hello and welcome to my talk about a tool called Rege.
It has something to do with a beehive and jail and I'm going to explain what it actually
does, why it does it that way, what are the goals and what's the initiative behind it.
So a relevant thing about me is I'm a co-founder of Hackerspace in my hometown.
I was lucky enough to marry this girl and she supports me in all my crazy IT endeavors
so Hackerspace was founded by us and it's a place where I do most of my development
in the open source community.
I've been a free business user since 2016.
I used it briefly before 5.0 came out.
And I'm somewhat involved in FreeBSD but I'm not a developer yet.
I'm a FreeBSD contributor and for those of you that don't know what cBSD is, it's a
jail and beehive manager.
It can also manage Zen and VirtualBox but Rege doesn't support these two.
I decided to have only FreeBSD native technologies supported.
And obviously I'm an author of the software I'm about to talk about.
So you might have seen similar tools like Vagrant and Docker Compose if you come from
the Linux world like I do.
And in that regard it's not revolutionary, it's actually pretty same thing.
It's a manual development in a virtual machine or the jail.
And currently jail has a really good support.
Beehive is worked on because it has different distributions of Linux, different operating
systems, versions and so on and it's a little bit harder to support because of those differences.
And Oleg, who is a lead developer of cBSD decided to create a cBSD file which resembles
somewhat Vagrant file in ideas and not the syntax.
And I decided to take a different approach.
So it's kind of a silly situation currently that there are two cBSD DevOps tools but we
were trying out things and whatever works best is gonna stay.
I'm rooting for the Rege of course.
So the concept is that, well before I start with this, it would say the name of the project
is Rege.
I have a dreadlocks and I'm a musician.
But I don't play Rege.
It comes from a totally different idea.
I have quite a few projects before this one that are all open source and now dead that
had somehow referenced some songs or ideas from the Rege movement and music.
And I said, okay how about I name this one Rege and stop the streak of resembling something
I actually don't want to resemble.
So that's where the name comes from.
It's me trying to come up with a name to stop the Rege streak.
So the basic concept behind Rege is that it uses cBSD for all heavy lifting.
All jail and beehive management is done with it.
Some of the networking is done with cBSD, some with RC.conf.
I'm gonna get to that a bit later.
And Rege has two entities.
One is a service, one is a project.
I intentionally called it a service because it can be a virtual machine or the jail.
And the project is you might want to have different jails for different stuff.
Let's say you're working with WordPress as a hoster and you know you need the PHP with
WordPress, Nginx on one side and MySQL on the other.
You probably don't want all of that to be inside the same container so you can split
those up.
You can influence the order of creation and booting and everything.
We still don't have dependencies between jails but we might have in the future because it's
a really nice feature.
You probably are not gonna type all the commands to create the jail and then all the services
inside of it.
You're gonna use some of the provisioners and I'm gonna talk about that in a while.
Where I come from, that's basically Serbia, we don't have IPv6.
Forgive me if I didn't implement IPv6 properly because I have a really limited resources
in testing that.
There is of course tunnels that I use and I try to combine stuff but yeah, I'm basically
with one hand behind the back.
So I really try to support it, I just don't know if I've done it properly.
Technologies, well, it's a mouthful.
With vNet jails you can use DHCP and I almost insist on using vNet because for me as a system
administrator it's easier than jails, I just fire up DHCP server, the DNS server, they
are interconnected and to be specific DHCP is ICS, DNS server is NSD and there's one
more DNS caching which is unbound.
There are, well, all these technologies you probably know what they are.
RTA, DVD is for IPv6 as I mentioned and PF, I would love to add IPFW, that's the future.
So I don't cut off, I don't know what percentage of free BSD people but yeah, we wanna support
everyone and everything ideally.
And these two make and POSIX shell are the only languages used to implement reggae.
I could get away with it because the CBSD is doing the whole stuff and I just need to
script a few things, right.
As I said, provisioners are supported.
You don't have to use them, you can still just create a jail and do your, maybe it's
a lab and you're playing with it, experimenting and whatnot but if you want you can run quite
a few automation scripts and you can even have multiple provisioners for a single jail.
That sounds crazy but if you think about it, sorry, wrong operating system.
Free BSD doesn't come with a pre-installed Python and if you want to use Ansible you
are gonna install Python first then the Ansible later.
And for situations like that it's really, really nice to have shell provisioner doing
like a first stage of the rocket launch and then Ansible does all the rest.
I use shell and Ansible extensively and the rest of the provisioners, I really try to
support them.
I used all of them or am using them at work or somewhere else but I'm not using them as
extensively as the first two so if you find a bug please report it.
I will be nice and fix it if I know how to.
So really it brings some things to the table that CBSD alone doesn't.
I mean that's the reason it's created because it builds on top of something I personally
consider a good software.
And what it brings is in order to run let's say Win
and Jails you will probably need a bridge and then some e-pairs and so on but bridge
interface has to be created or at least allowed different administrators to have their own
configuration of a bridge and not actually enforce what the CBSD comes with by default.
And it's initializing network in such a way that PF is already configured, bridge is configured,
IPv4 and IPv6 demons are stored and it's unbound and what not.
So it initializes quite a lot and you might not like it and if you don't you have quite
a few variables to disable stuff.
For example you can disable IPv6 or have your projects resigned in a different directory
not the default one and so on.
So there's quite a financialization that it does because if you currently read how to
start VNet jail in FreeBSD it's not really easy if you read it in different jail managers
it might be better.
I didn't check other documentation so I don't know but currently FreeBSD documentation
around jail is kind of scarcin, not really depicting at all.
And one of the things that it helps you with is how do you even start with it.
Because I come from a Linux world in 2016 I was like how am I doing stuff, what do I
do, how do I configure it and that was actually the reason I chose CBSD.
At the time it made most logic, it was most intuitive tool for me to run my jails.
Since then I discovered it's good for other things not just intuition right.
But yeah I just love the software.
The same as with the CBSD initialization because CBSD can do quite a lot.
It can track resources, it can give you the usage of network per jail, it can do stuff
and in order to do that it has to ask you things.
For example are you using IPFW or PF and things like that are you using ZFS or UFS, what should
I do, create clones or directories and so on.
Regga chose a different path or I chose it for it.
You can say use ZFS, yes or no and if it's no luckily we only have two file systems so
either you use ZFS or the other one UFS.
So the initial configuration is quite easier with Regga and CBSD and maybe if you're starting
with the stack it's going to help you on your way from infancy to pro how to even start
with CBSD and Regga.
There is one decision to, okay let me take a step back.
I try to create everything as the code but some things are just not meant to be like
how do you assign addresses.
CBSD has two, let's say two DHCP implementations.
One is DHCP, it's called DHCP and what it does is run through all the IP addresses and
finds the first free one and assign it to jail only on creation so it's not going to
scan every time just when the jail is created it's going to scan them.
So existing IP addresses and the configured IP addresses of jails that are not stored.
So there is a second implementation of the recipe, it's called real DHCP.
The idea is to have one master jail that has the CPU and DNS in it, authoritative DNS in
it and there is local unbound outside of jail that says okay if you want zone that your
jails are belonging to then look at here.
It's from the Regga and CBSD perspective it's not so much about caching, actually it's not
at all about caching although unbound is known for it and created for that purpose.
It's more like how to call it a cop at the junction you go over here and it's redirecting
the queries.
So the idea is that probably while developing with Regga you're going to have a private
IP address range and you want to still ask the DNS hey where is stuff because one thing
that's actually two things are annoying to me about Docker at least when I used it.
Docker containers know by name where other Docker containers are but you don't.
You have to use either IP addresses or etc host hackery or something.
And the second thing that really annoyed me is that I cannot have a user on this laptop
with I don't know UID of 1001 and have the same user in a Docker container and do development
inside of Docker container.
It just matching the IDs was really terrible.
I at least hope it was, it's not pertained but the idea behind that kind of frustration
led to okay how about I have a DNS server.
I mean it's what it's for to tell you where the IP address of this name is and so on.
So yeah I couldn't create just the code.
I still need one jail to do some maintenance stuff and some networking stuff.
The nice thing about IPFW is that you can insert a rule whenever you want.
If you're coming from Linux world that means it behaves like IP tables but PF doesn't.
And PF has a pretty static set of rules unless you're using anchors.
Anchors are a way to say okay this is a sub rule of the main rule and anchors can be changed
and they are per jail called cbsd slash your jail name.
So it's easier to see which rules are for which jails and I don't want to trash Docker
too much but if you ever seen IP tables rules after the Docker mangles them it's a mess.
It's a huge mess.
So I try to be nicer as much as technologies and freebies they allow just don't be sorry
don't be so negative towards developers and administrators they're gonna hate you.
And so yeah when I say late these anchors are created after the jail is stored so it
already has an IP address and can use the port redirection and whatever you need.
And yeah because until the jail is stored it already registered itself.
So it's a lease and DHCP registered in an NSD zone.
So these anchors can use host names instead of IP addresses and if you're using DHCP you
probably have no idea what's the IP address.
So the nice thing is that you can use names to really sort your networking and firewalling
I would say in a proper way in a more readable way.
And there is a concept of in something called DevOps that I still don't know what it means.
They say the DevOps is IP accounting they know what not to click on AWS otherwise it's
gonna cost you.
So it's like a administrator plus accounting right.
But yeah in a DevOps world you want your production to resemble development or maybe the other
way around.
But yeah the fewer the differences between your development and your production the bigger
the chances that you're gonna catch bugs in development not in production.
Also users are the best monitoring system in the world.
Okay so because of the vNet just the vNet implies that you're going to have to use some custom
VFS rules because you want access to BPF you want access to PF so it can have its own firewall.
And naturally DevFS rules are supported in reggae.
Unfortunately by number not by name but hopefully that will change.
Net warrior is integer or should I say unsigned integer it works like nice the bigger the
number the later you're going to boot.
So it's not a perfect solution but it's a solution to start your WordPress after the
MySQL for example.
And it even works if you remove the reggae you create everything with reggae remove it
it still works the boot order works.
So that I really try to make booting really really work even if I did something naughty
to my code and it breaks.
So I kind of have a fail safe.
I didn't know where majority of you are from but for some reason in Serbia package repository
is extremely slow.
If I get two mbits that's like wow that's a light speed.
I don't know why it works like that maybe it's our providers because I talk to different
people and they don't have that problem.
So I came up with solution work around.
What if all my gels just use proxy and first one is going to download everything and it's
going to be painfully slow.
But the next one all the next ones for just going to use the cached.
Just files and there is a reggae recipe for proxy.
So you don't have to type in a bunch of commands you just go to the repo download it type make
and you're going to have a proxy.
You're going to have to change the configuration to tell it to use it but it's as simple as
it gets.
In my open source career I mostly work with audio and that's mostly graphical.
So I needed something like don't pollute my host and let me use jail for development.
But on the other hand let me click on the buttons because I need to.
So reggae has a really easy way of forwarding.
I think it's called forwarding in X. Open the port and all the X applications are connected
to that port.
So X is on the X org is on host and your X client is inside the jail so you can interact
with it.
And yeah it supports both but I'm going to have to work real hard on this one as the
newest addition to the source code so it received the least amount of love and currently it
only supports free BSD virtual machines.
What's beneath it is C-BSD is using cloud in it to do your bootstrapping of a virtual
machine to have the initial configuration and then your provisioner or provisioners
can kick in and do whatever you like.
Whatever you told them to.
So what does development mean?
There is a devil mode because it's exposing so many things and doing it rather insecurely
for the sake of a developer being able to do stuff.
I kind of think the devil mode is pretty good.
It's so close to the devil, right?
So it has this development mode where you, for example, share your directory where the
services with the jail.
I borrowed this idea from Vagrant having a slash Vagrant being a mount point of your
project and you can interact with it either through the host or through the container.
And yeah, it's a mountain and slash user slash source.
It kind of made sense because I kind of expect people not to do free BSD kernel or user space
development inside a jail.
You might find that an obstacle, but you can still mount your own stuff on top of whatever
reggae and C-BSD do.
So you can add your mount points and stuff.
So it's not limiting if you're doing free BSD development, which I expect some of you
do.
It's not going to be in the way.
This user is in the jail and has the same user ID and group ID as the user and host
that executed make inside of a reggae service.
So that slash user slash source is all owner is the devil user and you can interact with
it.
It's read, write.
So the only difference is that the user name and group name is probably going to be different.
I say probably because I expect you not to name your user devil.
And there are, while I was working on this, I was pretty active for quite a few years
as a web developer, which is kind of strange for a free BSD guy, free BSD contributor.
And what I realized is how about I have one line saying, okay, I'm going to, in these
jails I'm going to use like Django or something as my framework that I'm going to use.
So it does a few alterations of how it does things, so it lets you run your frameworks
more easily.
And I shouldn't actually use plural because the only framework that's currently supported
is called print and guess who the author is.
But the idea is that you have a directory in your service called bin and inside of it
you have a devil.sh and Regga doesn't know what's inside of it.
It's just going to run it inside the jail.
And usually for the web development I like to have a T-max with split pane, back-end,
front-end, and it knows how to tell front-end where the back-end API is if you need to integrate
and you do.
But basically you can create your own devil script and the Regga will be happy about it.
So it can do much more than just one framework.
But in the future I'm going to add quite a few to make people not so much involved with
jails, easier to start using it.
So production is totally different thing.
I mean the opposite.
It's going to say, okay, this jail is going to start with the boot of the machine.
It's also going to try its best to remove everything this created like the user source
mount, some of the scripts that are installed for devil to work easily and so on.
So what's the idea here is that if you want to create like a build server or maybe on
your machine you're using devil mode and you created it like that and then afterwards you
say devil mode equals no, make down, make up, and make up is going to clean everything
that devil created and then you can make export and create an image, move it to some other
server import it there and it just means so that you can have like either your development
container productionized, not a good idea.
Don't do it if you can avoid it.
But sometimes you can't and it works on my machine so ship it.
But the more serious use case for it is to have your build server build the image of
a jail and then you deploy it somewhere.
So this is an example of, so up to here, first three commands are creating the project and
the project name is going to be as the directory you created.
So the project containing multiple services, well in this instance just want to make it
compact.
So up to here it's creating the project and then project expects services directory to
contain your jail or beehive definitions.
And the definitions are created with this, you can omit this part and it's not going
to create any provisioner for you or you can say here Ansible shall puppet and that's the
order of provisioners that are going to be run.
It has a few more expectations where things are going to be for a certain provisioner
but it's going to create a skeleton for you so you don't have to create them by yourself
and it's a, well read the code.
If you have the skeleton it's going to be more intuitive what you should do next with
your own code with your own development.
And it's pretty slick.
It can be done differently I just think to me this was most intuitive and I'm trying
not to go against intuition.
So there is, let's say all of us need something I don't know like MySQL.
We all here in this room are hosting WordPress and we all need MySQL WordPress and Nginx.
But you don't have to create it on your own.
There are pre-made recipes for that.
They are not images, they are still in this instance they are all Ansible.
And you can combine jails and beehives provision with different provisioners and in this case
it's going to download these three jails, configure them and interconnect them because
Nginx has to know where WordPress is and WordPress needs to know where the database is.
But it's not going to create a database for you.
It's still like okay I don't know what you want.
Is it a single instance or you're hosting multiple WordPress instances and you need
multiple databases and so on.
So that's left up to you.
But if you go to the MySQL everything is, if you want to look at code of this just add
jail-myscale and you're going to have the repository.
And there's a readme which tells you okay this is how you create a database in this
jail so you can do it differently of course but if you're coming from different environment
I try to hold your hand as much as I can but you can ignore it.
The same is for the WordPress and Nginx has a directory with quite a few examples how
you create your own hosts inside the Nginx configuration but it's not going to configure
it for you.
It's a recommendation and not much, okay you have to do it this way.
And this URL is probably the most complex project I did with Rege.
Most complex in a sense that it has the biggest number of jails and services inside of it
that need to talk to each other.
And well if you try to manage Jabber and Mail and do it responsibly you know that you need
all the help you can get.
So I try to create this service that creates the Mail and Jabber communication server it
gives you the documentation on how you should configure your DNS, what's inside of it, the
links towards specific services and their own configurations and examples and so on.
So it's my way of avoiding writing documentation.
I mean we all do that.
We have better things to do or better things to do.
So if you have an example it's a documentation on its own.
And yeah the future.
What can be better than documentation, right?
But what I want to say is that Oleg who is CBSD lead developer is Russian and I'm going
to quote him, my English is terrible so our documentation currently is not good.
I'm not going to say terrible but it's not good as it can be and that's literally our
next assignment.
We already talked a few months before about it and documentation is really killing us
or the lack of good documentation and way of searching it and browsing it and finding
what you need.
There is quite a few documents that describe how specific scenarios should be executed
or specific commands.
What options do they have?
It just still needs to be worded better and more coherent and connected better so that
you can say okay if I read this, this and this I know where I'm going to be and then
I know how to manage WordPress for example.
So documentation is a really big thing that maybe it's going to be the only thing that
we are going to work on besides the bugs.
So yeah sorry about not being very good with documents but we promise we will improve.
Now these two I hope they are not mutually exclusive.
Jail Conf is a much much simpler way.
It's in the base.
It really works wonderful and it can even manage your Beehive because today I don't
know with which version it's for but you can have a Beehive inside your jail and if you
have that you can only manage jail and that's kind of wonderful.
What we really need or at least I would like to have is Jail Conf D working really great.
Currently it doesn't.
One of the obstacles, well two of the obstacles, in Jail Conf you can define dependencies between
jails and that's how it's going to boot, it's going to create a tree and then go from the
leaves to the root.
But you can do that with Jail Conf D and there is a patch coming from a developer I know
from Yerevan called Antranik and he promised he's going to upstream that patch this weekend
so we are watching you.
But yeah it's almost there.
The second obstacle with Jail Conf D is that you cannot have common configuration like
you can in a Jail Conf because Jail Conf is one file with multiple jails.
Jail Conf D is multiple jails, sorry, multiple files, one jail profile.
You can probably have multiple jails per file but that kind of kills the idea.
The idea is to have better service jails start or stop or whatever and then probably most
of us jail managers, developers are going to unite in it and say okay this is how we
use it.
Now you can criticize us and why didn't you do that in the first place?
But I guess we needed to experiment and learn and see what works and what not so that we
know once we upstream it to Jail Conf it's going to be what we expect it to be.
And Kubernetes, all jokes aside, I don't know if you're following but there is more and
more Kubernetes support in Potsfry and there is, I hope I'm going to pronounce the name
properly, Doug Robson is working on Kubernetes support, Podman is already there and Doug
has a pretty initial version of Kubernetes working on FreeBSD with VNet and jails.
Why I'm hoping for this to happen is so that we can have easier transition from Linux to
FreeBSD and honestly there's a friend of mine who promised me that we are going to try mixed
Kubernetes data centers is Linux Freak, I'm a FreeBSD Freak so let's try to create one
domain that is going to be mixed operating systems in Kubernetes.
Who knows where it leads us?
Maybe we just lose our hair but if we do succeed it's a really easy way to switch to migrate
from one operating system to the other because realistically maybe you want to switch from
FreeBSD to Linux, please don't.
But yeah, who knows what's your use case and maybe your workplace is such that it simply
has to be like that.
So yeah, I'm hoping this will not live because it leaves more space for this and so I'm kind
of like a split brain person, I really don't know what I want with Kubernetes.
It's probably here to stay so we need to support it in order to be kinder towards other developers
and system administrators, maybe DevOps.
So I would like to thank a few communities and persons.
Telesenter for supporting my crazy ideas and testing everything I do.
At least few of the people are testing my crazy ideas and reporting back and sometimes
in doing slight development.
I'm really grateful to be physically in an environment that is supporting me in such
a way because usually I don't know about you but I suspect we're the crazy ones.
Why don't you use drugs like all normal kids or the Docker or whatever, right?
So yeah, it's really nice to be supported.
The FreeBSD community, I don't know how to say this enough.
They've been supportive and helpful and I didn't encounter a question that somebody
didn't answer if I was persistent enough.
In the FreeBSD community, all again in particular, he created cbsd by himself and it's an enormous
task.
It even has end curses commands to make it easier for you.
So it's enormous task that started 10 years ago, 2013, and so it's our big anniversary
this year.
I think it's somewhere during the summer but I will have to check that.
Usually we announced that on a cbsd site and I'm afraid I didn't remember it.
It was a few days before the FOSDEM and I was doing a bunch of things to basically prepare.
So these are, if you want to ask something, contribute whatever is on your mind around
regi cbsd or whatever music maybe.
These are my contacts and now is the right time to ask questions.
Thank you.
Oh, he's going to die.
He's going to die.
I have a question.
You spoke about order and it's just that you put, for example, mysec for WordPress or there
is also a mechanism that allows you like a readiness probe to check if the database is
ready to serve.
Okay, so the question was, if I understood correctly, if boot order can also check if
the database is stored before it stores the WordPress?
No, it cannot do that but it will at some point because the jail conf can have dependencies
and at some point I'm really hoping to switch to dependencies instead of boot order because
who likes boot order?
If you have like 200 jails, who knows what stores when?
But with dependencies it's much easier.
Any more questions?
Yes, mostly for cbsd but you can find one for the regi that depicts mostly how to initialize
it and start the really dumb project that almost has nothing in it.
Sorry, the question was, I didn't catch that second one.
Yes, so the question was, are there any demos and they're on YouTube.
Some of them are on Russian and some of them are on, it's called Askinema.
So even from the demo you can copy paste the text and do it yourself or commands or whatever.
Okay, anyone else?
Okay, then I'm going to have to say goodbye with the famous words, no ducker, no cry.
Thank you.