Is Lightning talk on DPC++?
Is it DPC++ first, I'm aware?
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
Okay, good afternoon.
Yeah, so I'm going to be talking about compiler
intrinsics in SQL, in DPC++ specifically.
This is Intel's open source SQL implementation.
This is what I work on.
Yeah, so hopefully I'll be able to say something
without saying too much in 10 minutes.
Yeah, so Codeplay, I work for Codeplay.
We had the first SQL implementation, compute CBP.
We now work, we were acquired by Intel.
So now we work on the Intel SQL implementation,
DPC++, that's what I work on.
We have lots of partners, you know,
hardware companies, that kind of thing.
Whoever needs an open CL implementation,
SQL implementation, and so on, come to us.
Yeah, so SQL is a single source heterogeneous programming API,
so you can write single source code
that can run on NVIDIA Intel AMD GPUs.
Close to the mic, okay.
Voice up, sorry.
Yeah, so it's great for someone who's developing
scientific applications to be able to write single source code
that runs on whatever GPU the implementation enables,
such as CUDA, Level Zero for Intel AMD GPUs, and so on.
Yeah, this is a really good thing.
So I work specifically on the NVIDIA and the HIP
the AMD backends for DPC++.
Okay, so yeah, I just want to talk a little bit about
compiler intrinsics and how kind of, you know,
math function calls work in SQL and DPC++ at the moment,
and how we can hopefully improve them
so that we're contributing upstream.
So what happens to SQL cause?
So essentially you get your SQL cause in your source code.
This is redirected to Sphere V OpenCL cause F.
You compile to Sphere V, you make a Sphere V module.
This is a symbol within the Sphere V module,
and then that is the implementation is provided by
a CL Level Zero Vulkan driver.
Okay, as I said, I don't work on the Sphere V backend at all.
I work the PTX, the CUDA, or the AMD GPU backends.
What do we do with these symbols so that we get to the native implementations?
We're not trying to reinvent the wheel.
We're not trying to do anything that the people who are making the GPUs
aren't doing already.
We're just trying to redirect to that.
So how do we go from this to that and then compile to our PTX module,
our AMD GPU module, HSA module, and so on?
So yeah, how do we go from Sphere V OCL to NV cause F?
So use the SHIM library. Easy peasy, that's fine.
You just redirect it, you compile it to Bitcode,
you link it at compilation time, and you get to this native Bitcode implementation.
This is great.
So we use libclc for this.
So libclc is written in OpenCL.
OpenCL does lots of stuff that SQL doesn't expose as easily,
like address spaces, that kind of thing.
So we write it in OpenCL.
This is great.
This makes our lives really, really easy.
We can do it.
So before we get into this, just why do we want to use a BC library in the first place?
Why don't we use a.so, why don't we just resolve to some symbol
that then a runtime is called and we don't care about it?
So on a GPU, the overhead of a function call is really high.
It's because we lose information about, say, address spaces, that kind of thing.
The GPU memory hierarchy is a bit more complex than, say, for CPUs.
So we really, really need to worry about this.
We want to inline everything so we don't lose any information
about our memory hierarchies.
We also allow compile time branching of code
based on the architecture, based on the backend, that kind of thing.
We don't want to have these checks at runtime.
We want high performance.
That's the name of the game for what we're doing.
This gives us greater optimization opportunities as well.
You can do lots of dead code elimination,
lots of fun stuff in the middle end
because you're doing all these checks at the IR level.
Okay, so this is just kind of what it looks like.
So we just have Spirbio CL, COSF.
We return nb-cosf. Great. Amazing.
That's so easy.
And then this is the implementation which is provided by NVIDIA.
This is in bit code.
We link this, and then this is just inlined into our IR.
This is great.
Okay.
Yes, so we're linking the SQL code with libclc.
Then we link that with the vendor provided BC library.
So we're linking, linking.
We get to the implementation. It's all inlined.
It's all great. We love it.
Okay. So this works well.
So this is a bit of code from libclc.
Because we're dealing in openclc, we could choose something else.
We could write a native IR.
We find that opencl is actually easier to use
than easier to maintain than writing a native IR.
So we end up with some funny kind of problems with mangling
and all this kind of thing.
This isn't nice.
Sometimes we need manual mangling.
This has got to do with namespaces when they're interpreted
by the opencl mangling, unfortunately.
Yeah, we need to sometimes as well.
Sometimes opencl isn't as good as we want it to be.
So we need to actually write in native IR as well.
So it's a mix of like lvm IR, libclc.
It's a bit messy. It's not great.
Yeah, so also we're exposing some compiler internals here.
This is the nvvm reflect pass,
which essentially takes your function call for nvvm reflect,
replaces it with the numeric value.
This is totally done at the IR level.
So you can branch at the IR level based on this is a high architecture,
a newer architecture, do this new implementation,
do this new built-in.
This is an old architecture, da-da-da, as well for things like rounding modes.
This pass is used.
We're exposing this in source code through hacks.
This isn't really, you know, it's not kosher.
But it works. Who cares?
Okay, but consider the new proposal to add FP accuracy attributes to math built-ins.
This is where we have, say, FP built-in cause,
and we specify the accuracy in ULP that we want it to be computed to.
Okay, this is totally lost on us.
Okay, so this is what it would look like.
Yeah, you have this attribute here.
You've FP max error.
This is really, really needed in sickle because sickle is targeting lots
and lots of different platforms.
All these platforms have different numerical accuracy guarantees.
We really, really need this.
We don't use built-ins at all.
We're sorry, we don't use LLVM intrinsics at all.
So this is, we need to get to a point where we can start using this compiler infrastructure.
We're not using it as much as you want to.
So we could do this using a libclc compiler kind of hack workaround.
We do another pass.
You just say compiler precision valve.
If it's that, do some precise square root.
If it's not, do some approx thing.
Yeah, we could do that.
The problem with libclc and this stuff, it's not upstreamable.
It's a collection of hacks.
It's not totally hacks, but it's a little bit messy.
It's not written in the same API.
It's opencl and it's lvmyr.
It's messy.
We can upstream this.
We can all benefit from this.
Okay.
So the pro about doing some, adding another hack to the kind of pass,
there's another hack to the bunch, is that it's easy to do.
Okay.
We can do this and we can keep going with our libclc implementation.
It's pretty straightforward.
We've been doing this the whole time.
Yeah, fine.
We don't need to worry about the broader LLVM concerns.
However, we miss out on LLVM community collaboration, which is why we're here.
And then how many of these workarounds do we actually need in order to keep up
with the latest trends?
And then libclc, as bad as it could be now, like it just degenerates into an
absolute mess and we don't want that.
Okay.
So we think the answer for this is to try and redirect, try and actually have it
call in the compiler intrinsic.
Okay.
We want to use compiler intrinsic and then have some generic behavior of these
are the intrinsic for offload targets.
Okay.
And this would be used by say open MP, by, by, you know, coup de clang and so on,
all these different targets.
But we don't have this transformation.
We're not comfortable with this connection.
Okay.
From an intrinsic to a vendor provided BC built in.
Why is that?
Essentially this needs to happen as early as possible in the, at the IR level.
We're adding an external dependency in our LLVM kind of, you know, pipeline.
We need to link this BC library early on in our, in our pipeline.
We don't do this.
We're not comfortable with doing this.
We need to figure out a way that people will be happy with us doing this.
Okay.
Obviously we're used to things resolving to external symbols, but then that's a
runtime thing.
It's not, it's not a compile time thing.
Okay.
This needs to be in line.
We need to be able to do some stuff with this at the IR level.
Okay.
So there will still be cases where we need libCLC potentially.
It's not going to, you know, just disappear from our SQL implementation.
Hopefully.
But we need to start pushing towards better kind of resolution, better use of
these intrinsics in LLVM for offload in general.
Okay.
So why?
Shared infrastructure, keep an eye, keep on the cutting edge of new
developments, left compiler hacks, and we make sickle compilation eventually
work upstream.
It doesn't at the moment, but eventually we want it to, of course.
We're trying to upstream as much as possible, but libCLC is not upstreamable.
And that's a problem.
Okay.
So the first step, try and have this discussion about making the
intrinsics work for offload.
Okay.
So time.
Time's up.
So we need to have this link step at the IR level early on in the IR kind of
pipeline.
There's problematic for some people, but we need to talk about this.
So please join in the discussion here.
This is MVPTX code gen for LLVM sign in front if you have any opinions on this.
Sorry, I kind of ran over a little bit, but yeah, any questions?
I was wondering, would it make sense to try to get rid of the mess by going to
an MLIR type of approach or like what are the benefits or downsides to MLIR?
So I'm not an expert.
So the question was, are there benefits?
Can we avoid this by going to MLIR?
I think it's more fundamental than MLIR.
I'm not an expert on MLIR, but I think we need basic resolution of intrinsic
presumably with MLIR.
You'll have, you know, other MLIR, our intrinsics that will need the same kind
of treatment.
We'll have the same questions there.
So this is the first case study.
This is the most simple case.
We're not trying to implement the new a few built-ins with the accuracy thing.
We're just trying to decide how do we make this dependency on this external
BC live work and do it in a very, very confined sort of way.
Yeah.
Thank you.
I have two questions.
First one is a tutorial to generate NV for a PTX from MLIR.
There is a whole section about linking with the Bitcoin library from NVIDIA.
So what's the difference with this?
And the second question is you mentioned NVVM, which is the closed source
PTX generator from NVIDIA.
And there is also the LLVM NVPTX back end.
Are we reaching SPE RT with the closed source one?
It depends on the application.
We find that with the second question first, is there still a big performance
gap between the native, say, NVCC compiler and LLVM clang?
So in terms of DPC++, which is a fork of LLVM, we're attaining, say, roughly
comparable performance, whether you're using SYCL or you're using CUDA with
NVCC, and then any improvements that we make to the kind of compiler or whatever.
They're shared by Clang CUDA as well.
So the first question again was how is this different from?
It's a tutorial to link Bitcoin with LLVM.
So essentially when you're linking Bitcoin or whatever, you're not using any
LLVM intrinsics.
You're just redirecting things yourself.
You're not using intrinsics.
So you need to do everything explicitly.
You need to either have a specific kind of driver path that will do this for you
or you need to specifically say, I want to link this in at this time or whatever.
And so it's more manual.
It's not happening automatically.
It's not happening really within the compiler.
It's happening at link time, LLVM link time.
All right.
Thank you, Hugh.
Thank you.