Okay. Hello. Bonjour.
Who did our good talk?
I think that's sort of the Brussels welcome.
Yeah. So I want to talk about
what we're doing in the Postgres project
with respect to translation.
It seems like the last two talks already
solved 50 percent of my problems.
So there was already a good outcome of coming here.
I want to talk a little bit more sort of
the lower levels of what GetTAC specifically does,
but I'll also goes kind of through
what other things we're doing.
So I am in the Postgres project.
I'm just a C programmer.
It's my job really to do the translation sort of as a hobby on the side.
I have done initially sort of most of the setup.
So of the source code level,
what he called internationalization at that case.
Then I'm also doing some of the translation.
Yeah. It turns out also
the first faucet I went to was 20 years ago.
I like coming here because there's
a Postgres dev room happening at
the same time in a different building,
but I like to come to all the other places
and sort of intersect with other communities and learn
about other kind of stuff that's happening.
So it's kind of a good benefit of FOSDEM.
So what's Postgres?
Don't need to go into details,
but it's a little bit different.
It has different requirements.
It's a database system.
It's fairly big and fairly old,
but it's different from like a GUI program, let's say.
Something we've leave office
or hear from KDE later on things like that.
I think it just lives much longer
and has longer stability requirements and things like that.
That also kind of makes the maintenance of everything
a little bit more complicated.
We also maintain back branches.
So we have a yearly release,
but we still maintain the old releases for at least five years.
So at any given moment,
we have four or five or six releases live.
That gives it interesting challenges
with back-patching stuff.
Just I was quite interested in the last question we had
in the previous talk about this translation memory
and sort of that rung through.
Can we automatically apply the memory
to the previous branches and stuff like that?
So this sort of stuff is a practical challenge
because you have to keep copying the same thing
to all the different branches and so on.
Any case, so what are we doing in Postgres?
You know we use GetX as in the title.
Now put this sort of standard new question mark.
It's kind of weird because again Postgres is old
and runs on servers is a little bit different
from sort of what runs on a laptop or an app.
Because for example, we also support operating systems
that might still already be forgotten like AIX and Solaris.
And they have GetXed originally came from the sort of
solaris sphere somehow and there's still a,
well I don't know what it is now,
but like a Solaris native Solaris GetXed exists.
It's you know, that's distinct from new.
But it's sort of old has bugs and doesn't parse stuff
correctly sometimes so when you just sort of use
you use the new version then sometimes the files
you distribute don't work on old Solaris for some reason
and then this is sort of just a weird situation.
You have to like then fix these things
and then or hope that Solaris dies at some point, right?
Stuff like that.
So it's like that.
So we have, I mean, you know, we hear from KDE Next.
I already looked at Hetzel at their abstract.
This is obviously not a lot in terms of how many languages
and message catalogs and strings we have,
but it's more than something you can just deal with
in an afternoon, right?
It's just a lot of stuff to move around.
I mentioned with the different branches,
we also have it in a separate Git repository.
I think that's kind of common, I think,
so that you can manage access to translators
separate from the source repository
and then you just move it back and forth.
Again, maybe the web label will help with that
and we have also sort of other projects in the vicinity
of the core server projects such as JDBC driver,
which is obviously in Java, which is slightly different
sort of tooling and stuff like that.
And PG Admin is a GUI.
They have their own workflow.
So it's all a little bit all over the place
and it's hard to kind of keep that all moving
in the same way.
And there's also some documentations are being translated,
but that's also handled completely separately.
We were actually just talking to break.
We could use Libra Translate for that maybe at some point.
So all kinds of interesting ideas already coming up here.
All right, so this is my like web late, but terrible job.
This is kind of how we handle it.
The web interface is under bobble.postgresql.org.
And that just gives you sort of the status, right?
Of what languages and what the message catalogs are.
And it does sort of the string extraction,
the merging in the background as you would do, you know,
in the make file, but it just kind of runs it for you
from a cron job.
Again, it's just sort of really old,
but it does the job.
And then the workflow is, yeah, you go like, you know,
you pick your language, pick what you want to work on.
You click on it, you download it,
you do the translation with the, you know,
the get text tools, whatever editor you want to use,
different people use different things.
And then you commit it back, right?
And there's different, all the branches are available here.
So you can scroll down and you're just going to fill these
up and so, yeah, these are the languages across here.
What the colors mean is that green is 100% translated.
And then one thing we did, which I don't,
we just kind of made up, but we decided if a message catalog
is not translated to at least 80%, we're not going to ship
it, right?
You don't want to just ship like one string.
I mean, you could, but it would be weird for a user
that all of a sudden the translated string pops up
and nothing else is translated, right?
It's maybe a little bit weird.
So that's something we sort of decided on until randomly
and it seems to actually kind of work pretty well.
So the yellow ones are the ones that we would ship
and then the white ones are just the ones
that are not complete at all.
All right, so workflow is the usual get text workflow
for at least C programs, you know,
there's other stuff happening nowadays.
So if the developer marks up the messages
with this kind of underscore thing that they recommend
and our developers are totally good about that, right?
They're all aware of that you need to do that.
And for the most part, it's wrapped into things like this.
So you don't actually have to manually mock up everything.
If you use like this sort of standard internal API,
say print an error, log an error, whatever the case may be,
then it's already done for you.
So that works pretty well.
It's, you know, every once in a while something gets missed,
but it's not a big problem.
All the developer group is aware of that.
Then I mentioned the website uses those standard tools
to give you something you just have to download
and then you just translated and upload it back.
Then at release time, someone, often me,
just then runs a script to copy that over,
which could be automated, but you know,
it's one of those things we have releases four times a year
and you just do it manually four times a year
or you could spend X hours automating it, right?
So usually it's just done manually.
All right, so this is our tool chain at the moment.
Again, GNU, question mark, get text.
We have a pretty standard sort of configure,
make, make, install, build system.
We don't use any of these make file templates
and things like that, that ship it, get text,
because we have our own sort of very convoluted build system
based on GNU make.
We're also in the process of getting rid of that.
So we're moving to, to Mason now,
which has some support for that built in,
but it's kind of incomplete.
So we're sort of stuck sort of halfway here, halfway there.
I have to kind of work,
that's kind of work we're doing right now.
I have to figure that out.
So people use whatever editor they want to use.
Poet it seems to be somewhat popular.
I use just Emacs.
Some teams have used, by teams I mean sort of language teams.
They have used crowd in,
which I suppose is sort of similar to Webblade maybe.
But again, we were just talking to break,
maybe we'll look at Webblade.
And then a horrible bag of shell scripts and pro scripts
and make files that sort of hold it all together,
which again could be replaced by something better.
It's just never really figured out what that could be.
So pros and cons of doing any of this.
One thing I obviously we want to translate
because we want to translate, right?
So that's sort of the ultimate requirement.
But what I found interesting
as a sort of secondary benefits is actually that
by putting all your messages of your programs
through a translation process,
you get an automatic review of every message string.
Because every thing you put in the source code
is looked again later by at least one more person
or several all the translators.
And you catch like typos and stuff like that,
but also if something doesn't make any sense, right?
Maybe some developer wrote it and it makes sense to them,
but then someone else who is not that very developer
looks at it again, it's like,
okay, I don't really understand this.
I can't translate it because I don't understand it.
Or it looks weird, could we look at it again?
So you get this review process
and we've gotten really good in Postgres
about really tuning error messages.
Because it's a complicated piece of software
and you get all these little weird scenarios
with sort of transaction processing
and weird little write ahead log and replication
and all these kinds of things.
And so you wanna be really good and precise
to explain to you, okay, this failed because of this.
And you could try this, but don't try that.
So this is really, I think people appreciate it.
Independent of translation and everything else,
I think people appreciate that.
And this process actually helps that
because you sort of refine your program's messages
through this process as well.
And secondly, actually it also turned out
that sometimes people come in, do some translation,
maybe find a bug or wanna look something up in a source code,
go into the source code and then become a programmer.
So you can also kind of recruit people that way.
It's kind of interesting.
So, but then there are many challenges, right?
So first of all, you wanna get people in there
to use the translation, right?
And it's just this, because Postgres is not sort of,
or similar systems as well, right?
It's not end user facing.
It's not used by sort of random average people, right?
It's used by technically minded people,
experts, database administrators and so on.
So a lot of those people, there's not too much pressure
to actually have things translated.
People will be, okay, it's not translated, it's fine, right?
Which is different from if LibreOffice or Firefox
is not translated and you install it in the school,
it wouldn't work.
It's just, you can't do that, right?
But here it's like, okay, if it's not,
if it doesn't get done, it's not a problem in a way,
but we just wanna do it because we like it.
But if it doesn't get done, it's like, okay,
then we'll just move on, right?
So you gotta kind of, it relies on a lot of enthusiasm,
individual enthusiasm, right?
A lot of the, yeah, I found also, at least personally,
as doing some of the translation work myself,
terminology is hard sometimes, right?
Because again, I just mentioned something like that.
It's not just press this button to download a thing.
Okay, you can translate that in any language probably by now.
But what if you get into terms like, you know,
sub-transaction rollback or incremental
materialized view maintenance, you know?
Some languages might not even have terms for that, maybe.
You know, sometimes when I do the work,
I pick, you know, I have some textbooks,
like academic textbooks in German in my case.
And I just go through them, like, anybody in here
talk about materialized views?
What kind of terminology are they using?
And then I have like six books and three do it this way,
three do it that way, and then I just pick something
at some point, right?
So in some way, we have to kind of define,
make up the terminology in some cases, even, right?
And as I alluded to, the workflow is not as cool
as what we saw in the previous talk,
so maybe we can improve that.
So here's some sort of source code level challenges.
Some of those are solvable, some of those are not.
People who work in translation know about, like,
plural issues, right?
We do handle that.
Works fine, but then if you, I've never figured out
how to handle the first one.
Like, if you have two or more numbers in a sentence,
like, then you would have to have some combinatorial
sort of list of translations.
What if the first one is singular and the last one
is five, and what if the first one is two
and the last one is 18, you know?
I don't think you can really solve that,
then you start rephrasing things in weird ways.
Well, we have the second one, which obviously
everybody knows you shouldn't do, if you sort of
paste terms together, that doesn't work, right?
Let's say you're just gonna make something up,
like, you cannot apply a generation expression
to a materialized view, let's say, something like that.
That's a thing that could happen in Postgres,
more or less, right?
It's like, okay, you shouldn't do that,
you shouldn't sort of stick that into the middle
of the sentence because then the grammar
doesn't match in some languages.
So you write those out.
But what if you have, like, five options here
and six options there?
Are you gonna make 30 strings in your source code?
At some point, probably not, right?
So, at some point then, developers,
the actual developers do get annoyed if you tell them,
like, no, you can't do that, you have to write
actually 35 error messages by hand,
so not gonna do that.
So in some cases, we did have 20 messages for some stuff
and we had to rephrase so that we only had
the number of answers.
You start then tweaking it, can you say something,
something, semicolon, something, something,
and then maybe at that point it's okay, I don't know,
but yeah, exactly.
So you have to make, use some judgment calls in these cases.
One thing that sometimes happens if developers
add a new file to source code, then it has to be added
somewhere else also to make sure the translation system
catches it and that sometimes gets forgotten.
It's just one of those things, I don't know
if there's a solution for that, you just gotta do it.
There's also some weird thing, we have, like, files
that get compiled into multiple components
and then you kind of have to add them to all of those
components and retranslate everything in each component
which could be handled with some of those translation
memory things and stuff like that, but it's just kind of
weird the way we have it laid out and kind of makes it annoying.
Yeah, so this is maybe specific to something like,
postcodes being A, a client server system, B, a database,
and C having its own sort of ideas about what encoding
on locale and stuff like that means, right?
So in, you know, a database stores data which is often text
which has encoding and because of, you know, nowadays
you think everything's UTF-8, but in a database
you can also store things in other encodings
for historical reasons, but, or in some cases
because UTF-8 doesn't actually match what doesn't support
what you want to store which sounds maybe bizarre
but happens especially in sort of Japanese
and things like that, so we do support automatic encoding
conversion between client and server so that all works
and happens, but then this also, what if you have,
you know, your strings, your translated strings
or in a file, they also have an encoding,
they then get loaded into the server process,
the server process, prints stuff to its own log
but also sends error messages to the client.
All of those things could have different ideas
of what they want, right?
You might want to log stuff in English to your server log
but the client wants the error message in French,
but, or for some, it maybe it's like legacy client
that wants it, you know, transcoded to Latin nine
or, and then at the same time there's a different client
connected that also is doing things
and is sent to a different language,
you want to log it to the same server log
in the same language and the same encoding
hopefully as the other guy.
All of this works quite poorly the way the get text
or the INTL APIs work, you can sort of have some subsets
with this working but if you really try hard,
it's a total mess and it just basically doesn't work.
And so that's a real problem really
and we'd have to really redesign some of this
to support all of these combinations.
Yeah, also the tools, well the tools are fine,
they're actually quite cool and get text has some internal
sort of optimizations that are quite interesting,
has like sort of internal parallelization
and stuff like that so work has been done
but I still find it quite slow, you know,
even on our scale I'm interested to see what the KDE report
is gonna be later on how they handle that
but it is still quite slow, right?
This sort of website thing I showed,
if you just do a full rebuild of that,
it takes like 20 minutes or something, right?
Just to re-merge and re-extract and recombine everything.
So also the format, the PO format is sort of pre-source control,
I find, because it has all these like dates
and time stems in it and which you don't need
because you have it in your source control management
but these, hello.
Can you be more explicit on the 20 minutes?
What do you do in these 20 minutes
because it sounds very slow?
Well, it runs a loop, it extracts,
runs xgettext over the source code
and then it runs message merge against all these catalogs
which are, you know, sort of this many by that many
times that many branches
and you run that on just a machine, right?
So, I mean, you could optimize this
by maybe a beefier machine
and you can probably parallelize this a little bit
but it's still, you know, the main message catalog
for the actual server has like, you know, 5,000 strings
and that is still gonna run like,
I don't really know why but it runs like a couple of minutes.
It's just, it's not, we're doing this build system work now,
right, when we go from make to mason or mason or ninja
because make is too slow
even if you don't have to do anything, right?
So we're trying to sort of go from,
I can rebuild everything in five seconds to two seconds
and this thing takes like 10 minutes
so that's just kind of annoying, right?
Yeah, and I mentioned sort of the back patching,
sort of you, oftentimes what happens is that
there's like a bug fix, right?
And because of the bug fix, there's a new message changes
and one new one is added and then,
so that then pops up in your website
but then it gets back patched,
the same bug fix gets back patched
so the same message has to then also be updated
in the back branches so you just kind of
have to like download this, upload this,
then it gets added to the translation memory,
then you can do this, I have a bunch of shell scripts
to kind of make this work, it's just all, could be better.
All right, so a lot of people know this chart here.
So, you know, some of the projects that we know,
maybe Postgres is somewhere in here,
KDE, LibreOffice, they're all pretty good
but then there's maybe things like that down here
that everybody builds on but they're sort of maintained by,
by a few people in there sort of on the side, right?
And this way, I mean, this is sort of a general problem.
I gave the same, I gave a talk,
it was the online one two years ago
about the documentation tool chain Postgres,
same problem, right?
We have, you know, open source,
everything's very successful but then there's like
these little tools you need just to make your build run,
right, and then there's, they don't have the same
necessarily amount of staffing and funding
and things like that but you still kind of rely on them
and they just barely sort of chug along.
So, that's a sort of general concern, right?
But it's, it applies here.
All right, so what are we doing?
What do we plan to do?
I mentioned we're in the middle, right now,
we're sort of redoing our build system
that is kind of a good reason to clean up some of that
old stuff that we don't need anymore.
We're also moving more to using ICU which is, you know,
internationalization library that does lots of good things
but then it adds another dimension to this issue of,
you know, locale encoding and then there's sort of
another dimension of what ICU thinks the current locale
and encoding is, it just gets ever more messy
and complicated and then one sort of important issue
in databases is the sort order, right?
That's a lot of people care about that,
what the sort order of your data is
and different collations have to be supported
and that's another kind of sort of localization
kind of work we do.
But all of this is sort of weirdly connector, right?
If you configure one part of the system to be
in this language then all of a sudden get text
also thinks that this is the same but maybe
you don't even want that, right?
You might want to error messages in French
but you want to sort something in Swedish, right?
That's why not.
But because of these APIs the way they're historically built
it just doesn't quite work smoothly.
But again, we want to modernize the workflows.
Again, maybe web late.
I heard of Omega T here also this weekend
and there's Crowdin but,
so the issue I had, I mean I heard of Web late
some years ago too but again the issue is sort of
we can't just adopt like the hottest new thing, right?
Because again, whatever the way I always think about it
is whatever I sort of do today in Postgres, right?
Some piece of code or make some infrastructure change
still has to work in 10 years, right?
And it doesn't, meaning it also has to like build
from source, right?
Because that's the way open source works, right?
So I can't just use a tool that was just invented yesterday
and I don't know if it's still gonna be here in two years.
Now they mentioned Web late is 11 years old
so that's pretty good so I think we can maybe look into that.
All right, so this is something maybe a question
anybody knows is GetX still the thing
or is it something totally different
that everybody should be using now
as part of those sort of the low level API of how this works?
I don't know.
Well, sort of half hoping that's from the ICU ecosystem
something would be evolving or it's sort of emerging
but I haven't seen anything like that
so I don't know if there's anything
or is this still the thing to use?
I don't know.
So maybe somebody has a, yes, please.
The ICU upcoming solution is Mesut format two.
It's currently in the ICU4J72 that came out in October
and it's in tech preview there but it's gonna progress
from there it's not yet in ICU4C.
It's effectively Mesut format two
is a new Mesut format syntax.
The resource level syntax for that
is a little bit more still in progress
but if you're moving towards more of an ICU world
that's likely going to provide a decent future thing
for you to migrate to from GetX.
It's not that yet but it's becoming that.
That is excellent news.
Thank you, I'll definitely look into that.
Webulate is adopting that as well or supporting that?
It's all compatible.
It seems like it supported a bunch of things.
So yeah, this is wonderful and useful information
we can like.
No message format two.
It does.
It's not there yet.
The specifications are two-point-four.
So yeah, this is good, thank you.
So this is also the end of my presentation.
So I just wanted to sort of say what we're doing
and what sort of the some of the unique challenges are.
I've got some good feedback here.
I'm gonna look into Weblate.
We're gonna look into sort of emerging ICU things,
update some of our infrastructure.
We have a few minutes for questions.
Otherwise, thank you very much for listening.
Yeah.
So if you're worried about Weblate,
it doesn't really interact with,
it doesn't go to the new automation system
because the way you communicate with Weblate
with the world and the translators is files.
Yeah.
Yeah, it sounds like it.
Yeah, it was kind of funny
because I had submitted various bugs
to savannah.new.org over the years.
Also feature requests and stuff like that.
And it just like two or three weeks ago,
all of these bugs were like updated
and some of them closed and it's like,
whoa, somebody know that I'm gonna complain
about them at first.
I don't know.
Is the person here in any case?
I don't know who is, no.
Well, I guess it's just sort of,
I mean, this is a problem or I guess it is a problem
in sort of some of these people maintain
some of these specially new tools
and some of these older tools
that are sort of on maintenance.
I mean, we don't need tons of new features,
but you don't really know, right?
It could just be that that person changed his job
and then nothing happens again for five years, right?
But well, got some good new information here, thank you.
All right, then we'll move on to the next one.