Okay, so good afternoon.
I'm Nilo Menes and I would like to share some scripts.
And after all these presentations we had this afternoon,
quick hacks that I need to
use to implement while translating a name document.
How Python developers could use name on the wiki.
Okay, so I will explain it better later on.
So translation documentation with cloud tools and scripts.
So how it started, we had
a document called the name for Python programmers.
That was written in English and Spanish by the same author.
And this document is simply a translation table from Python to name.
So if you already know how to write Python programs,
you can read this document and it will explain,
okay, this is a structure you have to write that way and so on and so on.
But it was written by the same developer in English and Spanish,
in a wiki format using the markdown and it's the wiki of GitHub.
So in the Brazilian name group,
when people started to say, hey,
it would be useful to get more users to the name language.
If we had this document,
the name for Python programmers also translated in Brazilian Portuguese.
And then I said, okay,
that I did some translations before,
I think I can help on this.
So I started checking how I could do the contribution.
So I went to the GitHub Wiki,
I saw that the source code was in markdown format.
I just check it out on Git and I started translating.
Just after the table of contents,
I say this will not end very well.
I will have lots of problems later on because this document will be changed,
it will be updated. Nobody will tell me that the original was updated.
And in a document,
you can also move the sections and do different things.
So I said, this is not a good start.
So the idea was,
how can I help translating but also building
an initial infrastructure to help
translating this document to other languages?
So how they were doing,
they just cloned the English page and they started writing,
overwriting the text in their native language.
If you are the same author, it's fine.
So he wrote the English version,
he also translated to Spanish.
Three or four languages, I think it's still walkable.
But if you start to have as many languages as we saw in very big projects,
you know that it's impossible to keep up to date.
So I started to think about how can I update this?
And I had the previous experience of working with translations in PO5,
using PO5 for Link City,
and also translations like December how to,
and very other document formats where we really have to translate,
copy and translate.
But the PO format started to be very interesting because I say,
if I manage to convert this markdown to PO and create
a process around it,
then we'll be back to the standard translation process where we can use PO edit,
for example, to do the translation and move on.
So I will report what I did and the tools I selected for doing this job.
As I said, it looked very much like an old problem.
So how to translate software to another language.
The PO and get text combinations is very, very good.
It's easy to use.
Even if it's the first time you are translating software to just tag
the text you want to be translated using get text is relatively easy.
But I wasn't working with source code.
I was working with markdown.
And the markdown, you also have
some extra markers regarding the text formatting,
and very specific items that I didn't want to spend time
creating a converter from markdown to the PO file format.
Of course, I started searching.
I found some tools.
But not all tools support the same kind of markdown as the GitHub markdown.
And also, they create PO files with different qualities.
So I spent some time tweaking.
So if you never worked with the PO file,
it looks like this.
You have a message ID that is usually the original string.
And you have the message string that is the translated one.
And you create a new file for each language you are working on.
So usually, English is the base language.
And then you create a PO file for Portuguese, another for Spanish,
and so on.
Pretty standard.
I think most of the afternoon, we heard about PO.
So I think it was a good idea to keep this format.
So this was the process if we were translating standard source code.
So we have the source file.
We extracted the PO file.
Using the PO file, we use a translation tool, or an editor,
to do the translation manually, string by string.
After that, we compile the MO file.
And the executables or the script can use the MO file
and present the text translated to the end user.
So I just needed to adapt this for markdown.
And there is also a very special point
regarding how the wiki is kept on GitHub that I will explain later.
So how to convert markdown, this is specific for GitHub's markdown
to the PO file.
And also, I started to test multiple packages.
Because as I said, if you Google, you'll
find many converters from markdown to PO file.
I think I tested two or three.
I didn't roll down each one.
But the final one is MDA PO.
There is a library, a series of Python scripts.
So it is much more easier for me to use packages
in the same language.
Because I could just write a Py project
and put all these libraries in the same Py project.
The previous one was in JavaScript.
And if you want to run something in JavaScript,
especially if you are not using Linux,
you need to install a lot of other software.
So this would enable the translation from markdown
to PO and vice versa.
Because this is the hardest part.
Once you transform the markdown file into a PO file,
you do the translation.
But the end, the main objective is
to get a translated markdown file back.
So you can use it in GitHub and present the page
in your native language with all the formatting
that the original auto did before.
And I also started to think, OK, maybe I
can write another script that will manipulate the PO file
and help me do the initial translation.
Why?
We have a series of tools for automatic translation.
But of course, this was something I just started.
I didn't have the integrations or anything like this.
But I also didn't want to mess with the PO file itself.
So I found a Python library called POlib
that does exactly this.
I can open a PO file.
I can, for example, do some filtering, like OK,
give me just the strings that are not yet translated.
And so it's very, very easy to build and manipulate
the PO files with it.
So this is the example program.
You simply open the file.
We start the translation.
And with the help with AWS Translate
that I was using, because most of the time I work with AWS,
I could easily send string by string to the cloud
and get an initial translation that I would just
review later on, because you can never
trust the automatic translation, especially
if you are working phrase by phrase.
It's very easy to miss your target.
But it's very good nowadays.
So I would say at least 80% of everything
you do in the automatic translation,
you can keep as it is, but you still have to fix the 20%.
And most of the times, the 20% is quite embarrassing.
So you really need to review and double check
before you publish anything.
And as it's a paid service, as many translation services,
and as our colleague, I didn't know the delivery translator
as that was presented this afternoon,
you don't want to pay every time you do this.
So I used the previous script to create a list of the strings
that were never translated.
They were still empty.
So I know that if I run it multiple times,
I will not be bugging AWS Translate
and paying for the translation of strings
that are already translated or reviewed.
And as you can see, the script is very simple.
You open the PO file, you send the text to the cloud,
in this case, AWS Translate.
You save, you replace the string,
and you save it in a new PO file.
It's done.
So the script is almost out of this.
You have it complete on GitHub.
And this is the main job.
Another advantage of these tools is
that you can create a list of words that
should not be translated.
And this helps a lot, especially if you have a product
or a document with a common name that you don't want
to be translated.
So you can pass this special list.
You can create some exceptions.
But as was explaining in the previous presentation,
it's also a problem.
Because most of the time, we select English
as the main or the source translation language.
You cannot create exclusion lists using programming
languages, keywords.
So in this document, Python, name for Python programmers,
of course, there are lots of source code.
And when I translate it to Portuguese, for example,
keywords like for, in, we're all translated to Portuguese.
So by using the automatic translation engine,
you have to review and revet this translation.
So the translated program will continue to be valid.
And you have to pay very close attention.
Because, of course, you will also
translate variable names if you have source code
in the document.
So you need to pay attention that the output's still
coherent.
And, of course, as you need to do this manual work,
you can use a PO edit tool or any other tool
that you are used to use to work with PO files.
So here we have the English version.
And there we have the Brazilian Portuguese version.
I could just step item by item and reveal these translations
until I was satisfied with the result.
And then you can simply generate the markdown file
from the PO file.
So we started with the markdown source code.
We tracked using MADPO to create the initial PO file.
I run the script that sends the untranslated strings
to AWS Translate.
But you can use any provider you want.
You review with PO edit.
And you do the opposite conversion from PO file
to markdown and publish the wiki.
So this is the workflow I tried to implement
using my collection of scripts or hacks.
It is not really a tool.
But with the intention to facilitate a single markdown
file translation.
So the document looks like this.
This is the English version.
Yes, I put the English.
This is the Portuguese one.
So in the end, I could publish this document in GitHub.
It's not yet fully integrated if the GitHub wiki,
because ideally I should put the GitHub wiki
of this documentation as a sub-module of my project.
So when I updated it, I will also
get the newest version of the markdown.
And if I do this kind of integration using GitHub,
I will be able to publish the markdown file also using Git.
For this initial version, I just went to the editor.
And I paste the markdown file.
But it's possible to do the integration.
It's a next step that I still have to do.
So I published the scripts in this GitHub.
So it's an info Python programmers.
It's useful for any markdown file you
may want to apply the same workflow.
And the page isn't better, because I
ask that all the translators, all the people that
can read Brazilian Portuguese to check if everything is fine.
Because the main goal to have a process
is that usually you never do the translation a single time.
The translation is something that you need to keep alive.
As soon as the English version is extended, translated,
updated, you have to do the same thing in Portuguese.
If you don't have an automatic process able to use
license this document and present a subset of changes,
you'll be obliged to review a full document.
And this can be very, very cumbersome over time
if the document has 15, 20 pages.
So it's not ideal.
And another advantage is that the tool
is smart enough to detect repetitions of the same string.
So you also don't have the boring work
to retranslate the same text multiple times.
This also saves a lot of time.
Yes.
So these are the main findings and the main problems
I try to solve.
And that's it if you have any questions.
You can sit.
If you have a big taste like you want a paragraph, it breaks each phrase.
So it's much easier.
And especially if your text has source code,
because the challenge was the source code.
And sometimes you have to keep the indentation and so on
and so on.
You don't want to pass the indentation
mass to the translator.
So if you use a tool like this, it will structure just the part
of the program with text.
And it will keep the white space, which is very important in Python.
So you can translate.
But you still have to pay attention because
of the automatic translation to translate everything
to the target language.
So you have to revert the keywords.
But at least the generation is quite strong.
So when you have generated this, the program is still
a correct program in the end.
So it's good.
OK.
It's the last one.
Thank you.