Okay. Hi folks.
Thanks for this talk.
I wanted also to thanks for them and
the organizers here for this Dev Room because I'm very happy
that the translation to make part of
the topics in such important events.
So it's a very good news, I think.
Well, I wanted to propose this talk because,
well, personally, I have
started Free Software in 2004 and I have
done some contributions to the Debian project for a long time.
But I only started translation in this project.
I have started that since 2018.
Well, I told myself,
how could we help new contributors,
new users, new potential commerce to help
the translations team with
the capabilities that Debian can provide for them,
and also with what Debian can't provide.
It's also what we're going to see and we're going to see why.
It's not so easy actually.
So I told myself also,
well, I'm sure some people think that,
oh, but why Debian doesn't choose
modern tools such as woodlates or such as model for editors,
or things like that.
So I had the thought about that.
I told myself, well,
why not share that with people to
understand why Debian works like that and how
a new user could contribute with this way of working.
We thought no problem and we had problems.
Well, we've had this faction.
So the example I take is of course,
this is a French translation team because it's the team,
I know the best of course.
It's a very small team.
It's a very, very small team as you see,
there are few people.
There have been people for a long time,
but it's never a team with 10 or 20 persons.
No, it's a very, very small team.
Also, it's not a team which have a lot of technical skills.
I mean, there are some Debian developers,
but which were technical,
there are one or two.
Most other Debian developers of this team are not uploaders.
That is, they are not considered,
or they're not considered themselves able to do
uploads of new packages or things like that.
So it's not a technical team.
It's really a translation team and not a technical team.
And amazing results are produced by this team.
I mean that it's a very small team,
but very amazing results exist.
For example, we have all the things we translate
and we know that we are the third language
best translated in the project.
And when we see the amount of work which is needed
to get that, I think the team may be very happy.
And I can say it because I don't make part of all the team
and I don't make part of all these projects,
so congratulations to other members of the staff.
So the websites, the installer,
all the things which are translated
from up to nearly 100%,
the Debian package descriptions, which are not translated,
of course, very much, but the most important are translated
and it's very important for us also
to enable French users to get the package description,
at least for those they have more chance to use.
So I think it's very, an amazing result
when we know the real size of the team.
Then we work for a project
which has been a very long history, as you know.
The first message, I was very happy to discover that,
preparing this talk.
The first message of the Debian translation team
for French is in 1998, it's very old.
The world has changed very much since this year, of course,
and in particular, the technical world.
So of course, the process, the workflow,
is made based today.
And we have webpages, webpages which enable
to have a tracking of the situations
and to have some statistics and to have some information,
some bots who automate some things
and also some statistics and some made based
to have a workflow between the members of the team
to ensure that the translation has a good quality.
The tools, as I said, are made based.
That is, on the Debian mailing list,
the Debian mailing list for the team, the French team,
there is a bot who is able to receive the topics,
the subject of the messages sent by the member of the list,
to pass them and to produce statistics from this
and to produce some status of the packages or the pages we
are translating.
So it's very important, of course,
because it enables all the members of the team
to know if, for example, someone is working on something
or the status of something, if it's up to date,
or if it's not up to date, or other information like that.
So the thing, of course, is, well, what
can we do with the made based process,
given the number of things we have to do?
Well, we track the changes, so it's very important.
We can know the status of the translations.
And even if we've stopped working for a long time,
we are able, easily, to join the team again
and to know what the situation and what about the situation.
There are also coordination pages,
so with the tracking pages, which enable to do that.
So we have the analysis for the websites.
We have the package translated.
We are, via profiles, packages are translated,
because they are classical programs.
So they use get text as many programs today.
Also descriptions of the depth core screens.
Depth core files, of course, the screens
that the user gets when he's installing a package
to set some configuration at the installation time.
And the website, of course, which is a very high work.
So I think the problem of the Debian project
and the reason for which it's probably very difficult
to use automated tools is that there is a lot of formats
which are used as inputs and also outputs.
I mean, inputs, we have at least a package description database,
which has some formats.
I'm not sure I know what it is about,
but it's not a format such as profiles or HTML files.
It's another kind of format.
It's a database.
HTML, of course, and the profiles.
And for the outputs, we need to produce, of course,
some translations, some typical translations
we find in any other kind of programs of the free software,
but also the websites, so HTML pages.
And various other formats, so it's
not so easy to ship that in a kind of automated tool
because it's really a really quite big task of administration
to set that initially.
And I remember that in the team, we
have not a lot of technical skills,
and we are not very numerous.
So we can understand that we prefer going out with mails,
even if it's probably not perfect,
but at least it enables people to work.
While changing to another kind of tools,
even if it would have benefits about the interface
and the user experience, it would be really a challenge,
a very important challenge.
So changing is very difficult. Is it a good idea also?
It's an idea that the team wonders sometimes.
Is it a good idea?
We wonder that in particular because that's right.
There are not a lot of new contributors
if we have a look annually.
However, when people come and contribute
to the translation projects in Debian, they stay with us.
They don't leave us.
So probably it means that once we manage to adopt the tools,
to adopt the process, we like it,
and people are comfortable with it.
So even if it's not modern, once you take the care to learn it,
at the end, I think we can be comfortable with that.
In particular because, well, we can get things offline.
In particular because we can take the poor
and do some stupid things without being sure you are not
breaking all of the process or you are not breaking
all the translation of others.
So I think it gives some benefits
that people are happy to have.
And that's the reason for which moving is difficult
because people are happy.
And we are not absolutely sure that changing that
would be a good idea.
And when we try changing, for example,
we tried to migrate the server for the package description
to another server in Debian, it takes some year
and it exhausted some people.
So I'm not sure it's the best idea we can have,
even if this migration was really important.
But imagine if we should have a migration with more impact
and more things to address.
So instead of changing things, I suggest
to propose to the users, to the new contributors,
a kind of approach which enable everyone to, well,
let's discover the project.
Let's discover the interactions you can have with the team
from the easiest to the most complex.
And from these bases, do your way.
Follow your way.
And the first step, for example, is for,
and also, yes, on every step of the way,
the idea is also to have two kinds of status.
So two kinds of status, we are going
to talk about that again in a few minutes.
But it's more or less, OK, either I am a reviewer
and I start to understand all the conventions of the team,
how the team works, et cetera, or I become a translator myself.
And of course, I start to contribute
with other translators.
So it's a way to contribute for the rhythm of everybody.
I suggest that the first thing you can do if you want
to contribute, because, again, there
are not some tools which are attractive,
but also start with the easy thing.
And translating the wiki pages of Debian, for example,
would be an easy thing, because much people
love to use a wiki.
It's not so difficult to use.
And using a wiki today is, well, OK, you take the page,
you cut and paste the contents, you
create a new page of the French wiki, and well, and it's done.
So it's not so complicated to do.
And it's the first step which, well,
creates a kind of initiation training for the translation.
We saw so much consequences for the project,
because it's not an official resource,
but it's a community resource.
It's not a resource maintained by Debian members,
so it's not a big problem if you do some mistakes or things
like that.
The next step is probably the package descriptions.
It's interesting, because there are a lot of responsibilities,
because, well, package descriptions
are what users will see on their screen
when they will search for a package.
However, the interface is simple.
It's a web interface, which is wild.
There are some conventions.
There are some rules to have.
But there are also a first contact
with the translation team.
And it's something which is important,
because we have people who review what you're doing.
So you can do what you do, what Debian used to do.
And for example, if you try to translate some things like that,
but Debian is used to translate differently,
you will know that.
If you're not compliant with some kind of syntax
or kind of a way to introduce things,
it will be said by the member of the team.
So it's a first responsibility, a first contact with the team,
but it's a simple interface without needing
to understand something.
So I think it's very interesting for that,
because it's a good point of beginning.
And especially what I like in the package description tools
is that it's very short.
At least you take some packages, such as LaTeX,
or of course LaTeX, when you start
translating the description of LaTeX packages,
it's less fun.
At least sometimes 2,000 lines for a description.
Somewhat difficult.
But if you translate some more typical packages,
it may be very short.
And you can do one package a day, for example.
So you can do really a true rhythm,
to learn a true rhythm, and not, well,
with a minimum follow up also.
So I think it's a first step, which is very interesting.
The next step could be the depth call screens
on your way, or the newcomer.
So depth call screens is other thing,
because now you'll have to pass your translations, proposals
on the mailing list, and to go in the process.
So to understand the virtual address
that we made in the topic, on the subject of the message,
to be sure that the robot is able to understand
what you're doing, and to report that
in the tracking stats, in the tracking tables.
So it's a bit more difficult. But well, you
start having an experience of the Debian ecosystem.
So we can consider that maybe you're
ready to understand that.
Maybe you will meet someone physically.
We will explain to you how things work.
And well, depth call, OK, you are going to now,
intend to translate, request for review,
last chance for a contributor for review.
So you are going to really come in the process,
to come in the Debian process, and to start contributing
to really important things also.
And it's the first responsibility
in the process of Debian with the main working, et cetera,
et cetera.
And once you are completely comfortable with that,
so the process is also here with coordination of the packages,
with the messages which mentioned their status.
And once the mail is received, of course,
you can translate your things.
You translate your profiles with your own editor.
Why not on WebLates?
Because I saw that WebLates can become
a dictionary of translations while using its own editor.
You test the results.
You also can do that.
You report when you finished and when the team is
OK with your translation.
You report a bug to upstream, to the package maintainer,
and it puts the profile in the package.
And the benefits of that is your user
preferred text editor, as I said, or also your PO editor.
PO editor localized are some editors, some KDE,
which work very much for that, to identify, in particular,
the fuzzy strings or the untranslated strings.
Because I forgot to precise some important things also,
is that if we should use some WebLates interface,
some things like that, there is another problem
for some contributors like me is the accessibility problems.
So it would prevent persons to contribute
due to accessibility problems.
With this method, unlike you can use some users.
Personally, I use Emacs.
We get texts.
It's easy because it's in text, and there are not
problems related to accessibility.
Well, once you are comfortable with that,
maybe you want to contribute to the effort of the Debian
community to contribute to main pages.
My pages is a big project, 2,000 pages, about,
and a lot of updates.
So it's a big project.
But the good thing is the method is the same.
So you close the gates, you translate the profiles,
you are on the mailing list with the topics,
the virtual topics to follow the process.
And when it's finished, you commit,
or you make someone in the team to commit.
So you know the process.
You know how it works.
You know the conventions in Debian.
So now you are able to contribute
to any project based on PO files,
even if it's not some packages themselves,
but you can do main pages, you can do package description,
you can do Debian packages themselves.
So it becomes for you easy to contribute
because you understand the process,
and also the human beings in the community.
Well, the benefits of the main pages
is that that, well, just translate and discuss.
You don't have any maintenance to do because German team does
that and does that very good.
So it's a very new area which is accessible for everybody
and which is very cool to use.
The next step is to keep recognizing.
And it's useful for the community, of course,
because as you know, main pages, Debian translates that,
but we don't translate only for Debian.
We translate for all the communities
because main pages are used in all the distributions.
So also, this translation is a way for you
to contribute for all the community.
Then you have documentation, the Debian specific documentation.
So related to the Debian software,
we have the release notes, of course.
We have the Debian developers reference, et cetera,
et cetera.
But also, now it's only profiles.
So it's not so difficult to understand
how it works and the process to have a review
and to have a quality assurance by the community
of the translators.
And packages, same thing in interaction with the community.
We can also now translate all the things.
According to your time, you will choose one of these projects
or just translate for one, two, three, or all those projects
according to the time and the energy you have.
The analysis also, of course, it starts being a bit different,
just like the website, because you will start to play with HTML.
So it starts to being different.
It's a new area.
And I think starting with package descriptions
avoids any difficulty from a technical point of view.
Then, PO-FISE, it starts making you
in front of the difficulty of the process.
But, well, OK, the process is done.
And to finish, you come to HTML pages,
where it may seem, for some people, somewhat difficult.
Because, well, you have to address tags and many things
that you have on the HTML page.
So it may be somewhat difficult.
And however, it's important, because on the website,
we have the security analysis, we have the publicity,
we have all the platform for the Debian project leader.
So it may become important.
And for any of these steps, you can, of course, take the time.
For example, it would take three years to package descriptions
and then wait still three years for main pages, et cetera,
according to your rhythm and your energy.
And especially, you can do what you want, review or translating.
Generally, when arriving, we suggest
to review, to understand the conventions,
to understand the things, and to not take some time in your life.
Then if you want to contribute to translating directly,
it's a good idea.
What I mean here is that we can do really at the, well,
with the ways, with minimum ways and minimum installations,
and the minimum understanding things,
and especially on the progressive ways.
Also, you can track in translations.
So you subscribe to the mailing list,
and you have a look at translations,
and you follow what happens in matter of review,
and in matter of translating new,
if you consider that it's simple or short enough
to make you spend the time to do it.
So review and translating are the two steps
you can do at any time in the process,
and in your way on Debian.
So to conclude, I would say that it's not an automated process,
because we don't have the capability to do that.
And I think the project is too complex today
to do that efficiently, and it would imply some engineering
to do things properly.
But we have today some way, I think.
And it's what I tried to suggest on the Wiki pages
about translation and how to contribute
and to start contributing and not being discouraged.
I could have been during some years.
There is a way from the most obvious, technically speaking,
to less obvious with a contact with the community, which
is progressive.
And you discover how things work, the conventions,
of course.
The team discovers also if you are ready to respect
how the team works, because we had some contributors where
we've used it was complicated because he decided
to do things like he wanted.
Yes, but there is a team history.
So you can do things like you want, as you want.
Even if you're right, take the time and respect
what other people do.
And also, it's important to say that on the mailing list,
also, if you start contributing via the mailing list,
you have the chance to get your native language.
Because in the French mailing list, but also in Italian,
in Spanish, or any language, you have,
for the translation teams, of course,
people speaking your native language.
So for example, now how to translate this English term
in the language, it may be useful.
And for example, in the package description,
we also have a glossary to help people to know,
OK, this English word which has a strange translation,
should I translate?
Or if I shouldn't translate, what should I do with that?
And if I should translate, what kind of words is used usually?
And once you do that, you can learn.
And also, without any complicated tools
or with no difficulties, you can start translating.
And so you can become a Debian translator.
Thanks.
Oops.
You've seen some feedback on some questions?
For me, I can have feedback and global feedback
on kind of all the things feedback.
Because I have seen that maybe there
is a fragmentation in different distribution.
In Linux, and some have advantage,
and the other not of this website.
And so because I have never found a distribution that
convinced me perfectly.
For instance, for me, you have problem with vision.
But for me, I have little problem with vision and granary.
And so I should appreciate scrolling
bar with a great and large line, a bit
to go to adjust some problems.
I doubt it's my MX Linux.
They have a good scrolling bar, but also problems.
So it's a kind I'd like to wish more cooperation
with Linux as a problem of system day also,
about something that I think is important
for Linux community in general to have a better cooperation
with different projects of distribution.
I think that the importance is free software,
even if what you say is right.
I'm OK with that.
According to my understanding of things and about translation,
it's right also.
Is that the user find a way for himself?
I mean, that's OK.
Debian has his way of work.
Ubuntu has his way of work.
And any project has his way of work according to the history,
according to what it needs to be doing, et cetera.
Well, the thing is how to enable a user
to find among all the existing ways a way for him.
And I think it's right for any new users,
that's exactly what you're saying,
but also it's right for new contributors.
Because contributing may work according to some rules,
some community interaction, some tools, of course.
So it's not a kind of what is better, what is not better.
It's only a kind of is it sweet for you, actually.
And in the community, the benefit
is that you have this diversity which
enables you to decide what is good for you
and what is good for your way of doing things.
So it's a good thing.
But yes, there are a lot of ways.
And to find the way it's good for you is not easy.
I think the De Leung community has something very good
on which we should all learn to do
is you have a very good translation workflow.
And I think this is something valuable.
And this is the reason why you are able to continue
doing some email translation.
Still, even if the world is using much different workflow,
I think that's your bigger value in this.
And my question would be, what are the limitations
that you see in the existing translation platform
in terms of accessibility for you who are blind,
but also in terms of way to collaborate as a team?
Because I did push forward late in many places.
It helps a lot.
But it doesn't create any miracle.
The community needs to find a way
to define the workflow, the way to collaborate together.
And this is something that the rest of the resource community
can learn from the De Leung community.
Your tools are a little bit prehistoric.
But your own way of working are very clear and easy
to understand.
And I would be interesting to have your feedback
on translation platform in terms of accessibility.
And what are lucky to have a proper collaboration
as a team in what we have today?
Thanks.
Because you sum up what I want to show here.
What you say is exactly what I think and I want to show.
But I know, and I'm aware from some feedbacks I can have.
And because I know there is a low stream of new,
a low flow of new contributors, maybe,
and I say maybe because I'm not sure myself about that.
Because for me, indeed, what the tools we are using now
are perfect because they are accessible, because they work,
and because they are able to have a record
and to have a team collaboration.
So for me, these tools are really perfect.
But in the new generation of new contributors,
I know that indeed there are some more friendly interfaces,
some more design, some ways to do a UI and UX, which
is more beautiful and more friendly, more attractive,
also, or you have less learning curve.
So you can come in the project, do something,
opt to leave, no problem.
You don't have to learn during some months, something,
et cetera, et cetera.
So also, the problem today, the new contributors
in our society is that people don't want less,
want to get involved in the long term.
They want to come, to try something, give it a try,
opt and to leave, because, well, we have our lives,
we have our obligations, et cetera.
And that's right in Debian.
It's something more difficult. Because in libraries,
for example, you can go, OK, you have an error,
or a mistake on the string, you open the relates, opt,
you fix the string, opt and you leave away.
And perfect.
Well, in Debian, it's not possible.
Well, it's possible for the package description,
because it's a web interface.
There is not a learning curve.
It's very simple.
But for people who don't want to do the effort to learn,
we don't want to do the efforts of understanding deeply things,
well, it may be destructive.
Is it bad news?
I don't know.
I'm not sure.
But the fact is that the team is small.
And the fact is that we have no few contributors.
So I wonder if it's a limitation.
But for contributors who try to be forced to do that,
I think these truths are indeed really perfect.
Yeah, just one more question for the mute finish.
So you've started a process to create new translations.
Can you give some examples how you
want to try in recipes to update existing translations,
like the original text changes, the English text changes?
How do you know about this?
Do you notify the same translator as before?
Can everybody jump in and think that?
Do you think that the product will
be possible in the
process of not watching the web?
Actually, for example, to take the depth
core for the main pages, for example,
when there is an update, the translator has a warning.
He knows that he has something, which
is because the translator is considered as the last one who
can do the changes or should do the changes.
Once he has this warning, either via mail
or because he has a look on the statistics page,
he says, OK, so I will do that.
So he sends a mail with an address saying that, OK,
this page, this description, this profile, I will translate it.
So there is a mail.
And the community has the information,
is notified that the person is going to translate.
After it, it will translate the profile,
or the file in it.
And then, OK, now I finished.
Thanks to review the translation.
So there are some review.
It's a process which can be five days or 10 days
according to the number of mistakes
which needs to be fixed, et cetera.
And at the end, he says, OK, last chance for change.
So OK, it's the last chance for you to review and to tell me
if there is a problem.
And once that's done, when the mail arrives on the community
team, if there is not any reply, well, OK,
the translator can either report a bug
to say to the maintainer of the package, OK,
there is a new translation.
It's updates.
Please put it in your package.
Or he can do it himself or herself
if the person has the permission to access to the git
and the repository and to do the translation.
So it's manual.
But of course, there are some scripts to do that.
You don't have to do that manually.
It's not mandatory.
But the process is really you have a follow up
of the situation via mail.
OK.
Thank you, Jochen.
Thanks.
Thank you.