So, let me put here some minutes.
My name is Paul.
I'm from Brazil.
And in Brazil, I help the translation team for Debian, translation for Portuguese.
I'm a Debian developer, too.
So I work with packages in translation for Portuguese, Brazilian Portuguese.
And I'm coordinating the translation here this afternoon.
We will have six talks today from different projects.
And each of them, they have 30 minutes.
So the speakers know they have 30 minutes to talk.
I don't think so.
I'll have to bring this here.
Ah, okay.
I live here.
Thank you.
So each speaker will have 30 minutes to talk, including the key part.
I would like to say thank you very much for Fosden organizers and for speakers to be here.
I'm sure that will be a great experience for everybody.
I believe this is the first time we have a translation dev room at Fosden.
So the first time we have a dedicated room for translation.
So this is good.
I hope this is the first of many dev rooms that will be on the future.
And I hope everybody enjoy it.
I will be sitting here if someone needs something with me, talk with me.
I will be there.
Yeah, I'm using this blue shirt.
So that's it.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.