Hopefully, yeah, I will wait. I just want to test the sound that it works on the other
side. One, two, three. Web light, web light, web
light, pontoon, web light, web light, web light, pontoon, web light, web light, web
light, web light, web light, web light. Yeah. It works like that. This is how you
celebrate. You just say it a lot of times. Yeah. Great.
So long two days, right? And a lot of to come. I just want to ask you if you can all do a
frowny face. Like you just ate something weird. Yeah. Test it. Test it on yourself because
you will need it throughout the talk because you are from different backgrounds.
Somebody is a developer. Somebody is not a developer. Somebody knows web light very well.
And somebody came here to get to know web light. Somebody was on my talk yesterday who
was not, can watch probably tomorrow or the after the recording. But I didn't get the
link yet. So probably soon it will be. So the frowny face will be in use if you don't
like something, if you feel like you are bored here. Just do your frowny face so I know that
I should go a little bit quicker to what I am just talking about. Yeah? Okay.
So I'm Benjamin. I'm from web light. I do the talking and Michael there do the coding.
So yeah. That's the web light team. And we also have a teammate named part. And he does
the coding part time. So what's web light? And okay. Web light is a liberal localization
platform. It's well documented piece of software. I want to point it out because sometimes if
you want to get to know the software, you get to ask a lot of questions other people.
With web light you don't have to. But yeah, you can still ask me if you don't find your
answer in the documentation. It's a couple of software. It's licensed under GPL 3. And
all the development is public on GitHub. We started as an open source project. And it's
not going to change. Because yeah, it's the best way to develop software. What web light
should do is to make the tough process of localization and coordination of a lot of
people and having so many things at so many places just easy. And it's for developers.
It's for translators. It's for managers. It's for everyone that's involved in the project
of localization. And wow. It's a weird color. But on X2logo you will read it's a verb. And
yeah, some of our users started using to web light. Which means I'm going to translate
something on web light. So we are a verb too. Web light works or is aimed that you will
just set it once or tell it that it needs to be set in some way in the future. And it
will do itself. So you just set it and forget it and let it work for you. Because you don't
want to do the work if it can be done by a great piece of software. It's supposed to
be having all translations. So not just one platform. Not just your website or your app.
Everything in one place. Many, many fans of localization file formats are supported. So
you don't have to use web light just for part of your workflow. Put there everything. And
it will give you a free time. Once you have it there, have your translations there, you
probably want to give it a context and communicate with other users. You can do that. If you
find that search string weird, you can just add a comment, notify the maintainers and
they will know it. Once you have it integrated, which means in the best way integrated with
your version control system, because that's why Michael started web light 11 years ago
to have some kind of translation software integrated to what you love to do. You love
to develop software. Not to send back and forth or use API calls or write scripts. You
just want to develop your software and let some other software do the parts you don't
fancy that much. Once you have your translations there, then you go to the editor if you are
a translator, which is a lovely part of web light where you can see all the context, all
the screenshots, all the communication with other translators, and where you can localize
the string to your desired language out of the search language or multiple languages.
Once that's done, web light does the magic, as Jean Baptiste from Fedora said, because
there are all the checks and fix-ups so you don't have to control the quality of your
I shouldn't be in front of that. You have the quality you want to, not some messy translations
that can be understood differently in the app in the end. Once this is done, or while
this has been happening, you have it in a database. We prefer the elephant, but you
can also use MariaDB, but elephant has more power, more strength for the best performance.
Once you finish there, web light stores it in the underlying Git repository. That's part
of the magic, because that's a tool you already know how to work with. If you are a little
bit lost about, let's say you got a merge conflict because you added the same thing
in web light and in your repository, because, yeah, you don't want to wait. You want to
have everything continuous. You just solve a merge conflict. If you don't know how to,
it's described in the documentation of web light. That's the easy part. That's the way
how to make it continuous with as fast as possible. Basically, you need to get your
translations in, then do as less work with help of machine translation and stuff, and
then get it out. In and out is very easy, because it's just syncing one Git repository
with the other. Or if you prefer work with the API, web light has it, so you can do that.
Or if you like to translate in some offline tool, in desktop application, you just download
the localization files in the file format you like, because web light can converse this
for you and then you can upload it back without being afraid of making the file invalid. Once
you have that everything set up, you can reuse your translations, because there is a translation
memory which you improved by your manual translations and with machine translation. So if you are,
let's say, translating the same project over and over again for new versions, like LibreOffice,
you can build your translation memory with help of machine translation, with help of
your community, and in the end you don't need that much of manual work, you don't need that
much questions to the machine translation engine, because you already have your core,
your basis in the translation memory which you can use as a source for the machine translation.
So that's the reuse. And as a result, what you want to get out of Web Light is your software
in your language, because, yeah, then you truly don't own it. You want to reduce as
much work as possible, because everybody wants to work on what they desire to do, not the
manual work that's again and again the same. So let translators do their work, let developers
do their work and happily be co-dependent. You want high quality translators, translations,
and you want the engagement from the community, because if they have the easy way, if they
figure out in their UI they are just watching, there is a mistake. And then they probably
know the best how to correct that mistake. But if they won't find the way how to correct
it, where, they won't send you an email. If they have the tool, it's their software, they
can make it better, very easy way, make it themselves, it's their software, so they
can work for the whole community and attract more translators, more users, because that's
how you do it. You, of course, want to free the time of developers. I think I already
said much about it. And you want to be prepared for the future versions and for the future
project, because usually you use the same translation, so you can be very well prepared
for that, too. Weblight as a project started, yeah, 11 years
ago as a part-time project, but now I will probably talk more about it if we have time
and the app. But now it's sustainable on itself without any venture funding or something like
that. How we get the funding, these are the four ways. We offer the hosting services to
commercial customers or to lovely projects like Fedora or some other projects like Open
SUSE because Michael started it while working in Open SUSE, are using Weblight for long
years, but they hosted themselves and just pay for the support because sometimes they
need a little bit of help with something. We also offer custom development because as
we are a small team, we are very flexible in delivering new features. And as we have
the same code base for everyone, no matter if you are a commercial customer of Weblight
services or if you are small or large, you have the same features. So if a very big corporate
like some Siemens company will pay for a nice feature, you as an Android developer of a
small podcast app can use it, too, and that's great. Or you can contribute to the code and
they will get it, too, because you want to support big companies, too. Give them something
back, maybe. And, of course, as every Libra project, we also accept donations. Then you
came here probably if you know Weblight to listen about the plans, what we plan for this
year, and this is it. We want to become more enterprise ready. The current state, because
some of you we met at GNU HealthCon, the good thing is that more of large parts of the work
at the backend is done. What means enterprise ready? At this moment, Weblight, as it started
as a small project and not aimed to be something that influential and that important to large
groups of people, to large projects, there is currently just a project and a component,
and that's it. But you will be able to create multiple levels of grouping, let's say, for
different versions. Yay! Fedora is happy. And we are happy, too. But give us time, give
us time, a little bit. And, of course, when you have the large group, large community,
you need to manage them, you need to give them access, and at this moment it's possible
in Weblight, you can connect your single sign-on method, like SAML or GitHub or GitLab, and
manage them there, or you can do it in Django admin, some strange thing. But this is a history
now. Now you can manage it fully inside Weblight, and there will be even more, so you can use
Weblight similarly like you are used to with GitLab, GitHub and other tools where you can
create the teams, organisations, and let them do their work without you having to pay attention
to that. All good? Yeah. Okay. Then, as Weblight, again,
most of the things are something we didn't plan in the original way, so now Weblight is
a little bit rusty to play the big part for large projects, and some of those is also
universal search hints, because at this moment search is on some levels or on the whole level,
but it's not that convenient, and it would search from one place, everything in between,
so you need to click through and then search for something. This will be changed also to
make it easier to navigate, because from our operating system, from our cooperative tools,
we got used to a nice universal search on every platform, so you will find that in Weblight
too. And, yeah, that's it. Of course, the UX can be better every time. We really want
to grow the team, so, yeah, if you know a developer, tell them it's a great project,
they can contribute, and they can get paid for it, which is really nice in open source
world. And, yeah, we want to continue organic growth, and after yesterday's talk, we got
to some talking, maybe we will do something with pontoon, maybe not, because there won't
be time, maybe it will make sense, maybe it will not, but we would like to be to investigate
that way too. And, yeah, as we still have some time, maybe we can talk about how Weblight
began. This is where Weblight began. This is Michael's office, who was on yesterday's
talk, lightning talk. Okay, good. So, this is small room on top of the large concrete
building we built in the Czech Republic, and it's like three to four metres, something
like that, and there used to be all the machinery for the elevators. So, it's not a garage project,
it's basically the elevator project, and it's weird because it was like on top of the elevator,
there was no elevator at the time when Michael was coding there, so, yeah, we need, like,
fire elevator or just use the steps and build them before, so, yeah, it takes time. And,
yeah, this is a website of Weblight where you can see all the translations that are happening
on hosted Weblight. These are some of our lovely users from the open source community.
What pushed us into big feeling of responsibility was when a few years ago, Fedora approached
us and realised that they want to use Weblight because it makes sense, and it doesn't make
sense if they want to create a great Linux distributions and they have a lot of other
work, they don't want to maintain Xanata because they don't have time. That's not their main
process. So, they switched to Weblight, they did it really, really well in the migration
process. Of course, they found a lot of bugs. We were able to fix them, thanks to them,
because, yeah, once a developer finds your bug, they are usually or technically skilled
people great to describe what's the problem, and then it's very easy to fix it. And, yeah,
that's what got us to the current state. And if you want to hear more about this thing,
why we feel that there should be something to connect Weblight with other tools and make
it easier for all the communities, you can listen to yesterday's talk why the recording
will be available. We will definitely let you know on our website, we will definitely
let you know about everything on our Mustanum account. And I think we don't need to take
the time about my story, just a funny part, my story with Weblight became we first met
with Michal at Fosdam in 2017, and I was here with a different project and another Michal,
yeah, popular name in the Czech Republic, introduced me to this Michal. That was my
colleague that time and that project, that was tourists, open source router, and then
we didn't see with Michal for two more years, and then in 2019, I came here looking for
a job. In 2018, I came here with a different project, and 2019, I just wanted to return
to Fosdam and be in the atmosphere, and that time I was living in Prague, we knew each
other, but we met here again and we started working together, so, yeah, tell that to people,
just come to Fosdam, but, yeah, you already tell them. So, yeah, I think we have like
12 minutes now for questions, so, yeah, let's talk, and you probably, you are all smiling.
There was no frowny faces. Okay, who has the question? Hello, Jean Baptiste.
The user experience for an end user is a system-wide, so when the user is using Linux and is using
strings translating from many different software, right now, Weblane can use a solution to allow
them to do a different collaboration, but we have some kind of a plan so that in the
future, we can search for translation coming from whatever data source, because we have
Weblane hosted for the federal project, we have the Weblane for LibreOffice, the one that
we have, and there are many other places where you can find the use for translation, but
as a translator, I would like to search for every existing translation of some terms,
and I want to see, okay, what is all consistent in my translation at the moment, and should
I align on the current way it is translated, or maybe it's wrongly translated in most places,
and I should go fix the translation. Okay. I would love to see something that helps us
to at least federate the knowledge, not having some kind of magic tool that we want to be
using for our translation, but just to know what's the trans state of translation, and
I think the Mozilla people have some tools that allow them to search for existing translation.
I would love to see some kind of tool that allows me to search for a string across all
the translation coming from any Weblane instance, or even from Mozilla.
Okay. I will try to sum up the question.
Now we will see if I was paying attention. So, the question was, if we plan to introduce
some place, it's slightly related. Yesterday, when I had my lightning talk about possible
translation MD, something like that, I meant to show people, show translators one place
where they can find the project they want to translate, and Jean Baptist would like
to take, to elevate it to another level, to have some kind of shared translation memory
or shared glossary where translators can go to and check how to translate the best, the
thing they are currently working on. Yesterday on my talk, I was trying to be not very imaginative
because I usually am very excited about everything, and then there is no time to do that.
I can imagine something like you just proposed, but I can't imagine anybody doing it because
that would just mean a lot of people working on it, and then we would need to help with
some licensing and stuff. So, yeah. It would be nice. I'm not opposed, but I can't imagine
at the moment I would start with what I was talking yesterday and then maybe on top of
that might be something to build on. Currently, you can search on hosted Weblight, which is
a pretty large base of open source projects. You can search through their translations because
they are open. You can search on Discover Weblight for the project so you can realize
through there, oh, I want to see how SUSE or Fedora is translating that. Or SUSE or
Fedora is translating that. You can go from there, but every time you have to go to that
particular space and search it there. So, yeah, maybe we will just, once we have the
translation MD, we think about for two years and not doing anything on it, and also
universal search, then we will just maybe throw it to some clever people with AI, but
I'm scared of what would happen from there. So, yeah, there is another question.
I'm looking for translation software and I'm using Android strings which can have like
template values that are automatically inserted to see the end result of the string with those
values. Say for instance I add another name or something and I can see how that looks
in the image results. So, some kind of a, okay, the question was if there is any plan to provide,
some kind of live preview of the strings that are translated. The answer is another thing
we were talking about through recent years and that's quite large to develop. So, again,
we would like to do that and you can support this effort if you help to find us frontend developers.
So, it's kind of you can do it, but it's not quite, it doesn't feel like a button wants
to turn the string and this was not the plan by intention of the feature. Okay. But we
can do it with the word. I'll find later or on the PNA. Okay, I will play a little bit
like a sports commentator. On the right we have, what's your name? Tobias. Tobias? Yes.
And on the left we have Michael from Weblade and Tobias is having an Android app and needs
to see it before he commits to the version and Michael is saying it's partially possible
and you can talk after the talk into the deep of this topic and we still have more time.
Thank you very much for Weblade and I apologize. Last week I opened a duplicated issue and
I'm so sorry. I will stop you here. It's not a problem. It's not a problem. It's a thing
that can be solved very easily. We will just tell you, go here, follow there. That's not
a problem. You can actually do this.
You can actually do this. Weblade uses translation memory. Once you have it, you can export it,
import it in TBX, which is a standard format and you can also use Weblade translation memory
as a source for I will repeat the questions at the end. Sorry. You can use also Weblade
as a source for your machine translation. So it's just clicking in the UI and it should
serve your needs. The question was if it's possible to use Weblade as a source for machine
translation. We still have time. Is there any other question?
Okay. Yeah.
So, we are not yet connected with the community and we will be happy to connect with them
and maybe figure out some deeper integration and more promotion in the community. Yeah.
I will get back to you after the talk. There was one more question.
I'm sorry. I have to stop you. I will go closer to you. Yeah. Or if you. Yeah.
Yes. It's in a context in the editor of Weblade. They're under the source and the field for
the translation. There are a few tabs like comments, like other translations in neighboring
projects and also or projects and components and also if you set up your machine translation
engines, they will see it there. So they don't have to look for it. They will your translators
will see it there and they will just click to copy it into the translation. And.
Like without offering translators to copy it, just translate everything through machine
translation. Yes. You can. Yes. Yes. There is an add-on called automatic translation
and you just install this add-on and instruct it to use particular or machine translation
engines you set up at your Weblade instance or for your project to insert translations
or suggestions for untranslated for or for all strings. So it is possible the add-on
is called automatic translations and you will find more info in the Weblade documentation.
Okay. We will get there after the talk. Thank you very much for being here. Thank you for
your time and enjoy rest of your FOSDEM experience. And see you next year.
Okay. Okay. Okay. I can do that. It's not all. It's just some. And there is the next
speaker is not here yet. So here we go. You can do it. You can do it. He will just take
a picture and we are setting off. I have no problem. I don't care. He's the one in charge.
Okay.