After two years of... for them at home. This is our first in-persona for them, so welcome.
So just to remember you... oh, where is the mouse? Okay. Just... oh, back. Okay, just
a few rules. You're not in your room anymore, so please keep all the rubbish on the trash
bin and just try to leave the room clean. There's rules about no food and no drinks,
or just... it's fine if you drink, but try not to bring your food with you in the room.
That's all. And so the post-COVID rule, so masks are not mandatory for the folks, but
we don't correct the use. If you want to use one, just feel free. And we try to ventilate
the room after each talk. So maybe if people in the back could help us, because we have
five minutes to switch from one speaker to the other, so feel free to help us. So aside
from that, this is the schedule for this morning. Yeah, we'll be the first speaker this morning
about BSD drivers, and we'll finish with the Kimura Linux, the last I'll finish at 2pm.
So that's mostly all. Thank you very much for being here, and enjoy your frozen.