Okay, I think we can start already.
Hi everybody, I'm Diego Barreiro.
I'm one of the open source contributors to the MIT App Inventor project and today I'm
going to be talking about App Inventor and how we can introduce artificial intelligence
to kids using this platform.
But before getting into it, I would like to introduce myself a little bit more.
I started coding with App Inventor when I was 14 years old, it was 2013 at that time,
and I basically wanted to build an app, I didn't know anything about coding, and a high
school teacher showed me this amazing platform.
So I just spent the next couple of years building apps with App Inventor and eventually I switched
it to Java coding and I was able to contribute to the project later on as I'm doing right
now.
So what is MIT App Inventor?
MIT Inventor is an online platform that enables anybody to build any kind of application without
having to learn any programming language like Java or coding that is nowadays the most popular
ones.
This is the interface and it has the mock phone on the center and on the left side we
can have the components, the elements that will make the app like buttons, labels, text
boxes, text areas, like any kind of interaction that the user will have with the app.
And then we can customize the properties like colors, text fonts, text sizes, whatever on
this panel so we can make the app look as we wish for the final user.
And how does the logic work?
Well we, most of you may know about the scratch.
App Inventor works somehow like a scratch using this block language.
So let's say that we want to play a sound when the app opens.
We will be using a block that says when the screen one has opened we want to play a specific
sound later on.
And that's how we can just make any kind of application.
MIT Inventor allows existing Android developers and Android developers to introduce new components
using extensions.
And we will be using today one of those extensions that was developed by a research project
at MIT that enables to classify images on different groups using artificial intelligence.
And to give some numbers of App Inventor it was tested in 2008 as a Google project.
And then a few years later it eventually was transferred to MIT.
Right now it has gathered over 18 million users since it was created, since it was transferred
to MIT with nearly 85 million apps that have been developed.
And on a monthly basis we get roughly around 1 million users.
And in terms of open search contributions we have seen 164 different contributors to
the project on GitHub.
So today I'm not going to be giving the classic talk.
I'm going to be showing a tutorial and people in the audience and at home can just follow
this tutorial by visiting the following link on how to build an app.
And what we will be doing today is building the pickup app.
Pickup is a game that is usually played with babies that when you see the baby that he
loves and when you hide yourself it just cries.
So to show the final result, this will be the final result.
Let me just switch to my phone.
I'm going to be mirroring this phone.
So I open the final app and I'm going to start using the camera.
I can see, yep, here I am.
I can start and I'm looking at the baby that he's happy.
If I hide myself it just cries.
So let's get into it.
So how we can use MIT App Inventor 2?
The standard instance of App Inventor is hosted at ai2.appinventor.mit.edu, but that requires
an account.
MIT has created this specific instance, code.appinventor.mit, that allows you to create these projects
without any existing account.
We will be using an anonymous account so that that can be cleaned up later after finishing.
And we will receive our code like the following one.
Now this is blurred, but you will be able to see our code.
And on the previous screen, if you want to recover the project later on, you can just
paste the code that you previously get right here.
And once that is done, you will be able to access an anonymous account, as you can see
over here, and you can just start creating the app.
So let's get into it.
So we can visit firstm23.appinventor.mit.edu, and we can click on this link.
This link is basically the code App Inventor instance, and we are loading a template project
for the pickable project.
So I'm going to click on this one.
So I click on Continue without an account.
And just wait a few seconds for the project to download from the repository, and here
it is.
That was faster than last night.
I can see the code here, so I can just copy paste the code to access this instance later
on.
And as this is a tutorial, we can see on the left side that we are seeing a description
of what we are trying to build with a detailed step-by-step guide.
And this is the instance of the project.
I can see the happy baby, and then the sad baby is hidden here.
Okay, so let me just continue the presentation.
The next step is turning the classifier.
I'm not going to get too deep into the machine learning and how it works.
I'm just going to be providing a very high-level overview of how this works.
So we will be using an image classification system that consists in creating two groups
of images.
So we are creating one group of images that is the face of myself looking at the baby
and another group of images that is me hiding from the baby so we can show the sad face.
So how does this work?
We can visit this website, classifier.appinventor.mit.edu to train this model.
Just as a side note, this instance only needs internet to load once.
To train the model, that all happens in your browser, so no servers are involved, no images
are transferred outside your desktop.
And this website is also open source, so you can just check.
There is the link on the FOSDAM23 website.
So we visit the website, and we start first creating the images.
So in this case, we will be creating one image group for me.
So I'm looking at the baby and not me.
I'm hiding from the baby.
If for example we are in a biology class and we want to classify trees, we will be creating
one group of images for each kind of tree.
So we can recognize them later on.
Then we will turn on the camera to take a photo of myself, setting the group of images
that I'm going to be saving this.
So if I'm looking at the camera, it's going to be the not me group.
If I'm looking at the camera, it's going to be the me group.
This is the same for the not me.
And once that is done, when we have a reasonable amount of images for each group, which will
be around 5 or 10 images for each group, we can train the model.
As again, this training happens on your computer, so no images transferred outside of your computer.
We can then test the model with new images to make sure that we have properly trained
the model and can identify ourselves.
And once that is done, we can export the model and load it into Appingmentor.
So I'm going to be doing that very quickly.
Go to first and enter tree, Appingmentor.mit.edu.
I open the classifier instance.
It's going to ask for permission to use the webcam for each.
There it is.
I just accepted it for.
So the first step is creating the labels.
First the me label, enter, and next the not me label.
And well, the light is quite hot.
I think it was.
Take a few more images of me looking to different places so I can train better the model.
One more.
So seven images should be fine for this demo to not take too much time.
And now for the not me, I'm going to take one photo of me not being there, basically.
I'm going to be using the right hand to hide myself so I can put this one in front of my
eyes.
Turn it upside down, diagonal, like more images.
The other hand as well.
Like that.
So that should be enough for now.
And once that is done, we can just hit the train button to train this model.
It will be built on the local machine without sending anywhere.
This was faster last night.
Seems like the time that we saved from the loading the project, we lost it here.
So now it's training.
Yeah, it's my laptop.
So this is our React app that has been open source and the only internet required is to
just get the initial web page later on.
We can just disconnect and it will work perfectly.
It's just offline training.
If you really want to be fully offline, you can just launch the React app locally and
it will work.
So now the model is built and to test it, I'm going to be looking at the camera as I
did before.
I captured the image and I can see that there is a 99.42 confidence that I'm looking at
the camera.
If I take a few images of myself hiding from it, there is a 99.33 confidence that I'm not
looking at the baby.
So once we have validated the model properly, we can export it to the app.
And we will get this model.mdl file for that inventor.
So let's go to the presentation.
And once we have the model, it's time to code the app using blocks.
I'm not going to go through the slides anymore.
For people at home, if you have internet problems or the streaming is down, feel free to follow
the slides.
It's a step-by-step guide.
But for here, I'm going to be showing the tutorial live.
So let's go back to the project that we just loaded.
And right here, we can see a quick description of the project of what we are going to do.
I set up a computer of how to connect to the MIT instance to the app.
I'm going to show that at the end of the presentation.
And we have here the pickup example.
This is the final result.
This is a link one of the MIT curriculum developers that made the original tutorial.
And yeah, basically, it says that we will be using the Personally Much Classified extension
that was developed by that research of MIT.
And the first step is loading, turning the model.
And then we have to upload the model.
To upload the model, we go to this section over here on the media.
We select the Just Uploaded Model file.
It should be here.
And now it's uploaded.
It's in the asset file of the app.
And we can just change the model of the Personally Much Classifier to the now loaded new model.
And we have just loaded the model properly to give an overview of how the app is going
to look.
There is going to be this status label that will tell the user when the app is ready to
work.
And it will be loading because it's the initial state.
It will let them go to the ready state.
And it will just identify the faces.
We have these two bars that will be showing which percentage of confidence that we are
looking at the baby or not.
This is going to be the live image from the camera that I just showed before.
And these are the interaction buttons to start the classification, to toggle the camera from
the front to the back camera.
And we have here the happy baby in this case.
So a pleasant attorney model.
This is the sequence of events that I was just talking about.
First we start the app.
The app will show to ready as soon as the classifier is ready to start working with
the app.
The user will press the start button.
And then the Personally Much Classifier extension will keep classifying the live stream video
from the camera continuously.
And once they have identified the result, if there is a higher confidence that the me
model is working, we will show the smiley face.
Otherwise the baby will just start crying.
So in this template, there is already a set of blocks that are available to speed up the
process.
And we can go here that we see the one Personally Much Classifier error.
So that means that if for any reason the Personally Much Classifier shows an error, maybe because
there are some missing things on the phone or whatever, we will set the status label
text to the actual error that we returned from the image classifier.
Once the image classifier is ready, we will enable the start button as well as the toggle
camera button.
We will set the status label text to be ready so the user knows that they can start using
the app.
And we will set the text boxes of each classification group to the previously defined labels me
and not me in this case.
If the user presses the toggle camera button, we will be changing from the front to the
back camera just every time that they press.
So we can use the front selfie camera or the back normal camera.
And once the user presses the start button, if the Personally Much Classifier is already
classifying an image, we will just stop it and we will show the start button with the
start text.
Otherwise, we have to start a classification, so to do so, we just invoke the start continuous
classification method and we change the text to stop because we will be changing the button
interactions.
And that's the quick overview of the code that is already available in the app.
So how does the image classification work in MIT Prementor?
Well we have this big block that is the when Personally Much Classifier has received a classification
succeeded, we will receive this result variable.
This result variable is a dictionary that just gives a little high level overview of
what is a dictionary.
It's a key value list of elements.
So if we have two different groups, me and not me, we will receive me equals a specific
value, not me equals a specific value.
If we have three groups, we have one, two, and three that they each equal to a specific
values.
This is a little example of how it looks like.
So we have key father equals this value, key mother equals this value, then equals this
value, etc.
For the image classifier, a specific example, we will have something like this.
We have me with this value and not me with this other specific value.
So how we can retrieve a value in the dictionaries area, in the dictionaries block area, we have
get value for a specific key.
And we will be doing something similar to this.
So we have the original dictionary here, we are building it in this area, make a dictionary
me and not me, and we will be getting the value of the group that we want to use right
now.
In this case it's the me example, if we want to take the not me, we just have to change
this label to not me.
And if we are using the wrong model because the groups are not the same, we just return
a zero because we cannot classify that group.
So let's get into it.
By default, the tutorial will provide this block that is some variables, some me confidence
level, and we have to complete them using this block.
So to do so, we will take the get for key in dictionary block, we join it to the me confidence
block, we remove, nice, get value for the key, and we will take from the text blocks
an empty text block to attach it right here, and we can type me.
So we can get the me group into the me confidence variable, the dictionary is the result, we
can just attach it here, and if not found, we will just return an empty zero value.
And for the not me confidence, it's basically the same, so we can copy paste the blocks,
we attach them to the not me confidence area, and we just have to prepend a not in front
of the me.
And now we have just defined that me confidence variable that can be accessed like that will
have the percentage of confidence that we are looking at the baby, and the not me confidence
is the opposite, it's how confident we are that we are not looking at the baby.
The next step, the interaction variables, and now we just have to recap what do we have
to do in the app.
So in the app, we have to first update these labels here with the percentage, and we have
to update these color bars with the correct confidence levels.
We can do that by going to these components, to these two horizontal arrangements, and
we have percentage one, bar graph one, percentage two, and bar graph two.
Percentage one, we can update the text to the percentage that we are showing.
One second, there it is.
We will be, so the value that we return from the dictionary goes from zero to one, but
we want to return a percentage which goes from zero to 100.
So we will take this me confidence value, and we will multiply it by 100, so we can
get the zero to 100 range.
We just join it right here with the math number, and we multiply it by 100.
But we will be missing the percentage sign.
To get the percentage sign, we can use the text blocks with the join block, so we can
join two texts together, and we can just create a new percentage symbol like this, using the
percentage symbol.
And this is for the percentage labels.
For the bar graph labels, we will be pledging with the length of the actual bar graph.
To do so, we have the width percent block that can modify the width according to a percentage,
and we already have defined the percentage right here, so we can just copy paste these
blocks and attach them to the width percent.
And this is for the me group.
For the not me group, we can copy paste the percentage one, which changes to percentage
two, and we change the me confidence value to the not me confidence value.
And for the bar graph, it's going to be bar graph two right here, and me confidence changes
to not me confidence.
And with that, we already have all the sequence of events for the labels updates.
You can just go to the next step and confirm that we have defined it correctly, which is
the same result.
The next step is the fancy image change that if we think that we are looking at the baby,
we will show the happy face, otherwise we just show the crying face.
We will be using the if then logic, so go to the control blocks, and we just take the
if then otherwise block.
We append it here, and what we will do is we will be comparing the me confidence value
to the not me confidence value to know if we are looking at the baby or not.
We go to the math blocks, we pick this comparator block, attach them to the if statement, and
we are going to be changing the comparison to higher or equal because we don't worry
about the equal in this case, we just want the higher or equal.
We take again the me confidence variable, we compare it here, and we take the not me
confidence value, and we compare it right here.
Then we will be updating the background of the app, which is available in the screen
one.
We take the background color block, we attach it here, and the tutorial already provides
the example colors, so I'm just going to be dragging this right below so I can have them
more easily accessible.
Right here.
And I can just join it here.
And for the baby images, we have two images available here, happy baby and sad baby.
So if we think that we are looking at the baby, we show the happy baby, so we use the
visible block.
And if not, we just hide, sorry, if we think that we are looking at the baby, we hide the
sad baby face.
We go to the logic blocks, we take the true, so we can set to true to visible, we can set
visible to true, and we set visible to false for the sad baby, like that.
And we just join it.
For the case of me confidence being higher than not me confidence, for the opposite case,
when we are not looking at the baby, we just change the background color to this pink color.
We hide the happy baby face, like that.
And we show the sad baby face, just like this.
And now the app is finished.
So here we can just check the final code, which is exactly the same as we have right
here.
There are other possibilities, like we can just implement a classifier using a different
person.
But to show how this works, we can use the MIT company app that is available on the Play
Store.
Let me just show my phone again.
Here it is.
So you can just go to the Play Store and go to MIT App Inventor, search MIT App Inventor,
and you have right here the company.
You can open it.
You can just ignore this warning.
It works without Wi-Fi, continue without Wi-Fi.
And over here you can connect the AI company.
And now can scan the QR code like this.
Sorry, it just disappeared.
It takes a few seconds to connect.
Let's see if it was faster than tonight.
Now it's loading the personal classifier extension into my phone.
This works with Wi-Fi.
It doesn't have to be connected.
It's just connected because I'm just mirroring the screen through that cable.
And I see here the layout of the app.
I can see that it shows ready.
So I can just toggle the camera to be the front one.
And I can look at the camera.
And I'm just going to restart.
And there is a higher confidence that I'm looking at the baby if I just put a hand in
front of it.
It's just crying.
And yeah, that's it.
Later, if you want to build any other apps, you can export it to APK files.
So you can start it on your phone or to Android app bundles if you want to distribute it through
Play Store.
But yeah, this is just a very high-level introduction to artificial intelligence in App
Elementor.
You can just build any kind of classifier, for example, to classify trees, flowers, to
classify even people.
For example, for a faculty, if you want to build an app that recognizes people in your
class as a game, you can just use App Inventor and build any kind of app.
Thank you so much.
And I hope that it was useful for everybody.
Any questions?
Do you mentor a tech-novation team?
No.
You have a serious advantage.
Sorry.
I'm a software engineer.
I just contributed to App Inventor.
I started building apps and then I transitioned to open source.
I participated in Google Summer of Code.
Like this option to export the standard app bundles was my project in 2020 for Google Summer
of Code.
But yeah, more technical than actually teaching to kids.
Any other questions?
What's your experience with the relation between the number of pictures you have to submit
to your classifier and your accuracy?
That's a very good question.
So for the linear example...
Maybe you can repeat this for the tempo.
Oh, yeah, sure.
So he was asking, what's the experience with the amount of images that we are going to
be using for the classifier?
So I haven't really tested it right now.
But we have seen that if we go higher than 10 images for each class, for each group of
images, we'll have really good results.
In this case, because I was just running very fast and using just a few number of images,
you can see that the confidence levels were a little bit like 80-20.
But if we provide more than 10 images for each class, we should be able to get around
over 90-95% of confidence for each number.
I'm not sure if there are any questions from the chat.
Let me just check.
Yeah.
What do you capture?
Was that just for your face or did the learning...
What was learned, is it just like eyes and stuff?
So can I go out there and have the same results?
It recognizes...
It depends on what you are training because in this case, we are just providing a very
specific gestures.
That's training my face like any face looking at the camera or a hand in front of the face.
By default, the model that is available, that is here, this model is trained by Salim, is
the example guide that is at the beginning of the tutorial.
And I just tested it last night.
And it worked with me because it recognizes the gestures, not the faces.
If instead we train recognizing people, we will all be looking in the same way as the
camera.
So it will just go for a specific facial features.
In this case, it will work.
You can just try if you want.
We can try.
It should work.
Can you...
It is going to be a little bit tough.
But Mark, can you just try with Mark, for example?
Toggle camera.
You can try it yourself.
You are different as well.
Toggle camera.
And just try it with...
And start.
Press start.
It is a happy face.
So if you put a hand in front, it is a sad face.
It is recognizing the gestures.
Very cool.
So can you also train it to recognize specific people?
Yeah, it can be trained.
But in this case, because the higher difference was the hand, it is just looking for the hand
and model.
But if you do not show the hand, it will look for faces.
Can you fit your own pencil film models into your app?
It can be fit because you can just use this website and fit any kind of models.
The only restriction is that it has to be an MLD file.
But yeah, it can classify any model, basically.
No problem.
Any other questions?
Well, I think we can leave it here.
Thank you so much.