Okay, 10-20. Welcome everyone. Everyone can hear me right? Good. Welcome to my talk about
Hetty. Well, first of all, I promised to wave to my wife. She's waching at home. Can you
all say hi, Susan? She never thought this would ever happen being talked to from the
biggest open source conference in the world. She's at the couch with a broken ankle and
a poor hair. Okay, my name is Mark Heezen. I'm a lecturer in IT at a applied university
in the Netherlands. And I'm doing this talk about Hetty. And Hetty is a gradual, multilingual
programming language for teaching. Instead of all the other languages here, they're for
learning, I think. This one's for teaching, specific. And it's multilingual. And why is
it here? It was invented and usually mostly built by Felina Herman, a professor in the
Netherlands. She's a professor mainly in how do we learn programming. She wrote a book
about it. You should definitely read it. What was it? The programmer's brain. You become
a really better programmer by just reading that. But how did she come to this? Somewhere
in the past, for her it was 2013, for me in 2019, there was a group of children that wanted
to learn programming. And, well, we program. So we said, I'll teach it. That's pretty easy.
We started to think, how do you teach programming? How were we taught programming? Well, we weren't.
We just sat in front of a computer with a cursor. And in my case, I started typing hexadecimal
coding. I typed over from the nibble or the byte. Those are magazines some of you might
know. Probably not. I see some nodding. But, okay. And this would result in three things.
It either worked. Those moments were pretty sparse. It wouldn't work. Or it said beep.
These were the three options I had. Felina was a little luckier. I was a few days or
a few years later a little luckier. We did not have a teacher, but we had a book. In
Felina's case, a book of basic programming. And once you get to this, well, you can read
it. You can read it. This is plain English. To us programmers, this is plain English.
It even has line numbers. So if there's an error, it actually tells you it's a line number
120. And it even puts out some text telling you what's wrong. Wow. Compilers are perfect
teachers. That's what we thought. This is how we learned. We never realized that 90%
or 99% of the people didn't think this. And they quit programming. They never got anywhere
further than beep. So most of the coding dojos or code clubs start using Scratch. It's pretty
easy. It takes a lot of the syntax away by using block programming. You can actually
ask children to build this. And some of them will say, oh, yeah. And some of them will
say, 14 or 15. Scratch is for kids. If I Google code, it never looks like this. I want to
do the real stuff. I want to do zim zalabim. So Felina started coding with this sort of
Python. And she said, the first thing I like to learn is input and output. She's a teacher.
She knows how to teach. Baby steps. The first thing is first, input and output. Let's use
some output. Print hello, everyone. Enter. And voila. Hello, everyone. Children really
like this. It's easy. Unless there's some red scribbling below, they don't care. They
still press enter. And this lovely teacher tells them some mumble jumble and then in
line five, name print is not defined. And the children, well, I did define print. If
they understand English, only if they understand English, mine don't. They're from eight years
old and up. They don't know. They don't know what is and they don't recognize that there's
a capital P in there. This one's even worse. It's missing a parenthesis at the end. And
their lovely compiler will tell you some empty lines and then unexpected EOF while parsing.
This eight year old kid asked me what is parsing? Try to explain parsing while print is not
even in their minds yet. It's not that easy. There's too much going on. Too much interference
in learning. This is not a way of learning. And there's even a better one since we're
using Python. Did anybody see it shift a little? There's a space in there. Well, Python knows
it's not supposed to be there. Unexpected indent. When I was finished explaining parsing,
this was my next problem. So compilers are lovely teachers. Okay, that was true for me.
That was true for some of you. And the 99% of the others that didn't make it to this
conference is was not a lovely teacher. The next phase, if I get through to input and
output, the next one is iteration repetition. For I in range for print I can I can explain
that. I think I have an old hour. Classes are an hour. Just one hour to explain repetition.
Well, the kids only see colons brackets and spaces. And they mumble jumble them through
each other. I can give them an example and they can press run and they say, okay, okay,
but it can never reproduce this. Not in an hour at least. Not my kids. Maybe some others
can but not in my class. Syntax creates too much cognitive load. They have to remember
too much things to actually get to the stuff I want them to learn. This is not new to programming.
This is true for any language. It's true for math. How did you do that? Well, we just start
with small bits. If you start writing, you write an A and an I and an N and an E. And
we would say to the kid that produced this, wow, that's a lovely A. Oh, and you already
made a word in. They're not separated much. It's a word. That's good. And that E is wonderful.
It's even nicely on the line. Three compliments, four compliments and a lot of learning. The
next thing they know is they can create words, cat, in, tree. And once they grasp that, we're
going to make it a little harder. We start sentences with a capital letter. And the capital
S or T is completely different than the lower one. So they have to learn a complete new
set of letters. The C looks alike, but some of them are very different. And in some languages,
almost all of them are different. After that, we teach them, okay, we started with a capital.
We end it with a period. And once we end it with a period, once they know a sentence ends
with a period, they can actually spread sentences over lines. This is maybe sixth grade or something.
Or I'm not sure where exactly we are now, but it's gradually changing. Rules are changing.
It's not bad to change the rules every now and then. It's good in this case. Same for
math. If I have five apples and I take three, how much do you have left? What? Two. They
know that. If you have three and I'm trying to take five, how much do you have left? Zero.
Yeah. Only years later, you'll learn that there is a possibility you have minus two
apples. Happy appetite. Dividing same. Eight divided by three, that's two. And then there
is two remaining. I cannot divide the latter two by three anymore. And then there is two
thirds and then there is 2.6666 and that takes a long life. Can we actually teach code gradually?
Well, yes, we can now. We can by using Hetty. This is Hetty. This is the program environment.
And the first line of code you can actually run is print hello world. And it works. And
you see there are no quotation marks, no brackets, no nothing. There are only three commands.
There's print for output and then there's ask and echo. Ask for input and echo is another
way of producing output. It produces the word, the text behind it and then followed by the
input. So if I run this, what is your name? And my name is Mark. And it says hello, Mark.
This is fun already. If it's not fun enough, they can actually have it spoken to.
Your name. Hello, Mark. And imagine a classroom full of 25 kids producing things like this.
And within a few seconds you're hearing, Mark is stupid and they're having a lot of fun
in a whole hour. With only three commands, they're having fun. As soon as they stop laughing,
or usually the next hour, the next lesson, the next lesson, the week later, we introduce
variables. This is probably the toughest part of programming. To kids, at least. At least
that's what I found. You can label things. Name is Hadi, age is 15, print name is eight
years old. I can run this code and it produces Hadi is 15 years old. They can play around
with this. They can create actually pretty nice programs. They're actually busy for another
hour. Sometimes two. Until they hit a snatch. Sometimes some of the kids find out that if
I ask what is your name and they produce so your name is name, most programmers will probably
realize oh, no, now we have a problem. Yeah. There's one name that I want to produce as
text and there's one name that I want to as variable. I can never, ever use the text anymore.
This is a learning opportunity. We can actually say okay, we have to make a distinction between
these. If I mean text, I put quotation marks around it. Ah, okay, that's a smart thing.
It's like they invented it themselves. Let them think so. It's gradual and it's 18 levels
and at the end you're speaking fluent Python. That's the gradual part. It's also multilingual.
Why? Well, we asked kids do you like Hadi? There was a small study. There's a paper about
it. It's in the slide deck at the end. There was only 39 kids in 12 online lessons. This
was corona time. We asked them what are the benefits, the challenges and the improvements.
These were the kids of Fellina's classes and they said well, it's great that it's stepwise.
I can excel level by level and I can follow on. The teachers that actually work with it
are usually normal teachers. They're not programmers. They teach for the first time programming.
They don't even know programming. They liked it and they said oh well, all kids, my whole
class is learning programming. Of course there are some kids that say you're going to be
a programmer but the rest is still dragging along. Some of the teachers said even the
girls now have the confidence to become a programmer. It's something they mentioned
out of their cells. What do they want? They want some improvements. First of all, they
want better error messages. We had very good error messages. I'll show you one. You cannot
read this but it says you typed comma but that is not allowed. We put a comma here as
a comma between quotes. Remember these are kids of 10 year olds and they just learned
that if there's a comma in the sentence they pause. They read you typed but that's not
allowed. Why cannot I type? We had to change that in you typed a comma but that's not allowed.
Almost all of those well thought of error messages weren't well thought of after all.
How they are and they wanted something really weird. They wanted Dutch keywords. Well, we're
in the Netherlands so it's not weird they want Dutch but why? Everybody's coding in
English. Print is the same in Dutch. Echo is the same but why? Let's look at the demo.
Let's see a nice error message. Print hello world with a capital P. It says print is not
a command in level one. Did you mean print? The first one is a capital P and the last
one is a small P. Maybe it gets even better. If I put a space in front of it, it runs.
But it gives me a warning. Oops. You started a line with a space on line one. Spaces confuse
me. Can you remove it? There's plenty of time to correct these ideas. I don't know. I should
change that. Then there's translation. I'm in English now. I can move to 45 languages
like Dutch. Yes, I want to reload. Now this whole program, every text, almost everything
is in Dutch except for ask. Ask was by the way the main reason they wanted it in Dutch
because in Dutch we don't usually have the S and the K so near one another. They write
X and it's a weird letter combination. There's a toggle where you can say I want to change
the commands in Dutch as well. Now everything is in Dutch. I can ask for the ones we don't
speak Dutch. That's the same as what's your name. It's still Mark. Hello, Mark. It works
even in Dutch. Once we had this, we realized that people were in India using Hindi, Thai,
Chinese, Arab. It's all those kids are just like in the Netherlands. They're just learning
a language. They don't know a P if they see one. To us, to me, these are images. These
are not letters. I cannot read this. I can copy paste some of this but I cannot read
this. The same is true for them. They cannot read these letters. They should be able to
put them into Arabic as well. This works, of course, I hope. I cannot check. Maybe I'm
cursing now. I guess it works. That's why it's multilingual. It's for the kids. Yes,
at the end, in level 18, we do tell them you better put it in English now. You know what
it all means but you better start using English now. From now on, no more Dutch or Arabic
or whatever. They're old enough to do that. It's built for teaching. It's built for teachers
as well as students. They like that the levels are step by step a guide. There's only small
thing they have to learn and the rest is not even possible. The teachers that do not know
programming but are teaching programming but using Hetty, they think, oh, I can do this.
This is not overwhelming. When I was using Scratch for the first time in a coded dojo,
I had to think of a program they could make. What can my students make? There's a lot of
examples on the Internet. I need to do research. I need to find the right thing and if I'm
planning a 20-day course, somewhere in level of day 18, I'm probably going to mess up something
I did in level 17. It's going to cost me time to get things right. I can find the
right one or that one or that one. If I'm not a real programmer, if I'm not very good
at it myself, which one should I take? If I choose one, I print it out, I hand it over
to my students and they open up Scratch and they start looking at Scratch and they start
looking at the lesson again, at the paper and they look at Scratch again. What was that?
They have to contact-switch over and over again. I see the students getting a little
distracted. I don't remember what was it. They're very impatient species, children.
We invented adventures. I'll show you in the last demo because the time is ticking away.
Then there is class management. That's the last thing I want to talk about, class management
as in there's a whole different type of kids in the class. There's this type that actually
read the paper, reproduced it in Scratch and tells the teacher, look, I did it. It just
wants a pattern of a bag. Yeah, it's right. In five minutes, they produce a mowing, running
around cat. It's lovely and they did it. The other one, and there are quite a few, they
drag just one thing on the screen, which I do now. Well, you could read the paper again.
I don't get it. Then there's this type, probably the level of Olivier, they would probably
produce something they want recognition for. They did this in five minutes as well because
they've been doing this for years at home. Now they want my help to get some synchronized
legs on the bottom of this Robin Hood. Once it run, I don't even know how to do that.
At least I can call Olivier now and help me out in this block programming. All these kids
are in the same class. I want them to move along about the same page. What was it? Base,
that's it. So we created something we call customization. First of all, let's put this
back into English. Let's see me in action. This is my account. As you have seen before,
maybe there are some tabs on the top of this. This is what we call adventures. There are
maybe 10, 15 different adventures. They come along every level, 18 levels along. They can
do rock, paper, scissors. First of all, it's just printing and at the end it's deciding
who won and playing against the computer and three players against, etc. So it's getting
more progressively difficult, but it's still the same program. As a teacher, I only have
to know 10 programs and it's all in view. I can just click on, I want to do the story
and I code it here. So for the kids, there is no context switching of paper or thing.
Then there's this teacher that can do, oh, teacher. Is this the teacher version? Where
is the teacher version? But I should be logged in in any of them. No, I'm not logged in in
any of them now. Why am I no longer logged in? I don't know my password because that's
very secure. So I need last pass and I cancelled everything. Oh well. How many minutes have
I left? Okay, that will work. What am I doing now?
Yes.
So this is where I was. I thought I was at my page. There is, if you're a teacher, you
can just request to become a teacher only, even if you're only teaching your own two
kids, you can actually become a teacher. And then there's this for teachers page and there's
a complete teacher manual. And there's a demo class in which I am a student. I can look
at some statistics. How many errors did I produce? At what level am I? What kind of
errors did I produce? How many successful programs? How many errors programs? And I
can customize the class. I can switch on and off all the levels. And what I do in real
life, I switch them all off except for the first one. So all the class has to stay in
less than one, in level one. I can automatically produce a schedule, put opening dates so they
automatically open every week, for instance, I can hide and show quizzes and puzzles. There's
a person puzzle at the end of all the adventures. And there's a quiz at the end 10 questions.
And I can ask if I can set this class to minimum quiz score of 80 before they can advance to
the next level. So if I save this and go to the other one. Oh, wow. Now it accidentally
logged in. I think it's because I have two of the same browsers now. Mark and class.
This one's not a secret. If I go to this now, you can see there's a lot less. Only two.
So this class only has two adventures. It has a puzzle and a quiz. And they cannot go
to level two unless they made the quiz until with 18 points, 80% of points. Okay, that's
customization. That's about it. Heady, it's called it's named after heavy Lamar, who knows
heavy Lamar. Oh, that's a lot of world famous actress, and a world infamous inventor. We're
still using a lot of our inventions. And of course, we're open source. We love your help.
If you think, ah, this is a good idea. And I'd like to work on an innovative gradual
parser. Actually, actually quite a feat. There's a paper about it. And it tells you a little
bit about an EVNF extension that we can merge partial grammars. We actually want help in
multilingual language. Like I said, we have 45 languages, and these are 45 languages.
As you can see, English is pretty well. And Dutch is pretty well. There's some other languages
are blue. We love help making all these ones as green as it. And of course, we want you
to help teachers. So go to your schools in the neighborhood and tell teachers about them.
And maybe help them get along get started. Once they get started. It's like oil it spreads.
I'm only teaching 40 kids now if I was I was teaching 40 teachers. That would go a lot
faster. There are some building videos for teachers. And this is where you can join.
Thank you very much.