Let's just fetch our micro blocks here.
This happened to me before.
Why did that go away?
Let's try this.
Let me just quit micro blocks a second.
Oh, there it goes.
No, I don't want to quit.
Okay, so the cable wasn't quite plugged in.
For some reason I lost my displays to something.
So I said basic sensors, just like that Heti language.
Actually let me just quit micro blocks really quick.
This cable is being a little flaky.
No, no, no.
And also in the display.
Okay.
This is what it looks like.
And you have outputs, you have inputs, and then you can do all the pins.
You have your control variables, operators, all sorts of stuff like that.
But I plugged in this board.
It showed a green here.
It's already connected.
So it already knows what this board is.
And when I click temperature, it tells me it's 19 degrees C. If I want to see the display,
I simply turn on the display.
Oh, let's see.
I need this quick camera.
So for those of you at home, there's my happy face.
And then I click temperature.
There it is there.
Keep losing this connection.
Okay.
All right.
Every time the HDMI pops in and out, it's causing micro blocks to be unhappy.
Sorry about that.
What's that?
Okay.
All right.
Let's just try this one more time.
Load micro blocks.
And another particularly cool.
It's okay.
It's very flaky.
Oh, I lost it.
Let me see.
What happened to my power?
So HDMI is lost.
Don't touch anything.
Yeah.
We might have a few screen issues here.
Let me just try really quickly if I can quit and open again.
Okay.
Quite briefly, I wanted to show you that you can graph something like the light level.
And you can also see the data of an input value and it will put zero at the bottom.
And I can watch this in real time.
And if I close my hand over it, it gets reflections on stuff.
But so you can see, you can plot data in real time, X, Y, and Z.
It has an accelerometer.
So that's very cool.
All right.
Now, we're going to go back.
So that's liveness.
There's no compile download.
It's just happening.
Next point is that you can do things in parallel.
So I'm going to show you a quick, how multitasking is handled through just opening the two button
blink program right here.
And I open this.
And if I press button, let me get my camera.
If I press button A, while I'm pressing it, it's going to repeat and blink 100 milliseconds.
While I press B, it does the same thing.
I can actually press A and B. And I can try to get them in sync or I can try to get them
on and off.
But it takes too long.
So just as Hetty has variables, I can do something like a delay.
So I can try to play around with it in real time.
And I set the delay to like 500.
And then I drag this delay variable in so I can play around with a slower blink time
and change it all I want while I'm experimenting.
And now, if I set that delay variable, you can also use say block.
So it's nice to just set a variable and say it.
Now I know what it is.
And if I'm pressing the A, now you see it's every 500.
And now I can more like get them on, off, on, off.
And if you were in an Arduino loop, just one Continue Forever loop, this would be a lot
harder to have either these different multitasking done for you, which is very, very cool.
The next thing is that it's autonomous.
So if I am programming and I'm doing these blocks on my IDE, then what happens is there's
actually an opcode, it looks a bit like assembly language representation of those blocks that
you can see.
And then in the actual board, it's actually in bytecode.
So if I were to turn on advanced blocks, I could show you the instructions.
You can see that, and then I could actually see the bytecode.
And the bytecode is then what is inside the virtual machine.
So that will have cool ramifications about sharing our files when we get to that point.
OK, so blocks equate to bytecode.
So it's autonomous in the sense that if I unplug it from my laptop and I plug it back
in, then what happened?
Did I lose my connection?
OK, I just, oh, I know what happened.
For autonomy, I made a mistake.
I actually need a when started block to set that delay because there was delay of zero.
So I actually needed this to be set.
We have to show our errors.
And now down here, there we go.
And I love having a co-speaker.
And then another very awesome aspect of it is its portability.
So microblocks, if you look at how we build the virtual machine, we have a platform I.O.
script with an any file that I looked last night.
There were up to 43 different boards.
And there's kind of about nine varieties that if you go into microblocks itself and you
want to update the firmware on a board, it will show you well, this is plugged in now.
I'm just updating the firmware on it.
But let me just unplug this for a moment.
And if you want to update the firmware on a board, there's like micro bits, caliope,
the ESP32.
There's some new electroph
a whole bunch of boards.
But there's also in the platform I.O.
any file, a whole bunch of Arduino boards and other stuff that's there.
So it's portable.
And I want to do a quick display of that where I take this quick ham.
I'm going to make it big.
And we apply power.
So I have a whole bunch of boards plugged into a USB strip.
So we don't lose the HDMI.
And Bernat's going to turn that on.
And now you can see I have the heartbeat program running on a whole bunch of different boards.
So I kind of cheated on a couple of boards that are new and didn't have full support
like this Mbits board.
But and of course the circuit playground doesn't have the same thing.
But on some of these OLED displays, you can actually use the micro bit type style display
box and it still works.
And then go around and push the A button on everything.
So the A buttons turn them all to smiles.
And whoops.
Dang.
Just so now they're all happy face.
And of course if they have B buttons, we can go back to our heart.
And this is the only one that has a side B button.
Voila.
So as you know, like getting used to a programming environment, when you pick up a different
board, do you want to get a different programming environment every time?
No, clearly not.
So portability is really cool.
Did I lose it completely?
All right.
I'm about to hand this off.
So that's good.
All right.
Let's hear.
Okay.
And then the last part to explain is shareability.
So yeah, I could do the same program.
So shareability is there's a few ways to deal with this.
Let me go in the slide show mode because I'm basically wrapped up.
One is like you can go to the file open save menu with micro blocks.
Let me just show you in real time here.
So you can just go in here and say file, save file open.
And then there's these other options like encoded in the URL.
So you can say file copy project URL to a clipboard.
And then you can open it, give that URL out.
And we do this, you know, embed a you just put a hyperlink on some documentation.
And you can open that right in the Chrome browser.
Chrome or Edge browser support the serial mode.
You can't unfortunately use Firefox.
I used to work from Mozilla.
Okay.
And then encoded in the picture.
So our documentation, we have pictures on the websites in the wiki in the learn section.
And the code is actually embedded in the picture.
So you drag the picture into your Chrome browser and or into your IDE standalone or Chrome
browser and it will actually load the code.
And then the last part is it's shareable by opening from the board.
And so I'm going to have Bernat demonstrate that as we hand off to more cool demo for
part two.
Okay.
Can you hear me?
Yes, of course you can.
So yeah, we were talking about portability.
And one of the aspects of portability is not just that the code is portable across boards,
but the board itself is an example of portability.
The board is actually it contains the program that you are seeing here, right?
In any other microcontroller environment, once the code is here, the code is here and
it's it's gone.
If you've lost your program, if you've lost your source, the source is gone.
Right?
And microblocks, we have a way, oops, not this, yeah, yeah, this microlock, sorry, that's
open from board.
Now, I'm in the browser version.
We have versions, we haven't mentioned that, but we have versions for the browser and for
Mac, Windows, Linux, and Chromebook and Raspberry Pi, etc.
So we have many platforms that we support.
This is the browser version.
And now it says plug in the board and connect and click the USB icon to connect.
So I'll just connect as it's set.
Now I select the USB port.
And now it's actually reading back the code.
And it's not like we embedded the blocks inside the board.
It's actually for the, I know this is a slightly geekier audience than our usual.
So we actually have a decompiler that John built in that's inspired in this quick decompiler
that John also worked on.
And what it does is it takes these bytecodes and it retranslates them into what we see
here.
Right?
And just to prove that it still works, it does.
And you know, we like to joke that micrologs is so portable that we could even port it
to a board that does not exist.
And that's actually a joke, but it's true.
Like we have a board that doesn't exist and can run micrologs.
Since micrologs is VM based, you could compile this VM for something that does not exist,
that is virtual.
And that's why we made Borde.
Borde is a result of the pandemic.
We were doing online classes and it was really hard to get hardware to kids.
So that was an idea like my boss and Jan's and Yatka's boss at SAP, she had this idea
that we needed something virtual so that kids who don't have access to hardware could still
at least try micrologs.
And that's why we made Borde.
And Borde, as you can see, can run the same code.
It's not a simulator.
That's very important.
It's running the exact same VM.
So it's a virtual board, not a simulator.
It has its own capabilities.
It has a couple of buttons.
It has a speaker.
It has a touchscreen.
It has a file system.
It can do HTTP client operation.
So it's a different sort of board.
Yeah, right.
So it does the same things.
But you know, this is nice, but micrologs was always about physical computing.
This is nice.
If you don't have a board, that's a good way to get started.
But our aim was always to teach physical computing, to do tangible things in the real world, in
the physical world.
So let me show you one thing that you would not be able to do with boarding.
And that's connecting external sensors to your board.
So just this funny sensor that I have in here, that's an RFID sensor.
That's the technical Mambo Jumbo for the thing that's in your credit card that lets you pay
contactlessly or on your subway card or your gym membership card or whatever.
And I happen to have some of these cards with me, as you all do, I'm sure.
So for example,
Do you want cards up here?
Yeah.
And maybe I need, yeah, I need a cable.
Oops.
It's physical.
So this board has a battery, but it's that that's the problems of the physical world
as well.
So I'm connecting an external battery to it.
Okay.
And now I'm just going to try.
This has a micro box program in it, by the way, that I can show later, maybe.
But I'll show it later.
So okay, so I made it so it recognizes this particular card and it plays a tone.
Okay, that's interesting.
Let's try another card.
Okay.
Let's try this one.
Cool.
I'm missing some.
No, wait.
Yes, we'll talk later.
I'll need a special number that comes with it as well.
Let's try with my bank ones and this one as well.
Okay.
So we have a bunch of cards and we've seen that each of them can make a note.
Let's try to maybe.
Oh yeah.
Where is it?
I know it's somewhere.
Oh, maybe.
Yeah.
You know, when you're having trouble paying, that's why.
Because it's okay.
Okay.
I'll try to play a song.
Where is it?
The second part.
Cathy, can you hand me your keys?
Okay.
So I was to show that programming is fun, but programming the real world and touching
actual things is a very engaging way to get kids and people that are not hardcore gigs
interested in what we do, which is programming computers.
That was all.
Go to the.
Oh yeah.
Go to the micro blocks website if you want to learn more about it.
Microblocks.fun.
Small, fast, human friendly.
That's our website.
We have a very nice, if I may say so, learn page with a lot of tutorials.
Microblocks is also translated to a lot of language.
I forgot how many.
The code is also translated just like Eddie.
And a little more translators just like Eddie.
Yeah.
And if you want to help out in our site, there is a whole section about how to contribute
and we have a space for everyone who wants to help out.
Thank you.
Do you have time for questions?
Just maybe one or two, right?
Any questions?
Is it expensive?
I was getting asked that a lot at the booth yesterday.
Because we were doing some demos in the SFC booth and the range, if I can pull it, this
how much was this?
Maybe $25 M5 stack.
Probably even less than $10 for the M5 atom.
The micro bits were retail at $15 until the pandemic supply and change shortage.
Now they're $20 or more.
The M bits, what was this one now?
$12, $25.
The Pico Ed is maybe $10.
This is maybe $25.
So I would say they range less than $50.
And then you can buy some of these educational boards.
Let me just show you.
Like some of the small boards with stuff already included, so you don't have to learn, but
the new Robatistan.com Pico Ed board, this is like $50.
But it has all these sensors and actuators.
And then you can pull apart the bricks, as they're called, and use cables to put them
back together.
I want to say the board is free, though.
We have other ranges from zero to...
And the cheapest of the ESP8266 is there a couple dollars.
But then you have to buy the sensors and actuators.
I actually find for teaching you probably want to buy something with integrated stuff.
And then you can buy all these kits and plug them together and run robots and the robotic
kits.
There's a ton of hardware out there.
Next question.
So do you have a free-made sort of workshop material?
Oh, hold on.
So first of all, in the learn site, you're going to find some resources that are like
full classes, like let's say this one that teaches you about main enumerals.
We also try to do activities that are not just about technology, right?
So we can get a more diverse audience interested.
If you make a project about bits and bytes, that's going to interest probably the people
in this room.
But you're already interested with... you're not the target audience, right?
But if we talk about main enumerals, maybe people who are interested in history or culture
are going to see the value in programming and microcontrollers.
So that's a whole activity.
And then you have actually...
And again, you drag the screenshots, pictures into the IDE and they will load.
And then you have a teacher's guide with extra information about what's being talked about.
And then there's...
We've done these things called activity cards.
And I put together a kit with a manufacturer and they included these activity cards, 10
two-sided cards in the kit.
And there's things like flashlight tag and sound and two-button texting.
It uses two microbits and use tilt to find the letters and punctuation and button A and
button B to find the letters and add.
And you can actually text messages directly between two microbits, for example, or clues
or other boards.
What do you mean, can you code...
We don't want people to have to go through this hard-on.
That's why we're making microblocks.
So you don't have to care about bits and byte codes.
No, this is coding.
You can see the off codes if you want and you can build other editors to the VM if you
want a text-based editor on top.
Go ahead.
I'm wondering, I'm familiar a bit with microbits.
And so what you do is you add sensors or you put them in little robot cars, I think, like
that.
Yes.
And?
If you go to the learn side again, there's...
You can select the microbit here and you'll see all these activities for the microbit.
And a lot of them are using external sensors, like this one uses motors to make a microbit
robot.
This one uses a ready-made robot car.
A lot of them use external sensors and activators.
So, for example, you ask, I deliver.
There's just five commands at the end of the radio.
Forward, back, left, right, and stop.
Every time the buttons go up, I stop.
And this one's running out of battery.
So the other one's faster.
We're over time, Kathy.
Okay.
Thank you, everyone.
Thank you.