So, yeah, this is quite insane if you ask me, at least of how many people are in this
very small room at this moment.
But thank you all for coming, first and foremost.
There is just, I have one more slide.
That's it.
And then I'll hand it over to the first speaker.
But of course, we are at FOSDAM, so we have to abide by their rules.
Please we just distributed some stickers.
Please don't go sticking them all over their property.
Keep them for your laptops.
That's what they're meant for after all.
Also be mindful of each other.
This is a very well packed room.
Apparently, it's going to get hot probably.
If you just have to leave, just please kindly ask the person next to you.
And please if somebody asks you, stand up, make some room.
Just cooperate a little bit.
It's going to be necessary in this situation at the moment.
So with that being said, is everybody ready for an entire block of pure chaos and fun
as well of everything to do with Nixx and NixxOS?
Yes.
Then all it is.
Thank you.