Please welcome the next speaker, Gova.
Hi, so my name is Gova Todionia, the H. Dawes Satoruya, which is a really not name, so you
can just call me Gova.
And I'm going to talk about this great thing called Futon.
So before that, I was sponsored by the Internet Foundation with a grant that is financed through
the European Commission called NGISU, and Generation Internet.
So if you have ideas and just want money, just apply to it.
It's actually a really cool thing.
So now, what is before?
So I guess the academic definition would be the programming protocol independent packet
processor.
It's a domain specific language for network devices.
Trying out data plane devices, switches, new equipment filters, etc.
Processed packets.
Okay, great.
But what does this actually mean?
Okay, so it's an upgrade basically for hardware optimized network processing.
Like, things seem different network, so you can just have like those FPGAs, DPUs, whatever,
and you can make them process network packets for you at an accelerated rate compared to
software.
So it roughly looks like C in a way.
As you can see, it has the same kind of syntax, like arguments, whatnot.
The thing is, there's a few things, there's a few how-to's.
You can see it has the state thing, it doesn't have a return.
You have transition select, what is this?
It looks a bit weird.
So let's explain this a bit.
This in P4 are replaced mostly by things called parser control packet.
So what is parser?
A parser is a function that is going to pass an incoming packet according to, well, the
same thing as in C, which means struct, type def, etc.
Say I'm going to define a struct, I'm going to say, if this element of a struct is this,
then I'm going to call this function.
Basically that's what the parser function does.
You have then the control functions.
What if I pass the packet, say, for example, you have this really long packet which says
I have up X, Y, Z, and then you want to remove the up X because you're on up X.
You're going to do this in a control function.
And then you have package, which defines basically the binding logic between the hardware.
Like oh, am I going, say I implement a firewall.
Oh, am I going to have new rules?
Or am I going to load new definitions and whatnot?
So that's basically it.
There are interesting keywords, there are other things, like, that I'm not going to
explain all of this because P4 is kind of like, this would basically be out of scope
for the talk and P4 is already complex enough as is.
So how do you want to use P4 in Nix?
There's a few ideas.
My take on it is let's make a transpiler.
Why?
Because transpiler allows you to use concepts within Nix, say, because P4 is a bit verbose,
because say you want to pass this IP TCP packet.
You need each time to redefine the IP header thingies.
So you want to redefine this truck, you want then to have it passed in a way, and then
sometimes you want this thing, sometimes you have this other IP struct because you don't
want to pass some optional data in the header that would slow down the process, et cetera.
So it's a bit verbose, let's just use Nix to basically reimplement parts of it and have
it in a nice packet.
So what is a transpiler?
In our case, it's Nix to P4 translator, which means you can define things in Nix, structs,
enums, whatnot, and it generates P4 code.
Then you have the P4 compiler, which actually processes the code that's generated, followed
by the target compiler, which in this case allows you to deploy your thing to, say, an
FPGA, a DPU, et cetera.
Basically the thing that allows you to run your thing, your program.
So what does it look like in action?
Basically this is a Nix file which allows you to define some P4 concept.
In this case, I defined a header flag which contains a few counts, like max ops, standards,
ops, et cetera.
And then a few headers.
In this case, I'm just defining SADATI, which has two flags, source and destination, both
of type bit eight.
That's basically just a way to redefine the annoying thing of P4.
Then you can also have include.
All of this is processed then by this function called run thread spire, mcat transpire, whatever
I called it now.
You just run this and it generates code for you.
And that's great.
So, we can simplify this, obviously, because that's a bit annoying to each time type this
header, this header, et cetera.
And the whole point of making this whole thing is to make it less verbose and to reuse code
so you can just have your own infra, mostly in Nix and a few bits and packages in P4 so
you can basically put everything in the same place.
In this case, you can just innovate things that I define in helpers and you can do the
same thing and you get your P4 source.
So that's a lot simpler and we don't have to define it each time.
We don't have to define market versus each time, which is a thing in P4 because if you
don't use standard P4, it's going to make you have to redefine all this as its program
you make.
It is thanks to helpers that I wrote down in my packages.
Great.
So, what does the hand-wistle look like?
Because I'm saying, oh, this is the Nix code, this is what it looks like, et cetera.
Yeah, it's great.
Okay.
So, this is basically the transpire.
It's kind of dirty Nix in a way.
You can see it's a lot of message functions.
But basically, the idea is that I define a module, a NixOS module, which verifies the
types of what I give it in this case, the header.
I give it a default type.
Then you can have the union, the content, the one-art, et cetera, which are then parsed
by the transpire, which are these huge nested functions, which basically just map strokes
like Nix, Nix, and H2S, I mean, into just P4 materials and then just write it.
Which is soft to search transpire.
It's nothing fancy, but it's fine.
And so, what does the hand-wistle look like after the transpire?
It looks like P4 code.
But pretty clean, you have the includes, the define, the maps, maxups, standard metadata,
then you have your access, et cetera.
And then you can include your own code.
And then this rule, P4 code, is then processed by the target compiler, which then processes
it to its own platform.
Say it can actually generate, like, say, eBPF code, so it runs on Linux.
eBPF is basically like this kernel thingy that you can run to have more privileges.
I'll explain it later if I have the time.
And this is BMPV2.
And BMPV2 is just a simplified model architecture.
I'll also talk about it later.
So basically, it's a soft to search transpiler that has multiple stages and allows you to
specify P4 functions and reuse concepts.
It's nothing fancy, but it's useful.
So now that I talked about BMPV2, I think I have the time to do it.
So what is it?
Glad you asked.
So the simple switch architecture is the defacto architecture that is used to basically test
P4C, which is the main compiler.
So it's basically like this kind of standard test setup that you can use to just see if
your code works.
But it's not fast.
You can't really target it to anywhere.
It's basically like this low user length thing that you can use to just test your program
that is not fast, but does mostly what you want.
It's basically just like this interface for targeting the switch.
It's an abstract interface.
And it's also used to just verify how P4C works.
So now to continue a bit more on P4, to set up, like to use P4, you need a target.
And the main targets that are currently implemented in P4C are user length, which is in this case
eBPF.
Some people are going to criticize this because eBPF is a click click channel.
But what I mean by user length is I mean it runs on a computer.
DPDK, which has, and this is why I'm saying it's user length, its own user length code
that can run.
But the DPDK also is like this, how do you call that?
An API, I guess.
It's an API that can target a bunch of devices.
So it's not only user length, but it has a user length point.
Then hardware, because you can use DPDK to also target hardware.
Say FPGAs, which are like for people that don't know things that you can use to say
program CPUs or whatnot.
You can basically just reconfigure the electrical level, electrical gates, etc.
And then custom
with a few better devices changes and like some say some some control functions usually
have a definition specific for eBPF and the like.
So there are a few changes, but overall you can target basically all of these with mostly
the same code, which is great.
But this also needs changes to be transpiler.
So you need to have more options so you can target every different one.
So you can say, have the role mess auto generated by transpiler.
So say you can just in Nix define, hey, I want target X and it's going to do it automatically
for you without having to change the P4 code, which is mess.
So now introducing FPGAs on Nix.
And I'm actually not kidding.
The thing is I forgot to actually take the picture before going to for them.
So imagine it's really hard.
Basically an FPGA connected to a computer who say USB or whatnot and then connected
to the network for Ethernet.
The idea is that we are not running Nix on an FPGA.
We are using Nix to define what the FPGA wants.
In this case, the network stack.
So we need to define like say the devices we have in Nix directly.
So say I'm going to have like a hardware dot, I know, a last order that type is my FPGA.
And then I'm going to explain how I can define it.
And you need some kind of auto reload deployment mechanism.
Usually like most FPGA providers just provide you a way through USB.
You can also have just an auto reload of fools through the control plane in P4 directly if
you want to go this way, which means basically no downtime network stack, which is nice.
And yeah, you can have a data plane mechanism for feeding data to your host.
All of this is a work in progress for now.
So the transpiler is down.
Basically most of the source to source transpiler, including the target sub package, you can
use BMP2 nowadays, you can use DPDK and whatnot.
But the hardware definitions are currently work in progress.
I haven't had the time to work on them yet, but it's close enough.
And software works.
So yeah, that's basically it.
Any questions?
Yeah.
How can you get a switch that runs P4?
So the question is, how can I get a switch that runs P4?
So you don't technically need a switch that runs P4.
You can just use any say FPGA or DPDU that you can reprogram and that is targeted by
DPDK.
You also have like some routers that have ASICs that are reprogrammable.
As long as you can target it with DPDK, which is basically the API you can target, you can
just use it and run P4 on it basically.
Yeah.
Okay.
So the question is, what makes Nix particularly nice in this case for P4?
So what makes Nix in this case useful is that it's at the border of basically like this
Boeing code to generate per target.
And you also need to actually target an infrastructure.
And basically, Nix is this great thing where you can just define an interface, an infrastructure
I mean, and you can then write automated code.
So Nix in this case has two key roles.
Just allowing you to write code with less, not having to rewrite every time thing.
Making it just basically this handy source tool.
And the thing is to define your network stack in the same place as you would define your
standard infrastructure, which means say, I want to define this server.
Okay, cool.
But now my server has like 100 million requests.
And I need to actually like upload this for some degree.
So I'm just going to say, hey, hardware definition.fpga is my PGA.
And now I have my speed magically.
Well, you need to pay for the PGA and pull anything but yeah, magically.
Any other questions?
Yeah.
This is useful for things that are not that work quite straight.
So you could do things that have nothing to do with networking for your targeting your
PGA.
Is there a scope for this or is it basically just the networking?
So the question is, is this going to be useful for other things than networking?
The answer is yes or no.
So the FPGA deployment mechanism, yes, is going to be useful in this case.
Because you can just reuse this thing and use it outside of the scope of PFA.
The reason to know is that everything else is basically PFA specific.
But yes, the last part is probably going to be reusable for other things than PFA, first
of all.
And second of all, there's going to be a few different FPGA targets probably.
Like there's always going to be proprietary ones with DPDK that have their own, say, deployment
binaries that are clusters that are pain.
But you can always see, like, try to implement, say, your these fingers and whatnot to have
an open source FPGA setup.
So yeah, you can use it outside of PFA, basically.
Yes?
If I can answer that in the first place, the P4 language is heavily exposed to the own
networking.
Like, a lot of people who are using it, like, Western Digital, like, the cache coherent
process in a way that you can do process.
That's a really good point, just for the live people.
Basically what was said is that you can use P4 to process any kind of stream and modify
it.
And it's used by companies to process this in an accelerated fashion, which is very true
and very handy.
It's not the most common user before, but before it's already not the weak commands.
We have two steps.
Yeah.
Did you want to do people?
Okay, let's do that.
So.
So, thank you, that was me, going to the party.
Here's my website, here's my email, and yeah, we have one last thing to show.
So.
I want to take a photo of your own.
Ah, sure.
It should be recorded so.
Yeah, I've got one online.
Okay.
Did I expect people to actually care about me, honestly?
DIMU.
So.
DIMU is a bit of a strange thing because the next talk is about secure boot.
Yes.
So it's a DIMU about secure boot?
There's, yeah, there's one thing I forgot to mention.
I'm working with people on this, but I'm also working on the secure boot thing is a bit,
at least.
So, what I wanted to show you is that.
Let me just do that.
Do that.
So, I can just do this.
I started this small PR the other day, which is like, grab support for secure boot.
So, yeah, I think now we can actually boot secure boot on XOS using grab.
And to head on to that, let me just show it there because it's, I have too many windows.
Ah, there we go.
Let me just.
Yeah, there we go.
Welcome to grab.
And I'm going to, I'm just going to zoom for the live.
Okay.
Yeah.
There we go.
And basically just this whole thing is working on a secure boot.
And as you can see, it's panicking, but it's close enough.
It's close enough.
So now.
I'm going to leave in a speaker explaining what Lensa Booty is.