Thank you.
So, hi.
Today, I'll tell you a success story of adopting Nix at the workplace, all the way from reproducible
CI builds to NixOS in production, and also what we have learned in the process.
By the way, you can use the QR code to follow the slides on your devices if you want.
I have some links there as well.
So first, about me, I'm, well, now ex-principal software engineer at Profion.
I've been using Nix in NixOS since 2016.
Now Profion was a security company, and we were custodians of the NRX open source project.
We were mostly focused on developing NRX and also providing network services around NRX.
But, unfortunately, just earlier, we actually closed the company because we were out of
money and couldn't secure funding or acquisition.
So NRX was a confidential computing, well, is a confidential computing platform, providing
you ability to run WebAssembly within TEEs, so hardware secure enclaves.
And well, I'm not going to go into too much detail, but the relevant part here is that
NRX builds trust based upon a remote attestation procedure.
And to do that, basically how it works is that we, as Profion, we build a portable,
mostly static NRX release binary, then we run it and we measure the memory pages within
a TE.
Then we add that to a allow list in an attestation service.
And finally, then the user uses the release binary, and they, well, they also run it on
a TE.
And we, in our attestation service, can verify that indeed they are running a trusted system,
this trusted release of NRX within a real TE.
But there are two questions, of course, which arise, which is what if the release version
of NRX is compromised, or what if actually our build pipeline is compromised?
So then you can also ask a question, so how can users actually verify that the source
code that we have released, we say, okay, this release corresponds to this source code,
how can I actually verify that it is indeed true?
So if you would try to just do plain cargo build with a Rust project, then you'll notice
that actually you get different binaries depending on the system in which you compile your binary.
And so the answer to this is actually to use a produceable builds, which, of course, Nix
gives us a way to do.
So here is an example as well.
So if I just compile it in the Docker container, right, and if I just do it locally, I get
exactly the same binary.
So I get exactly the same digest.
But so how do we actually get here?
It's all, of course, half of the shell.
How do you develop anything without the Nix shell before in your project, right?
And I got positive feedback on this, and, well, we infected the project with Nix.
Just a few months later after that, something very surprising to me happened.
It's one of our first outside contributions was actually an ARX build package.
So I just added a shell with actual build script by Vincent from Germany.
I don't know if you're here, but thank you very much if he's looking at this.
And so by the time we had to ship and release, you know, like a big release of ARX, we already
had all our Linux and Mac binary builds in the Flake.
And we could also build OCI images in the Flake.
I did some changes in the meantime.
So yeah, it just made sense to use Nix for this.
And we quickly discovered that actually building for ARM64 in QM on x86 runners was just too
slow.
So that's why I implemented cross compilation.
It was tricky, but eventually it worked.
But unfortunately it also made all functionality parameterized by the package set and also
made Flakes very difficult to maintain a review, especially for people who are not familiar
with Nix because I was the only Nix guy in the company.
So it complicated things.
And here's an example.
I don't know if you can see, but before it looked like a just normal kind of build script,
you know, like you would, if you, if you did get into packaging or no, Arch Linux packaging,
you would kind of understand what's happening here.
If you just use Rust, it's kind of clear what's happening.
But when you have cross compilation, it gets difficult, right?
You have a linker, you have a CC target prefix, right?
You have, it's not clear, like let in block, there are two different package sets.
So what's even worse is that, well, we had multiple repositories and initially we just
duplicated our Flakes, right?
Because we want to build everything reproducibly as well.
We want to have cross compilation.
We want to have just consistent, you know, CI.
And we basically each Flake was branched off from a different version of the original Flake,
right?
Because we also, we're keeping developing and changing things.
So they start to diverge in some supple ways, but they still largely were doing exactly
the same thing.
And another thing is that because the Flake logs were actually managed independently,
so we could benefit from some CI caching, but we actually couldn't because those potential
hits will actually become a miss.
So and then maintenance just became a burden over time.
So let's just take a step back and think about, okay, what do we actually want to do?
We just want to build some static Rust binaries, just like Cargo does, except it won't do
it reproducibly, right?
We also want to have an OCI image for that binary, and ideally you also want to have
a fast CI, but if you can't, all right, fine.
But we don't really care how any of this is done, right?
All we care about is that if Cargo can do it, we actually be able to do it as well.
It should just add functionality, not remove any functionality.
It doesn't make anything harder for us.
And you could say, right, there are templates in Flakes, right?
You could just write it once and then propagate across repositories and just use that.
But it's not much different from just duplicating the Flake as I did before, right?
You still have to adapt your template for the actual project, and you still have to
maintain it's going to get out of date, and there should be a better way.
So that's why I built a Mixify library.
It's designed to be an easy to use, batteries-included library with opinionated but customizable defaults,
and it just works well in CI.
It doesn't try to cover all use cases, but it should be good enough for most.
It just simply plugs into your existing language tooling and currently supports only Rust by
a crane backend, but it could support other back-ends as well if you want to, and there
is also support for other languages just kind of designed for.
So what does it actually do?
So per each default system, it provides you with a Flake check for listening and testing,
development shell of your tool chain, format of your to-do, nixfumt, and then releasing
debug builds for all targets with cross-compilation and OCI images and whatnot.
Here's an example.
So this is actually just a Rust Hello World application, right?
I have just simply one input, which is Mixify, and I have just outputs generated by this
makeFlake function, and the absolute minimum is just if I have one argument, which is a
source.
So Mixify will parse actually the Rust tool chain, a cargo.toml file if you're unfamiliar
with Rust.
So Rust tool chain defines basically what version of a tool chain I want, what targets
I want to have, and cargo.toml is just basically metadata about the package.
So let's look at the Mixflake shell.
I formatted the output because it just wouldn't fit on the screen, so this is the checks.
So I get my linting, my formatter, the Rust formatter, and the testing on check.
I get also a development shell with my tool chain and all the different systems.
I get nixfumt already predefined, and I also have an overlay with actually the tool chain
and all the packages, so including OCI images.
And finally, that's the packages that are generated.
So I have the native default build.
I have also profiles for release builds and debug builds.
You'll notice that there's no Darwin builds here, because again, I formatted.
On Darwin, you would see also builds for Darwin, but you cannot cross-compile from Linux to
Darwin, but you can do other way around.
So on Darwin, you would see that as well.
In fact, there was an issue with Mixpacker set right now.
There is no, like one of the Darwin was not able to compile for the other one, unless
you can check yourself.
So here's an example of nRx packaging with this tool.
So I can also configure, for example, some paths to ignore to improve caching.
I can configure the Clippy features, whatever I wanted to do there.
So it's pretty small, pretty simple.
I can add some, like for example, OpenSSL in my shell, and yeah, and it works.
And nRx itself is, by the way, anything but a simple project.
So it's using Nightly Rust.
It has seven crates in the workspace.
We actually use bin depth as well, so sometimes we build for three different targets at the
same time, basically the trim and the execution layer, which are merged later in one binary.
So this is what it means to actually build something in CI with this.
So we just simply have a match for all our hosts and targets, and we just simply do nix
build, and this is consistent in the same everywhere.
The only difference would be the name of the package, but again, it could be removed if
I wanted to.
So next we have testing, and we have linting.
It's pretty much exactly the same thing.
Again, it could be a shared GitHub action workflow and just used everywhere.
So how do we actually maintain and update this?
Nixify changes are actually, for us, was propagated automatically, so we used GitHub action to
actually do Nixflake update.
So the changes were already reviewed by me, so I've audited the changes essentially, and
then anyone in the team can actually, well, you can actually see the bottom, but you can
actually review and auto-merge this because the team trusts me.
This actually brings me to a trust question, which is an open question I just wanted to
raise.
So the Nixify state is essentially a root of a miracle tree, right, because it includes
all the dependencies and digests of those.
So I audit the state of the world, so a mixed package set and all the dependencies, so team
trusts me, therefore they trust the world or my audit of it, so it's a transitive trust.
But how can the team actually verify my audit?
So can I sign the Nixify root in any way?
Can I maybe add my signature on this?
So maybe Nix could validate my signature, maybe it could be like a parameter, trust,
only these projects.
So that's just an open question.
If you have answers, please let me know.
So eventually it was time to deploy our services, and for NRXP it requires the amount of three
kernel patches, Intel provided ASMD, PCCS service running, some U-Dev rules for the
hardware.
We had no dedicated operations engineer, and all our repositories were already Nixified,
so we just made, well, we also had two cloud providers, which is AWS, Nix, Linux, both had
Nix-OS support out of the box.
Before we had Nix, we actually used custom OCI images for PCCS and ASMD, and those were
basically just compiled once to some binaries that were put inside the image, and those
images were outdated, largely annotated, no one knew what to do with them.
We required custom provisioning steps, like to do podman secret create or something, and
we also need manual U-Dev rules set up.
So once again, open source come to help, so the PCCS and ASMD were actually turned out
to actually be supported by Nix-OS already.
Also the Intel SGX hardware was supported.
By the way, again, it's either Vincent or one of his team, someone from his team who
actually added this, so again, thank you.
So if we just list, just these six lines were enough for us to just enable the services
and all the hardware support.
So next step was that I just added some simple Nix-OS modules for our services, set up secret
management with soft-set Nix and deployment for deploy-RS, again, like simple tooling,
automate deployments to testing environments.
I set up CI to just test all PRs, so if the CI fails, the PR doesn't go through, so we
don't update anything.
And of course we have the automated updates, just like everywhere else, just for every
other repository.
So to begin with, we actually ended up doing this, so we actually were tracking tags of
different projects.
So you can see there are three groups of, well, these are the services, different environments,
so we just have three different inputs, and essentially we progress, we test things in
staging, then we go to production, right?
If I were to redo this, I would actually use branches, something like Nix package-set channels
where you essentially just do a release, right, then you merge it to, say, unstable, eventually
you test that, you can promote it to stable.
So I think that's more work upstream, but it's easier to, well, maintain downstream,
it just makes sense.
So you could ask, okay, why don't we just use OCI for this, but the thing to understand,
with Nix, we get source code references, not binary references, so essentially we get all
the benefits of binaries without actually sacrificing any usability.
In fact, we will get things, like updates, and the flag.log is nothing else than really
a software-built materials, right, which is the buzzword today, and everyone really cares
about it.
So because in the flag.log, what you get is that you can audit the whole state of the
world, right, you can audit all the service source code, you can audit all the build dependencies,
and you can audit also all the tooling that you used to actually deploy this stuff, right,
and you have a consistent, simple update procedure, which is Nix flag update, it's super fast
to deploy once you have your module set up and you know how to use Nix, it's just, boom,
you're just there, and of course you get rollbacks with Nix OS or really any deployment tool
that's used Nix.
So next step was actually providing things like AMIs and whatever else, so I used just
Nix OS generators for it, and the way I did it, I just simply imported the Nix OS module,
like a common module from our infrastructure, and it took me less than a day to set up,
and this is for SGX and AMD, SCV, again, it's extremely powerful and just extremely simple
to use.
I do have to mention that we asked ourselves a question, okay, so how many enterprises
would actually use Nix OS to deploy NARX, that was probably not so many, so once we
actually got a dedicated operations engineer, we eventually moved most of our services to
Kubernetes, but there was a little win, because for every service that actually required custom
kernel, custom services, custom U-dev rules, those things are difficult to set up, and
those actually were kept in Nix OS, which brings me to my next point, that Nix and Nix
OS actually, in my opinion at least, make difficult things simple, right, and in this
case for me it was great for prototyping, it was great for productivity, for composability,
for building literally anything anywhere, and for audibility and trust.
One particular thing I want to mention about productivity here is, like if you ask me one
killer feature of Nix, at least from my perspective, this is that, right, so we had for example
lab machines with SGX and AMD, SCV hardware, and I did it countless times when I was just
developing something as a feature branch, and I just needed to test it out, I just SSH,
I do Nix run, GitHub colon, you know, my repository, my branch, and I just run it, I don't need
to use Git to add a new remote, I don't need to set up my toolchain, nothing, I can just
SSH and run it, so I think that's really powerful.
So another thing is that if you introduce Nix, of course it's also your responsibility
to T-shirt, right, so you are the FM in RTFM, right, so for my case I had the Nix 101 classes
on Fridays, and the real uncommon thing about Nix, I think, to people, is the functional
programming part, so I ended up teaching a lot of functional programming principles to
actually explain Nix, and also just introducing teams to the ecosystem, because, well, if
you just newcomer to Nix, it may be overwhelming, it's not clear why there's Nix, a Nix package
set, a Nix device, how they're related, and I also created a Nix channel for questions,
so whenever people had questions I would just answer them.
So some derivations from this, it's really important to give people examples of how to
get things done, like real examples, and it's very great also to give analogies with known
technologies, and, okay, so this is not exactly what you would do in Nix, but I implemented
Fibonacci in Nix and in Rust, right, you have to just show them two side by side, right,
I have a main function here in Nix, I have a main function over here, both of which are
in both print Fibonacci examples, right, so it just works, you don't see but up here the
same, and yeah, so this kind of is an example of how you can show the people that, you know,
it's not so scary after all, right, it's just the same function, just look at it, right,
it's the same thing.
So one thing I noticed also that Nix is perceived as being pretty novel, so I asked people the
question like, okay, so how long do you think Nix exists, and I got answers all the way
from two to ten years, where ten was like a real stretch, you know, it can't be so long,
but the real answer is 20 years, if you look at the Git log, right, I don't know, maybe
it was not developed before, maybe it was earlier, but that's what I see from the Git
log.
Some frequently asked questions they've received is, okay, I'm not on Nix OS, how do I use
Nix?
Or I'm trying to use the flakes, but I get an error, and why are flakes experimental?
It is safe to depend on some other features, what if I get abandoned?
Where is our shell?
So a few things we can note here that, at least in my experience, Nix is tightly associated
with Nix OS, but we need to understand, or at least explain to newcomers, I believe,
that Nix is not just another package manager, right, so Nix OS is just one possible output
for Nix build, but it's just that, right, it can build many other things, and I think
we should present it as a generic build tool, which is not tied to a particular OS, and
sometimes for people familiar with Docker, I even presented something like Docker or
Podman, where you basically have a Docker file, you can build a Docker file, it's put
in your store, and you can run it afterwards, right, it's something like that, maybe.
So yeah, this thing was such a pain.
So come on, guys, we need to do something about this, right?
I mean, you hear about this Nix thing, it's so cool, but it's so difficult, so out there,
and your very first try in Nix is a failure, right, I understand that this error is descriptive,
yes, you read this, you kind of understand what to do, mostly, but it's just not a good
developer experience, right, and I think we should, I don't know, I don't know what to
do, there are possible solutions, but we really need to do something about this as a community.
So thank you, this, you can...
Yeah, as I said, profing close, I'm looking for a job, by the way, but yeah, any questions,
maybe?
Yeah, go ahead.
So you say Nix can basically be a generic build system, like the Nix or the Post
Connect, and there are any examples, like if you have a C project, Nix or the other,
then it's wrong.
Right, so the question is, can Nix be a generic build system like Maison, or you know, Autotools,
whatever, so I'm not a C developer, I've never was, I believe so, I believe you will be able
to do, at least for Rust, it was a breeze to do, I can definitely imagine doing that
for Go as well, and I think that was pretty, so for example, I compile, so we had a collection
of examples where we mostly compiled to Wazi, so for C it was actually very, very simple,
so I would think so.
The only thing to care, to think about though, so it's great for releases, not so great for
development because, for example, with Rust, you have this target directory with all your
cache, so you don't get that anymore, right?
Or, I mean, you have to, you can do things around it, you can maybe build some library
to actually achieve that.
Maybe you can do it and contribute.
If I may add about this, there is some RFC on how you can enable things to become, make
replacements, but there are much more things which are a bit complicated on how you make
it fast.
So, yeah, that is what he's looking for, I would say.
Okay, I'll check it out, thanks, I don't know that.
Thank you.