Please get another round of applause for the next speaker of the day.
Awesome. Thank you. So my voice was destroyed yesterday in the pub.
So everyone has to be very quiet.
Awesome. Good job. Okay.
Awesome. Awesome surprise with the secure demo.
Super awesome. I did not know about it.
Yeah. We'll talk about secure boot on Nixos.
So this was a team effort by
this fine gentleman and the other one over there,
who were happily coding while we were sitting on a boat while I was enjoying life.
All of this happened mostly at the ocean sprint in Lancer Roto,
which was also epic event for getting stuff done in the Nix world.
I can totally recommend going there.
Yeah. So secure boot.
I thought I introduced the shortest possible introduction to it that I can make.
Then we go on what is this Lancer boot thing and what status is it and how can you contribute?
But what's secure boot?
So what's the problem?
So imagine you're here at Fostem,
your laptop is encrypted.
Then you go out to the pub where you scream too loud and you can't talk afterwards.
While that is going on,
your laptop sits in your hotel room alone,
minding its own business and then many hours later,
you come back and type your passwords in there.
So is this still the software you think it is on your laptop?
Without secure boot, you don't really know.
So secure boot is one solution to this.
It's not a complete solution,
but it mitigates some of it.
The way it works in a very tiny nutshell is that
your UEFI firmware just verifies what it's booting.
So it just takes the bootloader,
checks the cryptographic signature on it,
and then the bootloader has then to look at operating system,
it boots and also check a cryptographic signature on it.
So you have like a chain of trust from your firmware all the way to your operating system.
If this all works, then someone else can't easily replace the operating system.
It's something that your laptop doesn't trust.
Now, the question is, okay,
it verifies cryptographic signatures with what?
Typically, if you buy a laptop,
it will trust the Microsoft CA and some OEM CA.
This is fine for Windows obviously,
and it's also fine for some of the other big distro.
So you can take Ubuntu and it works on a secure boot laptop.
You can take Fedora, it just works.
Unfortunately, for NixOS, it does not.
So what's the issue with secure boot and NixOS?
I think fundamentally, it's a very different model from other Linux distributions.
There is like a thing that centrally builds packets and you can download it from somewhere,
but it's mostly a build cache and you don't have to use it.
You can build all of this locally.
So and also, it's so configurable.
So it's very easy to end up with an init rd that is not cached,
or with a kernel that's not cached on cache.nixos,
and then you will obviously not get signed binaries even if
cache.nixos would sign them which it does not for secure boot.
So for now, we're targeting your own CA.
So you can just say, fuck it,
I will enroll my own keys to the firmware.
This is scary. It also looks scary if you do it,
but it works reasonably well.
But then comes the question every time I change the software on my laptop,
I just have to manually sign it and that sucks.
No one wants to do it.
So now we come to what is this Lancer boot thing actually.
This is actually the tooling that makes all of this convenient for NixOS.
So Lancer boot takes care of automatically resigning your system,
the boot, your kernel whenever you do a NixOS rebuild.
This is a one-line description of it.
It does not take care of generating keys initially,
it does not take care of enrolling them in the firmware.
This is something the user has to do once right now.
We have quick start documentation for that.
So I've heard that it has worked for other people.
Dooben has secure boot on his laptop.
Not bad. I have also heard that it did not work for other people.
But so far, I think the likelihood of trashing your system with it has been very low.
NixOS was very busy fixing the onboarding device.
Yeah. All of this revolves around unified kernel images.
This is a pretty recent technology out of the system,
the sphere.
A unified kernel image is a normal UFIPE file that can
just be booted by the firmware with some extra bits.
So it's basically a tiny archive of Linux kernel,
the Linux kernel's command line and the end RDE,
and then also container in some meta information.
So there's an OS release file in there,
and it has the name of this thing, the version.
This is basically used to generate the entry in the menu
when you select what to boot in system de-boot.
Then because it's all self-contained,
you just sign this one thing and you're good with secure boot.
Yeah. SVC grub support is nearing completion.
Also, Ryan keeps telling me that Linux support is also planned.
But so far, system de-boot is the thing to go.
Now, there's a PE stub.
So to form a unified kernel image,
you have to stub on some PE binary at the front.
There's one from system de-root called system de-stub.
It basically does exactly what I just told you.
So you have the stub at the front,
then the command line, the kernel,
init RDE and OS release which I ignored on this picture.
It works. The problem for NixOS is that
this kernel command line basically contains
a store path that changes for every NixOS generation.
So whenever you do NixOS rebuild,
if you experiment with your system a bit,
you will have a new one of these files in your slash boot directory.
This is problematic because you also have to kernel it in this one blob.
At least for me, they're around 40 megabytes.
The typical system partition,
the slash boot thing is like half a gigabyte.
I've seen NixOS systems with many generations.
I pointed you.
So in running out of space in your boot partitions,
very uncomfortable.
So that's why we wrote the Lancer boot stub.
It does the same as the system de-stub,
just that you don't have to embed the file,
the content of kernel and init RDE anymore.
You just embed a path to the file and the cryptographic hash to it.
So basically, just point somewhere and say what you expect to be at that location.
So then on the boot partition,
you also have these files and then you're good.
So the stub will get the file name,
load the file, check the hash,
and if everything works out,
it gets booted and since the hashes are assigned,
this is as secure as before.
Now, the nice thing is that this stub is now only like 100 kilobytes in size,
and you can have another one that has a different command line,
but may use the same kernel and same init RDE and for this new generation,
you just get another 100 kilobytes instead of 40 megabytes.
Now, Ryan can have his 600 generations.
Again, it is put folder.
Yeah. So obviously, maintaining our own stub is not something that we enjoy too much.
So there are discussions ongoing in the system D bug tracker
to upstream dysfunctionality that you can
just reference files on the boot partition instead of embedding them in the system D stub.
Then system D stub would just supersede
the Lancer-Botor stub and everyone is happy.
You know, the other, I said.
Awesome. The German is strong.
Yeah. So this is like the boot part of the whole secure boot tool chain,
but then there's also like the Nix part of it.
Big thing is the Lancer-Botor tool.
This is what is being called when you call Nixo as
rebuild and what it basically does is it takes
all the different generations you have in your NixoS
and assembles the Lancer-Botor stubs and prepares the boot partition and signs everything.
This is pretty involved due to non-reproducibility of kernels.
So it's a bit tricky at times and we had some issues with that.
But I think we're basically down to some polishing at this point to get this right.
Yeah. So we also depend on the boot spec RFC,
which is at the moment an experimental feature in Nix packages,
in NixoS where for each generation you get a nice JSON file describing which kernel,
which init RDE you want to boot and then the bootloader tooling can just take
the JSON and do whatever it needs to do.
So this has been also pretty nice.
Yeah. How to use this?
As I said, you have to do some manual step to onboard.
Yeah, we've tried to document them as user-friendly as possible given the topic.
If you are expected to be able to use NixoS,
you are expected to be able to restore your system from a backup if everything goes wrong.
But other than that,
you should be able to set this up if you want to.
Of course, if you want this to be an actual security feature,
then you may want to come back later.
But if you really, really want to use it as a security feature,
you definitely need a BIOS password,
otherwise someone can just turn secure would often.
Then you also need full disk encryption because otherwise,
someone can just read the private keys from your disk.
Yeah. But that being said,
when it all works,
it's not much more than SPC to create keys,
enrolling them after going to the BIOS menu and some very benign Nix configuration.
NixoS configuration. Yeah, that's it.
So I didn't want to go into too much technical things.
You can ask me about stuff.
Otherwise, you can use it today.
So I have this running.
So if I type device security,
then you don't see anything,
then I have to exit this.
You see that for me,
secure boot is active.
Yeah. As far as collaboration goes,
I have to find the button again.
The discussion mostly happens on the GitHub repository.
Open issues, we respond reasonably fast.
We're currently in the process of fixing all the bugs.
I think when we're bug-free,
we will just call it 1.0 and then afterwards,
there's like a million features that people want and they will all be very cool.
But bugs needs to be fixed first.
We discussed on matrix in the secure boot channel.
There are a couple of other matrix.
There are too many security related matrix channels.
You just join all of them and then it's fine.
There's one about boots back then,
there's one about NixoS and TPMs that I forgot to put on the slide.
Rust OS stuff has been helpful for the Rust UEFI development.
There's a very nice community over there for Rust UEFI programming.
You can also just ping me personally on matrix or on Mastodon.
You should also not be hard to find my Twitter handle somewhere.
That's it. I'm happy to take questions.
So many.
So what I personally find very nice is unlock.
Well, yeah, sorry.
The question was whether I can speculate on the cool features that are about to come.
Personally, I find all the TPM stuff very exciting.
The problem is mostly that the tooling is completely horrific and all the documentation
and terminology is like it's annoying on purpose.
So I'm really eager to make this usable for people
that don't want to know all the details about TPMs.
So for example, you want your disk encryption to be
unlocked if your system has not been tampered with.
This is like a, I mean,
not tampered with is complicated thing to define.
So and the usability aspects are hard,
but this is something I would really want.
So if my laptop is in good condition and my TPM believes everything is good,
then I don't want to type in my password again.
Yeah, then the whole.
Next question.
Yeah, yeah. Okay. Yeah.
There was a question here.
Yeah.
Have you tested this call boot also?
The question is whether we have tested it with core boot.
No, if you deploy core boot with a UFI payload,
it should just work.
I mean, it worked for buggy with limitations.
It worked for good.
Sorry, sir.
Not necessarily.
I don't want to hear that story now.
We are complaining to I think.
So the independent buyers vendors,
which implement UFI for most of the platforms actually implement buggy.
Please come to the issue tracker.
So if you use the Tiana core EDK2 on core boot,
it should work because this is also what we use in QMU for testing.
So another question.
Yeah. I mean, do you have a person as you?
I had a different question.
Okay. The person.
Yeah.
Could you use this with an encrypted disk?
But to verify it all next door and only the state of things in a separate.
So using it without an encrypted disk.
So first issue, if you don't put a private key on it and do
assigning some way somehow else, which we don't support right now,
you could at least avoid this problem.
But then there's the issue.
If you don't have integrity protection for your disk,
someone can just replace whatever is on your disk and put some other kernel.
You could use the MBRT for that.
But I'm not sure like the threat model makes sense overall.
It's hard to check.
So the thing is, so secure boot is like one aspect of a secure system.
Whenever we start to talk about it,
someone comes and wants a whole flower bouquet.
So what you say is definitely possible,
but somewhat out of scope for the secure boot effort.
We don't have any time for question anymore.
Okay. The next people also come up.
Thanks.