Okay, please welcome our next speaker Ivan to talk about contracts for free.
Hi everyone, it's a really quick talk about the Akitoi project and some unpopular opinion
about using runtime types.
So the thing is there is an old issue, maybe you know it in Nix which was closed since
because it will never be implemented, which is a bit embarrassing about the fact that
Nix have no any static type system.
The thing is I changed my mindset relatively recently about that, but I will talk about
it later because what's the issue about the type system?
It's the lack of a static type system, it's the error you get, you get them at the last
moment it's really inconsistent regarding where the mistake were made and when you read
your stack trace you get hard time to find where else the actual error and that is really
not helpless for example beginners trying to work on Nix expression or people trying
to debug Nix expression right then by other person.
So I changed my mindset because Nix is a really simple language and it should be a simple
language and it invites us to build construct in library space and if you look at Nix built-ins
for example, it's really few built-ins and a lot of things that could be built-ins are
actually implemented as Nix package libsing and there is a Nix package libtypes maybe
without a nest which is what you use when you define Nix option to say the option could
be that or that and everything.
And so I changed my mindset because Nix is made in two steps, you know, so it's the first
step that you evaluate the language and produce things in Nix, you symbolize Nix store and
after you build, you made your package but the instantiate part is guaranteed to terminate.
You know you will, the computation will always terminate which is what you expect for type
system actually and which is not the case of some type system or most of macro systems
that are not expected to terminate so actually it's a good guarantee and that's why we could
do a lot of things in Nix.
You can see it as, I changed my mind because I see that Nix is not really about the runtime
and programming language so we could do a check at runtime and I wrote a thing while
vacation and realized later that Ozerforsch already did it which is touched him, maybe
you know him, he worked on Twix right now and he also writes Nix one pager, one of the
best Nix starting guide at some point and the thing is it's really simple, you define
the data you want, just validator function so you say I want something like that and
you check at this point of your Nix expression what it evaluates, that's its respect to a
contract or validator function and that's help actually there to fail early where you
want it to fail and there is differences in implementation I will not talk really about
but I really simply by wrote didn't rely on Nix package and it's fully compatible with
Nix so you can define a thing and share them and the last thing is those compose, I go
back inside, you can define types, you can define validator, instruct, that became validator
and you can compose really complex things because it's really expressive and also the
nice things with runtime types is you can produce recoverable error which does the case
for type servers that exist in Nix itself so for example this will be unrecoverable
but if you use the runtime type you will recover this situation.
Last thing is I try to advertise this kind of technique because it helps a lot to debug
your application and to have assertion about this respect that and everything it doesn't
really solve the problem because it's not a real type system actually but if you're
not starting something from scratch if you are working on an existing Nix expression
Nix expression could be actually really large I think personally it helps if you're starting
and using from scratch there's really cool things that Q, Dal, Nikhael generate JSON
and you use that live in Nix package so you can use it really easily and there is also
I like personally ProNix because it generates Nix outputs rather than JSON.
Okay I think I said most of what I would say so don't hesitate if you have a question or
I want to share your opinion.