Thank you.
There's too many people there.
I wasn't ready for that.
If they told me I would have finished my slice sooner.
So yeah, thank you everyone for being there.
It's really energizing to see so many people interested in Nix, NixOS.
So I work at a company called Twig.
My name is Guillaume.
We love Nix, Twig.
If you don't know about us,
check out our blog, we have.
So it's okay.
So while my job as work is more data,
science, and just software in general,
I'm a Nix enthusiast.
I started three years ago,
could not stop since then.
My rabbit hole was just managing CUDA basically.
As a Nix enthusiast,
I have one thing I can't stop thinking about,
which is I want everyone to use Nix.
I want you to use Nix,
I want you to use Nix, I want.
So before I start,
does anyone not use Nix on a daily basis here?
Okay. So I want you to use Nix.
I want you to. Okay. So,
and to the other people in the room,
guys, what are you doing?
There's two people not using Nix.
So as you might know,
I want to be able to make anyone use Nix.
But there is a but.
In the sentence, we have both.
Anyone?
Nix.
In the same sentence.
Ideally, this is what the combination of
these words should mean.
Nix users know better.
So Nix is not an easy tool to use.
In order to be completely autonomous with Nix and NixOS,
you need a vast amount of knowledge to model your way.
Through all kinds of problems
and before you get anything to run properly.
However, I am a believer.
I think we can, in fact,
not have this but reach
this wonderful world where everyone can use it.
So let me tell you a story that happened
in a company that I might have heard about.
So in this company, we have Emma.
Say hello to Emma. Thank you.
The company didn't expect people to actually reply to that.
I'm delighted that you are. Thank you.
I feel less lonely there.
The company being rather small,
she has to handle all HR by herself because she's the HR.
So she manages the employees contract as any HR would.
It turns out that even though the company is small,
she has processed a lot of contracts.
I mean really a lot.
Oops. I spent too much time on this animation.
Not too good to let it go to waste. Sorry.
So she has been using a software for quite some time.
You might recognize the logo.
To process demo and it has been going fine.
But someday, a task come to her so huge is stupid.
We all know this kind of stupid task.
Let's say for instance that she has to go through
all the contracts and find
all the employees that had some specific terms.
She now has to spend hours and hours and days going
through all each one contract reading,
looking for the terms etc etc.
It's boring. It is repetitive.
If only there was a way to do it without doing it manually.
As she's starting to drown in her own despair,
suddenly appears in her slack.
Someone who says, I think I can be of help.
It's an engineer, she says.
Little does she know that it's not just an engineer.
Anyway, our hero knows that she uses a SAS to process
the contract and a SAS often has an API.
So it can be automated.
So he says, I can do it in minutes.
Is he a spy? He puts in his hacking gloves,
starts typing fursuously and am I is no.
He says, give me access to your account and I will get
the data on my machine and I will
proceed it for you and I will pass it to you.
But then Emma looks at him in fear.
It's forbidden by law.
Indeed, we now have to face a terrible foe.
GDPR. You should not have access to this data or will be in trouble.
There were these close to solving the problem.
But our hero knows that it ain't easy to run
a custom script on Novice computer.
You would have to grow through many challenges.
Making someone use a terminal,
installing dependencies,
sending the code and most of it all fixing it
because it never works on the first trial.
So if only there was a simple way to run
a program on someone computer without such hassle.
If only there was.
But fortunately for us, there's Nix.
A single flat road for the user. So step one, install Nix.
Step two, give her one liner to run a program.
Actually, this one. First one, you got the joke.
But it's beautiful and as you can imagine,
this is sort of a true story.
There really was an HR,
there really was a company and I can say it out loud,
I got HR to use Nix.
The command I just put you.
Yeah, I really do consider it an achievement.
I put it in my tiles.
If only it could be displayed over my head.
So when I submitted my talk,
I put the subtitle and you've seen it on
the first slide, it will be fine.
When I wrote it a month ago,
it was supposed to be sarcastic, ironic,
but I was supposed to roast Nix.
I'm in a toxic relationship as you can see.
But when I thought about this one story,
I realized that in fact,
it did work and that was what was incredible at the time.
I was just writing a script,
a Python script in five and shipping Python,
I've done it to some other people for the same reason,
like privacy and it's always nightmare
because people really wanted to work on
the machine and you can't touch it and stuff like that.
So this illustrates why I love Nix.
It just works.
Machines are capricious,
but Nix makes like a highway for us to make things run on them.
It pays the way for software to not just work on my machine,
but on any machine and I think this is
what makes Nix have such an impact.
If Nix can just do that,
it's already quite enough.
Is it sometimes a pain to write packages,
to have to debug them because you're
using a recursive function that at the end doesn't work and
you have really not the good error message?
Yes, sure, it is a pain to use.
But at the end of the day,
if it's the only way we have to do what I just did,
then isn't it worth it? Do you know it?
So my final word would be to all Nixers here,
let's not make other people use Nix because it's cool tech.
Let's make it because it makes someone else life cooler. Thank you.
Thank you.
So I have my minutes left.
It was just a silly story to get you to breathe a bit between
the interesting parts but if you have any questions.
We do have questions.
In which company does HJr not use Windows?
So the question is,
in which company does HJr not use Windows?
Which is a great tricky question that I did on purpose to,
yeah, it was on my quest as you could have seen.
It was for some companies I guess.
Yeah? Yeah?
Do you use Windows?
Sorry?
I see you use Windows.
I'm sorry. So the question is,
why do I use Windows because I can run NixOS on it anyway?
Some software just don't work yet.
If you can make Ableton work on NixOS, I'm taking it.
Still questions, how many minutes left? Yeah?
We have a few HJr to run Nix to run your script.
So why don't you for example use Nix to build an OCI image
and run for a proper container?
That's a very good question.
This is, sorry?
Oh yeah. So the question is, sorry.
Why didn't I just build a Docker image basically to run it?
This is what I did a few years ago when I had to
ship Python and it turns out that Docker was a pain
to use on someone's computer because there are too many buttons.
Docker desktop to get running on someone's machine that just
don't know or want to know how Docker works.
Sometimes just like you have to turn it on,
you have to wait for it to,
it's too complex to hear it in this situation.
Or you can argue against that but in my case it turns out to be.
I wanted to use Nix to be fair.
A lot of problem statement,
you said that you need to teach the HR person command line,
package manager, app N and then execute the script.
Now, Nix kind of solved three of those things,
you still need the command line.
Yeah.
Yes. Yeah.
So, so the question is,
I'm sorry I just can't get that in my head.
Thank you. So the question is,
so yeah, I said there were different parts of the problem to
solve like installing dependencies and moving the scripts
and getting people to use the command line to run the script etc.
So, but there's still the fact that we need to use the terminal.
I bypass that by giving things just to copy and paste.
Basically.
Then terminal on Mac isn't that hard to find actually.
It wasn't the hardest part.
The hardest parts were getting the API key from the SaaS.
Because you have to make people click through the UI of the SaaS.
Yeah. I think that's about it.
Thank you everyone.