Thank you.
Hello.
I hope you can hear me online.
Well, if not, complain on chat.
Okay, so we are going to talk about...
Nodr?
You can really yell, that's fine.
Okay.
We are going to talk about HPC, high-performance computing, and Nix, and how we kind of deal
with that.
My name is Rodrigo and my co-worker Raul here.
First, a bit of what we do.
Essentially, we work on a parallel concurrent task-based runtime, like similar to OpenMP,
if you are familiar.
We also need to work with a compiler based on LBM to read this pragmas in the code and
transfer them to function calls to the runtime.
In our job performance is critical, so we really need to take care.
And in general, we execute the workloads on several hundreds or even thousands of CPUs.
Here's a little example of something that we have observed.
We have a program here that runs...
And here you can see these are the CPUs, and this is the time of execution.
And we are examining this little point here, because the time here is slightly bigger than
what is normal.
And we can see that the problem is that the allocator took a bit longer.
So this is just an example.
In general, in HPC or this high-performance computing, it's just a lot of machines connected
by fiber optic.
They are managed by this SLUR diamond, which allows you to request a certain number of
nodes.
We don't have fruit in any node.
In general, it's very old kernels and very old software stack.
So yeah, we are stuck with that.
And in general, the state of the art now is to use LD library path to load all the software
and change versions.
Working with this technique is not very easy to reproduce.
So the question is, can we benefit from using Nix?
In general, we will get up-to-date packages, configuration options for every package, no
more LD library path.
And we can track everything that we use for an experiment.
The problem is we don't have fruit.
So we cannot install the Nix diamond, as we would like to do.
So let's take a closer look at what we do on how we do it.
In general, we work in these three hats, so to say.
In the development side, we take a program and we compile it several times until it actually
compiles.
We kind of need to do this cycle quickly.
So we want the compilation time to be very low.
So we need to reuse the already built tree to run the build command.
When we are finished, we switch to the experimentation side and we run this program in the machine.
And maybe we need to tickle with the arguments or the configuration file of the program to
get some results that we want to examine.
And then we also do some visualization of the results, but we are not going to talk
in this talk about this.
So we will focus first on the experimentation later in the development side.
So a bit of what we did.
We tried with individual installation of the Nix store by using user namespaces.
The problem is that the number of packages grows, so we would like to share the store
with several users.
So we use an auxiliary machine where we actually have a Nix demo and then we can perform the
build in that machine and then use the post-build hook to execute some script that copies the
output derivation to the actual cluster.
Problem is inside the cluster, Nix store doesn't work.
So we wrap the command Nix store in a shell script.
And when it's invoked by the auxiliary machine, it creates the namespace where it mounts the
Nix store there and then it runs the Nix store and receives the derivation so we can actually
copy it over SSH.
We also tried to patch the Nix diamond to run inside the machine, but it's a bit complicated
because we cannot even run a user diamond there.
Okay, so let's focus on the experimentation cycle.
The first requirement, the most important thing, well, assuming that you already have
like a program that somehow you built in a sandbox, we want to execute this program in
the machine and we want to make sure that this program doesn't load anything that is
outside the Nix store.
So especially the LD library path may have some path that actually has libraries for
your program, so we don't want that.
And also it may use the deal open to load other libraries.
So ideally we want something like the Nix boot with a sandbox that prevents accesses
to slash user or a slash opt-in.
And it needs to work in a store too.
Another requirement that we need is for MPI, the communication mechanism, to use this syscall
process VM read by that only works if the process are inside the same namespace.
So we solve this by running a check that checks if the namespace is already created and if
it is so, we enter it, otherwise we create another one.
So let's take an overview of how this works in the cluster.
We have here the login node and two compute nodes that were given to us for running our
program.
In general we have to wait a bit after requesting the nodes, it's fine.
After this moment we take a shell that is connected to one of the allocated nodes.
These are the nodes and each node in your case has two sockets.
So we usually run one process per socket.
And we talk to one of them only.
Inside this process we don't have Nix.
So we first load this namespace by using our script.
And then we can run other programs like S run, which is the client that will launch the
work load but is inside the Nix store.
So we can compile programs linked to this specific version of Nix, of a Slurm, sorry.
After that it requests the Slurm diamond to execute something in parallel and the Slurm
diamond forks in every process, one process that will run something, but it's outside
the namespace because it's not controlled by us.
So we execute our script again to join the namespace if it's found.
Otherwise we create another one, like in the second compute node.
And here we can see that we can communicate in the same node because they are both in
the same namespace and they're one too.
And here we use private optic communications.
Another requirement that we need is that we need custom packages.
We use that with this technique where we define a call package function that takes priority
over all attributes set.
So we can change software that is provided in upstream with Nix package S and we use
our best and first.
So we can hack on those without disturbing the whole package set.
Another thing that we need is to define package with compilers.
In general we use LBM with custom runtime.
So we use the RAPCC with and inject this little environment bar so we can load our runtime
without needing to recompile the compiler.
We also need, unfortunately, proprietary compilers and we use this RPM extract and the auto patch
of hook to fix the header so we can run them on Nix 2 and compile derivation for them.
Okay.
So, all right.
Okay, let's move on to the development cycle.
In general the development process consists in getting an application, adding some new
and confused to it, making things, testing and testing that is okay.
And this interactive workflow requires frequent changes in the source and compilation steps.
For this reason Nix build is not good to work with because every change in the source will
trigger a full copy of the source to the Nix store and a full compilation.
With big repositories this is a problem because, for example, in the slide we can see the time
about how much time it takes to build LLVM in a 32 core machine we have referring so
it's a big machine.
And we can see that although we use C-Cats we talk about different orders or magnitude
comparing it with simply reducing the previous build.
Another alternative could be using Nixl to get our tools to build the application but
this environment is not isolated from the system.
And we can find software that includes hard code paths directly to the system, like in
this case with a sigma module file of ROKEM that is CUDA for AMD for those who don't know
what is it.
And if we take an application that uses ROKEM and configure it and check the local output
we can see that at the end the installation selected is the system one instead of the
Nix packets we want to.
An insulated environment will prevent us from this situation avoiding the necessity of patching
the source to solve this problem.
Our solution for these two requirements is to first build an insulated environment with
a tool we named NixRAP.
NixRAP is a script that uses bubble wrap to enter a user name space where the Nix store
is available but not the system directories like in this case a slash user.
And in this environment we can launch our Nix tools like for example Nix build.
And this works because inside the name space Nix build creates a new sandbox in a nested
name space so the environment is not affected.
And the most powerful feature of it is running Nix Shell inside this isolated environment
to get your tools to build your application in an isolated environment so you don't have
to worry about accessing to the system.
And in this case is the previous example LLVM and reusing the build.
And finally if you are using us like us as Loom you can execute your application by running
NixRAP after the Loom step-forward process and your application.
Another requirement for us is since we are in an HPC environment we want to get the best
performance of the applications and for this reason we need to build the critical performance
software with CPU optimization flags.
Our solution for this situation is to override the compiler wrapper injected flags by overriding
the host platform attribute specifying the architecture and other stuff to the compiler
in a standard environment in NixRAP.
And finally we create the standard environment we will use to build our software with this
compiler wrapper.
I will talk about the conclusions.
In general we can actually benefit from using Nix but obviously we have some drawbacks.
Many cycles that I was talking about we can still do it very fast so it's very nice for
us.
And also if we have the chance to get something like a Nix demo we thought the root requirement
and still be able to share the Nix store that would be awesome.
Thank you very much.
We have five minutes left for questions.
If there are questions.
When I was working in the HPC environment there was always an issue with disk space.
How does it work with a dynamic Nix store where people could just say don't know anything
in the Nix store?
So the question is how can we manage to Nix store where users can install if that can
be an issue for this space?
So in general right now we have about 300 gigabytes of storage.
For our particular group we have around 2-3,000 gigabytes of space available.
In general in HPC people used to use a lot of space but if we share the store that will
be the best solution instead of every user to have their own installation.
And we also when we kind of annoy someone that says to us please use less space we run
their garbage collector.
Thank you.
Yeah.
So you said that the state of the art was people using L.D. library path on the machines.
But I guess that was interesting.
Did you consider using or can Nix use R-Path instead of using R-Path?
Because that would get rid of your problems there.
That and then the other thing you can do is there's a talk in the HPC department about
pre-binding the pass to S-O.
Okay.
I see your spec t-shirt from here.
Okay so question is about using R-Path?
R-Path, yeah.
Because I mean it takes precedence over L.D. library path.
You don't have to worry about the user being stupid.
Yeah.
So the problem is that you can see programs using D.L. Open to load their own.
They don't.
Sorry.
D.L. Open respects R-Path.
Yeah.
Ah.
Okay.
This is another.
We're doing something to be okay.
So.
Unless you can do like a new bind with a different namespace for D.L. Open that won't respect
that.
But most of them are not doing that.
Okay.
So D.L. Open is not only the only problem because we also see software trying to read
it C slash configuration file somewhere and we also want to prevent that.
In general we saw that it's safer to avoid the program from accessing any path than trying
to find every single option that the program can use to.
Okay.
There was still one eager question.
Can we find the next rapid script online?
Yeah I will I think I will upload it to the post on page.
Any other question.
Not so much of a question but a bit of a shameless plug.
The main blocker for having a rootless next demand was merged last week or the week before.
So hopefully that's going to eventually solve the third of your points.
Perfect.
Thank you.
So what about into your libraries on the system?
Are you only envisioning that you would install the library things like MBI through this because
that's not possible on some agencies.
Yeah it's a very good question.
For now we have been very lucky to be able to work with only proprietary packages that
can be put inside Nix.
But it may happen that the proprietary something it doesn't work.
So we don't have a solution for now.
One more.
Thank you.
Just switch it over again.