How many of you have used the two boxes?
Those two are two half boxes because the other half is in, you know, in Havana there.
But I guarantee those are two boxes.
So one for the networking and one for the computing.
I bought it years ago on eBay.
I think some startups run out of business and they had like many full-size rack full of nooks
and, you know, Nvidia boards.
So I bought one and I started to play with it.
So now I have ten nooks lying around at home, five GPU and I don't know what to do with them.
So this is how everything started.
So I have a single point of failure and all the SREs and DevOps here, you know, will hate it.
But it's my single point of failure and I love it.
And I call it Snowflake because it's unique.
And what it does, it does a very minimal setup.
It's the only long-living server or nooks, if I can call it server.
I will call it server.
So it's my only long-living server I have.
And it runs a DHCP server.
It runs Pixiboot, a TCP server and is the core of my home lab.
It runs there and it distributes the, you know, the Nix OS derivation that I want to netboot
on the other servers when I hook them to the network.
As you know, because you are here and you are like me, I tend to automate everything I can.
So as I said, this is the code that I wrote in the Nix OS derivation for the Snowflake server.
I start OpenSSH, I configure my keys.
I didn't, you know, paste that, the public key there because it was too long and not great,
but you know how to do it.
And I start PixiCore and I configure it with a package called Blackhole that is the distribution
I use for net booting.
And I'm going to, you know, get to net booting later on.
I have my.5 shared with the Nix OS configuration, so you can check that if you want.
So what is, my Snowflake server is used to do Pixibooting and NetBooting,
to distribute the images I want on my female labs.
And PixiCore is a tool that helps with that.
It can be used standalone, is a Go project that you run.
It expose a DHCP server, a proxy, an HTTP server to download the, you know,
the kernel and the initram disk.
And then this is Blackhole.
So Blackhole is the, when you do net booting, you need an operating system
to run on the new servers.
And I generate that from an Nix OS derivation.
It's also very lightweight because it says in RAM, so it's not persistent on disk,
so it needs to be as small as it can be.
So I use the net boot based profile and I change to minimal,
but I didn't update my slides.
So if the image is too big, you can use the installer minimal that is a bit smaller.
And then I install OpenSSH because this is what I use to enter into the server when it boots.
But what is net booting?
So from zero to zero in one minute because that's how good I am with Nix booting.
And so every server or many computers boots and they look for, you know,
an operating system on disk.
And if there is not an operating system on disk, they look for a USB one.
And if there is not a USB, the world becomes way bigger and they try to send a DHCP request
to the DHCP server, says, oh, I'm alive. What can I do?
And if you have a smart enough DHCP server, it replies with a package containing the IP address
for the server and then an address that can be used to download an init RAM disk
and a kernel and boot the server.
So this is, you know, very old style, but still in use.
You know, all the cloud providers that I had the opportunity to work with use this
because hardware doesn't change that quickly.
So, pixi booting is still there and this is the same things I use.
So I download the two binaries and the two packages and my server is ready to boot.
So for me, I take the compute modules out from my boxes, I hook it to the network
and they power on DHCP, kernel and I'm ready to SSH.
This is kind of the log you get from pixi core when it detects like a new server
ready to handle an installation process.
So, you know, the IP is assigned 162 and it downloads the kernel, the init RAM disk
that I generated with the black hole scripts that you just need to access the revision that you just see.
And it boots. So at the end of the booting process, you have an address that you can SSH into
and you have a server to play with.
Obviously, this is not persisted.
So when you reboot the server, the dance would start again and again forever
and you would get a fresh new server to use.
But for my ephemeral homelab, this is what I need.
I just need a quick way to prototype.
You can get enough RAM to be happy and for me, 8 gigabytes of RAM is happier than ever.
I can play with that.
Obviously, all the nooks can have, you know, disk attached to it and you can decide to persist the operating system on it.
So you can write a systemd script that does nixo X install at the end of the when the server is booted
and you don't need to touch anything.
When the black hole starts, it will run the system, the scripts and it will have a new persisted and flashed operating system.
As I said, I don't do that because I don't need it, but that's how the full cycle, lifecycle of the machine can be managed.
And how do you, if you persist a disk, how do you reboot the server and get back to the pixie dance is all on you.
In my case, I don't have, like the nooks doesn't really have a board, a BMC to control the server.
So I can't force the bootloader to netboot.
So I wipe the disk and I break the disk.
So it will go to that booting.
A bit rough, but, you know, homelabs, that's how it is.
So service discovery, in my case, it's way simpler than what it should be.
You can use console, core DNS or whatever you want, tiescale even.
So you can, you know, in black hole, you can register a tiescale daemon and have it registered there.
And you see that in the UI, I use my router.
So when I see that there are new servers with a NixOS host name, I know that there is a server ready to be to use and that is booted.
In the meantime, when it does the pixie dancing, the host name is pixie and a random MAC address.
So it kind of gives me enough control and I don't need to run anything else, but you can get fancier if you want.
So what is netbooting used for?
Only for ephemeral homelabs?
As I said, no.
Cloud providers or, you know, people managing data centers that I think you know more than me, but you can do that for inventory management.
So when you buy a shiny new server, it doesn't do much.
It doesn't know what to do.
So you just hook it to the network and the pixie then starts.
And instead of running a script that persists an operating system, you run a daemon that registers the server to an inventory management like Netbox or others.
So you know how much RAM it is, the model, whatever you can get from the system.
You inspect the system, you push the blob and you register a brand new server and you have it available in your system.
So it's kind of the same process I do for mine, but way cooler because the hardware is way more expensive.
You can do that for provisioning.
So as I told you before, I don't do provisioning because I don't want a persistent operating system on my homelab.
But you can format and partition disks using system if you want or any other way to run a script and you're ready to go.
For recovery is the same way.
As I said, I don't have a BMC, but you can break your disk and get back on pixie booting.
Some of the hardware have disk attached, but I don't really use disk much.
And even if you don't because I don't need it.
So my operating system is small enough and I do simple stuff that don't require me to swap or go on the disk.
So I can use the entire disk.
I can format it just for the data if I need to store some data.
In order to do orchestration, pixie core, you can declare MAC addresses and the images you want to push to.
So if you know the MAC address of your Ethernet cable, you can say, oh, on this MAC address, distribute this image.
Otherwise, distribute a different image so you can have servers running different net booting images.
And it's very convenient.
So now when it comes to electric wiring, I'm also not really an expert.
So what I have, I have a really powerful enough DC that is connected to a few fuse so I don't blow up all the nukes at the same time.
One at a time maybe, but not all together.
So that's why I have the fuse there.
Easy, cheap, it works.
And then to control the power consumption, I just cut the power at the beginning.
So I have a Raspberry Pi connected to a board of 16 relays that I control over an API.
So if I want to stop the Nuke number one, I just stop, cut the energy and the power for that Nuke and goodbye Nuke.
And playing with the GPIO, the Raspberry Pi is very easy and convenient.
So the prototype is good enough.
I want to change from a Raspberry Pi from ESP32 to experiment a little bit, but it's not really for NixOS because it doesn't run an operating system.
So just there.
And I got two new fancy boxes that I want to replace with the IKEA one because I think that will play a better role with my ambient there.
And I don't know if I'm late or earlier, but that's it.
OK, so yeah, this is my home lab and what I'm playing with.
So if you have any question or if you want to know more, I will just go back to the if I can.
My invite is to have a look at the dot file repo if I can.
Oh, I can do that.
The dot file because it has all the all the codes in there and you can play with it.
So coming back to these slides, the what is what I really like is the is the convenience of, you know, I have my NixOS derivation for this for these experiments.
I'm building two NixOS derivations and the the flake.
There's no flake one encapsulates the the other one so I can distribute it conveniently.
And it's a single flake file that contains and run both.
So it's you know, it's very easy and it's very easy when you get to it to get there.
It took me 135 questions on this course.
Thirty six thousand messages on metrics.
But I'm there as is there for you.
So play with it if you want.
So thank you. Yep.
Yeah, because it's very.
Yeah. How NixOS plays with the pizza booting and, you know, a net booting you have.
I didn't find there are other packages or other projects that helps you to package and operate in system like HashiCorp Packard is another one.
There is infra kit from Docker and all this kind of stuff.
So but NixOS gives you a full control on the on the distribution that you want to provide.
So, for example, at the beginning, I wasn't really looking at the size of the image.
So I was pushing in there everything I needed.
But then I started to realize that my image was like four gigabytes and my RAM I didn't have enough RAM or I didn't have enough RAM left to do the actual work.
So I started to iterate and play on what I was able to remove.
So I started to investigate about how to do a minimal operating system.
So I see that the minimal profiles I disabled the documentation I disabled, you know, everything I don't need it.
And I went back to like now the image is 400 megabytes in RAM when it's fully unpacked.
And it works. So it's going to stop.
I think that's really the power you get from NixOS compared with other systems.
Or getting questions answered.
I can also suggest the disk server, which is pretty great.
OK. Yeah, I would look at it. Thank you.
One more round of applause, please. Thank you.
Thank you.
We ready for the next.
Yes. Hi, I'm Philip.
I'm here on behalf of Selkrull, a company.
So we specialize on software delivery, customized to the clients, you know, what people want.
This talk is about Nix.
So like, you know, I'm here in Boston, 2023, of course.
And my talk is Pitfossil Nix and how to avoid them.
Right. So at Selkrull, we use NixOS for infrastructure.
We use Nix for CI, CD and setting up deaf environments.
Basically everywhere you can use Nix, we try to adopt it just because, you know, Nix is great.
You have all the repusability and everything that comes with that.
Right. So it is me.
All my socials are here.
If you want to reach out to me, my GitHub.
Right.
Right. Yes.
So Selkrull, I said, is, you know, a software company focused on creating customized high performance solutions.
Yes, I can. Right. Sorry.
So this is mainly in like the like functional programming realm of like Hestrel and stuff like that,
where, you know, people want customized solutions for certain problems.
Exactly. Right. So again, this hurts what Nix.
And this is right.
The goal of this talk is to make Nix more approachable.
Right. So when we adopted Nix, I mean, I wasn't there then.
All the developers weren't using Nix. Right.
And they still, you know, they tried to. Right.
So they asked the developers, they're not that into Nix. Right.
And they had some issues.
And I want to touch on that just so that, you know, a case study of how Nix works in Selkrull.
Right. Sorry. Right.
So I'm pretty new at Selkrull and I'm part of the SIU team.
So I try to push Nix to and oftentimes we have developers.