Thank you.
Hello, Fuzzdam.
I'm Yanem Dawey.
I'm working on a twig on a project called Nickel.
Nickel is a configuration language.
And is it?
Okay.
So in this talk, I want to talk about Nixcel, which is framework to use Nickel as an alternative
front-end language for Nix.
And my dear friend and colleague, Guillaume, who just got off stage, has a strange morning
routine where he stands in front of me and says, I have a question.
When?
So when can I use Nickel for Nix?
And so my primary motivation is just to be able to enjoy my morning coffee in peace.
And my second motivation is to try to get you as excited as Guillaume is about Nickel
or at least 10% would be ready for it because he's a very enthusiastic man.
So beside may be a few people who got lost because Fuzzdam is huge.
I think we all agree in this room that Nix is a powerful tool.
There are a bunch of things that only Nix is capable of.
And my personal favorites are dev shells.
So you need to hack on a project.
You just enter the directory, type Nix develop, you have all your tools you need, then you
exit the directory, everything is back to normal.
NixOS, we've talked about that.
Being able to manage your whole configuration in.files, rollbacks, competing version of
the same packages.
Pretty nice.
And I guess each one of you has their own usage for embedded or whatever of Nix, either
personal or professional.
And if that's the case, one of the main interface you have with Nix is the language, Nix expressions.
And in fact, it's a pretty simple language.
It's mostly JSON plus functions plus bit of more strange things, but mostly.
And paradoxically, the language is simple.
I find it quite hard to use actually.
Yes, it's two with only one O to use in practice for a bench and resin at least for Nix.
And one of the main issue is error reporting.
And I think it's a pretty fundamental problem in the language, which is dynamically typed
and lazy, is that when you make a mistake, your little mistake travel all around the
code base.
And only when something consumes your value, then everything blows up.
And the error usually points out deep inside Nix code because that's what is consuming
your value.
And I would like the error to point out the point when I made the mistake originally.
My favorite one is infinite recursion in the module system.
So I was a newbie at Nix.
I tried to move my Nix size config to flakes.
I made a typo on an argument to a simple module.
And I got infinite recursion, but nothing was recursive.
I didn't know what was happening at all.
Something can be said about discoverability, in particular when you're writing code.
So I'm writing some Nix code.
I would like to know what are the standard library functions that are available?
What are the list functions from Nix packages that I can use?
What are their type?
What argument should I put there?
I'm writing a flake.
What is the schema of a flake?
Could I have some completion or at least some in-code information to know what field I'm
supposed or attribute I'm supposed to fit?
And the last point is that Nix is simple.
And usually it's a good thing in language design.
Like you build a rock-solid core and then the rest can be done as library function.
But Nix is not a general purpose language.
It's a domain-specific language.
And if users of your domain found themselves having to solve the same problem again and
again and again, then maybe the domain-specific language should provide a native list way
to solve this problem.
And one example is overriding.
Something that you do a lot in Nix is taking a module or a configuration or whatever object,
tweaking a parameter and get the new result with all the dependency updated and so on.
And it's pretty not trivial to do in Nix.
There are a lot of different ways, a lot of different abstractions implemented by different
people.
And that makes for hard experience, in my opinion, especially as a newbie.
And it's not me saying that.
It's actually Alco, the creator of Nix, who wrote a gist some long time ago, which is
partly one of the origin of Nix about the deficiencies of the Nix language.
And one thing he says is that Nix is a DSL for package and configuration management,
but it doesn't have any notion of package nor configuration.
So to recap, one of the main things is developer experience in general.
Error reporting is one of the main interfaces with the language, but something goes wrong.
It's important.
There is something to be said about Nix being too simple somehow or too barebone for its
own good.
And so people reinvent the wheel in a lot of different ways.
And I mean, sometimes it's fine to have competing libraries and so on.
But for fundamental things, it's like when you want to put something in a standard library
of a long wait.
Like, that should be only one way to do it.
And it's efficient and so on.
So what can we do about it?
Well, I propose to do nickel.
Nickel is a general purpose domain-specific language, if that makes sense, for configuration.
And what nickel has, it has sound gradual typing.
It has optin static typing with higher rank polymorphism, structural typing with low polymorphism.
Contract is like, I've been found that, yeah, no.
I mean, yes, in fact, but that's not the point.
The point, I mean, those are means to an end.
And the end is that your practice is nice.
So here it's a little video demo.
On the right, we have something called a contract.
It's like a NixOS type, something that is checked at one time by the nickel interpreter.
And you write it actually pretty much like a type or a schema.
You say, oh, nickel derivation, this is taken from Nixl.
It's a contract defined by Nixl.
It should have a name, a version, dependencies, system, and so on.
You can attach other contracts and metadata in general to this field.
You can say, oh, name must be a string, version must be a string.
Dependency should be an array of derivation.
Derevation is another contract that you'll define somewhere.
You can attach default value.
Dependencies are empty by default.
You can attach, you can say that the field is optional, for example, because I think
Nix is not strictly required by building the derivation that version is defined.
And the thing is that all this metadata can be leveraged by the tooling.
On the left, we are trying to write something looking like a derivation that doesn't matter
at this point.
But we define an output field.
Field is just nickel name for attributes.
And we apply this contract.
We just import it.
And let's see how it turns out.
It turns out that we get completion for what we should put inside this output stuff, like
name, okay, we have documentation, we have the type, actually, type in the string is
name, whatever, the contract.
We get completion for building command and for nested recall, like, oh, what should I
put inside the building command?
You can leverage also this information, not only from DSP, but from the CLI.
Oh, no, sorry, I forgot.
You get completion for the standard library, and actually any library.
Those functions are statically typed, but that's another subject.
You can read this information from the CLI.
Using nickel query, you can say, oh, what's inside contract that's name?
What is the field nickel derivation?
We get documentation and what are the available fields?
You can say, oh, okay, what is build command in particular?
I get documentation and field.
Now what happens if I make a silly mistake and build command which should be a record
of strings, I just made it a string, like, instead of an attribute set.
I tried to run nickel on that.
What I get is a normal message.
The first blue part says, what is a contract that I just broke?
You should have a record with args and so on.
The second light points at where it defines the value, not where it's used.
It's red, and it says, oh, this is wrong.
This doesn't respect this contract.
The third part is not really useful there, but it's giving you the evaluated value, which
means that if build command was a complex expression but out of map and fold, you still
get the final stuff that it builds.
And this green thing here is taking who the L is imposing this contract.
So these points to build command field inside the nickel derivation contract, inside the
nixl library.
And so this is just runtime validation.
You could do it with libraries, nixos does it, but first I think this kind of nice structural
syntax for it, as well as this advanced error reporting, is really hard, if not impossible,
to achieve purely in library code because there are special things in the nickel interpreter
to handle contract application and track argument and the stack and so on.
So what nix is about is relevant, thorough, and early error reporting as much as possible.
Discourability, you can attach all those meta information to fields, and they are understood
by the tooling.
And in particular by the LSP, giving you interactive development process.
And then arguably the language is more sophisticated than nix, but as a user, I find it easier.
Okay, great.
That's fine, that's just me great 80,000 package.
No big deal.
Nope, not going to happen.
Nix package is a huge behemoth.
It's probably the, I mean, the most important thing in nix, I mean, the value of nix is
all this domain knowledge on how to build package, encoded in a code that can be action
by the machine and is not going anywhere.
So whatever we do, if we want to use an alternative frontend, we have to be able to use nix packages.
So meet your first nickel derivation.
It's a dev shell.
And from a distance, I want you to notice that there is no function at the top.
So usually nix packages, the first thing you do when you define a package is to define
a function.
This has a number of problems, one being that before doing anything with it, like getting
the name or the version, you have to apply it to some arguments.
And this argument may be packages, so you need to apply them and so on.
So you need to evaluate the transitive dependency before doing anything.
Here is just a flat record.
Record are recursive by default in nix.
So line one, we import some thing called builders.
We'll see later what is from the nix cell.
Builders is given by nix cell.
And line four to six, for now, our API is that you need to declare a bit like a flake,
but at the level of the derivation what you are going to take from the nix world.
But here I say I want to take CRL from nix packages.
Line nine to 12, I'm defining the actual derivation, so to speak, even if it seems way smaller.
So I give a name.
And then I put this input.crol in the pass.
So this funny looking string, I won't have time to detail, but it's called a symbolic
string is a way to simulate nix string context, but not only actually, it's a pretty generic
mechanism, but to have the same entities like input.crol is not actually a string, it's
a derivation which has a store pass and so on.
And you do that in nix and it's not trivial to do it in a different language, but yeah,
this is a solution to that.
And we are using this input.crol, but we haven't seen any inputs yet.
The other was called input spec.
So input is defined, not really, but it's defined line seven.
This is just a field without a definition.
And in nickel, the idea is that we call a recursive and we have something called merge
operation, which is the ampersand.
It's a bit like the slash slash of nix that is combining records, but it doesn't give
priority to the left hand side or right hand side.
It's just try to combine and see if there is a conflict, you have to use priorities.
A bit like the nix or the module system.
But it does what you expect naively when you start nix, that it works on nested record
and that it works on recursive record.
That is, if you override something there, everything that depends on it recursively
will be automatically overridden.
So what we do, line seven is a bit like defining a function argument.
So we're just doing function in different way, so to speak, but in a way that is way
nicer for nix because it just looks like configuration.
Combining is trivial, I just add one line and I merge with something that redefines
the value.
Combining stuff is trivial.
So for example, line 14 and 15, I use some predefined builders which are mostly looking
like this derivation and that has rest, they have environments and they see the virtual
environment in my shell.
So I will end up with a shell that has here well all the rest we can and see.
So I think I won't have time to dwell into the detail too much, but it's a bit convoluted
right now.
We have a lot of back and forth between nix and nikl.
Nix is a driver.
What's important is that these parts will get improved, but somehow it's naturally,
it's a bit orthogonal to all the design of the nikl style, what do the API look like,
what are the builders, how we do overriding.
It's orthogonal.
This part is just how do we communicate with nix packages.
Right now, nix is leading and everything that cross the boundaries can be functions.
It has to be data, so in practice it's JSON.
And so you have a bit of back and forth like what you input or I will extract that from
nix packages, I give you the derivation JSON.
Nikl has almost everything to build the derivation, but it cannot build it, so it cannot give
the argument to nix saying, hey, please can you call derivation for me.
But that works for now at least.
So it's something.
So the limitation of this model is that you have a lot of back and forth and the error
messages at the boundary are pretty bad.
If you try to import the packages that don't exist in nix packages, that's going to be
ugly.
And you can't override the nix package from within nikl.
That's kind of an important limitation because the only thing you can get is data.
You can do it on the nix side in the overarching flake, but it can't defeat the purpose.
We like to be able to do that from nikl.
The roadmap to solve that is to be able to import and involve nix expression directly
in nikl.
It's actually not that in reasonable because nix is simple and close to being a subset
of nikl.
So we are already able to transpire most of nix as far as the language is concerned, but
we are missing all the built-in dot atrof derivation and things like that to make it
work.
And I think it's the hardest part actually.
Having nikl built-in to build derivation would probably piggyback on nix, but so that at
least we don't have to do the last back and forth.
Okay, but...
Okay, we can do all the things and nikl becomes a driver and you don't have to go through
those back and forths you can override from nikl.
For nix, what does it mean?
I hope it means an improved developer experience, unified approach to configuration.
These look like configuration more than nix.
I find you just define a batch of fields and you merge stuff together.
And a smoother learning curve for the newcomers.
I didn't cover performance, but also having the merging being native and not a library
function has more room for optimizations.
And beyond, my secret dream is that nikl is a general purpose for configuration.
So you could use the same language with the same notion, same contracts, same data model
for all of your stack, terraform, Kubernetes, nix, exchange instinct between the layer.
And something we are working on is incremental evaluation.
It's a bit like incremental build, but at the level of evaluation I have this huge nix-OS
configuration.
I change one option.
I want the interpreter to only propagate the changes to what needs to be actually reconputed.
So to answer the initial question, nikl nix when?
Well now we can already do this stuff, well next week because we haven't merged everything.
But nixl will be released in 0.1.
You could do the variation in basic dev shells.
Nikl itself will reach 1.0 in the coming months.
And it's still rough around the edge.
You can't do everything you would like to do in nix.
But the point is that I think we did the hardest.
Like arriving at the first iteration was really complex and now everything is aligned and
somehow we just have to build the same to polish the API and so on.
And there is the same for terraform nikl.
Thank you.
So not yet.
Not yet.
Okay, sorry, did you finish your question?
So I'm asking if we are transpiling nix to nikl.
Right now, no, we are doing this back and forth with nix and JSON and so on.
But that's the plan in the end.
To transpile nix.
You could import foo.nix from nikl and that would give you a nikl value and then you can
do whatever you want with it.
Yes?
Yeah.
Yeah, it's true.
I guess you could.
But probably the idea here is to reuse a nikl overriding mechanism which is we hope way
simpler somehow.
You don't have to do anything to get your things to be overrideable easily.
So if I think terraform nix is not using a module-like system.
Yeah.
And there is terra nix maybe that is doing that.
I don't remember, yes.
But yeah, you could do that.
Actually, you could wrap any nix package with a nikl interface somehow like FFI.
Or you could redo it a bit to have a more, both are possible, I guess.
One more round of applause, please.
Thank you.