Okay, good morning everyone.
I want to talk about how we can dynamically change the load of the software front system
to be a better resident in clouds.
I did not move to IBM as part of the storage, Reddit storage moving to IBM.
So this is still a Reddit presentation.
I don't have the Ceph logo here because it's generic presentation but it would be highly
based on work that I did with others on Ceph.
So all the examples would be how this was implemented in Ceph and how we could use it
but the concepts are generic and not Ceph specific.
So it's a mix.
Okay, so we will talk.
We want what is optimal cluster performance and why we need optimal cluster performance.
It would be just at the beginning.
Then I'm going back to explain what we did in Ceph for brief version.
We have a new read balancer which I explained quite shortly.
It's not into full details but it's an infrastructure that could be used to better control the load
later.
Then some future plans that we already have which are good as examples to what we could
do with this infrastructure.
And then we'll go to the real problem, how we could actually dynamically change the way
the load is spread across Ceph cluster in case we need to do it because other things
change in the cluster.
How we could fit the way the load is spread in Ceph because we offer some kind of an external
change in the conditions that we need to respond to.
So again just an example, if we have a cluster, we have here nodes and we have three workloads
and they are split not totally evenly over the nodes.
And if we had bad luck we could see that some nodes are more loaded than the other nodes.
And the problem is, everyone probably guesses, one node reaches a 100% load then the entire
system starts to become slow because we have weakest link in the chain effect.
Assuming these workloads cannot respond fast enough so you get all kinds of queues created
and then TAC cluster loses its ability to perform well.
It still performs but not that well.
So we basically when we build cluster and we look from the outside we want the load
to be spread almost evenly so when one node reaches 100% we know the cluster is fully
occupied.
There is nothing we could do about it.
This is another image which shows something which is way better because the nodes, again
it's the same, it's created the same number, the areas of each workload are the same and
it actually shows cluster which, the cluster itself is balanced and we could get when it
fills up, it fills up together so we use the cluster for the best that we can.
So actually if we try to look at what we have, we want something flexible with fixed volume.
A balloon is what I found.
We want something, the performance that we want is the volume but it should be flexible
because we can't control all the workloads.
So if we take, for example, we have on the nodes a backup program which runs in nights
but not at the same time, it gradually goes over all the nodes.
So each one of the nodes gets some kind of peak either in iOS or in network traffic and
it peaks and it's more full than others, than the others, the other one and it goes over
all the nodes.
We can obviously mitigate this.
We can say, okay, we allocate some capacity for this backup program so we know that other
workloads could run on this node.
But if these backup programs work for an hour every day, then we allocate some capacity
for one hour and the other 23 hours it is not used, probably not used.
It's much better if we could incorporate these change, these backup runs over the cluster
and move the nodes with a backup to other nodes for some time for an hour, then the
backup finishes go to another node, then we move the nodes from back to the original node
and we make it its way more effective.
So in some sense, we do some kind of over-provisioning on the nodes when we know that most of the
time we are not over-provisioning and when we are over-provisioning we could mitigate
this.
That's the idea.
And the other use case that we could have that we could get a node coming to full capacity
when we didn't plan it, it could be all kinds of failure, NIC problems, all top of the rec
switch problems, other hardware, disk failure, all kinds of other stuff could bring to a
situation that may be bad but not critical enough to take node down and do full rebuild
and all this stuff.
The idea is to have something which is flexible and we could play with it.
The problem is that our balloon is built of Lego bricks and it's not as flexible as we
think.
So I want to show the amount of flexibility that we have that we could play with when
we talk about software-defined storage system and which are more challenging than other
workloads because it's stateful, stateless workloads are easier to manage flexibly.
So what we want to go from this, this is a copy of the first diagram that I showed and
this is where we want to be and I change only the orange workload.
It's the same numbers, exactly the same numbers, exactly the same area, orange area but split
differently.
That's the approach that I want to take but okay, it's a presentation.
I could do miracles in presentation, how I do it in real life and I want to show how
we could play assuming Ceph is or software-defined storage is the orange one, how we could play
with this to a limit.
We can't do all the magic that we could do in presentation but we could do reasonable
under some condition very good work under other condition, improve the situation not
to a perfect solution.
So it's all based on the idea of the Ceph read balancer and the idea today in Ceph we
have not in Ceph in every software-defined storage, the main balancing requirement is
that all the disks are full at the same percentage.
The first disk which is full, the system is full.
So this is our basic assumption.
Then what we're doing today, we try to do is that if we have replica 3 then we have
XPGs mapped to OSD, X divided by 3 would be primaries.
So the primaries are split evenly on the devices, not evenly, split according to the number
of the PGs.
So if we have a device with more PGs it has more primaries.
But we don't have anything that does it.
Actually what is happening today in Ceph is that we rely on the statistics of crash.
It works well for large clusters.
It doesn't work well for small cluster.
So the Ceph read balancer comes to fix this and it's what we currently have, more in the
next bullet, is for the small clusters where the statistics doesn't play well.
So what we actually did, we added three different things together, create a read balancer which
could actually split the reads evenly across OSD.
Actually what it does, it splits the primaries as I explained for replica X.
1 divided by replica X are primaries per OSD for the PGs.
So it just changes the primaries.
So first of all we created, it would be part of the REIF version.
So first of all we created some kind of score.
The score represents how well the read is balanced versus the optimum.
Optimum is 1.
If we have a score of 2, meaning that under full load of reads the system would perform
half of a good system.
If it's 3, for example we have replica 3 and the score is 3, and we have 3 disks and score
is 3, it means all the reads are for a single disk.
So it's obviously third of the optimal when the reads split evenly among 3 disks.
So that's what I have.
Score works really well when the read affinity of the devices is high and it's still monotonous
but it's more difficult to explain the numbers when you have a lot of devices with small,
OSDs with small read affinity numbers and I could explain later why it is, it's not
a good way to configure the system.
It creates all kinds of illegal configuration.
You have to do what the user asks you not to do but that's for side code.
Then we have two new commands, pgupmap commands.
We have pgupmap primary and rmpgupmap primary which actually say okay I get an OSPG, the
PG has x OSD there, make one of them the primary, I tell them which one.
So I could actually change the primary within a PG and it's metadata only, we don't move
data you must give an OSD which is part of the PG.
If you give OSD which is not part of the PG you get an error.
So we are not trying to do anything, it's very cheap, very fast, it just changes the
order of the OSDs within the PG.
That's everything that it does.
Since it's first version we want to make it opt-in option so we have a new command to
the OSD map tool which actually calculates everything and spits a script file that you
could run in order to get to the perfect distribution.
That's what we currently have.
So this is the example of when you run this you could see smaller clusters, a small cluster
tend to be less balanced because statistics doesn't play well.
So we have number of primaries for three OSDs, we have 11, 6, 15 obviously it's not balanced
and after you run it you get 10, 11, 11 which is obviously the best that you could get and
the number is not one because the average is 10 and two thirds so if you could have
10 and two thirds you get score of one but it's 1.03 really good and here obviously it's
1.4 because it's 15 divided by 10 and two thirds.
This is the out file that you could actually run as a script in order to apply the changes.
If you look really carefully you see that we have six changes but actually we could
only have five changes even maybe four we should just make this 10 so we have 11, 10,
11 that's because it's a greedy algorithm since these commands are really really very
don't have overhead run really fast it's not a problem.
If we would have need to move data this would be a totally wrong one because we have two
additional data movements we don't need it it's really simple so we didn't try to optimize
on the number of changes just to make it come.
So what is the implementation?
The implementation is we have two functions one of them is we have one it's an example
of calc desired primary distribution that's where we go over the configuration and decide
what's the final distribution of primary that we want for OSD how many primaries we want
to be on this OSD.
It's really it's some kind of policy function it's really simple today it's it's does one
divided by replica count as I said and it's about 40 lines of code something really simple
so adding more policy just for to understand if you want to add more policies and I'll
talk about more policies immediately if you want to add more policies then we're talking
about tens of lines of code nothing more than this.
Then we have the functions that actually takes the configuration and goes over all the PGs
it's all run by pool I didn't say this before it's all run by pool because pool represent
workload and it's important to balance per workload it goes over all the PGs on the pool
and does its work and switches what it has to switch in order to get into the what we
calculated here.
So basically this is function this is infrastructure function could be used we could add more and
I'll talk about more policies we could add more policies and adding the policy is really
something simple and the command is fast that's I'm keep on saying this because I want to
talk about dynamic that's the what is behind the dynamic thing it's a cheap operation that
we could run periodically and change things when we want to do it it's not involved in
any any high overhead or anything it's just a metadata operation.
So we had the very simple read balancer use case is small clusters small class it's very
important use case for Red Hat now IBM it's for ODF or for a CIF in OpenShift but there
is much more than we could do so now let's talk about the next well we have actually
two use cases.
So what we could do more we have a mechanism we could change the things but it's a pretty
strong mechanism then we want to use to use it further on so one thing and this is one
thing this is a use case for larger cluster load balance better on heterogeneous system.
So you have a large CIF cluster you started to work five years ago you have one terabyte
devices time comes you need more capacity and it doesn't make sense to buy one terabyte
devices anymore and you bought two terabyte devices now normally it means that you get
twice the workload on the two terabyte devices because you need the devices would be split
even fill filled evenly you could create policies that says that you change gradually and when
the smaller devices are not full then you have the same capacity it doesn't work because
every change is movement of data it's very expensive so you could in theory create really
really nice and nice policies in practice the price you pay in order to keep it is too
much eventually you have device which is twice as large it gets twice the capacity or you
define it as a smaller device then you lose capacity or it gets twice the load if it gets
twice the load the smaller devices are working on half the potential load.
So just for the numbers I have a little exercise so we have devices same technology the same
bandwidth same IOPS we have one OSD of two terabytes and four OSDs of one terabyte so
it's like three OSDs of two terabytes if you think about capacity so one of two terabytes
four of one terabyte so we have for each a PG one copy on the large device and two copies
on the small devices split so and so that's the assumption to just show a bit of play
with the numbers and for the convenience let's assume that we have 100 IOPS it's just easy
people like to think in round numbers so so under full load what happens this device goes
to 100 IOPS because that's what it could provide and these devices get half the load and they
would provide each 150 IOPS so total we have three 300 IOPS and there is not nothing we
could actually do about it because the requirements to have the capacity split twice here than
here is so strong that we can't change it can't play with it that's the rules of the
game once we did it we are bound in such a configuration actually we had a working cluster
and we added one larger disk and all the cluster performs way way worse than it used to be
so and it's not really something that we could do with it and except replace all the disks
with larger disk or something like this but if you want to do gradual we can't do with
it now there is something that we could do let's assume that we have for now on the read
only just read only load the capacity is still the same 30 Pg is 15 15 15 but the 10 primaries
here I moved them and move them here and split them here so we have here when you have only
reads all the devices are fully working under full load so we moved from 300 IOPS to 500
IOPS but just very minor change of changing primaries and splitting them differently across
the cluster now this is the best that we could get if we have read write obviously if we have
write only workload we can't improve using this technique because this technique changes only
reads so if we have write only we can change and if we have some rights we can't get as good as
this one because eventually this will get all the time twice rights than the others so there is
limitation to what we could do so so that the best potential is for read only but we could do also
with mixed read writes we could get a lot of improvement under full load a lot so that's the
idea and this is already planned for the next version on purpose we didn't put it on the first
version because we want adoption of the feature but this is we plan to add two sets for the next
version this is actually better supporting a different sizes of devices so so can we improve
on other loads which are not read only and I already said this we can do this but in order to do this
we in order to do good job we need to understand purple some some characteristic of the workload
and basically the read write ratio if we get read write ratio which is reasonably close to what we
actually have then we could do good a good improvement in the performance when we have when
we have different sized devices and mixed mixed workload well I said it there are limitation what
we could do so I said one thing we can't improve on write only using this technique I've seen I've
seen since it so it's real thing but if you use replica 3 and we instead of having 1 terabyte and
2 terabyte devices we have 1 terabyte and 5 terabyte devices I've seen this in real life we
can't improve we can't do well we can improve but we can't get to optimal performance when we have
5 terabyte devices and 1 terabyte devices on the same pool the numbers of two we could reduce it to
the minimum moving all reads out of the 5 terabyte devices but eventually when you have enough writes
the system would not perform optimally so we covered this so another case which was another
case which is well it's a no no big no no don't put SSDs and HDDs on the same pool everyone knows
this well if you could make if you can make sure that you have enough SSDs that sorry that every
PG is mapped to at least one SSD and then two HDDs preferably replica 3 one SSD two HDDs you could
actually get the effect of read flash cache without cache misses you always read from the SSDs and you
only write to the HDDs you could improve on the performance of your system and get really fast
read latencies so I'm breaking this no no but it is important don't mix the technologies if you
can't make sure that all the reads are from the faster device if you could make so if you take replica
3 and you put one third of your PGs of your OSDs are SSDs of the capacity one third of the capacities
on SSDs two third on HDDs and you could also make sure whatever techniques you use it's really easy
you need to change a bit the crash holes but that the all the copies you have one copy on SSD and
the other copies on HDDs you could actually improve your performance dramatically because the
bottleneck of HDD would be only for writes and all the reads would get the SSD or NVMe or whatever
performance so I'm breaking one of the big no-nos here but if you can't make sure that all the reads
are from the fast devices then you waste it wouldn't work eventually under full load you'll get the
known weakest link in the chain and it will be blocked but if you can do it so this is a way to
modernize the devices gradually and not moving all the HDD to SSDs at once one third in case
of replica 3 could be the first step and you could do it gradually and you don't want to do anything
so that's another thing that could be with the existing by the way for this because it's different
technique you don't need what we did in the in the read balancer it's enough to have good crash
holes this could be managed by crash holes differently okay now we come to the to the dynamic
um aspect of this so the thing is that we we have cluster we build cluster we know we have the
numbers how the cluster performs what are the network bandwidth how devices perform
it all works well until it doesn't so uh we may have problems hardware problems
uh we and we may have noisy neighbors where we work as i said full isolation of neighbors
has a cost if you prevent over provisioning in all costs well it has a cost it does cost you
depending on your workloads you you allocate a lot for temporary workloads so in some cases
doing over provisioning of nodes makes sense if you know how to behave and this is especially in
hyper convert in hyper converged so we know that hyperconverged deployment and noisy neighbors
uh it could be this in in kubernetes we tend to to limit we know how to limit no we use we tend to
limit um dcpus and memories and not network obviously for so defensive systems and network
network is really important so noisy neighbor on the network could cause huge performance problems
so the process and this is the the the process is i want to explain because uh it's it's more than
just technical thing we want to monitor the i-o performance all from OSD level and up we want to
identify what happens it could be on OSD level it could be on node level it could be on rec level
we need to understand what happens then we could tune up the system we could reduce the load if
the problem is temporary we don't want to move data even if the problem is that we have a fault
unique and we know that it would take 24 hours to fix it it may not be a worth the effort of
for a node to move all the data from this node to another node to other nodes to the rest of the
cluster and then move it back if we could make sure that we have a fault unique and until it
is fixed we don't read from this node at all we just write to it maybe we could live with it so
the idea is that we don't want the the obvious solution is mark osd is out and move the data
and everything fix itself but it costly especially if you have a lot of data over the node so this
is a way to reduce the load temporarily until it is until it is fixed and then once you did all your
magic fix everything you could go back to the normal so and by the way this is something that is
not related to software defined storage but it's much easier all this much easier to do for
stateless application if we have a web server that gives us the stock exchange quotes
and it doesn't function one of the servers doesn't function we change the proxy and we send
the request to other servers it's way more difficult to do with stateful application when
you can't exchange every server with every other server and you need there are more limitation and
obviously we talk about storage it's the most stateful thing that you could think of
so option one it's something we thought about even for the for the the read balancers we did
this is the what is a very good solution for the stateless part it's called the power of two
before you send a request you randomly select two candidates to get the request you find out who is
more loaded and you said to the one that is less loaded it does magic that's really really good
way to move the load from the loaded servers to the unloaded servers and it works unfortunately
in order to fix to do such thing in sef you need to go into the data path everything that i explained
until now is totally outside of the data path so you have to add things to the data path and to
change the clients and we thought about this also in order to do the the read balancing it would be
very simple every pg since we have read from non-replicine in sef now we could say for every pg
don't send the request to the primary send it randomly to any of the pgs and automatically
you get a balance spread sorry for each pg to any of those d's don't send to the primary
sd just send to whatever you have there we decided not to do it it's risky and we don't like to play
with the data path i don't like to play with data personally but it was a mutual decision not only me
so that's option two monitor centrally by the monitor centrally obviously
create the policy this is something that you need to get the function of the policy
that knows what to do when you find these discrepancies you need to understand what you're doing what you want to achieve
how much time you want to play with this before you decide to move data or maybe you need the
human involvement which is tell me okay i'm going to fix this don't do anything it's a policy you
need to do both in the terms of workload workflow and then program what you need to program for this
um the policy function is small we talked about this it's nothing and when the performance changes
first you need to notify operator because we suspected a lot of the problems could be
hardware problems that should be fixed and we just we need to tell something that we see something
bad and then change primary settings so we remove the load from the the the less performant osds or
or components to to other places and that's before monitoring the system and when it's
back to normal we could remove everything and go back to full thing so here is the conclusion it's
again it's data path against outside of the data path syncing uh the metadata the the the
performance to the clients which is also something that we didn't want to do versus the external
metadata configuration uh that we do on on the on the server side whatever because we trigger the
policy from from server side and no change so that's that's the idea for again this is for how
to implement this in in safe in the future but the idea we could if we measure if we know what's
going on we could improve to send at some point decide whether this improvement is good enough for
us until we fix or in some cases we decide to move data i'm not saying don't move data but don't
move it as the default option for every problem acknowledgement or it uh which worked with me a
lot on the ideas that i put here and she's now in IBM and Laura which uh did a lot of the coding with
me on this and actually since my coding skills were a bit rusty i couldn't do a lot without her
so thanks to Orit and Laura that helped in this project and i'm done questions yes please
yeah can you use the new OSD map that is like released for brief design like master can you use that to generate
a list of distribution of the primaries that will be optimal for all the clusters and use
the temporary up map feature that is already existing in all our releases to actually apply
that policy that this would be optimal okay basically i'd like to back forward but then
the question was if you could use the OSD map tool on older classes and then instead of using
the new pg up map use a temporary permit temp in order to do it i think it it should you uh
the OSD you should have a new Ceph cluster with all the new tools because there are some other
changes but you run OSD map tools on a file that generated from the OSD map tools work on configuration
file that you take so you could create a configuration file out of an old cluster
and run it with the new OSD map tool and then so i think actually the primary temp is how we we
tested this what is missing is that the newest map tool it relates on the score and actually i'm not
sure it not depends on the score but it uses a score internally so it should run on a new uh
on a new environment but i think it could it should be able to work uh i have my information
here uh it's uh or come i'll give you my email and send me i'll verify this it should work
i'm not 100 sure but it should work there no really if it doesn't work it is a problem it's
that's you said that uh it finds that it's especially good for smaller clusters how big
would you define smaller clusters the thing the question was how a what is small cluster and big
cluster the thing is the way crush works it uses statistics to do the the the split to to primaries
um if you have a cluster in which the primaries are not balanced probably it falls into the smaller
side but if you look at hundreds of always a hundred even it's not it's number of pgs not number
fours these uh in the past i did an experiment and i saw that you saw the score here 1.4 every time
that you double the number of the pgs roughly the score goes the difference from one goes to
by half so we put 1.4 for 32 pgs probably 1.2 around 1.2 for 64 it's large clusters with
pools with large large number of pgs usually somehow balance themselves but it's a matter of
of you need to look if you have unbalanced pool it's unbalanced pool doesn't matter which cluster
you are in but that's why we do it but most benefit for the larger pool the pools with the data
is when you have smaller clusters that it's not worth putting 512 pgs per pool and you
work with smaller numbers if you have 510 k or 2 k pgs per cluster probably your score would be
pretty good okay thanks yeah one minute yeah would it also be useful for erasure coded pools
uh the question whether it's good for erasure code is probably not well way way way less
sufficient i i tried to do the the the theory behind it and then maybe really really little
i don't know so currently we check in the code it doesn't work for erasure coded at all because we
think it doesn't worth the hassle so it's it's a tested and it works only on on replicas okay
my time is up thank you very much thank you it was pleasure being face to face here thank you