So, everyone will hear about Rook.
Let's welcome Alex and Dova to Mahan.
Hi, everyone.
Hope you're doing well, not feeling enough sleepy after the lunch.
We're here to talk about introduction to Ceph on Kubernetes using Rook.
Here's Alexander.
Alexander will introduce himself.
I'm Gaurav, Cloud Storage Engineer at Kubernetes Technologies.
And I'm also a community ambassador for the Ceph project from Indian region and been working
with the Ceph and Rook project since a long time and now a contributor to the Rook project.
I'm Alexander Trost, founding engineer of Cotechnologies Inc.
I'm a maintainer of the Rook project as well.
And, yeah, we want to talk about Rook for everyone who doesn't know it.
Want to get you started with storage.
Who doesn't need fast, reliable storage nowadays with the cloud native applications?
We're obviously talking about a bit more, well, more performance storage, I guess, depending
on who you're asking.
Well, the point of Rook in end is that with Kubernetes being kind of like with the shipping
container ship here, you have your Kubernetes that kind of abstracts everything, tries to,
well, provide you this one API for most to all things, depending on how far you want
to go with it.
And I guess for most people running Kubernetes, it kind of looks like that.
You have your big giant ship running your production applications and you have your
automation and CI CD process that kind of just try to keep it running.
And that's where the question with storage more and more comes into frame for people,
especially with local storage already, like, I think a year or so, a year or two even ago,
coming into, let's say, being better supported in Kubernetes in a native way and not just
having things around Kubernetes to try to make that an easier endeavor.
We have the question of how can I, for example, get my self storage talking with Kubernetes
so that I have storage for my applications.
And well, that's the simple interface.
It's more or less great that it's nowadays mainly one interface there called CSI, the
storage interface, which for, well, for storage vendors basically means they only need to
implement one storage or just they only need to implement one interface.
And as well for Kubernetes slash you as a user, you have one interface or like one way
on how you can get storage.
For somebody, if you want storage on Kubernetes, you have the way of using the Kubernetes
persistent volume claims.
We basically from application perspective claim storage and Kubernetes will take care
of, for example, talking with self storage and provisioning the volume and subsequently
the CSI driver from self will take care of the whole mapping the volume, mounting the
volume so that it is completely transparent to your application.
And the whole thing is with the CSI interface there.
It's like this one way for any storage vendor to also get their storage running.
Like there's, there's obviously more than self, but well, obviously with Rook self,
we're going to focus on self here.
And that's exactly kind of like a connector in between there.
So if you want storage, doesn't really matter if it's just self.
The point of obviously self is that we have the self-cis I that's disconnecting bits from
Kubernetes from the applications container side for your storage.
And that's already a point where kind of Rook or starting to talk about Rook here is that
you can run your self storage cluster.
Well on most to any hardware.
I don't know what we could run it on a Raspberry Pi as well.
Right.
Yes.
Easily.
Well, I think I've heard people run it on some Android phones or something even as well.
But it's like the well, you know, just because you can doesn't necessarily mean you should,
but that's the whole other discussion.
The point being you can technically have your self storage anywhere.
So it doesn't really matter if it's well, if it's on the metal in your own data center
or if it's just a few laptops thrown together, doesn't, that's the thing with staff in general.
It's like, you don't need the best hardware.
Like you don't need to buy that big box from the one storage hardware vendor, maybe to
explicitly go into that direction to have storage.
And that's the thing where kind of the combination of using Kubernetes and staff might come into
play or adjust for having storage for your applications, but also as a point for how
should I put it, for running SAV.
That's what RUG is about.
It's about running SAV, obviously the connecting part, setting that connection up between SAV
and Kubernetes as well.
But the idea is that RUG runs SAV in Kubernetes, in containers.
I think I mainly saw it from SAVADM last time we deployed a cluster on bare metal directly
that like SAVADM also one other way maybe to put like that to install, deploy, even
configure.
Easy to manage.
It's easily manageable.
It's one way to just install, run it.
It's kind of the same point for like RUG, where RUG is basically a SAV operator for
Kubernetes.
I'm going to go into a little bit more what I operated us because that's one of the vital
points in general just from running certain applications on Kubernetes.
Just again as we had it like running SAV on Kubernetes, with the operator pattern that
we have in Kubernetes, we can easily have most things that cause quite some pain depending
on how big you scale your storage cluster as well.
Obviously deployment, bootstrapping, configuration upgrades and everything.
That's all processes that I think there's probably 5 million Ansible playbooks to install
SAV.
There's well obviously SAVADM.
There's what it was called?
SAV deploy was there earlier.
SAV deploy as well, which is SAVADM I think now it is right?
SAV deploy earlier, SAVADM is now more advanced than the latest tool that everyone is using
these days.
There's more, I can already just think about 5 more tools on how to deploy SAV.
And ironically for the people that have looked into Kubernetes a bit more already, it's kind
of the same story for deploying Kubernetes.
But because of Kubernetes being kind of like this abstraction layer on top of hardware
to some degree, not like abstracting everything away.
But let me, if we skip this page.
It allows the root operator, that's exactly where this image comes in.
It's orchestrating a cluster.
It's not just a deployment obviously as well, but it's about using the Kubernetes APIs to
easily just take care of everything, so to say.
You want add a new node into your storage cluster.
What do you do technically speaking?
You just add it to Kubernetes and well, if everything goes well, 10 seconds later the
operator will be like, oh, new node, got to do my job, run the preparing job and everything,
get the node ready.
And a few seconds even later from that, the new SAV components, the OSDs on the disks,
depending on what disks are obviously as well, are taken care of.
To make this full circle there with Kubernetes side is like what the operator flow kind of
pattern it's mostly called is about.
It's about observing.
The operator is observing a status or even in Kubernetes case, custom resources.
I just think about it as like YAML, let's just give it a depth what it is, object of
YAML in Kubernetes, which the operator can watch on, as a user, either make a change
or even like my automatic CI CD process makes a change to it like, oh, a new node has been
added or something or I want to tweak something in the configuration of the cluster.
And so the operators are observing that and when there's a change or when there's even
in like the Kubernetes cluster, there's a change like a node missing or something, it
analyzes that change.
For example, if a node is gone or it's just not ready in Kubernetes terms anymore, let's
say network outage for like two of your nodes, the operator would analyze, well, observe
it first of all, analyze that and start acting upon that.
For example, in Kubernetes terms, it would take care of setting certain so-called, just
to have that term out there, potter disruption budgets, which kind of try to prevent other
nodes from potentially stopping the components of the SAV storage cluster.
And the point is really just that it's this like observe, analyze, act kind of loop because
in the end it just repeats itself all over again.
It's a whole deal with Kubernetes operators.
It's again, if like I want to, for I guess the people more already into SAV, if you want
to scale up some more SAV monitors, or well, SAV Mons, you just edit the object in Kubernetes
in the API and just crank the number from one count from three to five or something.
And again, this change is detected by the operator, analyzes it and acts upon it.
And that makes it quite convenient as well.
Again here, oh, the perfect way to YAML.
Sorry, it's a, I'm just this guy and come a little bit of clarification.
I don't have it mirrored on my screen, so it's a bit hard.
But that's exactly the YAML that we talked about.
Like as an example, I have my cluster running and let's say new SAV release.
What I would need to do to upgrade my cluster, I would basically go ahead and just change
the image to be well not 17.2.3, let's say.
17.2.5, that's the latest.
As an example, yeah, 17.2.5 as an example.
And again, operate with detected, analyze if every component is up to date or not, and
then even start the, well, I don't want to say complicated upgrade process, but there's,
especially with something like SAV, there's more than just, ah, let me just restart it.
There's checks before every component is restarted for SAV native ways of like, it's basically
commands that are, well, okay to stop, they're basically called like that.
And that's the whole idea there, that the operator helps you with that and in the end
just fully takes care of it.
So that in the end, for the main part of your work, you can just sit back, change it in
the YAML in a few minutes or it can even be hours depending on how big the cluster is.
The operator will take care of that.
As I mentioned before, like the example of the monitor count, for example, if you want
to change that, change it.
A few seconds later, the operator will pick that up and start making the changes necessary
or even if you would want to scale it down from like five to three or three to one, which
not recommended, we need highly availability there.
Or another option, the operator again watches it, takes care of doing it.
Or even if you want to specifically say on this one node, please use this one device
or even for this then, disk or NVMe, for example, use more than one storage team, OSD team
for that.
These things are possible and quite easily just by writing some lines of YAML in the
end.
According to your workload, you can easily just customize your, according to your workload,
you can easily customize your YAMLs.
That will make your life easier.
And we've mainly talked about having like the cluster running or even setting up the
cluster with the YAML definition of a self-cluster object.
But if you would, for example, want to, well, run some Prometheus in your Kubernetes cluster
and need storage for them.
To be able to use storage in SAV, you need to have a storage pool, for example, RBD storage,
block storage basically.
We also again just go ahead, create a SAV block pool object, which is simply containing
the information of, if we go from here, failure domain, where, well, you basically tell SAV
to only store data on different hosts to keep it simple for now.
The replicated size that there will be free total replica or free copies of data in your
cluster that require a safe replica.
Let's just skip to for now.
There's like a safe replica size, and even that you could technically set the compression
mode for this pool.
The point is, again, we can just write this in YAML, apply it against the Kubernetes API,
and a few seconds later, also for like the other objects, same way you need the SAV file
system, SAV object storage, same way the operator takes care of creating all the components.
For example, the MDS for a file system, we have the standard components, like the manager,
the monitors, operator, the OSDs, and even for the object store, for example, the RGW
components.
The operator simply takes care of that, and again, if you change the SAV version, a few
seconds to maybe a minute or two later, depending on what the state of your cluster is, operator
will take care of doing the update.
We've talked about deploying RookSAV cluster, mainly right now.
We want to highlight in that point as well the crew plugin that RookSAV is building and
providing, it allows you to have certain processes automated, even certain disaster recovery
cases are easier to handle with that.
And GURF will talk a bit about that.
So what's crew, right?
Crew is basically a package manager for kubectl plugins.
It makes the management of Kubernetes easier, and that's how the core developers and maintainers
came together and thought we can definitely write a plugin to make the lives of our developers
and administrators more easier.
Crew was the way to go since it's the de facto package manager for kubectl plugins.
So I mean, you can just do a kubectl install, kubectl crew install RookSAV.
That's how the plugin will be installed.
And just if you can see, we just ran the help command.
It shows a bunch of things that you could do.
You can just run a whole bunch of sef commands, rbd commands right now.
Also check the health of your cluster.
You could just do a bunch of things, like even if you want to remove an OSD.
So the need actually arises because, for example, if you want to use underlying tools like sef
object store or something like that to debug core troubleshooting issues and issues at
core OSD level.
I mean, crew plugin is definitely a great way to go as it provides common management
and troubleshooting tools for sef.
It's currently, I mean, a lot of things work.
We'll show you.
It's just like I mentioned, you just need to run kubectl crew install RookSAV.
It goes ahead quickly, installs the plugin.
It's I mean, way easier that you just don't need to earlier.
I mean, you had to go inside the toolbox pod to debug and troubleshoot every issue with
crew.
It provides such an ease of access that it makes, I mean, lives easier and troubleshooting
makes is definitely easier.
You could just override the cluster configuration just at the runtime and some of the disaster
recovery scenarios are also addressed.
Some of the troubleshooting scenarios that were addressed is mon recovery.
Suppose let's say you were have default three months in the cluster and majority of them
lose code.
I mean, recovering months from one maps.
I mean, just doing a bunch of tasks could be, if not done carefully, it could lead to
more disasters, but certainly with more automation in place when things are definitely working,
this is also made easier with the crew plugin.
And even if you want to troubleshoot CSI issues, it makes it easier for sure.
So yeah, I mean, just like if you want to restore mods with OSDs and even if we just
delete the RookSAV cluster after accidental deletion of custom resources, that could be
also restored.
And one of the common goals in the roadmap is also automating core dump collection,
because let's say if there's an issue that happens with the safe daemon and we want to
collect the core dump of the process for further investigation to share it with the developers
and with the community to understand what issues we are facing.
It can easily do well if you want to just do a performance profiling of a process with
GDB that could be made easier as well.
So these are some of the goals.
The current plugin is written in bash, but there's a work going on to rewrite the whole
plugin in Golang so that it's definitely more scalable and much more easier to manage and
even for contributors.
So yeah, just like that.
So, I guess the point we're more or less just trying to make is that if you have Kubernetes
or even run a distribution of, well, what is the range or open shift obviously as well
on your hardware and I wouldn't even put it to some degree as like you're confident enough
with Kubernetes to run it.
You can have it quite easy running a self cluster as well on top of that.
Obviously to some degree you need some self knowledge, but that's with everything.
If you run it in, if you want to run it in production, it's just that with this abstraction
layer again with Kubernetes, it makes it easier for you.
It's more of like you're kind of stamped in general there to think of more of like, oh,
well I have some nodes and they're simply there to take care of the components that
you need to run for the self cluster.
And especially with the root self operator obviously, it makes the process easier by
well a get ups approach for example, where you can just throw your Yamls into well into
get most of the time and have that automatic mechanism basically take care of this deployment
process.
So that again, the operator just takes this YAML takes care of it and makes the changes
necessary and with the root self crew plugin just to get that summarized real quick again.
It's a way for us to have certain automatic processes in the hand of admins when they
need to and not just as like, hey, here's like a 100 line bash script, please run that
one comment at a time.
And it simply allows it again, because we have this access to communities where we can
just ask Kubernetes, hey, where's the monitor running?
Oh, it's on node A and all that because well, we have an API that can tell us most of this
information and also for recovery scenarios there.
We can just ask Kubernetes to run a new pod or to well, have a new monitor for example,
then running with this old information from the other monitors to have this forum recovered
is required there.
And regarding root self is like a general outlook for the future.
One of the major points we're currently looking at is that we want to improve the cluster
manageability even more than we already have it at.
We want to make it easier.
We're using the root self plugin.
Right now you still need to do quite a lot of manual YAML editing of the objects that
we have in the API, but we would like to have, well, some more crew plugin commands there
again to extend that functionality, make it simply easier.
As well, improved security by having the operator and other components that are running in the
cluster, use separate access credentials to the cluster just to have there a bit more,
well, I guess to some degree, even transparency if you would look at like audit logging of
the self cluster and as well as encryption support for self-affairs and OSDs on partitions.
And as with everything, there's more.
Feel free to check out the roadmap MD file on the GitHub, github.com slash root.
The link will be shown as well.
If you want to get involved, if you want to contribute, if you have questions or anything,
we have, well, obviously to get up, there's even the GitHub discussions open.
If you have any, well, any more, more questions, I guess, then that might not fit on Slack.
Well, we have Twitter account, obviously.
We also have community meetings if you have any more pressing concerns to talk about.
And well, just kind of from that side as well, we're, as Gerv and I mentioned, we're from
Code Technology Sync.
We're building a company that wants to create a product around Rook7 and just in general,
try to help the community out there.
If we do talk with us or contact us as well.
And for now, thank you for listening and we'll gladly take some questions and can simply
take the last, I think you showed 50 minutes for questions or even just talking a bit about
certain scenarios here with everyone, I guess.
I would just like to add one more last thing before we go.
I'll just take it.
It's not a good idea that there's two like.
Yeah, I would just like to add one last thing.
If you want to check a demo and more troubleshooting scenarios, we did a talk at SEF virtual,
Summit 2022, which is already there on YouTube where we demoed a couple troubleshooting scenarios
and crew plugin.
I'll definitely share a reference and add a reference to here, but that'll be good to
check out as well if you want to check out a live demo.
Yeah.
Thanks.
Any questions?
Yeah.
Thank you.
Thank you for this talk.
I was wondering a bit about the downsides of using Rook with SEF because SEF is known
to be really hard in configuring getting the right performance to be some kind of functionality
there.
So if I summarize correctly, the question is what are the downsides?
I would more or less maybe put it at advantages, disadvantages of using Rook to run SEF on
Kubernetes, especially with SEF being quite complex.
Yeah.
Right.
In general, so if you have a decision on the loss of control that may have a concept,
if there is a...
If there's a loss of control on SEF side?
Yeah.
SEF has a lot of nubs and things to configure.
Are there some that we lose and we use Rook?
Oh, I see.
Okay.
And added to that question, if there's anything that's...
Well, you lose when you use Rook SEF.
I guess as a major downside that most people see as well is because you have an additional
layer with Kubernetes being that.
I guess maybe to address that a bit more from what is at least I know the error for some
of SEF ADM.
I think SEF ADM is for Rimmel, correct?
Uses Docker to run containers basically as well, right?
Pudman.
Yeah.
SEF ADM, right?
SEF ADM, for example, at least uses...
Kind of also introduces a scenario, so to say, with Docker slash Pudman.
One that runs container insert here.
It has more or less in regards to installing SEF, for example, in my eyes, but I'm very
biased to containers, obviously.
It has this aspect of here's the SEF image and it should work unless you have something
weird with the host OS going on.
Downside is, again, if Kubernetes just goes completely crazy, the SEF class is probably
also going to have a bad time, but that's kind of then like the weighing of, are you
confident enough, I guess, to run Kubernetes and even running a Kubernetes just for long
term?
Especially with Kubernetes, there's more of this talk about, what's it again, pets versus
cattle.
Instead of just having a cluster for every application or something even and just, oh,
we're done throwing it away versus for, well, obviously something as persistent and important
as a SEF cluster, you can just throw it away then.
From experience so far, I can tell that it is possible to run a Ruke SEF cluster over
multiple years.
I think I...
When did I start mine?
I think I had it running for two years and the only reason I shut it down was because
I had gotten new hardware in another location, I kind of just said it was like, do I migrate
it or do I not mine?
It was just, okay, let's just start from scratch, but it's also because that cluster I'm talking
about there had like 50 other applications running where it's just like, okay, let's
start from scratch anyway, so to say.
In regards to losing control, it's not necessarily.
You don't really have like a...
Like you don't have like a use this disk manual really way besides putting it in the YAML
and fingers crossed the operator takes care of preparing and then applying an OSD to that
disk or even partition.
But it's like, again, I think with most tools there that take away certain aspects at least
in regards to the installation or configuration.
That those points are taking away, but it lies in regards to configuring staff or even
certain aspects.
You can do everything as normal and at least from experience with staff, I guess to put
it like that has gotten a lot better as with the...
Now the config store.
The config store as it basically says, you have a config store in the monitors where
you can just easily set for certain components instead of always having to manually make
changes to any config files on the servers on your storage nodes themselves.
And it has gotten better.
That's awesome.
I would just like to say at a lot of places it gives you a control as well, right?
Because I mean, operator is responsible for reconciliation and taking charge when...
I mean, automated scenarios where we want recovery to happen, right?
And, Seth, the goal is to improve recovery and introductions.
You don't need any unexpected loss of control as well, right?
We would want to give admins a certain level of control.
We don't want them to go ahead and play around with the OSD.
So I think in many of the production scenarios, you need a certain set of control as well,
which Rook actually provides.
So at that point, I would certainly recommend and consider it as an advantage as well.
One, two, three.
Yeah.
Okay.
Please.
Sure.
We need three guys up here.
Okay, please go ahead.
We need forum.
Yeah, exactly.
Please go ahead.
It's a similar question, but do you expect much more performance here, rather than setting
up Kubernetes versus running some time?
Question is, if there's going to be a performance hit in regards to running, Seth and Kubernetes?
Depends on how you run it.
If you run it, like I'm personally preferring running the myRook, Seth clusters always with
host network, but you kind of can already, depending on how far you're with container
or Kubernetes, it goes over, well, host network.
Some like that, some don't.
I personally do more or less just do it because I don't want the traffic to go over the overlay
network.
I have some plug-in, some CNI, container network interface where anyone who wants to look into
that, that takes care of the network between your nodes.
So it more or less depends.
There's a lot of people using, well, just having Rook, Seth talk over the overlay network
as well.
It works fine as well.
It's just a preference, I would really more or less put it at.
Depending on what your network looks like, if you have 10G or something and your overlay
network in the end maybe brings the, like in the IPERF test at least, brings it down
to like 9.0 something, is it worth exposing that traffic to the host network then versus
just having it go over the overlay network?
But again, if you think about it, just another layout to consider.
If you want that, if you don't, and if you don't want that, there's also options like
maltos to allow you some more fine-grained network connections or config in regards to
the interfaces you want to pass in, like different VLANs or something.
But that's like, again, it depends.
Yeah, yeah.
Can you still manage your Seth cluster via the Seth dashboard or is it another dashboard
or do you need two dashboards?
The question was if you can still use the Seth dashboard, maybe just to expand on that
Seth manager dashboard, just to manage your Seth cluster.
To some degree, there is currently not a functionality to add new OSDs, I think, if I remember correctly.
That's one thing as well with the future roadmap part, with the more manager-ability, where
I also kind of looked at the dashboard and was like, wait, I have a create button.
Why?
Oh, why don't we?
But then it's the typical, oh, there's some roadblocks that we just need to get out of
the way and make sure that we are all, especially with operator and even Sethadium and others
out there, we're all aligned on the same way or if there's a manager interface, because
there is even one.
And I think if I understood you correctly or if I heard from the meetings correctly,
they are even looking into improving that interface further, it will hopefully be easier,
thankfully also faster, to have the dashboard as this point of contact as well.
Yeah, there's a lot of work that is currently going on.
I'll just keep it out.
I'll just say that there's a lot of work going on currently in the usability space from the
recent discussions in upstream that we have had to improve dashboard as well from both
Qubectl, from both Kubernetes and all standalone Seth perspective.
It's to make sure that, I mean, you can easily manage and monitor Seth even in the CNCA fold.
There has been recent discussions that have happened to improve it as well from Rook space.
So a lot of work is going on in the usability space.
But if you have any ideas, it'll be most welcome.
And really, it would be great to have, I mean, usability is one thing that really matters
a lot, right?
I mean, user experience is one thing that, I mean, we would certainly cater to improve
in Rook.
Should we have time for one more question?
Yeah.
Is your main use case to provide storage within a cluster where, for example, other applications
or is the use case more to use Kubernetes as an orchestrator for Seth that I put next
to my cluster where my main applications will have basically just the orchestration the
same way I'm not within the cluster.
So the question is, could I maybe modify it a bit more into the direction of, like, how
can you run Rook, I guess?
I think that plays into that as well.
Like you can run Rook, Seth.
You can run Rook, Seth in a way that you connected to an existing Seth cluster that it doesn't
even matter if it's a Rook, Seth cluster, just a Seth cluster works as well.
It mainly takes care of them just setting up the CSI driver then.
I know people use that to some degree as well.
If they have an existing or even an existing Rook, Seth cluster that they want to share
with the others.
There's also in this external mode the possibility of the Rook, Seth operator to manage certain
components.
So that, for example, if you want a file system, you could run those MDS demons that you need
for the file system in that cluster that your Kubernetes is running on then.
That works as well.
It's kind of like those two main external modes.
And obviously the case of running it in the same cluster.
That's kind of like this either you just share what you have or share and allow, like, Seth
file system or Seth objects or you can just run the demons in the same cluster then.
Both works for all the operators.
Does that answer that?
Yeah.
Thank you.
Done?
Any other questions?
There are no questions.
There are a bunch of stickers here for everyone.
Yeah.
Stickers?
And?
Do we have some more?
If you've asked the question just now, just come see me.
You've got a T-shirt too.
And maybe there's some leftover after that.