Please welcome Sanju and Pranik for us and enjoy.
Thank you guys.
Thank you. Good morning guys. I'm Sanju and he's Pranik. We work at Foonpei.
Yeah. Today we are going to discuss about the lessons that we learned while we managed the cluster first cluster at the scale
and some of the problems we have faced and the solutions that we have came up with.
Yeah. Foonpei is the leading Indian digital payments and technology company headquartered in Bangalore, India.
And it uses unified payments interface which is introduced by the Government of India.
So in India, if you are thinking of any payment, you can do it using Foonpei app. This is how our Foonpei app home screen looks like.
And we have like a VC 800K RPS on our edge layer every day and we do 130 million daily transactions.
So this will generate lots of records and this will generate lots of records and that documents that we have to store.
And as per the regulations in India, we have to store all of them in India only.
So Foonpei has a private cloud where we store all these things and we need a service to store and retrieve the files from the cloud.
We have developed a service called DarkStore which will drive the data to GlustrFS and which will fetch the data from the GlustrFS.
So coming to the question, why did we choose the GlustrFS?
We didn't want it to have a metadata server because we have lots of small files and storing all the metadata.
We didn't want it. So GlustrFS has no metadata server.
So we went ahead with it and our team had earlier success in the GlustrFS project.
So they were confident that, okay, GlustrFS will work for our use case. So we are here.
And this is the data flow to and from the GlustrFS.
So all the traffic is fronted by CDM and the request is forwarded to Nginx.
And Nginx will send the request to the API gateway and API gateway can choose to store or retrieve any file from the, any file.
Or it can choose to send the request to any backend service.
Now if the backend service wants to store this file or if it wants a file, it can be a post or get request.
I mean like it can store or it can retrieve. It will send the request to DarkStore.
Now the DarkStore will store the data or retrieve the data from GlustrFS servers.
And DarkStore also uses Elasticsearch to store some of the metadata.
And it uses Aerospipe to store the R3 later info and some of the rate limiting features.
It uses RMQ for asynchronous jobs like deletions and batch operations.
And this is our team.
Today's our agenda is an introduction to GlustrFS.
And then we will discuss about different problems that have faced and the solutions that we are using.
And we have some proposals as a roadmap.
What is GlustrFS? GlustrFS, it is a distributed file system.
That means whenever you do some write, the data is distributed across multiple servers.
These servers have some of the directories. We call them as BRICs.
And this is where the data is actually getting stored.
So this is a typical GlustrFS server.
Each server can have multiple BRICs.
The BRICs will have underlying file system where the data will be stored.
And in the root partition, we store the GlustrFS configuration.
This is how a 3x3 GlustrFS volume looks like.
When I say 3x3, whenever a write comes to GlustrFS mount point.
So how is it one point?
We can mount GlustrFS volume on any machine over the network.
And you can read and write from that machine.
Now from the client where the mount is happened, if any write comes.
So it is distributed across three sub-volumes based on the hash range allocation.
We will talk more about the hash range in the coming slides.
And another three stands for the data is replicated three times.
So whenever a write comes, the data will choose one of the sub-volume and in a sub-volume.
Sub-volume is a replica set.
Here it is a three, so it is replicated thrice.
Over to Praniv.
Hello.
Yeah, so let's look at some numbers that we see at phone pay for doc store service and then to GlustrFS.
In a day we see about 4.3 million uploads and the downloads are 9 million.
With peak upload RPS as 200 and download RPS as 800.
The aggregate upload size per day is just 150 GB, not a lot.
But the download size is 2.5 TB.
So it is completely read-heavy workload.
And this is after a CDN is fronting it.
That means only when the file is not available in your CDN, the call will come to GlustrFS,
which will download the file onto the CDN and then it will be served.
And this is how the RPS is distributed throughout the day.
RPS is request per second.
So the uploads actually are reasonably uniform from 6 am to 5 in the evening.
Then it tapers off for the rest of the day.
Whereas the downloads are in bimodal distribution with one peak at around 12 pm and another at around 7 pm.
The latencies are function of the size of the file.
So we have post upload latencies with mean of about 50ms to the P99 at around 250ms.
Similarly for GEDS, the mean is around 10ms and P99 is around 100ms.
Let us look at the configuration that we use at PhonePave for GlustrFS.
We have 30 nodes in the cluster.
Each node contributes two bricks and one brick corresponds to 10TB and that is a ZFS pool.
So 30 into 20, that is 600TB of available capacity and we use replica 3.
So the available size is 200TB, out of which 130TB is in use at the moment.
Let us now go to the problems that we face and how we solved it.
I will start off with the capacity expansion problem that we solved.
Then Sanju will take over and talk about the data migration problem that we solved.
I will talk about how performance issues are debugged and how we solved the problems using that method.
Then Sanju will finish it off with maintenance activities that we do to prevent the problems.
Before we talk about the capacity expansion problem, let us try to understand a bit about the distribution.
The data is distributed across the servers based on hashes.
In this diagram, we have three distributed subvolumes.
Each subvolume is a replica 3.
When you create a directory, each of the directory in these three replica sets will get a hash range.
Whenever you create a file or try to read a file, it will actually compute the hash of the name
and it will figure out which of these directories in these three subvolumes has that hash range
and tries to get that file or store that file in that node.
For folks who are well versed with the database, this is more like sharding.
The entity here that is getting sharded is the directory based on the file names.
The files actually can have varying sizes.
For example, in our setup, the minimum size would be less than a KB, but the maximum size is like 26 GB.
You will run into this problem where some of the shards or distributed subvolumes that you have
would fill up the space before the others.
You need to handle that part as well.
There is a feature in Lustreff called MinFreeDisk, where if you hit that level,
when you create the directory again, the hash range will not be allocated for the ones that met the threshold.
For example, here, even though there are three distributed subvolumes,
data is going to only two because the middle one actually has met the threshold.
The hash range will only be distributed between the two, 50% and 50% instead of one third that you would expect normally.
Let us talk about the actual process of increasing the capacity and why it did not work for us.
When you want to increase the capacity, that is, you bring in more distributed subvolumes or shards.
The way that you do it is you first do something called as the LustrePier probe.
That will bring the new machines into the cluster.
Then you do another operation called AddBrick that will add the bricks to your volume.
Then you have to do something called as the LustreVolumeRebalance to redistribute the data among the nodes equally.
What are the problems that we faced?
When we did the benchmark, the rebalance had this application latency impact in some cases up to 25 seconds.
As I mentioned, most of the P99 latencies were just in milliseconds.
This will be like a partial outage for us.
This is not going to work for us.
The other thing that we noticed is for large volumes, the rebalance may take up to months.
At the moment, the LustreFs rebalance does not have pause and resume.
We cannot do the maintenance activity in off-peak cars.
That is one more problem.
The other one that we have seen is when you do the data migration,
when it is going from one distributed sub-volume or short to two distributed sub-volumes,
you would expect 50% of the data to be transferred.
That is all right.
When you are going from nine short slash distributed sub-volumes to ten,
you want to only migrate like 10% of the data.
LustreFs is still transferring about 30% to 40% irrespective of what the number of sub-volumes are.
The rebalance itself may take so much time with our workload
that by the time we want to do the next capacity expansion, the rebalance may not even complete.
That is also not going to work for us.
These are the three main problems that we have seen.
This is the solution that we are using now.
Then there is a proposal as well.
Since we know that the hash range allocation is based on both the number of sub-volumes
and number of free sub-volumes, what we are doing is in our Docsor application,
every day in the night we create directories with a new basically.
The directory structure will be something like the namespace that the clients are going to use,
slash year slash month slash day.
Each day you are going to create new directories.
Based on the size that is available,
only the ones that have space will get the hash range allocation.
You will never run into the problem where you will have to rebalance that much
because we have seen that with our workloads, reads are distributed uniformly.
As we have seen, it is read-heavy workload and writes are just a few.
We were okay with the solution in the interim.
Long term, the solution that we have proposed,
and this is something that is yet to be accepted,
but there are some POCs that we did.
Very few use jump-consistent hash instead of the one that we have.
When you are going from 9 to 10 here, it is only about 10 percent that is getting rebalanced.
That is what we want to get to.
This is something that we are focusing on this year.
All right. Over to you, Sanjiv.
Let's look at the problems that we have faced while migrating the data.
We had a use case where we wanted to move complete data
which is present in one server to another server.
In ClusterFest, the standard way of doing this is to use a rebalance operation.
Sorry, replace-brick operation.
When you do replace-brick operation,
there is a process called a self-filled daemon
which will copy all the data which is present in the old server to a new server.
To copy 10 TB data, it takes around two to three weeks.
That is like a huge time.
We wanted to reduce this time, so we came up with a new approach.
Let us understand a few aspects of ClusterFest before we jump to the solution
so that we understand our approach better.
The right-flowing ClusterFest is something like this.
Whenever a right comes, based on the hash range allocation,
it will choose one of the sub-volume.
The data will go to all the servers in that sub-volume.
Now, let's say we have chosen a replica at 0
and the right will go to all the machines in that sub-volume.
It is a client-side replication,
so the client will send the right to all the machines
and it will wait for the success response to come.
The client will assume the right is successful
only when the core number of success responses has come.
Let's say one of the nodes is down.
In our case, we see like a server 2,
either it can be a node down or the brick process is unhealthy.
This can be unresponsive at times.
So something happened.
The right came to one of the sub-volume
and it went to all the three replica servers,
but server 2 didn't respond with the success response.
Now, server 1 and server 3 have responded with the success response.
So client assumes that the right is successful.
Now, when the server 2 is back up,
to have the consistency of the data,
server 2 should get the data which it has missed while it was down.
So who will take care of the job of doing this?
It is SHD.
So SHD is a daemon process which will read the pending heal data,
like whatever the data that was missing, we call it as a pending heal.
So it will read from one of the good copy.
In our case, server 1 and server 3 are the good copies
and server 2 is a bad copy.
So SHD will read the data from one of the good copy
and it will write to server 2.
So server 2 will have all the data
when the self-heal is completed healing the data.
We will use this as part of our approach as well.
Our approach is we will kill the brick
which we want to migrate from the server 3 to server 4.
So we have to copy all the data.
So self-heal is taking 2 to 3 weeks.
Here in our case, we will kill the brick
and we are using ZFS file system.
So we will take a ZFS snapshot
and we will transfer this snapshot from the server 3 to server 4.
It's like an old server to the new server.
And now we will perform the replace brick operation.
While we are performing the replace brick operation,
server 4, that is a new server, will already have all the data
which server 3 had.
Once the replace brick operation is performed,
server 4 is now part of the sub-volume
and the heals will take place from server 1 and server 2 to server 4.
So now we have reduced the amount of data that we are healing.
Previously we are copying all the data.
That is like a 10 Tb of data from server 3 to server 4.
But here in our case, we are healing only the data
which came after killing the brick before doing the replace brick operation.
So the data we heal is reduced hugely.
With this approach, now it is taking only 50 hours to complete this.
That is also, if we are using the spinning disk,
it will take 48 hours to transfer the snapshot of 10 Tb
and 2 hours for the healing of data.
But it is only 8 to 9 hours if we are using SSDs.
If you are using SSD, it takes like 8 hours to transfer the snapshot
and it takes around 40 minutes to complete the heals.
So that is like we came from like 2 to 3 weeks to 1 or 2 days,
or 9 hours we can say.
We are using Netcat utility.
It gave us very good performance.
It is like a 60% performance optimization.
And we have inflight checksum at both the ends,
in the old server and also in the new server.
So that it is like we are checking whether we are transferring the snapshot perfectly or not.
We are not using any data.
And yeah, it is at the time.
I have kept the commands that we have exactly used in this link
and we also have a rollback plan.
So let's say that we have started with this activity,
but we haven't performed the replace brick yet.
Because once the replace brick is performed,
it will be something like this.
The sub volume will already have the server 4 as a part of it.
Before we perform the replace brick,
that means when we are here, we don't want to do this anymore.
All we need to do is start the volume with the force
so that the brick process that we have killed will come up.
Once it is up, the good copies that we have,
SHD will copy the data from good copies to bad copy at the old server
so that we will have the consistent data across all our replicated servers.
Yeah, that is so easy.
And we want to popularize this method so that it helps the community.
Yeah, over to Pranith.
Yeah, so we will now talk about the performance issues that we faced
and how we solved them.
This is the graph that we have seen in our prod setup
while doing this migration when something happened that we did not account for.
So the latencies have shot up to one minute here
and I have said that it is supposed to be only milliseconds
so this is horrible.
There was like two hours of partial outage because of this.
So let's see how these things can be debugged and how they can be fixed.
So we have a method called Gluster Volume Profile in GlusterFS.
So what you do is you start profiling on the volume.
Then you run your benchmark or whatever is your workload.
Then you keep executing Gluster Volume Profile info incremental
and it will keep giving you the stats of what is happening to the volume during that time.
For each of the bricks that are there in the volume,
you will get an output like this where for that interval,
in this case interval 9, for each of the block size,
you will see the number of reads and writes that came
and for all of the internal file operations that you see on the volume,
you will get the number of calls and the latency distribution,
min max average latency and what is the percentage latency
that is taken by each of your file operation internally.
So what we have seen when this ZFS issue happened is the lookup call
is taking more than a second, which is not what we generally see.
So we knew something was happening during lookup operation.
So we did an trace on the brick and we have found
that there is one internal directory called GlusterFS indices exatrop.
To list three entries, it is basically taking 0.35 seconds.
So imagine this, so you do ls, it will just show you three entries,
but it will take like 0.35 seconds, sometimes it even takes a second.
So after looking at this, we found that ZFS has this behavior
where if you create a lot of files in one directory, like millions,
and then you delete most of them, and then if you do ls, it takes up to a second.
So this bug is open for more than like two years, I think.
So we didn't know whether ZFS would fix this issue anytime soon.
So in GlusterFS, we patched it by caching this information
so that we don't have to keep doing this operation.
So now you wouldn't see it if you are using any of the latest GlusterFS releases.
But yeah, this is one issue that we found and fixed.
The second one is about increasing the RPS that we have on our volume.
So there was a new application that was getting launched at the time,
and the RPS that they wanted was not what we are giving.
Basically, they wanted something like 360 RPS or something like that.
But when we did the benchmark, we were getting only like 250 RPS.
So we wanted to figure out what is happening.
So we ran benchmarks on product Gluster itself,
and we saw that one of the threads is getting saturated.
So there is a feature in GlusterFS called client IOT threads
where multiple threads would take the responsibility of sending it over the network.
So we thought, let's just enable it and it would solve all our problems.
We enabled it and it made it worse, like from 250, it went down.
So we realized that there is a contention problem in the client side that we are yet to fix.
So for now, what we did is to, on the containers of DockStore,
where it was doing only one mount,
we are now doing three mounts and distributing the uploads and downloads over.
Yes.
So can you repeat the...
Oh, yeah.
No, I didn't.
It's a Fuse mount.
Yeah, the thread that is saturating is Fuse thread.
Yeah, so the question is, which GlusterFS client we are using?
The answer is Fuse client and the thread that is saturating is Fuse thread.
So what we are doing is we have created multiple mounts on the container
and we are distributing the load in the application itself,
like the uploads will go to all three and even downloads will go to all three.
That is one thing that we did to solve the CPU saturation problem.
The other thing that we noticed, this is like part of the Gluster volume profile output,
where it will tell you for each block what is the number of reads and writes.
We have seen that most of the writes are coming as 8 KB.
So later when we looked at the Java application DockStore,
we saw that the IOW block that Java is using the default size is 8 KB.
So we just increased it to 128 KB.
So these two combined has given us 2X to 3X the number
and we also increased the number of VMs that we are using to mount the clients.
So put all together, we got something like 10X performance improvement
compared to the earlier one.
So we are set for maybe 2-3 years.
Alright, so let's now go on to health checks.
Okay, so for any production cluster,
some of the health checks are needed.
So I will talk about the minimal health checks that are needed for GlusterFist cluster.
So GlusterFist already provides POSIX health checks.
So it is a health checker thread which will do a write of 1 KB for every 15 or 30 minutes.
I mean seconds.
So there is one option to set the time interval in which you want to do this.
So if you set it as a zero, that means you are disabling the health check.
So you can set it as like a 10 seconds or something.
So it sends a write and check if the disk is responsive enough and brick is healthy or not.
If it didn't get a response in a particular time, it will kill the brick process
so that like we will get to know that something is wrong with the brick process.
So the other one we have is the rest of the things are we have a script and we have some config.
These are the things we have kept externally kind of thing.
The POSIX health checks are the one which come with the GlusterFist project.
So the cluster health checks that we have are like we have a config where we will specify number of nodes in the cluster.
So that is like an expected number of nodes in the cluster.
And using the GlusterPeerStatus or GlusterPourList command,
we can check the number of nodes that are present in the cluster.
And we will check if both of them are equal.
If not, we will raise an alert saying, okay, something is something unexpected is happening.
And we will also check whether the node is in connected state or not.
So in the GlusterFist cluster, the nodes can be in different state.
So it can be connected or rejected or disconnected based on how the GlusterFist management daemon is working.
So now we will see whether so the expected is all the nodes should be in a connected state.
We will check whether the nodes are connected or not.
If the nodes are not connected, then we will get an alert saying, okay, one of your node is not in a connected state.
And we have some of the health checks for the bricks as well.
So we have number of bricks that are present in each volume in the config.
And in the GlusterVolumeInfoOutput, you will get how many number of volumes that are present in that volume.
And you will check if they are equal.
The another check we have on the brick is if the brick is not online,
we will get to know it by checking the GlusterVolumeStatus command.
And if it is not online, you will get an alert saying that one of your brick is down.
And so whenever the server is down or the brick is down, there will be some of the pending heals.
And you can check the pending heals using the GlusterVolumeHealInfo command.
And if there are any pending heals, you will see an entry.
So if the entry is non-zero, then you will get an alert saying that, okay, you have some pending heals in your cluster.
That means something unexpected, unwanted is going on.
That can be like a brick is down or node is down, anything.
And we always log ProfileInfo Incremental to our debug logs using the health check
so that whenever we see some issue, like the parent just spoke about some of the issues that we can solve
by looking at the ProfileInfo output.
So in such cases, this output will be helpful.
So we always log into our log backup service.
And the exact commands that we are using are listed in this link.
So we have some of the maintenance activities.
So things can go back sometimes.
So we have a replica 3 set up in our production.
So at any point of time, the core number of brick process should be up
so that the reads and writes can go on smoothly.
So whenever we are doing something which might take some downtime of the brick process
or which can have some load on particular server, at that time, we do it only on one of the server from each replica set
so that even if that server goes down or the brick process running on that server goes down,
we won't be having an issue because there are two other replica servers which can do all the reads and writes.
So we are doing few activities in this way.
One is JFS scrubbing. JFS scrubbing is about doing the checksum of the data.
It will see if the data is in a proper condition or not.
And we do migrations in this way only.
So we are doing it on one server from each replica set so that even if it is down for some time
or something didn't work out, we are in a good place.
And upgrades also we will do in the same manner.
We have done some contributions.
So the data migration part that I have spoke, it's a production ready.
We have used it in our production.
And Pranith has given some of the developer sessions which has many internals of Glustrophis.
They are very useful for any Glustrophis developers who wants to learn about many translators that we have in Glustrophis.
And recently we have fixed one of the single point of failure which was present in the geo-replication feature.
It was merged into the upstream very recently last week.
And this year we are looking at another thing, the hashing strategy that Pranith has proposed.
Once it is accepted at the community, we will take it and develop it.
Yeah, that's all we had, folks. Thank you.
I just want to let you guys know that the production ready thing, we actually migrated in total 375 TB using the method that Sanju talked about.
So it is ready. So you guys can use it.
I think it should work even with basically any file system that has a snapshot feature, it should work.
Yeah, thank you, guys.
Yeah, I think we have a few minutes for questions if you have any. Otherwise, you guys can catch us there.
Yeah.
Yeah. So the question is, how do you handle a disk failure?
So basically, the problem that I showed you where we had the ZFS issue where it was taking like minutes of latency, that was the first time it happened on production for us.
And initially, we were waiting for the machine itself to be fixed so that it will come back again.
And it went for like a week or so. And the amount of data that needed to be healed became too much that it coincided with our PCARS.
So now the standard operating procedure that we have come up with after this issue is, if a machine goes down or disk goes down, we can just get it back on in nine hours.
So why do we have to wait? So we just consider that node dead. We get a new machine. We do whatever Sanju mentioned using ZFS snapshot migration.
And we just bring it up.
Do you have the ZFS backup somewhere? The answer is no. You have the ZFS data on the active bricks.
So you take a snapshot on the active bricks and do the snapshot. Yeah, one of the good ones. Yes.
Any other questions?
That's it, I think. Thank you, guys. Thanks a lot.