Okay, so hi everyone.
Awesome that you're all here.
I'm Jadka, this is Jens, and we will now present Snap, a programming language that we work
on together with Bernat and a few other people that I'll mention in a second.
And what we want to do with you today, or what you have to listen to, is first I'll
explain shortly what Snap is and why we care about it.
Then we'll show our three guiding principles, and if we have time in the end Jens will show
what's under the hood of Snap as well.
Okay, so Snap is a visual blocks-based programming language, and I'll show that to you in a second.
It's also like micro blocks live and parallel, and we develop it together with people at
UC Berkeley in California.
So we have three people, us three working together with three people from UC Berkeley
developing this thing together.
Snap is a blocks-based programming language, but it's aimed at high school and college
students.
But as you will see in a second, you can basically start whenever you want with it.
Okay, our three guiding principles, let's start with the first one, is low floor.
So this means that we really want to have engaging activities for entry-level programmers
so you don't get scared away, and that we really want to have fun activities that they
can do.
To show you that, I've built a super simple, what we call a micro world, so this is an
extension of Snap that I customized myself, and this only has these three blocks here.
And as you can see, you don't even have to read to use them.
We can just try them out and see what happens.
So let me increase the stage size a bit.
So I can click on that.
As you can see, it's live, so I'm clicking on it while it's in the palette and it's still
doing things.
I can click on that.
Nothing happens.
I see, oh wow, there's an input slot here.
Maybe I could type a number in here.
Let's see what happens now.
Ooh, okay, it's doing something.
This is stamping a flower, and this one is supposed to be a sponge.
It's clearing the stage again.
So since we're working with flowers, let me draw a beautiful petal real quick using the
costume editor.
Let's do a yellow one.
Oh, that's brown.
And then let me draw something.
Jip, jip, and let me even fill it maybe.
Yeah, wow, this is very beautiful.
And then let's make this even more beautiful.
And then let's also, that's important, move the rotation center, jip, and let's try the
same thing again.
Ah, okay, this is pretty cool.
So now if I want more flowers, I can build a larger script.
So I can use the central area of Snap to build more complex programs.
So I could go to a random position and draw another flower there, and go to a random position,
and draw another flower there.
And I could click on that forever.
But it would also be cool to just have a forever loop that does that.
So computers are really good at doing things automatically very often, so why don't I make
a loop?
So I already prepared this page here, and let's look for the infinity sign, because
what I want to build is an infinite loop.
And let's just copy that.
And then let's build our own control structure by just hiding it in the actual, ah no, we
don't hide it, let's just do it.
So this is going to be a control block, and I'm calling it infinity.
And this is going to have two inputs.
One is going to be, no it's only having one input, it's going to be the action.
So let me build this block, I already have it here.
So okay, no, let's do that again.
Jip.
Sorry, I'll just delete that and start over again.
Okay, I want to make a control structure, it's called infinity.
I want to add a parameter to that, and this is the action that I'm going to run.
I can even decide what I want this to look like, so as you might know from scratch, our
loops have the C-shaped, or from snap, our loops have the C-shaped command structure,
so I can click on that, and when I apply that, you see that I have the C-shaped block with
this infinity sign on it, and now I need to decide what I want to do with this block.
So first I want to run the action, I don't have a run block here, so let me just open
the hide block section, because I hit all the actual blocks from snap, and I'll show
you how to do that in a second, and let me drag out one of the run blocks, Jip, and what
I want to do is I want to run the action, and then I want to repeat the same thing,
and I want to run the action again.
So I think that's correct, let's try it.
So I made myself a forever loop, and let's clear the stage so we can actually see what's
happened, or what's happening, and let me drag this around here, and now I can run my
program and I built myself my own control structure, and it still looks very simple
for kids, but all of you obviously could do that.
So this is one thing that we really care about, we want really simple entry-level engaging
activities, and this is one of my favorite starter projects, but we also want teachers
to be able, educators to be able to build these micro-verts very easily, and we want
them to be able to customize Snap in a way that they can use it for their needs.
What I also wanted to show you in this project, let me make this stage a bit smaller again,
you can have several what we call scenes in a project, so this is basically a project
in another project, so I can now switch to that scene, and here I already prepared a
petal, and you see that I have more blocks than I had before, I also have a separate
stage so I can switch between scenes, and we can use that idea to build something like
language levels, so in the first micro-world I used, I just had that block that draws a
flower.
In the second micro-world, I want learners to be able to build this flower block themselves,
so we gave them all the tools that they need for that, so here for example, we only have
this block that stamps a leaf, so one of the petals, so what else do I need to build the
flower, I want to do that several times, so I might need a loop, and this one as you can
see has a number as an input, so I can specify the number of repeats, and of course I need
to turn in between, so what we want to do is we want to stamp, let's do a flower with
6 petals, and then I need to turn in between, and also I built this block myself, and I
want to turn 60 degrees each time, so let's clear before we draw a flower, jeep, and then
let's do one, so this is how the flower block was actually built in the first thing, so
we can help learners to gradually get new ideas, and then which I find pretty cool,
it's also super simple in Snap to prepare your own libraries, so I made one if you have
a kid in class that is just faster than the other kids, you can export a library and just
let them add more blocks, so here I added a few more blocks, for example these ones
let me change the appearance of the petal that I have, so this one for example changes
the size of it, let's set this to 100, and then you see the petal becomes super huge,
I can set that to 10, let's clear again, then it becomes super small, so maybe you want
to pick something in between, and we could even do that randomly, so for example I could
add this here, and I want the size to be between 20 and 40, and then I get differently sized
petals each time I do that, so if I do it like this, you see that this changes, and
I really like that about Snap that you can easily expand projects with fun ideas, so
they look differently and are more engaging, but you only need like one or two more ideas,
this one for example switches to the next costume, so if I wanted to add another petal,
let's draw one, let's do the one that I did before, but in blue this time, let's fill
it with something, okay, and then again let's move the rotation center to one of the tips,
and we can now use that, and each time we draw something, we draw a different flower,
so the next one in line, and then again we can combine that with what we had before,
and just create a beautiful flower field with the blocks that we made.
How do you do that if you want to create a micro world?
Let me go to the third one I prepared, so this is not actually a micro world, this is
regular Snap with all the blocks that you have, so as in other blocks best programming
languages we have different categories here, we have the palette on the left where you
find all the blocks for a specific category, as I mentioned before it's a live programming
language, so you can just click them and something happens immediately, and what I also added
here, or what I thought I added here but didn't, oh that's unfortunate, is the, so let's just
build it, is the project, so again we want to have all the blocks that we used last time,
so what we had was the next costume block, we had the set size tool block, we had the
pick random block, we also need a division block, we had a repeat block, we had a forever
block, we had a stamp block, and we had a turn block, and what was the last one?
The second to last one was clear, and what was the last one?
Go to random position, awesome, and we need to go to random position and let's assemble
these so that we actually can make sure that our script is working, so for a flower we
want to repeat a specific number of times, let's do six times, then we want a stamp,
then we want to turn the number of degrees, that's 360 divided by the number of petals
that I want, so six in this case, and before we wanted to do that we wanted to go to a
random position, so let's check that, that seems to work awesome, we wanted to do that
forever and so that all flowers don't look the same, we wanted to set the size to a random
position, a random size, a random number, let's do 20 to 30 maybe, and we need a second
costume so let's just duplicate that one and let's change the color a bit, yeah this is
very different, awesome, this is exactly what I, oh wow, okay, and so we have two costumes
so we can actually also use the next costume block and so we start with a clear stage,
let's add that at the beginning and let's see whether this works, okay awesome, and
now if you want to build your own micro world you can just go to the file menu and select
hide blocks and then that's the awesome thing that we added in the second last, like the
previous release, you can hide all the unused blocks and if I do that I only have the blocks
left in the palette that I used for my project and they are in these categories here and
I can even make the single palette that I had before by clicking on the settings menu
and then selecting the single palette and now you have all the blocks in like one palette
and you can make your own micro worlds that have all the blocks that you need for your
project that you want to do in class or with your kids or with some other people who want
to learn programming and then you can delete that and then you have your perfect Parsons
puzzle generator and so this is again the low floor idea that I mentioned, we really
want to have engaging activities that have a cool artifact that looks beautiful or is
fun to do but we also want to help teachers and educators to create these fun engaging
activities in a simple way.
Okay, the second idea that I wanted to present or that we think is or that we care about
is white walls so we want to allow for a huge variety of projects and the ones that we care
most about are media projects so we love this idea of media computation meaning you learn
general purpose programming by playing with sounds, images, texts and one example of your
project for that is for example from Snap you can access the microphone of your computer
so in this case if it's running it should be this for example is a visualization of
the frequency spectrum of my voice that's just picked up through the microphone so this
looks beautiful at the same time as it's interesting because you can talk about sounds from a physical
and computational perspective and we love to do stuff with the camera so this is another
project that I like very much.
This is pasting the webcam of my computer to the stage right now I set the transparency
to 50 percent let's make it fully transparent so the video is still there but you can't
see it anymore because all the pixels are transparent and then I'm sending a message
to the other sprite and what's that doing is it's drawing dots on the stage which size
corresponds to the brightness that it's measuring in the image that it picks up from the camera
and this is actually a pretty cool technique it's called dithering and this is how images
were made in newspapers back in the days when you weren't able to print different colors
so you just did differently sized dots to get like a more deep color space so this is
what we mean with white walls allow a variety of projects that are engaging and fun and
that also kids who don't necessarily like Fibonacci might find interesting and the last
idea for that I will hand over to Jens is no ceiling so as I said snap is a programming
language that's aimed for high schoolers and early college students so it's scratch
but with all the awesome ideas that make programming fun and Jens is going to show you these now
thank you Jens.
We're having kind of a conflict here because we want to have this low floor and the wide
walls for the kids but we're also having this idealist notion of blow of the ceiling like
we don't want to constrain kids we don't want to dumb down the language so it's okay for
kids and this is kind of coming from the 60s when you know some of you might remember logo
had the idea that you know you don't you don't make stuff easy for kids but you make it welcoming
for kids but you don't constrain it you let kids express everything they can and this
is only one part of the pedagogy the other part of the pedagogy is geared as Marx said
towards teachers towards educators because if you look at these micro worlds that Jager
has shown let me again go to oh yeah this is mine already so here is a bunch of blocks
like these aren't the regular blocks these are the ones that we made okay I need to stay
more in the center of so y'all at home can see me we want teachers to be able to build
these exercises to build these micro worlds for their kids so it's not just us you know
building something here's an exercise you can do with their kids but there's a teacher
there's an educator wants to teach something as yet got it about what was then called you
remember the total turtle trip theorem that was kind of what he had got showed you about
so we build a micro world to that which language are they going to build this sub language
in are they going to have to learn another language to build these little domain specific
languages no you saw yet got build these blocks in snap itself and so we want to take this
even further and find out whether we can maybe even invent a language that lets us build
a block space language inside the block space language and for this we really kind of want
to do things that we can do in the UI we only be able to do it in the language so in this
palette here I made a little block and it shows me some tools so if I click on this
I'm getting some more blocks and I can again hide these it's a very simple block I can
build myself that just shows and hides me some blocks and now I can kind of explore
some of these things so I can for example look at this block that the flower block and
I can see how it is defined and see it is defined with its own blocks so I can open
this and edited but I can also get the definition of this in a program so now I'm getting the
definition of this block and I can see that it's a function I can take this out and I
can do some other interesting things with that so here is our split block for example
I can split hello world by the space and I get hello and world I can split it by letters
and I get each letter so what happens if I split a script by blocks?
If I split a script by blocks I'm getting a syntax tree a table of the syntax elements
in there so I can do this with you know the definition of my flower block and oh wow so
I can so this is a table so I can also flatten this so I'm not saying I don't want the length
of this I want it flattened so now I'm getting a list of all the syntax elements that make
up the definition of this flower block and that's kind of interesting because now I can
find out for example so here I can take out the turn block and I can say you know do all
of these does this list contain this turn block and says yes the turn block is part
of the definition of this list so but what about for example the clear block is that
also in there?
No it's not present in there so this is interesting I could maybe discover something else so
what I can I can look at all the blocks that I have in this micro world this is a list
of all the blocks in this micro world so I'd like to find out which blocks contain this
turn block so I could say you know I want to keep I want to filter from my blocks those
that contain this block let's see whether that works yeah so I'm getting a list of two
blocks that all use this block now I can turn this into its own block I make a block that
says this is the collars of a block block and the block should be an input so I'm saying
this is a block and in order to define this well I just did define this I just dragged
this in and I say okay this should work for any block so not just this block but for any
block and so now I have this block that gives me the collars of for example this block let
me see whether it works so this block is used by two other blocks and this block isn't used
by any other block and huh let me see maybe I can get a whole report by looking at all
the blocks and by mapping over all the blocks I want to see the block and I want to see
its collars right so what we're now doing is really an introspection of the system of
the block system in itself so if I map this I'm sort of getting this interesting structure
so data structure it's a table and it's a graph really a reverse dependency graph of
all the blocks and the blocks it uses and I get a report of the overall structure of
my micro world and folks this is something interesting as you think about this so we're
starting with this easy simple thing that we can build worlds for kids and we want to
build these little domain specific languages but we want to have a language that actually
lets us build these things in itself and this is why we build introspection and kind of
all the goodies of functional programming into this language but we didn't want to make
it so that you kind of have to go down to memory addresses but we want to represent
everything in blocks and this is kind of the idea of no ceiling because at one point you
know we start doing this with kids but we actually build it for the University of California
at Berkeley and they're using it for their introductory course of computer science for
non-majors and you know this goes up quite a long way so we actually want to be able
to do scheme in this and to really teach abstraction so at one point you really want to blow off
the ceiling and we don't want to do just only this imperative style programming where you
know one follows the other and you've got the puzzle pieces but we actually do a high
order function you do kind of recursive you build your own control structures you build
your own language it's a little stiff and it's challenging to try to accommodate you
know the let's draw a flower with a bunch of three blocks to let's invent our own programming
language in the same environment and in order to build such an environment the whole thing
that you see here your nerds I can show you right the whole thing you see here isn't using
blockly or library but what you're seeing here is actually an operating system that
runs inside a single canvas element in the browser and there's sort of a pill you can
take to switch to dev mode and you're sort of inside this environment that some of you
might recognize looks a lot like squeak so anybody you know squeak and so it's kind of
the same morphing environment where you could just get you know any things you can directly
manipulate them for example you can make this bold but you can also use this to you know
let's make a slider I can attach the slider set the target to the string morph to the
font size I can change it I can make it horizontal and now my slider governs for examples the
size the font size of this I can make other elements like for example color palette and
I could set the target of the color palette also to the string and now I can change the
color and the size I can still edit it so this is basically our own system that is kind
of self sustained in the browser and everything that you see in snap is sort of an application
inside this really OS inside the browser and comes with its own green threading model which
is how we do parallelism so in order to go up on the ladder of abstraction on the back
hand side we have to go kind of down to not the metal but to kind of a metal of sorts
of the browser okay this was kind of our ideas if you'd like to check it out it runs on snap.berkeley.edu
give it a try yourself you'll find lots of material there is it's open source by the
way it's free and open source it's an AGPL license so if you want to know so it's copy
left it so you know everything is open source about it we write the front end the back end
the community side it's not as big as some other languages but we've got a vibrant community
it's all hosted on github please do contribute please do fork it many people have forked
it please let us know what you think and thanks for coming.
So I found that really fascinating and as a list programmer I couldn't help but think
about macros when you were showing the exploding of blocks so would it be possible once you
get the abstract syntax tree to annotate it let's say add a sound between each step and
then recreate a new block from an existing block.
Yes if we had more time I could show you this we do have macros okay yes so I showed you
the split block which takes apart the stuff we has a join block that you can pass in a
text and text trace but yeah.
Well this is running in the web in a browser so your phone can run the thing in a browser
what you get here is you can publish it as a URL and yes and then you can run it on the
phone and it's something I like to do with kids a lot it's also interesting if you do
stuff on touch devices like on tablets or stuff like that you kind of need to be considerate
of which gestures to use because you don't have mouse over or you know so yeah it's fun.
And you can also embed it on iFrames in your website.
Yes please.
I was wondering like in your mind about the future do you see anything like that this
is becoming more mainstream and also for adults like one programmer building their own stuff
with something like this.
That's a good question I really have this dream that I think blocks based programming
if we take away the kitty stigma of it and if we dare move on from this sometimes horrible
imperative paradigm to the beauty and joy of functional programming that you know we
get these expressions that actually make things easier to understand that make things more
accessible and that this is a great way to be to actually you know express many things
inside professional development so we write the software in a way that we like to use
it ourselves and we hope that it might convince others to actually build and embed this into
enterprise applications because often enough if you think about these low code no code
things you know you move you click together some pre-configured stuff but then you need
to write some glue code and the glue code often enough is terrible and awful and this
is where I would love to see a blocks based environment that has no ceiling.
Yes.
It is this scheme in the browser.
Exactly.
And we do have stickers and buttons here take all you want.
Yeah.
Thank you very much again.
Thank you.