All right. Hello, everyone. Thanks for coming. My name is Adam. I work for Red Hat and I
do CentroStream for Day Job. I'm the CentroStream lead. And I want to talk to you about CentroStream
and how we, Red Hat, use it to get work done on RHEL and how you can use it to participate
but also build your stuff. We'll see. Okay. So just to set the context, before CentroStream
we did something like this, like when we created RHEL, we took what's in Fedora, that's where
the innovation happens, and then we had a long process to build RHEL out of some of
that and when that got out somewhere later, CentroStream, Centro's Linux happened. And
yeah, that was interesting but the problem was that when you find something in that rebuild,
you can't really change much because the goal was to be a rebuild of RHEL. So what we did
with CentroStream, we kind of switched it a little bit. Now the process is like there's
more steps. So we have Fedora still. There's nothing changing about Fedora, that's still
the primary place. Where innovation happened, that's the upstream. Where something called
Fedora ELN, which is like a subset of the content, rebuilt with RHEL configuration,
and that's the next major RHEL release. So if you go out and look at Fedora ELN, that's
what RHEL 10 is sort of right now. Then CentroStream happens, this is where the development of
RHEL happens in public. And if you talk to Red Hatters, they will sort of somehow combine
these together, CentroStream and RHEL, because this is really our development space. And
I'll have more details later. So this is tracking the next minor version of RHEL, and this is
what you can use, but you can also contribute to it, and we'll get into details. So this
is basically if you heard Fedora ELN and CentroStream, this is what it is. And I have some more details
here. This is Fedora, Fedora-wide sources. This has its own sources, and this is the
real build flag. And you can also see there's a different amount of packages. This is like
more information there. Okay, so let's talk about how we get work done, or how you can
get work done in CentroStream, how that works. So there's this diagram, and we're not going
to go box after box, no worries, but I just want to demonstrate that you see that we have
Bugzilla where work tracking happens, there's a merge request coming to the GitLab, and
then basically everything is synced. So the upper part is the CentroStream infrastructure.
This is RHEL internal infrastructure. And as change happens, it gets built in both,
it gets tested in both, and when that passes test, both get released further to the process,
and finally it gets into both RHEL and Centro. There's something called Centro's development
compose and production compose, which is basically when this compose is sort of like a repo and
ISO and container images, it's like a snapshot that you can consume. And, yeah, there's one
that happens after the test, that happens every day, and then the verification, this
is like an internal process paperwork and stuff, and then that goes to the production
compose. And I can even show you how that happens in the system. So this is what a Bugzilla
bug looks like, someone was adding, this is like half a year ago, a multi-pass TCP to
RHEL, so they created this, they did the merge request in GitLab, everything was visible
publicly, and they submitted a build first in CentroStream, that got through, got built
in RHEL as well, if I scroll down there's tags, that was like the multiple steps, the
gate pending candidate, that's how you can know where it's in the process, and it basically
got through that, and now if you're using CentroStream, you already have it installed,
because that's half a year ago for that change, but this is basically the flow, how it works.
Let's talk about contributions now. For some context, I'm starting with RHEL 8, Red Hat
publicly said that we'll do minor releases of RHEL every six months, and major releases
of RHEL every three years, and this is what we've been sort of doing, 8 and 9, and something
called ABI, I got that as a note for myself, with RHEL we make some promises to customers
about ABI guarantees and support statements, et cetera, basically whatever you would expect
from Enterprise OS, so we don't want to break things for customers in the major version,
and this will influence what contributions we can take, so the easiest one is bug fixes,
if you find a bug and you can fix it, feel free to do so, we'll be very happy to take
it, test it, and if it doesn't break things for the customers, merge it, get it in, and
that's the easiest way to contribute. You can also contribute stable updates from upstream,
and by stable, that gets to the promises, basically as RHEL ages, it gets further from
the upstream, because we need to keep things sort of stable in the ABI way, so we still
release updates, like every single minor release, but most of them are backwards, so again,
welcome to contribute updates, our stable will fix them, fix and test them, build them
and get them in, but yeah, and backported features, this is what I mentioned, basically
already, I just have a slide for that, okay, what we can take is the ABI noncompatible
updates, and if you're wondering about details, there's the document called RHEL application
compatibility guide, you can find it online on Red Hat's website, and it will explain
exactly how it works, but most packages have the ABI stable for the entire ten years of
the life cycle, and we take it pretty seriously at Red Hat, because customers build applications
and they want them to run forever without changing them, so we don't want to break this
for them, so please don't submit things that would break ABI, we would need to politely
explain why not, and reject it, that's what you can contribute to Fedora, ELN, for example,
we'll get to that.
Okay, I have maybe for docs, typos, man pages, there's a thing for customers, if they go
to the customer portal and they have a bug with documentation, they can report an issue
and get it fixed that way, otherwise we tend to batch them together, so they land all at
once, so maintainers can focus more on actual feature development, backporting and stuff,
so these are welcome, but they might take longer to get in because of this.
And this is a detailed image of the life cycle, if you want to get your change into a specific
minor version of RHEL, we don't have a way in the bugzilla to really communicate it,
you can get in touch with the maintainer, you can anticipate, by the way, minor release,
this is the dark blue, extended update support, this is the light blue, and then update services
for SAP, so even like we're done with minor, we're still maybe supposing it for up to four
years, and the arrows is where the syntax framework happens, so it tracks all of them
and just changes make it to the minor releases, and yeah, you can sort of anticipate what
it gets, but there's no communication, like where exactly, so if you really need to, you
would need to talk to the maintainer.
We have this for eight, and there's also seven, there's a lot of things going in the background.
And if you want to contribute, let's talk about how.
So you can open bugs in bugzilla, you can test stream, if you find something, you can
open bugs and hopefully get it into the next minor release, you can open merge requests
in GitLab, create a GitLab account, but first please make sure that you have a bug, so you
start the conversation with the maintainer, so they know what's coming, and they can also
help you with the change.
And then you can track the change, this is again from the diagram, we have these three
tags in Koji, which we use to track the process, and you can preview things in the production
compose page where it gets.
You can get the composites on this URL, and there's slash production slash development,
but otherwise they go to the mirror, so if you go to Centos or you will find Centos stream
there.
Okay, let's have a look at use of Centos stream, of course you can use it to preview rel test
features that are in development, see what's coming before it actually gets to rel.
I think one of the interesting part is that you can use it, if you build something on
top of rel, you can use Centos stream in your CI to preview how it would work on the future
rel, so you can get ready for the next minor release.
One advantage, like compared to a rebuild, is that if you find a bug in Centos stream
you can actually get it fixed for you and get it in rel proper, so this is like what
we're trying to do there.
And this is actually one of the most interesting for me, so we have special interest groups,
there's like the Hyperscale SIG, there's Cloud SIG, there's the K-mode SIG, and they work
in the Centos stream community and they build their own stuff on top of Centos stream, so
they have like a stable enterprise platform, but again compared to a rebuild they can actually
influence what's happening, they can submit changes and break things for them and get
it into rel proper, I know the Hyperscale SIG they're maintaining a bunch of stuff before
they actually merge it, and there's really interesting stuff going on, you're welcome
to come in and create your own SIG and use the community build system to build everything
and Centos stream is definitely there as the primer build targets.
So that was mostly Centos stream, I have something about Centos stream 10 and rel 10 as well,
basically we've saw this diagram and with rel 10 we're right here, so if you want to
contribute towards rel 10, get it in Fedora rawhide, which means it gets in Fedora ELN
if it's within the rel package set, and at this point you can change ABIs, you can do
whatever Fedora would normally do through Fedora changes, so this is like the most flexible
time of contribution to, towards Centos stream 10 and rel 10, and later when we get to do
stream, this is from rel 9, but the process is the same, we have rawhide and Fedora ELN,
imagine this like get branches and Fedora rawhide is the rebuild ELN, follows it and
we branch Centos stream from that and then later start doing rel, and yeah, we call that
bootstrap that phase that will be happening somewhere later, and yeah, that's how it happens,
so you can get your changes to Fedora ELN right now, and that was a different
process.
yangud
you