Hi and welcome everyone.
I'm here today to speak to you a little bit about Wiki Media's open source ecosystem.
So I assume all of you know what Wikipedia is.
And maybe some of you know that it runs on a software that is called MediaWiki.
So all the wikis run on this software but there's also tens of thousands of websites
around the world that use this.
A very cool example is NASA is using it for some other projects.
But this is sort of the core of Wikipedia and the other projects and it's of course
something that is open source that anyone can contribute to.
But it's not what I'm going to be talking about today.
Because surrounding Wikipedia and all the other projects there is a huge ecosystem of
software tools.
You can think of these as like third party integrations.
People build bots that do edits on Wikipedia that fight vandalism.
There are machine learning algorithms.
There are pipelines for data that then go to research purposes.
There's a lot going on.
So I'm going to be talking about this part.
Just a quick word about me.
I'm a software engineer with a technical engagement team.
You can see we're part of the technology department.
And our team is kind of split into parts.
We have the cloud services team, SREs and engineers that build services and platforms
for all these tool developers.
Then we have developer advocacy.
They do a lot of things.
They are writing documents and running outreach programs.
And doing everything so that our technical contributors can build cool stuff on top of
our platforms and content.
So just to give you an idea of the scale of this, we have over 300,000 editors that contribute
to Wikimedia projects every month.
Wikimedia Commons, which is the project that is for free media files, videos, images, so
on.
There are now over 90 million media files on there.
And we have 1.7 billion unique devices that access Wikimedia against statistics for every
month.
So some of you may recognize at least some of these projects.
Of course, Wikipedia is the flagship.
There are other ones like Wikidata, Commons that we just mentioned, the dictionary, and
many more.
So yeah, we're going to take a look at these tools, ecosystems that I mentioned in the
beginning.
And we're going to start from Wikipedia.
This is the thing that most people know about us.
And from there, we're going to explore the tools that are community created software
that interacts with and contributes to Wikimedia project in some way.
An example here is PyWikibot.
It's a framework for building bots.
So if you have a wiki and you want to run some kind of bot that does something, some
type of edits, you would very likely use PyWikibot as a framework to develop this.
And yeah.
From the tools themselves, we're going to go and have a look at the services and the
platforms that support them.
And we're going to start with an example of a couple tools and how they actually integrate
with one of the projects.
So this is a wiki project called Women in Red.
And a wiki project is a group of users from Wikipedia that decide that they want to work
on something specific, they come together to work as a group.
And in this case, it's to fight the content gender gap.
So they observed that only around 15% of English Wikipedia biographies were about women.
And as of the 23rd of January this year, they have managed to take this number up to around
90.45% in about seven or eight years.
And so where does this very precise statistic come from?
You can see mentioned here and in red it's something called human nicking.
And so this is what we would call a tool.
And in this case, this is a dashboard.
It provides statistics about the gender gap on all the Wikimedia projects.
And you can see here that female content is the orange part and then the rest is male.
And if you go to this website, you can see it in a more granular way by country, by project,
by date of birth and so on.
So if you want to contribute to this project, an easy way to do it is to go to this Wiki
Project site and you can see different lists that have been curated.
For instance, here we can see female activists.
So you can get a list of all the female activists.
And there are many, many categories like this.
And some of these lists are curated by humans, but most of these lists actually come from
a bot that's called a Stereobol, which makes queries on Wikidata, which is another one
of the projects.
You can think of it like a huge knowledge graph that you can query using a similar language
to SQL.
It's called Sparkle.
So you can use Wikidata to get lists with very high granularity.
You can have activists from Germany or activists from Germany that were born after a certain
date.
And so this is what the Stereobol does.
So we have seen two different tools.
One was a dashboard, one was a bot.
And there are thousands of these tools.
There are thousands of maintainers.
And we're going to take a look at how we sustain these people.
So I mentioned that my team is the cloud services team.
And what we do is we provide hosting.
We provide compute, virtual machines.
We provide data services for all these tools to function.
So again, to give you an idea of the scale of this, 30% of all the edits on Wikipedia
as of 2020 were made by bots hosted on our services.
For Wikidata, that number is a little bit higher.
It's around 50%.
So just to make you aware that this is a quite important part of the ecosystem.
So I mentioned there are thousands of tools.
And as of a couple years ago, we now have a catalog where you can browse and search
and find a tool you need for your project.
Or if you are a tool maintainer, you can add it here so that people know it exists.
Then what you see here are lists that have been curated.
We have something called a Coolest Tool Award.
If you look down, you can see that Humanike was one of the award-winning tools in 2021.
Some of you may recognize this as a Jupyter notebook.
So this is a Jupyter hub deployment that we have that is directly integrated with all
of our data services so that people can access dumps, they can access Wiki Replicas, they
can access a lot of things that otherwise would be gigabyte and gigabyte and gigabyte
of data they would have to download onto their own computers.
A similar tool is called Quarry.
It's a public query interface for Wiki Replicas.
Wiki Replicas, I didn't mention it.
There are replicas of our production databases.
And the cool thing about this is that all the queries are public.
So people can actually search and see other people's queries and be inspired.
Or if you're not very good with SQL, well, you can adapt someone's query to your needs.
Here you can see a specific query.
So these services are still kind of tools that serve this ecosystem, but we also need
somewhere to host them.
So we have a platform as a services offering.
It's called Toolforge.
It's not quite as fancy as Heroku or DigitalOcean or anything of this sort.
If you look closely, you see that you have to actually SSH into it.
But it's still very powerful and very convenient for our users.
It integrates again with data sources and it has managed databases, a Redis instance,
a Elasticsearch cluster that everyone can use without having to maintain all these systems
themselves.
So yeah, the back end here is Kubernetes.
Then for more complicated projects, some projects need more compute, for instance.
We also have a Cloud VPS offering so that people can spin up their own virtual machines
and basically do what they want on them.
So this runs on top of OpenStack.
And how could one get involved with this?
So it's possible to get involved in any of these layers, either as a tool maintainer
or as maintainer of any of these platforms.
And that's kind of the thing I wanted to highlight a little bit today, is that this is kind of
a unique opportunity to actually contribute to platform and to infrastructure.
We have people that work with our team and they are on our IRC channels and they push
patches just like everyone else.
And if you don't know, you would think they are just another software engineer on the
team.
And I asked some of them, what brings you here?
And of course, many of them associate with their free knowledge and free knowledge movement
and open source and all of that.
But many also said that this is a unique opportunity to actually play with things like OpenStack
or Terraform or Kubernetes in a situation where actually you have real traffic and real
users which is something that is kind of very difficult to do at home.
And there are not many other projects where you would have this possibility.
So some ways to get involved.
We have several outreach programs.
We have Outreachy which is an internship that runs twice a year.
It's targeted more towards underrepresented demographic.
Google Summer of Code, that's once a year.
And both programs are open to anyone.
So you don't have to be a student.
You can be someone who is changing careers or doing some kind of a letter move.
Google Summer of Code has also become more flexible.
It's not just summer anymore.
There are shorter projects.
There are longer projects.
So that could be a way to get involved and get some kind of hands-on mentorship.
Another way would be to come to the Wikimedia Hackathons.
We have one in Athens in May this year.
And then one is part of Wikimedia that takes part in Singapore, that is in Singapore in
August.
And of course if you are brave you can just dive right in because everything we do is
open and it's out there on the internet.
Documentation of course but like just even our project boards and fabricator that's a
collaborative software for task management and such.
So if you go there you will see that there is a huge variety of tasks.
You can see the work boards of different teams at the foundation.
You can see volunteer led projects and projects where people work together alongside each
other.
So a way could be simply to find something that interests you and look at the documentation
and then come on our IRC channels and contact us and that's it.
So yeah I have added some links which can be helpful to get started.
And you are of course free to just reach out to me.
I had my Twitter handle on the first slide.
My slides are published on the website.
We have 45 seconds for questions.
Thank you.
Thank you Sabina.