Hello everyone. It's good to be back. It's been a while. This is my first time giving
a talk here. I'm really pleased to be here. My name is Joe. I am a coder. I work in London
for local government. I work a lot with geospatial data and I am a Python programmer. Have we
got any Python coders in today? Anyone using Jupyter? Cool. Right, so let's go. So in lockdown
in 21, we had a census in England and Wales and the data is coming now. Most of the data,
all of the data, sorry, is spatial data. So we want to look at this on a map. Why? Most
of the data is geospatial. In local government, everything that we do generally happens somewhere,
whether it's collecting a bin, looking after young people, looking after old people, cleaning
the streets. We always have to think about where this is happening. Apparently, 60% of
all data is geospatial data. So I spend a lot of my time making maps in terms of data
for this. Now, I'm going to be focusing on one part of the census data set today and
that's the east end of London in an area called Tower Hamlets. This may be familiar to some
people if you've ever seen places like Columbia Road, Bethnal Green, Canary Wharf. These are
all parts of the east end of London and this is the main area I'm going to be talking about.
So where is Tower Hamlets in London? So what you can see here is a very small area. It's
20 square kilometres. But this is quite a special area because in the whole of England
and Wales, it has the highest population density. It has the most people packed into a small
area. It also has the fastest growing population. So it's becoming more and more dense. So in
terms of providing services for residents, we need to have a big think about where all
the people are and how they fit in. Now, when we make maps, the first thing we usually do
is we make a Coropleth map. However, the data set for population density in our area, and
I do apologise, I couldn't fit it all on screen, it doesn't appear very well as a Coropleth.
The reason is because the data set is not very evenly distributed. There is, as we will
see, some areas with extremely high population density. So over here you've got Whitechapel.
We have very high population density in Whitechapel. Over here we have a new development which
used to be industrial land. Again, very, very high density developments, big towers full
of people. And then we also have, just to the south of the financial sector, some areas
with a very high population density with a lot of people packed into a small place. But
in terms of the data viz, this map doesn't really help very much. So the Coropleth data
viz didn't work for us. So we began to think, what else can we try? And we checked the data
distribution and sure enough, we've got some serious outliers. This is why the Coropleth
map didn't work very well for us. So what did we do next? We tried to log transform
the data. And yeah, you can see this area here. You can begin to see the density there.
There's quite a few large developments with a lot of people squeezed in. Whitechapel,
you don't see so much happening there. But you do see just to the south of the financial
sector, high density of population. The areas with low density, this is where all the banks
are. So obviously there's no people living in there. This is an old dock near to the
Tower of London. There's no people living there. There's some very nice pubs though,
if you ever find yourself in that area. The Dickens Inn is excellent. I can recommend
that to everybody. And then up here in the north, we have Victoria Park, which is where
the east end borders with Hackney. And obviously there's no people there, at least having their
address registered there. Log transform data looks better on a corrupt
left map. However, you can see the legend. You lose the data. So you can try to fix the
legend. But we want to write as little code as we possibly can. We don't want to keep
fixing legends and things like that. So we began to think about other ways to visualize
our data set. So what did we do? I am a Python coder, but there's a really nice package in
R called Cartogram. And this is a technique called a density equalization algorithm that
basically turns your data set into a Voronoi first, and then it rescales the polygons from
the Voronoi relative to an attribute of the data. This technique is quite popular. There's
a wonderful geographer called Danny Darling, who has an amazing website called World Mapper,
which I strongly recommend you have a look at. And they do things like showing poverty,
inequality, food pressure all around the world. And they size the geographies relative to
the attributes of the geospatial data. So this is a great technique. There is one issue
here though, is that if you want to overlay different layers, then it becomes difficult.
And also the map does look a little bit unfamiliar as well. But it does show particularly where
you have clustering, where you have a number of census areas, and I'm going to say a little
bit more about census areas, where you have a few together that have high data attribute
value, then they all get bigger together. So what we can see here is just to the south
of the financial sector, you can see there's a lot of worker bees all crammed into this
place, and then it increases the volume on the map. So it's a nice database, but still
we have a small challenge if we want to add more data over the top. And also it's a bit
unfamiliar for people that don't use cartograms. So this is a map made using Data Racker. It's
a very nice website. And they have something called a symbol plot. And what this does is
it just basically shows little mountains, little peaks that show the value of the data
attribute that you're interested in at the place where that data is happening. And so
again we can see over here you've got Whitechapel, lots of people packed in there, just to the
south of the financial sector, lots of people packed in there, the new developments here
by the river in Blackwall and here by the river in the old industrial zone. So this
is quite interesting. It gives us some context and it gives us the data. I really like this
database, but it's Data Rapper, so it's not FOSS and it's not Python, and I like to use
Python. So it was great, but it helped, but it didn't do everything that we needed it
to do. The other thing that you will notice, and I'll try to explain this briefly, is that
we have one really high value here. And there's a reason for this. It's an outlier because
actually it's this value here. It's an outlier because, and the reason why it's an outlier
is because the actual census area is really, really small. And the thing about the people
who produce the census data is that they have to create census areas using roughly 100 to
600 people. Generally speaking, it's about 300 people, but they have to make it all fit
together like a big jigsaw puzzle. So sometimes it's hard for them to make it work really
well. So in this case, this census area with really high density is actually just one building.
And so it's not a particularly big building, but everyone's squeezed in there. So yeah,
so the data is quite hard to work with, but it is interesting. So when I was working with
Data Wrapper, I really liked it. And it did remind me of when I was young and I was reading
Lord of the Rings books, I used to really like the map at the front of all these mountains,
showing the Misty Mountains in those books. And so I was thinking I could probably make
a mountain with Python. How hard can it be? It turns out it's really easy. This is the
essence of the library. It's just one function. You take a point on a map, you turn that point
into a line. The line has a start point, which is just a couple of points of longitude, a
tiny little bit of longitude to the west of your point. Then you convert your point to
a latitude, which is kind of like a proxy for the height of the mountain using some
kind of algorithm that you choose. In my case, I'm just like using a range. So I take the
minimum and maximum value of the input range, which is a separate function here. And range
one is essentially the minimum population density and the maximum. And then I convert
that to latitude values. And then the third point on the line is just a little bit of
longitude to the east of my point. And then you use that to create a small triangle. Really
easy, really easy, and a lot of fun as well. So this is what I made with Python. And it's
very similar to the data wrapper map. But I was going for like a kind of hand-drawn kind
of a look to make it look like something from Lord of the Rings. And it's the same thing.
You've got Whitechapel here. You've got the financial sector here. And so on and so on.
So that was fun. But population density, we were just talking about the reasons why it's
a messy data set. There's one place in Chelsea which has a population density of 2 million
people per square kilometre. So this is a very difficult data set to represent using
any tools available. So it's interesting. The other thing about Kensington in Chelsea
is this is where Grenfell Tower is, if anybody knows about that story. This is where it happened.
So let's try some other data sets to see if they're really messy. This is people that
live in one-bedroom homes. So this is tiny little flats filled with people. And so you
can see all the worker bees for the financial sector. A lot of those are living in one-bedroom
flats. And actually the new build. This is a very new development here. And this is a
very new development here. So it looks like people who are building homes now are building
a lot of one-bedroom homes. Two-bedroom homes. Generally everything is kind of the same.
Nothing really jumps out here. Three-bedroom homes. What you can start to see with three-bedroom
homes is that it's generally even. But actually in this area here, which is Bowe, which is
near the Bowe Bales Church, which is used to decide if someone's a traditional East
End Cockney or not, that's kind of this area really. So the Cockneys seem to have three-bedroom
homes generally. And then four or more. And what you see here is in the areas where the
financial workers live, there's still quite a lot of four-bedroom homes. But in some of
these new build areas, there's very, very few relative to the rest of the area. So let's
look at another slightly more famous area. This is Westminster in central London. And
so you can see this is where Hyde Park is. There's no one living there. Again, this is
the population density data set. And then you've got an open street map, base map, just
to help with orientation. And then in a future version of the module, I think I might do
some more stuff with open street map. And then if you look at some of the outer London
areas, and this is where I live, you can see areas of urban density. But you can also see
some very suburban areas where the population density is lower. This is like where most
people are living in houses, basically. And you can also see green space. So we're nearly
finished. I just want to give a massive shout to nbdev. It's really good if you use Jupyter.
Just check it out. Number one, if you're trying to do version control on Jupyter notebooks,
it helps you with any clashes and any merge conflicts because it removes the metadata
in the JSON that sometimes causes conflicts. If you have a team of people working on the
same notebook, this is a real lifesaver. And also it just bakes in good practice. So it
means that your code gets shared on GitHub really easily. It helps you or encourages
you at least to write good documentation for your team and the community. It also encourages
you to write good tests. And it enables you to publish modules. So big shout to them.
I'd also like to thank Jaric, who has produced a wonderful PWA for Fostem called Sir John
O'Rocks. Do check it out. It's a really good way of looking at the schedule for Fostem
and you can watch the videos with Sir John O'Rocks. And also Ed, who's going to be giving
a really cool talk on OSM and Wikidata. And finally, I'd like to thank all the council
coders everywhere. Thanks for having me.