Hi, everybody. My name is Drew Devault, and today I'm going to give a quick talk giving
you a sneak peek at a microkernel I've been working on called Helios. So why should we
write new kernels? These are the reasons that I came up with for writing new kernels. You
know, is Linux good enough? I don't know, but kernel hacking is really, really fun,
so I'm enjoying myself working on it, which is reason enough. I also want to prove if
the programming language Herr is useful for writing kernels. Herr is a programming language
I developed along with many of the people in this room and many people outside of this
room, which one of the stated goals is to be useful for systems programming and to be
able to write kernels with. So in order to prove that that's possible, we have to write
a kernel. Other goals is I want to know if we can do better than the SEL4 microkernel,
which is a microkernel that inspired a lot of the system design for Helios. And if I
were to be particularly ambitious and bold, I would wonder if it's possible to do better
than Linux. And so we've had Linux now for, what, 30 years? Maybe a little bit less than
30 years. And I think it's time for some innovation in kernels. SEL4 is cool, but maybe we can
do better. And you know, at the end of the day, we're having fun doing it and that's
enough. So enter Helios. Helios is a microkernel, which again is largely inspired by SEL4 and
is written in Herr to prove that Herr can be used to write kernels and also because
it's fun to write kernels and maybe we can make it good. It runs right now on x86.64
and ARM64 and support for RISC-V is coming, which is all of the targets that Herr presently
supports. The kernel itself is quite small. The portable code base is about 8,500 lines
of code. And then on top of that, for each architecture, we have about 3,000 lines of
code. And that's it. That's the whole microkernel. The kernel is licensed under the GNU public
license and I suppose here, I should mention these small line codes don't include the boot
loaders, which themselves maybe add 2,000 lines of code per target. And it's written
in Herr, which is again a systems programming language that I designed with the help of
about 80 contributors. This is the pitch from the website, but the short version is that
Herr is a systems programming language, which is designed to be very simple. We have a specification
which is less than 100 pages. We have a small compiler. We have a minimal runtime, manual
memory management. And the goals is to use it for systems programming. So that includes
others, daemons, system tools, and also things like kernels.
Further about Herr, again, it's a general purpose systems programming language. So in
addition to kernels, we also use it in user space on Linux and FreeBSD, working on OpenBSD
and NetBSD user space support as well. We've been working on it now for about three years.
And the footprint of the programming language is also small. We have an 18,000 line compiler,
our backend cube, not LLVM. Our backend is cube, which is about 12,000 lines of C99.
And together, this is enough to bootstrap the compiler plus, you know, bin utils is
required. And it runs again on these three targets.
If you've never seen any Herr code before, I just have a small sample here. I'm not going
to go into too much detail about exactly what any of this code does. But this is just what
it looks like. If you're familiar with C, a lot of things here probably look fairly
recognizable to you. Some things maybe don't. Namespaces are nice, you know. But this is
just a peek at what Herr looks like. And this particular code sample is the entry point
for the Helios microkernel. So this is the first line of portable code. There's also
some architecture specific setup code, and the bootloader runs before any of this. But
this is the first line of code that runs on all architectures.
So what is Helios? What is the goal of the design? It's a microkernel, so it's designed
to be as small as possible and to move any tasks which can be performed in user space
into user space contrasted with something like Linux, which is a monolithic design.
The kernel is very, very small and simple. It only has 14 syscalls of which 12 related
to capabilities. A user's capability-based security, which is essentially this means
of controlling access to resources on the system like memory, like hardware I.O., memory
mapped I.O., processes, threads, address spaces. All of these things are represented by capabilities,
and the syscall API is used for working with those capabilities. And then each process
on the system has access to some subset of capabilities, which entitles it to rights
to use resources, which is a really good approach for sandboxing and security.
It's especially good when compared to a monolithic design like Linux. The example I usually reach
for to explain why Helios's design is more secure than Linux is to consider the case
of a floppy disk driver. So if you have a floppy disk driver on Linux, it's compiled
into your kernel and runs in ring 0. And if there's a bug in it, the worst thing that
bug can do is completely compromise your system. Whereas on Helios, the worst thing a bug in
your floppy disk driver could do is erase your floppy disk. All drivers, in addition
to user space processes, are sandboxed with the MMU, just like user space processes generally
are on systems like Linux. Of course, for a microkernel, inter-process communication
is critical. We have two approaches to IPC, which again are largely inspired by SEL4.
We have synchronous IPC via endpoints and asynchronous via notifications, as well as
the ability to set up shared memory so that you can communicate more efficiently than
using SysCalls for IPC. Where is the project at now? It's fairly mature. We're about nine
months in. The capabilities are working. Inter-process communication is also working. We also have
preemptive scheduling, so we do actually have processes which get scheduled. But the scheduler
is very simple. We don't have support for SMP yet, so it's all running on one core.
And it's just a simple round robin scheduler, but we will make improvements in this domain.
We also have support for hardware IO and IRQs, both in user space, so it is now possible
to write user space drivers for hardware in Helios or on top of Helios. And in terms of
booting, we currently have support for EFI on ARM and multi-boot on X8664. We're going
to also bring EFI to X8664 as soon as somebody can be bothered to implement position independent
code for our back-end. And does it work? The answer is self-evidently yes, because this
slide deck you're viewing right now is running on this Raspberry Pi, which is running on
Helios. I promised that I would not do any talks about Helios until I could actually
present that talk from Helios. And I initially was going to try and write an Intel HD graphics
driver from X86 laptop, and then I started looking at the IHD manuals, of which there's
about 18 volumes per Intel hardware revision. Among those are about 100,000 pages of PDF.
And after about two days of reading those PDFs, I forgot about that and instead ported
the entire kernel to ARM so I could write GPU driver for the Raspberry Pi instead. That
ARM port took about 42 days to complete from start to finish. The Raspberry Pi here is
running its GPU driver and a serial driver in user space. The GPU driver is driving the
projector and I'm switching between slides by typing letters into the serial port. The
slide deck itself is encoded as QOI, quite okay, images, on a tarball, which essentially
acts like an INIT RAMFS. And there's basically no hacks here. There's no smoke and mirrors.
I actually ported the entire Helios kernel to ARM. There's no SOC specific build, so
this same configuration should work on any other ARM device, which implements an EFI
boot. I am using EDK to boot through EFI. I'm using device trees to enumerate the hardware
instead of drivers. So there's very little on the way of hacks. 42 days for a complete
port to ARM. No hacks. It just works.
Thank you. So where's the project going from here? The kernel itself is done in big error
quotes in terms of the fact that it's almost functionally complete. It needs to be polished
and we need to, you know, if you do a Git grep on todo, you find about 100 things that
still need to be fixed, just little stuff. We need to add multiprocessing support. I
want to port it to RISC-V as well, which maybe it'll take more than 40 days because I'm not
going to kill myself over this one without a deadline like Fostom. I mentioned earlier
that I want to expand the bootloader options, so I want to add EFI support for x86.64 and
we also intend to boot RISC-V over EFI. And I want to improve the documentation, of course.
The docs are actually already kind of okay. They're at aries.org. If you're curious, the
kernel docs are maybe about 60% complete. And if you're curious to play with Helios,
you can definitely use those as a starting point and ask an IRC if you encounter a stub
where there should be docs. In the big picture, this is our plans. So, like I said, the kernel
is almost functionally complete, but it's a macrokernel, so that doesn't mean that it
can necessarily do very much that it's useful. But we're going to go to user space and build
more stuff. We have this idea of kind of layers of support. So at the core is the microkernel,
Helios, but then we're going to build additional projects on top of it, which will expand it
into a complete operating system. We have now Mercury, which is a driver framework.
This already exists and is fairly mature and has become even more so in the past week or
so. And then we've just started last week working on Venus, which is going to be our
collection of drivers. Just any kind of hardware that we want to support, the driver for it
will probably end up in Venus and be built on top of the Mercury framework. And together
these will present an interface to Gaia, which will take these abstractions for accessing
hardware and build them into an actual programming environment, which will resemble Unix or Plan
9. We're also going to build Luna, which will be a POSIX compatibility layer. Gaia itself
will not be POSIX. I think that there's room for beyond POSIX, I hope. But we do want POSIX
software to work, so we'll have this compatibility layer. And then we'll tie it all together
with Ares, which will be a more complete operating system that provides a package manager and
a service manager and other things that you might be used to from a complete experience.
I want to give some quick acknowledgments as well to the people who made this possible.
I want to thank Ember Savadi and Alexei Yeren in particular for their early experiments
with kernel programming in HAIR. These early kernels for x86 and RISC-V, they never made
it to user space. They weren't very sophisticated, but they did answer a lot of the problems
that needed to be answered for us to know how do we do HAIR development in RISC-0. And
so this was very valuable for establishing things like booting up, dealing with the MMU,
and other questions for how to get a kernel going in HAIR. And the HAIR community itself
deserves a big shout out because none of this would be possible without the immense amount
of work which people have put into it. Many of the people who contributed to HAIR are
in this room and I offer them my thanks. But many people are not here. There's about 80
people who run into making HAIR possible. I also want to thank the OS dev community
on the Barat Chats IRC. These guys are incredibly smart and incredibly friendly and incredibly
helpful. And if you want to get involved in kernel hacking and do any kind of work in
RISC-0 yourself, this is an indispensable resource. Definitely check these guys out.
And also we owe some acknowledgements to SEL4 because a lot of our design is inspired or
stolen from SEL4. I should have updated this slide. We have a birds of a feather and a
couple of hours for HAIR, the programming language. So it's not about Helios, it's about the language
that Helios is implemented in. So if you want to learn more about the language, please come
there. There's also a talk tomorrow in the microkernel room where I'm going to have a
full hour to talk about Helios and I'll go into a lot more depth. So you're welcome to
come check that out. If you want to see any resources online about the system, the links
are here. This is a link to the website which contains mostly documentation, a link to the
source code, to the website for the programming language and to the IRC channel where we hang
out and we'll answer your questions. And that's it. That's Helios. Thank you very much.