All right.
So let's get started again.
The next talk is by Anton about optimizing BPF hash map in France.
Hello.
I'm Anton, working at DataPod team at Isovalent.
And yeah, this is talk about how simple it is to optimize BPF hash map.
So about a year ago, like a little less, Andrej Nachryk proposed, suggested to try new hash
functions for BPF hash map and BPF text trace map.
And in Xilu, we use, and in TatraGone, we use hashes extensively.
So for us, it's a big deal, and I decided to give it a try.
So I will briefly provide some benchmarking how-to 101, and then we'll take a look at
different hash functions.
And then we'll see benchmarks for hash maps, which utilize old hash functions and new hash
functions.
So first thing to do when you benchmark is to try to reduce noise, because modern CPUs
do everything to ruin your benchmarking.
They will run on different frequency.
Hyperthreading will get in, and in the best case, you benchmark inside kernel, because
you can disable preemption and interrupts.
So benchmark, we take, if we want to benchmark some function, we first measure some kind
of time source or clock source, and then we execute our function, maybe in a loop, and
then we measure time once again, and then we divide the number of observations by the
number of loops and get our result.
So in some cases, we can't execute our function in a loop.
For example, if it's not like an abstract hash function, if it's just part of kernel,
then n is obviously equal to one, and we need to take into account the time it takes to
get time.
And one obvious way to do this is to benchmark an empty loop, and this gives us roughly how
long the get time function works.
And typically, people benchmark with something like RDSC instruction, and if you don't reduce
noise, then RDSC instruction is pretty unstable.
So here, my CPU obviously runs on two different frequencies, and if my function, which I want
to benchmark, runs 30, 40 cycles, then deviation in this case is bigger than the function itself,
so I control-line it.
So if we disable, like, reduce noise, as I said, then results become way more stable.
So here, it's like, maybe it looks scary, but it's actually like 37 plus minus one cycle.
So even for very small functions, this makes benchmarking more reliable.
But in this form, RDSC doesn't work because it's not a serializing instruction, which
means that if you insert your code here, then it can be executed in the middle of code and
even after your code, so, and it can differ from execution to execution, and so we need
some way to serialize it.
Luckily, there are known ways to do this, so we just serialize it.
And there is a white paper written maybe 10 years ago about Itanium, and it's still valid
with some changes from architecture to architecture, but yeah, we can do this.
In this case, benchmarking, like the offset, takes a little bit more, like it's not 37
cycles anymore, it's 70 cycles, but again, it's pretty stable, and we can use this number
to offset our measurements.
And in fact, I did such benchmarking when I don't run in a loop.
It's then switched to, like, more dumb benchmarks when you do loops over BPF maps because it's
harder to port things, and if you want someone else to try these benchmarks, they will have
to patch their kernel, and this is not simple.
So let's take a look at several hash functions of interest.
So JHash is currently used hash function in the BPF.
It's Bob Jenkins hash, and it probably was developed some 30 years ago.
So SpookyHash is another, it's a newer version, it's not a newer version, it's a newer hash
from Bob Jenkins, and then there goes XXH hashes, XXH32.964 is the previous generation
of these functions.
They are available in kernel, and we can try them as well, and XXH3 is like the state of
art hash function.
So if we just take a look at this plot, the orange line which goes there is JHash, which
is currently used.
The green line, which looks to be green in here, is like the previous generation XXH64.
The blue line, this is the newest generation XXH3, and while it looks here that it doesn't
perform as well as XXH64, for small keys it does outperform it, and for BPF hash maps we
are primarily interested in using it for small keys.
I don't know, actually I never use it for huge keys, and in any case this XXH3 works
faster than Jenkins hash, and later I will show that it can actually run even more faster.
But one interesting thing is that this spooky hash, it actually performs pretty bad for
small keys, because it has a lot of setup which it does in any case, but later it starts
outperform every hash function, I was interested when it does it, so it does it at about key
size of 9000.
It's cool but it's not the key size of interest for us.
If we take a look at XXH3 and JHash, we can see that the blue line XXH3, it actually outperforms
like JHash for all key sizes, and there is also this green line, it's JHash2, it's an
optimized version of JHash which can be used if your key size is multiple of four, and
it's actually used in Blom filters but for some reason not in hash maps.
So if we take a closer look at small key sizes, we see that yes, XXH3 outperforms JHash, so
for me it's enough reason to try to benchmark maps with it.
And let's take a look now at BPF maps which use hash functions, so first one is tech trace
map and then hash map in Blom filters.
So stick trace was actually the main reason for Andre to propose XXH3, because what it
does is it takes a stack trace and then it hashes it and creates a map of IDs which refers
to the traces, and if there are hash collisions then old stack traces are lost and we get
incorrect picture about the system.
And stack traces is not too random, so if your hash function is not very good, if it
doesn't have very good avalanche properties, then it will create more collisions for less
random data.
And XXH3 behaves way better than JHash for avalanche properties and this is one of reasons
and the main reason to use it for stack trace.
The other reason as a benchmark, it's also like for stack trace, it also runs about twice
faster for typical key sizes because typical key size is like 8 bytes per stack depth and
this is typically like 60, 80, 100 bytes.
So XXH3 is a very good candidate here.
So for hash benchmarks I was primarily focused on lookups because this is what we do the
most and this is the thing which is easy to measure compared to more complex pictures.
So there are some links to benchmarks I used and scripts to actually execute benchmark
and plot it because for every change I had to draw some like 100 or 150 pictures for
different key sizes, for different fullness of hash maps, so it's impossible to do otherwise.
And I had a few pictures here.
So if we just use XXH3 then it looks like the new map which is orange, it outperforms
the original map which is blue.
And here is lookup speed in cycles, vertical and horizontal axis is key size.
So the bigger the key the better the more gain from using the new hash function.
But if we take like a bigger map I see that XXH3 as it is degrades for key size 4 and
this is already like for me as a blocker I can't like propose a change which degrades
existing applications.
So then I went to a different architecture, micro architecture and here I saw that it
degrades for different key size like here it degrades for key size 12 and if we take
like a bigger map it also degrades for key size 24.
And then I thought how to fix this because if it works for bigger keys then maybe I can
utilize this.
And I did the same thing as bloom filter currently does.
So bloom filter executes JHash2 for key sizes divisible by 4 and it uses JHash in other cases.
So I did the same.
Utilize JHash2 for key sizes of which are divisible by 4 but for small ones like it's
plus key length divided by 4, key length 32 it's actually computed.
It's just key length divided by 4 but it's computed during hash initialization and we
can decide for which key sizes we do this.
And with this hash function I finally see that it doesn't degrade anywhere.
So this is like 10K, 100K and 100% full which is like the worst case.
And if we take another slice this is 100K map with key size 8 and on the left side it's
almost empty.
On the right side it's 100% full.
And the bigger key size the bigger gain for particular key size.
So for key size 64 map with new hash function runs about 50% faster and for key size 128
it runs almost twice faster.
And bloom filters as I mentioned they use the JHash2 for keys divisible by 4.
So I don't expect any gain for keys divisible by 4 at least for small keys.
And it looks like this.
So this is like an extreme case of bloom filter with 9 hashes.
But I just did it so it reproduces the plot of hash function here.
And yes for small keys it is the same.
And for bigger keys we have a gain.
And here is the key size 240 where XH3 function originally utilizes vector instructions and
we can't use obviously vector instructions in BPF maps.
And for key size 240 it is expected to start using vector instructions.
But there is also scalar implementation which works faster than JHash but it degrades at
this point.
So and another thing to mention that old hash functions JHash XXH64 they were...
They were designed and optimized with O2 option in mind.
So if we switch to O3 then they will behave the same.
But XXH3 actually runs like 50, 60% faster.
So it actually performs way better with O3.
So I just jump like here.
So and I know that like O3 is no go for kernel.
Like there were several attempts to introduce it.
And the reason was that there are no candidates which benefit from this O3.
But this one is a particular candidate like hash.
If we could use O3 for hash map because not only for XXH3 because it should be inlined.
Then in this case we would be able to get rid of this composite hash which mixes hashes
and just use it as is.
So yeah as I said for stuck trace map it definitely makes sense to use it.
So there is both benefiting in speed.
Small one because stuck trace map the bottleneck for speed is not the hash.
But the bottleneck for hash collisions is the hash.
And for hash map it's a question maybe someone would advise me on what to do with O3.
And after I run like benchmarks on slightly bigger number of architectures then I think
there's also like a good candidate to use in the hash map.
So here are some links for benchmarks and paper which I use it for those who will be
reading this and thank you.
All right thanks a lot any questions you.
For the O3 thing can you only compile maybe the like the hash map file with O3.
Yeah yeah if it is like currently it is disabled like for every file in kernel.
For custom build we can enable it but like generally we just pass O2 everywhere.
If it's possible just to compile BPF maps with O3 this will solve the thing.
It's not such a big change.
So you don't have to compile the whole kernel with O3?
Yeah yeah yeah.
So only it's local code.
Okay.
Any other questions?
No then thanks a lot.