So, we're ready for our next talk.
Alex is going to talk about the new file system that they're proposing, Composivest, and opportunistically
sharing verified image file system.
Thank you.
All right, thank you.
Can you hear me?
Yeah?
All right.
All right, I'm Alex.
You may also know me from hits such as Flatpak, Flathub, GNOME, GTK, all such stuff.
But this here is my first kernel file system, which I proposed on the list a couple of months
ago.
It's not actually like a file system, a real file system.
It's more targeted for read-only images such that you would typically have many of them
running on the system, maybe on a container host or in my case, my primary concern is
the OSTree verified boot use case.
So rather than talking about composeFS first, I'm going to talk about OSTree because it
kind of explains where this comes from.
So in OSTree, we have images.
Normally the images are not simple like this, but actually the full-root file system for
your system that you want to boot.
But they're used in a bunch of files, and they have metadata and permissions and names
and whatnot.
So they're basically images.
And we have this repository format, which is the core format of OSTree.
And what we do is we take all the files, like the regular files, in the image and we hash
them.
And we store them by the hash name in this repository format.
So if you look at any of those files, they're just the same file with the name of their
own content.
And then we take all the directories we have, such as the sub-derp thing, and we make a
small descriptor of them, the names of the file in them, their permissions and whatnot,
and a reference to the content of the file by the checksum.
And we do the same for the root directory.
And this time we refer to the sub-directory by the checksum of the descriptor.
And then we add a final commit description, which describes, well, it has a pointer, meaning
the checksum of the root directory, and a parent doesn't have a parent because this
is the first commit, some metadata.
And then we add the refs file, which is basically just a file that says we have a branch called
image, and this is the current head.
So if anyone thinks this looks like the.get directory in any of your checkouts, that's
true.
It's basically Git for operating systems.
There are some details in exactly how the object files are stored, but basically the
entire structure is Git, right?
It's just a copy of Git.
And you can see even more clearly if you create a new commit, the new version, we added the
readme.
So all we have to do is add the file, the new root directory, and the new commit that
points to the previous one, and then we update the ref to the latest head.
So basically re-implementing Git for large binary trees.
But you can't use this directly.
Like you can't boot from a repository like this.
So when you do deploy, we call it deploy when you run a new version of something.
Typically you have a pre-existing version.
So you download the new version of the thing you want to run, which is very simple because
you can just iterate over these recursive descriptions of the image.
And whenever you have a reference to an object you already have downloaded, you can just
stop because recursively you know you have all the previous things.
So it's very efficient to get the new version.
And then we create a deploy directory, which is basically a hard-linked form that points
back into the objects, like the regular file objects.
So we create the directories with the right permissions and whatnot.
Whenever there's a regular file, we just point it at the same file by using a hardlink to
the one in the repository.
And then we somehow set some boot configuration that points to this particular commit, which
means this directory, and somewhere in the unit RDE we find this directory, bind-mounted,
read-only on the root, on top of the root, and then we boot into that.
And there are some clear advantages over this, over what would be the alternative, which
is the traditional A, B, but block device.
You have two block devices and you flash new image from B and then you boot into B.
First of all, it's very easy to do efficient downloads and deltas are very small.
You can easily store however many versions of things you want, whether they're related
or not, like if it's multiple versions of the same branch.
You can keep the last 10 or whatever.
Plus you can also have completely unrelated, you can have both the Fedora and a rel or
Debian or whatever.
And you can easily switch between them atomically.
And all the updates are atomic, we never modify an existing thing that you're running, we
always create a new deploy directory and we boot into that.
And also the format is very, it's very, very viable.
Like it's recursively describing itself and all you need is the signature, and there's
a GPG signature on the commit object.
So if you trust the commit object, you trust the root hash, you trust the hash of the subdirectories
and the files and whatnot.
The problem that I want to address is that this doesn't do runtime verification.
We verify when we download things, we can verify when we do the deploy or rather the
fact that we're deploying is going to cause us to verify things.
But if after some point after that something modifies, say we have a random bit flip on
the disk or we have a malicious evil mate style attack, someone could easily just remove
or modify a file in the deploy directory.
And to protect against this, the kernel has two features, the invert and fsverity.
The invertity is what you use in the typical AV image system because it's block based,
but it's completely a read-only block device.
There's no way we can do OSTRI like updates to its file system.
You just cannot write to it.
So the other thing is fsverity.
And fsverity sort of matches very well with the OSTRI repository format because if you
enable fsverity on a particular file, it essentially makes it immutable.
And immutable is exactly what these content address files are.
So it's good.
But the problem is that fsverity doesn't go all the way, it only protects the content
of the file.
You can easily make it set UID or replace it with a different one that has a different
fsverity or just add a new file or whatever.
So it doesn't protect structure.
So that's why composefs was created, to have another layer that does the structure.
And now I'm sort of going away from the OSTRI use case and this is the native way to use
composefs where you just have a directory with some data.
This is the same kind of example that I had in the posterior format.
And you just run mk-composefs on that directory and it creates this image file that contains
all the metadata for the structure of the thing.
And this object directory which is just copies of these files stored by fsverity-digest.
And they obviously are just pure files, you can cat them and they're just regular files
with the same contents.
They're actually pure data files.
You can see they don't have the executable rights or if you have some complex metadata
or extended attributes or whatever.
These are just regular files with content.
And then you mount the thing using composefs, pointing it at this object directory and then
you get a reproduction of the original image that you can look at.
Whenever you cat this, it will just do overlayfs style stacking, read the backing file.
So everything is always from the page cache.
And also the actual mount is not a loopback mount.
We just do stacking style, direct access of the file from the page cache.
So that gives you the general ability to reproduce this image.
But to get the fsverity or complete structural verification, you actually use fsverity on
the descriptor itself.
So if you enable fsverity on that, that makes it immutable.
So the file system cannot change or the file can't change on the file system.
At least the kernel API doesn't allow you and if it's somehow otherwise modified on
disk or whatnot, it will detect it.
And you can see I actually pass the digest, the expected digest, and whenever it mounts
it it starts by verifying before it does any IO, does it actually have the expected fsverity
digest?
And if so, we can rely on the kernel to basically do all our verification from us.
And if you replace something, we have in the metadata for all these backing files the expected
verity digest.
So if you replace something or if there's a random bit flip, it will detect it.
And actually the descriptor itself is very simple.
This is not a traditional file system where we have to update things at runtime.
We can just compute a very simple descriptor of this.
It's basically a fixed-size header followed by a table of fixed-size inode data.
But if the file system has n n inodes, then there are n copies of that structure.
And some of them point into the variable-size data at the end, which we found with the VData
offset in the header.
And that's basically all there is to it.
Inode zero is the root file system, or is the root inode.
You can look at that and if it's a type directory, then the variable data points to a table of
darenths, which is basically a pre-sorted table of darenths plus names that you use binary
search.
You get a new I know, then you just look at that offset.
And all this is just done by mapping the page cache directly.
So it's very simple in terms of structure.
If you want to use this actually with OSTree, it's slightly different.
Like we can't just, we don't want to take the OSTree repository, create this directory,
and then run mk-compose-fs on it.
Where we ship a library, libcompose-fs, where you basically link OSTree with this library
and it can generate these images directly from the metadata that exists in the repository.
So we don't have to do any kind of expensive IO to create these images.
Because it's just a metadata, right?
It's not very large.
You can put it into memory, generate these, optimize them, and just write a single file.
And the way we can do it, it's very flexible so we can ensure that we can use the existing
repository for the backing files.
And it's also designed so that there's a standardized way.
We put everything, so every time you create a new image based on the same OSTree commit,
we will be creating the exact same binary file.
Like bit by bit.
So what you do is then when you create the commit on the server, you basically generate
one of these, take the digest of it, like the Fs-varied to digest of it, put it in the
same commit, and then whenever you recreate, there's no need to extend the OSTree format
on the network or anything.
What you do is when you deploy a commit, instead of making this hardling form, you recreate
one of these and then you use the supply digest as the expected digest when you mount it.
So if anything anywhere went wrong or was attacked or whatever, it will refuse to mount
it.
So obviously you have to put that trusted digest somewhere in your secure boot stack
or whatever.
Something would have to, it has to be trusted, but that's outside exactly of the scope of
ComposeFS.
And it's very similar to what you would do with the M-variety in a pure image-based system.
But another interesting use case is the container use case.
And Giuseppe, who is not here actually, but he is one of the other people behind the ComposeFS
people, or developers, he is more, he's one of the part-man developers.
So his use case is to use this for containers because containers are also used images, right?
And it would be nice if we can get this very, what I call opportunistic sharing of files.
Like if you use layers and stuff, you can sort of share stuff between different containers,
but you have to manually ensure you do the right thing, whereas with this opportunistic
style of sharing, whenever you happen to have a file that is identical, it just automatically
gets shared.
But like on disk and in page cache, because of the way these things work.
So we also don't want to like change the container format.
There was a talk yesterday about using the M-variety in SquashFS for, it's not sharing,
but like the similar kind of way you can mount an image.
But we don't want to, that forces all the users to create a new form of container.
But we want to use, allow this for all existing tarball-based layered OCI images.
So an image, in the OSI world, is a list of tarballs that you extract in order and then
you mount it using OverlyFS.
There is an extension of this called E-tar, E-star GC, which is some weird-ass hack where
you put an index at the end of the G-zip and then you can use partial HTTP downloads to
just get the index and you can see which part of the layer you already have and you can
just range HTTP gets to only download those parts.
So if you happen to have one of those archives in your layers, we can, in combination with
the locally stored content storage, avoid downloading the parts that we don't need.
If you don't have them, we have to download everything, which is what we do now, but we
can do better.
But even then, you can still hash them locally and get all the sharing and then you combine
this with creating an OverlyFS, or a composite FS for the entire image.
So you mount, this is for the local storage of images.
You can use, instead of storing these layers, you store the repository, content stored repository
plus these generated composed FS images and then whenever you run this, you just mount
it and it goes.
It's also nice, you can easily combine all the layers.
So if you have a 10 layer container and you want to resolve libc, which is in the base
layer, you have to do a negative denture lookup in every layer before you reach the bottom
most.
But since the image is just metadata, it's very cheap to create a completely squashed
composed FS image for single layer lookups.
And I don't know if anyone is following the list, but there are some discussions about
this.
I'm trying to get it merged upstream.
And one alternative has appeared, that there's waste, you can actually use some of OverlyFS
features to sort of get these features.
If you use the not super well-known or documented features called Overlay redirect and Overlay
metacopy, you can create an OverlayFS layer that does a similar style of here are the
metadata for this attribute redirected to a different path, which would be the content
address name in the lower layer.
And then you can use some kind of read-only file system for the upper layer where you
store all these extended attribute files that just contain this structure.
So this combination of OverlayFS plus right now EROFS is probably the best approach for
those, for the upper layer.
You can sort of create this.
Unfortunately, that doesn't do the verification.
You can use DVRT on the Overlay, or I mean on the read-only file system itself.
But you need some kind of extension to overlay itself to allow this recording of the expected
Fs verity of the backing file.
But that does seem like a trivial thing.
The less trivial part, and this is where opinions on the list vary, is I think this kind of
combination of things is way more complicated than the simple, like composeFS is, I think,
100 lines of code.
It's very direct.
It doesn't use loopback devices, device buffer devices.
When you do a lookup in this combined thing of a particular file, you would do a lookup
in the Overlay layer in the read-only system and in all the backing layers.
So there's just like four times more INODES around, there's four times more D-cache lookups,
and it just uses more memory and performs worse.
So I ran some simple lookups.
These are just, some people complain about the measurements here.
I'm just comparing like a recursive find or L-S-L-R, which is basically just measuring
the performance of lookups and readers.
But on the other hand, that's all that composeFS does.
All the actual IO performance is left to the backing file system.
So wherever you store your real files, that's where streaming performance and things like
that would appear.
So I'm personally in the automotive use case right now, so we have very harsh requirements
on cool boot performance, so the cold cache numbers are very important to me.
I mean, you might not, this is like listing recursively a large developer snapshot, like
a three gigabyte CentroStream 9 image.
So it's not an operation you might do, but just looking at the numbers, the recursive
listing is more than like three times slower for the cold cache situation because it has
to do multiple lookups.
And even for the cached case, where most things should be from the decached anyway, that's,
you know, I think I've seen better numbers than this.
I think that, but there's at least 10% difference in the warm cache situation.
I hope that was useful to someone.
Yeah, we have some time for questions.
So you said about halfway through that you're, one of the goals was to actually keep the,
reading the OCI image format, but I think everybody pretty much agrees the OCI image
format is crap for lazy pulling of container images.
Basically because it has an end to end hash, so you can't do the hash until you pull the
whole image.
And that means signatures are completely rubbish anyway.
In order to fix this, we have to do a Merkle tree or something else anyway.
So the image format is going to have to change radically to something that will be much
more suitable for your image.
So I think trying to keep the image compatibility, which is partly what the argument over this
versus the internal alternatives is not going to be a good argument for that.
And I think you should consider.
I agree and I don't agree.
I mean, I think I'm not a fan of OCI.
I've been part of the OCI specification team for a bit.
I used to be one of the Docker maintainers a long time ago.
It is not nice, but it is what we have and it's everywhere.
It's so easy as a developer sitting around thinking this is bullshit, we should just
fix it.
But there are trillions of dollars invested in the existing containers.
It's going to be a long time.
Even when we replace it, this will still do the right thing.
True.
But like there are discussions of OCI v2.
I don't follow them because the whole thing is bullshit.
But even then, if we just had a better way to get partial updates for an image file,
you could still use this to use it.
Before taking the next question, I'm obliged to point out from the chat that these performance
numbers are before optimizing overlay FS and E-ROVs.
Yeah.
So, yeah.
There's been some work in that and optimizing.
There's ideas to make the overlays stuff work better.
Would that be possible?
Sure.
Maybe.
Oh, hi.
I actually still had a question.
So here in the back.
Well, it's not really a question, more a remark.
I think there's sort of like one missing slide in your deck, namely one use case that you
haven't considered at all but still really worth calling out.
Many remote build systems, such as like GOMA, Bazel, et cetera, are all nowadays converging
on the single remote execution protocol called RE v2.
And that one is actually also using a CAS as a data store for storing both input files
for like compiler binaries, source files, header files, but also output files, object
files that are generated.
I actually maintain one of the implementations.
And one of the hard parts of implementing such a build cluster is instantiating the
data that's stored in the CAS in the form of an input route on disk where you can just
run a compiler against certain source files.
And a tool like Composivest would also really help in such an implementation.
That's just something I wanted to call out.
And you should really also market it towards those kinds of use cases.
It makes a lot of sense.
Yeah.
I'm sure.
Images are used for all sorts of stuff.
I'm sure there are many use cases other than the ones I've mainly focused on.
Okay.
Then since you already ended the Q&A a bit early, then the next talk is going to be recorded.
This gives us a bit more time to prepare.
Thank you very much for the talk.
Thank you for all the questions and being here.
Thank you very much.