Hi, welcome to my talk. My name is Bartosz Goaszewski. I work for Linaro. And today I
wanted to talk about an issue that had been bothering me for some time, namely a certain
family of youth after free bugs in the kernel that has been for a long time blamed on DevRes
and that I decided to investigate a bit and only to find out that reality is often disappointing
and everything is broken and the problem is actually much worse than if that was DevRes's
fault. So yeah, without further ado, let's back in because the time is short. So typically,
your typical probe function in a device driver would look something like this without DevRes.
So you allocate some resource. If it fails, you bail out. You allocate a second resource.
If it fails, you free the previous one, bail out, and so on and so forth. So every next
resource would need, if it fails, you need to free the previous ones. Alternatively,
you would do something like this. You would have labels at the end of the function and
just jump to it when it's one of the allocations or resource, like you wouldn't be able to
acquire one of the resources. You would jump to it and free every previously allocated
resource in reverse order and then you need your remove function that would also drop
these resources in reverse order. But you can use DevRes and in this case, it looks
much better. You allocate a resource. If it fails, you bail out. You allocate a second
resource. If it fails, you bail out immediately. You don't have to free those resources yourself.
When a driver is detached, they will be dropped automatically in reverse order and with that,
you no longer need your remove function. So that is pretty sweet. But you will notice
when you, if you send enough patches to different subsystems, you will notice that certain maintainers
show aversion to DevRes. You would get comments like, oh no, keep DevRes out of my subsystem
or don't you know DevRes leads to, you see these interfaces leads to crashes. But without,
you would probably not get a lot of explanation on what the problem is.
And so I, last year I stumbled upon a talk by Laurent Panchak from last year's Linux
Plumbers Conference. Actually, the link is below so you can watch it. And yes, I watched
that and then I started browsing lore and noticed that Laurent actually had sent an
email about that already in 2015 saying that if you open a device note in user space and
you unbind the driver that exposed it, exported it and try to do something with that open
file descriptor, call one of the system calls, you will get a nice fact-race in your kernel
log. So I thought, okay, that's interesting. I read through a discussion. I found out that
there were several such discussions previously, of which I had not been aware. And I don't
want to go into much detail, but the gist of it is that there are certain users in the
kernel, mostly device drivers, only device drivers, that allocate using DevRisk, like
the case alloc in this example, allocate memory that is dropped in remove, but that's actually
still referenced elsewhere, which leads to use after free bugs. And the first thing that
popped in my mind was how is that different from calling any, from dropping these resources
in remove? And I wasn't the only one because many people asked about it. And one of the
responses was something like this. It's not, it's the same thing, but the problem is that
people don't understand the lifetime rules and expect magic interfaces to fix it for
them. So I thought that this, while this is certainly true, I think that driver developers
should not be expected to understand every detail of how kernel subsystems work, because
they actually should care more about making the device work. And I would argue that you
should actually expect magic interfaces in drivers to fix stuff for you. And if it's
not straightforward, then it's a problem of the subsystem or of given interface and not
of device driver developers. So I decided to investigate and see if maybe something
changed. And I do maintain the GPO subsystem, so this was the first one that I tried. I
opened, sorry, I had this serial to USB converter, converter cable plugged in that actually also
has four GPO pins. So I opened the GPO device, I unplugged the cable, I tried to read the
value of the pin and sure enough it's crushed, no point in their friends. I was like, okay,
that's interesting. I did not expect that, but it's certainly interesting. So I tried
a different subsystem, I tried I2C. Surprisingly, it didn't crash, it just, like when I tried
to unbind the driver, just hang, froze and did nothing. Okay, so that's interesting.
But I realized that when I unplugged the cable, I had my PicoCon console open and it just,
it didn't crash, it just exited. So certainly UART is doing something right and other subsystems
are not doing it correctly. So I decided to investigate a bit. So in the GPIO subsystem,
we have two types of structures. One that the driver see, this is the GPIO chip, and
the second one that the drivers, the GPIO providers don't touch, don't even have access
to, which is the GPIO device. And so this will be important in a second. So I looked
at the crash that I had in GPIO and it turned out that it was a no pointer to reference
at a certain line, the one that you can see above. And at the moment where I, like I still
had my device open, I tried to call one of the system calls and it turned out that the
chip that you can see above when the referencing GDev was null, was already gone. So this has
nothing to do with DevRisk, it's just that we had a bug in the GPIO character device
code where when we, when the driver is going away and it calls GPIO chip remove, it can
be called from DevRisk or it can be called in your remove function. We simply set the
chip to null because the driver is gone, but the struck device still can be referenced
elsewhere. So we just numbed down, which is the correct thing to do, but it still needs
to be checked in the character device code. This was what we were not doing and this needs
fixing clearly. And there is also a question of a race condition in the system callbacks
where if, even if we do check it in the beginning, we still need some locking because otherwise
the driver can be removed when we are still executing the system call. So I looked at
that and I thought, okay, this is easy enough to fix and that's definitely not linked to
those errors that the discussion in the email thread was about. So I went over to I2C, I
decided to see what's going on in I2C, why does it, why can't I unbind the driver for
as long as I keep the device open? And it turned out that there is this strange completion
and a comment about it making it so that when the driver is trying to delete the I2C adapter,
it waits for as long as there are still references to the underlying struck device. Okay, it's
not definitely the freezing when you're trying to unbind the driver is not the correct way,
but at least it doesn't crash and someone had something, there was a purpose to doing
that. So I thought, okay, so why does UART work? I looked at the UART code and figured
out that actually UART does a smart thing. First, when you go into any of the system
call callbacks in the kernel, you check, you have a similar split like GPIO where you have
a structure that lives for as long as the struck device lives and a separate structure
that is allocated by the driver. So it turned out that, yeah, it first checks if the driver
is still there. If it is, then it locks it so that it cannot go away from under an executing
system call. Okay, so this definitely makes sense. And I also noticed that spy def works
fine, but upon further inspection of the code, it turns out that it also suffers from a race
condition because when the spy def spy is checked, the spin lock is only taken for the
duration of the check, for reading of the pointer. But later it's still that the underlying
driver can still go away while the lock is already released. So this is a concurrency
issue. So I started thinking that there is some misconception about DevRIS. I decided
to fix some things. I started with GPIO. I sent some patches. They went into mainline.
In this case, they did fix the issues. The kernel would no longer crash when the user
space would unbind the driver and use the character device. I also sent some fixes for
spy def and then I sent a fix for I2C. I removed this completion. This is when things went
sideways actually. I removed that completion. I added locking. I started fiddling with this
character device. And I was proud of myself because I thought that I fixed this problem
that has for a long time existed in I2C. And Wolfram, the maintainer of I2C, took that
patch, reviewed it, said it passes all his stress testing. But he's having a gut feeling
that something is wrong. And after a couple of days, he sends me an email and says, okay,
I found this discussion from a couple of years ago where this was explained in detail. And
what happened? So what turned out to be the case with I2C? It turns out that I2C is a
subsystem where drivers allocate the I2C adapter which embeds struck device. And they allocate
that structure as part of a usually bigger structure that contains driver specific fields
in probe. And then in the remove callback, they drop that memory. But it contains struck
device which is reference counted unlike the structure that embeds it. So this is why this
whole completion, waiting for completion, is there in I2C because you must not drop
free this memory containing struck device for as long as there are references to struck
device. And I noticed that this is not the only subsystem that does it. So every driver
subsystem does things a bit differently. Some of them have that split. Some of them don't.
For instance, spy has the same problem as I2C, but unlike I2C, it doesn't expect the
driver to allocate that data as part of the driver data. It expects it to be allocated
separately and handed over to the spy subsystem, which is not probably it could do some improvement,
but at least it doesn't crush and doesn't require the same type of synchronous waiting
for dropping all the references to struck device. So actually, this talk should be called
don't let drivers allocate and control the lifetime of struck device because this is
the culprit, basically. So we have those systems that allocate struck device. And there are
more references to it. It's still referenced elsewhere. And then we drop this memory and
we still, when the reference is like, the struck device no longer exists, but it's still
referenced somewhere. And then the driver model tries to call, for instance, the release
call back of the device. And there's nothing there. So we have those questions. So I didn't
look at all the subsystems clearly. And there are too many. But I just noticed that certain
parts of the kernel get it right. So GPIO now with those fixes is fine. UART is fine.
Wojondock is fine. They have this split where the struck device is allocated and managed
by the subsystem, while driver data does not contain the struck device. I'm not talking
about the struck device that is passed to probe. I'm talking about struck device that
is allocated by the drivers or the respective subsystems for those proper underlying devices.
So like we have this, let's say, a platform device for a GPIO chip. And then we allocate
a struck device per every bank, just an example. And many subsystems do that too. So there
is this problem, but there are also other problems. So even those subsystems that get
this part right often suffer from concurrency issues because there is no locking in the
system callbacks in the kernel. So even if they do check if the driver is still there
or the device is still there attached to the driver, they often don't lock the state. So
it's possible that the driver will go away while they're still executing and they're
referencing that pointer. This was the case in Spy, for instance. And I think that the
issue is just about the logical scope of objects and not the scope understood as the scope
of a variable in C programming language, but more like a logical scope of objects where
you have... If something is allocated in probe when you first attach the device to the driver
and you allocate something in the probe, it should only need to exist for as long as the
driver is attached. And as soon as it goes away, it should be freed and removed, be it
with deveres or in remove. And yeah, so there is this problem with many subsystems that
they don't have this and they let drivers allocate some data in probe and then handle
it over to the subsystem or even do it implicitly, which leads to all these errors. So I know
that Laurent's area of interest would probably be media and urine, so I just skim through
the user space, device, notes, codes in those subsystems and noticed that they seem to be
getting part of it correctly. But there are conferencing issues as well. And the problem
with DRM is that the device handling code, the character block device handling code is
not centralized within the subsystem, meaning that we have many different struct file operations
with different implementations for different callbacks. Correct me if I'm wrong afterwards,
but it seemed like it from, I'm not an expert on DRM, but it seemed like it just from looking
at it. So what about deveres? Is it safe? I have found no evidence that it isn't. And
if something can be freed and removed, it can be freed with deveres because deveres
will do just that. It will, as soon as the driver gets detached from the device, the
other way around, it will free all resources allocated with deveres in reverse order. There
are some issues, like devmkrealoc could use some semantic clarification because as it
is right now, it's not clear whether the order, if you call devmkrealoc, does the order change
or not when releasing those resources? In any case, it is my strong belief that deveres
makes code much more readable, safer, and it actually should be encouraged and not discouraged.
But it has a limited scope. And on that point, how can we supplement it? Because a certain
semblance of automated resource management, or AI, if you will, in C would be useful in
the kernel. So yeah, the first thing that comes to mind would be using Rust. With Rust,
these situations that I described would clearly never be allowed to happen. But that's not,
until now, we're still coding in C. So I was thinking that if you've ever coded in a user
space library like Gilib, for instance, which is, I believe, the golden standard of C programming
in user space, you would notice that they make use of a lot of cleanup attributes. And
this is something that GCC and Clang support, and I haven't seen that in the kernel, and
I'm wondering why. Because if we would use reference counting in conjunction with cleanup,
we could actually make it...
If I can interject for one second. But actually, at least not in core kernel code, but Peter
Zilstra used this somewhere in the kernel source code tree, at least, and I had proposed
something like this, at least in person, to a couple of people before, because I want
to make use of this as well. So I would be very happy if this happened.
Yeah. So I have a small example. So if you are not familiar with the cleanup attribute,
it allows you to specify a cleanup function for a variable, and when the variable goes
out of scope, it's called, so it's like a destructor in C++, basically. Alone, it's
useful within the scope of a single code block or a single function. But in conjunction...
Well, this is just another example of how to use it. But in conjunction with reference
counting, it's quite useful, because you can see the foo and bar, foo create and bar functions
on the right. You allocate a reference counted, automatically reference counted resource.
You do something with it. If you bail out, the reference count goes to zero, and then
it's freed. But if you return it while also increasing the ref count, and then grab it
in another function in bar, in this case, then as soon as the foo create function returns,
the reference count is decreased, but it's already two, so it goes down to one, and we,
without having to control free those resources manually, we just keep track of the references
just by using reference counting and cleanup. And this is what GLIP does a lot, and it works
quite nice. It makes programming in C and user space much easier. And what to do about
the offending subsystems? It's a case-by-case issue, because every subsystem does it differently,
and I tried, I spoke to Wolfram a bit about what can we do in I2C, and it would be very
hard, because you would have to do a sweeping change across the entire subsystem to make
drivers not allocate I2C adapter, not I2C adapter, but rather the underlying struct
device on its own. Instead, let I2C, the I2C subsystem, handle it. Yeah, so just wanted
to bring that up, and that's it. I'm right on time.
Thank you. All right, questions? Thank you. I like your second slight title when you say
I was not completely wrong with my talk, so thank you for that. It was a bit worrying.
A few comments. It's multiple problems, actually, that you're trying to solve here. One is the
race condition between ICTLs, or user space access in general, and the remove function.
And for everything that's based on character devices, there's a patchy version from Dan
Williams that was posted in 2021, I think. I don't know if you've seen that one, that
attempts to fix it at the C dev level, which I think is the right place to do it instead
of duplicating the same fix in all the subsystems. So it has been positively reviewed, not merged.
I think it was just one review command that said that DebugFS and ProkFS had similar constructs,
and so he was asked to just refactor the code to reuse the same instead of duplicating it.
But that should be something we could upstream and solve. So that's one of them. I agree
with you that there's nothing wrong with DevRace or managed API in general. It was mostly DevM
case at the lock in particular that I had trouble with. Things like DevM, IORimap, for
instance, is perfectly fine because you tie the lifetime management of the resource with
the physical struct device, which is removed at the end of the remove function, and that
is what you should do. So that's totally fine. The issues with DevM functions come when we
try to tie, as you said, the lifetime of a resource to the wrong device. DRM has grown
its custom managed helpers based on DevRace, so not DevM, but it's DRMM, that do it relatively
right. They tie the memory management to the CDEV that's exposed to user space, but where
it breaks is when you have one physical device that exposed multiple CDEVs, because then
you have a top-level data structure that covers all of those. So even if you allocate each
of them dynamically, you will need to make sure that the top-level structure will be
released only when nothing else can have a reference to it. So I think there will always
be cases where reference counting will be needed, and the drivers will have to handle
that, but in many cases helpers should be possible to make it simpler.
And also I mentioned that on the slide that I didn't say it out loud. You have some DevRace
resources, the DevRace helpers that reach into other subsystems, which also have their
own issues, so this can be dangerous as well.
So I have seen in multiple places where drivers are allocating the struct device that is then
getting passed to the framework, but then the solution that they are using is that they
are basically instead of freeing the device in remove, they are just dropping the reference
to that device that has been allocated. So someone is taking the ownership of that device,
and then you rely on the reference counting to that device, and then freeing that struct
device only from the release callback that is then set by the driver itself.
This is what Spy does, but I2C is a worse example because you usually have a driver
data. Inside it you have I2C adapter. Inside it you have struct device, and this struct
device has this release callback. But in the release callback you are in the subsystem,
it cannot know what the outer layer structure is and where is it, what offset it has to
free it.
So the driver when it allocates the subsystems, it sets the release callback of the struct
device. It is another work around I guess.
I see that in multiple places. Video analytics does that, so it probably is a release callback.
Most of the drivers implement an empty one, which shows that it does not write. So it
is difficult to do, which is problematic because most drivers want to be tried with the thing.
Yeah, this is why I am saying that it is probably, it seems to me that the right thing to do
is not let drivers allocate struct device, instead do it in the subsystem if you need
to. This also hides some additional complexity from the driver developers.
On the slide about the state of the current subsystems, you had a question mark after
SPI. I wonder if you have doubts if it is fine today.
Yeah, yeah, I think, no, no, this is the one, right?
That one.
This one?
Yeah, there is a question mark in the SPI.
Yes, yeah, I put it there because I have not investigated that in detail, so I was not
sure if it works fine. It looks to be working fine, like just from testing it. I was not
sure if that is the, if it is correctly implemented, let us say, because it sounds good in theory.
All right, the last question. So for systems like I2C, has anybody calculated the amount
of pain?
Sorry?
For things like the I2C, has anybody calculated the amount of actual work to fix this?
It looks like it is a lot, because I did send some proposition to Wolfram about wrapping
every the reference of the I2C adapter that dev into a helper that would then allow us
to change that struck device into a pointer instead of the proper structure and allocate
that inside the subsystem, but it is not going to be easy. This is why I dropped the patch.
I told Wolfram not to pursue that, because it looks to me like it is not going to be
that easy and I do not really want to get my hands dirty.
So for somebody else, then?
It has been like this for a long time, so I am not sure if anyone is going to step up
to try to fix that. Thank you.
All right, thanks.