This is a file system update and its future.
Hello everyone, thanks for listening to my topic.
Here are the file system updates and its future.
Due to my visa application issue, I didn't find a proper way to go to Brussels on site.
Therefore, I have to upload a video for online presentation.
My name is Xiang Gao and I've been working on Lynx kernel staffs for most 7 years,
mainly focusing on the local file system staff.
I guess E-RFS is still a familiar staff for some people.
And here I try to give more useful information of E-RFS.
Hopefully, it is helpful to everyone.
So E-RFS stands for Enhanced Read-Only File System.
It was originally started in late 2017 and available since 4.19.
It is designed to be a generic high-performance read-only file system
with a very simple but effective core-on-disk format design.
As a result, it almost has a better performance among the current kernel read-only file system.
E-RFS is kernel multiple as a SQL or cover format replacement of traditional CPIO and TAR.
And it is currently contributed by community libraries,
IWAC, Dance, Copad, Google, Huawei, OPPO, and more.
So as an option, E-RFS supports profile of the four and LVM a transparent data compression.
However, E-RFS can live without compression as well.
It is targeted for various high-performance read-only solutions
such as system partitions and APX for Android, Smartphone,
and other embedded systems,
Blue CDs and Container Images, as well as AR datasets.
There are many useful features which are actively under development,
so if you have any suggestions or contributions, always welcome.
There are several main use cases for E-RFS.
The first main use case is Android system partitions.
So Android has several read-only partitions which behave as system firewall,
which means Android core can only be changed by way of an update.
So in this way, it has many benefits such as it is easy for vendors to shift, distribute,
keep original signing, golden images to each instance,
and it is easy to go back to the original ship's date or do incremental updates.
And it is easy to check data corruption or do data recovery even in a very low level,
such as hardware.
Also, it is easy for real storage devices to do hardware write protection and even more.
So why are we introducing E-RFS?
Basically, because it is read-only compression solutions,
the internal cannot meet our performance requirements.
But we need to do compression for our low-ended Android devices, smartphones at that time.
That is why we designed E-RFS and sorted out from the beginning.
We handled many basic common issues of generating read-only use cases
to get high performance read-only file system.
In addition, it is good to switch E-PX to E-RFS on disk format as well.
Also, currently, E-PK is also another cover format.
If it becomes E-RFS mumble, that may leverage the latest on-demand
devices running on Android Cloudfish emulator.
Our second main language use case for E-RFS is container image with a user space program called Netas.
Tellingfly Netas is a user space example which uses E-RFS to leverage its functionality
to do faster container image distribution like lazy polling and data de-tuberation across layers and images.
Currently, Netas can do lazy polling for Netas, E-RFS images, as well as StarGZ images
and original OCI images with an extra minimal index, which is much similar to another project
which is called OCI.
For more details of Netas itself, you could also refer to another topic which is called Netas image service
for confidential containers at confidential computing dev room.
On the left-hand side, it is Netas architecture.
You could see that image format could be built with advanced features such as lazy polling, data de-tuberation,
and native OCI compatible molds.
And the read-only file system for containers such as 1C, KATA, KATA-CC, E-R Molds,
and software package can be run by Netas D with Linux, Mac OS, FUSE, Wotawa, FFS, and E-RFS,
over FFS cache with pitch cache sharing.
So on the right-hand side, it is some partners which are Netas and Dragonfly solutions.
The second demo, E-RFS is running with Netas for container images.
So first, we need to run Netas container.
And it finished in 16 seconds.
Then it runs OCI container.
You can see that it finished in 27 seconds.
So that it induces time due to lazy polling.
So this is the third demo. In this demo, E-RFS is running with original OCI and Netas LIM indexes for lazy polling.
Note that this use case is still under development so that we could optimize it even further.
So first, we start or read in OCI container.
And it costs 26 seconds.
And we view Netas LIM indexes for OCI images.
So next, we start a zero OCI container.
And you can see it costs 21 seconds. And that is the file system.
You could see that the Netas LIM indexes is very small.
So next, I will go into take some minutes to give a brief introduction of E-RFS core internals.
So as an effective read-only internal solutions, core E-RFS on disk format is quite simple.
Almost all E-RFS on disk structures are well aligned and lead within your single block,
which means they are never across two blocks for performance.
So on the left-hand side, it is on disk superblock format,
which contains the overall five system statistics and the root I-node NID.
Each E-RFS I-node is aligned in I-node slot so that the basic I-node information can be in the same block.
And they can be read and advanced.
On the right-hand side, there are E-RFS on this I-node format.
Short, extended attributes can be kept just next to the core on disk I-node,
as well as chunk, compress indexes, and the in-line data.
Here is E-RFS on disk directory format.
E-RFS directories consist of several directory blocks.
Each block contains two parts called the direct part and the name part,
so that with such on-disk design, E-RFS can do a name lookup with binary search,
which makes E-RFS more effective than others exist in kernel read-only FL systems
and keep it in a simple implementation.
So here is an overview of the net-as-use case.
You can see that it has almost two parts.
One part is called bootstrap, also called primary device, which has a meta-block and a data block.
So the meta-block could have super-block, I-nodes, and some in-line data.
And the other data blocks could have directory blocks or some blocks for regular files.
And the other part is called the blocks, which could have external data,
which is separated with chunks, so that in such designs,
the blocks can be referred with the metadata.
And the details of compressed data is somewhat not quite trivial,
but it could be referred from the following links as well, if you have more interesting.
Here is the E-RFS recent updates.
The first two features called chunk-based file,
which could implement sparse files and data-deduplicated plain files.
The next feature is called multiple devices and blocks.
So E-RFS images can refer to other external data as well.
Since 5.19, E-RFS over IFS cache has been already landed,
which is already mentioned by some materials available online as the following links.
Since 6.1, E-RFS has been introduced a special I-node called piped I-node for tail data,
so that tail data or the whole files can be deduced or compressed together.
Also, since 6.1, E-RFS supported global compressed data deduplication by using ruling cache.
E-RFS over IFS cache sharing is still working in progress.
So here is E-RFS compressed data deduplication test result.
You can see that compared with scratchFS, E-RFS is more space-saving by using this new optimization.
So in the next year, we've already planted some new features.
Many of them are already working in progress, such as verification solutions
and data deduplicated encryption solutions.
We also have IFS cache improvements together with bad-dense forks,
such as failover, multiple dimmers and directories, as well as dimmers.
And more features can be referred to with the following links.
So that's all of my topic. Thanks for listening again.
If you have more interest in E-RFS, please kindly contact and join us. Thank you.
We actually have time for five minutes of questions.
We don't know how bad the lag actually is, but we can type the question into the chat if you have one.
Or you can just ask it.
Thanks for the talk. There was mention of a self-contained verification solution.
Did you compare it with the m-variety and what advantages do you see in the verification solution you are working on?
I mean, you can also write it, yeah.
We have no idea what the lag is.
Can you put some of your out?
Sure. Do you have the app installed, like the FOSM app?
If you go into the schedule, then you just need to click a link.
I'm sorry.
Okay.
This is a text-only development room, by the way, as you can see.