So the next talk is by Andrei on hacking the Linux kernel to get more FPS.
Thank you.
Can you hear me?
It's working.
Hello.
Is it green?
Yes.
Okay.
Hello.
Hi everyone.
I'm a kernel developer from Brazil and I work for the Open Source Consorteci Yale.
Does anyone here play on Linux?
Okay.
Wow.
Cool.
And I hope it's been great.
And in this talk it's not very, very technical.
It's just collected some work that has been done by a ton of people to make game on Linux
better on the kernel side.
So as you probably know, Linux kernel has not really a roadmap.
It's a lot like trying to implement, oh, we need 10 new file systems by the next year
or any kind of this.
It's all driven by use case.
And I mean, if you don't have any real use case, it will be very hard to get your code
in the kernel.
So it's all about new use case.
So for instance, some use of goals.
We had the Android that pushed a lot of new kinds of kernel like VRM and then a container
that helped us grow the C group's things.
And then the cloud that mess up a little bit in the file system stack.
So in the past before proton and this kind of stuff, games on Linux was not that easy.
We had a lot of native things, but it was really on and off.
And Jlib C has some API.
It's not that stable on the long term.
And to play online, wine wasn't so stable either back then.
So we had some native ports along the way.
And also the source engine was one of these native ports.
And one very interesting example of how the native version is hard to get right.
By tracking finish, it runs very, very bad on native.
But if you run the Windows version for proton, it goes very great.
So it was on and off.
We had a very big financial interest on Game of Linux.
Until things changed.
So proton was announced some years ago.
Is a big project from Valve to be able to run Windows games on Linux as good as possible.
So Valve has been paying a lot of community developers and consultancies like Yagale to
enhance the Linux gaming in all the stack from Wine, Mesa, and the kernel.
And after that, things started really speeding up.
And now we have the Steam Deck.
And we can see on what was all this effort about now.
Now we have the big picture why they are pushing so hard for the Linux gaming.
And this is from the website Boiling Steam.
And this is from two years ago.
It's not really up to date.
But you can see this is like the numbers of the red one is the reported games on the proton
database.
And the blue one is like games that are running very nice.
So you can see that by time we are really increasing the number of games that we can
run on Linux.
And this is the Linux market share of the Steam users.
And you can see that it's really, really small.
But you can see that it's getting bigger in a...
Well, it's getting bigger all of the time.
If this line goes by infinity, you get all the market on one day.
Okay.
So now about the kernel features that have appeared just because people decide to play
game of Linux.
The first one is a very dramatic one.
I don't know why people hate that so much, but you can now have a case-insensitive folder
on your file system Linux.
And people were very mad about that.
But yeah, it's operational, so it doesn't matter if you don't want to use that.
And to achieve that, it was needed to create a Unicode subsystem on the kernel.
So now in the kernel, we have often emojis and etc.
And this is one of the things that I want you...
That I like about Linux kernel development is that this was developed for the Linux for
gaming use case.
But then I think the Google people was like, hey, this is very cool.
And then they make it support for FQFS for Android.
And yeah, so every part of the community can benefit from the effort from each other.
So yeah, now we have case-insensitive for Linux due to games.
And this is, of course, because NTFS is a case-insensitive file system.
And it's very troublesome to do that, to do the file path lookup from the user space.
If you need to emulate on user space the case-insensitive thing, it's very hard to do that, because you
need to try all sorts of combinations.
But on the kernel side, it's very easy to do.
You kind of abstract all the things for the user space.
Futex is what I'm most known for, is the work that I was involved with.
So Futex is something that is exposed from the kernel.
So user space can create mutex, semaphores, barriers, all kind of cool, synchronous sync
prim chips.
And on the Windows side, you have something similar.
You have the sync API from the Windows kernel.
And then you have this function from the Windows called wait for multiple objects.
That for some reason, games really like to call that.
They really rely on that.
And on Linux, it was not that easy to emulate that, to try and emulate that.
We tried with EventFudy, but EventFudy doesn't scale so well if you have so many waiters.
So we moved to Futex.
And then after some years, I finally managed to get it right.
And it was merged.
So nowadays, you can wait on multiple Futexes on Linux.
And this was created for gaming, but I know that some distributed systems and databases
also want you to have this operation.
But yeah, I assume you need to expose that using patrons.
And the Futex effort kind of created the Futex 2 project because I was there on the main
list.
Hey, hey, I need a new Futex operation.
I was like, OK, but you need to solve all the other Futex stuff going on.
And I spent some time collecting why were people so disappointed with Futex.
And now we know what we need to improve for Futex.
And I work on the Futex 2 thing to have a lot of cool Futex operations.
Cisco user Dispatched is a feature from their Linux kernel that also was created for gaming
because usually when you are developing a Windows game, you want to call Cisco, you
just use the wrapper.
But some games, because of the DRM thing, they use it to call the Cisco directly using
the x86 instruction.
But of course, on Linux, that Cisco number didn't match it, the Windows one.
And it was very hard for a line to deal with that.
So basically nowadays you can select a memory region and say that every time you have Cisco
there, it will not go directly to the Cisco path.
It will call another program to another backend to see if it really should be issued that
Cisco number.
So yeah, it calls the Cisco, but get back to user space, I think, like that.
GPU driver, so on DRM we are working hard to make AMD GPU better.
So in the past months, we have been, after the Cinec release, the AMD GPU was exposed
to all sorts of gamers and user cases.
And this has been popping a lot of bug reports, and we are trying to fix them.
And also, as I said, this is like kind of pushing the limits of the driver and the hardware.
We are working on new DRM features like a sync page flip in the atomic API, and also
working to have a better GPU reset rendering.
Because nowadays if your AMD GPU resets, you need to press the button because it won't
work again.
Also, we are trying to get HDR on Linux and also support 3D image on DRM.
Also in this kind of error rendering area, we are trying to have a nice feedback for
the user when the kernel crashes.
Kind of a Windows blue screen with a link to figure out what is going on.
Also we have enabled Pstore and Kdub on Cinec, so you can have the last D-mask in a safe
place to check out what went wrong.
And if everything goes right, you can submit that for, I don't know, for the Cine server
so they can have a look and help you to figure out what is going on.
So, hardware enabled, a lot of drivers for the Cine deck and some work on the GY6 to
have a pattern on how GY6 exposes features to user space.
Oops.
Well, that is a lot of things, smaller things, smaller projects like the split-lock detector
handling.
So basically on x86 you have this feature that is the split-lock that you can do atomic
operations on all in memory, but it seems that you shouldn't do that.
And then if you do that nowadays, the kernel will penalize you and make your code run very
slow.
And of course games worth doing that.
So we kind of added a button on the kernel so you can turn off, so you can play your
games.
HDI had the bottleneck.
I mean, it was okay, but given that a lot of people start using VR, and VR has a lot
of HDI devices, we kind of discovered that it has had a bottleneck and then we fixed
that.
So some semantics on Unix sockets, on timestamps, on the time counter, because Windows and Linux,
they play very different on the timekeeping thing.
And yeah, a lot of documentation that we are trying to improve along the Linux kernel.
Out of three, this is very interesting because a lot of people do on the free time, they
try to hack the Linux kernel to play faster games.
And some people develop test schedulers, because on Linux, as you may know, we have the CFS,
but people have cool ideas of how to test schedule could be better for desktop use case
to reduce the latency, et cetera.
And these people, some of the projects are not very committed to make this upstream.
So yeah, they use the creativity and try a lot of different ideas.
And another interesting thing is that there are some projects out there like Zen kernel,
Shenmote kernel, Likorex kernel, that are basically a bunch of unofficial kernel releases
made by the community to have a better Linux gaming kernel.
And it's very fun because they grab a lot of out of patches, they grab working on progress
patches and make it together and do a release.
It's a very experimental kernel.
Of course, it has some bugs, it has some problems, but I think it's cool to try out to see if
your games run better on those kernels.
And yeah, I also checked those kernels to see what they come with, to see if there are
cool ideas going on there.
And for the future, I think we are going to try to enhance the power management so the
handheld devices can have better battery life.
And there are so many layers of GPU abstraction nowadays with all the strong translation.
And I think we are trying to...
I think the bottleneck will be on VRM.
And we will need to support that huge stack better.
And here at the end, I have some lists of the patches that I set so we can have a look.
And I think that's it.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Time for questions.
Please raise your hand.
No question?
I have a question.
For the task scheduler, did you look into the upstream development that is going on
right now where you can specify schedulers through eBPF, for example?
Oh, yeah.
I have heard about that.
But I don't know if the people tried to replicate those schedulers using eBPF.
But yeah, we'll have a look at that.
Might be interesting.
Yeah, sure.
Cool.
Thanks a lot.
Oh, there's what...
Sorry, sorry, sorry.
One question.
Thank you.
I had a question about how hard is it to introduce new stuff into the kernel that only you need?
Like, you told us, like, some things were just used by you for gaming.
So it's pretty new.
You just have to use it.
How hard is it?
Is it easy?
Depends on.
If you really... if you mess with a bunch of code, if you decrease the performance of
something like on the server side, people will not be so happy about that.
But if you don't mess with things that already exist, people will be okay with that.
Thank you.