Okay, we're ready for our next talk.
Daniel is going to talk about MetaNet devices.
Thanks.
All right.
Thanks a lot.
So, yeah.
So, this talk is about MetaNet devices.
This work has been done by my colleague and myself.
We are at Isovalent software engineers working on the kernel and also psyllium.
So, really, the goal is the question we were asking ourselves, like, how can we leverage
the BPF infrastructure in the kernel and also the networking features to really achieve
maximum performance for Kubernetes parts?
And before I go into the kernel bits, just a really quick recap around Kubernetes and
parts and what it is.
So, basically, what you can see here is a host.
A host can have one or many parts in Kubernetes.
It's an orchestration system, essentially, and a part is usually defined as a network
namespace and it is connected to typically to weave devices to get traffic in and out
of them.
A part can have one or many containers that are sharing this network namespace.
So, yeah, and CNI is basically a networking plugin which will set up various things.
When a part comes up, for example, it will set up Net devices, assign IP addresses.
It has an IPAM infrastructure to manage a pool of addresses.
It will install routes.
In the case of psyllium, which is a CNI, it will also set up the BPF data paths to basically
route traffic in and out.
It has various features on top as well, such as policy enforcement, load balancing, bandwidth
management, and so on and so forth.
But I don't want to make this talk about all the different features about psyllium, but
rather about performance.
There was an interesting keynote last year at the SA Econ from Brandon Gregg where he
talked about computing performance and what's on the horizon.
He had a couple of predictions and one was quite interesting when he was talking about
OS performance.
The statement that he made is that given the kernel is becoming increasingly complex, the
performance defaults are getting worse and worse.
He stated that it basically takes a whole US team to make the operating system perform
well.
The problem is, given all these performance teams they are trying to optimize at the larger
scale, nobody is actually looking at the defaults anymore and how they can be optimized.
This was quite interesting.
In case of defaults, we were wondering, given two Kubernetes nodes with part to part and
they connected with 100 gigabit NIC, we wanted to look at the single flow, like a single
TCP stream.
We asked what's the default baseline you can get to, where are bottlenecks, how can they
be overcome, and actually can we provide better defaults out of that, what we figure out.
Why buttering with single stream performance?
First of all, it's interesting for the kernel to cope with growing NIC speeds, 100, 200
gigabit or more, how can this be maxed out with the single stream.
There are lots of data intensive workloads from user and customer sites around machine
learning, AI and so on, but generally it's also interesting to be able to free up the
resources and give them to the application instead of the kernel having to block them.
The assumptions for our test is usually the Kubernetes worker nodes that users run, they
are quite generic, they can run any kind of workloads.
What we are also seeing is a large number of users typically just stick to defaults,
they don't tune specifically the kernel.
There's an interesting cloud native usage report where they try to get some insights
into how Kubernetes deployments usually look like.
There's definitely an increasing trend to have a higher density of containers per host,
so around 50 or more is expected these days and the number of pods per node is also increasing.
The question now is, so a very basic compatibility setting, for example, for the kernel, for
the case of psyllium, we used the, like if you deployed in a basic mode, we just used
the upper stack for routing and forwarding.
There are various reasons why people might want to use that.
For example, in case of Kubernetes, there's a component called QProxy which uses NetFilter
IP tables for service management, for service load balancing, some people stick to that.
Or they have custom NetFilter rules, so maybe they require to use the upper stack for that,
or just simply they for now just went with defaults and might look into more tuning at
a later point in time.
When we try to look at the performance for that, what you can see here is on the yellow
bar is the host to host performance for a single stream, so we got to 4 gigabit per
second but then if you do the pod to pod connectivity, it's really reduced dramatically.
One of the reasons is, and I will get into this in a bit, is because the upper stack
is giving false feedback to the TCP stack, one thing that we did a year ago or so is
to introduce a feature which is called BPF host routing, where we don't use the upper
stack.
For BPF itself, given we attach to physical devices but also to these devices, we added
a couple of new helper functions there, one is called BPF redirect peer, what this is
basically doing is adding a fast switch into the network name space for the ingress traffic,
so basically we're just, instead of going to the usual Xmid route to the weaves devices,
we can retrieve the weaves device inside the pod and just scrub the packet to remove the
necessary data that we typically remove from switching network namespaces but also to set
the device to the device inside the pod and then circle around in the main receive loop
without going to a per CPU backlog queue that you would normally do when you transfer data
through weaves devices and we don't need to use the upper stack because there's all the
information already available in BPF context and for the way out we added a helper which
is called BPF redirect neighbor, so that one will basically insert the packet into the
neighboring subsystem of the kernel, so usually we can do a flip lookup out of BPF, so there's
a helper for this as well and then combined with this for the resolution of neighbors,
it will allow that you don't need to go to the upper stack, so the nice benefit you get
as well with this is that the socket context for the network packet for the SKP is retained
all the way to the physical device until the packet is actually sent out and this is not
the case when you normally go to the upper stack, so then the TCP stack actually thinks
that like once you go to the upper stack that it already left the node but it's actually
not the case and this way it can be retained and this is how the complete picture looks
like and if you look at the performance it's already much better, so we were able to get
almost to 40 gigabit per second under 1.5k MTU, so this was interesting, now the question
is like how could we close the remaining gap?
On the 8k MTU we also did some tests and one thing to note here is that we were able to
like for single TCP stream to get to 98 gigabit per second for the host to host case but still
like the situation looks quite the same for the WEEF with the BPF host routing, so there's
still like a small gap that we want to close here as well and that's where we introduce
a new device type as a WEEF replacement, so we call this meta device because it's programmable
to a BPF and you can implement various, you know, like your own business logic into this,
so it's flexible and this time like the main difference is that this also gets like a faster
switch on the Egress side for the Egress traffic so it doesn't need to go to the per CPU backlog
view for the Egress as well.
So if you look at the flame graphs, so that's like the worst case scenario where we compared
the WEEF and the meta device, so what you can see here on the WEEF device, like on XMID
it will basically scrub the packet data, it will unqueue the packet to a per CPU backlog
view and then at some point there's a network's action, it will pick up the packets from the
queue again and in the worst case it can be deferred to the kernel software queue daemon
and then you see this rescheduling where you have a new stack where this is processed again
and then from the BPF side it will reach BPF from the TC ingress on the host WEEF where
we then can only forward this to the physical device to leave the node, right?
And all of this can be done in one go without rescheduling through this meta device, so
it will scrub the packet, it will switch the network namespace, it will reset the device
pointers and it will then directly call the BPF program and if the BPF program says that
based on the FIP lookup and so on that it will forward the packet directly to the physical
device then it will avoid this rescheduling scenario.
So like on the right side, I mean it's really straightforward, that's how the implementation
of the driver ex-mid routine looks like, so it will basically just call into BPF and then
based on the verdict push it out.
It's really just like 500 lines of code, so it's very simple and straightforward, I think
it's just one fifth of the WEEF driver that we have right now and the other focus that
we wanted to put into is compatibility as well so that like given in Sium we need to
support multiple kernels, the ideal case would be like that we don't need to change much
of the BPF program and can keep it as is.
And in case of XTP we didn't want to implement it because like for the WEEF case it really
is very complex, it even adds multi-queue support which you normally would not need
on a virtual device, so we wanted to keep it as simple as possible and to have to flip
the ability that this can be added as a single or paired device.
Like for the WEEF replacement it would be a paired device but you could also do it as
a single device and then implement whatever logic you would want in BPF for that.
So looking at the performance, again like the TCP stream under 8K, so this is really
able to reach through this approach the full 98 gigabit per second and in terms of latency,
so we did some Netperf TCP or R measurements as well where you get the minimum, the P90,
99 latency and so on, so this is really on par with the host.
So now we were asking ourselves can we push this even further, I mean well so we were
able to get to 98 gigabit per second but like the cost for like a megabyte to transfer can
just push even more and there's a relatively recent kernel feature which is called big
TCP.
It landed for IPv6 only in 519 and was developed by Google and the whole idea behind big TCP
is to even more aggressively aggregate for geo and gso, so normally the kernel will try
it basically out of the incoming packet stream, create a super packet and then we'll push
it up to the networking stack so it only needs to be traversed once and the limit up until
that point was for 64K packets simply because in the IP header that's the maximum packet
size that you can do and the idea for a big TCP for IPv6 was that well maybe we could
create a hop by hop header in the geo layer and then add and then like the 16 bit packet
length field can be overcome because there is a jumbogram extension in there which allows
for 32 bits field.
So you can do much more aggressive aggregation and yeah, so this is also now supported with
the new release where this will be set up for all the devices and the need for automatically
for IPv6.
Actually like this week there was also, got also merged for IPv4 now so this will land
in kernel 6.3 which is exciting and when we looked at the performance again under big
TCP turns out like the using the upper stack is currently broken into kernel so that still
needs to be fixed, we will look into that.
So forwarding there wouldn't work then with the host routing cases so it will basically
bump up the regular weave one to get this on par with the meta and also the host so
it will basically hide those glitches.
The latency is still better in terms of like the short packet request response type workloads
for the meta so that's still on par with the host.
So what is the remaining offender like when you run all these features together it's basically
the copying to users so like between 60 and 70% of the cycles is really spent on copying
all this data to user space.
So the next question we ask ourselves actually in this experiment, so what if we combine
the whole big TCP stuff with TCP zero copy so what if we could leverage the memory map
TCP and it turns out that's currently not possible in the kernel, that's a limitation
because in the GRO layer big TCP will create a frag list which is essentially like a list
of SKBs you know as a single big one that is being pushed up the stack and TCP zero
copy only works on the SKB frags so that's like an internal so where basically you have
a single SKB and it has like the pages as read only attached in the nonlinear section.
So that currently does not work combining those two would probably have like really
big potential but what we now try to do is we just looked at the just using the TCP zero
copy to see how it looks without the big TCP.
Generally speaking is not as straightforward to deploy because first of all you need to
rewrite your application in order to leverage memory map TCP this can be done for RX but
also for TX or both and it needs driver changes and in particular driver changes to be able
to split the header from the data because the data you want to memory map to user space.
Some Nix might do this with the hardware and some others you would have to do some kind
of pseudo header data splits over you basically just copy the header into a linear section.
So this is how it would look like we tried this for 4K and 8K MTU.
There's a great talk from Eric Dumasay the TCP maintainer in terms of what all the all
those things you need to do in order to be able to make use of this for example you also
need to align the TCP window scale to 12 segments so that you fill exactly those pages.
And yeah the driver support can be very different like we had in our lab MLX 500 gigabit Nix
and they did not implement the header data splits so my colleague Nikolai did the POC
implementation to change the driver to be able to do that so that we could get some
measurements out of this and if you want to look into an example application and how you
can implement that there's one in the networking self test in the upstream tree called TCP
mmap which is useful also for the benchmarking.
So you really need to align various different settings like for our test implementation
we used for MLX 5 the non-striding modes or the legacy modes we need to switch that off
and Eve tool first because I mean for the POC it was easier to do the way like the packet
layout is done there then you need to align the MTU to either one page or two pages and
you need to do various other settings like in the for the course of time I will not go
into all of the details.
In generally I would think it would be useful addition to the kernel to have like a configuration
framework for that and to be able to have more drivers supporting the header data split
there's actually one in Windows kernel turns out so there's some documentation around there
that we found while preparing for the talk the other thing is a caveat is like the TCP
zero copy may like the benefits might be limited if you then actually go in your application
and then touch the data because then they need to be pulled into the cache which they
would be if like if you would have to copy things to user but they may not be like if
you just memory map so the applications there is mostly like on the for example storage
side where you wouldn't have to do that and looking at the data for 4k MTU we tried with
the implementation we got to 81 gigabit per second so that's a bit limiting could also
be that this is mostly because the implementation was you know a PLC with lots of optimization
potential that can still be there but we looked at it came to you and there we were able to
get to 98 gigabit per second but the interesting piece here is the cost per megabyte we could
we were able to reduce from 85 down to 27 microseconds per megabyte so this really is
significant and yeah because of the avoidance that you don't copy anymore so as a summary
so we started with the default and then you know switch to the 8k MTU then we went to
the host routing that we covered then the addition of the meta device where we can avoid
where we can do this low latency you know for ingress and egress then the big TCP and
that all works without changes to the application and with that you can already get like a 2x
improvement and then it gets even more dramatic but it's of course dependent on your application
for the zero copy some of the future directions as I mentioned earlier it would be useful
to have like a generic header data split framework for NIC drivers that they can implement that
and expose it this setting there's potential here as well to optimize for example like
the header pages could be the head page could be packed with the headers it could get recycling
which we didn't implement here and in future big TCP would be interesting to combine with
the zero copy so that discovers the frag list in geo and the other thing that is at
some point on the horizon is to push the big TCP actually onto the wire as well if the
hardware supports that and yeah so with that I'm done with the talk and the prototype for
the meta device is currently you can find on this branch we are working on pushing this
upstream in the coming months and there's also the prototype public for the MLX 5 header
data split and yeah so the plan is basically to get this into upstream kernel and then
also to get this integrated into psyllium for the for the next release yeah thank you
are there any questions thanks we already have two questions in the chat so we can start
with them if there are no in the room alright so the first question we got was can we my
well not really a question so much as a comment I think which is can we please come up with
a better name than meta for this just call it BPF or BPF dev or something yeah the other
thing was if the perf benefit comes from calling sure from inside the network namespace can
we just make vf do that instead I think we could but the question is like I haven't looked
into the the like how it would affect the XTP related bits so it felt easier to do something
simple and start from scratch like one thing I don't really like about the weave devices
to be honest how complex it got with the older XTP additions and it's not even that beneficial
and it added like multi queue support and all of that which was not needed at all for
a virtual device so I really wanted to have something simple and yeah and easy so any
more questions from the audience here I have a question you are about big TCP and TCP zero
copy it's in your lab you only did benchmarks host to host right because so but also part
to part so we tried both yeah okay because do you know how it would work with the switches
do you need special switch support for no no so the big TCP is only local to the node
so like the packets on the wire they will still be your MTU size packets it's just that
the the aggregation on like for the local stack is much bigger so it's it doesn't affect
anything on the wire that's a nice thing okay and for zero copy I mean like for the zero
copy you need to change definitely the MTU which also affects the rest of your network
of course so that's one thing that would be required for that thank you.