Hello, everyone.
And now we have a talk by Johannes Bergberg.
I hope he pronounced that right.
He's a JBM developer working on profiles and the underlying technology.
He currently works on a JAP, profiling, documentation, smaller utilities and the Firefox profiler.
He's going to have a talk on Firefox profilers beyond the web using Firefox profiler to view
Java profiling data.
And yes?
Yeah.
Thanks for the kind introduction.
Yes, I'm Johannes Bergberg, working at the submachine team at SAP.
We create the best JDKs, so just download it.
But I'm here because I worked on the Firefox profiler in the recent months.
And yeah, I'm going to start now.
Because when I'm telling people that I'm like working at SAP at Firefox profiler, they first
ask me two questions.
Like, first, wait, SAP does open source?
Yes, SAP does open source.
And quite a lot, for example, here at submachine, my team, we're working on the open JDK.
For example, if you've ever used JDK 17, we have the JDK 17 maintainer in our team.
So we do many nice projects in this field.
SAP also works with the Eclipse foundation or other parts.
So yeah, we're doing quite a bit of open source.
But how did I end up here talking to you in this Marcel Daffrom as a JDK developer, which
normally doesn't happen?
So I had a problem.
I had a project on debugging last year.
So what I wanted to do essentially is that I had on the one hand my IDE and on the other
hand the JVM.
They wanted to improve the protocol in between.
So I had some test cases and some of these did some integration testings.
For example, here they parsed some program and I did something with it and they wanted
to see why it was slower than I expected.
And so what I wanted to do is just write a plug on my IDE, tell it that, hey, profile
it and show me the profile and it's off.
And I wanted to do it with open source.
Because I like open source and that our team open source is really key.
So I didn't find anything, but I found some tools that got into this direction.
So essentially there were tools that produced some flame crafts and as the UI.
And Mario Fusco said a few days back, allow frame crafts.
When you do something stupid, it punches you in your face and it's impossible not to see
it.
So that's great.
You can use flame crafts for things, but sometimes they are not enough.
So when you regard visualizations, you have the easy tools that are easy to use but don't
have that many features.
And on the other hand, you have the big tool.
It's called JMC.
There's lots of features but has a quite steep learning curve.
So I had to write my own because I wanted to have something with more visualizations
than just flame crafts.
That was usable, also usable to the end user.
And not just open JDK developer like James Z is.
And I wanted to just right click on a method, on a test method and just tell my IDE hey,
run the thing.
So I don't end up writing so much code.
And so writing your own intelligent plugin, and that's the IDE I'm targeting.
But it's quite the same for other IDE tools like Visual Studio Code.
It's quite simple.
You can just download some templates and work on them.
So this I did in August in like half a week.
But then it came to visualization options.
So I looked around and thought maybe creating my own visualizations like flame crafts and
so on.
But this turned out to be cumbersome.
And really would take a lot of work.
So I looked around for web based visualizations because you can just embed a web based profile
and view into your IDE.
Because for example in Telstra you have a chromium and embedded chromium and in VS code
it's essentially a browser anyway.
So that's no problem.
iPhone speed scope, which is quite nice.
But the problem is it doesn't show anything other than stack traces and some profile timing
information and I wanted to show more.
There is kind of an existing plugin for IntelliJ but that only shows flame graphs and so we're
back to step on.
And then I found Firefox profile and this is how I ended up here.
So essentially Firefox profile is this large application that you've probably seen in some
other talks today too.
This is actually taken from a previous talk because I was too lazy to run Firefox profile.
And you see here it's like it does everything and it's quite cool.
One of the many advantages is that it's developed by a small team that answer even stupid questions
in a matrix channel.
So check it out if you have some questions.
And they were working with me on my project.
And also it's backed by cooperation.
It's backed by Mozilla which is quite cool because it's not a one man project like other
tools are.
And so what did I do to integrate it and what might you do if you want to also use Firefox
profile?
It essentially points down to creating a tool converter that my data format, it's a JFR
file format to the Firefox profile format.
And then you put it in the server because Firefox profile likes it when you can just
say take this file from a URL so you put it in the server.
That's fine.
For me I created the travel in server.
Then you can just wrap it in IntelliJ plugin or with code plugin or so on.
And then I took the Firefox profile.
You can use profile.Firefox.com but you would typically just host it your own because Daniel
Burks and Demos like Bully today when they have time and you can control all the changes
that come into your Firefox profile UI and also you can use a modified version which
I did to put all my progress that is still out there and not merged into one version.
So the things you'll later see that are in my tool are sometimes not yet in the mainstream
Firefox profile.
So shortly to the file format.
So file format is quite simple.
It's just a JSON file and this is zipped and it has some metadata information like
the name, the interval, some settings and then you have to fetch information.
So for every fetch you have a separate section in the profile and you have a list of samples
there and this list contains essentially the time of when the sample is taken, the stack
and the CPU delta that's the elapsed CPU time since the last sample so it can be used to
show the CPU usage data.
Then the stack is not all the stack but it's an index into the stack array and this contains
like the list of stacks and where the stack is just the frame, a pointer to the previous
stack like the top frame and then the previous stack so it points back and then the category
and of course the frame is an index into the frame area and that contains the function
align so what you need for a frame and then of course function is not really the function
but it's an index into the functions.
Everyone you get the point here because name and file are of course not strings but they
are indexes into the string table.
That's quite hard to debug sometimes and I had many struggles with it but it's quite
performant and it's easy for the front end to see.
So after I explained you how I did it, here's the plugin.
I call the Java JFR Profi- plugin.
You can find it in the track frames marketplace and on GitHub it's open source, it's MIT license
I believe and it works because JFR was open source with JDK 11 so it's all open source.
Just try it out.
So how can you get it, just open your IDE and go into the plugin install, view and type
in Java JFR profile and you get it.
Then you get some nice buttons when you right click and you can just click on the button
profile with JFR then you profile it and then here's a simple example application that just
computes complicated or something like that and then you can see that it executes the
program with some JFR related options to profile it and then it opens automatically the profile
of JFR file, you get the call tree.
You can also look at how every frame is executed whether it's in interpretive mode or in JIT
compiles then you can double click and jump back to the IDE so it has basic IDE integrations
and you can shift double click and see the source view that was presented in the previous
talk shortly so you can see here that in this code the recursive call is called the most
and is found the most time in the static calls and then you can have a function table which
lists all the methods combined so from all the stack traces and you see what method is
used the most.
That's not yet in the main line Firefox profileer.
You can have some plain proofs and you can have some nice tool tips and you can get some
information on the profile you can even upload it like a normal Firefox profile so you can
use these so you can share these profiles and view them in a normal profile.5.
So come just with some few features and then we can also any JFR file like the default
like the de facto standard for profiling files in Java and you can see here that we get also
some crafts that show us the CPU load and give us some summary on GC like how much memory
requested and what's also cool we can not only see timing but we can also see a call
tree for other things like for Java error for thread starts where did they happen or
for object allocation and when you get to Java error you see that this code uses error
to create error every time like probably the parsing files so we can also see as the last
part the marker chart so we can get all the events that the JVM emits so for example we
see here at the top that we had to drop in the memory that the heap was large and we
investigated we could zoom in and see okay that's probably because here GC happened and
this GC took like 10 milliseconds this is quite nice because you can then investigate
have the call tree as a simple thing and then later drop in and go deep dive into the data
and if you know async profile it also supports async profile and also when you want to create
a profile you can decide where you want JFR the built in for the JDK or async profile
and that's all but I think I still have some time so I hope this works because I can tell
you a lot that it might work and control you some screens but here is the actual working
hopefully working prototype so just right click on the main method tell it profile with
JFR and then it tells me hey I profile it then it opens the profile and then you can
just look at it zoom around zoom around and see that you have to select the main the main
tray thread you can jump back to the source code you can shift double click and everything
and the cool thing is you can even open as I showed you arbitrary JFRs they shouldn't
be too large because then my program runs out of memory sometimes it's still a prototype
so try it if you want I would be happy to have any feedback go to the GitHub issue pages
and eventually you find this plugin as I said in the chat brain marketplace you find me
on Mastodon on Twitter and on GitHub where you also find the sub project so you can use
parts of this project like only the converter and only the JFR to Firefox profile server
you find more information on my tool and also a background information to this talk into
blog posts on my blog and you can find the sub machine team at the sweet sub machine
at Twitter and find out about our great projects at sub machine AO that's for me thanks.
Thank you very much and we have quite a bit of time for questions so thank you have you
received any feedback from users about this tool like some colleagues or yes good questions
yeah I received quite some feedback on Twitter they were quite happy I did some internal
I showed it internally at SAP to some colleagues and they were quite happy I also showed it
to friends of mine and also it was quite great it still has of course problems because it's
a prototype it might not everything might work but yeah I'm looking forward so just
give it a try it's free open source open some issues on GitHub if you like so yeah I will
steal the mic did you add to forward some patches upstream to make it work in the first
time so for example this feature here is like not yet in master but for example what I added
was you saw this here this listing of the categories this is something that I added
and I added pull requests for the function table which is not yet in because it's far
more work added some resizing and searching that's yet that's I think in so I added some
pull requests that are in but not all of them but I hope I get it in the next few months
you can give beers to the upstream developers are here to get the patch yeah but but I fixed
all the bugs that they wanted to be fixed so I think we're working more like colleagues
I will ask a follow-up question quickly do you have to do anything Java specific in that
case there's nothing that is real and Java specific so the only the converters like Java
specific because it takes Java data and processes it but anything else in the UI is generic
yeah I was wondering if this could be useful to profile like a big Java applications that
run native code and the other way around and how would that work thinking of like for example
Firefox for Android I don't think we have a lot of like insight into the performance
of our Java code and that would be useful to have so so it's a summarize it where they
can like work with chain I or something like that I think asking profile is a quite nice
profile that I also support and this gives you information on native on native traces
and I'm working on getting a profiling a pain to open JDK that improves this lots but if
you want to know more about the struggles come tomorrow to my talk in the food a room
they hear enough about this topic hi yeah thanks for the presentation very impressive
the question I had actually I have two questions the first one is and what is about Firefox
profiler that made you choose it I suppose and then the second question is could you
see the potential for maybe a tool like this to sort of like actually have a web-based
editor yes the first thing why did I choose it because it's a nice project and I didn't
want to write everything on my own and it contained lots of the features that I already
wanted so yeah and they could ask questions because when you're working like alone on
such a prototype is that you don't get any feedback here got a lot of feedback on progress
and it was a quite good learning experience and the other thing is yeah as I said the
project consists only of a tiny intelligent wrapper around the other code and this can
be used to just integrate it into your spring web app to directly show it in the web I'm
I have some ideas on this just follow my blog to know more about this on my photo almost
in what do you think about the upload local profile is this an important feature in Europe
is it something that you'll is it part of the features that made you choose Firefox
profile it's quite a great feature because you can essentially know those you could later
than trust tell other people I have some performance issue here for example for four issues essentially
the same thing most all of us and I hope I can like open it to use it in a corporate
setting for example adding features to to use Microsoft tries for it so it's more safe
because currently you're applying it in into the web and that's not that great when you're
doing like internal company stuff but this feature then could really make it easy for
people to just say hey here I have some problem give me your sector is just uploaded and you're
fine so maybe next feature could be a server and no not the promise it's it's just me currently
working on it and so it's just a prototype I have to see what could be implemented in the future
any other questions we still have three minutes so if you have questions we can take them no well
then thank you very much do you want to add anything else yeah just try it out I would like
to have some users because I want to know what features are important to you and also where you
find some problems for example someone found that the Microsoft support wasn't there so on Microsoft
to trust first on Windows so if you find any issues please drop by and come to the matrix
channel for the of the Firefox profile there you can find me sitting around all day and can also
answer questions you may clear on it thank you very much