Hello, thanks everybody for coming. I will be talking today about what we know about
how Firefox uses power, what we can know about it, what we can do about it. First, what we
will cover today. So first, why do we care about this topic? Then how can we understand
power used locally, which means like if Firefox is using too much power on your own computer,
what can you do about it? And then how can we understand it about all users in general
in the world, so the entire race populations? And I will finish by explaining what we have
done, what we have improved and what we are still doing. So first, why do we care? There
are really two different sets of reasons. The first one is user experience. We very
frequently see users complaining that, okay, Firefox is using too much resources, too much
CPU. My computer is noisy, like the fans are making noise, they are going at full speed.
Or laptop is hot, if people are using a laptop. Or maybe the battery life is too short. So
all of those are reasons for an individual to want to use less power. There is another
set of reasons, which is sustainability. Mozilla cares about sustainability, made climate
commitments about being carbon neutral, about producing your greenhouse gas footprint. And
because we are Mozilla, we do things in the open. We want to lead on this and do it openly.
We want to share our tools, any material we have on this, methodologies. And also we want
to improve our products so that they are more sustainable. And the reason why we care so
much about our product is because when estimating our carbon footprint, because we have many
users, the use of our product is actually 98% of our footprint. So playing less, having
more efficient offices, this is all very great, but if we want to save a lot of power, that's
really looking at the product that we should look at.
So I said we will look locally first because I think there are some people in the room
who likely think, Firefox uses too much power on my computer, I want the battery to last
longer, and that's a very valued use case. And if we want to optimize for everybody,
we want first to be able to optimize to have it running correctly on one specific machine
in front of us before trying to go at scale. So I will present a few tools that we have
for this. But first I will explain how Firefox uses power. It's desktop applications, so
like any other computer application, it's using CPU time, using GPU time, waking up
CPUs, and actually CPUs are pretty good at saving power when we ask them to do nothing.
They go into deep sleep mode, they use almost no power. The problem is if we keep waking
them up, they can't really sleep, and that wastes a lot of power. And then there's a
few more things that we can do that use a little bit of power but not as much, like
transmitting network packets, for example, or writing to disks. And they are not where
we should focus our time if we really want to have a big impact. So this is how we use
power. And next, how we waste power. It's almost the same thing, the only difference
is when we do it for no user benefit. If we use CPU time and the user doesn't see a benefit
in what we are doing with the CPU, it's a waste. And same for all the other ways we
could use resources. And some typical ways to waste power is waking up threads too often,
playing animations even though they are completely invisible, or more generally doing things
in the background, things that have no visible effects. So typically when someone wants to
understand local power use, there's two reasons. Either Firefox is supposed to be guilty of
using too much power, there's like one core used at 100%, sometimes even more than one
core. Or sometimes the user is looking at the operating system task manager for a completely
different reason and notices that, okay, there are some Firefox processes that should be
idle because Firefox is supposed to be doing nothing, it's in the background, but it's
using 1% of the CPU or 0. something. Why? It used to be difficult to figure out answers
to those questions, we now have good tooling for it. So the first tool I wanted to share
is the Firefox task manager. You can open it by typing about processes in the address
bar. You can also use the shift escape keyboard shortcut that will open it directly. And it's
very similar to a task manager you would see in an operating system. It's showing you a
list of processes, how much memory is used by each, how much memory and CPU. But unlike
the operating system, it knows exactly which tab we are loading in which process. So if
you see that there's one process that's using a lot of CPU, and you see that it's a tab
that you actually don't really care about, you can just close that tab and this is done.
Because very often we have people who say, oh, Firefox is a lot of CPU, but you know
I have 50 tabs, so maybe it's because we've made it have Firefox is a lot. Naturally,
very often it's just there's one tab that's misbehaving, and finding quickly the right
one and closing it is the most efficient way to fix it. Something else I want to show on
this is that the numbers, the percentage of CPU's are very precious here. A lot more than
on the operating system task managers. For example, on the third process here you see
0.0, 11 percent. On the operating system you just see 0 in this case. And the reason why
we want to show it when it's almost nothing is because almost nothing means we are still
waking up the CPU to do a little bit of something. And we want to be able to catch this. Because
we use this kind of tooling to find real bugs. This is a screenshot captured on Nike. If
you are on a release build you won't see the thread names unless you enable it in about
config. Okay, so let's assume you have found that there's a real problem there and it's
not a tab you can easily close. The next step, which is more in the tooling, is using the
Firefox profiler. I won't go into details on the Firefox profiler because the next presentation
is also about the profiler. But I will say that we recently added a preset for power
profiling which configures the profiler in a way that causes very little overhead. And
we also have a power profiling mode that was added recently that will be able to say how
many watts we used, not just how much CPU. So you can enable it quickly with this preset.
I just wanted to show an example of how precise the measurement can be. This is a profile
showing Firefox doing nothing. There was just one thing that was left. It was the cursor
in the address bar. It was blinking. On all the spikes that you can see in here, they
are whenever the cursor appears or disappears. And here we could select this area and see
in the tool tip exactly how much power we used to do this tiny thing. So anything we
do, we can see it in the profiler, see how much power we used and correlate. Honestly,
I never thought we could see things like this. I thought we could see bigger things like
loading a page but blinking the cursor, that was a surprise. And a good one. Another thing
in the profiler that I wanted to share, and it's the last one because the next talk will
be all about the profiler, is the profiler records many markers. And especially I wanted
to show the awake and vulnerable markers that make it easy to see why we were waking up
of thread. Whenever the thread wakes up, there's an awake marker. It often says which priority
the thread was in from the operating system point of view and which core of a thing run.
And runnable markers only exist on nightly but they say exactly what we run at that time,
which is very convenient to then fail a bug if it's something we should not be running.
One last thing there, task manager. If you hover with a mouse next to the PID, there's
a profiler icon that appears. If you click it, it will profile for five seconds the entire
process. A few seconds later, you will see a tab opening that shows everything happening
in that process. That's all I will say about troubleshooting local excessive power use.
I hope you will make good use of the tools I was just showing. And I will talk about
what's happening in the wild. So that's for all our users. And whenever we care about
what's happening for all users, we think telemetry because that's a great way to know about what's
happening in computers that are not in front of us. I added data collection for a few things
that I will use over the last couple months. Most notably CPU time used, GPU time used,
the number of wake-ups that we caused. And also we can break down this data by process
type. And here by process type, I mean is it the parent process that's showing the Firefox
user interface? Is it a content process that's showing the tab in the foreground? A content
process that's for background tab. On the native channel, we can even break it down
by thread name, which is a lot more detailed. And I will show the use we are making of this
data. So I said we care about sustainability and we have climate commitments. And one obvious
use case for having this kind of data is estimating our carbon footprint. So thanks to the telemetry,
we know that on average every day we use between 60 and 80 million hours of CPU time. And I
mean about 15 million hours of GPU time. Those are big numbers. It's hard to think about
what they mean. But we can try to use those numbers to convert to CO2 equivalent by using
the CPU specifications from CPU manufacturers, information about which CPU model is being
used, and electricity, carbon intensity by country. So we will be publishing our carbon
footprint in a couple months for last year. And it's based on this kind of data. And I
just wanted to give a sense of scale because millions of hours, that means nothing to me.
The amount of power that could be needed to power Firefox for all of our users, which
is hundreds of millions of users, would be equivalent of a small thermal power station.
Or if you're thinking more renewable energy, we would need to cover about the roofs of
50,000 houses with photovoltaic panels. So even if we save just 1% of the power, that
still means a lot compared to other things we could do in our personal lives as engineers.
Another example of using telemetry data is verifying that the fix we landed actually
had the impact we expected. And this is a case where we fixed something related to how
timers were implemented, timers for web pages. And this chart shows how many times we wake
up various threads. So it's from native users. And you see that there's a change happening
here, something trending down. Before, it was about 7% of the wake-ups for the time
of thread. And after, it was about 5%. So we already had an impact with this fix. And
before we collected this kind of telemetry, it would have been impossible to know. And
last but not least, we used this telemetry to verify our ideas about how we can reduce
power use. And when I started working on this project, I had the assumption, and other people
too, that we use a lot of power in background tabs. And that's probably because as someone
who uses Firefox and the internet a lot, I have many background tabs. And we just collected
data. So this is a breakdown per process type. We see that the biggest slice here is the
foreground tab, not background. Second biggest is the GPU, so showing things on screen. Then
we've got the parent process, which is the UI, when the user is interacting or not interacting.
And only then, we have background tabs. So it's between 7% and 8%. Still worth optimizing,
but if we spent all of our efforts optimizing this, we would be missing the biggest part
of the thing, which is foreground tabs. Another idea that we tested is, maybe it's all those
ads that are on web pages. They use a lot of power. We should do something about them.
We also collected data, it turns out to be less than 2% of the total. Maybe it's still
worth doing something about it, but again, it's not where we have the biggest wins. And
maybe it also means that tracking protection works very well in Firefox, and we are already
blocking many things. And the last section of this presentation will be about improvements,
what we have done to reduce power use, and what we can still do. We fixed many bugs.
When I wrote this slide, it was 26 bugs that we fixed, only with the intent of reducing
power use. But if I wrote this slide today, it would be 27, because one was fixed overnight.
The bugs go in various categories. It's almost always the same kind of things that we find.
Sometimes we have timers that really should have been stopped, but keep repeating, but
they are not really useful. It's one of those bugs that we fixed this night, something that
was waking up every 10 seconds, even when you do nothing with Firefox. I'm happy this
bug is finally fixed. Sometimes it's animations that are animating, but they are animating
stuff that's not even on screen. Maybe because it's a background window, background tab,
or something hidden for some other reason. When we can stop those animations, it's much
better. And when I said bogus animation, it's sometimes we have animations that kept running
even though the window was closed. I think we fixed all of those cases, but we might
still find more. And I wrote in pointless thread backups. That's what I was showing
before with a chart about timer threads and HKZs where we have always massive CPUs. Thanks
to all the contributors who helped with this, it's the work of many people mostly on the
platform team. And I will just showcase a few examples of bug fixes we did that had
a big impact. So this one is specifically about Windows 11. Windows 11 has an efficiency
mode for processes. It's not completely clear what it does, but when reading the documentation,
it's mostly letting the operating system know that this process is doing nothing that's
user visible. So we could execute the CPU at the lowest possible frequency. And for
CPUs with efficiency or performance scores, always select efficiency scores. And thanks
to poor profiling that I mentioned before, we could actually verify the impact that we
had when deciding that we set content processes for background tabs in efficiency mode. If
you look at the slides later on, click the link, you can see it in the profile. But on
my computer when I tested it divided by five, the power use of a tab using the CPU in the
background continuously. Another thing I said, we have many bugs that are the same category
of bug. And when we can, it's nice to eliminate the entire category of bugs at once. And for
animation that are broken in HKZs, it's almost impossible to write tests for all the possible
HKZs. But we have a very extensive test suite. So one idea I had was, what if at the end
of every automated test we run, we verify that nothing is animating anymore? Sounds
very easy. We did it. The part that was not easy was fixing all the HKZs we uncovered.
But that's why I'm confident it won't regress as much as it used to. Next things we can
do, because we still have many ideas of how we could do better. I mentioned background
tabs. We still have lots of ideas about how background tabs could be more efficient, how
we could be more aggressive about reducing the frequency of timers for hearing there,
how we could limit CPU use there. I keep talking about timers, but there's a lot we can do
about timers. And there's actually currently one engineer working full time and improving
on timer APIs. The main idea there is to group timers. The most expensive part about timers
is they wake up the CPU. So if when we do wake up the CPU, we decide to run many timers
at once, it would be much cheaper in terms of power. And we are working on those kind
of improvements. We still have cases where we have videos that are being decoded, but
not played in a place where they are visible for users, like background tabs and things
like that. We try to stop those, but there are cases that we are still working on. Hidden
animations. So animations that keep running when something has been completely closed,
I'm confident we fixed most of those. Animations that keep running even though they are covered
by something else. We still have many cases. And the biggest one is fully occluded window,
which is you have a window that's entirely above a browser window where we have animation.
We try to detect that we have got to detect it at least on Mac and on Windows. It's not
working as well as it should be. And I think we can do much better. So there's probably
there will probably be we're going in that direction. And another thing that I like to
do is to test the profile. Also because testing the capabilities of a profiler is what happens
if Firefox is started and there's nothing. You open Firefox, you load about blank, literally
nothing. And then you go to a meeting or go for a walk or do something else. And then
you come back a few hours later, you capture the profile and you see what happens. I would
like what happened to be almost nothing. It's currently still more than I would like. And
we can still improve things there. And I think it would typically help for sustainability
there for people who are not using laptops that tend to go into sleep mode, but more desktop
computers that might turn on things on their computer. And then they go home for the night
or for the weekend and the computer keeps running the entire weekend. I think it might
have an impact for those cases. And some more ideas that are not ready to do something about
for everybody, but that could be experimented with. Experiments you could run individually
like if you want to test it for yourself. Or experiments we could run on a few thousand
users to see what's the impact. So the preferences there that I'm giving is when showing the
chart, I said that displaying the foreground tab is what's using almost half of the entire
program that we use for Firefox. By default, we display stuff, especially animation 60
times per second or more if you have a screen with a first stop refresh rate. Do you really
need that? I think most people don't. And we have a pref to limit the refresh rate.
So if you want to have only half the frames, just set it to 30 and you will see what happens.
I think for most use cases, except maybe first video games, it should be fine. Another thing
we'd like to explore is the cost of video autoplay. We already block videos that could
make sound because it's noisy and that's annoying. But videos that are just there in a corner,
typically news articles with someone waving hands and talking, but you can't hear them
because you're reading the article and you don't care. They use a lot of power. We could
probably stop that. And there's a price that you can set that will block both on the audio
and there's video. Even if there's just video, it will block it. And that's all I wanted
to share for today. And I'm happy to take questions if you have, but first, thanks for
your attention.
So who has any questions? In the case that you have a lot of background
apps, does Firefox suspend those processes? And if so, does the memory gets freed and
does with the process manager show that or not? Sorry, a lot of question.
So the question is, if you have lots of background tabs, is Firefox suspending those processes?
Is the memory getting freed? There are multiple answers to that question because there are
different cases. By default, the answer is mostly no, we don't suspend them. One thing
we do is we throttle any activity there. So if a tab is trying to do things every 10 milliseconds,
we will not allow that. And we will limit to once per second, which saves a lot of power
already. I think we can do better. I would like if it was only once per minute and then
maybe after a few minutes or a few hours, suspend completely. There are cases where
the tabs are completely unloaded. One of the cases when we are using way too much memory
and we are about to crash out of memory, then we will, as a priority, unload the tab that's
abusing the memory. There's another case, which is when you session restore, we don't
reload the tab until you click them, except for the foreground tabs. So then you will
have many tabs, but they don't actually use memory or power. And one more case is Firefox
on Android. By the way, everything I said in this slide show was about Firefox desktop,
but we are also looking at the power use of Firefox on Android. And on Android, when you
put a tab in the background, it's completely suspended. Nothing runs anymore.
Any other question? Okay. Can you just say it? So, okay.
So I just tried to see what my Firefox is doing about processes that I just learned about.
And the first line is the Firefox main process itself, which is my use of between 20 and
50% of CPU. So that's not any of that. So do you have any idea what that is doing?
So the question is, I just learned about about processes and quickly wanted to see what my
Firefox was doing. And the process that's using the most CPU there is the parent process,
which is using about 20% of the core. Do we have any idea of what it is doing? So the
way I would figure this out is to click the profile icon and look at the profile. And
if you want to send me that profile, I can tell you exactly. But otherwise I will just
say a quick guess, which is what happens most of the time, is unless you are running on
Windows, but I guess you're probably on Linux or something else, we run... So I said GPU
process is a large part. We actually only have a GPU process on Windows to prevent graphics
driver from crashing from crashing into your browser. So the graphics part happens on the
parent process outside of Windows. And it's very likely that you have animations that
are running and causing things to be displayed. And with a profile I could tell you which
animations are running and why.
We have questions here in the matrix room. Have somebody ever compared worldwide power
usage of Firefox versus other proprietary browser webs?
I missed a few ones. So worldwide power of Firefox compared to other browsers? Have we
ever compared? I would say no, because I think the other browsers don't publish worldwide
power use. And I'm hoping we'll be publishing this as part of our greenhouse gas footprint
report. I don't think computing browsers publish any of that. And we were actually thinking
that if we start publishing that maybe we will push the competition to also publish
this kind of information.
Great. Any other?
So this is kind of an extension to the configuration options that you showed. But are there other
tweakables that we could apply to Firefox on mobile devices? Like by and from Librem
and so on where we definitely don't need 60 frames a second.
I'm not sure I understand entirely, but I think you were asking other things that we
could do on mobile to reduce power usage?
Yes, but it is a mobile platform running on it. So it's the desktop version of Firefox.
So you have a mobile device running the desktop version of Firefox. And you are wondering if
there are things you could do to reduce power usage.
If you are showing anyone try to eliminate entirely background apps and try to suspend
them. Otherwise, the answer is almost always the same. Capture a profile, see what's in
there. Because whenever we try to optimize by just guessing, almost all the time we are
like I said, background apps, it's not that bad. And it's not that bad. And profiling is
always the way to know exactly where you should be spending your time when you want to optimize.
And if you want help with profiling, the next talk will be about the profiler. And we are
very happy to help about understanding profiles.
Hi. My question is regarding hardware encoding. For example, in HTML and depending on the
user, you can give a list of different content types or formats. Has there been any exploration
into changing maybe the preferred format loaded to optimize for less power consumption as
opposed to faster or higher resolution?
So what I understood of the question is, has there been any exploration to changing the
kind of content types we accept, for example, for images or media, to reduce power use?
I think the answer is no. But I know there's currently exploration in terms of what we
can do to reduce bandwidth use. And bandwidth also uses power in some ways. And we were
thinking about this mostly in the case of estimating the cost of VPNs for users. And
for users who really care about privacy and really want privacy on a VPN, could we do
things to reduce the cost for them to pay for that VPN that charges for bandwidth?
So I'm afraid that all the time we have, however, if you can see Florian put his email there
for questions and also share it in the matrix room. And we also have that matrix room. Please
also add questions there. And there will be member stuff there and also other volunteer
resilient ones. Thank you very much. We need to change up for the next. Thank you very
much, Florian.
Sure.