So now we have two presenters, Benjamin DeKosny and Morgan Reschenberger.
So Benjamin is a member of the Modilla Performance Engineering team and Morgan is a senior software
engineer working on platform accessibility and Morgan if you want to repeat your name
probably the right pronunciation. No you got it, Morgan Reschenberger that's me.
Yeah we're going to talk to you about an accessibility project called
Cache the World and the way that we're monitoring and measuring performance.
So I'm Benjamin, I am on the performance team and I'm going to be talking about
the collaboration from the performance side. And I'm Morgan, I'm on the accessibility team.
I'm going to talk about the accessibility side. We put the matrix rooms for both of our teams here
so if you have topic related questions after this you can follow up there.
So here's the agenda, we're going to just talk a little bit about accessibility in
Firefox. Morgan's going to go through intro to the rendering and accessibility architecture
and some of the changes that happened with Cache the World. I'm going to talk a little bit about
how we're measuring performance and some of those questions and current problems. We're going to go
through our future work plans and then we're going to open it up for questions.
So the first thing is scoping context for accessibility in Firefox. The goal is of
course a faster accessibility engine and more performant web use for users, all users and
especially users using accessible technologies. We also want to try to create a performance
testing infrastructure that will be able to prove these things and test the more we change
our internal infrastructures, we want to be able to make sure that we can catch problems.
We also wanted to establish some accessibility metrics and we want to work in public with
public dashboards that show the kind of performance that we're getting. We want to
improve our documentation, we want to improve the debug experience and as such we're going to talk
a little bit later about the profile markers that Nazeem talked about earlier but specifically the
accessibility ones and we want to set up an infrastructure for collaboration.
So scope on this is we're going to be talking about screen readers pretty much only and we're
not going to be talking about any of these other accessibility technologies like screen
magnification, contrast modes, on-screen keyboards, subtitles, any of that, that's all
deferred until later in this work. So context for Firefox and accessible technologies is not great
from the free software perspective, like almost all our users are on Windows and then you have
a very small sliver of Mac and Linux and Linux is like under a percent. We just have to know where
we are and that's where we are. In general 5.5% of all Firefox page loads for the month of January
were had some accessible technology built in and that's not evenly distributed across the OSes. We
see a much higher use on Windows and you know Linux isn't bad, Orca, yay! And then Mac is
far below that but for the most part if we were talking about who is touching this work and who
do we have to care about, it's these Windows users. And then here just for a little bit more context
about in that 5.5% of page loads that use accessible technologies like what accessible
technologies are they using? They're using mostly screen magnifiers which is the black line and then
the purple line is speech rec in general and then underneath that is NVDA which is the Windows
screen reader. So those are like the top three that we really have to care about.
More again. Before we get into all the details about the performance work, I want to give you
some background on how rendering works in web browsers and how it translates to
the accessibility architecture that we're going to be talking about today.
The general job of a web browser is to convert HTML and CSS written by web authors into visual
navigable content. We do this through a rendering engine in Firefox called Gecko. It has five
different phases and stages that produce artifacts that are used in the following phases and stages.
So first we parse the HTML document. This creates the DOM or document object model which is a
hierarchical view of the web page. Then we look at the CSS and figure out the style information for
each node, what visual changes we need to make when we render. Then we do layout which computes
positional and size information for each of these nodes. It also constructs an artifact with that
information called the frame tree which becomes useful later. Then we do painting and compositing
and rendering which is the visual part of rendering. But this process is all extremely visual, right?
What if you do not navigate the web visually? What if you navigate it with technology like a screen
reader which turns visual content into audio? What do you do then? How does a screen reader figure
out what it should be telling you? That's the job of the accessibility engine. Like we have a
rendering engine, we also have an accessibility engine in Firefox. It doesn't have a fun name.
So if you can come up with a fun name, you should let me know on matrix. What it does is it takes
in those artifacts we talked about before, the DOM, the frame tree, style structs, et cetera,
and it marshals them into a new kind of tree which we call the accessibility tree or I like to call
it the accessibility tree because that's more fun. But it takes all of those and computes
excessively relevant information. So this is stuff like semantic, role, name, the kinds of actions you
can perform on an element, things like that. This is not necessarily one-to-one. There's not a single
accessible for every node in the DOM tree or a single accessible for every frame in the frame
tree. We care about different things which is why we have to build a new structure. And building
the structure happens in the content process. We have one accessibility tree per web page.
So let's take a look at how these queries happen from an assistive technology standpoint. So at
the bottom here, I've got a couple different kinds of assistive technologies. These are ones that
Benjamin mentioned on that graph from before. So we have screen readers, voice control, window managers,
et cetera. These clients or ATs make requests to Firefox for web content information. So if you are
navigating with a screen reader, the screen reader needs to ask what node is focused and what should
I say about it to the end user? The way that those requests happen are through platform-specific APIs,
but they all hit the parent process in Firefox. The assistive technologies are separate applications.
So they are communicating with Firefox through the parent process. Each web page lives in one or more
other processes, one or more content processes, and is not reachable by the assistive technology
directly. So we can't inject the screen reader into web content for a lot of reasons, security
being one of them. All these calls go through the parent process. And there are some problems with
this architecture that motivate what we're going to talk about next. So let's get into it.
Like I said, computation of the relevant properties that the assistive technologies are requesting,
that all happens using the accessibility tree in the content process. The result gets sent to the
parent process from content via IPC, interprocess communication. This is slow and it's also
synchronous. So if a call gets blocked or is taking a really long time in content,
you can't do anything. The parent process just hangs. And because the parent process includes
all of the browser UI as well, it just looks like Firefox is not responding, which isn't great.
So what can we do about that? Well, our solution is this project we call Cache the World,
which introduces a cache in the parent process that keeps track of snippets of content information
that we need to compute and respond to those API calls. So we're trying to offload as much work as
we can from content into parent. And this cache gets updated asynchronously based on content
mutations. So we no longer have this problem of synchronous blocking IPC.
Cool. So now I'm back and I'm going to talk a little bit about, like, how do we see if this
stuff's working? So the first thing we did is actually not at all metric or measurement-based,
but it was more about helping debug in the profiler. So one of my great colleagues, Michael
Kamala, added some accessibility markers in the profiler to kind of, like, get us an idea of,
like, what's going on where? You can see the specific calls here. And then I'm going to show
you what it looks like kind of in the profiler. So the red circle is where we start to drop in to
some of the accessibility calls. So watch this space, because we're going to be adding more
markers here. The second thing we had to do is really come up with, like, how do we test
accessibility? And what's going on here? There's a huge amount of screen reader. There's just, like,
a whole bunch of different screen readers. And they're all different. And each OS has a different
strategy for dealing with this. So we have, like, a huge complex testing matrix here. In addition,
we had to, like, in terms of testing, we had to, like, run a large number of variations to kind of
verify our results. We have five different variations starting with the baseline. And then
we kind of, like, have caches on and off with the accessibility implicitly on by just plugging in
screen reader. And also with accessibility forced on with preferences. So we have a really large
matrix of five on our tasks here. And then we were looking for specific problematic web content
that would really trigger kind of the worst case scenarios here. And they are, in general,
the worst case web content for this are really large static web pages. So what did we do? We added
three specific sites. Actually, I think we have, like, five sites. But in general, it's, like,
Wikipedia World War II is a great test page for testing accessibility. We have some
search box links because we're Firefox engineers. And then what WG HTML specs. So these kind of,
like, really large static pages, which is not necessarily how a lot of the web is built right
now. But these are, like, specific problem points that we wanted to be aware of and address.
And then comes a question of, like, well, what are we measuring? What's important? And we have,
like, three general choices here. We have, like, W3C, navigation timing, kind of page load metrics,
like, OG performance metrics, that segment browser page load into distinct phases,
H
flows and time and measure. And that's really showing the most promise, frankly, and what we're
going to be using more of in the future. Whoops. And so what we're trying to work in public,
and we have some public dashboards for this work, which are at the end here. Whoops. Sorry.
So this is, like, some preliminary results. This graph's a little hard to understand,
and I'm sorry about that. We have the blue baseline performance. We have these dotted lines with the
caches turned off. And then we have with the caches turned on. And so we're seeing, like,
eh, not great performance for these static web pages right now, at least on Linux. I think
that actually varies on Windows. But we're seeing some wins and some more, even performance on
things like IMD web pages, which aren't, like, these pathological test cases. So in general,
what we're going to be doing is we're going to be trying to align the profile markers that were put
in to performance metrics using our internal tools at first. And we're just going to try to
start measuring, like, the actual cache creation time. And we also want to start paying attention
to not just straight, class-seq page load, but we want to start thinking about page reload,
tab switching, and one of the other leads on this project, Jamie T., has a great blog post about
those kind of, like, anecdotal performance measurements. We definitely want accessibility
first metrics, and we would like to get away from generic page load type metrics on this.
We have a public dashboard, work in progress. It will continue to evolve as this work evolves.
And then really quickly, future work. Yeah, so the accessibility team at Mozilla is responsible
for a lot more than just the accessibility engine. We're also responsible for high contrast mode,
Zoom, Firefox front end, usability and accessibility. So we've got a lot of projects apart from this
that we're working on, but our main goal for this half is to ship Cache the World to release. We're
currently in beta, and we have a lot of promising results. So we're really optimistic about getting
this to all of our users. We're also planning on working on optimizations based on the performance
work that you're seeing here. We have a couple of optimizations in mind. Like, we know we can
improve on cache granularity, but this work will inform the kind of work that we're doing next.
And then performance team is going to really try to get these Windows results in since we know it's
so important. At the same time, we want to make sure that Linux performance doesn't degrade. Also,
we would like to kind of, like, put this into standard continuous integration tests infrastructure,
kind of tune our markers, make sure we're measuring what we think we're measuring, and then things
that we deem successful in a wide variety of web content. We want to try to push out to public
telemetry so that we can actually measure much larger environments and users. And then, of course,
all the internal collaborations inside of Mozilla with PerfTools and ETL and DevOps to try and make
all the magic happen. We have some questions. If we have time for questions, we have time for
questions. We have time for questions. Fantastic. And if you have other thoughts, you can email us.
Or, you know, Twitter. And I'm on MasterCard. I'm not. Are there any questions? All right.
So complete. Yeah. We actually, on the slide deck, but not in our presentation, we did have,
we have some additional resources and notes for people who are trying to work with accessibility,
maybe new to it, and things that, here's some resources for you to use. Again, Jamie's blog post,
really, I'm going to really hype that again. Please read it. Morgan is going to put a video up. That
has to be redone because there is some internal stuff that can't be shown. But there's a great,
she has a great walkthrough about how to debug CSS for accessibility. And then I have a web page on
color and contrast for accessibility and how you can compute colors at work for a wide variety of
people. And also I want to shamelessly plug that you can contribute to Firefox. Oh, yeah. And if
you are interested in working on platform specific bugs or front end bugs or whatever,
accessibility is a great place to get involved because we span a lot of components and we could
always use your help. So if you are interested, we have an accessibility room on matrix at the
Mozilla domain. And you should reach out. And we're there. So. Thin. Yeah. Oh, great. We'll take a
question. Hi. So you mentioned it's not safe to embed the screen reader directly into the web
page because of security concerns. But now with caching, you're providing a little bit more
information to this parent process. Are there any security considerations you have to look at or
address doing this work? We're paying attention to the kind of information that we're caching. We,
of course, don't want to give any private user information away. Largely the information we're
caching is already represented in the parent process in some form. But the way that we compute
things is different than how DOM or layout or other parts of the browser compute them. We're
caching really, really granular information as well. So, yeah. We're not currently concerned
about security risk. But that is a consideration. Oh, cool. Yeah, that's what that website is. Oh,
sorry. Do we have tests with accessibility? Are we performance testing for accessibility? Yes,
we're starting to do that. And. Yeah. So we're. Okay. So the question is like how, like what's,
what's the method there? And you can contact me offline if we, if we're running close. But we're
using a standard framework for performance testing called browser time, which is open source. And,
yes, what we're doing is we have OS specific handlers that basically start screen readers
before we start running that and then stop it when we're done. So it's just RAI, straight style on
that. Yeah. And then pointing that to Windows too. One of the difficulties with that approach that
we're running into is that we are most interested in perceived performance. So we want to know how
does the user feel about this? Like is it perceivably faster? And that's really hard to do because
screen readers are difficult to automate from that perspective. Speech rate is extremely variable.
Right. You can, you know, do key presses and stuff, but it's really hard to get the kinds of
measurements we want. So we're aware that the performance testing we're doing right now is
a number and it's something that we can track consistently, but it isn't entirely what we would
like to be. And there's different strategies on the Windows screen readers about like having to
have the full page ready before we actually start, start in with the speech. And that's not, that's
like configurable and that's not the default setting for, on Linux for instance. So Orca, I think,
is actually pretty smart about this. And they, they can do partial, partial reads and start the
speech earlier. So, so we're not getting quite sure. Note that the caching of the parent moves
information into a process that is not exposed to web content. There's nothing before that.
It's not appearing here. Maybe. Yes. Yeah. Oh, can you talk about how the cache is populated
and invalidated? Oh, sure. How much time do we have? So the cache is populated from content. So
it's a push based cache. We aren't invalidating from parent because we can't observe content
mutations from parent effectively. Each content process is responsible for monitoring their own
mutations and pushing or invalidating stuff in the parent process as needed. We have an initial
cache push that, oh no, sorry. On, on page load we collect a bunch of information and push it
always. So there isn't any sort of mutation that we're responding to there. That is one of our big
performance concerns is the initial cache push varies by page size or scales by page size. And
that's really costly. But that's why you put all those big tests. Yeah. Yeah. But from, from
initial cache push onward, we're responding to mutations in content from content. Are there any
other questions? Yeah, go into the limit. On the web app side, what may impact negatively the
performance of the accessibility? Like how could you design web content such that it's, it's optimal
for accessibility? That's a great question. And we'll come back at you later with an answer. Yeah,
we're still, we're still like kind of early in phase on this, but I feel it would be a great idea
to do some kind of like web content help to get people to know like the performance choices are
making for accessibility. Oh yeah. Performa, could we come up with some guidelines for
performance linting and general guidelines for how to do perform an accessibility request submitted.
Thank you. So thank you very much. We are done.