So hello everyone and thank you very much for resisting this late in the evening.
And we have our last talk and we have Emil Liharo.
And you welcome Odyssejia on the localization system and tool chain management and he's
going to have a talk on the road to Int message format.
So the last talk by Matiasz if you were here was a lot about where we are now, what we
can provide now already in pontoon and otherwise, how localization is now happening at Mozilla.
What I'm going to be talking to you about is what's kind of coming up, what are some
of the next things in localization that we're working on and that we think are really quite
important.
And so yeah, I'm on the same thing with Matiasz and my staff, software engineer, but I've
been doing this sort of stuff kind of for fun, for ages it feels like now.
So turns out that when you get really into localization in JavaScript in particular,
there aren't too many other people who are that into it and then somehow you might end
up hired by Mozilla to do the things you were doing for fun, for pay.
So that's kind of nice.
Hint, hint, you know, it's a good company.
In addition to working just on code at Mozilla, I spent a lot of time in a bunch of different
standards bodies working on the standards for localization in particular.
And some of the work I'm presenting here is really the work that's going elsewhere than
just at Mozilla because we want to have, we fundamentally want to make the world a better
place, the internet a better place for everyone, not just Firefox users, but everyone's internet
is better if they use Firefox.
But you're here so you might have heard this one before.
On localization, this is again covering a bit of what Matias was saying, that quite
often localization is one of those aspects of how do you really build an application
or a site or anything that comes up way too late.
You end up making some choices early on and then you end up needing to live with those
choices later.
And they might not be the best stuff, best ones.
And the need for localization comes after you've made the choices or you discover that,
hey, this thing, oh, good grief, we need to support Arabic now.
That will be interesting.
And a lot of the sort of scope of localization is interesting because there isn't necessarily
one right answer.
So of course we're working on a new right answer and, you know, there's an XKCD comic
on that.
I don't have it on these slides.
Don't worry.
I'm not sure what I'm talking about.
So things could definitely be better.
So we're trying to make some of this improvement happen.
It should be easier to localize content.
And there should be a common way of doing this so that the experience and the benefits
that you get from using software and libraries in one place can map to elsewhere.
Right now there's a lot of differences in how localization ends up depending on the formats
you use and the tool chains you use and all of this.
And that is not optimal.
And fundamentally a lot of actually when you start getting deep into it, UI and UX design
ends up being limited to some extent by the fact that most of localization work is working
around strings rather than the complex structures like HTML allows us to represent and other
aspects that make life more complicated.
So we want to improve all of that.
So let's start with this.
This is nominally something simple.
Basically most of you can read HTML to figure out that here we have this small little span
that says that Brussels is the capital of Belgium.
I've lived here.
I know it's more complicated than that.
Let's just go on.
And Brussels here happens to be a link.
So how do we make this localizable?
How do we actually localize this in a way that works really in the end for everyone?
And one way that we're trying to sort of build towards is something a little bit like this
that you could add an identifier to the element there where you say that this is the Brussels
message that we're really dealing with and include in the HTML something like what we
have for CSS now where you say that here's this resource that's attached.
Here's a link to a resource that's necessary for figuring out what's really the content
of this page.
And then separately you have a message here in Finnish because I can and I could not pick
between French and Flemish because it gets complicated.
I've lived here.
I know.
Brussels is a very simple language.
And here the format that we're using, I'm going to get to that later, but there's a
couple of interesting things here.
In particular the fact that we're marking up the Brussels text there as the contents
of the text of a link so that we'll be able to map that to the link, the Ahref that we
have in the source document there in English.
And because it's, you know, of course a little bit more complicated than this, it happens
to be a link to Wikipedia.
So in this particular case, but not usually at all, we could allow the translator to say
that hang on, this link in Finnish should really go to the Finnish Wikipedia page on
Brussels rather than the English one.
And this is like, I can present to you, you can see the screen, you can kind of get what
you're looking at here, but honestly getting this to a state where you can get a translator
who's not a developer to see this and understand what they're supposed to do and not screw
it up and provide useful things, useful content in all the languages, well, the languages
that this translator is working on, it gets kind of hard.
So we're trying to, you know, make that a thing.
And the rest of this presentation is really going to answer these three questions that
I kind of would have hoped some of you would be asking, but you're not.
They're really questions in my head I wish you would be asking, you might have as well.
But these are the questions of the theoretical guy in my head might be asking, what's the
format of this thing that we just saw?
And is this really going to work like everywhere?
And how's this going to make my life better now?
Or do I need to start using this whole new thing?
And that's going to be a pain.
So I don't want to do that.
To tackle the first one, the answer ultimately to all of that is to standardize everything.
And the first thing we're going to talk about standardizing is the message there itself.
And one particular thing that some of you might have noticed is that it had curly braces
around the text there, around the Bruce cell on the back up.
And this is because it turns out that when you're building a message formatting language
like this, oh, good grief, all the corner cases.
Oh, good grief, is it like hard, like proper hard because you're trying to write a formatting
language that developers understand and then get the developers to write content in that
language that translators understand without needing to have the developers necessarily
understand how translators think.
So you need to find an intermediate language for the communication to happen that explicitly
limits and forces the communication to work in a way that works.
And this is one of the reasons why some parts of this work have been in the active standards
but for like three years so far.
But one reason for those curly braces there is that quite often messages get complicated
because you need to vary different parts of them depending on different variables.
In English, for instance, it matters, is it a he or a she or a they who might have done
the action here of sent an invite to a party.
So we need to have a language message format two which I'm presenting to you here to enable
this sort of a communication.
And of course it gets more complicated than this.
Because you can have stuff like here we have a need to include something more in the message
of the relative time, like say three days ago that's included here.
So the language needs to allow for internal variables for this message to be definable
in a way that translators can kind of see what's going on and hopefully not touch it
too much because hopefully they don't need to do that but still be able to do so if they
really really need to.
So this is about the space of what's possible in most current, no, in some of the current
message formatting languages, at least Project Fluent which we maintain and work with and
maybe one or two of those.
But when it gets really more complicated than that, this gets on the edges of not really
even supported anywhere.
When you have here what we have are multiple different variables being defined and then
the matching on which of these messages really the message we're building, it depends on
how many people as well as the agenda of the host.
So this isn't even a full listing of the whole set of possible when cases that could be selected
here.
But this is all possible.
It quite often happens when you really want to formulate UX experience that is approaching
natural language.
And this is again referring to what I mentioned earlier.
A lot of this stuff just isn't, is the choices that people are making now regarding message
formatting, how do they formulate it, are driven by the limitations of the technologies
that we have available for us.
So UX itself is being driven in certain directions because message formatting is hard.
You don't end up really having messages like this in your UI if you care about localization
because whoever is filtering your messages before they go to the translators, the localizers,
is going to tell you, yeah, no, you can't do that.
They're not going to ever be able to work with it.
So please fix.
And then you end up even maybe building the UI differently in order to accommodate these
needs.
With message format two, which this is, I kind of hope we can get beyond that.
Have the possibility and the options of having even richer content in everything that we're
working with.
But the second question there was about is this really going to work everywhere?
And yes.
And we're doing that by trying to make much of the work happen at the lowest possible
appropriate level for the work.
So a lot of this is happening in the Unicode Consortium, and then we've got work going
on in TC39 for JavaScript.
It's being added to the ICU libraries provided by Unicode as well.
And eventually we're hoping to get probably in What We G, discussions ongoing about the
structure of the HTML stuff that I was showing you earlier, because that doesn't exist either
yet.
And one particular part of this, my background is as a JavaScript developer, is that this
is the first time we're really adding something to the JavaScript language itself at the level
of JSON.parse where you have this string representation of a thing that's not JavaScript and you get
an object or a thing out of it.
I think that's really cool.
But we're still working on that.
And the part here that makes this extra interesting is that we're not just talking about a new
syntax.
But effectively through the work we've been doing, it's looking an awful lot like everything
in every single message formatting language that currently exists and is in use somewhere
that is, you know, that we can know about that is not like closed and proprietary is
supported in the data model that we end up with for message format 2.
So for example, to answer the earlier talks, questions about how do you get support for
something like Fluent into software like Translate Toolkit, one quite probable answer for the
general case of this is that what you'll be able to do is take messages that you have
in.properties files, Fluent, get text, xlyph, pretty much anything, and parse that into
a defined data model structure for message format 2, then be able to work with that using
tools, runtime, whatever, and possibly from there get it out in a different format altogether
that's then supported by other tooling.
So it's a lot of this work is trying to figure out that, hang on, messages aren't really
all that complicated as data structures in the end.
However, we can at least express the level of that complexity.
So we should enable.
Hello again.
So yeah.
Think I was about done with this slide.
Going on.
One key part here is that all of this is already real.
So what I showed you in HTML is not exactly what we use internally at Mozilla, but it's
effectively the same as how Firefox is now already translated.
We have by now literal years of experience of working with tooling like this and seeing
how it empowers UI UX development of a relatively complicated piece of software like Firefox
to improve itself and to enable easier and better communication between developers and
translators.
And so we're bringing a lot of that knowledge and experience into what we're doing in the
Unicode Consortium when designing message format two, which is yes, taking inspiration,
but also learnings from Fluent and many other systems that make it honestly a better, better
than Fluent currently is, for instance, which is why we're not pitching that as the really
cool sexy thing.
Even though, I mean, if you're interested, there is the currently coolest thing around
that's real.
This is still in progress.
So you could be interested in that.
As I mentioned, the syntax itself for messages is getting defined under the Unicode Common
Language Data Repository Technical Committee.
There's a working, it gets complicated in these things.
And there's an implementation available in ICU 72 for Java.
And the JavaScript proposals, there's two of them at stage one currently for this, are
progressing in TC39, which is the body that defines JavaScript effectively.
And there's a polyfill package for JavaScript if you want to start playing around with what
message format two looks like and how you can work with it.
But yeah, all of this is, of course, completely public.
All of the repositories, all of the work standards are being developed completely in the open.
And I mean, honestly, localization is one of those weird places where we don't need
to filter anyone on credentials for anything.
Because in terms of who wants to actually participate in the standards actions and standards
work, it's enough that you show up and you show some level of interest and we'll let
you in in all the inside clubs because there aren't any.
It's a community where really you can, if you're interested, you should not be afraid
of someone saying, no, you don't belong here because you do.
We need always more people participating.
Yeah, there's links to me as well.
And also this talk is available at the URL there at the bottom.
It's also attached to the talk on Pentabarth.
But yeah, that was me.
Are there any questions?
Give me the mic and I'll repeat the question.
The question is, was what really makes message format two better than fluent?
And one particular example is when you get to complicated stuff like this, is having
the effectively enforcing the data structure that you end up getting from this to be one
that contains full messages that you end up representing to translators.
Other than this, it gets into really nitty gritty details.
The other big benefit of message format two over fluent is that message format two is
becoming a Unicode standard rather than effectively a project built entirely from within Mozilla.
I see you use some kind of typing in those iterations.
Are those standard as well?
So the question here is about seeing the sort of typing that you see, the colon number and
the colon relative time and actually the colon gender is the same sort of thing here.
What are those and are these custom or centrally defined?
And the answer is kind of yes and no.
And it's complicated.
Because what you're looking at here are effectively functions that act a little bit like types,
but they're not exactly like types.
They're declaring, for example, that the count that we're getting, let's handle it as a number,
but also let's in the value of it that we end up assigning to count other use an offset
of one.
So it's an operation happening on the input argument count.
And on the third line in the match for the host's gender, we could imagine host being
some complicated object that's defining a whole person and we're picking the gender
information from that more complex thing.
But yes, in many cases they work kind of like types.
And these are the capital number, capital date time and capital platform functions that
can be used in this sort of way as well.
Just be loud.
I'll repeat your question.
So in the beginning you kind of talked about how translating is supposed to be no text,
but it's more structured and you showed the example with the anchors.
And then it sort of escalates to what's actually in this locale, this whole structure of the
page doesn't make any sort of sense anymore.
So we have to kind of like switch things around a lot based on the locale.
And I'm wondering if you have any thoughts on like what's out of scope here perhaps and
if there are any other tools in development that you know of that kind of like are supposed
to encompass not just message forwarding on small sentences or whatever but also just
restructuring pages based on different locales.
So if I've understood the question is what happens when you have a complicated thing
like a whole page that you're translating and in comparing the source locale and the
target locale, the target locale ends up having very different structure that might go much
deeper I suppose than just a simple link that I'm showing in this example of how does this
really work.
The answer is it's complicated and it depends on your use case.
This work in particular is trying to build tools that could enable that sort of representation
within message format 2 so you could end up somewhere really complicated but you probably
don't want to.
You're probably in that sort of a situation needing to build more tools that are more
specific to the use case that you have.
When you have, when you need to reformat a whole page in order to work with a specific
locale it's, there is no universal answer to this.
This is the closest thing but I don't know where it's really going to go.
We have a question in the live stream.
Translators often are not programmers.
They already struggle with translating strings with HTML tags and other technical terms.
The message format curly braces syntax might be difficult to understand and error prone.
So here we're talking about something, let's take this example of if you put this in front
of a translator.
Yeah, you don't.
This is not really what we want to do.
What we want to do is create a format that enables a, like HTML, a representation of
something like a message in a way that is relatively readable but is not necessarily
easy to edit and modify for someone who doesn't exactly know what they're dealing with.
A little bit like what happens if you take JSON and put it into a Word document and then
you start editing it and then you have to figure out that, oh, there's a curly quote
somewhere that ended up screwing that.
This sort of thing can happen entirely well when you end up dealing with complicated messages
like this.
So the answer here is that you end up using tooling that gets this to not be presented
as one thing to a translator but three, yeah, in this case, three or more different messages
where you end up asking a translator wants to translate name, invited you to her party
on relative date.
And then second to ask them to translate name invited you to his party on relative date.
And in Finnish, allow a translator because Finnish doesn't, he and she translated the
same word.
So in Finnish, the equivalent of this message would end up being effectively just the third
case without the whole matching because the structure of the language works differently.
So you do end up, when working with messages of this level of complexity, effectively needed
to rely on tooling.
But the wonderful thing about message format two is that we can transform this representation
of this message into any other representation of this message that's hopefully going to
work with whatever tooling is then available for the actual translation work to happen
in.
So, X-Lift two, for instance, or other targets that are commonly supported by software used
for translation, or some really simple representation that can be mapped then back to this, but
still allows a translator to just see a simpler thing at once rather than a really complicated
thing.
I think there's more questions, but are we out of time?
Two minutes.
Guy in front, yellow.
Okay, so my question is, I can guess that you're targeting the new message format as
a successor of all previous attempts at message format.
Technically, it is relatively easy to make sure that everything representable in previous
message format is representable in the new one.
How are you solving the problem that you are really encompassing all the different languages
in the world?
Because like all the examples we saw were in English, perhaps some of the others might
be like French or another European language.
The case in here is just for female or male.
So, in the same language, it's much more complicated than the noun system.
In some languages, you might be writing a single message in several writing systems.
So, how do you make sure that the new message format encompasses all these different strange
cases for localization?
If I understand the question right, you're asking how do you make sure that this isn't
really what seems to work for English in a couple of languages around English, but hopefully
all the languages?
Or a sizable number of languages.
The short answer here is that with Fluent, we're already doing exactly this using
representation of messages that is very close to this.
So, for instance, at Mozilla, from this experience, we can say that the simpler than this structure
that we have for Fluent ends up working in all of the languages that we need to deal
with through Fluent, which is about 100 for Firefox, 200 overall for all of the different
projects that we are currently translating.
Currently from this, the work being done for message format 2 is by no means done really
from an English language point of view.
After main contributors currently working on the specification, my background is Finnish.
There's a Polish guy, then there's a Romanian, then there's a Sri Lankan.
And there's a couple of others who are on the periphery of this who are from a much
wider variety of backgrounds than this.
So, we are bringing and ensuring that these sorts of considerations are actively being
remembered to be taken care of.
So, to some extent, we are relying on the expertise that we have.
To some extent, we are relying on the experience we have with working with similar formats
than what we're presenting here.
But also, we're trying to build a core specification for message formatting that is sufficiently
small but modular and powerful to then enable the support later on that is required by human
languages.
We're trying to limit to just being able to support human languages, but it might go a
little bit beyond that, too.
I think we're out of time.
I'm very happy to have people come and ask me questions after.
Thank you.