So we are at our penultimate talk for this dev room and we have Mathias Horvat, which
I hope I pronounced it right, with the staff software engineer on the Mozilla localization
team and is going to talk about how you can localise your open source project with pontoon.
Thank you. Hello everyone. First of all I would like to thank you all for coming all
the way to Brussels to listen to me. I really appreciate it. I hope you are having a good
day today and you are going to be having a good day tomorrow. As Francesca said I am
an engineer with Mozilla for some time now and today I wanted to talk to you about localization,
specifically how we do localization at Mozilla and hopefully how it can benefit you as well,
be it within Mozilla or some Mozilla related project or not. But first things first, I
have to mention something very important. This is Intish, she is my oldest daughter
and she just turned seven today and her dad is at some conference with geeks spending
time away from her. But can somebody take a picture? I actually brought her to Brussels
so she is here. So we spent like an hour today together and by the time I get back home she
is going to go to bed. No I am kidding. But I actually wanted to make this talk shorter
because I want to spend more time with her so sorry about that. It is going to be a pretty
short talk and then if you are going to have any questions, Emily, you will answer them.
Is that fine? Thank you. Emily is my colleague over there who is going to do the last talk
today. So big round of applause for Emily for being the last to speak today. She really
appreciates that. Okay, back to localization and to some serious business. This is actual
data. There is just 13% of Firefox users that are based in the US. That is maybe not very
surprising. What could be a little bit more surprising is that 60% of all Firefox users
use non-default locale which is ENUS, American English. In case it is not obvious, what I
am trying to say is that localization matters. It is actually very important. We all, me
included, often think of localization as an obstacle or something that we are going to
do later or we are going to do it one day. But it actually really matters because apparently
it keeps the door shut if you don't do localization of your software. I want to say a few things
first about how localization actually works at Mozilla. It is driven by hundreds if not
thousands of contributors, volunteers who spend their free time contributing to Mozilla
because they like it or because they like the products that Mozilla develops or they
like the mission or they care about their language. We are truly grateful that we have
such an, as we call it, army of awesome people who are, as you saw earlier, basically responsible
for 60% of the Firefox market share. There is not just Firefox. As you will see later,
there is many, many more projects that Mozilla localizes. The platform that we use for localization
is called Pontun. It is like a classic translation management system through which localizers
interact. But it is basically, as I mentioned, just an interface. The actual strings, the
actual English strings and translations are stored in repositories. Usually that is GitHub.
I think also GitLab sometimes. There is also hg.mozilla.org. That is what we call a single
source of truth. Then Pontun is basically just an interface because many of our localizers
are surprised, not really developers, don't really want to work with repositories directly.
It's much easier for them to make contributions through a tool that is hopefully not much
more complicated to use than, say, email client or Facebook. As you can see from this page,
this is a profile page of one of our active localizers. We really like version control
systems in particular GitHub, as you can say, by a particular widget on this page. The way
things work is that localizer would log in, they start by picking their team, their locale,
like the localizer's software to French. They start on the French page in this case, which
has some basic stats, some basic information about the locale in general, and more importantly,
at least all the projects that this community localizes. This is a screenshot so I can't
really scroll. There's 35 projects in total that the French community localizes. I think
in total we have 36, and they are being translated to over 200 different locales. For those of
you who are not familiar, the difference between a language and locale is that Spanish is one
language, but then you have several variants of Spanish, for example, like Spanish-Spanish
or Argentine-Spanish or Mexican-Spanish, those are locales, so all specific variants. Localizer
would go to this page, pick one project, for example, AMO frontend, which is not fully
translated yet, and then the translate view opens up, which is again a pretty straightforward
page. On the left you see the list of strings, and in the middle you have on top source string
and then the text field into which you enter translations. And then in the bottom right
corner you see two tabs from which translators get some inspiration from. You get suggestions
from several machine translation engines, translation memory, and you can also look
into how other locales might have translated the same string. There's two ways most of
our teams operate in. One is some localizers submit translations directly, which means
as soon as they are submitted to pontoon they end up in the version control system and can
be used in product. The alternative and more common way is that localizers just submit
suggestions and those suggestions then need to be approved by our trusted localizers who
have worked with localization for some time and have a proven track record of submitting
quality translations, and then they get into the repository. So here in this case we're
actually seeing on the left, we're seeing strings with corresponding suggestions, which
are then approved by a reviewer. Maybe one more detail around this. Since you see the
source string and the translation also in the sidebar on the left, the status boxes
on the left are actually check boxes, so you can select multiple strings and approve them
at the same time or reject them all at once. One last thing before I start with the presentation
of pontoon. We're currently working on pre-translation feature, which is essentially engaging machine
translation and translation memory, and as soon as source strings get exposed in the
repository to be translated, and as soon as they're served to localizers, and localizers
get notifications, hey, new strings are available, these strings get pre-translated using a combination
of translation memory and machine translation. So if we find a perfect match, we would use
translation memory. If we don't find anything usable in translation memory, we fall back
to machine translation. This is a pretty controversial topic, because pre-translation can yield interesting
results. Thank you. And that means that we're really slowly rolling this out for particular
project locale combinations, where there's actual needs, where, for example, localizers
are a little bit falling behind, but at the same time they have reviewers who are active
enough to hop in and correct potential errors that the pre-translation produces. Pontoon
is open source, it's freely available, so there's actually other users of pontoon outside
Mozilla. We're not aware of many, maybe a dozen, but we also don't know in case there
are more. It's relatively easy to set it up. We sadly don't offer any official support,
but if you do come to our discourse, I'm going to send the link, I'm going to show the links
at the last slide, or to our chat, chat.mozilla.org. We try to help, but like I said, we don't
offer any official support. There are some requirements that need to be met in order
for a project to be localized with pontoon. Obviously you need to use GitHub or some other
VCS back end as a storage for translations. Then you have two options for organizing the
files, either you follow a predefined folder structure or you use our out and end.tomos
specification which is then wrapped by pontoon to detect where the source files are and where
the translations are submitted. Obviously you need to store your translations in one
of the supported file formats. Here's some of them. You might be familiar with Fluent.
This is one of the formats that Mozilla developed. It's now basically slowly being... Emil is
going to talk about it in the next talk. It's basically transitioning slowly towards message
formats two, which is the format that is being developed. That's why there's an asterisk
at the end. We don't technically have a full blown support for it yet, but we're working
on that. There's also most common file formats are supported by pontoon. Once your project
meets those requirements, you just need to create it on your pontoon instance, which
is typically a very simple step. You need to add a project name, select target locales,
and add a link to your repository. That's basically it. You save it, you sync it, and
you have strings ready. Now the tricky part here is that you need your own instance. That's
a little bit more work than filling out this form. Like I said, there is documentation
on how to do that in our repository. It is, however, in our minds for some time now. We're
testing what is, whether there's an interest for us to create something like a multi-talent
pontoon instance where you wouldn't need to maintain your own instance. You would just
come and create your own project there and use that instance. That's pretty much it.
I would like to end here. This is the link to the repository, obviously, and all the
links to this course and to chat that I mentioned and the documentation are there. You can also
find me on matrix or Twitter. Sorry. Matt Jess. You can send me an email. I'd be also
happy to answer any questions here. Thank you. Thank you very much. We already have
two questions in the matrix room. One is, does it support more complex translation like
full articles? As an example given, what we can find on support.mazilla.org? Short answer,
pontoon is designed to be software localization translation system and we currently don't
have any support for, yeah, I don't know how to call it, like articles, longer blocks of
text. We sometimes abuse that, basically, and split some of the articles or some of
our web pages by paragraphs into multiple strings. But that's not really it. That's
not really the same as Wikipedia localization works or how MDN localization used to work
in the past. We have a ticket on file for that probably since the first week since pontoon
repository was created. But there has been basically no work on that. We do not only
do we try to help you if you want to set up your instance, we're very happy to take patches.
This one would be obviously huge. But anything that doesn't interfere with Mozilla needs,
we would be happy to support. The reason why we haven't implemented that feature is because
at Mozilla there simply was no real need for that apart from the exceptions that I mentioned
earlier. I hope that answers the question. We have another question from Sylvia. I wonder,
why does pontoon exist when other of us translation projects like Webblade exist? What Webblade
not yet around when the project started? Were there any specific feature design decision
you were missing that didn't work with Webblade? Not to say that pontoon shouldn't exist, I'm
just wondering what is unique selling feature. That's a great question. I think it's good
that people have options when they go to the store and they can choose different types
of milk or different types of cars. So it's sort of like the same question as why does
BMW exist if there's Mercedes? I think pontoon, I don't know Webblade too well, I have to
admit that. I was at the presentation today and from what I heard, I think it's an amazing
piece of software. I know that, for example, Mozilla is very eager about supporting natural
sounding translations through Fluent and Message Format. We have special UI for that. Maybe
that also exists in Webblade, I don't know, but I would guess that no, because Fluent
never really passed the borders of Mozilla very intensively. So that would be one of
the things that, and the Message Format support which is related to that, would be one of
the things that comes to my mind. But other than that, I think it's mostly, there's probably
a bunch of other tools. I don't know if Poodle is still in development. There's also closed
source systems. I don't think, I think it's good that people have different choices and
somebody likes that type of UI, somebody likes other types of UI.
Are there any other questions? I see. Can we add support for Firefox translations in
addition to Google and Cstrand? Is it easy to do?
It's very easy to do. Actually, we've been, when we started working on pre-translation
support, we wanted to only use machine translation engines that could be customized and trained
with our own data. And when we were evaluating several engines, obviously Firefox translations
was the first on the list. The challenge at that point, and that was maybe half a year
ago, things might have changed, was that the quality was a little bit lower, at least from
our experience. We were using, I think, BlueScore system, and I think BlueScore was about 5-10%
lower for the locales that were supported by Firefox translations. And it's killing
us because we would like to work with Firefox translations. And I'm sure that one day we
will. And the other issue was that, at least at that point, there was maybe a dozen of
locales that Firefox translations support, whereas with Alt and Mal, it's around 50,
and then there's 50 additional supported by the generic engine of Google. So yeah, hopefully
we're going to extend support to Firefox translations soon. And it's actually a good point, since
adding an engine itself is quite trivial, we should probably just add it, not to pre-translation,
but at least to that machinery tab where you could get suggestions from. Shit, why we haven't
done that? Thank you.
We do collect that, yes. Oh, sorry, sorry. So the question was, the suggestion was that
it would be nice to also collect telemetry to see which engine is preferred by users.
We actually do that already for each translation that's submitted by just copying it over from
memory or any of the machine translation engine. We keep track of that. And we can see that,
okay, this engine is more likely to be used than the other. Yeah.
So one thing I was wondering regarding like Fluent, for example, like other libraries,
for example, the Translate toolkit does not have support for Fluent yet. And I was wondering
if Mozilla was planning to help on the development of Fluent support in the Translate toolkit.
And another thing is that if there are any way of doing like validations, verifications,
because in our project we have a lot of very beautiful translators, but they are many times
it's the first time they translate, so they make a lot of mistakes with the HTML, markdown
syntax, and if you have any kind of validation.
Okay. Thank you. So maybe I can split my answer into two pieces. One piece around Fluent support
in Translate toolkits or maybe some other libraries. And the other question is about
whether pontoon has any sort of quality checks. So the first question, I think Emily will
have much better answer to that in the next talk, which is going to be about message format
2.0 standard, which I see, maybe I don't see clearly, Emily is going to correct me, which
I see as Fluent 2.0. It's developed under the standardization bodies, and that I think
means that the wider support in multiple tools is going to come. If you're specifically interested
about Fluent and adding Fluent support to Translate toolkit, then I think we should
definitely talk and see if there's an opportunity for that. So, translate toolkit already supports
Fluent. That's the answer to the first question. Thank you. The second question about quality
checks, and that's actually related to translate toolkit, pontoon uses three different libraries
for quality checks. One is actually two are internal Mozilla libraries, and another one
is translate toolkit library, which also has its own checks. So, yes, if there are any
obvious errors that can be automatically detected, we will most likely detect it. There's probably
errors that we could detect, but we don't, but I think most of them we do. We work on
improvements to our check system through developers telling us, oh, you broke our product. Okay,
apparently our checks are not good enough. So, over the years, I think our check system
became quite bulletproof. Thank you. We have time for one last question. If someone has
one. I don't see anyone. So, thank you very much, everyone, and thank you very much. Yeah,
thank you. There's a cake on their deceit. Just check it.
Thank you.