One minute, please sit down everyone.
I start.
Whenever you are ready.
Okay.
Team, team.
You started?
So, hello, everyone.
Welcome to our third call where we have Vincent.
Vincent Turo is a UI engineer on Mozilla privacy and security products team working on tools
like Firefox Relay and Firefox Monitor.
He's going to talk about over a decade of anti-tracking work at Mozilla.
Thank you, Francesca.
That was actually the first sentence of my presentation just gone now.
Yeah, so I work on the privacy and security products team.
Yeah, and so I want to start this presentation with a bit of a personal anecdote.
My open source journey started with the release of Firefox 1.0.
It was my first interaction with open source software.
Later started using Linux, started contributing.
First with translations.
Later I became a software engineer.
But I only joined Mozilla as an employee about a year and a half ago.
So for this presentation where I'm going to discuss a little over a decade of anti-tracking
work at Mozilla, I'm going to be leaning a lot on the experience of my coworkers, specifically
Luke Crouch and Max Crawford, other engineers on the privacy and security products team.
They wrote this blog post.
So most of the content of this presentation is also in the blog post.
So if you want to have a quick high level recap, you can read that afterwards.
It's also linked on the Fostom site, I think.
But Luke has been at Mozilla for basically forever.
Mozilla threw in through lots of institutional knowledge.
So lots of the content is by him.
Max did most of the illustrations.
So that's where credit is due.
So tracking, it can be beneficial.
I want to do one short scary slide and then the rest will be more positive.
But I want to take a bit of a moment to discuss the risk of tracking.
Why are we actually trying to minimize the harmful effects of tracking?
So tracking is a personal risk.
You can fall victim to phishing attacks, for example.
Or the people around you can fall victim to it.
So if more of your data leaks, it can be used to impersonate you and get, for example, people
around you to transfer large sums of money or whatever.
So if someone contacts my father and says, hey, it's your son, could you please wire
me 5,000 euros?
It's a lot less believable than if they were to say, hey, it's Vincent.
I just got fired from Mozilla.
Hopefully, it never happens.
Could you wire me 5,000 euros because I'm in money trouble or whatever?
That's a lot more convincing.
So data can be abused.
But it's also a more societal risk.
So ransomware has been in the news a lot recently.
It costs a lot of money.
It can even be used to convince people not to vote if they are aligned with a certain
political party or et cetera.
So there's risks involved with tracking.
The rest of my presentation should be more positive.
I'm going to discuss what we're doing to minimize those harmful effects to allow you to confidently
use the internet carefree.
So there's a variety of ways to track you.
Historically, a lot of attention both inside of Mozilla and outside of Mozilla has been
given to tracking cookies.
So I'll start my presentation with an overview of what we've been doing there.
And then I'll go over these other forms as well.
So cookies and a bunch of related technologies that all call cookies.
There are bits of data that websites can store on your computer, which can be useful.
So if you load a website and the website sees a bit of data that proves that you are you,
it can decide to give you your shopping card or your private messages or whatever and not
show someone else's.
So that's a good thing.
That can also be used to track you if you don't want that.
So every website you visit can set cookies.
But not just that website.
Websites can also embed other websites.
So for example, a website could contain a YouTube video and then YouTube can set cookies
as well.
It can contain ads.
And then those are often also served by a third party website can also set cookies.
Websites can even embed other websites without just seeing them.
So for example, with the goal of tracking you.
So those can also set cookies.
So we've been clamping down on that primarily through Firefox.
So I'll start my overview with Firefox private browsing introduced in 2008 after a Chrome
was released which had an incognito window.
But a private browsing window is basically a window that as soon as you close it forgets
everything you did in there, forgets the cookies that were stored as well.
It's often jokingly referred to as porn mode but it's definitely also an anti-tracking
tool.
So for example, my girlfriend used it as such.
She's a kind of ridiculous Harry Potter fan, like participates in international pub quizzes
about Harry Potter level.
But she's also a high school teacher.
And so sometimes she'll need to show a video of something that happened in the news recently.
And she'll go to YouTube, share her screen, and show a YouTube video to her class.
And she doesn't necessarily want her entire private life, which is entirely Harry Potter,
shown in the YouTube recommendations.
So what she does is at home when she's listening to Harry Potter music or ASMR or podcast
or whatever on YouTube, she'll open a private browsing window and do that thing in there.
And then if she closes it, then YouTube can't correlate those two sessions.
So won't show Harry Potter recommendations when she's sharing something with her class.
Another reason why I'm starting my overview with this private browsing window is that
it's we interpret if someone uses a private browsing window, we interpret that as a signal
that someone wants less tracking and is willing to accept some more breakage.
And so unfortunately often when we're trying to block tracking, websites assume that they
can track you and then build their functionality on that.
So there's a risk if you combat that, that you break the website.
So whenever we want to introduce new measures to combat tracking, we'll first introduce
it in private browsing, see how much it breaks there, and then later we can try to port it
over to your regular browsing window.
So that's why I mentioned private browsing first.
In 2013, we introduced more granular cookie control.
So you could make that trade-off yourself as a user.
You could choose, for example, to not use cookies at all.
Lots of breakage.
You wouldn't even be able to log into websites anymore, but also remove that tracking factor.
You could also choose to, for example, not the third-party cookie.
So if you visit a website, then that YouTube video that's in there might not be able to
set cookies.
Less breakage, but still quite a bit.
So it gave you that control, which is helpful, but it's also kind of out of the way.
You have to know of these options.
You have to understand what they do, understand their risks, and just making that trade-off
between breakage and less tracking isn't a great one in the first place.
So later on, we also introduced a block list so that basically a list of cookies that we
know are just used to track you.
Don't provide any functionality for you as a user.
And we allowed you to block those cookies.
So less breakage doesn't prevent all tracking, but helps there.
And then not too long ago, 2021, that's really state-of-the-art anti-tracking cookie work.
We introduced what we call total cookie protection.
So that doesn't actually block cookies.
But for example, if you visit youtube.com and then later visit a different website that
also includes a YouTube video, they'll both have cookies, but they'll be different cookie
jars.
So YouTube will still not be able to correlate those two sessions.
So that helps prevent that tracking factor without actually breaking it, because from
YouTube's point of view, they still have cookies.
So that's the work so far.
Obviously the timeline here stops at 2021.
We're in 2023 now, but they're still the future.
So we're always working on more things to combat that.
But that's my overview of cookies so far.
With that, let's move on to IP addresses.
So IP addresses are basically addresses for every device that's connected to the internet.
They're relatively stable.
They can change, but most of the time, most devices have the same address.
And this is a pretty strong identifier.
Like for example, I'm the only one that uses this phone.
It often has the same IP address.
So everything you can link to that IP address is quite sure to be me.
Same goes for this laptop, for example.
And they're not just tools to link you, but they're also often correlated to the same
to your geographical location.
So it's not super specific, but when I'm at home, you can deduce from my IP address which
city I am.
I'm in.
So yeah, that's the risk of IP addresses.
So whatever we've been doing there.
Well, like cookies, oh, I forgot this.
So the thing with IP addresses, it's inherently if two devices connect to each other via the
internet, they can see each other's IP addresses.
And so that means by virtue of connecting to a website, that website will be able to
see your IP address.
And again, websites can embed other websites.
So those embedded websites can also see your IP address.
So just like we did for cookie protection, we introduced a block list of IP addresses
that are known to track you and not provide other functionality.
As I mentioned, first in private browsing later also gave you that option in your regular
browser window, browsing, which is good.
If you never even connect to a tracking server or to an answer or whatever, it can't track
you.
It can't see your IP address.
But obviously, we can only do this for connections that don't provide any functionality.
We can't start blocking youtube.com because you won't be able to visit to view that video
anymore.
So to battle that, in 2019, we introduced Firefox private network, which is in between
your browser and the website you're connecting to.
And so instead of connecting directly to that website, you'll connect to Firefox private
network and then Firefox private network connects to the website you're trying to view.
And then from the point of view of that website, it will see the IP address of Firefox private
network.
So in 2020, we expanded that to your entire device with Mozilla VPN, which protects not
just your browser traffic, but everything on your device.
And you can also use it on multiple devices.
Yeah, so that's our IP protection so far.
Yeah, then I'll move on to email addresses, which is the fun part because I worked specifically
on Firefox relay product here that I'll discuss in a second.
The first is a question that blew my mind when Luke first mentioned it.
But email addresses, they feel like you can easily create a new email address, right?
You go to g1.com, enter a username and a password, and you've got a new email address.
So they feel like they're easy to change.
But in practice, you've probably changed your house address more often than you've changed
your email address.
I've moved a lot, like, I don't know, six times in the past 10 years maybe, but all
the time I've been reachable via the same email address.
So if you have that on file, there's so much history about me that you know via that email
address.
So it's a pretty stable identifier.
And it's cool if you block all your third-party tracking cookies and you hide your IP address,
but if you then go on and sign in with your email address, they can just correlate that
back together.
And this happens, for example, if you go to an online store and you buy clothes or whatever
and you sign in with your email address and then have the clothes delivered from the point
of view from that store, you're a very attractive customer.
Like, compared to some random on the street, you're far more likely to make another purchase
there than some random person is, right?
So what that store then does is they go to Instagram or whatever, and they're like, hey,
here's an advertising campaign.
There's also a list of all the email addresses of our customers.
Could you please show those ads to those customers?
And so from the point of view of that store, that's great news.
They can advertise to you.
You're a high-potential customer.
But from the point of view of Instagram or Facebook, Meta, whatever, owns it, it's even
better because they have not just your activity on Instagram and Facebook and WhatsApp, et
cetera.
They go, hey, you're a customer of that store and of any other stores that have done the
same.
So lots of ways to track you, and that's the voluntary part, voluntary data sharing by
third parties.
But in 2018, I believe, we introduced Firefox Monitor, which basically it keeps track of
data leaks that happen.
And if you sign up for Firefox Monitor, it will warn you if your data was found in a
data leak, if there was a hack or whatever, to remind you, hey, maybe you want to change
your password.
But what we saw is that many people use the same email address at different services.
So if there's data leaks in different services with the same email address, you can link
the two data leaks, the data in the two data leaks.
You can link them together and know that they're about the same person.
And many people even, probably not all of you, but other people also use the same password
across different websites.
So even if there's not a data leak in a different website, by using your email address and your
password, they're still able to extract data from those other websites.
So that's obviously not great.
So in 2020, we introduced Firefox Relay.
And what basically Firefox Relay does is it provides you with a unique email address per
service.
So if you have a sign up form, you need to leave your email address.
You hit the Relay button, and it will generate a new email address.
So I know ZQF40 at multmail.com, for example.
And it will forward all email that goes to that email address to your true email address.
So the store will still be able to communicate with you, send you emails at that address,
but that won't have your actual email address on file.
And so if there's a data leak there, your data can be linked to your data elsewhere,
because you have two different email addresses there.
So that's Firefox Relay.
Yeah.
Oh, actually, I'm doing well on time.
You're welcome, Francesca.
So then I lost the phone numbers.
So kind of similar threat, right?
It was super annoying when I started to use Relay, and cool, you can leave your email
address.
And I'm like, ha ha ha, I've got my Firefox Relay address.
You can catch me.
And then they're like, can you give your phone number two?
A bit of a shame.
So what we did is late last year, we introduced phone masking for Firefox Relay, added this
graphic to our website.
But it works similar to email masking.
You get a phone number mask, so a new phone number, and all the text messages, all the
phone calls that go to that phone number will be forwarded to your true number without having
to share your true phone number.
And so if you get, for example, a text message saying, hey, it's your bank.
Could you please change your password, go to this website and change it?
That's an additional signal where you can see, well, this is not actually my true phone
number, which my bank has.
So this is probably a scammer.
This is a pretty new edition.
So unfortunately for probably most of you, also for myself, especially given that I work
on it, not available outside the US and Canada yet, but hopefully soon.
But yeah, so the point there is lots of this work is like the broadening of the scope beyond
just tracking cookies.
That's all quite recent works.
You should saw like 2018 onwards, we started to broaden our focus.
That's also when the security and privacy products team around then started.
So yeah, we're not done yet.
Obviously this is the overview of the timeline so far.
And yeah, if you have any ideas of what we can do, do leave them on Mozilla Connect.
And that's, I think everything I had.
Damn, my practice was so much slower.
Thank you very much.
And so does anyone have any questions?
So especially with the IP and email protection, it really seems like you have a single part
of the page.
What do you do to mitigate any risks?
So the question was if, that's what you, yeah.
So the question is if, especially for Mozilla VPN and Firefox Relay, Mozilla is kind of
the single point of failure there.
And yeah, that's true.
So the point of failure here is, for example, for Firefox Relay, if you're, imagine we're
doing everything to prevent it, but imagine there's a data leak at Firefox Relay.
What then happens is your email address still gets public, which is annoying, obviously.
But you're basically back at where you were before, right?
But there's just one place where it could fill IE Firefox Relay rather than all those
places that store your other email address.
So yeah, it's annoying.
Ideally we'd have, I'm not sure, I'm sure Luke has probably a couple of ideas around
minimizing that that we might look at at some point.
If you have, looks like you have an idea.
Because especially if you are like the central place where you store everything, you become
a very attractive target.
Yeah that's true.
So yeah, if the, we're saying if we're a central place that has, have lots of email
address, obviously we become a bigger target.
That is true.
I wouldn't say like right now Firefox Relay and VPN as well aren't that big compared
to like there's far bigger data, data faults.
But that's definitely something we're aware of and want to minimize.
I think right now for, at least for me personally the, for me personally that is still worth
it, right?
The risk is smaller for using Firefox Relay.
For, if I want to order a ticket for example, like a concert ticket, I'll give them a Relay
address, they'll forward me the ticket and I'm done with it and I never knew that again.
For your, if you're interacting with your bank for example, I would use your actual
email address.
So it's, yeah, there's definitely a risk calculation to make there.
Nothing is a, yeah, all these products are not a perfect solution.
I think that's basically the threat in all of this.
It's all about trying to find that balance, like with the trying to block cookies for
example, it's all trying to find this balance between how much tracking do we want to allow
and how much breakage do we want to allow.
There's always tracking that we can't prevent and there's always downsides of our anti-tracking
measures that we can't prevent.
So yeah, I wish I had a better answer but that's it.
We have a personal sign matrix.
Okay.
It currently doesn't work with short.
Ah, okay.
So Danny on our matrix is asking that I'm not, yeah, so is asking about Firefox Relay
phone number masks, not working with a bunch of tools.
That is something we're aware of and working to fix for those who are familiar with phone
number masking.
Yeah.
So my question is, is it correct to state that at the moment none of the services we
demonstrate actually treat our data end to end and then end to end encryption so that
you can't see our data and follow up question to this question, if you have any plans to
implement end to end detection, is it even realistic in this space?
So the question is, do we end to end and create the data we're handling?
Obviously not applicable to everything like cookie, et cetera, not.
For emails, that's basically not possible because we need to know your email address
to actually be able to forward email.
We don't store the emails we forward so we get them for them to you and forget about
them.
So, um, damn it.
Uh, VPN, actually I'm not sure maybe, but I see why you are here.
Is that encrypted?
I think your connection via VPN is encrypted, right?
So yeah, um, VPN works the way that you generate like this.
We're using one.
Sorry for putting you on the spot, but.
Hi.
Um, yeah.
So VPN works, um, we're using the Wagga protocol.
So on the client, you generate your own private key and you only upload the public key to
the mother, the mother VPN network.
And then during the server handshake with a partner, you generate a session key.
So essentially even if your public key gets leaked, we can't see anything.
Yeah.
So VPN is, is entered and encrypted.
We can't see your, uh, what, what you pass through there.
Hey.
Hi.
Uh, I wonder how does a Firefox relay, um, like, uh, prevent spam?
Like how does, what kind of like mechanism does it use to catch?
Uh, so there's a basic spam filter.
Um, we make sure that if, uh, so if we forward our email and your email and you mark market
as spam in your, uh, in your inbox, Firefox relay gets a signal and stop forwarding emails
to that email address because, uh, you know, it's spam.
I wouldn't know.
So the question was what service do we use to, to detect spam, um, come to our matrix
and I'll find out for you.
Uh, yeah.
All right.
I reckon engineers will know that.
Yeah.
I'm not involved with that part of the implementation.
Um, but we do have a number of anti-spam and anti abuse mechanisms in there.
Um, cause obviously we don't want to get blocked by other people as well.
Uh, thank you for the talk.
Uh, might sound like a stupid question.
You mentioned the three or four products like relay VPN and monitor.
Are they free, including the VPN?
Uh, no.
So the VPN is paid.
I would also recommend you not to use a free VPN.
They're almost all shady.
Uh, quite a few of the paid ones are also pretty shady actually.
Um, but no.
So the VPN is, I believe if you pay annually, I think five euros a month.
Uh, I see not.
So that's good.
Uh, Firefox relay has a free plan which gives you just five email addresses.
Uh, so that works with them.
If you want to give every service a unique email address, that's not great.
Um, but they cost one euro a month.
Um, and, um, monitor is free.
Uh, yeah.
And so part of this is also like part of what we're doing at Mozilla is, is, you know, building
these, these, uh, privacy protecting tools.
Uh, we're also trying to find ways to have those finance themselves.
So that's what, yeah, it's not, um, yeah, we're not trying to sell ads or anything.
You pay for it.
You're the customer.
That's, that's the idea there.
All right.
So I think it's pretty obvious that the technologies that are being used to track is now kind
of almost requires to have a sort of centralized entity to sort of resolve it.
Whereas cookie protection could be kind of done decentralized and that obviously makes
Mozilla as a, as an organization, a kind of a target of critique, I guess, because you
become centralized to some sort of tracking.
Is there some sort of track or something that happens at Mozilla to mitigate the risks of
being a single entity that could store too much information?
Like for instance, in terms of relays, there is separate entity that, or, or an entrenched
thing that tries to ensure that you don't store too much data so that at least you can't
kind of try to monetize it yourself.
Um, they, yeah, everyone can hear it.
Right.
So, um, one, one strategy there that we have as a Mozilla, we have our lean data practices.
So that means collect as little, as little data as possible.
That's one way to mitigate that.
So for example, in Firefox Relay, it's why we only store your email address.
We don't store the emails we forward.
You can choose, so you can choose to store, uh, associations like which lay, which mass
data use of which website, but you can also choose to have that stored locally if you
have the extension or just not stored at all.
Um, and yeah, in terms of, we'd like, like, it's definitely something we'd like.
I don't, I'm not sure of initiatives going on there.
Um, and we do, um, not last night train of thought, but, um, yeah.
Thank you very much.
Unfortunately, this last question we have time off.
Please put the rest in the matrix room.
Okay, I'll leave, uh, go ahead and as I
I think I like 100% my fingers for this team.
Like 100%.
Yeah.
Oh, cool.
It's like fresh air, like you've got everything.
You can come on and make sure you're not wasting anything.
Thank you.
No, no.
And then obviously you're live.
Yes.
You have an adapter.
Thank you.
Wonderful.
I think most of you are going to turn on your second screen.
It's not on, I think.
It's on.
It's difficult.
So why doesn't that see it?
I think what people are asking about is the current voting party.
What does that do in the voting party?
So in countries where, for example, ISPs are net worth,
and they're not worth.
They're not worth.
I think it would be very secure.
I get the title more.
It's a different department.
I'm sorry, I can't talk, but it depends if you just scatter over there.
There's a better poll.
Yes.
It's coming.