We're ready for our next talk.
Mathieu is going to talk about MPTCP in the upstream kernel.
Thanks.
Yes, so hello everybody.
So welcome to this short presentation about MPTCP in the Linux kernel.
So it was a long road that started almost 15 years ago.
So I'm indeed Mathieu Barthes, working at Tesserys in Louvannan, so it's 30 kilometers
from here.
And let's start by a quick overview of the agenda.
So today I suggest to begin with a short introduction of multiparse TCP and its main use cases.
I will try to be quick for those who already know about that, but still trying to make
the concepts clear for everybody, hopefully.
Then I will explain what we can do today and what's expected for later.
I will finish by giving some explanation about why it took so long to have it included in
the official versions.
So MPTCP is short for multiparse TCP.
This is an extension to TCP that breaks the assumption that a connection is linked to
a fixed pair of IP addresses and ports.
In one sentence, it allows to exchange data for a single connection over different paths,
similar to mostly.
Now that you can have multiple paths for the same connection, you can then have more redundancy,
more bandwidth, and many more things.
But enough with the nice definitions, let's have a look at a typical use case.
Here is a classical MPTCP use case with smartphones.
So a smartphone can typically connect to both Wi-Fi and cellular networks.
That's a completely different view from the 70s, when TCP was designed and where everything
was fixed and clearly not transportable.
Let's take a typical scenario.
So you are here in the room connected to the Wi-Fi access point.
Quickly you realize that A, you have enough and don't want to listen to me anymore, and
B, you got called by the smell of the fries outside.
You then decide to watch the video stream about the history of fries, why not, on your
smartphone and leave the building to get real ones, much better.
Slowly the Wi-Fi signal will become weaker and weaker and likely the video will stop.
It will only restart when the system detected the issue and each app will then have to handle
that by reconnecting to the server and then continue where it was if it can.
It's clearly not a smooth experience for both devs and end users, of course.
In other words, do not leave the building if you don't have MPTCP on your phone.
Of course, there are fries for everybody.
So I guess you already got that MPTCP is going to improve this situation.
And yes, it will because it helps supporting seamless handover scenarios.
MPTCP allows to create multiple paths for the same connection.
So these paths are called subflows and they look like TCP connection when you look at
packet traces.
Except that these packets contain additional TCP options to let the client and server attach
new subflows.
They can also announce available IP address.
Of course, they need to have some numbers to reassemble the data and more things.
Multiple paths can be used at the same time like here on the slide.
So with the same workout scenario, the frustration of being disconnected from one network goes
away.
Indeed, MPTCP can quickly take the decision to continue the communication on another path
and even use multiple paths at the same time when one can no longer cope with the demand.
This kind of use case is already supported by Apple with apps like Siri, Maps, Music
and others, but also by Samsung and LG in some countries like South Korea and Turkey.
Another use case which is one that kept us busy for a bit of time at my company is the
hybrid access network case.
Many people are stuck at home with a not so great internet connection.
That's usually because they are using a copper line and are far away from the street cabinet.
Improving the situation is costly, but also takes time, especially if it is needed to
dig new and long trenches to bring fiber to home.
On the other hand, different assets of the network operator can be used, like the available
capacity on the mobile network, so I mean 4G and 5G.
With the help of a transplant proxy installed in the residential gateways for the client
side and the telco cloud of the operator for the server side, Multipass TCP is used
in the middle to offer more bandwidth to the end users.
One last use case that can be quite interesting is that MPTCP can also play a key role in
managing data between cellular networks like 5G and fix one like Wi-Fi.
The 3GPP, which is the organization in charge of defining the 5G technologies, suggests
operator to set up an ATSSS core function.
The goal is to use MPTCP to have a seamless handover between networks, so 4G, 5G and
Wi-Fi, not to break connection when you go from one to another, but also to reduce the
utilization of the mobile network and avoid the situation of this mobile network in the
future.
MPTCP is then part of 5G, but I cannot tell you if this is the same 5G as the one they
put in the COVID vaccine.
Anyway, enough with the theory, how do we use it and what can we do with it today?
So MPTCP in the upstream kernel is fairly new.
A recent ten of kernel is required.
An application can create an MPTCP circuit and use it like it would do with a TCP circuit.
So it's just one line change.
You can see on the slide that IP proto MPTCP is used instead of TCP.
So yes, the application needs to explicitly pick MPTCP, but it is also possible to change
the behaviour of existing applications by forcing them to create an MPTCP circuit thanks
to LD preload.
It is also required to configure the network side to tell the kernel that multiple interfaces
can be used.
So tools like Network Manager and MPTCP can help doing that automatically, but it is also
possible to do it manually with the IP tool.
So it's probably better with an example.
So just install a recent GNU Linux distribution, so a Fedora, Ubuntu, you name it, then you
set up the network configuration.
So here in this example, you can see that we need to declare which other IP addresses
can be used to create new subflows.
That's for the client side on the top and also to signal the IP addresses to the other
side.
It is also needed to tell the kernel that traffic generated from one IP should go through
the right interface.
So here we do that manually, but this can be done of course by Network Manager and others.
Finally at the end you can see that we need to run the application and here we use IP
Iperf3 and we use it with MPTCP IH just to force it to create an MPTCP circuit.
So the last table Linux kernel supports most of the protocol features.
So using multiple subflows, announcing IP addresses, priority fast-close, which is the
equivalent of TCP reset and many other things.
It also supports many circuit options used by many apps.
So for example TCP fast-open can be used with MPTCP for those who know what it is.
And it's also important to support these options because some existing applications depends
on them and would fail if they are not supported.
It is also possible to retrieve information from the user space thanks to MIP counters,
so also an INET-DAG interface and MPTCP circuit option, which is the equivalent of TCP info.
It's also important to mention that two pass managers are available and one packet scheduler,
but maybe better if I explain what it is.
So quickly just about the MPTCP pass manager, so it's a component that is in charge of creating
additional subflows, removing them if needed, announcing addresses, priority, etc.
It is needed on both hands but serves different purposes.
So for example here it is traditionally the client who creates new pass and the server
which announce additional addresses.
There are two pass managers available.
One where the user can define global settings to get the same behavior for all the MPTCP
connection, that's per net namespace, and also another one where the KNL notifies MPTCP
events to user space via Netlink and accepts commands to create, for example, new subflow
and announce IP addresses, etc.
So ensure the user space can control the pass manager and take decision per connection.
The other important component that I mentioned before is the MPTCP packet scheduler.
Its role is to decide on which available pass the next packet will be sent to.
So it can also decide to retransmit one packet to another pass if needed, and that's what
we call a reinjection.
The packet scheduler relies on the TCP congestion control algorithm used on each subflow to
know if more data can be pushed.
But additionally to better use all available resources and sometimes limited buffers, it
has also to send packets in a way to reduce packet reordering on one side, but also on
top of that it might decide to penalize some subflow that could impact the MPTCP connection
because some networks are quite bad with losses, buffer bloat and others.
So the packet scheduler in this case might also be able to trigger a reinjection of data
from one subflow to another, like if a failure has been detected.
So there is an internal packet scheduler for the moment, and only one, but other ones will
be able to be built with eBPF.
So yes, we need eBPF for the packet scheduler, and not just to look cool or to be accepted
to conferences.
So in fact, eBPF here will avoid us to maintain all sorts of different packet scheduler in
the kernel.
It's a bit similar to TCP congestion control.
There are a few in the kernel, but sometimes no longer maintained.
So quite a bit of work has already been done, and it is already possible to do some experimentation
if you use a development version in OGetTree.
But this work is currently on hold because we ended up discussing the behavior of the
current internal scheduler and its API, and yes, some work is still needed here.
But there are also some circuit options that need to be supported, but most likely they
are specific to some very specific use cases.
So it should be fine, but feel free to report them if some are missing.
And one last thing that is worth mentioning is the support of Golang.
As you may know, Golang does not depend on a C runtime library or libc, and it is then
not possible to use the LD preload technique with MPTCPIs to use MPTCP.
Also the default net package doesn't allow application to create MPTCP circuit on UDP
or TCP, and a feature request has been sent to let apps easily create MPTCP circuit.
But quickly the question Golang developers asked was, then why not using MPTCP by default
when a stream connection is requested?
So when asking for TCP.
And the proposition has been accepted, so we hope that some application using the net
package will be able to create MPTCP connection, and maybe later that will become the new default
behavior.
So I will now finish this presentation with a bit of history.
I think it is worth telling you that because it was not easy to get MPTCP in the official
Linux kernel, it could be good to say a few words about that.
So still it was not as long an intense as having the full real-time support, and I see
that some people here really know what I'm talking about.
The development of MPTCP in the Linux kernel started in Belgium, at the university in Louvain
and Eve, something like 15 years ago.
Surprisingly, it didn't involve bees.
No, of course it did.
The legend says that the ID popped up when the young authors were drinking bees at a
crowd pub where the bartender was able to cope with the high demand by using multiple
bee pumps at the same time.
More seriously, it started as a fork, but more to do some experimentation and to validate
the concept.
So at the beginning of his PhD, Sebastian just wanted to prove it could work.
He started to modify TCP by adding more condition.
So just if it is multi-pass TCP, do that, if not do something else.
Later, more people, mostly Christophe and Gregory, joined the project to help Sebastian.
They then took over his work to make it, let's call it, production ready, but also to be
able to reach high performances.
In other words, to get the modification in the Linux kernel were consequent and optimized
for the MPTCP use case.
In parallel, MPTCP v0 RFC has been published in 2013.
The same year, a big company with a logo looking like an apple, if you see, announced its support
for the client side.
Of course they needed to have the support for the backend side, and I will let you imagine
what they used.
So if we concentrate on the very beginning of the project, we can say that it was easy
to fork, but you will pay for it.
Please don't read the two lines out of the context.
But anyway, there are different utilization of a fork.
You can pick your level.
So I let you guess which one has been picked here, probably ultra-violence.
Only because the Linux kernel is big.
It's also complex, and the development is very active.
So small modifications should not be difficult to maintain in a fork, but here we are talking
about quite a lot of code, and an important part is modifying the network stack, which
still has many adaptations specific to MPTCP.
And in fact, from those that are even duplicated functions that were adapted for MPTCP case.
So imagine that the code is modified on TCP side.
We don't see it directly, and then we need to adapt it later to MPTCP.
But still that was not the nightmare level.
This is the nightmare level.
So imagine that you have to deploy it on various embedded systems with different LTS kernels
from very old version, like 3.4.
So that's what we had to do at TESRS, and I explain why some of my colleagues here look
like the avatar just by mentioning kernel backports.
In the meantime, very old version have been deprecated, but thanks to the embedded system
wall, this took time.
So of course, this backboard job brought the drought of having to deal with many conflicts,
but good tools like git re-re-re and top-git help a lot for that.
So also add to that a bunch of batch script, and it was possible to automate most of this
laborious task.
Top-git allows us to create a tree with dependency.
That's what we can not really clearly see on the side, but it's also very handy if a
fork has to be maintained by a team where regular sync with the upstream have to be
done as well.
So at the end for us, what we were doing is that we were applying the patch at the bottom
and then propagate it to all the kernel versions, and then we had to resolve a few conflicts.
But likely we're not doing that too much.
At the end, the fork is still quite well used today despite all the work that has been done
on the upstream code.
I even published new releases last Friday and probably one of the last one.
But on the bright side, the migration process has started with just take time.
The MPTCP support in the upstream kernel has started in 2020.
Why a so long delay?
Was it an homage to the Belgium Rideway company?
It was not, in fact, a new idea.
A few discussion and attempts have been made in the past, but were not successful.
In our case, it was not an easy task to upstream MPTCP.
First, because the Linux TCP stack is highly optimized, but also because the NetDev maintainers
have been clear on that topic.
It is okay to include MPTCP in the official Linux kernel, but the new implementation cannot
affect the existing TCP stack, which means no performance regression, maintainable and
possible to disable it, can be extended via user space.
You know it's what I said earlier, you might already understand that we are not allowed
to take the initial fork as it was.
So it was built to support experiments and rapid changes, but not generic enough.
Also at the end, it was and still used on environment where the majority of the connection
are using MPTCP and not the opposite.
So what were the solutions?
A rewrite almost from scratch was needed.
That's probably why it took so long to say, okay, we need to do it.
A key difference with the upstream kernel is that a new circuit type is used.
So there is no clean separation.
The user space interacts with the MPTCP circuit, which controls the different TCP subfruits.
Thanks to the TCP upper layer protocol, ULP, that was introduced in 2017 for KTLS, it was
possible to minimize the modification in TCP code while still avoiding duplicating code.
An SKB extension mechanism has also been initially developed for MPTCP, not to include the socket
buffer side for the generic case.
This is also used now by other components today.
Also we had to be very careful when modifying the TCP stacks.
So any ID to avoid that, we're good to take.
One last point is that the APIs have been defined to have to maintain multiple versions
of pass manager and packet scheduler in the kernel, even if the last one is still ongoing.
But also one thing is that we needed to do a lot of work.
Here I just want to say a special thanks to our ex-maintenor, Matt Martino and other fellows
and Intel who had to step out very recently.
In conclusion, it was a long road and it's not over.
Thank you.
We have time for a couple of questions.
Just two quick questions.
One, when you have multiple connections, can you kind of do it raid one sort of style,
like where traffic goes on both simultaneously so that you don't have to resend something
if something gets dropped?
And can you speak also about SCTP and what's going on if it's dead or if you know?
Because it's sort of in a similar space and I never understood why people focus more on
MPTCP than SCTP.
Thank you.
I will maybe start just with the SCTP aspect because I don't know much about it.
From what I remember is that here with multi-pass TCP, we do an extension to TCP.
So most likely where TCP was working before, MPTCP can work.
There are some exceptions with some nasty middle boxes, but I think that's the main
reason why we can see multi-pass TCP in the field and maybe not SCTP.
I think it is not dead and still used for data centers, but I don't know exactly about
that.
For the other question, I have not understood everything, you said that you wanted to aggregate
multiple pass.
I mean you have your two pass, can you send the same data simultaneously?
Yes you can.
So there is even a packet scheduler called redundant packet scheduler.
There is one small bit that is important to mention is that each pass is still a TCP connection,
which means that if you have some losses on one pass, you still need to retransmit it
on the same pass.
So at some point it might be okay to say that, okay, the other side received it via the other
side, via the other pass.
So if you got a loss on one pass.
So the end host doesn't need it, but because there are middle boxes and others on the pass,
you need to retransmit it at the TCP level.
I don't know if it's clear, but you can do reinjection, but you need to continue retransmit
on the same pass.
You can't just, when you find it received that request, just drop it.
If you want to do that, the best is probably to stop the connection.
Like if you want to have a low latency thing, or if you want a low latency, maybe don't
use TCP, but that's another question, not the topic.
But if you want to do that, it's probably best to stop the pass and recreate it.
Thank you.
So I looked at the CCTLs for MPTCP, and I found one called DSS checksum.
And reading the patch notes, it's something to do with middle boxes.
So is that giving you issues?
And why is it, and last question, pending that, why is it not on by default?
Yes, no, good question.
So in short, middle boxes are not nasty.
They like to modify everything, and I will not comment too much about that because at
my company, we do a transplant proxy, so we are kind of middle box.
But what can happen is that middle boxes can change a lot of things in TCP.
For example, you have all protocols, like FTP, where the IP address is sent on the by
screen, but like in clear text.
Which means that if you have a NAT, you probably have a NAT that starts to look at the connection,
identify it is FTP, and modify the text in the by stream, like the IP addresses.
But because it does that, the size can change.
And if they don't update MPTCP header, because we need to add some information to be able
to reassemble the data on the other hand, they can mess up with MPTCP.
So there is this checksum mechanism, but there is one big inconvenience, is that for the
moment, there is no hardware acceleration, so it's quite costly.
And the other thing is that at the end, it's quite rare that you have some middle boxes
modifying the by stream like that.
I know that in the past, you had some, if you were going on some website, for example,
with 480 without HTTPS, it's possible that some by stream were injected.
And probably when they do the injection, they don't modify MPTCP.
Sorry, we need to move on.
Yeah, sorry.
Otherwise we won't be on schedule.
So that's why we don't have checksum, but thank you.
Thank you so much for the talk.
Thank you for the questions.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Do you have a question?