Hello. Our next talk is going to be by Ahmad about having something to hide.
Thank you. Yes, so my name is Ahmad Fatoum. I'm an embedded Linux engineer with Pingotronix
and thanks for attending my talk on having something to hide trusted key storage in Linux.
So Pingotronix, the company I work for is a German Linux consulting company. We specialize
in embedded systems. So all around embedded Linux consulting around drivers, boot loaders,
kernel porting. And in the course of one project, I had occasion to get more familiar with kernels
trusted key subsystem, which I will talk about today. But first I will talk about what we
need to store these keys for. This is usually disk encryption. So if you install a new Linux
distribution on many systems, you already have whole disk encryption out of the box.
And it's just really one click affair. But what are the mechanisms underlying that? That's
usually the encrypt. So the encrypt is device mapper with the crypt target. And what it
does is that it maps physical devices to a virtual device and applies some transformation
to it. In this case, it's cryptography. And you see how that looks like in code at the
end of the slides. You specify a range. You start from the first block, the number of
blocks. You specify that you want to use crypt. You specify your crypto parameters. For example,
here it's AES. And then you reference crypto keys that you want to use for this symmetric
encryption here is 32 byte long key with the name key. And it's of type log on. And in
the line after that, you see this key being added. And that's all you need to do. So to
initialize your DMCrypt, there is a DMCetup tool you can call and then you have DMCrypt
running. You can use this virtual device, just write to it. And the physical device,
things that will be written there will be encrypted with these parameters that you have
set. Most people don't do this manually via DMCetup, but they have a wrapper around that
that's usually crypt setup with looks. So looks is desk encryption specification. You
see at the end how the header is laid out. You have this binary header that's still there
for competibilities. And you have a JSON area that can describe these parameters that we
had in our DMCetup table, like what sort of algorithm is used or what HMAC is used. And
then there is this key slots area. And in this key slots area, you have this volume
key that was at 32 byte long key that we had. That key is what's actually used for crypto.
But if that leaks, yeah, you have all your data encrypted with it. So the idea with the
M crypt is with what crypt setup and looks do is that you can have multiple key phrases,
for example, your normal key phrase that you always enter or a recovery key. And then in
turn you encrypt that volume key with each time with a different key. And that's stored
in these key slots area. And that way you can have multiple pass phrases for the same
volume. And yeah, where does that pass phrase come from? So it's usually entered by the
user. So in the initRD you are asked what's the pass phrase that you want and then you
enter it. You could be a bit more sophisticated and insert USB sticks that has a file that's
the same code pass, basically, you could insert a feeder security key or a smart card. But
what all of these have in common is that the user is inserting or writing or you need user
involvement. And in my project, it was an embedded system. And we don't have really
a user powering up the devices. And yeah, we need some sort of automated solution for
unattended boots. And here is where trusted storage comes in. So in the regular case,
the trusted storage is like the memory of the user or his USB stick. But for an unattended
boot, you need some on chip or off chip device that's appropriately secure, that can hold
the key. Such device is in many systems as a TPM or the trusted platform with us. This
is an industry wide standard. It's also an international standard and it's mandated by
Windows 11, which helps its adoption in a lot of modern systems, because you couldn't
boot Linux otherwise. They are available as discrete devices as chips, sometimes on like
a breakout board for your motherboard, but they can also be implemented in firmware.
And TPMs have this standardized interface where you can talk to them and they provide
you a lot of services. What's interesting for us is that it has a random number generator
built in. So it has its own entropy source and gives you access to it. And it holds a
unique never disclosed key. And with this unique never disclosed key, you can encrypt
arbitrary data. So instead of having a passphrase that you need to remember, you could have
an encrypted passphrase and then you pass it to the TPM and the TPM will decrypt it
with this unique never disclosed key that it has inside and then pass you the data in
a decrypted form, which you can then pass into the encrypt or into crypt setup or whatever.
And you can make this even dependent on having reached a state that's on integrity measurement.
So each boot state could verify the boot stage after it and then tell the TPM this is a measurement
value. And these measurement values are concatenated and hashed and kept in the TPM. And you can
configure the TPM to only release and only to decrypt data when it reaches that state.
And then you can be, yeah, and when you configure it correctly, the TPM would only decrypt your
encrypted blob when you are indeed in that measured boot state that you want to be. You
can even bind it to a time. So after a given time has elapsed, you can't access it anymore.
Yeah. How does it look like in practice? The kernel has drivers for that that abstract
away the different modes of communication. It can be I squared C, it can be SPI. You
don't need to worry about that in user space. You have these device files that provide you
access. There are user space libraries that wrap that and there is even a system D support
since I think a year and a half or so where you can enroll looks keys into TPMs. It's very easy
to set up. But what's whatever you do is a common way of using this with looks has a common, you
could call it issue that privileged user space has access to this key material. So if you
have seen there is this Jason area where you could store stuff. So you could store your
encrypted key there. And what would happen on boot is that prep setup or system decrypt
setup or whatever would go there. It would get this encrypted key, encrypted key to send
it to the TPM. The TPM would do its checks and see, okay, I'm in the correct state. It
will decrypt this data and then send it back to your user space. And then your user space
now has this passphrase which it could use to decrypt the encrypt key and then it would
pass it into the kernel again. So it's a real roundabout way to get the encrypt key into
the kernel key ring. So the idea behind trusted key was why not directly decrypt the TPM secured
key into the kernel key ring and reference it from there without involving user space
at all. And yeah, so it has been implemented. It was first added in 2010. The first kernel
was released in 2011. It was originally TPM specific, but the naming was held generic
enough I think in hopes that it can be extended in future. So the same patch series that added
also encrypted keys. So encrypted keys are keys that you can only observe from user space
in encrypted forms. That's how it should be. So you tell the kernel, generate a key for
me and then when you try to export the key, you only get it in encrypted form and then
when you want to load it, you give it the current encrypted form and it will decrypt
it, but it will stay in kernel memory in decrypted form. And that's encrypted keys and trusted
key additionally have a hardware root of trust. So they use a TPM for doing the encryption
and decryption. So in theory, you shouldn't be able to decrypt a trusted key to load it
and have it decrypted on another system than the one where you generate it on because on
the other system you would have another trust source with its own unique key which is used
for the encryption. How does it look like in code? So it's basically the same line as
we have seen before, but instead of having a 32 byte long login key, we have a 32 byte
trusted key here. It's called KMK and to create it, you can use a keyctl command, you add a
trusted key, you don't specify the key material like we did with the login key because you
can't do that. You can just ask the kernel to generate you a 32 byte key and then when
you try to pipe it, which is a command to pipe the key contents out, unlike a user key
which would just output the key material in plain text, it would output the encrypted
key and that you can store wherever and use it on subsequent boots. So what the rest does
is it sets up a loop device and does the encrypt on it and write it works and then it reboots.
And then on the second boot, if you were to create a new trusted key, it would be completely
different, it would be generated randomly and you want to use the keys that you have stored
already, which is what the blue line is doing, it does add trusted KMK, but instead of creating
a new key, it loads the key blobs that we have stored and with that, you should be able
to read back what you have written before. Yeah, so that's how it works. We have a way
to do it in user space already and that's how it's usually done. And not everyone agrees
that sets strict advantages by doing it in the kernel, but what was interesting to me
is that it is a very useful interface to represent much more than just TPMs because on modern
system, you can have offship secure enclaves, basically a TPM that doesn't speak the TPM
level and doesn't implement everything, but it implements part of it. You can have an
onship trusted execution environment, you can have crypto units inside everyday socks,
very often you have a crypto accelerator that also has access to a key that it could use
for wrapping and unwrapping data. And indeed in 2019, work started from Sumit Garg at Linaro
to generalize trusted keys and add T support in the first instance. So what is T? T is
also an API standard and what it's about, it's having a hardware isolated environment
where you can run trusted applications on the same CPU where you execute your Linux,
but thanks to this hardware isolation, normally arm trust zone, if you do everything right
and have firewalls in place and all that stuff, you shouldn't be able to read the secure memory
from your normal world, which is Linux. And these trusted application can do basically
everything. You can have a trusted applications that offers you a TPM and in that case you
could just use trusted keys with TPMs, but you can do basically anything, it's software.
So you can just do random number generation in T, you can do key sealing and unsealing
with a hardware unique key. So that's available on some processors that when you are in the
secure mode, you have access to a key that you can never see from Linux, which is unique
and fused in. And there are even people doing clock reset power domain support stuff in
it because they don't want Linux to have access to these things. So if you are interested,
you can just grab the kernel tree for T client driver and see all the stuff that's there.
And what was interesting to me was the crypto unit inside the IMX SoC, it's called Calm
by FreeScale. And we already have a calm driver in Linux. It does random number generation,
it does crypto acceleration. It works a bit like a network card. So I have these shared
TMA rings where you push jobs you want the calm to do. And then the calm replies to you.
And yeah, you can do as I said, script acceleration RNG. And it also has access to a one time
programmable master key that's fused by NXP in the factory. And that's unique between
devices. That's that's a selling point. And the calm can use it for red blob generation,
which means it seals and uncears user supplied data using it. Basically the same we have
seen with the TPM and with T and it has black blob generation. So TPMs are very slow. And
you I don't know if they support crypto offloading, but you probably don't want to do that in
if you want to do something quickly. But the calm can do it much quicker. And you can have
this key never exit the calm and use it for crypto inside the calm. You are of course limited
to the crypto algorithms account supports. But the possibility is there if you don't
want your key to even enter the kernel, it should be all the time in in the calm itself.
And yeah, so why do we need that for the common use case is certificate storage. So you are
a vendor and you need to call into your own cloud and you have client certificates for
that. And you don't want someone to be able to dissolve as this emm see and read it out
and get access to your certificates. And thus you decrypt the certificates and at runtime
encrypted into memory, maybe normal memory, maybe unshipped memory, however, whatever.
And yeah, we had many customers with that needed something like that. And we had been carrying
out of three patches for it in 2015. We send it out the first time to get some feedback.
Back then it was using the standard thing, a custom CFS interface. And in the following
years, NXP tried to upstream their own new key types to represent, to wrap this, this
hardware functionality. And finally, in 2019 work began on generalizing trusted keys. And
it was finally merged in 2021. In 2021. I also started then with implementing it for
Calm and that support is now available since 519. And it's usable exactly the same way
as with TPMs. You can't do this measurement stuff because Calm doesn't have support for
that. But on NXP socks, you would rather use their form of a ferrified boot. So this unique
key that's inside the Calm, it's only released when the sock believes it's in a high assurance
boot state. That means that the boot ROM has verified the boot loader. And then you are
supposed to keep that chain of verification going and boot loader, verify the kernel,
verify the initRD and so on.
Yeah, some interesting tidbits while I upstream the series. T and TPM both don't use a kernel
entropy pool for TPMs. They always have a random number generator for T. It was specified that
they need to provide random number generation. That's not something that I wanted to do for
Calm because we have a perfectly fine Calm RNG driver. Not everyone was fine with it,
but eventually stubbornness prevailed. You can now choose it for existing back ends as
well. You can specify trusted RNG equals kernel and then you can even for T or TPM use the
kernel entropy pool if you want to use that. The default is leaving it to the trust source
to decide what it wants to do. And that's also useful for devices like on the iNIC 6
ultra light light. You can guess from the name. It's supposed to be very lightweight
and their crypto unit doesn't support an RNG. So you rather want to use the kernel driver
that's available that does this a bit differently than have to do it in your own driver.
And what was also interesting hardware feature bits were broken on some variants. So you
can ask the Calm what features it supports and there are Calms that support, do as it
says they have a blob support, but say like a support so they fail with an internal exception
when you try to use it because it's because the ceiling and unsealing is a space. But
yeah, that's one more thing the kernel needs to take into account to work on these systems.
And that's also something I only learned about while getting review feedback was not something
I anticipated. As you have seen, NXP had different. Okay. NXP had different attempts on getting
into the corner and they applied that to the vendor tree. They called it secure keys. And
during the upstreaming feedback, I was asked if I wouldn't want to change my modifier key
to be compatible with an XP kernel. So people have an easier time migrating to it. That
was no problem for me. It broke my interface, but I needed a migration step anyway. And
yeah, it makes stuff easier for most of you as a user set one to switch. And yeah, so
I did set why did I need a migration step because I was using looks before, but looks
doesn't have trusted key support. So what I did is I used the M Crip directly. I basically
did the same thing that looks would be doing, but only on the M Crip part. And I would exclude
the header you had seen in the first one in the first of the first slides, you can specify
the range of blocks that it should work on. And then you can just cut out the looks area
and do the M Crip directly. And yeah, and you need a one time import step because the
first time you don't want to generate the trusted key randomly, but you want to take
the ones that you have already been using for years. Of course, in a new product, you
don't want that non upstream patch I linked there, but in an existing product. Yeah, that's
how you could do it. Old key blob put into CFS gets a plain text key out key city and
imports and you have the new key blob. We store both alongside. So if the update fails
for whatever reason, you can fall back to the old system and use the old key blob and
both work. Finally, what more is there to do? So is
encrypted key support for the M Crip, E-Crypt of S, E-FAM and V-DIM. There's direct key
support trusted key support without involving encrypted key for the M Crip. And yeah, you
can use encrypted keys. Future candidates would be S Crip. There has been attempts one
for the old key setup scheme. The second by me for the new key setup scheme. UBS authentication
also currently uses a logon key that could be changed to be a trusted or an encrypted
key. But yeah, these patches are have died down. Look support would be awesome because
yeah, with looks it just works out of the box with the M Crip. We still need to do it
manually, but that enables us to do it completely in the kernel without involving userspace.
And yeah, you don't really want userspace messing with a DMA capable device that could
just override the kernel if you give it access. So trusted keys was the correct solution for
us there. And that concludes my talk and I would accept your questions if you have any.
Thank you. And we have some time for a few questions. I have a question. Are you aware
of any way to kind of get this step of getting the secret from the hardware to automate that
into the kernel as well so you don't need userspace interaction, userspace utilities?
My use case is mainly like the root file system. And to forgo using an init ramfs that needs
to run a lot of commands. So you could from the kernel command line similar like with
the a minute also get the key. Personally, I would if I had said a requirement, I would
consider doing it from the bootloader and then have the kernel read it off the kernel
command line because the encrypted key blobs there is nothing confidential about it. So
yeah, in theory, the kernel could accept it over the kernel command line, but there is
nothing like that. It's currently.
I can repeat the question if it's too. Is there a way to also combine this hardware
keys with some pin and looks so you have to authorize yourself to the device?
Not really the desire how it's meant to be used because well, yeah, as a key material
shouldn't exit the kernel and you directly reference the M crypt key. You insert the
key in the current hearing and directly reference it. So I don't know how to do it to easily
factor in a user pin. There's a passphrase option.
Apparently, there is a passphrase option that I need to look up when using trusted keys.
Thanks for the talk. Would it be possible to add a manual step before communicating
with a TPM, for example, a fingerprint scanner or anything like that? Is there a hardware
and software option to combine the two verification steps?
Currently you need to have an in its RDR. So in my case, you have an in its RDR. I don't
even have an in its RDR. I don't use it for the root file system. But if you were to use
it for the root file system, for example, you could in the in its RDR first check that
you have this, that fingerprint is there, but there is no way to wire it in the kernel.
First this needs to happen. That's more of a policy thing that you would do in user space.