I'm going to talk about walking native stacks in BPF without frame pointers.
Thanks.
So, yeah.
So, my name is Vaishali.
I work at Polu-Simmons as a software engineer, mostly on profiling and eBPF related stuff.
And before that I have worked in different corner subsystems as part of my job.
My name is Javier.
And I've been working at Polu-Simmons for a year, mostly working on native stack unwinding.
And before I was working on web reliability and dev tooling at Facebook.
So before we get into the talk, let's talk about the agenda.
So we'll first address the first question, which is always being asked, that why there
is a need for a DWARF-based stack walker in eBPF.
And we will briefly go through the design of our stack walker, we'll also go from how
we went from the prototype to making it production ready.
And then what were a bunch of the learnings so far, especially when we are interacting
with the eBPF subsystem of the kernel.
And then our future plans.
So as I said, we work on the production profilers.
Generally sampling profilers collect the stack traces at particular intervals and attaches
values to it.
Note that profilers generally need both user application stacks and kernel stacks.
Stack walking is part of the process for collecting the stack traces.
In simple words, it involves iterating over all the stack frames and collecting the return
addresses.
Historically, there has been a dedicated register to store the value of it in both x86 and ARM.
Although it has fallen victim of some of the compiler optimisations, so most of the runtime
actually severs it.
It's called frame pointer, as many of you have heard of it.
And when we don't have the frame pointer, walking the stack becomes like magnitude of
like a lengthy process.
So instead of involving a couple of memory accesses per frame, which is quite fast,
we will have to do more work in the stack walkers.
The stack walking is also common practice in debuggers, right?
So what's the current state of the world with respect to frame pointers?
So it's not a problem for especially hyperscalers.
As you may know, in production, they are always running the applications which has the frame
pointers unable, because whenever they have to inspect the incidents, getting faster and
the reliable stack registers must.
Go runtime enables the frame pointers since go 1.7 in x86 and 1.12 in ARM64.
Mac OS is always compiled with frame pointers.
There's also an amazing work going on for the compact frame format.
It's called simple frame format, and there has been like support being added in the tool
chains, and now there is also like a mailing list discussion going on in the kernel about
having an unwinded stack walker, sorry, a stack walker for unwinding the user stacks.
But the thing is that we want it now.
We want to support all the distros.
We want to support all the run times.
And the one thing that comes across a lot of this is dwarf, and that's why we are using
it.
So where does it come from?
So like some of you might be wondering about like the exceptions in C++ or, for example,
Rust tool chain which is like always disabling the frame pointers, but when you use the panic,
it always has the full back dress.
The reason is that it has the.eh frame section which is being used for that or debug frame.
So most of the time either of the tool chains have this section.
And the other idea is that you can also unwind the tables by synthesizing it from the object
code.
This is like the approach which is being used in org, one of the kernel second minder which
was added I guess six years ago.
So we'll talk about in detail about.eh frame in a minute.
But before that, let's see who else is using.eh frame.
So of course we are not the first one who are going to use it.
Perf does that.
Since I think since when the Perf event, open Cisco was introduced in 3.4, so it collects
the registers for the profile processes as well as a copy of the stack for every sample.
While this approach has been proven to work, there are a bunch of drawbacks which we wanted
to avoid.
One of the things is that kernel copies the user stake for every sample and this can be
quite a bit of data, especially for the CPU intensive applications.
Another thing is that when we are copying the data in the user space, the implications
of one process having another process's data can also be complicated.
So those are a bunch of things we wanted to avoid.
And stack walking using BPF makes sense to us because we don't have to copy the whole
stack.
Instead, a lot of the information still stays in the kernel, especially in the case of stack
walking mechanism.
Once it has been implemented, we can leverage the Perf subsystem to get the samples on CPU
cycles, instructions, access, et cetera.
It can also help us to develop other tools like allocation tracers, runtime-specific
profilers like for the JVM or Ruby, et cetera.
Now some of you might be wondering that why do we want to implement something new when
we already have BPF get stack ID?
So the reason is that it also uses frame pointers to unwind it.
Having a fully featured dwarf unwinder in kernel is unlikely to happen.
There is a mailing list discussion.
You can go and check it out.
Why?
So now before we dive into the design of our stack walker, I wanted to give some information
on what ES frame has and how we can use it.
So ES frame section contains one or more call frame information records.
The main goal of the call frame information records is to provide answers on how to restore
the register for the previous frame and the locations such as whether they have been pushed
to the stack or not.
And all of this would actually generate the huge unwind tables.
And for these reasons, the format attempts to be compact.
And it only contains the information that is being needed.
The unwind tables encoded in the CFI format are in the form of opcodes.
And we basically have to evaluate it.
And then in the case of stack walking, once it has been evaluated, we generate the table
that contains for each instruction boundary how to restore the value of the previous register.
It has sort of two layers to it.
One is this sort of helps with the repetitive patterns for compressing.
And it allows for a more compact representation of some data.
As in some cases, a specialized opcodes that consumes one or two or four bytes.
So it doesn't have to be four bytes all the time.
And the second layer is like a special opcode that contains under the set of opcodes which
is like arbitrary expressions.
And they need to be actually evaluated for that.
And this would mean that we will actually have to implement the full below VM in the
EBPF to evaluate any expression, which is not practical.
So we are going to also mention what we are doing to actually come over those challenges.
For those who are not aware of what is the general flow of the EBPF applications, generally
this is how it would look like.
Very high level overview.
So in the user space, we are using the driver program, which is written in Go.
We use the BPF Go.
It creates the map, attaches the map, attaches the BPF program to the CPU cycles of perf
content, and then reads, passes, and evaluates the EBPF section of the process.
And in the BPF program, we fetched the table from the current PID and then have an unwinding
algorithm which processes the reward for information.
So we'll go in depth for each component.
But let's see what the algorithm looks like.
So first what we are doing is we are just reading three registers.
First one is RIP, the second one is stack pointer, RSP, and the third one is RBP, which
is commonly used as frame pointer when they are enabled.
Next we are going for the unwind frame count, which is less than, and when it's less than
maximum depth.
We find the unwind table row for the program counter.
Then we go for adding the instruction pointer to the stack, calculate the previous frames,
stack pointer, update the registers, and continue with the next frame.
So this is like a very simple binary search.
But when it has to scale, we need to also think about storing the unwind information
and how can it work with all the run times, et cetera.
So Javier will now talk about that.
Cool.
So as Vaisal said, we need somewhere where to store the unwind information.
We're going to look later at how this table looks like.
But first let's see what are the possibilities here.
So one possibility, for example, will be to store the unwind information in process.
We could do this using a combination of P trace, mmap, and mlock.
And this will require us to basically hijack the processes execution, introduce a new memory
mapping inside of them, and then we have to lock the memory because in BPF and in our
type of BPF programs, page faults are not allowed.
The problem with these approaches, of course, will be altering the execution flow of applications,
which is something that we never want to do.
This complicates things a lot.
For example, one of the biggest problems is the life cycle.
So for example, if our profiler dies before we finish cleaning up, who is going to clean
up that memory segment?
Or how is this going to be perceived by developers if they see that the memory of their application
has increased behind their backs just because some observability tool is doing something
that is not great?
But also there's another problem that is sharing memory is harder.
There is same page optimization from the kernel.
But if you don't think about that, it's a problem to have the same information generated
over and over, for example, for libc for every single process in your machine.
So that's why we ended up using another solution, which is pretty typical in the BPF space,
which is using BPF maps.
In case you're not familiar, BPF maps are data structures that can be written or read
from both user and kernel space.
We're using hash tables everywhere, which in the case of BPF, they're basically a mapping
of bytes to bytes that store arbitrary information.
So some BPF maps, some BPF programs as well allow to lazily allocate memory for their
data structures.
But in the case of our tracing program, we cannot do that.
And this has some implications.
So we need to memlock that, well, the kernel, sorry, user space memlocks that memory, and
otherwise our program wouldn't be able to run.
And by using this approach, we are also able to reuse these memory mappings, which is great,
right?
Because that means we don't have to do the same work over and over, and we use less space.
So let's take a look at the logical representation of the unwind tables.
So this is not how the layout is in memory, but think about, for example, the unwind tables
for libc, MySQL, Zlib, and systemd.
How they will be laid out in memory if we could allocate a large chunk of memory.
But in reality, there's limits everywhere, obviously.
And in BPF, we have done some tests.
I mean, the machines that we want, the kernels we want to support, we can allocate up to
25,000 unwind entries per value of the hash map.
So obviously, this was a problem for us, because in some cases, we have some customers that
have applications with unwind tables with three, four million unwind rows, which is
quite ridiculous.
Just to give you an idea, libc, I think, has like 60K entries.
So having a couple million is significant.
But yeah, we came up with the same solution that you would use in any other data-intensive
application, which is to partition or shard the data.
So the way we're doing this is we have multiple entries that are allocated when our profilers
start running.
We allocate a different number, depending on the available memory on the system and
the overhead that you're willing to pay.
And yeah, depending on how many shards you have, you have a different CPU to memory trade-off,
because the more memory you use, it has to be locked in memory.
It can never be swapped out, which is, in some applications, no ideal.
But at the same time, that means that you don't have to regenerate the tables if they
are full, and then you want to give other processes a fair chance to be profiled.
So the way this will work, for example, for a process like systemd is that will be the
representation of the size of its unwind tables.
Because it's bigger than the size of a shard, it will have to be chunked.
So here, we can see how this is chunked in two.
The first chunk will go in the shard zero, and a bunch of the unwind entries from the
tail will go to the shard one.
And of course, because we have this new layer of indirection, we need to somehow keep track
of all this bookkeeping and know what is the state of the world.
We're doing this, of course, with more BVF maps.
So our process has multiple mappings.
Each mapping has one or more chunks.
And then each chunk maps to exactly one shard, and in particular the region within one shard,
because you can have from one unwind entry up to 2050k.
Of course, this has the benefit that I was mentioning before.
That is, because we were sharing the unwind tables, that means that we spend actually
not that many CPU cycles doing all the work that Charlie was mentioning before.
We need to find the elf section where the door of CFI information is, but also we need
to parse, evaluate it.
We have two levels of VM that have to run, which is not something that is very CPU consuming
but still has to happen.
It has to process a bunch of information and generate these unwind tables in our custom
formats.
So by sharing this, for example, LIPST will be shared for all the processes, so that means
that we only need to add the bookkeeping data structures, which are really cheap to generate.
In some of the tests that we've been running, we use less than 0.9% CPU within the total
CPU cycles that our profiler uses to generate the unwind tables.
Of course, there's a lot of things that we need to take into account, like, for example,
what happens if we run out of space, right?
So what we do is we adaptively decide what to do in the moment.
We might wait a little bit until resetting the state, or we might decide to give chance
to other processes to be profiled, so we wipe the whole thing and start again.
As you can see, this is very similar to a Bump allocator.
This is basically a Bump allocator that has been chunked up.
So the process of unwinding this is we start with a PID, we check if it has unwind information,
then we need to find the mapping, and for each mapping, we know the minimum and the
maximum program counter, so we need to do a linear search to find it.
Then we find the chunk.
With the chunk, we already have the shared information, so once we have the shared information,
we have to traverse up to 250,000 items.
We do this with a simple binary search.
This takes between seven or eight iterations.
Once we have the unwind action that tells us how to restore the previous frame registers,
we do those operations and we are ready to go to the next frame.
We are pretty much done for that frame.
If the stack trace is correct, we know this because basically a stack, when you have frame
pointers, the bottom of the stack is defined in applications with frame pointers.
When you reach RBP equals zero, this is defined by the API.
When you have unwind tables, it's defined by not having that program counter cover by
any unwind table and having RBP zero.
This is a requirement by the API, so if some application doesn't respect it, it's completely
broken.
So once we verify that the stack is correct, that we have reached the bottom of the stack,
we hash the addresses and we add the hash to a map and we bump a counter.
We do this, I think it is 19 times a second for every single CPU in your box.
Every couple seconds we collect all this information, we generate a profile, we send it to some
server for inspection.
Of course, BPF is an interesting environment to work with.
It is amazing and we really, really like it.
But we need to be aware of some stuff.
First of all, because we cannot page in or page out pages that contain the unwind tables,
that has to be locked in memory.
We need to be very careful with how we organize our data and the layout of that data to make
it as small as possible.
So we basically pack every single thing that can be packed.
Then there's some interesting BPF things that for most people that have written BPF programs,
this is well known, but I just want to talk a little bit about how we are dealing with
some of the BPF challenges.
So one of these is a stack size which is easy to work around.
If I am not mistaken, we have 512 bytes which is not a lot.
So we use another BPF map that we use sort of a global data structure.
And that stores basically like kind of your heap, if you will.
And then for the program size, this is a limitation that comes in two ways.
First, there's probably some limitation in the amount of how many upcodes you can load
in the kernel, but also the BPF verifier that ensures that the BPF code is safe to load,
for example.
You don't do any dereference that could go wrong or that your program terminates.
It has some limits.
It could theoretically run forever trying to verify your program, but it has some limits.
And we hit this limit everywhere in our code.
For example, we hit it when running our binary search.
It complains, saying that it is too complex for each to analyze.
So what we do here is that not only we have sharded our data, we have sharded our code,
our code and data, the same thing, right?
So we basically have our program split into many subprograms, and we keep the states, and
we basically execute one program after each other and continue the state.
So one of the techniques we use is BPF tail calls.
Two other things that are way more modern and they're amazing too are bounded loops
and BPF loop, which is a wonderful helper.
The problem is that while we use bounded loops right now, we don't use BPF loop because it's
only supported in modern kernels.
But it's great.
If you can use it, you should.
Now because we're a profiler and we want to minimize the impact we have on the machines
we run, I want to talk a little bit about performance in user space.
So many Go applications, well, our profiler is written in Go, and many Go applications
and APIs are in design with performance in mind.
And this is something that can be seen in the dwarf and elf library that Go ships with
in the Sandal library, as well as binary read and binary write that we use everywhere because
we're dealing with raw bytes and we read them and write them all the time to the BPF maps.
So it is interesting to know that both these binary read and binary write low level APIs
actually allocate in the fast path, which can be problematic.
So there's a lot of things that in the future we're going to be reinventing to make faster.
And then we profiler, profiler, alerting, production.
We have found a lot of opportunities and there's a lot more work to do because there's not
much time.
We're going to quickly skip through testing, but the idea here is that we try to be pragmatic
and we have a lot of unit tests for the core functions and then we use snapshot testing
for the unwind tables.
We have a GitHub repository where we have a visual representation of the unwind tables
and then we generate them every time on CI and locally and we verify that there are no
changes compared to last time.
I think there's only like two or three minutes left.
So let me talk about the different environments and some of the interesting stuff that we
have found.
While we were profiling our profiler in production, we realized that we were spending a ridiculous
amount of CPU cycles reading files from disk.
I think the total is just a bunch, a part of the flame graph, but I think in total it
was like 20% of the CPU cycles.
So it turns out this was because our cloud provider has very slow disks that are orders
of magnitude slower than our fast NVMe's in the team.
Another thing that is very interesting that is not a new fact and everybody knows about
is that different configuration is the biggest source of trouble.
And we could see this the other day and if you're interested you can check the pull request.
The whole project is open source which is the interaction between signals and BPF.
What happened basically, Go has an embedded profiler and we use it all in production for
reasons, but it triggers SIGPROF a couple of times a second.
That was interrupting the process execution and at that time our process was booting up
and it was loading our BPF program because it's quite long and complex.
The verifier takes a couple milliseconds to load it, but it was getting interrupted all
the time.
So the BPF whenever it detects that the verifier has been interrupted it retries the process,
basically wasting all the previous CPU cycles because it starts from scratch.
But then it retries up to five times and then it says I couldn't do it and of course when
we can't load a BPF program we are completely useless so we just crash.
There is many other considerations such as what do you do with short leaf processes because
you have to generate metadata.
But even though we have an optimizer for this, we are not that bad and we can profile processes
that run even for one second in your box.
And then the important thing here is that this is our format for our custom at one table
but it doesn't matter.
The important bit here is that it mostly fits in L2 cache so we basically incur on two L2
misses and it is pretty fast.
On a machine with a bunch of processes with up to 90 frames we can do the full and one
processing 0.5 milliseconds.
On a CPU that is five years old.
Cool.
So we are going to do mixing and wind modes.
So being able to unwind JIT sections we are applying RM64 support by the end of the year
and this feature is going to be enabled by default in a few weeks because right now it
is under a feature flag.
We have many other things we want to support including high level languages and we are
open source.
So if you want to contribute or you have anything you want to discuss we meet biweekly on Mondays
as part of the program project.
So there is a bunch of links that we are going to upload to the presentation in the Folsom
website and thank you.