Okay, so we'll start now.
The topic of this presentation is
overview of secure boot state in the ARM-based socks,
and this is the second edition of this presentation.
No mic here. It's only for the video.
Okay, so the first edition was taken place like two years ago.
So now we want to present some update from
the research that we have about two years ago.
Maybe you can speak up a little bit.
Okay.
We can hear you.
Okay. Sorry for some technical issue.
Okay. Sorry for that.
Okay. Okay.
So it is an agenda for this presentation.
So first, I will tell you who I am and where I work.
So say a couple of work was about our company.
Next, I will just present shortly what do you mean by secure boot,
in the case of ARM socks,
and present how the typical implementation and workflow works.
Later, we'll show the results from the fifth edition.
So from the 2028.
Then we will discuss the two cases that we check for this edition.
So the Mediatek and the Rockchip cases.
Next, we will summarize the whole presentation.
So try to look what was difference between those two editions of
the presentation and with some Q&A session.
So this is me.
I'm Tomasz Ziecki and I'm an embedded systems team leader at 3M DEP.
I work there over three years now.
Mostly, I work on the embedded systems built with the Yoctop project.
So I try to integrate the update system and
the OS creation for the embedded devices.
But because I work with the embedded devices,
I try to touch different areas of the whole life of the devices.
So one of the things I work with is also the system security.
This is the topic of this presentation.
So here a couple of words about our company.
We are from Poland and based in Gdańsk.
We are the core book license service providers since 2016.
Also, UFI adopters since 2018, Yoctop participants.
So this is the area which I work with from 2019.
Also, like the consultants for the FWPD project and IBM OpenPower Foundation members.
Okay. So now, let's explain this.
What do you mean by the secure boot in the context of this presentation?
So here we are focused on the ARM context,
which is like the feature of the Boot Room.
One of the features that Boot Room has.
Maybe we should call it more like the verified boot because the case here is
that when we start the firmware,
the next steps of the loaded images are like verified.
The signature is verified by the previous part of the firmware.
So that's why we should call it the verified boot maybe.
So we need to use some private key to sign the binary that we put into our machine.
Then we also need to take the public key from that private key and put it also there.
So when we start it,
we'll be able to verify the signature and decide if
it should be loaded or not.
In ARM context,
we assume that the Boot Room is our root of trust.
We need to take that assumption because most of them are closed source.
Probably it will be better if they will be open source,
but it is what it is.
Basically, the meaning of the secure boot can be
different for any given architecture.
So if you will be talking about the x86,
that would be a different scenario.
So this is the typical implementation.
We have the public key that needs to be written inside our SOC.
Different vendors will have
some different way to achieve that.
So we can, for example, fuse them using electrical fuse.
So one time write them in our SOC and
later use it every time that we start our firmware.
There's also a possibility for the OTP registers.
So those are the one-time programmable.
So as the name says,
also it can be used only one time.
One of those two possibilities
allow us to make from our Boot Room our root of trust,
which we later use to expand it to the chain of trust.
Next components can use like different keys.
So in case of secure boot,
we talk about the step between the Boot Room and the Boot Loader.
Here we have some one key that was used to sign
the binary and that public key that was used to verify it.
But the later steps of starting our machine can use different keys.
So that will be it.
So typically we have like,
let's say our host machine that
should be some secure location and our target device.
So on our host machine,
we generate some private keys,
rebuild binary, and use specific tool to sign them.
Later, we need to take the public key part of that keys,
also the sign as binary and put it in the target device,
and then try to verify it.
Yes. So if the verification will be successful,
then we will just boot another step.
If not, then specific things can happen
depends on the vendor that we are using.
Also, let's say maybe a couple of works
about what it is to sign the binary.
Basically, what is common between all the vendors probably is
that a sign-in binary means that we take
the original binary and add some header on top of it.
This header contain the digital signature
and also some specific format at this type,
which can be different across some vendors or can be
also different within one vendor.
But when we are using different signing tools,
so if we try to sign our binary,
we can always try to dump the few couple of bytes of
our signed image and check if everything goes as expected.
This is a quick recap from the last edition.
So we look at the 11 cases,
five of them like the NXP, IMX,
and Lirescape, STSTM,
and V
looks like fully open-sourced, let's say.
There was non-NDA problems with them,
so everyone could try to take the documentation
that needed fusing and signing tools,
and try to implement the secure boot on them.
We have couple of cases where there are information that
there is some secure boot to enable on that given machine,
but it is under the NDA.
So we're talking here about the Marvel Armada,
Texas Instruments, CITARA, Qualcomm, and Microchips.
Also, we talk about two folks from
the Chinese vendors like Rockship and Alwino,
where some documentation was there,
another was missing.
Also, there were some information about tools,
but we were not able to find them or maybe use them correctly.
So now, I will go through three or four vendors
that were listed from the last edition,
and talk about the differences
that was between those three years.
So now, let's start from the NXP.
In this case, I think this is
the easiest way to start with the secure boot on the Arm socks,
because the full documentation is there.
All documentation is probably like,
all documentation is publicly available,
so everyone can use it.
We have the hub for four,
so the high assurance boot mechanism
on the platforms that are the NXP IMX 50, 53,
6, 7, and 8M.
The application note is here.
The only difference between here and there is
that those applications are under the free registration to the site.
The same is for the IMX 8 and IMX 8X,
which uses the A-HAB mechanism,
so advanced high assurance boot.
The same for COIC-Q, and as you see here,
the signing tool are available after the free registration.
For Marvel Armada, we can look at
the manuals that are available on the sites.
We saw that for the 3D8 and 3D9X families,
we have some information that NDA is needed.
For other families like, I believe 8K,
there is only information that there is
a secure boot available but nothing else there.
At the last edition,
we present that in the U-Boot repositories,
we can find some information about how to implement
the secure boot on the Marvel Armada. But now, it is not there.
It is only on all the releases.
So this is another difficult step that need to be taken to
find those informations.
But yeah, if you will just use this from the 2018 branch,
we'll see the information how to implement the secure boot.
But yeah, still this is only the theoretical knowledge and
there's no step-by-step solution how to achieve that.
So probably, this I won't throw mistakes.
In video taglia, another quick update.
Last time, we saw that there are
some documentations and tools available.
We checked that within last year and it looks like,
the documentation is some kind of uncertain because in one point,
it tells that the secure boot is available and they also
provides the flashing tools,
the script called FlashSH.
But in the other place,
they just say that the secure boot will be available in the future.
Nobody exactly know when the future will be.
But yeah, that will be it.
Also about fusing, there's additional script for that.
But documentation of it is also some kind of updated.
There's also one thread in the form of
Nvidia where someone tried to use it to
fuse keys on its platform and it caused the platform to break.
Because it looks like not every board can be fused and before we execute that,
we just need to check the serial numbers
because some of them are supported some not.
Also update on Alwina.
So still, we think that there's
no official documentation about the Alwina socks
with which would tell us about the secure boot and
also no official documentation about secure boot itself.
But we found some interesting case on the forum where someone was able to
use the NanoPioneer with Alwina H3.
He there provides all the useful links,
there's like 10 or 15 of them,
or also the whole list of the verification process.
With the link to the Sanxi Tools repository,
which contains some tools which need to be used in order to find the binaries,
and also fuse the sock.
The one vulnerability though is that in any case when we,
oh sorry, yeah, the one vulnerability is here that if we try to
start our firmware which is signed and the verification fails,
the platform always goes to the cell mode,
which is some kind like the debit mode.
This debit mode can be accessed via the USB port.
So if the verification fails,
someone could always plug in the USB,
start some MeCom and then read everything from the fuses or maybe even wipe them.
So the solution there for that was just to destroy
the data lines on that given port.
So even if the platform goes into the cell mode,
no one will be able to just read anything from it.
Okay, so now the media tech case.
Documentation is provided on the GitLab pages.
It is based on the Yocto project like project.
So the steps there needs to be done inside
the Yocto project build system to achieve
the signing to achieve the implementing the secure boot.
But basically, as in other ARM socks,
the boot run there is like the root of trust.
Later, we just achieve it using other mechanism to have the whole chain of trust.
So after secure boot,
we have the TFA trusted board boot,
and then we can use the U-Boot feed verified boot to load our kernel image.
So if we have all those steps, then we have whole boot process verified.
Yeah, and it also was shown in a couple of reports,
that the media tech boot run has some vulnerability,
which if we power it in some special scenario,
then the boot run may just skip the process of verification the image and still load the firmware.
So it looks like even if we have the public key in the fuses and
also the public key in the fuses,
and we provide the unsigned image and use this vulnerability,
we will be still able to boot our platform.
This is a short recap how the secure boot looks on the media tech.
So we have the BL1 step,
which is like the boot run,
which loads the hash based on the root of trust public key.
So this is the public key that we put in the fuses.
And calculates also the sha of the signatures of the BL2.
So this is like the next step loaded.
After that, we compare those two values and if everything is okay,
we go next and the same.
Yeah, and then we load the signature from the BL2,
and also calculate the sha of it,
made the comparison and if everything is once again is okay,
we boot the next steps.
And here's the process of enabling the secure boot.
It is not clear from the documentation on which socks the secure boot can be enabled.
The documentation mentioned the MT-8365 and MT-8395 ones.
Different socks may have different FUS indexes.
So it isn't really like we need to check those before we try to fuse our fuses in those socks.
But unfortunately, those information is provided with NDA.
In the process of enabling the secure boot,
we need to create two keys, private keys and provide them to our build system,
which find the BL2 load firmware and also something called the download agent,
which is later used by additional proprietary tools to flush the image inside our platform.
Which is also described like here, so we have the FUS writer tool.
This is another tool provided with the NDA only,
which can be used to check the secure boot state on our platform
and check if the download agent authentication bits are set.
If they are not set, we just need to set them and then provide the public key
which will be fused on the key hash zero field.
And after that, we will just sign our firmware and use this public key to verify it.
Okay, so now let's go to the Rokchips case.
The public key here can be stored in a fuses in the OTP
and it depends on which sock we are using.
If the verification of loaded binary will be successful,
then we'll just extend our Rokchips stuff,
so the bootgum as in the other ARM core socks to the chain of trust.
And later, in case of Rokchips,
we can use the fit verified boot mechanism from the SPL to the U-Boot
and from the U-Boot to kernel to provide the whole chain of trust.
So basically, to establish it, we need to like once again
generate some private and public key file,
burn the key public key into the fuses OTP registers,
depends on which sock we are using.
Then sign our firmware called edb-loaded image in case of Rokchips,
which is like the U-Boot TPL plus SPL merge into one file.
Then configure verified boot in SPL and U-Boot,
which means that we will use the fit images to verify it from the SPL to U-Boot
and from the U-Boot to kernel and just flush our signed images.
Documentation for Rokchips and for our winner is like hard to find.
And if we find any, probably it will be outdated or really short
or just not such useful at fifth.
So here we have diagram of finding the whole of enabling the secure boot.
But basically, it is something I just described on the previous slide.
And sorry for that, but because of time,
we'll go just need to skip description of it.
And now we can talk about signing code in Rokchips.
So code can be signed using one of the two tools,
the Erika-signed tool, which can be started on Linux,
or secure boot tool, which can be started on Windows.
Linux tools can be found on the Erika-bin repository.
Windows tools was a couple days ago, a couple days.
Some time ago was on the repository called calls tools,
but now we are not able to find it.
For some reasons, the Rokchips based repositories
are maintained in such way that some things may be missing after some time.
But if you use the Erika-signed tool, we can just generate the signing keys.
And those keys can be used later with the Linux or Windows tools.
And also the Erika repository provides the INI files,
which are the files that can be used to create the INI mini loader,
used later to fuse our keys in the firmware.
And basically any given firmware that we want to sign and use in our socks
can be also signed with those two tools.
There is another tool just to bind the effuses.
And we have for that the effuse tool, which is only for the Windows machines.
It turns out that when we bind the effuses on the Rokchips socks,
we also need to provide the voltage for one of the pins of the sock.
So it is not visible here, but there should be like faucc, faucc, faue, effuse pin,
which needs to be powered up when we want to fuse the keys in our sock.
So for that we need to find some pin that is there and provide the power by ourselves.
Or maybe our platform has some special circuit just to enable that.
Also this information comes from another documentation that I have to find.
This is a summarize of enable the secure boot.
So we need to create loader using the boot merger script that is in the Erika bin repository.
Next we create the keys with Erika sign tool.
Next we need to sign the loader with secure boot tool because from what we know now,
only sign it with that tool binaries can be later used on our socks.
We try to sign with the Erika sign tool and it doesn't work.
And now it looks like this can be hard to achieve
because there is no way to download the secure boot tool from what we know now.
Then we need to use the effuse tool to fuse our public key in socks
and use another tool called the Erika develop tool,
which is in the Erika bin repository just to load the sign net loader into our platform
and had secure boot enabled.
Here's a link for the blog post which describes all of that containing all of that
what we've done with the workship platforms.
So this is the summarize of where we are after the second edition.
The changes are here about the NXP platforms where it looks like we now need to register
to get the socks reference documentation.
The Nvidia Tegra looks like the documentation is uncertain and may be outdated.
The workship one we know now that it can be achieved,
but still the documentation is not the best quality.
The same with the all winner.
And for the media tech, we see that NDA is needed to achieve the secure boot.
So this is the summary of the presentation.
Looks like our knowledge is expanded over the last two years.
We, for example, know now how to enable the secure boot on the workship.
Still the general principles is common for all the vendors.
So we want to authenticate image before we load it.
We have some private key to sign the firmware.
We need to fuse the public key inside the sock.
And the boot room is still fitting as the root of trust.
All cases use the SHA-2456 as a hash function for digital signatures.
And we see that more and more cases the documentation is
under the NDA or the quality of it is really not the best.
Okay, here's the way of how you can contact us.
And thank you for that presentation.
I think we are a little after time.
Maybe one question if there is any.
Okay.
Yes?
The question is about in NXP secure boot.
You have a possibility to use ROM in your bootloader to check the fiber block.
So you can use the secure boot of NXP for more components like fit and
you bought and so on.
Do you know if any of those new or the chips you have analyzed other platforms
have similar things but you can call the ROM and use it as a root for trust.
Okay.
So the question was that the NXP provides the possibility to use the boot
run to verify other parts of the firmware loaded in the whole process.
And the question is if other vendors also provide such things.
From what we know, this is only like the NXP case.
And yeah, basically that's the answer.
And yeah, maybe this one.
How is given that you analyzed so many vendors,
how is the support among the vendors for different types of key with different
trust boundaries like the delegation key for like some facility like the production in Asia.
Then you would revoke that key using your own back levels and use cases like this.
Okay.
So the question was, I believe, if we try to somehow,
if there are any process to in order to change the key used to find the female.
Yes.
Or to have multiple keys like you would hand out one key.
Okay.
To have like multiple keys to one person and to another team, to another company,
maybe even later revoke it.
I believe that this will be depends on if we have some mechanism in our socks to provide
more than one public key.
Yeah.
But as we said, those are one time only flashed in the socks.
So if there is only one place, then I think that it will be only one,
the private key used later for the verification.
Okay.
Thank you.