So, the thing about QuestDB, apart from being open source, we want people to know us because
we try to be very performant, but specifically in small machines.
Like perform very well in 120 CPUs and 200 gigs of RAM.
It's okay.
Performing very well in 4 CPUs and 16 of RAM, 16 gigs, is more difficult.
So we try to optimize for that.
Actually in the past we were optimizing for the larger instance use case and then we realized
not everybody has a super large instance at home.
We try to be better at that.
We also try to be very good with developer experience that you get performance out of
the box.
There are many things you can tweak in QuestDB.
In every other database, every other system, a lot of configuration.
The memory, page size, the buffers and whatnot, with CPUs, the what, blah, blah, blah, blah.
By default, if you don't touch anything, we should perform well.
And then if you have expert tolerance, you might fine tune.
But we try hard to make developer experience simple and that's why we choose SQL also for
querying data.
So another time series database make the tradeoff.
We want to perform.
We need to use a different language, which is cool because, you know, I get it.
We choose SQL because we want developers to have an easy way learning QuestDB.
For ingesting data, you can use SQL but we also offer a different protocol which is faster.
That's why we have library so you don't have to go low level to be performant.
But that's the idea.
And we are open source, very proud about being open source.
But why we are building another database?
There are a lot of databases.
If you walk around, you're going to read about every type of database out there.
Just today here, I saw MongoDB, I saw Clickhouse.
There's a SQL about MariaDB.
Why you need another database?
Another open source database?
Because different data look different and can have different problems.
And in our case, we are specialized on time series.
We don't do anything else.
I mean, if you try to use QuestDB for full text analytics, we are truly the worst database
ever for that.
If you try to use QuestDB for geospatial queries, we support some geospatial things kind of
a bit.
We have a specific data type about geohasses.
So we have a type about that.
But we are not good for geospatial unless it is part of time series plus geo.
That's kind of the idea.
And we specialize only on time series analytics, on data which is changing over time and you
want to monitor and track those changes.
That's the idea.
We are not good for anything else.
If you try to use QuestDB for everything, boy, what a disappointment we are going to be.
But if you try for time series database, this will be one of the good ones.
That's kind of the idea.
And that's why we are building QuestDB because there are a lot of time series data out there.
And how do you know if you have a time series stolen?
I have here a lot of things.
I want to just read a couple of them.
But basically, if most of the time you are reading data on a slice of time, tell me which
energy consumption I have over the last minute.
Tell me how is the nuclear reactor doing in the past 10 microseconds.
Tell me what is the conversion for this user in the past week.
Let me know for all the data I have a moving vehicle, which was the last position I saw
it and what was the sensor in this particular point in time.
So if you have that, time series can be interesting.
Also with time series you have other types of tolerance.
Data tends to be inserting faster than it reads.
Databases, historically, have been optimized for reads.
They try every trick in the book for making reads super fast.
When you insert data, you need to define indexes.
And they are going to index by many different things.
And they keep caching memory for a lot of things and blah, blah, blah, blah.
So reading is the key thing.
Because usually you read data much more than you write.
Not so intense databases.
We can support heavy reads on top of that.
But we need to support heavy inserts and keep perform of that.
We don't use indexes.
The performance we see today is with no indexes.
We don't need them.
We don't want them.
Because having an index slows down ingestion.
It's a luxury we cannot have.
So we have some kind of indexing, but we don't have indexes.
Not as you know them.
That's kind of the idea here.
So it's slightly different.
And when you have data that you are writing very often, that data is going to grow.
And it can grow fast.
And you need to have some way of loading or deleting that data.
On a traditional database, you just don't say, oh, I have, I don't know, I'm Amazon.
And I'm getting users.
It's like, oh, I already have a million users.
A million won.
I'm going to delay the old users.
But you don't do that.
I mean, sometimes you do.
You don't really do that on your databases.
On time series database, almost all of them have some mechanism to deal with historical
data and do something with that.
In our case, you can mount partitions.
You can mount to cheaper storage.
Those kind of things.
But we have the command Sunday.
It is designed for that kind of thing.
That kind of area.
Many other things about how you have a time series stolen.
But that kind of the area.
But better than me just telling you, I'm going to show you some queries on top of demo data
sets.
So you get the feeling of what a time series database might be interesting.
And then we'll go into details about the ingesting data and about all those things.
Does that sound good so far?
Yeah.
Do you have any questions?
I'm happy to take them during the talk, by the way.
Not only at the end.
So we have a live demo.
Demo.questdb.io.
This is running on a large machine on AWS.
We don't need all the power.
But since it's open to the public.
And here we have a few different data sets.
That is one.
You are in a big data room.
So you're truly familiar with the taxi rides.
New York City taxi rides data set.
It's the city of New York has a data set which is very cool for machine learning and for
big data.
Which is taxi rides in the city of New York.
And the rides started when it finished.
Also the coordinate and a few things.
Like the tip and the amount of the fur.
How many people blah blah blah.
So we took that open data set and we just put it here on QuestDB.
A few years of the data set.
Yes, you know.
Lot of columns here.
So let me just show you how big this is.
This is right now.
Is the size okay?
Maybe not.
So it's 1.6 billion rows.
Which is not huge.
I mean if you have a relational database, 1.6 billion rows.
Relational databases today they are great.
But 1.6 billion rows is like yeah, I couldn't work with that.
I'm not super comfortable.
For us it's cute.
It's like it's a data set which is respectable but not really cute.
But 1.6 billion rows.
So now what if I want to do something like for example, I don't know.
I want to calculate the average of whichever, this for example.
This number.
I want to average the fair amount over 1.6 billion trips.
How long do you expect your database to take to go do a full scan over
1.6 billion rows and compute the average?
No indexes, no anything.
How long would you say?
More or less.
Ball park.
1.6 billion rows.
No one?
Sorry?
How is the size in gigabytes?
Megabytes.
I don't know for the whole data set but this is a double.
I mean I'm really just no.
It's big.
When you download the CSV, it's about 600 megabytes and you have several of those.
This is in the, you know, it's laggish.
But anyway.
Well, actually it was slower than I thought.
It took, usually it takes half a second.
This time it took 0.6 seconds.
I know it's slow.
I know but this was a reason.
Sorry about that.
But I told you, I told you we are a time series database.
We are super slow for other things.
This is not a time series query.
Did you see any time stamp here?
I didn't see anything.
This is just a full scan.
We parallelize.
We read data and we are slow.
We take almost over half a second to go over only 1.6 billion rows.
Unforgivable.
Sorry about that.
But there will be here.
No, that's okay.
I mean I'm kind of half kidding but not really.
But wait until I put a time dimension.
Now yes.
I want only, for example, I want only one year of data.
I'm going to just also add another computation because I know that person.
It's just counting data which is super fast.
So I'm going to add another computation.
So I'm going to count the data and only for 2016.
And this is better.
This is already 100 milliseconds because we are going only over a few rows.
We are going only about...
Yeah, it's only 146 million rows.
This is much more manageable.
So only 140 million rows.
That's better.
So we can go actually very fast on this.
And then if you keep going down, oh no, I want only one month of data which is, I don't
know, still, yeah, 12 million rows.
So a month of data is 60 milliseconds.
For one day of data, of course, is way faster.
This is already 50 milliseconds.
If I go to one specific hour and minute, it will be, you know, kind of not much faster
because...
What?
It's under one millisecond.
Oh yeah, it's under one millisecond actually.
Thank you for that.
But still, like, you know, we have partitions.
So basically, one thing we do, we only go to the partition where the data is stored.
So we only attack that part of the data.
But that's another thing.
For when you have like that time component, we are quite fast, or fairly fast.
That's kind of the beauty for a time series database.
And we can do also interesting, other interesting things.
If I go to the same table and I saw you, what this looked like, you can see that for the
same second, I have many trips because this is New York baby.
And in New York, you know, the city that never leaves.
You can't get back in every corner.
You get rich when you land in New York.
I spent one year there.
It's not like that.
Anyway, so in every particular second, even at midnight, you have always a few trips,
at least.
Okay?
So actually, you could do that.
You could do something like, I want to know the, I want to, if I want to do something
like give me the daytime on how many trips are ending where this daytime is in, for example,
June 21st.
Siri, what are you doing there, man?
I didn't even know I had Siri here.
Okay.
So, I don't know.
For example, in this particular minute, in one particular day, I want to sample in one
second interval and know how many trips I have for every particular second.
So that's another thing you can do in a time series database.
Rather than grouping by columns that you can also do, you can group by time.
You call the sample by.
So we can sample by any, we go from microsecond to year, I guess.
Yeah, microsecond to year.
So you can group by microsecond, millisecond, second, year, day, whatever.
So in this case, I'm saying, okay, in this particular second, I have six trips and five
trips and blah, blah, blah.
You get there, yeah?
So something I wanted to show you, which is another cool one, it's, I have this data set
with several trips every second.
I have another data set also with data from Manhattan is the weather data set.
So maybe it could be interesting to know, to join those two data sets.
It will be cool to know the weather that they had for a particular trip, because maybe that
gives me some insight.
I don't know.
The challenge is this data set, of course, is real life.
It's a different open data set.
It's not at the same resolution.
We don't have weather changes every second.
In my hometown, sometimes that happens.
And when I was living in London, that was crazy.
But in real life, we don't measure, we don't store weather changes every second.
In this particular data set, we have about two or three records every hour.
So now if I want to join a data set with subsecond resolution, a data set with subhour resolution,
and I want to do a join, if I want to do it in other databases, I could do it.
It will take me a while.
Then I will think I have it, and I wouldn't.
And then it will be like, yeah, this makes sense or not really.
And a week later, I will be crying.
I don't know that.
So I still know.
So one thing we have here, we have a demo set, some example points.
I'm going to move on to another thing really quickly, because otherwise.
But this one I really like, we have a special type of join, which we call an as of join,
which basically does this.
I'm going to select the data from the table I told you already for one particular day
in time.
And then I'm going to do what we call an as of join, which basically says, this table
has a timestamp.
We call it the designated timestamp.
You decide which is the column.
You have several.
So we have the designated timestamp in one.
The timestamp in the other joined by the ones that are closer to each other.
In this case, as of means the one which is exactly the same or immediately before me,
the one which is closer to me.
So what happened before we have also the one strictly behind me before me cannot be the
same.
But that's the idea.
So in this case, for getting to different data sets, I can just do that.
Also, I want to add here the timestamp for the other table.
So it's clear.
So if I run this query, now here I can see for each record on the New York taxi rides,
I'm always getting the same timestamp in the weather data set, because I have only one
entry every 40 or 45 minutes.
If I move to a different point in the day to this day, but instead of at 12, at 1255,
for example, I should see already that I'm matching to a different entry on this table.
So that's it.
I have different resolutions.
I don't care which one we joined by time, because we're about time.
That's kind of the idea.
That's what I think is I have more interesting queries, but maybe for a different date.
So that's the first thing.
So I told you, okay, now you get the idea why tensile is coming to the extent that kind
of things we can do down sampling, all those things in machine learning is very important.
You have data maybe every second, and then you want to do a forecasting and doesn't make
sense to train a model with every second data.
In many cases, maybe you want to down sample to 15 minutes interval with this trick, you
can do it easily.
So that's kind of the idea.
But I was speaking about ingesting data.
So ingesting over 1 million times three years per second on a single instance.
It's interesting.
But ingesting over 1 million records per second, a single instance, it's easy, actually.
I could just write to a file appending lines, and that will be it.
The interesting bit is actually being able to ingest data while you are able to put it
in real time, the same data you're ingesting.
That's the trick.
Because you're ingesting, I mean, you put it there, and you're like, why ingesting 1
million records?
When you think about this, like, well, wait, but how long do I have to wait to put in the
data?
So the idea is you can put in the data at the same time.
All benchmarks are lies, of course, on the same benchmark that I want to tell you, other
people will tell you the contrary, and I'm totally fine with that.
A couple of years ago, we published an article saying, hey, we can ingest now at 1.4 million.
The slides are linked already on the first page, by the way.
Thank you.
So our CTO posted about how we were ingesting 1.4 million records per second.
These records were, they had like 20 columns, 10 dimensions, 10 strings, and 10 metrics,
10 numbers.
We're pulling guest records of 20 columns with 10 strings and 10 numbers, 1.4 million
records per second, while running queries, which is the other bit.
So we were able to scan over 4 million, 4 billion records per second, at the same time,
in relatively small machines, relatively small.
So that's kind of the idea.
And these benchmarks, we didn't write it.
There is a benchmark specifically for time series databases.
As I told you earlier, if you load data in QuestDB, you can load relational data into
QuestDB, and you can run queries.
If you try to run a conventional benchmark on QuestDB, it's going to be super slow.
We are not designed for full-text search.
We are not designed for just operations within individual records or doing updating data.
We are not designed for that.
We can do it, but we are not designed for that.
So there is also the other time series databases.
So InfluxDB, another open source database, created this benchmark, the TSVS benchmark,
which is specifically about time series databases.
So the queries and the ingestion patterns matches what you would expect from a time
series database.
Now it's maintained by time scale, which is another open source database on top of Postgres.
And we have our own, you know, the recent adapter for running that on top of QuestDB.
And with that benchmark, it's with the one that we are getting those results.
So with that particular benchmark is the one giving the results.
So you know, your management might vary also depending on the hardware.
If you try to run the benchmark in the cloud, it's going to be slower, always.
Because in the cloud, by default, you use on AWS, you use CVS, on well cloud, you use
the attached storage, it's networking storage, has on latency, because they are not local
disk.
They are super cool, but they are not local.
It's going to be always slower.
You want to get this on Google Cloud or AWS, you can do it, you have to use NVMe disk,
which are local disk without attached to the instance, but they disappear when they when
you close the instance.
But with those disks, you will be getting the same benchmark.
So hardware is also important with the benchmark.
But that's the idea, you know, that that's how how we did it.
Before I tell you a bit about the technical decisions that they will not have super time,
but I want to show you how we are doing this ingestion.
So let me ask if I can move this out of the way.
So this is a scraping go.
I don't know any go at all.
But I know to run this so you know, and I don't want to advocate.
I mean, I couldn't tell you that I know a lot of go but I have no idea.
So go long, it's a language.
So yeah, we have our it's pretty cool.
So we have this library or package or whatever they call it in go, which is our official
package.
Caro, whatever.
I don't know.
So this is I'm missing languages here.
Anyway, it's not that happy.
Thank you.
So yeah, this is our theme.
I'm connecting to local host to the default port in QuestDB.
I'm going to be simulating data.
So I'm simulating IoT data.
And I'm going to be putting a device type which can be red or blue or green or yellow.
I'm going to be outputting duration, latitude, longitude, speed, and time stamping nanoseconds.
And I'm going to do this in chunks of in batches of 50,000 records.
I want to do this 200 times.
50,000 records 200 times, 10 million records.
I want to be inserting 10 million records on a database on a table that does not exist.
QuestDB will create it automatically when it starts saving data.
So if I run this is scraping go, which you run doing go run, well, don't go.
So go run is ingesting data, it should take less than 10 seconds because we are guessing
10 million.
And that's finished.
So let me just go to my local host here.
Let me just sell it.
Sell it.
How many records did we ingest it for?
I have to refresh the tables.
Okay.
How many records I ingested 10 million records.
That's good.
Can you tell me the terrible so I can see what happened here.
Sample by one second.
And he's telling me, yeah, you know, in the first second, only half a million because
we we didn't start it at the top of the second.
It was totally at second or something.
But after that, 1 million, 1 million, 1 million.
Hey, you see, you see the idea.
Okay, that's not too bad.
I can do this slightly better.
I can run this script actually twice ingesting in the same instant to two different tables.
So now if I refresh, I should see I have two tables, not only one.
So I have two tables here, same hardware and everything.
If I run again, I'm going to select only the last 10 rows.
So we only see the latest run.
So you can see it's lower now, I was actually ingesting to two tables, selling guest in
only 700,000 per second, something like that.
But if I go to the same time to the other table, I can just do a union.
If I go to the table here, you should see that at the same time in the yeah, I cannot
apply limit here.
Sorry.
I can't apply the union, so I should see that, you know, even if I was going to slower, the
other table was reading data.
And in this format, you cannot see it very well.
But we can do something I told you earlier, I can just rather than do a join, I can just
do something like as of join the first query with the second.
So I should be able to do this.
Now I have in the first run, we were running only one instance of sending data.
And this one is the one in which I was running to.
So you can see for this particular second, we were ingesting 700,000 records in one,
700,000 records in the other same time.
So about 1.4 something million in total, because we're in different tables out of the box.
If I configure the writers and how many threads I have for processing things, I can get it
slightly faster than this.
But that's good enough.
On a local M1 laptop, SSD, it's fast.
But that's the idea.
So that's the one million there.
I wasn't lying.
I was just telling you things.
I have only a few minutes, but that's cool.
How we got here?
First, we can do a lot of essentials about the data.
This is time serious.
So we know people usually want to get not individual rows, but computations of a rows.
We know people mostly want to group by things that are in the data, like a string, like
the country name or the device name or the brand or whatever.
So instead of storing strings, we have a special symbol, which is called a special type, which
is called a symbol.
If you give me a string, we convert into a number and we do look up automatically those
things.
So we make a lot of assumptions because we hyper-specialize on one particular use case.
We optimize the storage.
We don't use indexes because we store everything always in incremental order per partition.
If we get data out of order, we have to regrade the partitions, but we don't need indexes because
we always have the data physically in order so we can scan super quickly back and forth.
That's kind of the idea.
We also parallelize as much as we can using different things.
This is written in Java, and it's from scratch.
You will see some databases, which I love, like MongoDB, excellent device for content.
They have a time series module.
We use the same MongoDB collections for doing time series.
They cannot be as fast because they are using exactly what they are using for content.
It's very convenient.
I can do everything, but same thing with all the engines that are building on top of other
things.
We don't have any dependencies.
Everything is built for scratch.
Usually we are writing some of the libraries in Java, like strings and loggers and so on,
to avoid conversions.
There are things that we don't use, so we don't use them.
We have libraries for rings.
We have libraries for memory management.
We have libraries for absolutely everything, drag-written in our own version.
We have our own Just-In-Time compiler because the original Just-In-Time compiler in Java
was not performing enough for some of the parallelization in what it wanted to do.
We wrote everything.
Our Java is kind of weird.
Jeremy can tell you more about that.
It's super weird Java, but it's still Java.
That's kind of the idea.
We even wrote our own input output functions.
That's kind of a thing.
Why?
Because we can get nanoseconds faster.
This is log4j.
Log4j.
We don't speak about log4j, which is awesome.
This is log4j.
This is the nanoseconds, the operations you can do in each nanosecond.
With log4j, log in, integer, you can do 82 operations per nanosecond.
We can do 800 operations per nanosecond, which is, do you have to go down to the nanosecond?
If you are doing a crude application, probably not.
It really depends what you are building.
That's kind of why we are writing things from scratch.
Basically the approach of QSDBT performance, you know, this is like, I don't know who you
are, but I don't know you, but I will find you and I will kill you.
That's kind of the same approach I see on QSDBT.
They are like, I don't know, we are so we can get faster at some obscure thing here.
That's kind of the idea.
We try to be a good team player.
Jeremy here has contributed himself only alone.
The connectors for Kafka Connect, connectors for Apache Flink.
So we try to integrate with the rest of the ecosystem.
We love it if you try QSDBT.
You are open source geeks.
You like GitHub stars.
We like GitHub stars.
Please contribute.
Please start on GitHub if you like it.
We have a contributor Slack channel.
We are quite friendly.
We are fast.
We work with interesting problems.
If you like interesting problems, if you like weird Java, we would love to have you here.
So thank you very much.
I can't take any questions outside.
One question from the chat.
Thank you.
Someone is asking if QSDBT can work with GPS data.
Yes, you can work with GPS data.
We have double.
You can use for that.
We don't have a lot of geospatial functions.
We have geohashes which basically allow you to define in which a different resolution
in which a square in the world something is.
So if you're telling us about finding where a point is in the world, a particular point
in time, QSDBT is very cool.
If you need to do other things with support on Mac libraries, COS and all those things
to do your own calculations.
But yeah, it can be used for GPS.
Some people are doing asset tracking with QSDBT.
Thank you.
Mr.