So today I want to talk a little bit about Change Data Capture, CDC, street processing,
with the magic plane.
This talk is split into three parts.
The first part is for people that have never heard of the plane before.
The second part is maybe a little bit more deeper than the plane SBL, like SIPO.
And then the third part, we could dive really, really deep into Under the Hood.
So, we're going to go through a little bit of the
introduction, but just to summarize it.
So from the open source side, part of the plane before became part of the Apache Sofa Foundation,
2014, I'm a member of the management committee of Apache Flink.
Over the years I also made it to the top one contributors.
According to the additions in top one, I don't know which refactoring I did to become a top
one contributor.
And among the core people that try to design SIPO every day and evolve SIPO.
Can we revise?
Yeah.
I went through a couple of companies.
The latest one was a co-founder, was in Meroc, and they were acquired by Confl and the beginning
of this year.
And now I'm a principal software engineer at Confl.
So, let's talk about SIPO.
Before I start with an introduction to Flink, I would actually like to talk about stream
processing in general.
Because when you do stream processing, you basically always can identify roughly four
building blocks.
So, let's talk about those building blocks first.
So, first of all, you need streams, right?
You want to handle data.
You maybe want to create some pipeline from source to sink.
You might want to distribute your streams because you have a lot of data.
So, maybe it wants to be allowed, it's really independent of the load.
You want to join streams together.
You want to enrich streams.
Maybe there is a control stream and the main stream.
You want to dynamically modify the behavior of the application while the application is
running.
Sometimes there is a bug in your application or you just want to trace certain behavior
then you also want to be in place.
Time, working with time is also a very, very important concept because on one side you
want to make progress in your pipeline.
But at some points you also want to synchronize.
So, if you have two streams, maybe you want to wait for the other stream.
Maybe you want to log or you want to buffer some of the streams.
Maybe if the second event doesn't come in, you want to time out after some time.
Maybe you also want to replay historical data.
So, you want to fast forward at the time.
You don't want to wait another hour to find an hour window.
No, this should be quicker.
Then when we talk about offering, what I just said, or in general storing data, state is
a very important component in stream processing.
State can be, for example, a machine learning model that is updated from time to time to
classify your incoming streams.
It can be cached if you don't want to look up in the database for every record that comes
in, in a general state, and it can be more and more terrified.
And also at some point it needs to expire.
If you have a state with a streaming application that is very useful and comfortable,
I actually make sure that I can create this natural of money for streaming.
So, I want to say thank you for this streaming application.
I want to make it version it so every night I want to create a short version.
Maybe I want to form my streaming application in a staging class, in general, in a cluster,
and play around with data on the state.
Maybe I want to do some testing or I want to put time to record this part in my application.
So, let's talk a little bit about what makes a link unique compared to other competitors.
First of all, what I just showed is that a link is one of the best stream processors
for all of these use cases and building blocks.
So, when you design a streaming application, you can start with a whiteboard and you just
draw some circles.
What do you actually want to do?
Maybe you want to read from some sources.
Maybe you want to normalize your data.
You want to filter some data out.
You want to join the data and in the end you want to sync it somewhere else.
This is how it starts.
This is also how you have to reason about when you're creating a pipeline.
And what a link does under the hood is it has a parallelism and scalability built in.
So, you don't have to think of threading or network transfers or anything like that.
Under the hood there are sharks, there are petitions depending on the connectors.
There are sub-tasks that in parallel execute operations.
Each of these tasks, or some of these tasks, can stay cool and have some little storage
local to the operator.
Very important.
So, the state basically scales out and scales in with the operator.
You don't need to query to a database which would increase the status.
And then, of course, you have troubles and then the whole pipeline runs.
And now comes the important part.
What we expect really unique is that this possibility of creating a consistent snapshot
of your entire stream of topology.
So, there are networking object points and barriers which are traveling through the topology
and make a backup of each state of operator.
And then this snapshot is then persisted on a long-term to storage like S3 or HVFS or
some other industry devices.
When we talk about use cases, there are plenty of use cases.
We have process detections, logs, IOTs, any kind of events, user interactions,
people using the filter of raw detection for machine learning, for event driven applications,
for ETL, for data integration, for analytics.
So, things has become over the last 10 years, it has become like a very large platform.
You can connect various connectors from various systems and read and write files, databases,
the key value source, and it's also like event driven applications where maybe you want to send out an email
or don't connect to it.
You can also implement something custom that talks to some rest API as well as this is seen.
So, I also want to quickly talk about things, APIs.
So, this is the API stack.
The two main APIs are data stream API, table API, OTP, table API, and there's also stateful functions.
Stateful functions is some project that tries to execute like an connector model on a patch of link
but will not go to the detail here.
So, first of all, all APIs are built on a dataflow runtime so there's no pin-in-matching
or anything involved under the hood.
It's really a dataflow runtime whenever the result is ready, it will be streamed to the next operator.
On top of that, there is a low-level stream operator API which you can use but this is for Exoprocess, I would say.
And then we have the mainstream APIs on top.
And the specialty about table and SQL API is that there is an optimizer planning stage in between
so this helps you in creating the most efficient pipelines.
The optimizer will make sure that the streaming will be executed more efficiently.
Let's also quickly look at the APIs.
So, this is like a basic, kind of, example.
So, you're creating a stream for just the elements and then you're executing this on a cluster
or in your IDE, then you're retrieving the result back and you have an iterator locally
and you can just print it locally.
It's not very useful but this is a minimal example of the Java API in this case, we also have an API.
The important thing is that the stream, the industry API, basically exposes all the building blocks
that I mentioned on my previous slide.
So, you can have very abstract operator topologies and you can use built-in functions like man, process,
and which each of them take, user-defined functions and then you can really define your business logic
and those user-defined functions and you can also use completely arbitrary Java records,
for example, Python records that flow between the operators.
And conceptually, that is interesting when we talk about change data capture,
conceptually the data stream API does not know about changes, it only knows about records
so there is no change flag or anything like that.
So, conceptually the data stream API is the app that can only, or insert only a block
and also when you look at the output, 1, 2, 3, it is in Java also.
So, now let's take a look at table API and SQL API.
So, like, usually you just say to this table API or SQL, because it is a unified API,
you can decide whether you want to define your pipeline automatically
or whether you want to use standard SQL for defining your topology.
Then in the end, you also execute and you can also print locally in your IDP.
Here, this API abstracts all building blocks, so you have no access to timers or state
or anything like this, this will be done after the port.
Also, the operator topology is determined by the planner, not by you.
The nice thing here is you can focus on your business logic
and you do this deliberately to optimize our process with these declarations
and make something efficient out of it.
Internally, it uses highly efficient records, also up to the engine, not to you.
What you will see maybe is like a road type, if you really want to go out of table API,
then you see a road type which can work as an impressive program.
The interesting thing here is that essentially we are working with tables here,
tables and views for databases, but under the hood there is actually a change loop.
That's what I want to show in the following slides.
You can also see that, like for example, if you execute this theory here,
you will get this output when you run it in IDP.
You already see that there is of course an F0 column with a 1.3 output,
but there is an additional column first column which already shows
that there is some change flag attached to every record.
In this case, it's just inserted.
The nice thing about the links API is that you can mix and match them.
You can, for example, start with data stream API,
then you go into table API, or by the way around,
if you have SQL, you can do the table in SQL first.
Then if you have some more complex logic,
or any timer services, or like a very complex stage,
then you can go to data stream API and do it there,
and then you can switch back to SQL,
or you can just use the SQL connectors,
but you find the entire pipeline in data stream API.
That is up to you, but yeah,
the APIs for that are present to go back and forth with those two.
Now let's really talk about change-loss for your processes.
If you think about data processing,
in most of the cases actually data processing
is always consuming a stream of changes,
because if this would not be like a continuous input stream,
then your company, your project, whatever it would actually be,
so it's actually very common that data flows in continuously.
The link API is the link runtime,
it sees everything basically as a stream.
It just distinguishes between a bounded stream and unbounded stream.
Bounded means you define a start and an end,
and the end is coming there.
Unbounded means you start somewhere,
and now it can be somewhere in the past,
and then you start processing the future.
This is up to you.
If you really think a bit about this,
data processing is just a special case of stream processing.
So, data processing means that,
okay, through the bounded nature of the stream,
I can maybe do some more specialized operators,
like sorting for example, it's easier in such a thing.
You can also use different algorithms if you have sorting,
like Solar
much join or something like this.
So, the runtime has special operators and special handling of bounded streams,
but in general, you can process everything for the stream.
So, those bounded and unbounded data.
So, how does actually things look like?
So, how can I work with streams in the end-to-end sequence?
So, the first answer to this, I already mentioned it before,
is you actually don't block the streams.
So, what you work with is dynamic tables.
It's just a concept we call dynamic tables.
It's a concept similar to materialized views and materialized view maintenance.
So, what you do as a user is you define your tables.
On the left side, we have transactions,
and on the right side, we have revenue.
And then in the middle, you define a standing, running,
and then you define a sequence of three ones,
which gets translated into a pipeline to
which you execute the right and right.
So, then the question is, okay, if we have this,
like it's a big SQL kind of a database,
and the answer to that is no, it's not a database,
because we are not in charge of the data.
So, you can bring your own data into your own systems.
So, it reads, it's more like a process that leads from all different kinds of systems
to different kinds of systems.
So, if a table is not a stream,
or if I don't work with streams,
how does that actually relate with each other?
And an interesting piece of, or like an interesting term,
here is called stream table duality.
So, you can basically see a stream as the change log
of a continuously changing table.
So, it is possible, and I will also show an example shortly,
that you can convert from a table into a stream
and from a stream into a table.
You can do it back and forth, I think that is possible.
Usually, you as a user, you don't see that.
Under the hood, the runtime, all the sources,
all the things, all the operators,
they work with change logs under the hood.
So, in Flink, we have four different kinds of change bags for each record.
So, we have insertions.
Insertions are also the default input and output for bounded dash queries.
And then we have update for, which basically removes the previously included result.
Then we have update after to update something.
And then we have to use the last result in the data store.
When we see only, insert only in a log,
then we call this end only or insert only log.
It contains some kind of deletion or update before we call this
updating table or an updating stream.
And if it never contains an update before but only update afters,
then there is a primary key involved and then we call this absurdity.
So, let me make a complete example.
So, again, we have on the left side, the sections on the right,
and in the middle, we have some in and some grouping by name of the transactions.
So, what happens now is, like in the logical table,
there is a new record coming in called Alice.
This is how it will be represented in the change bag under the hood.
And then this is what comes out.
So, we are summing here.
So, 56 is the first result that we are also using.
So, now the next red row comes in, the bottom comes in.
Again, it will be added.
So, it will be done table.
But now it comes in.
There is another Alice and we want to do five Alice.
So, that means the sum is not updating or to update the sum to the newest number.
That means first we have to remove the old record.
If we want to materialize our change log to the table,
so we also have to remove the row in the table.
And then we can finally add the updated row.
And this is what the change log looks like.
And if you would apply this change log to a sequel or some key values there,
store like the search or so, then the result would be there.
And if we were to find a primary key on the think table,
actually we don't need this update before because then it would be now searching operation.
And here we can basically say 50% of traffic if we do not want to support W
in the rows in the sink.
So, I already mentioned that each sink and each source,
that they declare a change.modo which changes the
And yeah, I give like a quick example of various connectors.
So, when we, for example, read from a file system,
this is usually a scan operation.
So, it is very common that when you read from a file,
that this is just in support, there are no updates coming through file system.
Sometimes they do, but in the general case,
you just scan through a file.
So Kafka, in the early days Kafka was actually just a log.
So, every record that came in through Kafka was also considered like an insert only record.
Then later, Kafka also added some absurd functionality.
So, we also have a connector called Kafka Absurd Forget.
That means when a value in Kafka is null, it means an issue.
So, the Kafka Absurd Connector, for example,
would produce insertions and divisions.
If you define the JPC connector, JPC also doesn't have this concept of updates.
So, in the same case, we would scan the entire table
and this scan only produces insertions.
So, we have all the insertions for JPC.
But that comes back to most complex case.
What happens if you use, for example, a BCL,
you connect it to the database to consume the change of this JPC log from the database.
You put this into Kafka and then you consume from Kafka.
In this case, for example, this could, for example,
have all kinds of changes that can then be evaluated by the end.
The optimizer basically tracks the changes through the entire topology
and the thing appears what it can digest and the optimizer will react
sometimes with an error message, but sometimes it will support a need.
So, let's quickly also talk about these two different modes.
I already said that sometimes you can do Absurds where there's no update before.
Then sometimes you need all four kinds of changes.
I've got to change things and this is called retracts versus Absurd.
So, retract has this nice property that there is no primary key required.
This works for almost all external systems, which is great.
You can also support up-link-it-goes, which you cannot support in the Absurd.
The table is only an Absurd table.
Interestingly, it also retracts. So, this retracting of the previous omitted record
is actually often required in distributed systems.
I also have a little example on the right side, but I will show shortly.
So, let me explain this first.
So, this is a count of a count. So, we are creating a histogram.
The single query itself is not so important.
What is important, what is actually flowing in the cluster through the operators.
So, whatever record comes in, the first count operator will identify this.
Okay, this is the first time, so the count is one.
And then since we want to do a count of a count, the next operator will also count this as one
and it will keep some state. How many records have we seen for this particular count?
So, now comes the second record.
And we have to update our count. So, now the count is two, but one anymore.
And interestingly, if we do like a hash partition for some characters,
it might be that the count ends up in a completely different operator.
But what happens with the old count?
So, now you have two threads or two operators,
for instance, it's not an operator, that have a count
and that's where we need to remove the count in the other operator.
This is why in this case, the rejection is required because the update before
needs to go to the subclass one and remove the outdated record.
But the general absurd is an optimization, it uses traffic, it uses computation
and if it's possible, it's great, but usually there is a lot of distractions going on in the...
And I also have some examples here.
Like if you would do an explain on some SQL query in Google SQL,
the bottom part is what you would see.
So, let's assume we have a table transactions, a table payment,
that's the result. The table result can consume all kinds of changes,
just so if I see the table also.
And you join transactions and payments.
And you'll explain, you also see that there is,
you can get information to explain about the change book mode.
For example, if the input here is insert only, insert only,
then also the join will produce insert only result.
And for example, if we do an outer join, in this case, a left outer join,
then things become a bit more complex.
So here you have insert only, insert only,
but since that outer join will emit another first,
there is one thing, one record comes in, there is no matching record, not so hard.
And you have to emit another first for the other side,
and when the other side is coming in, then you have to remove the null again
and emit the final result.
And that's why for example here, we have all kinds of changes coming out of the join.
And we can even make it more complicated.
So if we define the primary key on transactions and payments,
then the optimizer will recognize how okay the left input spec
and the right input spec will contain our key.
That is great.
So I can remove the update for, so you can see that there is one,
that the default is not necessary anymore,
because we can do up-source on the result.
So this query is obviously more efficient than the other one.
And the other good optimizer can also range between those different modes.
I don't want to get into details here, but if it's also necessary,
you can go from updating to the direction that you want.
But that's not also one of the other points.
And depending on the operators, you also can switch between these modes.
For example, if you have a regular join between the two append-only tables,
then also the resulting table will be append-only.
And I showed already that if there is one of the tables updating,
the results will be updating.
And if there is an outer join, then there is always updating.
And now comes the interesting part.
If you have an append-only table, and you join it to an updating table,
there is a special kind of join, which we call temporal join.
A temporal join will actually produce an append-only table,
because it looks at the table at a point, a specific point in time.
It's a very interesting operator.
Unfortunately, we don't have enough time.
But I just want to show you an example of this very, very useful join operator.
So let's assume we have some ORRAs table, and ORRAs have currency,
and there is a currency rates table.
And obviously, you don't want to join those two tables
with the latest currency rates, but you actually want to know
what was the currency rate at the time when the order was created.
And this syntax here with the for system turn S off
actually allows you to consume all the changes from the rates table
and join it with ORRAs at the point when the order is finished.
This is just one example of a very sophisticated join operation.
And by the way, for system turn S off,
this system is there for the OEC.
So I also have prepared a demo.
I think we still have seven minutes left, so it should be good for the C.
So I also want to show you some of the CVC capabilities.
So I will run everything in my IDE.
I will use Java for this example.
I have a MySQL container that I'm running,
so we'll start with a SQL container for this process.
And this container will create a MySQL instance,
and it will also be filled already with three or four rows.
I have a big example here.
I can simply run the examples in the main method of the IDE.
So what I'm doing here is I'm creating different tables to connect to SQL.
One is a JPC one, which fills against the table once.
And the other one is a CVC one,
which continuously monitors the tables and the X.
So I'll just run this.
So here we see the first few results.
As you can see, the application has not stopped.
So it is waiting for more records to come.
And now I want to insert more values into MySQL.
I could have used the MySQL CLI client for that,
but I can also use F
enough you can also use it for the best degree of just setting one record into the database.
And as you can see, it will all immediately show up also in MySQL
and from MySQL via CVC to the link and then to the next system.
We have also more sophisticated examples here.
I don't think that we have more time for that,
but we can do a lot of things with Blink SQL.
I think we could spend a day on the way to SQL.
So too long to get rid of.
Yeah, Blink SQL is very powerful.
It has been crafted over years and years and years by many, many companies, many teams.
It's very flexible for integrating various systems of different semantics.
And there is way more.
So I just showed some operators, but we have a large, large coverage of SQL standard.
So over Windows support, for aggregating, for swimming,
we support the recognized laws for pattern matching and complex pen processing.
We have tons of obsessions, windows for cutting your swimming pieces.
Then there is a huge CVC connector ecosystem, not part of Orphanage,
but also quite useful as a little GitHub star already.
Then something new, TableStore, which tries to be the first streaming data warehouse kind of thing.
It's in a very, very early version, but it's very promising.
So I would recommend to maybe look into one of these sub-projects as well.
It's not only things that speak, but also the ecosystem around things that are close and close.
I'm happy to take questions.
I think we have three minutes left, but otherwise I will also speak outside for any questions.
Thank you very much.
Yeah, the question is, if you have a large transaction that's happening, or some others may know what the transaction is,
but the question is, how does it handle transactions that also take a lot of time before the transaction has ended?
In general, I think we are not very good at transaction handling in things,
but you have a lot of possibilities to buffer all the data from this transaction and stay in the grid up to terabyte.
And then just wait until the transaction closes, and then you're creating the execution of the transaction.
And that is possible.
So firstly, I would maybe do some stuff in the industry API first until the transaction ended, and then push the
application.
Thank you.
I'm going to check.
I was going to say, the question was how far does this yield?
I think there is Apple that processes things, like all the big banks use it for credit card fraud detection and stuff like that.
So I don't think that most companies in this room, they will not reach the scalability limits of link,
because we are not at Apple.
Unless here some Apple or Alibaba people are in this room, then maybe.
I don't know.
Yeah, this table store is a very, very interesting approach.
It started last year or two years ago.
It's rather new.
I think it was last year, early last year.
It doesn't really fit to Apache Flink, but it's still very useful.
And yeah, we will see.
Maybe it will leave the Apache Software Foundation soon, but yeah, not allowed to.
And not the software foundation, but the Flink project itself.
We will see.
Because it doesn't fit really well.
But it's in general, like we still have this vision of Flink as a database.
We will see.
Sorry, Christian. This is about big states, because you mentioned that you can have a terabyte of state.
But when you create a checkpoint, and if this checkpoint will be very big, and storage of it can be long,
is it like a huge DC post to write into the store?
Yeah, so the question was, how can we actually snapshot large state in general?
And this is exactly where Flink distinguishes, like where it differs from competitors.
Because there is a lot of engineering involved to make this as efficient as possible.
I'm sure there's even more to do.
It's still not perfectly efficient.
There's more optimizations that you can do.
But for example, there is like differential snapshots involved.
There is local recovery involved.
There are many, many algorithms under the hood to make it as quickly as possible.
But yeah, of course, if you have terabytes of state, and the machine has died completely,
then you obviously need to restore these terabytes of state from S3 into your task manager again.
And this can take time.
So it tries its best.
But of course, you need to do benchmarks for your use case.
It's going to be longer than we set it outside.
One last question.
In case of out of memory issues or network outages, does it guarantee that everything is as you written in SQL or in data streams API?
Yeah, so we guarantee exactly once end to end if the connectors source and sink support that.
Especially for state, so there are no duplicates in state, we might need to reprocess data during a failure.
But yeah, like end to end exactly once semantics are possible.
Thank you very much.
And I'm waiting outside.