Thanks very much. Thank you. So welcome everyone and I'm glad that you're here on Saturday
early morning in this first session. So I would like to make it as easy as possible.
Thanks for the O'Gallantas, Jervis and Yarmur for inviting me to talk today about stream processing.
The fact is I don't know your background so I'm not sure exactly how much experience
you have with real time stream processing. So if you see some concepts are easy, just get everyone
after a few of these concepts. So I'll be talking today about real time stream processing on
additive and there is one of the blocks. So that's what the main focus will be. Obviously this title
as it is could be a startup company. So you would expect to have some ideas today where you can use
some of these ideas in your world or in your experience or in your days of study, whatever
you want. Whether you are a Java developer or data scientist or ML ops, so it doesn't matter.
So there is something for everyone here today. So that's the main focus for this session.
So anyone recognize these guys on the screen here?
Right, so that's where I came from. I'm based in Liverpool in the UK and on the right side is the
Liverpool for Coqola which is basically one of the top football teams in the UK. So I want
just to highlight this screen here just to tell you that's real time stream processing is not
in a specific domain, it could be in any domain. If you look at it, do you know how long it takes
for example for an eye to blink? Come again. Yeah, so it takes over half one third of seconds.
So that's pretty fast. So if you're thinking about like maybe minutes or hours, probably this is not
the right discussion room for you. We're talking about sub-milliseconds today. So whether it's for
example you use it in finance, whether you use it in IOD devices, smart devices, whether you use it
in sports, hospitals or machine learning or what we're trying to do today for stream processing.
So that's the main idea and obviously if you're working with real time stream processing you focus
on the real time data right? And I've seen it so many times where platforms and tools focus on
you know how much data you can process and you see these benchmarks everywhere on the internet
and this is pretty cool I think but the key source and the secret source for this is to use something
in combination between real time data and historical data. So the main reason for this is
to look at context. So without you know knowing what's going on, you probably don't benefit much
from the real time data you're processing. So what you want is always to go back and check what's
going on with the context of this data. There is a problem in this script source obviously because
what you're looking at is kind of like you know two different data types and you want to make
sure that you process it at the same speed or you know very close to the same speed. Obviously it
becomes really problem when you try to scale it. So if you have I don't know like maybe a few
cases of data that you want to process probably it's not too much topic for you but when you
start to scale it up it becomes really problem you know to understand how you want to scale it.
So do you scale your data or do you scale your compute or do you scale both and at what speed.
So we will discuss all these concepts today and if I ask you now how much did you process? Probably
because in this room I would assume you have over million transactions per second or few
millions or I don't know some of you might be processing billions of transactions per second.
So that's pretty good and what we want today is to focus this domain into very
specific area and this area essentially what we're trying to do today is to analyze traces. So
it doesn't matter if it is like operating system traces or platform traces or it's
like programming language traces what we want is to make sure that we have environment
and within this environment you can scale your logs basically scale your processing
and at the same time provide some kind of analytics right. So again if you look at how
much data you can process the number by itself doesn't give you much what's going on here.
So what you want is to find this specific information you're looking for
or kind of like looking at finding the needles or finding the hidden areas within your data.
So if you look at how much logs you process per day or per week and you store it somewhere
on you know
official hard drive or you store it in mori or you store it in the cloud. So what you want is
to you know make sense of it and some companies do this process manually which means they run
software and they go through their logs and this is kind of a patch service and they try to
understand what's going on within the logs. So obviously this is a problem when you want to scale
it and with the scaling you have different logs stored in different places and you want to make
sure basically to have a platform where in this platform we kind of like looking at some kind of
results. So for the sake of this discussion today we'll focus on two different solutions. So one of
a kind of like to provide some kind of alerts and the other is provide some kind of trends within
your data. Obviously I work for a company called Hezakast. So Hezakast as a platform allows you to
do so but obviously you might have heard of some companies or you know they do some kind of stream
processing. So this is kind of like you know overview what's going on with this domain at this
time. Obviously you can split it depending on you're looking for open source solution or
I don't know, hardware solution or you know some kind of management service and what you look at
is which domain you are. So are you looking to capture your data or some kind of you know
streaming your data or you want to do some kind of transformation on your data or do some kind
of analytical machine learning. So you can see that you split it into 12 squares and within this
where these like tools and platforms are you know spread it over. So obviously some tools exist on
this screen for whatever reason but obviously this might give you some ideas but it's hard
it's hard to decide which tool you want to go for. Simply because I think the distribution is not
clear here so it tells you basically which tool is open source for example and where in process you
can use it but it doesn't give you a full picture on you know how to do it in practical terms.
And so this is where it might be easier to understand what we're talking about. So if you
remember from my slide where I discussed the historical data and the new data. So today we're
kind of like you know trying to split everything into two categories. So on one side you get like
stream processing engines so these engines are pretty fast in you know streaming events
and on this far right side you have some kind of fast data stores which are you know are pretty
fast in handling data at speed. So again the solution for break time stream processing
is kind of combination and you want to process data in this moment and at the same time you want
to actually also access data stored somewhere. So that's where is a cast fit into this area here.
So the platform itself obviously for those who don't know by the way we have one of the masterminds
of Hezakast sitting in this room. So this is the platform so it's open source platform it doesn't
matter where your shop is coming from whether it's a passion car or passion board. So IOT devices
for example I don't know some kind of enterprise applications or even like within Hezakast or even
you can write your own connector and you feed it into the platform. So platform historically used
to be two different components so the IMPG and the JET engine and essentially now it's all packaged
in one one jar file. As you see here it allows you to load your data from R-Biscuits into memory so
you have access to external data and pretty much like instantaneously and this will where you know
you can provide context what's going on with your data and at the same time you can actually do
stream processing so that's what JET engine is. So from here you can do some kind I don't know
maybe like data transformation or do some kind of stream processing as we will do today or even
like define machine learning if you want to. You can connect it to some clients so these are some
clients here so written in various languages. If you're from data science background which means
your programming languages in general are not preferred for you so you might be considered
using SQL to do what I'm planning today so this is another option you can do and once you process
this data where you load it into memory for a JET file data and at the same time you have some
kind of data coming in. In CASCAT topic for example and you do the combination or even
you do transformation you can proceed to do some kind of visualization. So the good thing about
HESECAS in general when it comes to scaling is it's partition aware so which means basically
your compute your JET engine or your process essentially can be or can detect where your data
is stored so this is like you know we are trying to have as low latency as possible when it comes
to processing this data. So this is very important to understand because latency is your enemy when
it comes to stream processing so what you want is kind of like having a platform where you avoid
network folks for example you avoid IO to your hard disk you try to also avoid every time or
context switching between threads so you want to avoid all of these but at the same time you want
your process to be as close as possible to your data. You can apply some kind of you know machine
learning on this and the scaling itself could be done in various ways so the main thing to take
away from here is this no master worker relationship so all nodes basically are peers and we've done
this study it's a bit outdated but it's kind of like 1 billion transactions per second on 45 nodes
so what we're trying to do now is to add one zero into this number here and even though it's pretty
impressive what is nice about it is the linear scaling which means more data you can add you
know more nodes into it so that's the historical bit of this talk so let's just move to the technical
part so for this demo what I wanted is kind of like you know show you some some ideas right
so you should be able to take these ideas and apply it you know anywhere obviously the solution
as itself would be like you know project by itself so feel free to edit and change it so all
source code is available on github and the documentation as well so you can go through it
so the main idea when it comes to analyzing or you know making sense out of your traces and
logs is to store it somewhere close to you know you will compute first of all and it shouldn't
be stored locally right so you want to store it first of all the first thing is to store on the
cloud so for this for the sake of this demo what I'm doing is I'm storing everything onto the cloud
so there is a solution called hazelgas hurricane which is kind of like service so you don't need
to download jar run your relic you can simply click and play so you can create that cloud
you run everything I'm discussing today so you create an instance of hazelgas and from there
you can pretty much proceed to what I'm planning to do so the first option we were talking about
is kind of like storing everything into the cloud so once we have all the data obviously we need
some kind of you know trace message which makes sense so this trace message could be you know
changed based on how you want to approach it right so for example if you're working with machine
learning you probably look for some kind of I don't know classification solution for you
you know for your tests or you could be looking for NLP if you don't want to work with machine
learning you probably want to look for some kind of trends so you look for processing your data
doesn't matter if you're using machine learning in this case you want to have some kind of data
stored somewhere so it could be in JSON format or it could be like bar charge swing so it depends
again how much the speed is important to you so the option first option is to go through the
alerts so in alerts what we're trying to do here is to take everything and start in that cloud so
obviously we don't store it on the cloud on our basis what we try to do is store it in memory
my preference in this case is to use some kind of map structure so map structure allows you to
essentially random access and rebalance between various nodes within your cluster and at the same
time you want to have some key value so in order to know where this node is coming from so in this
case could be like ID address for example so this is where and report number so as key and the value
could be anything that makes sense to you so in this case for example you can track level of this
error sorry this level and message for example if you want to do some kind of NLP processing
and some kind of you know process or thread name on this obviously once you have your
dm value what you can do is proceed and store it into memory so this is where you get this
set to has a task and what we're trying to do is create the IMAP and once you have the IMAP
means you should be able to store it you know access and do stream processing as I will show you
so first message is to store it into the cloud store it in memory in this case i'm using
gazakas and i'm using IMAP and second stage is to do the stream processing right so there are a
couple of options here for you so first option is to use SQL so SQL is built within gazakas which
means or on top of gazakas which means you should be able to work your data so you provide some kind
of specific messages that you're looking for obviously depends on your input you can do some
kind of SQL so whether it's in your joy for example or search and so on or the other option is to do
some kind of prediction so you're getting some logs you don't know exactly what's going on to
happen next and you try to predict to provide some kind of you know alerts or trends so we need to
build the trends so in order to do this what I did is kind of like use the same key but for my
value what I'm using is some kind of log score so log score is not important what I'm saying here
is I want to give value for is every single message or every single log message so this could be for
example how you know how important this specific message is for you or could be for example how
serious or how you know dangerous the message is so as levels in logs you can define score so
instead of having four levels for example you can spread it either from one one to one hundred
so this should give you some kind of predictions why because if you have for example 10 messages
10 local messages or for example warning you don't know exactly if the 11 matches will be warning or
not if you want to predict it obviously it doesn't give you how much will be warning or not whereas
if you use some kind of numerical value you can get as close as possible to this so we get key
from there we get score from here and what we do next is to do some kind of predictions on the logs
so in this process what we have is exactly my key and the value which is like the score on each log
message and I imported into Helical so Helical allows you to basically input and output from two
different maps and do stream processing so we'll build the train based on previous logs
scores and we use the prediction on top of it to provide some kind of alert so zero means don't
alert one means alert and as you can see here the actual workflow kind of like you build you read
from then you define trend map so which is like normal map and from there you can use it to predict
what's going to happen next obviously do some kind of visualization so how does it look like
so this is kind of the prediction part of it so we take the logs map and we build trend map out of
it so trend map would start reading messages and the scores and build train for you and from this
trend I can use some kind of machine learning it doesn't have to be machine learning in this case
it's linear regression but it could be anything to be honest and we check the values and we try to
use some kind of prediction based on the previous values to decide if you want to send an alert or
not and obviously this is kind of like describing the exact thing so when it there is a one on your
values it's alert send alert when it's zero or not and here there are three ways to do it
so this is where the stream processing comes into place so you could simply use SPL to read from
them out and do some query if you want obviously this is batch which means it's not real time
stream processing or you can even like create a pipeline or create a process and from this
process you can read the logs and do the same thing so you can use either SQL or Java to do it
but first two options are batch which means like you can process the data in real time you want to
change this in real time so the third option is the journal map so journal map will track all
changes so it's going to be honest so you have the logs stored and you have logs coming into Kafka
topic and you can basically store both into journal map so we're on 5.2 version within
hezakas 5.3 will have the SQL features on top of it which allows you if you're for example data
scientist to just do the queries and change the data and obviously it's ring buffer so this is
very important to understand so you can start processing your data from start or you know from
the end and what you want is kind of like you know using this kind of alert to it so the first part
is to read it so this is the actual map we built in the first option and from here you define the
key for example and the value and you start for example to do some kind of filtering so this
happens in real time on continuous and the map inset will allow you to basically track changes
so to give you some takeaways and best practices so we just try to summarize everything we discussed
today obviously there are more to discuss but this should give you something to go out and try
so first of thing you need to store your logs into some kind of platform so in this case i'm
using hezakas obviously you don't have to use hezakas the idea here is to do some kind of compute
onto circle data to provide some context as well as real-time data and from there you need to store
it on the cloud so you need to store it somewhere where you can access logs from multiple places
obviously you have to be stored in memory and from there you need to choose format if you for
example looking to provide some you know i don't know some predictions you probably need to use
JSON format or for example if you want just to do some analysis you can sync and it's faster if you want to speed
unit it is some kind of map structure obviously when you store it in memory because this will allow
some kind of random access and also you need to consider how you empty your map so because
you're limited on size obviously and finally you need to consider security so whatever you
send to the cloud you need to make sure that you don't load something you know personally whatever
so if you're interested in this topic we're running on conference next month so feel free
to scan this code we provide training for this all free obviously and everything i mentioned today
is up so you should be able to do everything i mentioned today i'll be sharing around here if
you want to have a chat or if you want to discuss it a little bit more obviously within half an hour
there's not much to give but hopefully you've got some ideas from mr and hopefully it will be also
useful for you so with that being said thanks very much for listening open for questions