You have image?
Okay.
Thank you. Okay.
Thanks. I think the technical issues are now solved.
So thanks again, everyone, for being here.
So I'm going to talk today about Apache VIN.
Apache VIN is a framework for data processing that runs on
top of several platforms, and it's a special event for doing
streaming analytics. So have you already introduced me?
My name is Israel. So I work as a cloud data engineer in
Google Cloud, helping customers doing data engineering on top
of Google Cloud. A lot of the work that I do is actually
helping customers with Apache VIN and particularly Dataflow,
which is our runner for Apache VIN.
So Apache VIN. What is it? Apache VIN is a framework for
data processing. It allows to run data pipelines like
Flink, like Spark, like so many other big data systems.
It has two main features. The first one is that it's an
unified computing model for batch and streaming.
Any pipeline that you have written in Apache VIN for a batch
use case, you may easily use it in streaming as well.
So the same code, you use all that code and you have to add
some small additions that we're going to talk about in a bit.
And the other main feature is that it runs everywhere and you
can run your pipeline in many different languages, for some
definition of everywhere. So you can write your pipeline in
Java, in Python, in Go. You may also run your pipeline in
any of the programming languages of the Java Victor
matching. For instance, I have here highlighted Scala because
there is a framework called XIO, though don't buy Spotify,
on top of Apache VIN for, let's say, Scala native development
of pipeline. So you don't have to use like a Java looking
code in Scala. So it's a functional code. There are lots
of people using, for instance, Kotlin also on top of the
Java Victor matching with a Java VIN SDK. So that's about the
programming language that you may use. And you may run a
VIN pipeline on top of runners. So there's a direct runner for
local running and local testing of pipelines. It's not meant
for, let's say, to be used with real world use cases. But then
you can run your pipeline on top of Dataflow, on top of
Flink, on top of Hazelcast, Spark, many different runners.
So basically when you write a pipeline in Apache VIN, you are
not tied to the platform where you're running. So you may move
it to different platforms with some minor comments. So Apache
VIN is a theoretical model for computing. Not all the runners
implement the model, let's say, to the same degree of extent.
So right now, as of now, I would say Dataflow and Flink are
probably the ones that are covered like fully covered.
Other runners may have some gaps. A silly example, Hadoop.
You may run a Apache VIN pipeline on top of Hadoop also, but
you cannot run streaming on top of Hadoop because it doesn't
support the streaming. So it also depends on the capability
of the runner. So what you're able to do with VIN, it depends
on the capabilities of the runner. So there's no magic.
So if VIN is batch and streaming, but if your platform doesn't
support streaming, for instance, you cannot do streaming.
So let's talk about streaming. What's the problem with streaming?
It's extremely interesting. So in streaming, you are getting
data, a lot of data, continuously. There is no beginning
and there's no end. So you cannot know in advance where are
the boundaries of your data. And it's coming continuously from
many different places. Think, I don't know, like you are
designing a mobile application for a game or whatever, and
people are using it and sending events to your systems every
once in a while. So because the application is deployed in the
wild world, data will come. Who knows how? Okay. So it will
come out of order. So some users will be, I don't know, in the
underground and without the phone coverage, still try
attempting to send in events and then they will send the
events late. Like for instance here, let's see if I can put
the pointer. So this is data that is supposed to be produced
around 8 in the morning. Maybe the network latency and so on,
but more or less you get it around 8 in the morning in your
system. So this is the time where you are seeing the data
in your system, but for whatever reason, you may also
get very late data. And depending on what you want to do,
you may want to process this data as it was produced, not as
you are receiving it. So this is actually the problem with
microvatching. So I remember when I started hearing about
the streaming in the first days, many years ago, a lot of
people said, ah, Spark, I don't like it because it does
microvatching, it doesn't do real streaming. I had no clue
what they meant. It's like, well, you have to group things,
no, to process it somehow. So if the data is infinite, you
will need to process it. The problem with microvatching,
which is not happening in Spark anymore, so this was really
like ancient times, the problem with microvatching is that
you are doing the batches as you see the data, okay? And
then you may have the data that belongs together in
buckets that are separate. Like for instance, this was
data that was produced at 8 in the morning. If you are
doing buckets of one hour, so while you may capture here
this message, but then if you have late data, you will
capture it in a bucket that doesn't belong, that element
doesn't belong with the rest of the elements there if you
want to process them together. So you need to solve this
problem of lack of order in streaming, okay? And this is
what you can easily solve with Apache Bin. Let's talk
about the watermark. There are many ways of doing stream
processing. One of the most popular is in a concept of
watermark. There is no one dimension of time. There are
two dimensions of time, at least. That is the event
time, the moment in which the data was produced, and that
is the processing time, the moment in which you see the
data. They will never be the same. They can be really
close sometimes, but it's not, you cannot grant it how
close or how far you are going to be from that moment,
okay? So we put time in two dimensions, okay? So the
ideal is, for instance, like this straight line in blue,
for sure. This sun is impossible, okay? You cannot see
data before it's produced, or not yet, at least, okay? So
according to the laws of physics, okay? So, but then
what's most likely what will happen is that you will
have some delay, okay? Sometimes it will be closer to
the ideal. Sometimes it will be farther from the ideal,
okay? So, and you need to take this into account, okay?
So let's see an example that might be a little bit more
telling, okay? So Star Wars, okay? So have you ever,
like, watched a Star Wars movie? So Star Wars were
released out of order, out of order, okay? So the first
movie was episode four. This is purely streaming. This
is what happens in the streaming, okay? You are
expecting events, okay, at the beginning of the session,
in the middle of the session, the end of the session,
okay? And then you get end of the session, middle of
the session, beginning of the session. And you need to
reorder things, okay? Depending on what you want to do,
you may need to reorder, okay? If you don't care,
look, I don't want to, I don't care. I just want to
count how many movies per year were released, okay?
Well, you don't need event time, okay? But if you
want to reconstruct the story, okay? Who did what
before or after? Who, what happened? So you need to
actually be able to reconstruct that time, okay? So
the time where the movies were released, it's processing
time, event time is the time in which actually the events
are happening, okay? So, and this is the kind of
problems that we can solve using Apache VIN or Flink
or many other streaming systems. Let's see how we can
deal with this. The classical way is using windowing,
okay? Windowing is grouping things based on temporal
properties. When we do a data pipeline, we need to
solve one question, which is what we are going to
compute. But if you want to do this in the streaming
and group things based on temporal properties, you need
to answer three additional questions. Where, when, and
how. Let's see some details. The what? This is easy.
We are going to be aggregating, okay? So this is
Java code and it's in Java here as an example. So it's
Apache VIN API. I haven't entered into details.
There's a link at the end with more details, okay? So
don't mind the details right now. So we're aggregating
things together. So this is what we are happening. We
are not doing any kind of temporal based logic yet,
okay? We're just aggregating stuff together, okay? So
we are summing up all the numbers here, okay? So this
is the operation that we are doing. Send us in batch.
This is in batch, okay? So imagine that we are getting
this batch, okay? The problems that when we are
working in streaming, we don't see the full data at
once, okay? And we need to produce output at some
point so we cannot wait forever. So we need to
decide how to group things together. So for instance
here, we are going to group things in windows of two
minutes, okay? But the windows of two minutes are not
in processing time. They are in event time, okay? For
instance, so here, this message here, so this message
here, we sit around 12, okay? And we put it in the
window of 12, okay? But this message over here, so
this was received between 1208 and 1209, okay? And we
are able still to attribute it to assign it to the
window between 12 and 1202 in event time, okay? Because
well, so we can wait for late data and put it in the
right window despite the message being quite late
compared to the processing time, okay? And same with
the rest of windows. Now the question is, okay, good.
So you are waiting until 1208, so what if your message
shows up at 8 p.m.? What do you do? Like eight hours
after. So we need to do another decision, okay? So we
have already made the decision on how we are going to
group things together. Here is with easy windows. There
are more windows in Apache Bin, not entering two
details right now. But now we need to decide how long do
we wait? Okay? So we are going to wait until the
watermark, okay? The watermark is this relationship
between processing time and event time that in the case
of Bin and depending on the runner is calculated and
estimated on the fly as data goes through our pipeline
and this is estimated and when you are, when you
trespass the watermark, you have a certain degree of
warranty that your data is complete, okay? A certain
degree of warranty, okay? It cannot be granted because
well, so the future cannot be known, okay? So we cannot
travel in time, okay? So here, for instance, so we are
processing data and the watermark and the nine, this
number here that we were processing before, now it's
left out of the window. So what does it mean if we are
processing data? We were summing up numbers, that
number, that nine, we are not counting it. As soon as
we see it in our pipeline, it will be dropped, like
lost, okay? So the pipeline will ignore it, okay? And
it may make sense, okay? So you cannot wait forever.
At some point you will have to stop and move on, okay?
But maybe you want to take it into account, okay? So
maybe you, I don't know, like this is a billion
embarrassing thing and every penny counts, okay? So
then you need to process it. Well, you have to take
yet another decision. How we are going to wait for
late data and how we are going to actually update the
data, okay? Here I'm summing numbers. It's easy,
commutative, associative, really no big deal, okay? So
I can do it like say, I can do it like a monoid in
big data processing. So I can just take the aggregation,
the previous aggregation and keep aggregating. I don't
need to keep all the numbers that I have seen so far.
So it is easy. In other cases, for any non-associative,
non-commutative operation, so you may need to have
actually full data to produce an update, okay? And if
you are working in streaming, maybe you don't want to
accumulate all the data, okay? Because that will
increase the amount of resources that you will need
for your pie brand. It will have impact in performance,
latency, and so on. So here we are accumulating because
the operation allows it and we are actually waiting
for late data, okay? So now we are waiting for late
data, but we don't want to wait forever. We want to
have some numbers, okay? So we are actually producing
several outputs per window, okay? So like for instance
here, continuing with the first, so when the watermark
is trespassed, we produce an output, okay? And then when
we see the new number, so we produce the output, we
produce it really late, okay? But well, so this is, so
we cannot make magic, okay? So this is when we see the
data, so we cannot process it earlier than this, okay?
We may actually decide to produce data, some output,
even before the watermark, because the watermark can be
really slow. It depends on the pace of the updates of
the data. If for whatever reason users are sending
your data with a lot of lateness, the watermark can
progress really slowly, okay? And so the watermark, how
you produce output is always a trade-off in the streaming
between completeness and latency. You need to make a
decision, okay? So here we put an early trigger, so
we are producing output soon, low latency, but it's
not, it's incomplete, because well, so later on we are
going to keep seeing numbers until the watermark.
Good. So basically this is streaming in Apache Bin in
10 minutes. This is a lot of information explained very
quickly. If you want to get deeper, if you want to get
deeper, there is this example here, okay? So in Java and
in Python, so it's available in the two languages, and
you can see everything that we have seen in the previous
slides with all details, okay? And you may run this
locally if you want, so you don't have to have like an
environment, so like a cloud environment, a cluster or a
stream processor or anything like that, so it may run
locally with some synthetic data, made up data, okay?
Now, this is the classic way of doing streaming in Apache
Bin. This has been around for years already, okay? So
this is the same model that is implemented in Spark, it's
the same model that is implemented in Flink, so they
are all kind of similar. There are other things that you
can also do in Apache Bin in streaming, like anything that
you can do in Apache Bin, you can also do it in
streaming, and I'm going to highlight here a couple of
those, okay? I'm leaving out a lot of stuff, because well,
so time is limited, and leave it out, for instance, SQL,
so that was a great talk by Timo focusing on SQL, so you
can also do SQL in Apache Bin if you want in streaming,
okay? So similar examples to what Timo did, and you can
actually run that on Flink if you want, okay? So it may
make sense if you want, I don't know, if at some point
you want to move away from Flink to Dataflow, you want
to move away from Dataflow to Spark, so in order to have
this portability. One thing that you can do in streaming
is stateful functions, and stateful functions are very
interesting for windowing between quotes that doesn't
depend on time. Very typically, I work with customers,
it's like all this windowing triggers things, it's super
interesting, but look, whenever I see a message of this
type, I want to have all the messages that I have seen so
far in a group and do these calculations, and I don't
care about time, okay? I don't care about grouping things
in time. I want to group things by some logic, okay? I'm
going to give you a predicate, you pass a message, if the
message fulfills a condition, I want to close the previous
window and start a new one. How can you do that in
Apache Vint? You can do that with stateful functions, okay?
Stateful functions, so here we have some input, here we
have a map, it's called a part of Apache Vint, and we do
some transformation, and we want to accumulate a state
here, okay? So depending on what we see at some point, we
do something else, and this is mutable state, okay? In a
system like Dataflow, like Flink, like all the systems
where Apache Vint runs, having a state, mutable state in
streaming that is computed in a consistent way is extremely
difficult, okay? One way to shoot yourself in your feet
with systems like this in streaming is trying to keep
accumulating a state using some kind of external system,
okay? Because runners will have, sometimes will have
issues that will be errors, that will be retries,
infrastructure will die, you will have auto scaling, there
are all kinds of situations that the runner may want to
retract the computation and recompute again, okay? So,
and then in all these kinds of situations, having any kind
of external system for mutable state, it's complex, okay?
It's doable, okay? You may have, and you will have with
Apache Vint in any kind of the runners that you can run, you
will have this end-to-end exactly once processing, but
this end-to-end exactly once processing doesn't mean that
your code is going to be executed exactly once. It may
be executed more than once, okay? This is what makes
maintaining external state to a pipeline complex. But if
the state is internal to the pipeline, then, well, so the
system itself can, let's say, take care of the problems of
reprocessing and maintain a mutable state in a consistent
way. So, this is what it's a stateful function in Apache
Vint, and you can use it for use cases like this, okay?
For instance, say that I want to produce windows between
codes based on some kind of property. So, I keep seeing
messages, okay, that I keep processing, okay, and then I
keep accumulating the messages in some state, okay? I
maintain a buffer, like I keep every single message that I
see, and I count, okay? Because, well, the buffer cannot,
so the buffer must have some boundaries, okay? So, because
this is local state that is maintaining the machine in the
worker, in the executor where you are running, and the
executor will have limited resources. Maybe very large
resources, but limited anyways, okay? So, you keep
accumulating, and then you keep processing here, for
instance. So, typically, you can use this, for instance, for
batching to call in an external service, but you can also
do here, whenever I see a specific type of message, I
emit some output, okay? I emit some output, and then I have
applied a window. All the messages that I have in the
buffer, I type a new session ID, a new window ID, and then
I emit them. I hold them for a while until I see the right
message that I need, and then I emit them. There are two
problems here. We want to, so customers always think that
streaming is complex, and they want to get away of all the
temporal base calculations, okay? So complex, so messy.
Look, my algorithm is really much simpler, but it is not.
So, you are in the streaming, so you cannot ignore time,
okay? You have situations where you will see the messages
out of order, and you will have situations where you
will not see the messages for a while, okay? And then you
need to decide what to do in these two cases, even if you
don't want to, okay? What happens when I see out of
order? You may say, I don't care, unlikely, but well, in
some situations, it might be true, okay? Or you may have
to wait, like, some timer in order to give room for late
data to arrive into your code and actually produce the
actual output, okay? So this will be an event time timer,
okay? Look, in event time, you are going to see the messages
and order, okay? So wait 30 seconds, 2 minutes, and so on.
And then when you have seen all the messages, it's the moment
in which you apply the session. That's called an event
time timer. And you may have also problems of staleness,
okay? I'm waiting for the end of my session, but I have not
seen messages. I haven't seen messages in the last 5
minutes in processing time, okay? The problem with event
time is that depends on the progress of the watermark. But
if you stop seeing messages, the watermark will stop
advancing. The watermark is always estimated in being
runners or normally estimated as the time stamp of the
oldest message waiting to be processed, okay? So literally
you may stop your pipeline waiting forever for some data
that maybe it will never arrive, okay? So processing time
timer solved this problem, okay? After 10 minutes, like,
measure with a clock, if nothing comes, I don't care
about the watermark. I don't want to keep going, okay? So
keep going. So data has been lost for whatever reason, and
we cannot wait forever. So this is a stateful function, and
it's also very useful in streaming because it allows you
to apply logic that goes beyond the temporal properties
that we have seen in the previous slides. And here you
have some examples and links. The slides are already
available through the first time website, so I encourage
you to have a look at these examples. What else can I do
in streaming? Matched learning inference, okay? So there
are many ways to do matched learning inference in
streaming at a scale, okay? Many of those quite expensive.
So you can deploy endpoints in cloud platforms, with
GPUs, with a lot of stuff, okay? And normally, so well,
so those are, those solve a lot of functionality for you,
but they are expensive. So what if you want to apply
matched learning inference in a pipeline in Apache Bin?
Well, you could do that, okay? You could be thinking,
well, I can do that, so I can, I don't know, like importance
of flow, load the model, apply it, so you could do a lot
of stuff, okay, yourself. But this is already solved for
you in Apache Bin, okay? So you can run matched learning
inference with the so-called run inference transform, okay?
So we see it here. So right now, it has, let's say, out-of-the-box
support for PyTorch, TensorFlow, and scikit-learn, with more
coming. When you're running a distributed system, and you
want to apply a model, each one of the workers in this
distributed system will have its own memory. So the Apache
Bin runs on top of shared nothing architecture, okay?
Like Flink, Dataflow, Spark. Workers are independent of
each other. They don't share any common state. The state
that we have seen before is actually maintained per key
and per window if we apply it. The per window is totally
local for the worker, and two workers cannot share a state.
But the model, we don't want to instantiate a model if we
have 100 workers 100 times, because the model is going to
be the same for every worker, right? So the model doesn't
change. The model is actually read-only. Run inference
solving this problem by having some state that is shared
across all the workers, and it's transparent for you.
So this is something that you can always implement in a
distributed system, but it's complex. This is the problem
that is solved with run inference. It's only one copy of
the model per, let's say, machine where you're running,
okay? So in memory, okay? Because what you need always
to make an instance in memory to be able to apply it.
But if you have, I don't know, like 100 threads, 100
sub-workers, 100 CPUs inside the same machine, you will
not have 100 copies of the model. Regardless of the
computation model of how the runner is implemented on top
of the machines. There will be only one copy in the
memory of the machine. So this is the problem that is solved
with run inference, okay? So if you want to apply a
streaming inference, it's a very convenient way of doing
this with very little code. And depending on the runner,
this is a possibility in data flow. This is also a
possibility if you are running on top of Kubernetes in a
runner that supports Kubernetes, like, for instance,
Flink. You can do also hinting of the resources that
your transformation is going to need, okay? Hinting of
transformations could be, look, this transformation is
going to need this amount of memory, minimal, okay? But
hinting could also be, look, this is a step that is
running ML inference. So use a GPU for this step, okay?
And then the runner will take care of making sure that
the step that is running, the virtual machine, the same
matches the infrastructure hints that you provide for
the code, and you will have, let's say, different types
of nodes for different types of transformations. One of
the problems of shared-nath in architectures is that
all the workers are alike. All the workers are the same.
With this, you can have different types of workers for
different kinds of transformations, which, let's
say, in terms of cost, it's better. I don't have to
say optimal, so maybe that's better alternatives. But
basically, you use GPUs in the workers where you need to
use GPUs. You don't use them in the workers where you
don't need to use them. And you don't have to worry
about assigning work to different workers. That's
actually done by the runner automatically with these
hints, okay? If you want to know more, here you have
some links. So I have only five minutes left, so I'm
leaving the best for the end of the presentation.
Great. You, look, Israel, you showed some Java at the
beginning. Now you tell me ML inference is so cool, but
it's Python, right? So it's PyTorch, TensorFlow,
Second-Land, it's all Python. One of the things that you
can do in Apache VIN is in cross-language transforms.
Anything that you have available in any of the SDKs,
in any language, you may use it in any other language.
As long as the runner supports this, okay? So it's not
supported by all the runners, but it's supported by the
main runners, okay? So basically, run inference may be
used in Java. If you want to use any transformation from
any language, you have to add some boilerplate code, not
so much, but a little bit. This is already done, let's
say, for the main transforms that are most popular or
that they say that make more sense to be used in
different languages, like a map. Well, using a map from
Java in Python doesn't really make sense, okay? Using
run inference makes using connectors, input-output
connectors from another SDK in Python, for instance,
makes sense because the amount of input-output
connectors that you have per SDK is not the same. So you
may write, I don't know, like the two databases in
Java and two message queues in Python, but maybe you
don't have the same functionalities in all the SDKs.
You can use any connector from any SDK, and this makes
it quite flexible, okay? So these are the so-called
multi-language pipelines, and basically it means that
you can run any transformation in any SDK, and this
is implemented because the runner environment is
containerized, okay? So there's a container per
language, and there's some magic that makes, let's
say, the container communicates between the
Nsals, okay? And the serialization between
programming languages. So this is part of the boilerplate
that you need to take care of. If you use things like
Apache B, the schemas that I haven't talked about in
this talk, so it will be transparent for you, anything
that you have in one schema in one language, you will
be able to serialize it, and they serialize it to any
other language. So if you follow, let's say, if you
follow the Apache B in Capstone, it's quite
straightforward to use these kind of things. Well,
thanks, everyone, so far for your attention. So here
and almost there, don't, here are some links that I
recommend you to have a look if you want to learn
more about Apache B. I have covered a lot of stuff in
a very short time, okay? So there's a lot of things
behind everything that I have explained here. If you
want to know more about all the windowing, streaming,
trigger, triggers, watermarks, and so on, I strongly
recommend you this book. It was released some time
ago. You may think that it's outdated. It's not
outdated. So let's say this is the same model that is
applied in many different streaming systems, and this
is not a book about Apache B. It's a book about the
streaming systems with lots of examples coming from
Apache B. But also examples coming from Flink, Kafka,
PubSub, and many other systems, and it's really, it's
very interesting. It's my favorite book, one of my
favorite books, the other one being the book actually
from Martin Kledman about data intensive applications.
And if you want to know more about BIN, so I recommend
you, the BIN College. There are lots of videos with
lots of details about the things that I have explained
here in YouTube. Some of them are actually linked in
the slides. For sure, the main site of Apache BIN and
the programming guide and all the documentation that is
there. And if you want to learn more about Apache BIN,
there is also the videos of Apache BIN Summit, the
previous editions. And if you want to participate, if
you are here today, so you may be interested in
streaming. So the call for papers is open until March
20th. I think BIN Summit will be in June in New York.
And well, I encourage you to submit talks.
Well, this is all. So thanks all for your attention.
It's time for questions.
So what's the advantage of fishing BIN if you are
already using Flink? So it's portability mainly. So if
tomorrow you want to move away from Flink for whatever
reason, so you should be able to move to other runners
that have the same level of functionality, like for
instance, Dataflow. I don't know. So we have one of
the main committers here of Apache Flink. Say that he
gets hit by a bus. We don't want that to happen. But
that may happen. Everything may happen. So the way
you know the world is really very uncertain. So
basically you have portability.
Thank you very much. Unfortunately we don't have
time for more questions right now, but I'm sure you
will be happy to answer it.
Thanks.