Hello and welcome to my open source firmware status on AMD platforms presentation.
My name is Michal Zhygowski.
I'm a firmware engineer from Freedom Depth.
We are based in Poland.
I'm a Kerbernet guy mainly developing support for various platforms, mainly inter-platforms.
I also maintain the Braswell SoC, PC Engine platforms.
I'm also at the OpenPower system software technical work group chair.
And I'm basically playing with open source firmware since 2017.
For those who do not know Freedom Depth, we are in various places.
Like we're Kerbernet license service providers, we're UFI adopters.
We also provide FWD, the firmware update project consultation services.
And also we do some Yacht stuff.
So a little bit of information that I will use throughout the presentation about the
micro-ecitectures.
So in previous years I have been talking about various older platforms as well like for PC
Engine, APU1, KGP, D16, APU2.
All micro-ecitectures called Puma, Baldoser, Pile Driver and so on.
So I have based on some sample platforms so that you can sort of imagine what I'm talking
about if I mention some platforms.
And there are also the newer mobile socks from the Ryzen series which are supported
by Corewood.
This is Picasso and Cezanne micro-ecitectures.
These are the newer APU series from the Zencore architecture.
And also I will be talking about the newest developments like the Mendocino, Phoenix and
Glinda socks.
Note that they could be previously known as under different names because the original,
the target names were actually embargoed.
So you may have heard of Sabrina or Morgana socks as well earlier that were being developed
for Corewood.
So those have changed the names to the Mendocino and Phoenix.
So to review the last year's status, we had Picasso and Cezanne development quite complete
but there was no FSP yet for this design.
But this has actually changed.
The FSP was published in September last year.
There was also a development of the PSP firmware, AAB partition recovery supporting the AMD
AWW tool in Corewood.
So one of the patches was merged and the single one that I linked above is probably
duplicating the functionality.
So the whole AAB scheming stuff is used for any recovery in case of corruption of the
first partition or if the memory configuration after some changes in the setup application
would like make the system unbootable, then the PSP can, for example, switch to the AAB
partition and still be able to, for example, initialize the memory and boot the platform.
There was also an effort to implement the PSP firmware extraction with the same tool.
But it's still not merged.
It seems that the activity there quite stopped and there is no further work continuation
for this feature.
And I mentioned last year that there were new patches for the Sabrina sock.
The Sabrina has changed the name to the Menduchino, I believe.
And yeah, I said that in 2021 there was another negative attitude towards the old AMD platforms
that were entirely open with full source code for the CPU initialization.
If you'd like to see more details, please refer to the Corewood leadership meeting minutes
or the mailing list.
I'll also be talking about it also later in the presentation.
So in 2022, we also had many new features, option deprecations with each release.
Those deprecations sometimes causes the platforms to drop out from the master branch and they
are moved to the stable branch.
These new releases tend to move the whole Corewood drivers and code quality to the higher
level by replacing the old interfaces that were, for example, buggy or had some kind
of assumptions that made some old platforms, for example, boot.
And they were hiding some small errors because of those assumptions.
So it is necessary to bring these new interfaces to the old platforms as well.
But sometimes there's not enough time or resources, the hardware, to test everything.
So some platforms naturally will be moved to the old branches.
But thanks to the companies like PCNGs and a few Corewood developers, certain platforms
get the required support and the new interfaces are implemented.
So the platforms like PCNGs, APU2 is still in the master branch, but some other boards
were unfortunately dropped.
So another year came with new Corewood releases, as I said, and many old AMD platforms were
actually dropped.
To those platforms we can count PCNGs, APU1, some MSI MS7721, Lenovo AMD G505S, etc., etc.
That is a little bit unfortunate to see, but there was a lack of actually any testing or
maintainership that could also bring those platforms to the newest code, despite our
sincere efforts.
So we tried our best to actually implement the new interfaces and we sent patches quite
early.
It was in May 2021.
But the problem with reviewing the old code is that there is not enough understanding
how those old AMD platforms work, because the initial code that landed to Corewood was
kind of maybe proof of concept quality and was depending on the EJISA code that was published
by AMD.
And it was not in the best quality, so if something didn't work there, it was hard to
actually locate debug on the Corewood site.
And there were also promises that the code will be maintained, will be cleaned up, but
it didn't really happen.
So this burden of maintaining those old platforms were shifted to Corewood developers.
So through all those years, the code didn't improve that much.
So in such circumstances, the platforms will slowly naturally die on the Corewood master
branch that will be shifted to the branches created during each release.
We tried to save one of the old platforms, which is the KGP D16, we have sent over 50
patches that influenced simply the first booting stage of Corewood.
So this is just the beginning, but already the mass of code is enormous and we like the
reviewers to actually process all those patches.
So it is pretty hard to maintain those alternating platforms because like I said, there is very
little understanding how all those platforms will work despite all the documentation.
So Intel platforms are more straightforward, I would say, at least for other developers.
That's how it is.
Without the new SOCs, so AMD Cezanne development has been stabilized, there are many Chromebooks
running on it, and we even have seen two non-Chrombook platforms that have been actually sent for
review by the Starlabs.
These two laptops, unfortunately, cannot be built without the blobs or can be built, but
it will not produce a functional image because certain PSP blobs that are required, for example,
for the memorization, cannot be there due to the NDA stuff and so on.
So this is something that also needs to be solved.
But all other components are actually in place and you can track those patches and see what
is its progress.
As I said, AMD, Mendocino and Phoenix are quite new architectures that are being developed
in an upstream core boot.
While the Mendocino is quite in a more advanced state at Phoenix, Phoenix is a newer one.
And FSP is not published for those micro-architectures yet.
You can also notice some PSP blobs that are present in the AMD blobs repository.
AMD Glinda is like the newest micro-architecture that has seen the sunlight.
There is practically no information about that in public.
It may be also an embargoed codename, so it may change in the future.
And I do not have much else to say about that yet.
But regarding the blobs situation, the Starlabs could build the firmware for their laptops,
and probably boot core boot, but they cannot publish the necessary blob that is provided
by the board code to initialize the memory because each design may be different and requires
different configuration, how the memory topology looks like on a given platform.
So you have to provide that by the board code, and this becomes the problem because Chromebooks
have only soldered down memory, and there is no support, for example, to build the blob
with a memory configuration for a platform that has a solde modules, for example.
But I believe this is the main reason why this cannot be built to a functional image,
core boot image.
But the PSB, all the PSP blobs and FSP is present in the AMD blobs repository.
You can check its license on the repository.
It is quite permissive.
It allows the redistribution, so it's similar to the Intel FSP and micro-code licenses.
And of course, you cannot decompile, disassembly, et cetera, et cetera.
I've also took a quick look at the FSP release intervals, and these are quite delayed, I
would say.
For example, between the FSP for Picasso and the CZAN, there is one and a half year of
distance in the comments, initial comments on the AMD blobs repository.
And for example, the CZAN FSP was released one and a quarter year after the launch of
the processors themselves.
So as you can see, the delay is quite huge.
For Intel, I would say it is like a few months or half a year after the initial release of
the CPUs where the FSP is available.
So it is like much more stabilized ecosystem for Intel.
FSP for AMD is quite a new invention, I would say.
It's like maybe three or maximum four years old, while FSP is like for over seven years
or so on the open source firmware market.
Regarding the server platform status for AMD, nothing much happened here since the last
year.
We had those initiatives, for example, from Google, Rominec that showed the AMD, Rom,
and Milan proof of concept Linux boot or boot stuff.
But nothing else happened.
On the recent OSFC 2022, which was in September in Sweden, there was also something new, similar
to what Rominec showed.
So Brian Cantrell from Oxite showed some proof of concept of their firmware on AMD, which
was also based on Linux boot stuff.
But they had implemented some better initialization of the PCI Express so that the storages and
other I.O. could also work.
It was also very, very basic.
So nothing close to what you would normally see in the UFI from independent bios vendors.
Okay.
So to summarize up, what is actually the future of the AMD platforms in Corbout?
So for sure, the Chromebooks will be gaining the support.
They are backed by Google cooperation efforts.
They have partners, they have Corbout developers working in AMD.
And their partnership will make the project successful, for sure.
But for such old platforms like KGP or all the models that I mentioned that were dropped,
it is pretty difficult to actually keep them in the main tree.
It requires significant effort to actually maintain a board.
So either there must be a community that is willing to test Corbout images on their devices
but, on the second hand, who is brave enough to flash their daily laptop and possibly break
it because something didn't work.
So it is also not for everyone.
Also the quality of the initial code that was published for those old platforms, it
was just getting older and older and the actual cost and the effort that would be required
to bring it to the quality we would want is bigger and bigger.
So while, for example, the model of dropping the siliconization vendor code is good for
initial launch of the platform because you have everything modular and you just tune
it, in the long term it is not maintainable.
It can speed up the platform shipment by maybe 50%.
But in the long term it is a burden for the project that is supporting this vendor code.
And then we end up with such situation where the boards are simply dropping out of the
tree.
So in such conditions, all the AMD boards will naturally die and will be moved to the
branches.
So we may expect further platforms being dropped out and I think the next one on the aim is
probably APC and APU2.
For now it supports all the recent interfaces but we have no idea how long it will last.
Also we think that the lack of strategy for the long term support by the core boot leadership
is largely decreasing the value of the project itself because many people rather don't like
their boards being dropped because if they clone core boot, they clone the code from
the master branch.
And if the issue make menu config and want to choose the board, they see it's no longer
there.
So basically they think, oh, it is not supported anymore.
So this kind of value is decreased because people see that something is already not supported
and they lose their hope in the project.
So a new strategy would be required to actually keep those AMD platforms alive in the tree.
So what we think can save those platforms is our Dasharo firmware.
We are open for any AMD outcast from the core boot and we are working hard to actually prepare
a strategy that will make these platform support more sustainable.
We often also disagreed on many core boot leadership meetings with the current core
boot strategy but we also offered various ideas like crowd-firing and other stuff that
could potentially solve the problems like we were noticing but unfortunately those were
rejected.
If you would like, you can visit core boot leadership meetings for more details.
Also I have a short announcement for you.
Unfortunately, the official PC engines open source firmware support has been ended by
the PC engines company and the for 1901 was the last version that we released in the format
we have been doing for the past few years, monthly.
But do not worry, our commitment is still strong.
We want to further improve the PC engines firmware but this time we would like to release
it under the Dasharo branch with new features like UFI interface, DMA protection, setup
applications, setup BIOS password and stuff like that.
But it will be only a community-driven project.
We will not have any funding for that.
So your support is actually crucial in determining the roadmap and how and what the pace of the
development will be.
So I encourage you to take us our survey.
Your input is very valuable for us.
If you have any insight or want to support us, please do.
So to sum up, we want to make Dasharo a paradise for all AMD platforms and outcasts.
Of course, like I said, it will be community-driven so we want to make a success and have community
involved as much as possible.
Also, what we offer with Dasharo is we are ready to go test binary releases with transparent
validation.
We publish all the test cases on our documentation page.
You can use our hardware and software tools.
We have validated and used daily during the development which can help you in case of
any recovery or even deployment of the firmware.
We also provide high-quality documentation which explains every KVets and procedures
for the updates or the deployment and recovery of a platform.
So if you want to know more, please feel free to sign up to the Dasharo newsletter to get
up-to-date information about new features or releases.
So you may also find the new initiatives and new projects that we plan on the Dasharo documentation
page.
So I encourage you to visit.
Of course, I will gladly talk more about the IMD platforms because I'm pretty much short
on time here and cannot explain every small detail.
So if anyone is interested, we can go later in the evening for some beers and talk a little
bit more.
We can think on the Forza matrix or we can join the Sharo matrix as well where we are
more responsive, we can just come up with some good plays I think and talk a little bit
more.
The frame depth is also planning to hold two events in March.
It will be the Sharo User Group which is a forum of the Sharo users.
This will be like a small event with more structured schedule where we will discuss
different topics related to the Sharo.
And right after that, we will hold the Sharo Developers virtual pub where this will be
more like relaxed forum event where we will discuss any topic community wants and what
is of interest of them.
And yeah, feel free to be invited.
You can see more details in the blog post I link in the slides.
So that will be everything from my site and I'm open for your questions.
Yes?
I have a question regarding the PC Engine.
So the question was who was actually developing Core Boot for PC Engine platforms.
So PC Engine's company was responsible only for producing the hardware and distributing
it to the users.
And the initial support was being developed by a company called Elton.
But then they shifted the Core Boot work to PM depth, so to us.
And we were maintaining and improving, releasing the Core Boot binaries each month since 2016.
So it was like our efforts for all those monthly releases.
Okay, Theory?
I understand that Core Boot is not building the runs directly to test the platforms.
So the burden is on the users to build stuff.
Do you have any insights for facilitating testing in the future to prevent the boards
from being dropped?
So the question was whether we have a strategy for the boards being dropped because it is
users' burden to build and test the runs.
So like it was written on the slides, we are still working on the strategy for long-term
sustainable support for all the old AMD platforms.
But we want to shift the burden to build the runs from the users and instead provide tested
images.
At least tested what we can test in our environment, in our laboratory.
And if someone still has some issues or have some future requests, we encourage to create
issues on our GitHub.
And then we are considering what is the problem, what is the case, what is the cause of the
problem, actually, how to solve it.
And we try to narrow it down and in cloud possibly the fix in the next release.
But of course, as I said, if it is a community-driven effort, the pace will depend on the support
level.
So if somebody is able to contribute in any way, for example, fix the code themselves
or, let's say, provide the logs or flash our, for example, testing binaries to check
or gather more information because we may not necessarily have the exact hardware configuration,
then it may be the right step to make users less burdened with all those troubles with
flashing and breaking stuff.
Okay.
Any more questions?
Maybe.
Okay.
Let's change.
Yeah.
So the question is, what are the state of the patches and why actually there is a problem
to get the old AMD boards upstream?
So like I said, this cold is very old and it was in very bad quality, committed initially
with promises from AMD for the maintainer ship, which didn't happen.
So with each year, the code just was getting older and older and people who actually knew
something about it are no longer a part of Corb or are they just simply retired or out
of business.
And basically there is very few people that can actually understand what the given code
does and actually give some meaningful review for those patches.
So that is why it is very difficult to get something upstream for such an old AMD platform.
Okay.
In theory.
So the question is about the Corbud branching model.
How does it work and how to apply patches on them?
So whenever a Corbud issues a new release, so a tag is placed on the repository, the
current revision that is tagged is being cloned into the branch and called, for example, 4.19
branch.
And these branches are in no means stale.
So these can also be contributed to by the Garrett review system, but you have to target
the specific branch.
So even if you hook onto some revision on the branch, for example, and you want to patch
it, it doesn't mean that in the half a year it will not have the same tree state because
some backported patches could be landed on the branch and then your patches that you
were kept, for example, as a file, were no longer applied.
So it is not like that, that the platforms are just lying there with no option to improve.
That's not true.
You can always send patches to the previous branches as well.
So it works like any master branch, but you have to just target the older branch with
your patches that you sent.
So the development might still be active, but it does not longer benefit from the new
features that are basically landing on the master branch.
Okay.
Any more questions?
Yes, please.
So for example, again, for the QGB-16, which is based on corg.11, we know that corg.11
is moving for that platform.
So can we hope that the corg.11 branch involves the point where that was more of my question,
where you were expecting corg.11 on the non-master branch, but the branch that is still active
for that one?
Okay.
So the question is, what can you expect on the 4.11 branch, for example, with KGPE?
Well, that depends on the community.
If they were to backport some patches that should land on the 4.11 branch, that is possible
actually.
But probably the older the branch, the less activity there will be on them.
And if somebody would like to backport some features, then it's probably more efficient
to do it on newer branches because the gap is just only getting bigger and bigger.
So if anything, it would be better to work on the fork that we already have, where we
rebase all the code, rewritten most of the parts that were in very, very bad shape.
And yeah.
So basically, it is not impossible to have something being developed on the 4.11, but
it is rather unlikely to happen right now.
Okay.
The time is up, so I can answer any questions later in face-to-face talk.
And yeah.
Next presentation in eight minutes from theory about the HEDS project update.
So stay with us.
Have a great day here.
Thank you.