Hi, I'm Sean.
Today I'm going to talk about semi-hosting in the context of U-Boot and what it is and
how it works and maybe why you might want to use it.
So first I want to ask how do you bootstrap a system?
So you might do this for two reasons.
One, you have a new board right from the factory and it has nothing on it at all and you have
to get something on it.
And the other one is maybe you bricked it and this happens to me sometimes, actually
happens quite a lot, especially when I'm working on U-Boot and the board will no longer boot.
So there's two basic steps usually.
The first one is you want to get something running on your board and the second one is
you want to then write something to storage so you don't have to do the process again.
So there's a variety of protocols you can use.
USB, of course, I like UMS, it's very nice, it makes your device look like a USB flash
drive which is very, very convenient.
There's also a bunch of Ethernet stuff, the classic TFTP.
Fast Boot makes an appearance twice because it can do both.
If you have an SD card, bootstrapping is super easy, you just pop out the SD card and put
whatever you want on it and put the SD card back in.
But a lot of boards don't have SD cards, so this is not always an option.
There's serial.
This is usually kind of slow, so you might only want to use it for the code execution
part but it's definitely there.
Some boards have it built into the bootloader, you can just flash something over serial.
And there's also JTAG.
And JTAG is kind of a classic one.
Also slow, you probably wouldn't want to flash your whole root file system over it but it's
pretty reliable and a lot of boards have it.
What if you only have JTAG and you don't have any of these other nice protocols?
So I'd like to take a little bit of a different approach to the problem and let's talk about
something totally different which is the NXP Core IQ line of communications processors.
These are the newest iterations of a very old line which stretches to the M68K and there's
a very long lineage of power PC stuff in there.
And they tend to have lots of Ethernet, some PCIe, some USB, but not any display interfaces,
so they're not really media socks.
And they often have hardware accelerated networking.
So you can do some stuff in hardware which you would normally do in software.
And this is kind of the main selling point on why you might want to use these.
So all of these have something they call a reset configuration word or RCW.
And this started back in the power PC days as just basic initialization.
What NDS ministry sock is going to be, maybe what dividers you're going to have on some
clocks, how wide your boot bus is, what are you going to do with your debug pins.
This is kind of a small amount of data so they stuck it on some pull ups and pull downs
on some of the pins.
And this is a very standard thing you'll see on a lot of different socks.
And then they wanted some pin muxing because when they originally started with this, all
the pins were fixed function and you can sell more chips if you can change the function
of some of the pins so that you can use USB on one chip and maybe Ethernet on another.
So they added some pin muxing and they added it to the RCW.
And then they added a lot more pin muxing because the more pin muxing you have, the
more applications your chip can fit into.
And so they started running out of pins because they started getting maybe like 128, 256,
512 bits of stuff that they needed to configure.
And so they decided they were going to put the RCW on the boot device.
So the first thing the sock does when it boots up is it reads off this RCW and it configures
all the pins and then it continues with the boot.
And this is kind of convenient but it creates a chicken and egg problem where in order for
your sock to boot up there has to be something on your initial device.
And if you're in a situation where you have to boot strap it, there's nothing there.
So the sock won't boot up.
So what they did is they created a hard coded reset configuration board.
This is for maximum compatibility.
They would disable all the peripherals and you would just have your boot device.
And so you could always boot into this and be safe and not break your board.
But this is not so great because they never added runtime pin muxing.
So this chip you select a function for your pins and you can't change it.
There are a few pins where you can change it but for the most of them you're stuck.
So when you have this maximum compatibility RCW with everything disabled, you have no
Ethernet, you have no USB, you have no serial even and all you get is JTAG and your boot
device.
So NXP knew they had a problem and they decided to solve it by introducing this override.
So you would boot via the hard coded reset configuration board and then you would program
via JTAG the values that you actually wanted that would enable all your peripherals for
your board and then you would do a partial reset and it would come up and it would load
everything like it was supposed to.
But there's a couple problems with this.
The main one is that they never documented this stuff so in order to use it you have
to use the JTAG probe which is like most JTAG probes kind of a gouge because they know you're
buying the chips so you got to have the JTAG probe and you have to use their IDE which
is a yearly subscription and they're not cheap.
So this is not a great situation and if you didn't think this was great, here's a glowing
review I found on the forums.
Our manufacturer uses a single PC to perform the initial programming.
On this PC they have an evaluation copy of CodeWarrior which is their IDE.
Every time that evaluation copy expires they erase the hard drive of the PC, install the
OS again and load another evaluation copy.
So this is not ideal and I thought about how I might address this and make it better and
I remembered something that I had learned about a couple months ago which is called
semi-hosting and the basic idea of semi-hosting is that you attach a debugger, in my case
it's over JTAG and your code is going to execute a special breakpoint instruction and
when your debugger sees this it will read out their an opcode in R0 and an argument
in R1 and it will do something for you and then it will give you a return code back in
R0.
And this is very very similar to how sys calls work because your program will execute a special
instruction, the operating system will read out your registers, it will do something for
you and give you a return code.
So what do you get?
Well the thing that I wanted most is serial because I didn't have any.
So first I looked at some of the sys write C and sys write C is basically put char.
So we can implement put S here and so we're going to take in a string and we're going
to loop over all the characters in the string and for each character we're going to trap
or execute our breakpoint instruction and we're going to pass for our opcode write C
and we're also going to pass a pointer to the character and if you may know that put
char actually just takes the character and so this is kind of an unfortunate performance
implication because we have one breakpoint and one memory access per character in the
string and for JTAG this is not very performant.
If you've ever used a 300 baud modem you know that it's very slow.
This is even slower so this is really not useful if you actually want to use your serial
output.
So we can do better though.
They also have something called sys write zero and this is basically put S. So our PIDUS
implementation gets very simple.
We're just going to trap with write zero and now we get one breakpoint per string but we
still have to do one memory access per character and the problem is that we don't want to read
off the end of the string.
We have to make sure that we don't go past the null terminator.
So the debugger has to read a character and then see is it the null terminator and if
it's not you read another character and you keep doing this and we really don't want to
go off the end.
But the problem is that for JTAG setting up a read is a pretty intensive process.
There's a lot of overhead and it can be still pretty slow.
So this is faster, about ten times as fast but it's still slow.
Really not usable.
But we can do even better.
So we're going to use sys write which is basically the write system call and for this
one because we have multiple parameters, the previous ones only had one parameter so it
just goes in the argument.
But for this one we're going to fill in our arguments inside of a struct and we're going
to take the file descriptor and the buffer and the length of the buffer and we're going
to fill this in with standard out and our string and the length of our string and then
we're going to trap and we're going to pass a pointer to our struct and this is generally
how we pass multiple arguments to semi-hosting because there's only one argument register
so they will take a pointer to the struct.
And so now we get one breakpoint per string and two memory accesses per string and this
is reasonably fast.
We can do stuff with this and it's not glacially slow.
So this is the kind of implementation I ended up using it.
And if you've been paying attention you'll note that sys write kind of implies the existence
of sys open and you can open any file on your host system which is pretty convenient and
you can do all the standard stuff like seeking it and reading it and closing it.
We don't get stat but we do get the file length which is mostly what we want because usually
we just want to open it, find out how long it is and then read the whole thing.
So in U-Boot you may classically do something like this.
If you want to load your Linux and then boot it, you're going to load it from MMC0, add
a particular address and then you're going to give it a file name and then you'll boot
it.
And so we can replace this with load hostfs which is the something on your host debugger
file system and that Linux image will get read from the directory that you're running
your debugger from.
And it's the same structure because under the hood it's using the same API.
And there's a dash because there's only one hostfs and we don't need to have multiple
debugger support.
And there's a special file called colon TT which I think stands for teletype and this
is your standard in and standard out.
And almost everybody uses this except QMU because QMU doesn't have this huge overhead
for memory accesses so they don't actually care if you can use your console with read
and write and so you just use write zero with them and it works.
So one classic problem with booting with JTAG is that your regular boot process is going
to look something like load SPL and SPL is going to initialize DRAM and then SPL is going
to load regular U-Boot into DRAM and execute it.
And when you do this with JTAG instead you have to load SPL over JTAG and JTAG is going
to run and initialize DRAM and sometime you have to load U-Boot into DRAM over JTAG.
But we don't really know when.
And so a really classic way to do this is you just pick a time and you wait that long
and then you load U-Boot.
But this is kind of awful because if you have any kind of variance in how long DRAM initialization
takes or how long it takes, especially if you're doing other hardware initialization,
you have to just wait a lot longer and in the average case you're going to be doing
nothing.
And this can really drive you nuts as a developer because you might be waiting like 20 seconds
because sometimes it takes 20 seconds but most of the time it doesn't.
So you can also re-implement DRAM in TCL and this is a really common thing for vendors
to do because they love just, you know, it's very simple for them.
They just write all the registers and it happens over JTAG.
And this avoids the whole timing problem because we know exactly when DRAM has been initialized.
But it's a totally different process from normal.
You have to specify your parameters in a different format, in a different language.
It's not going to be tested as much and it probably won't initialize things in the same
way.
So it can be more buggy and it's kind of worrisome, especially when you have to, your regular
U-Boot will work fine and maybe this doesn't work so well.
But semi-hosting makes this really simple because SPL can load and then it will, over
JTAG, initialize DRAM and it says to your host, please load U-Boot at this address and
your host will do that and then it continues on its way.
And it's extremely simple to use and it solves this whole timing problem, which can be very
annoying.
So what else do you get?
Well, we get some error handling.
Error know is practically essential to find out why something failed.
Is error is not.
The idea of is error is that you will pass in a return code and is error will tell you
if it's an error or not.
But the problem is that some of these semi-hosting commands have different semantics for the return
code.
But most of the time, the semantic is negative numbers are errors.
So effectively, you're doing this whole big semi-hosting call just to compare to zero.
So I don't really know why this is in here.
And there's actually several functions that are kind of like that.
For example, sys time will get you the real time, which can be helpful if your device
doesn't have an RTC or you don't want to initialize it.
But sys elapsed will get you the number of ticks that your program has been running.
So maybe you would use this for benchmarking.
But the overhead of doing semi-hosting is a lot larger than the amount of precision
that you're going to get.
So I'm not really sure why you use that one either.
There's some libc emulation.
You can pass it in a command line.
U-Boot, we don't really need this because we have the environment and we have the device
tree.
And those are kind of classic ways to pass in parameters.
But if you're not using U-Boot and you don't have this sort of system set up, you can get
command line parameters pretty easily.
There's also assist heap, which is where you tell the device where it thinks the heap is
and where it should malloc stuff.
But usually you know this when you compile.
You say this address range is going to be where I'm going to stick my heap.
So also I'm not really sure why that's in there.
And as you may have noticed, you can write files.
So of course you can mess things up, especially on Unix, where you can open up a lot of files
that aren't really files and do some fun stuff with them.
But you can also just run arbitrary commands and you can remove files too.
So you have to really trust this stuff that you're going to run.
Because as far as I know, no one does sandboxing.
They just implement all this stuff.
So maybe they shouldn't, but that's how it is.
So if you've ever used semi-hosting before, you may be familiar with this problem.
Breakpoints are actually invalid instructions and your program will crash unless there is
a debugger attached and the debugger will handle it for you and you won't end up executing
it.
So typically you would have to have two programs.
One with semi-hosting enabled and one with semi-hosting not enabled.
And the one with semi-hosting enabled you'd have to run with a debugger.
But we can get around this using a pretty simple trick.
This one is from Tom Verbuehr.
And the idea is that in your synchronous support handler, you first check to make sure that
we have an invalid instruction and otherwise you panic which probably involves printing
out the registers or doing something complaining loudly on the serial which you might not have.
Then you would do, we need to check to make sure our instruction which is held in ELR
is the semi-hosting ARM64 HALT instruction which is the special breakpoint.
And the lower bits of the PC are actually not the PC on ARM because they have stuff
like are you in thumb mode or not.
So we need to mask those off.
You could probably just do and tilde 3.
And if we actually find out that it wasn't supposed to be a semi-hosting instruction,
we're going to disable semi-hosting which on your processor can do whatever it wants
but on U-Boot it just sets a global variable that says we don't have semi-hosting, don't
try it again.
And then we pretend that we get a failure.
Negative one is almost always a failure.
And then we advance the PC by 4 bytes.
So if you want to use semi-hosting in U-Boot, you can enable these configs.
The first one enables semi-hosting of any kind and also enables this command.
The second one, semi-hosting serial, will get you some serial input and output.
And you'll probably want this serial put s because normally U-Boot will print a character
at a time and put s will group those characters into strings and print them all at once.
And if you want to have this thing, you will need to enable config semi-hosting fallback.
And if you want to use it in SPL, then you can enable the SPL versions.
There's no serial version because U-Boot always enables the serial device in SPL that it's
using in the regular U-Boot.
And these are the things that I worked on adding.
And I also worked on config semi-hosting a lot but the basic support was already there.
There's also RISC-V support from Kautok console.
And this is pretty recently added so it's either in the January release or maybe the
March release, I'm not sure.
And if you want to know more about how to enable this, we have a documentation link.
And of course you're also going to need a debugger.
So I like to use OpenOCD, maybe because I'm a masochist.
And OpenOCD is a debug server for JTAG.
So the idea is you launch OpenOCD and it connects to your debug probe and then you can tell
the debug probe to do things like start or stop your processor and you can also attach
the GDB to it like it's a running process.
So this is pretty simple for OpenOCD.
You just halt the processor, you enable semi-hosting and then you resume it.
And typically what you would do is in between this enabling semi-hosting and resuming, you
would load your program and then resume at a particular address.
And this you could stick in a script and just run and automate the whole thing.
So there's a couple of downsides to OpenOCD.
You can kind of think of this as like a wish list or things that annoy me but not enough
that I fix them.
The one of them is that it uses the same terminal for regular logging messages like I attached
to the debugger and that sort of thing as semi-hosting output so they can be kind of
get intermixed.
So you have to watch out for that.
The serial is cooked, which means that when you type something, nothing happens until
you hit enter and then everything happens.
And this is kind of okay because if you're editing a command line, it's generally really
slow if you hit backspace and then you have to go to U-Boot and U-Boot interprets the
backspace and echoes it back and then it gets displayed on your terminal.
So cooked is nice here.
The problem is that OpenOCD is single-threaded so while it's waiting for you to input, it's
not doing anything.
So if you unplug the device or you hit control C in your debugger, it won't notice until
you hit enter.
So this can be kind of fun especially because even if you know about it, you might forget.
And this single-threaded thing also ties into there's no sandboxing.
So ideally you would do something like fork off another process and maybe unshare some
stuff or put it in a CH root and then that would be where you would run all your semi-hosting
stuff.
You could run the file and you could limit it to just a few files but there's no sandboxing.
So your whole system is there.
Once again, you have to trust your stuff.
So should you use semi-hosting?
I would say not unless you have to, especially not the serial stuff.
But it's good to have.
If you have to use it, it's nice.
And sometimes it's convenient.
If you're doing emulation, it can be really simple because you don't have to emulate an
MMC device.
You don't have to write a driver for an MMC device.
You just call your semi-hosting instruction and you can load the file right into where
you want it.
And you don't have to do any hardware.
And if you're already using JTAG boot, this can be really nice to solve some of your sequencing
stuff.
But I wouldn't recommend it in general.
So I'd like to thank a couple people.
Tom Verbuheir wrote a blog post on this stuff that got me thinking about the whole thing.
Andre Pshivara did the initial semi-hosting and he also worked with me when I was upstreaming
my stuff, so I'm grateful for that.
And of course, Tom Reaney and Simon Glass, who reviewed and merged all of this code and
a lot of other patches along the years.
And of course Merrick, who put me up to this talk.
And Seiko, who employed me while I was writing the code.
And if you're interested in this, there's that blog post I was talking about.
There is the RISC-V software spec, which is just the ARM software spec, but they use a
different instruction and different registers.
And of course the ARM software spec.
And this link may die because ARM has a tendency to rearrange things, but for now it works.
Thank you.
Does anyone have a question?
Questions?
Yes, I do.
Can you actually use semi-hosting for serial bundle in Linux?
Yes, but only for debug prints and I haven't looked into it that closely.
I think the whole stopping Linux to do a breakpoint is kind of invasive because Linux tends
not to like that because your interrupts for that core will just not happen while it's
stuck on the debugger.
And you can kind of break your devices that expect there to be an interrupt that gets
handled in a reasonable manner.
So typically when you stop the processor in Linux, like your EMMC will just break.
So generally I've only seen it for debug prints and usually only if like you can't get to
the real serial console.
Yeah.
Okay since we have a couple minutes I have a one more slide.
So normally when you will print something this is what it gets, it'll get like hello
and it'll normally print this like H E L L O slash R slash N and it inserts the slash
R and it'll do it one character at a time.
But as we've established earlier this is gleefully slow on semi-hosted hardware.
So what I initially did was this and I printed out hello slash N and then I added the dash
slash R. But this will actually break things because they expect it to be R N and not
N R even though like functionally they're the same.
So I ended up having to do it the other way.
So if you ever implement this stuff be aware of that.
Although if you are doing this like on a microcontroller you can probably just put hello R N in your
strings and maybe that's better.