So today we will talk about Trustful
Free Platform Module Project.
So hello, I'm Mache.
I am currently Engineering Manager at 3M DEP.
I'm an apostles contributor for several years.
I'm interested in various stuff, build systems.
I enjoy build-rebrosivity especially.
I like embedded systems in general.
I work to several layers with embedded Linux projects.
Now I'm also working with some stuff with Cardboard.
Also, security aspects is what I'm interested in.
You can have some compact information on the slide
if you want to reach me.
Some of you already heard that.
We are a free and deb, a parent-based company
of various variants in the market.
We work mostly in open-source firmware and embedded Linux
areas.
And we are a part of various organizations, various open
source initiatives like Corebook Listener Service Providers
or Reactor Participants.
So to the agenda, so let's start with explaining
what the TWPM project is, why we decided to start one.
We'll talk some stuff about TPM modules.
Then we'll explain how we started such project, what
challenges do we expect, what roadmap we have,
and what's the current state of the project.
So trustful reverse trusted.
So you probably know the trusted platform modules.
So we came up with a trust world free platform module.
So to indicate that the goal would
be to make it a bit more trustworthy than it is today
by providing the open-source firmware for that one.
And the goal also would be to be compliant with the TCGPC client
specification, which might be, in fact, quite difficult
or maybe even impossible.
We'll see.
We will discuss also that later.
But yeah, that's the goal.
The project is funded by the internet, by NGI Azure Fund.
So why we came up with the idea?
The traditional TPMs are dedicated microcontrollers.
And not typically, they always have proprietary firmware,
which can be easily audited, at least not by regular users,
maybe by some governance, maybe.
If there are bugs, they might not
be fixed depending on what the vendor is planning for,
site line TPM module, TPM chip.
There are also capabilities which
might be limited in some cases.
And if there is no firmware update from vendor,
they might not be modified by a user.
There are also several different interfaces,
LPC, which is present mostly on older motherboards,
but it's still commonly used.
There is also SPI, which is typically
present on newer PCs.
And there is also I2RC, which is present mostly
on mobile devices, or also on TALOS.
So another problem is that if you at some point
wanted to buy a TPM module, you probably
know that there are a bunch of different types of connectors
need to get one which is compatible with your mainboard.
Even if they look the same, they are really not.
And if you plug an incompatible one,
you may even break your module or even your mainboard.
For example, we can see LPC connectors for MSI and Asus.
They look the same.
The MTP is in the same place.
But the ground and power is swapped,
so some smoke may happen if you look at Asus to MSI
or all the way around.
Similar stuff for SPI.
Also, connectors look the same at the first glance,
but they are very, very different
for different motherboards.
Even for the same vendor, you can
have different type of connectors,
and there are many, many more.
So at first, we wanted also to address the hardware problem.
But it looks too complex.
We want to focus on just the firmware for start.
The variety of connectors is huge, bigger than anticipated.
So at the state of the project, we focus purely on the firmware
and connect it even by some jumper wires to the motherboard
just to have some proof of concept in the firmware.
And then we can worry about some other stuff.
So how can we start with the project?
We need some code to process our TPM2 commands.
There are a few simulators or command processors out there.
At least we know of two of them, the Microsoft implementation,
which provides simulator code for various OSs.
There are also some interesting samples in that repository.
There is FTP and trusted application
for us, Parham TransZone.
And there are also some samples for STM32, Nucleo,
which is what we will be interested the most.
And then we also have a simulator from IBM.
Maybe there is some more.
I think these two are the most popular ones.
So we took a look at the Nucleo sample
we just mentioned just before from the Microsoft TPM reference
stack.
So it was created like four years ago,
contributed, and it's not either maintained or tested.
So there is no single person who knows if it ever worked,
basically.
It looks like it was developed in a Tonic True Studio, which
is another existing software.
Currently, it was replaced by some other STM32 integrated
development environment.
And we also asked about the status in general of the sample
codes.
So the answer is that these are just
contributed at some point in time
and may or may not work currently.
So we took a closer look at that piece of code.
We have converted the project into the newer programs.
We're able to build at least to a certain point
to at least run it on the Nucleo board.
We noticed there is some VCOM application.
It was presumably used for testing the solution
on the application for Windows.
We haven't even tried to bother with that.
In fact, as we know, what kind it might be
to build some old Visual Studio stuff.
But we look at the code.
We saw that the STM32 code can accept TPM commands via USB
CDC.
It can process it.
It can return some response, or some simple command response
was there.
But what was important is some custom protocol
was involved here.
So there was no interoperability with existing tools,
such as TPM tools stack, or with existing TPM interfaces,
because it was a very custom one.
And the interoperability is a major goal of this project
as well.
Also, the resources on the NCEU was quite low.
So at this point, we had a rough idea
of what we have to face with.
So we want to also show how different the flow is
for the TPM2 simulator versus the TPM2 actual hardware.
The block on the top is, we can say,
what Microsoft or IBM reference implementation provides.
It just provides TPM2 command processing.
For the simulator, that's fine.
It uses sockets and communicates with the TPM2 software
stack in the OS directly.
But in case of the hardware, you need
to plug in the actual module to the motherboard.
So we need all of the plumbing.
So there are also dedicated specifications
on that in the TCG.
So those are the orange blocks that
needs to be implemented in the firmware.
So we need all of the plumbing to pass the commands
from the microcontroller through the motherboard connectors
to the OS drivers, and then at last to the TPM2 software
stack in the operating system.
What are the challenges, current and expected?
One of the first was the global chip shortage,
which happened in the meantime.
So even if you wanted to use the STM32L4,
it was no longer available to the source.
The other microcontroller was also quite difficult to get.
And the project in the samples was developed
using the hardware abstraction layer from STM.
And if you wanted to switch to another hardware,
you would need to rewrite that thing at least to some point
to another hardware abstraction layer,
and then the chip becomes unavailable,
and that would go on forever.
Also, we do not have the requirements
clarified that were at that point.
So we believe that what must be done
is to have some OS handling the TPM stack.
So we are looking into ZFRA OS to have some better hardware
coverage and just implement the TPM stack in the ZFRA OS.
So we can switch between boards more easily.
Another challenge is different types of timing problems.
The TCG specification requires some timing
at different levels on the hardware level.
For example, some registers must respond in some milliseconds
and so on.
It might be difficult to achieve such responsiveness
on just a microcontroller.
Maybe we will need to fall back to FPGA in some cases.
Definitely, we need to fall back to FPGA for LPC interface,
which is not existent on general purpose microcontrollers.
So we are developing a hardware block in FPGA for that.
There are also some NVRAM improvements
which can be made, and as said before,
a full compliance might be quite difficult
or might be even impossible to achieve.
For example, in case of the strict initialization time
and power requirements, because the power requirements are
quite low, I don't remember the exact value right now,
but typical microcontroller plus FPGA and also the boot time
might be challenging here.
It's a lot of moving parts.
We are still looking into that.
So the roadmap, the first step on the project plan
was public side view to documentation.
So that one is already live, although there is not
much content there yet.
We are just starting, we can say.
But what's there is already there.
We have already some structure.
And the roadmap is also public.
Then the hardware, as mentioned before,
we started with the nuclear as it was supported
by the Microsoft samples.
We're still exploring that, but just probably not
enough of a hardware to accomplish
the goals of this project.
Another one we are exploring right now
is one which is based on the EOS S3 SoC.
It combines Cortex-M4 and FPGA in a single chip.
That might be interesting to have a Cortex-M4 for TPM to stack
and to have some FPGA for fast response and LPC communication.
The far point which we are working on right now
is LPC implementation, FPGA.
So that's required to target the mainboards which
are currently in the market, which have only the LPC
interface.
Then we need to implement also all of the plumbing I showed
before on the slides.
So TPM registers as defined in the specification.
Also there is some specialized FIFA protocol
to pass the commands between the TPM and the host.
So that's a screenshot of some testing at the LPC module.
We are using Verilock Ecos, I believe, for creating the data
and GTK way for drawing that out currently.
Then some testing is also necessary.
We are already preparing some test cases.
We can start preparing them based on the regular TPM
modules.
And we want to expect that our module will
meet the same criteria.
Of course, we'll add some specific test cases later on
as well.
SPI protocol is also tricky, even though it
should be simpler in theory because the typical MCUs have
SPI.
But typically they are tested, let's say, in master mode,
not in the slave mode.
That's the most common case.
And also the frequency is limited.
The frequency of SPI on motherboards
is like 40, can be 40 megahertz or more.
But typical SPI on, for example, the STM32
is advertised to up to 24 megahertz.
But in reality, we have not been able to achieve that event
so far.
So that also might be difficult. And maybe also
FPGA can help you to achieve the timing requirements we need.
The eight point is exactly exploring
the usage of simpler hardware platforms.
So maybe we were hoping that maybe we
can achieve at least SPI connection on a board
without FPGA.
That would be simpler and would give more users
ability to test that out, at least on even Raspberry Pi
or with the motherboard so they can push that forward
and have some TPM module on some regular development boards
even.
So I already mentioned some TPM stack improvements.
Sorry, the flash drive for TPM stack improvements.
For example, the more test suites,
there are some problems we already seen with what was there.
There is no Redundancy at least.
Maybe also encryption because the SPI could be read out
from the board.
But we may leave the encryption for later.
But at least we would like to have the Redundancy
because otherwise it would be quite easy to pick the TPM
boards, which is not what we want.
We also need some unique identification
and some source of entropy.
That would be required to have some unique ID for each device.
And we need some entropy for cryptographic operations.
This is left for later.
We will see what kind of hardware
we will end up in the end.
We might use some hardware specific features.
And if not, maybe we can use FPGA finally.
Manufacturing, as you might know,
each TPM must contain unique key, endorsement key,
and also certificate related to that.
So we might provide a way for a user
to generate the endorsement key for their TPM.
So just to provide some scripts and procedures
how they can provision the TPM device.
And then also we imagine that it would
be nice to have some nice built system
so we can configure what kind of interface I want to target.
I have a motherboard with SPI, so I just
flip the SPI switch, rebuild the project.
I check the hash algorithm I'm interested in.
I choose what kind of hardware entropy I'm interested in.
And the goal here is to make the transition
between the boards more easy.
I can plug out my TPM, flush another firmware,
and use it on my new motherboard, which now supports SPI
and previously it was like LPC.
What's currently in progress is the LPC module
I showed the screenshot from.
The next TPM registers will be implemented.
We want to pursue as much as we can in the FPGA,
also in the simulation, before we
stick to serving hardware.
And we also need to determine how big of the FPGAs
would be required here.
We also in the parallel exploring the path of not using
FPGA and using SPI for on the STM or under microcontroller.
Maybe even if we could reduce the frequency to lower,
use it with the Raspberry Pi as a proof of concept that
would already be quite an achievement, I believe.
Maybe even if it wouldn't work with the regular mainboards,
maybe after some time it could be improved.
But it could be a nice step forward.
And dogs, we are working on the dogs.
They will be progressively filled with the results
of our parallel to work.
Yes, if you are interested in the progress
and maybe want to contribute, maybe
want to discuss about the project and create it,
start you can join our communication channels.
On the other hand, if you want to join the team or work daily
on open source signal projects, you
might approach me directly or use contact information
from the next slide.
So that would be it.
And we might have some questions.
Yes.
You mentioned the timing of problems.
Have you looked into how the system behaves if you delay?
Maybe they are.
Will things not work if you are too late
answering some things?
So I'm not sure if I follow exactly.
You're asking about some timing issues we had.
There are some timings defined by the TCG specification.
So for example, they say the given command,
TPM to command, must respond with the given time.
So that's one.
If you don't respond in that time, what happens?
And did you look into that?
We are not at the stage even currently.
We are at the lower layer.
So we are trying to get the planning done
so we can even send one command.
But on the lower level, yes, there
are also problems with timing.
At least on the SPI part, for example,
we had a problem that the STM32 we've been using
doesn't give us the enough flexibility
that we needed to follow this back in some cases.
There is SPI IP block, which can just send and receive
some data over the SPI.
But if you would want to specify some more,
like at the start of the transmission,
pull that line down or up, that might be more tricky to do
as well.
So maybe the FPGA would also help here.
Yes?
I have a couple questions about FPGA.
Have you selected an FPGA?
So the question was, if we selected FPGA, no.
As I said, we are just exploring the hardware on the right.
So they use S3 SOC.
So that one has Cortex M4 and FPGA integrated.
We need the one SOC, and that's the one we are analyzing right
now.
Maybe it would be fit for the project.
If you wanted to use FPGA only, because what is also important
here is that we require we need CPU to process the TPM stack
commands.
So either we can use hard CPU like that with FPGA combined,
or we need to use full-blown FPGA, soft call, and so on.
And that's another complexity.
We might be not also not that much experience with that,
because we need to run the TPM stack on the CPU.
So the question is, if we need to use internal flash
so that flash is not pampered with,
yes, that would be preferable, of course.
But at this point, we are flexible enough
to just have anything working, prove
that it's even feasible with some limitations,
even if the flash is separate.
It can be read out.
We might not care right now.
We focus on the most important part
to even prove that it's feasible or not.
And maybe other stuff can be handled later
once we prove that we can do it or not.
Yeah?
The hardware?
It's actually right that your problem
is that you're trying to receive data over SPI.
Essentially, your device tries to be an SPI slave,
but the SDM 32 SPI is not flexible enough.
And you want to report that M. Is that right?
So yes, it's right that we want to be a SPI slave,
because the main board is master.
Yeah?
Right.
So are you aware of chip lineup from Cypress of the feedback?
It's like a perfect tab plus a little bit of not really
FPGA but programmable code, which you can configure to some degree.
Probably.
If you implement your custom SPI handling in the M,
you will still get the perfect M to handle all the actual
processing stuff.
OK.
So there is a suggestion from the audience on the Cypress
series.
BSoC.
BSoC, yeah?
So I don't think we have considered that so far.
So thank you for that.
From the hardware with hard CPU plus FPGA,
we found so far like the EOS S3, which we're looking into.
It has some support, which is a plus, of course.
There are, I think, also one board from Goin, like Tank
Nano.
It was the name, I think.
So thanks for checking out the Cypress BSoC.
Yeah?
Did you consider trying to get an emulator-based development
environment working, maybe using some like QMU so that you are
sort of decoupling your hardware debug from your software
debug.
And depending on that QMU, you can implement the virtual LPC
and SPI devices.
And it also has a Cortex-M emulator, QMU as well.
So perhaps you're just thinking perhaps that might be a
possibility.
So the question is if we consider some emulator
development environments.
So as I showed, we are right now exploring some, at least
for the FPGA part, we start with simulation.
And we developed like LPC slave and host.
And we can test that out in a simulation for simulating the
whole Cortex-M. We have not done so far.
Maybe that's also something to consider.
Any more questions?
We can have one more, I believe.
OK.
It's a big risk to, let's say, move away from the hardware
part first.
Because a big part of using a TPM is actually being a trusted
device, somewhere you come back, and it's usable, though
it's virtual.
And by now, putting a lot of folks in the software and just
kind of ignoring the hardware part.
So the question is, I believe, if we have, let's say, software
film-aligning on the STM32, and how we can make sure that the
software was not tampered with, for example.
Yeah?
Yeah, tampered or maybe extracted or whatever.
OK.
Also, we know there are existing mechanisms, for
example, for different vectors have already microcontrollers,
different types of secure boots, and so on.
So we can verify if it's our firmware, if it's signed.
User can sign its own firmware, and otherwise the
firmware wouldn't boot, for example.
I believe, once we have the functionality, there are
already existing mechanisms that can prove that the
firmware was not tampered with.
But that's my understanding.
OK, so we are out of time.
Thank you.