Thank you.
So hello, everyone.
We have this talk with lots of nice acronyms.
We hope you enjoy it.
We will talk about accessibility today and about how to make your web applications more
accessible or with some easy tricks and make it accessible to everyone.
And we are Maximilian and I'm Danny.
We are from Deutsche Bahn.
It's a German railway company.
And yeah, we're both working in front ends, working for web applications.
Okay.
So, we want to start with a site from Bill Clinton.
It says congratulations to the launch of the web accessibility initiative, an effort to
ensure that people with disabilities have access to the internet's worldwide web.
And did some of you guess from which year this site is?
I will just give it.
It's from 1997, so accessibility is not a very new topic, a very new thing.
It was still there every time.
And yeah, we want to start a little bit with the awareness of accessibility, why it matters.
Then I will say something to some implementation things and then how you can ensure your application
is accessible.
Great.
Thanks a lot, Danny.
So first of all, accessibility, and we heard the talk by Mike.
It was really amazing to see so much even also regarding Drupal and all of the open
source CMS, for example, the development over there.
But when we talk about accessibility, it's quite easy to say that it's only about a specific
group in the end who would have disabilities.
And even also already said something about it.
It's really about including all the people in there.
This is the main paradigm in the end.
But even also it's us as developers who are bringing in the barriers, who are bringing
in a non-responsive layout in the end, who are bringing in something which doesn't work
under different circumstances.
So this is something that we even also want to dig a little bit more into detail today
and show you some things regarding those aspects.
So you might think of blindness, first of all, but it's about so much more.
It's about permanent disabilities, it's about temporary disabilities, and even also
situational accessibility issues in the end.
There might be, for example, you might be in a situation where you do have probably,
for example, your child on your arm or where you do have only one arm, even also for controlling
your device.
It might be light condition in the end.
There are so many more things than just this one thing that we might think about quite
easily in the very beginning.
To come to the topic why it's even more important is it's a legal topic.
There is the European Accessibility Act, who was enacted in 2019 already.
It needs to be even also transferred to the law in each country in the European Union,
in Germany, for example.
That's even already law since one year now, 2021, two years, sorry, 2021.
But for example, they will only penalize this until the beginning of the year 2025, but
it's similar to GDPR.
We even also, like we waited for a long time and didn't think it through, and so many companies
only started to think about and to enact on this topic when it was quite near to the state
in 2019 with GDPR.
To clarify things up a little bit about the structure, how it's being managed, how especially
for the web, and we're mainly talking about the web, there's obviously also accessibility
regarding applications about native development.
The structure is obviously in general, it's W3C, and they do have a web accessibility
initiative, WAI, who's formulating those web content accessibility guidelines.
These are some words that we're also using in our presentation in the end.
All of these rules, all of these principles divide into four categories in the end.
There are, I think, 60 or 70 principles who are divided into those four fields.
It's about perceivable, operable, understandable, and robust criteria that you could test, for
example, your website against, or that you could ensure the compliance of your web pages,
of your website or web application against.
Even also, those play up into three conformance levels.
We've listed them over here.
It's about that A is really the basis, and it should be ensured in all circumstances.
It's, for example, about providing alternative texts in the end for your images.
This is probably quite a simple one.
The other two criteria, this is about really dividing in between, for example, governance,
or governmental services in the end, who need to ensure that it's about these AAA criteria
that need to be followed in the end.
For example, for private companies, it's most likely about AA that they need to follow.
All of those criteria are like structures in those conformance levels.
Why is it important in open source projects?
You most likely know this image.
It's always used in the context of security, for example, but it's even also similar.
I mean, accessibility, it's even also some kind of a quality attribute in the end, which
is underlying and an attribute or something that you could also use for accessibility.
If you do have an inaccessible UI library, for example, or if there's something that
is inaccessible in this UI library, it might lead to problems in so many more projects.
The general paradigm about this is if there's even only one accessibility issue on the website,
it's inaccessible.
It's not about the amount.
It then is inaccessible.
That's very important in the end.
You need to test it and you need to, for ensuring this, it should be accessible.
That's why it's so important even also to test your stuff, but even also to contribute
if you do find something on the Internet to contribute to those libraries.
This might be groundwork for many other websites in the end.
Just one simple commercial about us, about Deutsche Bahn.
We even also do have a design system at Deutsche Bahn.
We obviously, in the very beginning, we started as inner source because it was kind of small
initiative obviously.
You only have some developers.
You have some designers over there.
Then we thought about quite quickly to go open source because from my point of view,
I'm even also doing privately, developing some polyfills and that stuff.
I think open source is one of the paragidings.
It's about learning in public.
Isn't it?
It's going out.
It's talking to each other.
It's about really getting feedback and that stuff.
We decided quite early to go open source and get feedback from the public even also to
get that information.
I'll lead over to Danny then for the implementation part.
Thank you.
Now, we want to focus on what's important when implementing an application or an UI
library.
What's the most important thing?
The most important thing, the really most important thing is use semantic HTML.
That's really the most important thing.
I can't say it often.
If you only use diffs, then you make things much more harder to bring in accessibility
later.
To make your application accessible later, it's way harder.
It's easier to change the button style of a button than to bring in accessibility to
a diff element.
A very big thing is that you use landmarks.
Landmarks are used to structure your web page to big elements.
Like a header, like a navigation, a side container, main part.
The landmarks are very important for screen readers to identify where is your structure
of the site.
Where is your navigation?
Where can I switch the sites?
Where is my main content?
This makes it really more easy for users of screen readers to find the content and to
navigate between them.
Another thing is the headlines.
When you use headlines, be sure they are in the right order.
Don't leave out some levels of the headlines or mix the levels.
Just don't make an H1 and after that an H5.
The headlines are like in a book.
If you open a book and you have the index, your web page should be structured like a
book.
Another thing are buttons and links.
People just use buttons and make on-click handlers.
On-click handler will navigate to another page.
Which isn't a good thing.
Please use links to navigate to things and use buttons to do things.
To make actions.
Don't use this.
Never.
Forms are also a great example where accessibility matters a lot.
You have separate elements in the structure of HTML for the label and for the input field.
You should link them together using the ID attribute and the connection.
You also can use area attributes to give another hint.
This is probably the sun.
A great example of accessibility.
You can use descriptions for more hints which are read out by a screen reader to the users
so that the users know the description is linked to this input field of my form.
The ID attribute is also very important.
It's not an art tech by the way.
It's an art attribute.
You should always use an art attribute to describe what's visible on an image.
It's very important that people who can't see an image that they know what it describes.
The only thing when you should use an empty art attribute is when you have just like a
decorative image.
You have a disk icon for a submit button and the submit button already shows it, the text
submit, then it doesn't make sense to have more content.
But otherwise describe your images.
Model dialogues are also a great example.
There are lots of U.I. libraries in the web which are not accessible and lots of U.I.
libraries implement like models from times where the browser didn't support the native
dialogue element.
These libraries have a big issue because when a model appears, sometimes a screen reader
will not notice there's a model and will so it will read out the content behind and that
doesn't make it accessible.
It's not good.
So the native dialogue element is a really good way to use and to make your application
and especially models accessible.
And there are other cool things which are not only good for accessibility issues.
As you can see, this is a detailed summary element in HTML.
And it helps also because if you use like command F or control F on Windows and search
for a term, it will automatically expand and will show where's the content inside the summary.
So, yeah.
That's also a good example for semantic HTML elements.
And there are other things like autocompletion for data lists.
So there are a lot of things that get more and more standardized and available in HTML
5 now and can be used by developers to implement which makes your application more accessible
without using area attributes.
So, area attributes are a way to it's like if you don't find a semantic HTML element,
then you may have to use a div.
And then you can think about do I need some area attribute?
There are some area attributes which helps for making things that aren't natively accessible
that helps to make them accessible.
For example, if you have an area life attribute, it helps to read out if you like notifications
on your site when you get notified from a server or something, a message appears and
you have to find a way to tell the user there was some message occurs.
So there are area life can be used to read it out for screen reader users.
Yeah.
And now may you ask how can I test easily that my application is accessible and I will
turn it over to Maxime.
Thanks, Denny.
So one thing that I'd like to quite quickly add to what you said, think of those HTML
contacts like little microfinance that the browser delivers to the user without the need
for JavaScript.
It's there already.
We do have polyfills for most of these features already.
So use them and by stabilizing this stuff even also through the browser vendors, we
might get better features even also in the future.
Like for example, on mobile devices you might get a different UI, you might get a different
keyboard or even also what we've shown regarding details and summary.
It might be something that the browser vendors then could innovate on and for example bring
in this cool feature regarding site search.
So QA and testing.
We had this question previously regarding testing.
I think one of the easiest things is really to use, let's say easiest things, you do have
the keyboard in front of you most of the time.
So you could use the keyboard, use the tab key to try to navigate in the application
that you're responsible for, that you're working for in the end and try to reach all of the
interactive elements in there.
Try to control the navigation for example.
Try to see whether the focus is existing for example.
There are so many things which are related to keyboard controls even only on the page
where we do assume that the users are using a mouse but this is even also something that
is beneficial for screen readers even also.
It's obviously not something that is the only part, screen readers is even also what Danny
talked about regarding semantic HTML but if you do see that it's not controllable by keyboard
it's most likely even also giving screen reader users a hard time in the end.
And this is the easiest one, Mike talked about some other tools we like to highlight at least
Chrome developer tools so they do have some really nice stuff especially for contrast
ratio for example we wanted to highlight over here.
They do have Google Lighthouse where you could obviously measure so much more stuff but they
do have an accessibility section in there even also giving you great tips in the end
and they even also provide you insights into the accessibility tree which is the basis
for rendering that stuff later on then in the or telling it to the screen reader.
There was a great talk yesterday by Mozilla even also in optimizing this regarding performance
and accessibility performance I would really suggest you to have a look on the recording
for this one.
Another part is the X DevTools.
They do have something for CLI even also they do have plugins for the browsers.
Why have we used the foster website over here?
No hard feelings I'm sorry about it.
Total issues 35.
Let's skip that.
Next slide.
Still it's about the same message it's about the humans test with humans in the end.
But it's something which gives you insight quite quickly it's something that is really
low level in the end but talk to colleagues in your company in your field in the end.
I'm even also working with several colleagues with disabilities and it was really inspiring
in the end to see how all of this works and to go through this stuff.
This is something that is really important talk to the users in the end who are using
this.
One of the last things previous to the questions that we wanted to bring up because we talked
about it we had a quick conversation about it.
We do know CVEs for example for a global database regarding security issues.
Why don't we even also do this for accessibility vulnerabilities in the end because it's even
also something that is becoming or that should become more important and that even also becomes
legal.
So why not do something similar for accessibility and we leave you with this.
Thank you very much for your attention and let's go over to your questions now.
Yes please.
I could repeat it.
There are some elements for the date picker.
It depends on the I would say yeah sure sorry I should repeat it.
There are some elements in the end.
Yeah yeah sorry.
There are some elements the question was there are some elements like for example the date
picker which are currently already identified as not being responsible in even the native
browser implementation.
So I think and the question was about whether I do know libraries which I could for example
recommend I think in the end it's depending on the context that you're working in.
So for example if there's a great Angular plugin you couldn't use it in your context
so you always need to sadly do the research and search for a good plugin.
I think and I talked about the standards previously I think it's so important to support those
standards because if we do standardize all of this stuff then the browser vendors do
have the chance even also to make things better in the future.
This is the main point so I couldn't necessarily give a give a perfect suggestion at the moment
but I do know about those issues at least date pickers it's quite hard.
There's another initiative who are trying to even also come up with new solutions because
even also most designers think about that these ugly let's say ugly standard elements
in the browser that they that we need to overlay them because of design reasons and there's
another initiative I don't remember the name who are even already coming up with something
for example for the select menu to build this new but again I'm sorry I could even also
we could add it to the slides afterwards and then it's in the link on the custom website.
Yep thank you.
Any more questions?
Yes please.
Yeah it's you Pablo.
My question here is that by the time a developer has a chance to do that it's been in this space.
At Dogebahn how do you approach this from a design perspective?
Actually I know how to do this in a way that will pass a test.
Yeah.
So I do even also say the question again how do we approach accessibility not in the end
not a testing but even already like for example in the concept phase and design process exactly.
So I think it's mainly about to have this scaling in an organization it's only the first
most important thing is about awareness from my point of view.
So even already in our onboarding sessions for new employees we are having onboarding
sessions we do have talks we do we do educate on accessibility even already.
So I think the main thing is about awareness for all involved people in the end for product
owners for designers for developers for testing in the end.
I think it's mainly about awareness I would say and then you could only scale.
So and I'd like to thank you for your product because we're really looking forward to your
product you talked about thank you.
So another question for.
I'm afraid it's not only about awareness it's also about the right skill set.
We are really struggling to find a talent accessibility talent in the design space.
Awareness is fine but it's also about experience and really challenging projects.
Totally totally it wasn't it wasn't about only aware you haven't said I know you haven't
said it.
It's it's repeated quite quickly it's not about only awareness it's even about the skill
sets it's about experiences but you need to start somewhere.
I mean you could build up experiences by starting and then having all the people getting those
experiences in the end.
I think I couldn't I couldn't have a better answer at least.
We do have several teams who are specifically working on this even also education but even
also testing from the very beginning even already educating concept and designers and
all of these colleagues.
But in the end I think it's yeah it's about skill set awareness and all of this stuff
education talking to each other all of all of that stuff.
This is what I could tell you for the moment but we could follow up.
Time's up okay.
Yeah we are still yeah sorry we are still here if you do have anything else to follow
up.
Yeah just come to us please.
Thank you.