Well, thank you all for coming. This is great. Now, where are my notes? They're not on the
screen. It's never good to go off and to give a talk where it's like, I cannot see what's
on the screen behind me. So, let's see if I can change that. And there you go. So, my
name is Mike Gifford. I'm with Civic Actions. I'm a senior strategist there. What I do there
is a lot of work on accessibility and sustainability. I'm also a Drupal core accessibility maintainer.
And I like to do a lot of talks on open source and accessibility and why it matters. Because
I think that there's something unique with our community that we can do, changes that
we can make that make a huge impact. So, and also just as a disclaimer, I'm not a designer.
I'm a PHP developer that sort of got the, you know, wandered into accessibility and then
suddenly had to deal with a lot of front-end stuff that I was not familiar with prior to
getting involved. So, definitely appreciate having all these, the attention of the designers
and that I've learned a lot from the design community I've worked with. But, a couple
things I assume that everyone here knows about open source. So, there's a great range of
open source tools. We know that there's only, you know, here we're going to be talking about
a few of them, but there's lots of really good accessibility open source tools out there.
I also want to go off and, you know, look at those. As you know, there's a lot of open
source tools that are really not, they're essentially dead in the water. Somebody released
the project. They don't have a community around them. I think focusing on those pieces of
software around accessibility that actually have a group of, that are actively engaged
really does matter, especially if you're starting to get involved with them. I'm also going
to use the short-term OSS for open source software. As far as accessibility, I just
want to remind people that it's not a small portion of the population. We're not just
talking about people who are blind. We're talking about 25% of the population. And if
you look at permanent, temporary, and situational disabilities, you're talking about 100% of
the population. Right now, you can probably all see the slides here, but if the sun were
in a slightly different position, you know, there would be a point where you may not be
able to see that, even in this presentation, just because we've got these gorgeous open
windows and, you know, yeah. So we have to go off and think about how accessibility can
affect all of us. We also have to keep in mind that there's both visible and invisible
disabilities. Many of us, how many here know that they work with people with disabilities?
Okay. There's a lot of people who don't know because you can't tell somebody who's colorblind.
You can't tell somebody who's dyslexic. You can't tell somebody who has low vision. There's
a lot of disabilities you cannot tell by looking at somebody from the outside. Even people
who are legally blind, you may not know that they are legally blind because they've learned
how to go off and interact with them, or interact with you. I'm also going to use the short-term
ALI, which is a numerum. There's 11 letters between A and Y, and it's what it stands
for. So why open source and accessibility? So bugs. Bugs are a big one. When in most
proprietary projects, you don't actually get to see a list of the issues that are there.
You don't get to get an opportunity to see who made what problems have already been reported,
but in open source communities, basically every one of them has an issue queue, and
often those issues are either identified as bugs, which is an important clarification.
Accessibility issues should not be future requests. They should be bugs. And they should
be tagged for accessibility, which many of them are so that people can find them more
quickly. With the Drupal community, we've actually started the process of trying to
tag them for specific WCAG success criteria. The advantage of that is that you can actually
start to understand who is affected by the accessibility challenges and have a more fine-grained
attempt to understand what are these issues, who does it affect, and how serious a concern
is this. So we're looking to try to do that with the Drupal community.
So open source communities are also really good because they tend to focus on trying
to have a... try to find a merit-based approach argument. So you're not looking for something
that is who's the most popular in the community. You want to try and find a best-cased argument
for why this is the best pattern for your project. So it's a really interesting experience
from that perspective. It's also neat because anyone can submit a bug. You just need often
an account on GitHub or Mantis or whichever else. That's a really useful feature as well
because you can be inclusive. Does anyone here know where to go off and submit issues
to Office 365 when you run into a bug at Office 365? Yeah. Good luck.
So the other thing is community interest. It's really interesting being involved in
the open source community because people want to have others use their code base. It's part
of the whole sort of feeling of this. You don't release the software so that other people
can say, wow, that's really great software. You release it so that people can use it and
say, this is neat. I have to learn from this. This is something that I can use to benefit
me. And so there's an inherent interest in the developers getting access to the code
and engaging with the population. And I think bringing people into the community is something
that's not easy to do, but it's something that many successful open source communities
are able to accomplish. The dripple phrase is, come for the code, stay for the community.
And not that dripple is the only content management system or piece of software out there. It's
one you should all use, of course. But it's not the only one out there. But that idea
is something that's mirrored by many other effective open source tools as well.
I also think that it's something where it takes a village to maintain any piece of software.
The internet changes very quickly. If you want to go off and adjust in time and be able
to make modifications over time, you kind of need to have a large group of people who
you can engage with them on. Some of the accessibility issues are really very complicated. The kinds
of issues that the dripple community has dealt with, even the simple ones. Does everyone
know about CSS display none? There's a really simple CSS code that is a huge accessibility
problem because developers or designers and developers use it to go off and hide certain
pieces of code from the browser so you don't want to see it. But it also hides it from
screen reader users. Trying to go from find a way to hide code visually but not hide it
for people who need to use it for assistive technology is a really big issue still. Technically,
not that complicated, but I'm sure that somebody here could write a PhD on how we dealt with
CSS and the challenges of CSS displaying none in the dripple community. Learning and sharing
is important. Trying to be able to engage with others. What we learn in dripple, we
try and share with WordPress and Joomla and Type03 and others. Again, that's something
we can benefit from that is unique to the open source community. Codes of conduct.
Diversity accessibility is part of a DIA framework, the idea of diversity equity inclusion. How
do you try and make sure that we are bringing in people and having a structure to go off
and see that there is more diversity represented and you're not just having a bunch of white
guys speaking at events is really important. Having that structure is useful for accessibility.
You don't necessarily have this for a piece of commercial software, but if you're trying
to engage a community, you're probably going to eventually, if you grow big enough, have
a code of conduct that deals with feedback mechanisms, deals with bad actors, deals with
people who act like people do sometimes. We don't always act in the most dignified and
organized and respectful manners, even in our issue queues. Having forums to try and
help moderate and manage that is important. The in-person events are also quite useful.
Again, you get to meet people. I don't know if there's anyone here who is blind or low
vision, but there certainly have been other people at this conference who have seen who
are either in a wheelchair or using a guide dog. There have been some people here who
have permanent disabilities that we would typically identify as being more severely
disabled. A lot of times community events like this will think about that. There will
be an accessibility page. People will ask questions about the accessibility of the website.
That also really helps. There's a low cost of entry. This may be a surprise to you.
But people who are disabled in our economy are generally the least well off. They're
the poorest of the poor because they often get a subsidy from the government. They often
cannot get jobs. That subsidy is often below their living wage. But just a quick joke.
Who here knows who the richest blind user in the world is? Who's the richest blind
user in the world? It's not Stevie Wonder. It's Google. Google is a blind user. Can't
see. Also, students are another element of low income populations. If you want to attract
students and engage students, open source is a great way to do that. There's a focus
on training materials, trying to bring people in and to document things. If you can document
an accessible way to do things, if you can provide a best practice that addresses accessibility
issues, it's much more likely that other people will follow that practice going ahead. It's
also really useful for a lot of open source communities to have a community where you
can reach out to an expert and get feedback if you get stuck. The number of stupid questions
I've asked that I've been able to get somebody who knows a lot more than me to be able to
help move me ahead so I can learn a little more about the project. It's really quite
important. Interoperability and standards. When I first started getting involved in accessibility
in Drupal, I thought, oh, because Drupal cares about standards, I can probably go off and
fix up the accessibility issues in Drupal in, I don't know, a year or two. Shouldn't
be a big deal because we care about open standards. Here we are more than a decade after me being
deeply involved in accessibility issues and we're not there yet. We're further ahead.
There's one of the most successful open source projects in the world but there's just a lot
of issues that you, it's a complex issue. There's a lot of, the more you dig, the further
you know, the more there is to do. It's an ongoing process and the goal of accessibility
really is to try and get, to be more accessible today than you were yesterday. That's the
goal. Let's see. If you're looking at an open source project and you're trying to figure
out how to go off and get acceptance and whatnot around that, just talking about open standards
and the value of interoperability, the value of, like if you build two standards that meet
accessibility, it'll also be useful for future use cases as well. Like, I don't know, how
many people here are designing for voice interfaces? Okay. You're not doing it now but probably
in the next FOSFSTM or one afterwards you're probably going to be designing for voice interfaces.
If you build for accessibility, it'll be much easier to interact with your voice interfaces
because the semantics are built in there and that's what really is important for driving
voice interfaces. Yeah. Open standards and just having communities that care about this
stuff. This is something that it takes a while to go off and to build up and maintain and
to sustain that sort of caring about it when you've got deadlines and ideas of, you know,
yeah, product deadlines and client deadlines and all that sort of stuff. So open accessibility
reporting, I wanted to talk a little bit about this. This is a, in the US, VPATs are a much
bigger deal. So VPAT is the Voluntary Product Accessibility Template. This is not something
that is very common in Europe because VPATs were a good effort 20 years ago but they don't
really cut the mustard in the rest of the world. They're not good enough for Europe
and they shouldn't be because they're largely a sales document at this point. But the WC3
went off and produced an evaluation methodology that's really quite useful and was developed
in Holland and was able to meet with Hiddi DeReeves who went off and developed the tool
that is behind the WCAG EM license. There's an interface that allows you to go from, to
guide you through the process of doing an accessibility report. And one of the neat
things about this is it has the ability to write a machine readable document that describes
the website you're meeting, you're trying to address. So if you're looking at an institutional
website, if you have the ability to have a machine readable, you can compare all of the
instances of all the software, all the licenses in one place. You can get a sense of how your
website compares to how accessible it is today versus how accessible it was two years ago.
Having that ability to manage that is really quite useful. And civic actions went off and
liked the idea of having something for procurement that could satisfy the VPAT requirements but
followed the modern model that the WCAG EM implemented. So we forked the WC3's WCAG EM
methodology and we created OpenACR which is an open source platform for creating accessibility
confirmation reports. So if you're looking at providing reporting of different products,
the OpenACR is a good format to do that and it was developed and paid for by the US government
but it's available for everyone. So cooperation versus competition. I want to say that there's
a neat thing about open source is there's a great deal of both. Yeah, there's tension
but we collaborate with each other. It's really quite nice. I'm on the Drupal Slack channel
of course but I'm also on the Twitter Slack channel so people can catch me in either of
those, not the Twitter, the WordPress Slack channel. So you can catch me in either of
those places even though they're often conflicting areas. But an area we worked with recently
was working with the European Commission with the WeFor Authors cluster and this was an
effort to take the authoring tools and how do we try and make the authoring tools better
so that the authors are able to go and to create, it would be easier for authors to
create accessible content. Right now most accessibility errors are caused by authors
who use WCAG editors to go off and create the content and there isn't necessarily enough
guidelines to structure them into doing the creating good accessible content. There's
something called the ATAG, which is the Authoring Tool Accessibility Guidelines and ATAG Part
B is all about trying to make it easier for people to do the right thing with accessibility
if you're creating a content and generally the authoring interfaces are not given enough
attention. This is the only study that I know of that certainly the Drupal community has
done to try and say how do we engage with authors to try and find ways to help authors
create better content. That's not something that is done often enough. And I also want
to just phrase the Drupal's proudly found elsewhere, this idea that you don't have to
build it all yourself. There are times where you can pick another project like we don't
have our own WYSIWYG editor, we use CKE editor. So when we have an accessibility problem in
CKE editor, we push it back upstream. We're involved in engaging upstream with other open
source projects. So I want to say it's really important for people, I know I'm running out
of time, but the idea of engaging with people and having lived experience. People with disabilities
have a lot of additional ideas to share and to contribute to your open source projects.
So don't rely on the automated tools, don't rely on your manual testing, don't rely on
your third party accessibility auditor. Try and bring in, those things are all good, they're
all useful. But if you actually have people with lived experience with disability testing
your interface, you will have a much different experience. You will have something you will
learn a lot more. And we can't necessarily assume that everyone with a disability has
the, like not every blind screen reader user is going to have the same experience. You're
going to, just like regular people, they're going to have a different experience with
the interface and they're going to use things differently and navigate differently to manage
the interface. Yeah, so the more diverse people you engage with, the more robust and structured
thing you're going to have. So it's definitely useful there. Talent is another big one. Thinking
that you have open source projects need talent and there's a real need to try and build up
and to involve those people with a range of different skills and requirements. But also
people with disabilities are often very qualified but are restricted from working for, even
for tech projects. Whether that's because they don't want to go into the office or because
it's too difficult or order us for them to work with somebody else's IT infrastructure.
Because the interfaces that they work with are not built for accessibility. There's also
often not a culture of addressing and including people with disabilities within your organization.
So just making it so that you're as much as possible removing the stigma and seeing disability
is not something that you have to make special adjustments for but it's really a point of
innovation and a point of, yeah, it's a learning point for everyone to go up and build better
products if you have people who interact differently with the web. So sort of thinking about that
talent aspect when you're looking at your organization. Innovation, we've got Deque's
Axe, we've got tools like Luxembourg's Simply Alley PDF caller. My slides are all available
so all this stuff is going to be up online. There's a tool called Alley Watch, we're using
that right now which is doing some incredibly fast scanning of websites. We're looking at
being able to do government wide accessibility scans. We're also seeing tools like Sally
and Editorally which help to go off and support the authoring environment to give feedback
to authors who are in accessibility. I'm a big fan of Microsoft's accessibility insights.
I've got to say when I went to their office I was shocked at how amazing their team was
and how they were doing so much stuff the right way. I was like, I did have to tell
them that I was in the belly of the evil empire but was really impressed. It was a mind blowing
experience. Also, NDDA is an excellent screen reader developed by two blind developers in
Australia. Think about the money that's gone into tools like JAWS and VoiceOver from corporations
and governments and yet you've got two people who believed in open source that were able
to go off and build a really strong screen reader from that. There's other stuff that's
next but you're going to have to go off and read the slide later and get into that. There's
a lot of enterprise tools that are built on open source tools and there's the ability
to scale and to push up software and to engage with accessibility in your CI CD pipeline
is definitely something that is more and more accessible. Much easier for all organizations
to deal with. Now, if you have any questions, please let me know. Anyone using any accessibility
tools?
Right. You mentioned that one of the best ways of testing applications is to actually
get people who have disabilities ranging and there's all sorts of disabilities to actually
come in with accessibility. Do you know of any resources where we can learn how to do
moderating the accessibility test on people with accessibility issues?
The question is how do we learn how to go off and do accessibility testing and how do
we learn to do usability testing with or usability research with people with disabilities? In
terms of accessibility tests, there are some tools out there. If you look at Microsoft
accessibility insights, there are a series of videos associated with that. As with the
Wave toolbar, there are ones that can walk you through that. They may not be as prominent.
They may not be a what's your first step to get started. They do exist. We have a lot
of accessibility documentation as well which you can find on our sub site there that points
to some of that. It is a bit of an issue. As far as the usability research, I was just
reaching out to the Fable tech labs folks. They do amazing work with people with disabilities.
The thing is that people often expect to have people with disabilities do this for free.
But they don't have a lot of money to go off and sit around and do usability testing. We
should be assuming we are paying people with disabilities to do these tests. By engaging
with Fable, you will be paying people with disabilities to go off and do these tests
and get live feedback from people. You can learn a lot from that process. Not that you
always need to use Fable, but it will help you get some insights on how to do that. Any
other question? One more question? Yep.
You had this DEI mentioned before and I was thinking that we have sort of continued from
this instance of differences in the
like feedback and
Experience of like how they experience the software right so like when you do accessibility testing for blind people
You know that there are these difficulties
And I think it's also like very big thing to have a lot of
Newer divers and that yeah, also getting those feedback from the people who are usually maybe more quiet in the crowd
and have their experience also so it will be
For sure I mean there's a I didn't raise
Neurodiversity so the question was about neurodiversity and how do we try and make sure that we encourage more?
more support and testing and engagement with people of different neurodiverse backgrounds and
absolutely and and it's it's you know everything from from cognitive disabilities to
PTSD to
You know looking at people who have have
You know issues with dyslexia like there's a range of different, you know disability people have
Willings that I the WK has really failed on is is they've sort of allowed us to think that you could have one
One sort of website to solve all of your issues
And I'm baffled at how many how many websites don't provide support for even dark mode like all of our browsers and all of our system
Technologies provide support for dark mode. We've got SVGs and other tools that can provide excellent support for dark mode
Why why are doing our design systems not have support for dark mode generally they don't
Why aren't we trying to go off and build for that as part of our expectations?
This is something that would help a lot of people
even if they're people who who just are spending too much time in front of the screen and want to be able to have a little
Bit of a less intense experience especially in the evening
We should be building for that
And it's something that that I hope we do more and I think that that will help a lot of people with with
Neurodiversity issues, but but also just realizing that people like there's a there's a tool that was built by the by the IDRC
Which is the inclusive design research center in Canada?
That that's called the fluid sorry the the the the preferences editor
And it allows you to go off and swap your fonts your colors your you can go from two columns to one column
You can you have a table of contents that explodes and my time is up, so that's all I have to say on the subject
You