So we have Emma and Jess talking about what they learned about the Creative Freedom Summit.
So give a hand for them.
Hi everybody and welcome to our talk.
We're very excited to be here at FOSTA.
It's both of our first times here.
So very excited and nervous.
Had a great time yesterday.
So today we're just going to go through a summit that we hosted two weeks ago.
We're going to explain what it is for people who weren't aware of it and then we're also
going to see what went well and what could be improved.
So just a small introduction first then.
So my name is Emma Kidney.
I'm an Associate Software Engineer at Redhat in their Community Platform Engineering team.
Kind of the last year or so I've kind of been more at doing design work.
Kind of slowly doing more design work, less dead work.
I'm part of the Fedora design team and yeah, I utilize lots in every aspect of my work.
Yeah, I'm an active member of the Fedora community.
So I'll just pass you over to Jess then.
So I'm Jess and so I joined the Redhat team in 2022 as a Fedora community designer intern
for the Community Platform Engineering group.
And I've got all open source software, Inkscape, Penpot of course.
And just loads of other ones and creating numerous logos for the Fedora project as well
that you might have seen around.
So including this one.
So yeah, so a little bit of the Creative Freedom Summit.
It was a summit that we held, was it two weeks ago?
Yeah, two weeks ago.
So it was all over Jitsy and PeerTube and it's just, again, promoting loads of creative
software that people might know about.
So yeah, basically, yeah.
What is the Creative Freedom Summit?
So it's a virtual event focused on promoting open source tools, spreading knowledge of
how to use them and connecting creators across the FOSS ecosystem.
So the Summit's accomplishments and shortcomings will be examined in light of the first year.
So what we, so the primary goals for this were, of course, promote open source creative
software and also spreading knowledge of how to use it.
So it's very important, like there's so many free software that people don't know about
and it's great to give them that recognition.
And also connecting creators across the FOSS ecosystem so other people who use these open
source software can connect with each other and share ideas and all that sort of stuff.
And then our secondary goals were to promote the Fedora design team as well as a welcoming
group.
So especially if you don't have a platform to show off what you've done on open source
software, you can always join the Fedora design team.
We also created potential onboarding path for new design contributors as well and spread
info on how to use the creative open source tools in communities.
So again, same as the last one.
So showing how the Fedora design team will choose to make community stuff happen and
have sessions like how the Fedora design team do this, that and the other and hoping it
makes sense for easier for people to get involved.
So what topics do we cover?
So again, pen path.
So if you don't know what it is, if you missed the first talk, it's a web based design and
prototyping platform.
Inkscape as well, which I love.
And powerful, it's a vector based graphics editor.
Blender, Krita and Caiden live, I assume you might have went to the KDE stand that was
around and GIMP and accessibility as well, which is very important in the design aspect
of things like colour blindness palettes and stuff like that.
And then the free software was actually, it's like free patterns for different crafts, so
more kind of a hands on design thing rather than technical.
And creative professional, professional using open source software.
So we had some people as well who, and of course, us as well, like using free open source
in a professional aspect and many others.
So we had an amazing line up of speakers, so Maureen Duffy and David Roy, to name a
few.
And we had social hours that include the audience and helped build a sense of community.
So some of these include a hack and craft, which is kind of like the free software.
It's by the same person, Morgan Lemmer-Weber.
And so we were basically like for the hack and craft, we were all like knitting and making
sewing things, but also talking about open source and Pictionary and Gartic phone.
So it was really fun.
And then of course, wouldn't be possible without our sponsors.
So Fedora and Red Hat were the main sponsors.
And then the platforms we used to share was element, so people could interact in the chat.
Jitsi was for the live streaming part.
Oh, sorry.
Jitsi was the video part, so we all went into a call and then Piritu was the live streaming
part of it.
So yeah, I'm going to hand you over to Emma for the retrospective.
Nice.
Okay.
The retrospective.
So just some details then as well.
So when it took place, as Jess said, around two-ish weeks ago, January 17th to the 19th.
What platform?
We used Jitsi, streamed with Piritu, and then Element and Matrix were used for the audience
to interact with each other and the speakers.
What if you didn't make it?
The recordings are available on the Create Freedom Summit's Piritu.
And we'll soon be uploaded to Fedora YouTube when editing is complete, where we have some
great contributors at the minute converting the raw video files over into properly-caught
and published talks.
And was there a badge?
The important question when an event is run by Fedora.
Yes, there was a badge.
It was designed by Jess again and was able to be claimed by anyone with Fedora badges
account and it was claimed around 48 times, I believe.
And also if you're wondering why we had a badge, the Summit was all about promoting
open source design and then obviously as the Fedora design team, there can be a lot of
overlap then between the two communities.
Here's just an example of what the setup looked like if you were to attend the Summit.
So at the top there you have a little widget for the livestream.
We have another little kind of notepad feature there where you can type out any questions
you might have, some information, kind of frequently asked questions and then we have
the chat there then so people can interact with each other.
And also the background channel for the talk.
Oh yeah, oh yeah, because if you wanted to just watch the talk and not be involved in
the chat room, you just watch directly with the Piritu link as well.
How did the event go?
It went very well.
We had 18 speakers take part with an average of 50 viewers per session which is very good
for our first time round.
We had more than 700 unique viewers spread out across 54 different countries.
In the element chat room we came up to around 250 members.
So we were kind of aiming for 100 in the element chat room but so the fact we kind of doubled
that is great.
So what went well?
Viewers loved the setup we had.
They were able to watch videos soon after they were live as well due to the system that
we were using.
The chat room was very friendly and there was a real strong sense of community there.
The audience had a lot of back and forth with the speakers as well.
There was a lot of interactions at the social events and a lot of interest.
Also no code of conduct issues which is always nice.
So we got to see some amazing work.
We had some speed painting sessions there with grease pencil and blender that's been
painting with Krita.
An Inkscape tutorial.
There's a software blender as well.
There was a good few things about blender.
What can we improve for next year?
So what didn't work?
We're going to try and create a guide for next year with guidance on how to use the
platform because from a newbie perspective if you're not familiar with matrix elements
or that kind of thing it can be a bit far and a bit hard to get into.
We also need to look into auto captions then as well.
Since we used Jitsi and PureTube we did not have live captions during the summit.
We were able to add them in post production but it would have been nice to have it while
the event was happening.
So we're going to look into some open source tools that can be used alongside Jitsi.
Hopefully we can stick with that arrangement and then if not maybe look into some alternatives.
So what's next then?
So calls for proposals.
So dependent on speaker capacity and interest we'll probably do a call for proposals around
two to three months prior to the event.
There's a lot of interest in the audience to get involved themselves, present their
own talks and share their knowledge.
We want to keep group and interaction growing throughout the year.
This can bring more people into the community, maintain their interests, maybe have socials,
fire challenges, little mini events, spread the word so participate in talks like this
one, get involved in more of the open source design forums, all the different communities.
Planning is a major part so we're going to give ourselves some more time to implement
improvements, trials, some things out and then if any errors come up.
So yeah I'm going to pass it over to Jess then just in case you're interested in participating
in Fedora.
So a little bit of a segue I suppose since we're all, it's very heavily supported by
the Fedora design team so if you would like to be interested in the next one.
So if you would like to, there's a Fedora account that you can create.
You can create it at accounts.fidoraproduct.org and you can use it to sign into the element
as well and it's very kind of, it's like the main account to use especially with a somewhat
like this.
So if you want to learn more about Fedora, it's all on the Fedora docs and also if you
do join.fidoraproduct.org it gives you all the links that you can use as well.
Shows our missions, our foundations, all the user documentation and you can look us up
and ping us if you need anything.
And then also yeah you can hang out with us.
So in the element chat we have a Fedora design element chat where people share what they've
been contributing and if anyone needs feedback from like the more senior people or like just
in general it's a really good place to be.
Fedora marketing as well and there's many more channels as well even if you're not really
interested in design, there's infrastructure, there's many more, loads.
So and yeah where to find us.
So the matrix channel there, creativefreedom.fidora.in and then our website is the creativefreedom.com
where you can get all the information and we have like when we were playing it as well
we had all of our, we had a live like schedule going on and you can click on it and it brings
you to the streams and then again the Fedora design team matrix channel is there and then
that's us.
So if you have any questions.
Yeah so.
We're planning on making kind of like an annual event so it will hopefully happen around January
next year as well.
So feel free to enter the matrix channel, ping myself or Jess, we'd be more than happy
to punch in the right direction if you're not sure on how to use matrix or element,
anything like that.
So yeah I think that's our talk.
Thank you.
Does anyone have any questions?
No?
Yes.
I understand this is going to be online this year, do you plan to keep that format for the
future?
It's, I suppose it's making open source design tools kind of more accessible so we'd like
to kind of keep it a virtual event I think for the foreseeable future.
Maybe there might be so many events, things like that we haven't really discussed it but
we do like the online aspect that you know anyone can join so it is yeah.
Yeah I suppose it's yeah just making it more accessible for people.
So yeah does anyone else have any questions?
Yeah.
So I'll just repeat the question so we were just asked what would we like to see more
of in the next summit.
So I suppose just getting the numbers off like you know like it's good to see you know
just make make it more well it is approachable I suppose but I don't know it's a tough question.
I'd like to see more of like the craft inside a thing and the open source design aspect
because I thought that was really interesting when Morgan came in and was talking about
having you know open source design say of like sewing patterns things like that making
clothing more accessible to people it was kind of an aspect of design I didn't really
think of even though I'm into like crocheting and knitting and stuff myself so it was mad
just to kind of see like a hobby and like work kind of come together then so I thought
that was quite interesting yeah I'd like to see more of that.
Okay yeah we also have a stand-down in Building H as well so we'll probably be there after
this.
Thank you.