Hello, everyone. Thanks for being here so early on a Sunday morning. My name is Laura.
I work at Calabra. And today I'd like to share with you a word story about how we built and
grew our laboratory for upstream testing. I'm going to share with you a little bit about
our infrastructure, as well as some of the challenges that we have to face while scaling
up. So our main goal was to build a big test bed for open source projects to use. So of course,
we're going to need diverse ecosystem of devices. So many different devices of different
architectures and from different vendors. Of course, we're going to need a software to
automate the tests on the actual devices. We need a monitoring system, so a way to monitor
and assess the health of the devices that we have in the lab. And we also need some recovery
strategies. So mainly, when devices start to misbehave or don't behave, it's expected we need
some way of recovering them automatically, or putting them offline automatically if they're
not reliable to run tests. So it all starts with a commit. The developer pushes the changes into a
development branch. The artifacts for the tests are built automatically. A test job is submitted
and run. The results are gathered and parsed. And finally, a report is generated and sent back to the
developer. So from the lab perspective, we're interested in the part that runs the test jobs
and makes the results available. What we chose for our lab is lava, as we saw earlier. This is the
linear automation and validation architecture. So it automates the boot and deploy phases of the
apprentice system on the device. It has a really scalable scheduler. It allows to run thousands of
jobs on hundreds of devices on a single instance. So that's really convenient for big labs. It
handles the power on the devices. So it switches the power on and off on the devices when needed.
And it also helps monitoring the serial output. And finally, it also makes the results of the
tests available in many different formats, which is, again, pretty convenient. Lava, again, just
takes care of this part of the CI loop, while all the other phases needs to be implemented with
different tools. So in order to run devices in lava, we need to fulfill set of base requirements.
Of course, we're going to need to be able to turn on and off the power on the devices remotely.
We need access to a reliable serial console remotely. And finally, we need some way of
booting an arbitrary combination of kernel, device tree, and root of us remotely. For all the devices
that we have in the lab, we rely on TFTP. So we need network connectivity at the bootloader level.
And that means that we often have to build our custom bootloaders and enable all the features
that we need for debugging. So there are a few steps to prepare the devices before they enter
the lab. As far as the configuration of the devices itself in lava, we have a couple of...
You only need to define some Jinja 2 and YAML templates. So the device type template basically
defines the characteristic of the device type. So for example, which kind of bootloader run on a
certain device, which kind of command line options are needed for booting. Well, the device dictionary
defines device specific characteristics. So for example, what command do we need to run to turn on
and off the power or to access the serial console. And finally, we have the health check, which is a
special kind of job associated to each device type. And the aim of the health check is to assess
the health status of each device. It's supposed to be run on a fairly regular basis. We run a
health check on every device that we have in the lab every day. And examples of tests that you can
fit in a health check are, for example, a battery test, or you can check the temperature on the
device to make sure it's not overheating. You can check the network connectivity. Basically, all the
tests that you need to make sure that the device is functional, you can fit them in health check.
And whenever a device fails its health check, lava automatically puts it offline.
So it's really useful just to shut down all the devices that are not reliable at the moment.
So Colabra maintains a laboratory running lava. And we have, as of a couple of days ago,
217 devices of 38 different types spread across 16 racks. Each rack is controlled by its own server.
And that's also where the lava dispatcher runs. And of course, besides all the device types,
devices, we also have a bunch of hardware equipment that we need to automate the boot
and test phases on our devices. And this is what the device distribution looked like in January.
So the vast majority of our devices are x86, 64, and arm 64 platforms. And we also have some QAML
instances that are mainly used by kernel CI. And the very vast majority of our devices are
actually Chromebook laptops. But we also have some embedded SPC devices as well.
So what kind of hardware do we have in the lab? So different devices as usually different
requirements. So for embedded SPCs, what we use to control the power on them remotely are
Ethernet control relays and PDUs. I left there some examples of the actual models that we currently
have in the lab. Chromebooks are kind of a different beast. They have their own hardware
debug interface, which is the Servo v4 and this user cables. So Servo v4 allows you to control
the power on the device to access the serial consoles on the device, and also provides network
connectivity through an internet port. So you can fit everything you need to automate the
boot and test phases on a Chromebook that fits inside just one hardware box. As an alternative,
you also have CZ cables, which pretty much have the same functionality except for the network
connectivity that you have to provide through usually to a USB to Ethernet adapter. We have a
couple of servers as well in the lab. And for those we use the IPMI standard protocol just to
control the power and access the serial consoles. And for all the devices, of course, we're going
to need a bunch of USB cables with their fragilities. And also we use USB hubs. We find especially
useful the switchable hubs such as the YKush, especially for those devices that are controlled
by just one USB connection such as the Chromebooks. So that's really convenient just not to have
them to manually intervene every time you need to re-plug the USB connection. As for the software,
I left here a couple of links. You want to check them out. We use PDU daemon to execute comments
on the PDUs. We use Conservo to access the serial consoles and monitor the output. And the HDC tools
are just for the Chromebooks. These are the software tools that allows you to interact
with the servo v4 and with the CZ cable as well just to control the power and serial on the
Chromebooks. For the interaction with lava, we use lava CLI. It's a command line interface.
And that's useful to run the tests on the device and also configure and push the templates.
Finally, we also have a lava GitLab runner that serves as a bridge between GitLab and lava.
And yeah, that's pretty much it for the software side. So in our lab, we have two major users.
One is kernel CI, which is focused on continuous testing of the Linux kernel.
It's not only boot tests. We have a bunch of other test suites running on them. And
the type of testing that kernel CI does is post merge. So changes are
tested after they landed on a set of monitor trees. So after the tests have run, kernel CI
will generate some build reports as well as some regression reports for every regression that is
found. The other major player in our lab is mezoci. That's DCI for meza 3D. And it does
conformance testing and also performance tracking. There are a bunch of test suites that are currently
run by mezoci. I left the list here. A bunch of APIs and drivers are tested. And while kernel CI
only does post merge testing, meza CI also does pre-merge conformance tests. So that's a little
bit of both. And in this diagram, you can see what the usage of kernel CI and meza CI in our
laboratory. As you can see, both projects keep our lab pretty busy. Kernel CI uses
almost all the architectures that we have in the lab while meza CI is focused more on x86,
64, and ARM 64. And with so many jobs running every day in our lab, of course, the impact
of any error or unreliability in the infrastructure can be quite big. So for pre-merge tests,
you have the merge requests from users can get blocked. And definitely, if a certain device type
is not available. And also, yeah, there is a risk of merge requests getting rejected if there are
many errors in the lab. So what we need to make sure from the lab perspective is that
the merge requests from users do get rejected only because the change is introduced,
made the test fail, and not because of any infrastructure error. Well, for post-merge
tests, we have a risk of reporting false regressions. In this case, we want to make
sure again that the infrastructure errors are reported as such by lava. And lava defines
different types of exceptions that you can raise based on the type of error that occurs.
We need just to make sure that the devices and lava itself is configured properly to do so.
So yeah, this is just a minimal list of the common issues that we have seen over the years.
Of course, there can be other degradation. You can have faulty cables at any time or
batteries just failing, power chargers not working properly. All kinds of network issues can happen
at any time and they can have quite a big impact. We also saw some issues related to the rack setup.
So for example, we had some laptops where the lid was likely too closed because of how it was set
up in the rack and it was causing the device to enter suspend unexpectedly. So we have all kind
of different errors that can happen. Of course, we can have firmware bugs either in the firmware
running or the actual devices or also firmware running in the hardware debug interface. So that's
a lot of errors that can happen. I gather a few of my favorite pitfalls. These are issues, tricky ones
that we have found recently and we're still dealing with some of those. So one of the things
that we saw is that sometimes it happens that the serial console will just stop outputting anything
on the serial console. And if this happens during the test phase, it's kind of hard to understand
in an automated way whether the kernel is hanging or whether your USB cable connection has dropped
or if it's just like a reliable serial connection. So that's usually a tricky one to deal with.
Another serial related one is caused by interference. So not all devices can have multiple
UART connections for debug. Most of our devices in the lab don't. So we have to share the same
serial connection between the kernel and the test shell. And this sometimes can cause some
interference and of course you will confuse lava about the outcome. So one way that we are
thinking of many solutions to deal with this kind of serial issue stuff and one approach that we are
looking into is actually using a docker container. So running a docker container, connecting to the
device over SSH and run the tests on the SSH console. This way we can probably work around some of these
serial issues. So as I said there are also network connectivity issues from time to time and
if the network drops during the bootloader phase that's usually something we can easily catch
because lava of course monitors the serial output. And if our bootloader is nice enough to
print error messages we can just catch the right patterns at the right time and just raise
an infrastructure error so that won't officiate like the outcome of the test. When this happens
we can also configure lava to retry the job if needed. So when this happens it's useful to catch
error patterns. If network decides to drop during the test phase that's usually
worse especially for devices that rely on a network phase system. So it's usually pretty
hard to recover from this. We have seen occasional USB disconnection for whatever reason and yet it's
hard to recover from these kind of issues usually. So these are some of the best practices we came
upon while working on these issues. So the first one is about writing robust health checks. So as
I said devices will be put offline by lava if the health check fails so we need to make sure that
the health checks catch as many issues as possible automatically. We found very useful to monitor the
lava infrastructure error exceptions and this is mainly to catch issues with specific racks or
specific device types. We usually try to monitor also the device itself and the job queue as well
and this is to make sure that we have enough devices of a certain device type to feed all
the pipelines for the projects and also to minimize if a certain device type goes offline
and if we have redundancy we're able to recover from that. Last but not least as I said
one best practice is to try and isolate the test shell output and kernel messages whenever possible.
If not we're trying to work around some of these issues.
So next steps for our lab is of course increase the lab capacity and try to cover even more
platform and different vendors as soon as they come out. While doing this we are continuing to
improve our infrastructure and our monitoring tools. I haven't included in this presentation
how we actually monitor things but yeah lava does have some APIs that you can use to monitor
the status of each device and also of the server and yeah of course while keeping to keep adding
new lab devices we also want to increase the coverage of test suites so we're working on
adding even more tests to it on kernel ci and mezoci as well and that's it. If you have any
questions I think I have time right.
Any questions?
So in your experience how often is something wrong with the lab? Very often I'd say.
Can you give me a specific question?
Yeah I don't have data at hand with the actual failures but yeah it happens pretty often. I mean
we have so many jobs running every day and we rely heavily on USB which is kind of not great,
like it breaks pretty often. I'd say the most common issues that we have is usually due to the
serial consoles being not too reliable. The vast majority of devices that we have are Chromebooks
and we're using like these hardware debug interfaces that were meant for debugging so sometimes like
the serial connection is not great and that caused all kind of issues so we try at least to retry
the jobs when possible and catch the infrastructure errors as they come out.
I'd say we don't have to manually intervene every day. I'd go like every couple of days we need to
maybe replug some of the devices because we as I said we use the switchable hubs to try and
avoid having to reset the connection manually but we don't have this set up on each and every
device that we have. We're working on it but yeah I'd say like at least a couple of times a week.
I haven't like really checked the frequency of it but yeah of course there's people in the lab
actually taking care of all the devices.
So from the lab perspective we don't really care about the test suites running. It's more the
responsibility of kernel CI and mazoci. You can check out the the links that I left like everything
is of course open source so you can check out all the test suites and how they work.
Yeah some tests you just need a run disk. Some other tests rely the most heavier ones
rely on natural practice system.
Yeah.
I mean it depends on the type of tests that you need to run. We use a lot of Chromebooks
because we need Chromebooks so yeah you cannot really emulate one.
Yeah.
All right no more questions so thank you. Thank you.