Welcome to this session about LKFT, the Linux Canal Functional Testing Project.
My name is Remi Dureffot.
I'm a principal technique at Linau.
I've been working on open source projects since 2007 and I've been the lava architect
and main developer since for eight years now, so quite some time now.
So I will speak today about LKFT because it's a project I'm working with.
So what is LKFT?
So the goal of LKFT is to improve the Linux Canal quality on the ARM architecture by performing
regression testing and reporting on selected Linux Canal branches and the Android command
kernel in real time.
That's what is written on the website.
So it's a project that is led by Linau.
The goal is to build and test a set of Linux Canal trees.
So we care mainly about LTS trees, main line and next.
For LTS in particular, we have a 48 hour SLA, which means that we have to provide a full
report in less than 48 hours for any change on LTS.
If you look at the numbers for 2023, we tested 465 RCs.
As we test main line and next, we also build and tested 2628 different commit versions,
which means that we built 1.6 million kernels and ran 200 million tests in a year.
That's only for Linux.
If you look at Android command kernel, only for the test that's 58 million tests, 580
million tests.
So VTS and CTS mainly.
And this is all done by only three people.
So the question is how do we do to build that many kernels and test that many kernels with
only three people?
Obviously automation.
So my goal today is to show you the architecture of LTFT and to also show you the different
tools that we created and maintain to make that possible.
Because I'm sure that you can go back home with some of these tools and might be useful
for you.
So let's look at the architecture now.
So this is a really simple view.
We have a set of trees in GITLab.
They are just simple mirrors in GITLab of the official trees.
We just use GITLab for a scheduling mechanism.
So it will pull the new changes and it will run a GITLab CI pipeline.
But we won't do anything specific in GITLab CI pipeline.
We won't do build or test inside it.
It's too slow and costly.
So we just use it for submitting a plan to our system that will do the build and test
and reporting.
And at the end we will just get a report that three engineers will look at and decide if
we have to report something to the main developers or if we can just find a commit ourself and
send a batch.
Let's dig in a bit now.
So as I said, we don't use GITLab CI for building.
We submit only from GITLab CI, a build request to our system.
So for building we created a tool which is called TextMake.
I will explain the different tools later on.
I'm just showing the architecture right now.
So we use a tool called TextMake that allows for building the system with different combinations
of options.
And we created a software as a service that allows to use TextMake at a large scale in
the cloud.
So we can build something like 5,000 kernels in parallel in the cloud in some minutes.
When one build is finished, so when TextMake finishes build, they are sent to a storage.
It's an S3-like bucket somewhere.
Once a result is sent to Squad, which is the second project that we also maintain, that
will be what that is like where everything is stored.
As we send results really early, if there is a build failure, a build regression, you
will notice that in some minutes or hours depending on how long the build takes.
Because for example, if you do an all-mode config build with Clang, it will take up
to one or two hours easily.
But this way we can have early regressions that we can send immediately to the main list,
saying that it's failing to build on this architecture for this tool chain.
That's for building.
I will explain TextMake a bit later on.
So as I said, when a TextMake build finishes, we send the result to Squad, we store it in
the storage, and we also submit multiple test runs that will be done in the cloud.
So we do tests in the cloud and on physical devices.
For the cloud, we have a product called TextRun that will allow you to test on virtual devices,
so QMU and a VP.
And the same, we have a system that allows you to scale in the cloud the TextRun processes.
So you can spawn the same thousands of processes of TextRun processes in parallel in the cloud.
And they will send the result to Squad also.
Testing in virtualization is nice.
You find a lot of bugs because you can test a lot of different combinations.
But that's not enough.
You have to test on real devices.
That's where a second software comes in, which is Lava, that will allow you to test on real
devices.
So the same when TextMake finishes to build.
It will submit a set of test requests to Lava that will run on real hardware in this case.
So obviously we run less tests on real devices and on virtual devices because we don't have
enough board.
That is the single point that you're missing.
And the same results are sent to Squad.
And then when everything is finished, we have a full report that we can provide to the developers
that we test, we run something like thousands of tests, thousands of builds, and everything
is working or we found some regressions.
That's the overall architecture.
I will now look at the different projects so you can know if something can be useful
for you.
So let's look at the build parts.
So as I said before, we use TextMake.
It's a project that we created to make building easy and repolucible.
So it's an open source command line application.
It allows for a portable and repeatable Linux-candled builds.
So for that we use containers.
We provide a set of containers with all the tools you need inside and everything is done
inside a container.
So it can be repolucible from one machine to another.
So because that's often a problem when you report a build failure, it's always a nightmare
to know the exact tools that you're using, everything.
So as everything is inside a container, you can just repolucible it in another machine.
So we support multiple toolchains, GTC from 8 to 12, client from 10 to 15.
In fact, 16 has been added this week.
We also have a Clang Android version and a Clang Nightly.
Clang Nightly is specific because we rebuild the Clang toolchain every night and we push
it to our system so we can just test with the latest Clang.
We also support multiple target architectures, all the ARM versions, Intel AMDs, and then
some MIPS, PowerPC, ResV5, and some exotic one like S390, SH4, things like that.
So building is really simple.
You just specify the target architecture, so x8664 in this case.
You just specify the toolchain, so I want to use GTC12.
You just need to have text make installed on your computer because everything will then
be done inside a container where you will have GTC12 to chain for x8664.
If you want to build with GTC13, just change toolchain to GTC13 and it will use another
container to build it.
And as I said before, we have a private software that allows to run text make at large scale
in the cloud, but I'm not presenting that it's a close-up software.
So just to explain how it's working, text make will pull the right container for you.
So for this specific target arch toolchain couple, it will be x8664, GTC12 container.
We have thousands of containers, hundreds of containers.
It will create a unique build directory, so it's reproducible from one build to another.
And then we just start a Pullman container, jump into it, and just build.
We advise to use Pullman obviously and not Docker because it will be a rootless container,
so you can at least don't run as a boot in your build.
And then it will invoke a set of different make commands depending on what you want to
build.
And then it will move everything to a specific directory that will be kept on the machine,
and it will have all the artifacts, kernel, adders, et cetera.
And you also have metadata that will include a lot of metadata about your build, like version
of your toolchain of different utilities on the machine, the time taken by different steps,
the size of everything, et cetera.
Very useful for debugging also what's going on if something breaks.
We provide multiple containers that you can reuse.
And it's an open sub-product, so you can contribute to it a few months, and you can just use it
right now.
And some kind of developer use it for reproducing build failures.
And in fact, as I said, we have a client nightly toolchain that is rebuilt nightly.
It's in fact because the client project asked us to do that because they use Tuxmake with
client nightly for validating their client version against different kernel versions
to see if clang is not regressing.
That's for building.
So now how do we test?
So as I said, we test on virtual devices with Tux1 and on physical devices with Lava.
So for Tux1, it's the same.
It's an open source, a common-line application.
It's the same for Tuxmake but for running.
It allows for portable and repeatable kernel tests.
We support multiple devices, FVP MVA, which is an ARMv9.3 emulator, a simulator.
That's the latest version that you can try for ARM.
And then multiple ARM versions with multiple QEMU devices, many ARM Intel MIPS in many
different versions and PPC, et cetera, and multiple test suites, so LTP, K-Unit, K-S
is not quite easy to do.
The same, the common-line is quite simple.
We also use Sponman for containerizing everything.
You specify the device that you want to use, the kernel that you want, can be your URL,
obviously, and root file system also if you want.
And again, we have a SAS that allows to run that at large scale in the cloud.
When you call that common-line, Tux1 will download all the artifacts that you need,
so kernel, DTP, more root file system modules.
It will inject the modules inside the root file system for you so that it will be used
at boot time.
And start the container, start QEMU system, so R64 in this case, look at the output, et
cetera, et cetera, all the classical things, and store the results.
As I said, we provide a lot of root file systems because we know it's painful to build your
root file system for multiple architectures.
So we do the work for that.
We use Billroot and Debian.
Billroot allows us to have the 19 supported architectures, one root file system for each.
And for the main one, one supported by Debian, we do provide the Debian root file system that
we build.
And obviously, if you build your own one, you can use it if you want.
And we will do the job of rebuilding the Billroot and Debian file systems regularly.
And in fact, it's a fun thing, we've actually found bugs in QEMU before pushing the new
file systems, we test in our system with the new root file systems.
And the last time we did that, we found issues in QEMU 7.2 that are currently being fixed
by QEMU developers.
Something fun because Tuxmake and Tuxrun has been done by the same team.
So we make the work to combine the two tools together.
So obviously, you can, doing a bisection of a build failure is quite easy, you just need
a lot of CPU time.
Same for a runtime issue, which is you find a regression where a test fail on a specific
architecture.
For example, when you run an LTP test on QEMU ARM64, it's failing, and you want to bisect
that.
So find the faulty commit.
You have a good commit and a bad commit, and you want to find the faulty commit.
It allows to help you on that, but thanks to Tuxmake and Tuxrun, we can automate all
that job of testing.
So with this command line, Git will call Tuxmake on different commits to try to find the faulty
one.
And Tuxmake will just build, and at the end of the build, thanks to minus my result hook,
it will exec the command that is behind that will run Tuxrun with the kernel that has been
just built.
So it will build with Tuxmake, and at the end run with Tuxrun the exact LTP test that
fails, and if it's passing, it will return zero.
If it's failing, it will return one.
So based on that, Git will be able to find the faulty commit for you, which is quite...
We found a lot of regression, or test regression, and found the faulty commit thanks to just
that command line, which is really cool.
Thanks to Endos for the idea.
So that was all virtual built in containers, test on virtual devices, but as I said before,
we have to test on physical devices, because multiple bugs are only found on physical devices,
because they are based on drivers failing, and things like that.
So for that, we use Lava, like some people in this room.
So Lava stands for Linau Automated Validation Architecture.
It's a text execution system.
So it will allow it for testing software on real hardware, automatically for you.
So it will automatically deploy, boot, and test your software on your hardware.
So it's used by Kernel CI a lot, by LKFT obviously, and you can do system level testing,
boot level testing.
You can do boot loader also testing.
You can test directly your boot loader on the firmware, and it currently supports 356
different device types.
So from IoT to phones, Raspberry Pi-like boards, and servers.
So multiple different device types.
So for example, if you want to test on a Raspberry Pi without Lava, you will have to pour on
the board, download the artifacts, so kernel rootfs, files, dtbs, place them on a specific
directory, like NFS or TFT directory, connect to the serial, type a lot of commands, boot
boards, watch the boot outputs, type the logging prompt, et cetera, et cetera.
So really painful to do that manually.
Lava will just do exactly what I just listed automatically for you.
It will just provide a job definition, which is a YAML file, with links to all the artifacts
that you want to test.
You specify the kind of board that you have.
So it's a Raspberry Pi 4B, and Lava will know then how to interact with that board.
And you will say that I have a U-Boot installed on it, and I have a TFTP server.
Just use that and test what I want to test on it.
And Lava will do that automatically for you.
Obviously you can have multiple boards attached to the same worker, and you can have multiple
workers on a Lava instance.
So as a user, it's really an abstraction of the hardware.
You just send a YAML file and you get results.
And all the hardware part is done automatically by Lava for you.
So as I said, maybe you remember the first LKFT diagram.
I'm sure you don't.
There was a small box called keyscash.
So when we submit jobs to Lava, we submit multiple jobs for the same artifacts at the
same time.
We have multiple devices.
So the scheduler will start the job for the same artifacts all at the same time.
So it will download multiple times the same artifact at the same time, which just should
be able to cache that and decrease network usage.
So we tried squid.
And the short answer is squid is not working for that use case for different reasons.
The first one is that, as I said before, all the artifacts are stored in an S3-like bucket.
So it's somewhere on internet.
So obviously we use SSL, HTTPS to download it.
And squid and HTTPS are not really working well together.
You have to fake SSL certificates.
It's all creepy things to do.
And also a thing that, as I said, we download.
Lava will start all the jobs at the same time.
So they will more or less download all the same artifacts at exactly the same time.
And if you do that with squid, squid will download if you ask for n times the same file
to squid.
If it's not already cached, squid will download it n times.
And only when one is finished, or when download is finished, the next one will use a cached
version.
So it's just pointless for us.
It's just not working.
So we created a tool called keyscache.
The keys is for keep it simple, stupid.
It's a simple and stupid caching server.
It's not a proxy.
It's a service, which means that it can handle HTTPS.
And it will only download once when you have multiple clients.
And it will strain to the clients while downloading.
It's not transparent because it's not a proxy.
And because it's not transparent, it can do HTTPS.
Because you will have to prefix your URL by the keyscache instance that you have.
And you will talk to keyscache directly.
It also automatically retries on failures because we found multiple failures that all
the HTTP code that you can have when you request on an S3 like bucket.
Just insane.
And sometimes also you will get, the connection will finish like if everything was done correctly.
And in fact the file is not complete.
It's a partial download.
And you don't get any errors.
So keyscache will detect that for you.
It will detect that it's a partial download.
And it will retry and only the remaining things for you.
And it's fully transparent as a user.
It will do that in the background and still stream your data to you.
So thanks to that, we've been using it for 2.5 years now.
In the graph, in green is what we serve locally from keyscache.
And in red is what we download from internet.
So we downloaded 25 terabytes of data from internet.
And we serve 1.3 petabytes of data in the local network, which is a 52 times expansion
ratio.
So it's quite useful.
It improves stability also.
So it's really cool.
It's a good tool for your CI if you don't use it already.
And last but not the least, we store all the job results in squad.
So it's software quality dashboards.
It will store, it's a data lake.
It will store all the results for you in different categories.
And it will allow you to create reports.
So failures, regressions, et cetera.
Everything is stored in this one.
And then we extract data and make report based on squad.
And that's all.
That's what I just explained.
If you have any questions, I have some time for questions.
Five minutes, perfect.
Oh, yeah.
That's good.
Testing methods, like which we use LTP, KUnit, KSelfSets, all the kernel test suites that
we...
We are not creating new test suites.
We are using test suites that don't exist.
And we run...
We build for the community and we test for the community.
And then we provide reports.
We obviously interact a lot with the test suite maintainers because we found bugs in
the test suite too.
We have to report to them.
And there's this reporting a lot to them.
And one of our project is to test KSelfSets in advance, test KSelfSets master to find
bugs in KSelfSets before they actually run in production after.
If you find any problems and report them, are current developers actually looking at
them or do you have to ping them and make sure they take care of the problem?
Okay, so we have an SLA with Greg Krotman.
So he's waiting for our results.
So they will look at it for LTS and for mainline and next.
We are used to reports.
We report a lot of issues.
So they know us.
If you look at LWN articles about, they classify the different contributions to the kernel.
And Linaro is in the tested by top, top in the tested by.
So they know us a lot.
So they know that we provide good results.
And when we provide a mail, there is every tool they need for reproducible, reproducing
a build.
So we provide all the binaries that they need for reproducing it.
If it's a big failure, we provide a tax make command line that they can use.
And they are now used to use tax make for rebuilding things.
And if it's a test failure, we provide the logs, obviously, the job definition and all
the binaries they need for reproducing it.
Do you actually check that every problem you found is actually fixed?
And those are all the bugs that we found fixed.
Not all of them.
Some bugs that they don't care about.
Yeah.
Okay.
Depends on the hard to fix it.
Yeah.
If you found some bugs on SH4, no one will care, for example.
My QEMU 7.2 has been released recently, just not working on SH4.
I cannot answer that.
We use AWS.
No, it's not that bad.
No, not.
As we have a dynamic system, which means we do not rent 5,000 machines.
Obviously not.
It's impossible for us.
We are a small company.
Everything is dynamic.
So from one second to another, if you look at the graph of usage, when Anders submits
a plan for testing, in one minute we will book 5,000 machines for building it.
Likely more 1.5 thousand machines to build it.
They will build and they will just stop at the end.
So no, we don't have 5,000 machines.
How many devices do you have in your Lava test rig?
So we have multiple Lava instances in LKFT, how many devices?
About 20.
About 5 different device types.
Dragon Balls.
Junos.
X15.
Yeah, X15.
But yeah, you can have really large labs in Lava.
We have another one for just linear usage where we have something like 100 balls, I
think.
The main one.
Yeah.
Thanks.