No problem. Hello. How's it going, everybody? A lot of people in this room didn't really
expect so many. This is wonderful. Thank you for coming to see us. Just want to say that
we want to talk today about mutation testing. That's what we're here for. If you like this
penguin, does anyone not like this penguin? Just you. Okay. Personal vendetta noted. So
this is a penguin generated by Dolly. Hopefully it's friendly enough because this is going
to be part of our talk. We're going to see a lot of penguins in this talk. If anyone
has a personal objective of penguins, please speak now. Otherwise, if you like penguins,
can I get a hand up just to see? Are we cool with that? Awesome. I've never seen so many
people want to put their hands up but not really be sure. I absolutely love the energy
in this room. My name's Max. I'm this guy. As you can tell, I'm also this guy. But I'm
here to talk to you about mutation testing. I work for a company called Vonage and I'm
a Python developer advocate there. What that means is that I maintain our Python tooling.
I'm here to talk about mutation testing because I've just went through this process myself
of understanding all this stuff and applying it to my own work. I want to show you how
that went. But with me, not only do I have the tallest person in the room. Stand up straight.
I don't know. This person is 196 centimeters tall. I'm 177. I'm not sure. I'm average in
Britain. In this place, right? This person knows a lot more about mutation testing than
me. I'm really not the expert here but I just want to say this is Parko.
I'm Parko. I work for Opavaleo, a small consulting company in the Netherlands. I got into mutation
testing via my thesis. When I wrote my thesis on test effectiveness, I wanted to learn more
about mutation. After that, I got into speaking at conferences and spreading the word about
this awesome tool. I hope at the end of the tool you have another cool tool in your toolbox
to write better code. Awesome. If we're cool with that, we do have
to do the obligatory. These companies paid for us to come here and pay for our flights
and stuff. What my company does, I'll just quickly tell you. We do communications APIs
as a service basically. Things like SMS, voice calls, video chats, two-factor authentication,
all via API. That's what we do. That's really just what I want to say. It is relevant because
I'll show you what I actually applied this to which was one of our SDKs.
For me, we don't actually have a product to sell. Also, definitely didn't fly here from
the Netherlands just to make sure. It's just a two-hour car drive. We're here just a consultancy
company and we really like to share knowledge. That's mostly the reason why I'm here to tell
you more and teach you more. Quite simple. He doesn't have the funding crush that I
do unfortunately. Luckily, we're all good. There's two of us on this talk. There's two
of us here. Actually, there is a third person in this talk. We've seen a hint about this
person already. This person's really the thing that's going to tie this whole talk together
and it's going to get us all feeling good about mutation testing. This person's very
important. Say hello to Henry. This is Henry. Look at his little face. Heck yeah. Hands
up if you think Henry's a cute AF penguin. That's frick. Thank you very much. Yes, I'm
glad we agree. I'm glad we're on the same page. Now, just some quick audience participation
because if you can't tell, we're quite big on audience participation. Quick question
here. Who has heard of this stock photo but more importantly, who's heard of testing?
This is just a check to see if we found the room. Thank you very much. Great stuff. Okay.
Who's heard about code coverage? A lot of people, maybe not everybody and that's okay
if you haven't. We're going to talk about code coverage. Please don't worry if you haven't.
It's awesome to know that some people have. That's a good starting point too. Okay. Final
one. I'm going to say other than via knowing about this talk, who's heard of mutation testing?
Oh, quite a few. Yeah. Quick break in. Who actually was already using mutates testing?
Ah, nice. There are enough quick wins here. Hopefully, you have some good experiences.
Yeah. Really nice to see that people are familiar with the concept. If you're not, it's also
okay because we're going to go through this like you don't know anything at all. When
I started doing this a few months ago, I didn't know anything at all. I want to take you through
that journey as well. That's what we're going to do. Before that, what I want to do first
is give us some background. What I actually really want to do is pass the Paco who knows
a lot more about this than me. I'm going to pass to you right now. This is going to be
some improvising. Good luck. I'm going to drink water with this. I'll feed you. Nice. Great.
So yeah, we're first going to talk a bit about testing in general. And then we're going to
more specifically talk about unit testing. So just a quick check. Does anybody know what
a unit test is? That's great. I don't have to explain that part. For those who don't
know, it's the smallest possible test you can write in your code base. Just in one method
and you write one test for it to test the outcome of the method. Now, there are many
different reasons why we're writing unit tests. And I think one of them, my favorite or the
most used one is for maintenance. Rewrite tests because we want to be confident in the
changes we make to our code base. So whenever we make a small change, we add a new field
to some endpoint that we know that we didn't completely break the database integration
because it can happen at times. So yeah, that's very important. Maintenance regression testing.
But there are more reasons. One I like also a lot is tests can actually serve documentation
purposes as documentation. You can use tests to describe certain scenarios in your code
base that when you have a specific test for that, it already makes clear this is intended
behavior. And I have some example. I have an example for this, which is I worked for
a company where we had an endpoint that returned warehouses. And these warehouses, just the
domain object, had a soft delete. So there was a flag in there that indicated whether
it was deleted or not. And at some point, so this endpoint returned both deleted and
non-deleted warehouses. And at some point over time, as we were working on it, a new
guy came in and looked at it and said, hmm, that's strange. Why are we returning deleted
warehouses? Why would you want that? It was a fair question because we also forgot. And
there was only one test which tested the success flow. And you can already kind of guess here
a bit. So the success flow in this case, I mean, they only returned non-deleted warehouses
in the test. So he made the changes. And we all thought, oh, this makes sense. It looks
broken. Of course, didn't check with product management. The product team deployed it.
And then you can guess, of course, this was broken. So we had to revert it. And the whole
lesson here was just one test which also included a negative scenario with tests with warehouses
that were deleted could have already been a trigger to think like, hey, this behavior
is intended. And that's where tests can serve as sort of a documentation purpose. Also very
useful in getting to learn a new code base. So whenever you're on a new code base, you
have this very complicated method. A test can help you step through the method to sort
of explain what's going on, for example, while debugging it.
Another one, this one is here for the consultant. So who here works as a consultant? Oh, not
that many. Wow. Because we're sort of the root of all evil always. We tend to run to
the next project. And we don't have to maintain our own code often, not always. And so I have
this nice quote that's mostly also for us. Keep in mind that you're not doing this only
for yourself. I had a colleague who once told me, keep in mind that you always have this
point in your development process where you think, OK, should I write a unit test for
this? It's going to be a painful unit test. I know that it works. Do we really have to
document it? We all know how it works. Yeah, sure. We all know how it works. But we also
leave the project and then go on and go to another project. We as in consultants. And
I was speaking to myself, what would I do if I would be the next person? So what would
what would I do if I were the next John or Jane Doe working on this project? So tests
are not there just for you, but also for the next person working.
I would like to jump in here because I've been that person. Thank you. I've been the
person who works on a project after someone's left that. And honestly, if you have good
documentation or if you don't have that, if you have good testing, thank you, you do your
water break. So if you have good testing, it can really help you understand what a project
does. And so when I came to a certain project recently, I didn't have necessarily the kind
of testing that I would have liked to really document my code that well. And so, like,
honestly, if I had someone like Parker, who actually was a bit more conscientious with
what they tested, that would have really helped me get on board with the project quickly.
But as it was, this was a real problem for me. And it was something that we want to hopefully
avoid other people having to deal with as well. Like quick question, actually, has anybody
ever taken over a code base that they may be look at and go, what the heck is this?
Okay. So you know what the point of this is of this slide, right? You know why we're saying
this. We know this is important. Now let's stop that from happening to the next generation
of very pain developers, right? Let's stop that happening.
Yes. So write tests. And so if all these reasons haven't convinced you, there's often maybe
a team lead or a boss or somebody else who's telling you to write tests. In most cases,
there's always, of course, exceptions. Ah, okay. Wow. This is annoying. So at the end
of the day, we're all writing tests. If it's not for ourselves, then it's for someone else.
And as we're, even though we're now sort of happily all adding tests, we also have to
sort of sketch a problem scenario here. And this problem is that as projects evolve and
grow, our tests also evolve and grow. But the problem is that we do refactor a lot and
we spend a lot of time on keeping our production code clean and well monitored. We have lots
of metrics. Where, on the other hand, for tests, what you can see on long-living projects
is that sometimes you just get tests where nothing more than a blank set up and tear
down and some mocking going on because the functionality already moved long ago. Which
means to the point that test code is often not monitored. Test code is sort of the kid
that didn't get all the attention it needed. So there is still one metric for testing.
What do you think is the most used metric for test code? Yes. Yeah. We sort of gave
it away already in the intro. But yes. Yes. Code coverage. Code coverage tells you how
much of the code is executed when you run the test suite. And I personally really like
code coverage because it already helps you write more and better tests. And I want to
go through a simple example here to show you how it can already help you. So here we have
a submit method. So this is the Python guy. I'm the Java guy. Yeah. He said simple example.
But I don't speak that much. Yeah. So the context is you're at a conference and you
have a service where you can submit proposals. You can only have you can't have more than
three or more proposals and you can submit after the deadline. If you do that there will
be a failure and otherwise you will get success. So quite a simple method with everything as
a parameter just to make it easy to explain. So if you would take method coverage. Method
coverage is the simplest coverage metric we can get which checks is this method coverage
as a no. We can add one simple test called a test X which submits a proposal. There are
no open proposals which is good. We have a deadline that's 999 seconds in the future.
So great. Now we can get a step further. We can get into statement coverage. And with
statement coverage we check if each statement was executed. And now we see hey we didn't
cover our unhappy flow. So we need to add another test. In this case we add another
test which has five open proposals which means this check evaluates to true and we have a
negative scenario. And we can even go one step further through for example condition
coverage. And with condition coverage we check if each Boolean subexpression has been evaluated
to both true and false. Because what we don't know now is whether our deadline check is
actually working. We just know that it returns false but we haven't seen it return true yet.
So we add one more test now with a deadline that is 999 seconds in the past. And now we
have three tests. And this is already why I like code coverage so much. Because it really
helps you write proper tests. Proper it helps you write tests because let me get on to the
good part here. As I said write better and more tests. Code coverage is really easy and
cheap to measure. In most I think most of languages it's just a matter of instrumenting
the code. You run the test suite and you get a nice report out of it that everybody can
quickly see and you can quickly see the pain points of where you're lacking in testing.
But to get a bit further so it guarantees as I mentioned it shows you what you didn't
test. But the only guarantee and I'm going to get to the bad parts next is that the only
thing that shows you what you did test didn't crash. It doesn't guarantee anything actually
about the functionality. Because code coverage can actually be quite misleading. It doesn't
guarantee any test quality. So if I take this method for example this is a valid unit test.
This test generates coverage. It calls a method. But there is no assertion on the result which
makes this test for example generate 80% coverage. Yet the test actually only guarantees it's
that the method doesn't crash. It doesn't tell us whether it's true or false or anything.
And this is the pain point of code coverage which brings us to something nice which Max
told me about which is called the good hot slow. So can you maybe explain a bit about
that? Can I grab your clicker? Can I explain about good hot slow? No, sorry. Just kidding.
So when a metric becomes a target it ceases to be a good metric. So quick question. Has
anyone ever written a unit test just to get coverage up rather than because the test was
useful? Come on, let's be honest. This is the safe space. Okay. Microphone. Okay. Hello
everybody. Welcome to the live stream. This is our radio announcer voice. Right. So this
is something I'll be honest I've done this. We now know a lot of people in the room have
done this. But what we don't want to have is with code coverage. It's supposed to tell
us something about our code. But if instead we turn that into a target that can really
limit what we actually, you know, what the kind of useful tests that we actually create.
And that leads to a few quite big questions that we do genuinely care about. So I'll wait
for that photo if you. Cool. Sorry, I'm very audience participation. I'm very sorry. So
the next question that we ask there is how do we know if our tests are high quality?
How do we know if these tests are actually good quality tests? We test them. Great. Great
answer. I've got a further follow up question for you. How can we understand what our tests
are really doing? Same answer. If anyone I see a hand. I literally had a code base where
I could delete half the tests and nothing changed. And they all yeah. So I'm in delete
half the code. Hello. Yes. So I'm just for the livestream. I'll just repeat that because
that's a really good point. I won't repeat this wearing, but I do understand and appreciate
that, you know, that emotion behind it. If you end up, you know, shipping some code that
does not do what it's supposed to do. You end up with users getting very angry at you
and yeah, that's a problem. That's going to be an issue. And that is a way of finding
out. But I guess the real question we're asking here is how do we know if we can trust our
tests? That's really the crux of this problem. And so as it turns out, the very famous Roman
poet, Juvanal, actually in 100 AD after he had a few drinks, he was able to summarise
this in such a beautiful way. And this was something that maybe wasn't appreciated at
the time because, you know, obviously he was talking about mutation testing 2000 years
before it was relevant. But I will mention it here. It's who watches the watches, right?
And this is the question. Who's testing our tests? Who cares about that? How do we actually
gain trustworthiness for our tests? And I see there's people in production who's having
bugs. There's people who understand here that this is a really big deal. Luckily, we have
a two word answer for you, which is the reason we're all in this room. Mutation testing. So
put the odd one out. You might see here, that's Henry. He's having a great time. But maybe
he shouldn't be still in a row of pigeons. But more importantly right now, I'll just
explain the basic premise and then Paco here will explain in a little more detail how it's
actually kind of done. So first of all, mutation testing. This is a really quick summary. What
you do is you introduce some faults in your code. So just a few little things that you
change. And for each of those little changes, that's a mutant version of your code. Once
you've got that, you run your test suite against those mutant versions of your code. And if
they fail, awesome. Because that means that your tests have actually picked up that change.
And that's a good thing. That's good. We want those tests to fail if our code changes. But
if they don't fail, that's a bad time. Because that means those tests didn't test that change.
It didn't test for that. And so that's something that could have made it to production. So
what mutation testing kind of gives you is a way to evaluate that test quality. But this
is very abstract. So let's look at penguins. I like penguins. So Henry here, he's a great
example. And he's going to bring all this home. So I was kind of unfamiliar to the topic.
So I kind of created some analogies with penguins that really helped me. So I'll share those
with you. So the way I kind of imagined my software is we do lots of stuff with messaging.
And so I imagine software that works properly to be like a pigeon or a dove, like a bird
that can fly. I've used a dove here because Paco has a deadly fear of pigeons. He's terrified
of them. Not fear. Vendetta. He has a personal vendetta against pigeons. Sorry. He doesn't
like them. So I've used a dove here. But ideally we want something that I can tie a message
to the bird's leg and it can go and deliver that message for me. So it can go do something
like that. So one of the key features of penguins is that they're not very good at flying.
Can we all agree that that's probably not the best? If you want to tie a message to
a bird's leg and get it to deliver it, a penguin might not be the bird you choose unless you
may be delivering something underwater. So this is the kind of example here where we've
got a bird, but it's not the kind of thing that performs the way we expect it to. And
this would cause some serious problems if we tried to use this kind of thing in production.
If we wanted to send a message via a penguin, we're going to have a tough time, right? So
Paco, I'd like you, if possible, to explain this in a way that makes more sense than what
I just did. Good luck. We only have one mic. It's a bit stiffly.
Yeah. So let's get into the process of mutation testing. The first step of mutation testing.
So what Max just taught you is about introducing faults. So you can introduce faults manually,
but this is a process that's, well, manually, and that means it's a lot of work and it's
usually also not that reproducible. You don't want to do it manually. We want to do this
in an automated manner. This is where mutates testing comes in. In the first step of mutation
testing, we're going to generate mutants. And each mutant is just a very tiny version
of the production code. Mutates testing works with the concept of mutators, and mutators
are the ones that are making these very small changes.
So what we have in this case, we have a perfectly fine DOV, which is the production code. And
then at the end of it, we have a mutator which generates, makes a tiny change, which kind
of transforms this into Henry, our penguin who can fly, and we want our software to fly.
So this would be a bad thing. So how does it look? Because this is still a bit abstract.
I'm going to give you some examples. This would be an example here. So for the Dutch,
and I think for other countries as well, you have to be 17 years in order to apply for
driving license. This could be code that's in your code base, which will fly, which is
good. Now, the mutant would be the entire code base stays the same, and just this little
piece change. So here we inverted the logic. This is, of course, a bug. This is something
we don't want to manage and get into production. And actually, just from this single line,
we can already generate quite some mutants, because we can not only avert the conditional
operator, we can also change the conditional boundaries. So this means that we now have
age larger than 17, which is a very nice bug that would force us to test the edge cases,
the famous off by one errors, whether we forgot our equal operation in our conditional check.
This will help you find that one. But it can also just return always true or false. We
can generate quite some mutants for this, and we can do the same for, for example, mathematical
operations. We can make each plus into a minus, each multiplication into a division, et cetera.
And there are more. We also have the ability to remove statements. So in this case, we
have a method that adds a published date to some object. And we can also just remove the
whole setter. And now this means that we have a bug in which we don't set this attribute
anymore, which is something that, of course, we don't want to make to production. What's
important to note here is that with mutates testing, it's always important that the code
actually compiles, because we're not testing the compiler. We're testing the code. The
compiler is definitely out of scope here. Now at the end of step one, we have a lot
of Henry's. We have a lot of mutants. And now Henry is going to try to fly. So he already
got his wings ready to try to fly. And now for each Henry, we're going to run the test
suite. And if this test suite fails, as Max already mentioned, then we have, then we,
then it's good because then we expose Henry 40s, which is just a penguin, something that
can't fly. So this is great. The not so happy scenario is where the test passed, which means
that Henry made it into production. And as we know, well, assuming that it also got through
the PR, of course, we have more than just tests. Is that a problem? Because Henry is
not supposed to fly. And now we have a bug into production. So this is something that
you don't want. So this is the theory of mutates testing. And now, Max, you can tell a bit
more about the frameworks. Sure. It works for me.
Alrighty. So first of all, I just want to say I'm so proud of this prompt. I don't know
why Dali chose this, but I'm really happy. Like I think I typed in penguin trying to
be a pigeon and it came up with this and I'm very happy. Okay. So moving on, yeah, frameworks.
So this is going to get a little bit more specific to, you know, to actually implementing
this stuff. So anyone here who is a Python developer? Heck yeah. Alright. Awesome. So
I'm going to show you what I did in Python. So as you can see, you know, Parker is a Java
developer. He'll explain Java in a sec. But I'll just show you the kind of basic concepts
but using my code and using what I did. So there's two kind of main supported packages
that you can use in Python. It's not like in Java there's an enterprise thing you can
get. In Python it's very community supported. So you're not going to get big products. But
what we do have are these nice supported reposts for mutates testing which have these packages.
So I am not a professional. In this I'm not a doctor, I'm not a lawyer, I'm not a professional
financial advisor. I'm just a person who has a certain opinion. And so my opinion of those
two frameworks I showed you, there's mutmut and cosmic ray. And personally I prefer mutmut.
Because it's easier to get going. Oh, angry face, shaken hairs. You don't like mutmut.
We will talk later. So if we have time, we'll have a third presenter very shortly. So for
now while I've still got the mic, while I'm still here, we'll talk about mutmut. And so
this framework is quite simple to use. The reason I kind of like it is because it's very
much you install it and you run it. There's a bit of config you can do. But really it's
quite simple just to get an idea of your code base and what's going on. So I want to show
you this slide. This is the SDK that I maintain. And I'm showing you this because it's what
I've applied my mutation testing to. So it's where I'm showing my examples. But basically
what we do is when we go here, I had this locally first of all. So I installed mutmut
with pip install. It's that simple. It's a Python package. It's what we do. If you went
to my talk a mile earlier, you know why that's a bad idea. But I did it. So after we do that,
we've got mutmutrun which just runs those tests for you. So when we do that, I'll show
you what my output was. So when I ran this myself, I actually got a whole lot of this
output. But really what's important here is that first of all, it ran my entire test suite.
And the reason it ran my entire test suite is just to check how long that's supposed
to take and just to make sure everything does work as expected. Because there's various types
of mutants to do with timeouts as well that we might want to consider. After it's done
that, what it will do is it will generate mutants based on the lines of code in my code
base. That's what it will do. And once it's done that, it will run my tests against those.
So there's a few different types. And it can characterize them like this. So the first
type is mutants that we've caught, not killed. We never kill a penguin. We love penguins.
We catch them. We've caught them and put them back into the zoo. In this case, we've managed
to say, yep, our test failed. That's great. But it could be the case where the mutant's
timed out. So it's taken way too long for this code to run. Or it's taken enough time
that we feel like we're not so feeling great about that code. Alternatively, we might end
up in a situation where the mutant survived and made it through our test code. In that
case, it corresponds to a bug that might make it to production. So when I ran this on my
particular SDK, what I saw was that we checked the stuff. I created 682 mutants, versions
of my code with changes in them. And it managed to catch 512 of those, but it managed to miss
170 of them. Now, if that's a good number or a bad number, we'll talk about later. But
what's important now is let's just look at some of those mutants. So first of all, the
ones that we actually did catch, here's a couple of examples. So here's a line where
basically we say here are some valid message channels. So for our messages API, here's
some valid message ways you can send, right? But what's important here is that this basically
removed the ability to send an SMS. And so when I tried to test that, it failed, which
is what we want to see. Here's another one. Again, this is Python. So if you're a Java
dev, don't worry, we'll look after you soon. And here's another one. We've got a decorator
here which basically runs this method. And we can see when we remove that, that will
never happen. This is actually through pedantic if anyone has used that before. But basically
it means that we're not going to round a number anymore. And so when we test for that, a number
doesn't get rounded and we catch that. But that is not really very interesting. That
doesn't tell us anything. That tells us about this much, right? It doesn't tell us much
at all. And the reason for that is that we kind of know that our test work for that.
Thank you very much. I'll do the M&M thing. So we kind of know that our test worked for
that. And so what's kind of useful is to see if we do much show, we can see the mutants
that we didn't catch. We can also do HTML which shows us essentially an HTML coverage
output as well so we can see in a list all of the mutants that we didn't catch. So with
much show on that code base that I just showed you, we can see the 170 meters that survived.
It shows you the indices of these. And then we can manually specify the ones we want to
look at. So here we can see, for example, that we changed the authentication method
to fail. And we can see in this case we caught that because we did a test for authentication
and it failed so that's great. But more importantly, though, is you get this HTML output which
you can then explore. You can explore every method, every sort of module that you have.
You can explore all the methods inside of there and which ones were and were caught.
And you do that with the HTML command. So to do that, I'll just show you this is a mutant
that we did not catch. And I want to show you why we didn't catch it and what it's going
to do. And I'll just do that for a few just so you get some context if that's cool. So
first of all, what this mutant did was it renamed the logger. Now, I think logging is
out of scope of my test code. So personally, I don't care too much about anything related
to logging. So I don't mind if I don't get a pass here. Here's another one. In this case,
what we do is we've slightly changed the value of a constant. This is just part of a function
signature. And we don't, again, we don't care about this that much. This isn't something
that I really mind about. What's more important, though, is this mutant here. Because this
is from a client class where we instantiate all of our different API classes. And you
can see we actually set voice to none. So we completely remove that instantiation and
our tests are still passing. So the reason that actually still works, our test code still
works, even though this isn't testing that case, is because our tests actually, they
test the voice API separately. They call it manually. But if our clients are calling it
like this, maybe we should have a test for this as well. So this tells me, hey, maybe
my test suite does need to be expanded. Does that make sense? I'm seeing some very, very
like, yeah, yeah, that makes sense. I like it. Awesome. Okay. So if you are a Python dev,
this isn't the end of the talk, by the way. We've got some more context and we'll show
you about CI. But if you are interested, feel free to scan this. You've got four seconds
before I move slides. And as I move slides, in slow motion, I'll be passing over this
microphone. This was just Python, of course. I think there are more non-Python devs here.
Not Python. We, of course, have more frameworks. I think there are more languages out there,
but I think they're the most important ones that I like personally. And pretty much the
only really good one for Java is PyTest. And we also have Striker. And Striker is one that
supports quite some languages. It supports JavaScript, C sharp, Scala. Of course, it doesn't
do this in one to each one has their own dependencies, because you can't have one solution for all.
But what you particularly like about it is that it supports JavaScript. And this brings
this kind of back-end heavy tool. Testing is usually mostly, I think, in front-end can
use some law when it comes to testing often. This also brings the testing frameworks and
the testing quality more to the front-end. So that's what I really like.
But we wanted to discuss a bit more. Mike's already sort of introduced it. So what is
a good mutation score? We had the Goodhart's law where we sort of saw that code coverage
can also lead to people implementing tests just to improve coverage, not just sort of
defeats the purpose. You're doing it just for the metric, not for the actual purpose.
And how does this work with mutation score? Now, first, here's a picture of how PyTest
report looks. So not to bash on Python, but much prettier and much clearer. Because now,
particularly what is interesting about this one, it shows you both the line coverage and
the mutation coverage. We can ignore the test train. And this shows us the sweet spots in
a report. Because at the end, we have generated a lot of mutants. We have a lot of classes.
And we only have very little time. So where are we going to look and investigate this
report and see where the strains are? And the one that's the least interesting here
is the notification service. The notification service also doesn't have any coverage. And
if there's no coverage, then the mutants are also not interesting because you have a bigger
problem here, which is you don't have tests at all for this. Then you have a choice. You
have the proposal service and proposed service too. Now, the fact that they are named equally
is because they're from another example. But proposed service too is the one that has 100%
coverage, and yet it didn't kill a single mutant. And this is the sweet spot. Because
this means that we have code that is well tested, or at least there's tests that covering
this piece of code. But there's no single bug that was caught. So this deserves some
attention because it means that we didn't fully test this. So these are the hotspots
where you open a report. The ones with high line coverage and low mutation coverage, those
are the ones you really want to go through. Those are the ones that give you the findings
to go through a team and say, hey, see, we need mutation testing. Because here, just
these two classes alone already, it showed me that we need to improve our quality.
And now back to the score. So the example we had, we managed to kill 512 out of 682
mutant, which is about a 75% score. Now, the question is, is this a good score?
Is this a good score?
Yes, yes. The golden answer. It depends. I love that answer. We already saw that 100%
doesn't make sense. Things like logging, and there are more things like generated code,
et cetera, things that you don't necessarily want to test, even though there are mutates
generators for it. There are a couple things you can, of course, do. You can also, depending
on the language and the framework you use, you can tweak the mutation testing framework
quite a bit. For example, the PyTest version actually out of the box already ignores and
doesn't mutate any logging lines. And all the big frameworks are known to the tool.
So anything that goes to SLF4J, it doesn't mutate it. So it also doesn't appear in your
report, which is quite nice. And you can easily add things. Like if you have a custom metrics
facade somewhere, also typically something you don't want to cover in unit tests, you
can add that as well. So the thing here is that mutates testing is not really a score
you want to achieve. It's more that the report can be interesting to look at and gives you
sort of the nice spots. And once you completely set it up nice and you're familiar with the
report, you can maybe start looking at the score, but definitely it shouldn't become
an 80% goal or something like it was with code coverage. It's just there, it goes through
the report instead. So now we've sort of discussed all the tools you need. We have discussed
the frameworks. We have discussed the technology. And now it's time, of course, for you to fly.
So how would you get started on this? And the thing that's important here is if you
want to start, so you now think, oh, this is a great talk. I want to start with mutates
testing. Depending on the size of your project, it might be wise to just start with just a
single package. I've done this on projects that are a couple of, say, thousand lines
big. And even though in Max's example we had 682 mutants, this can also, depending on the
kind of code you have, easily grow to tens of thousands of mutants, which can be quite
slow. It can also be that there's something weird in your code base that doesn't really
work well with mutation testing or something that's just extremely slow. An example that
I had was that we had, so what's good to keep in mind is actually just to take a side step,
the mutates testing framework also measures in the beginning for each individual test
which code it covers. So there's a nice graph from code, production code, to the tests.
It helps us optimize because if we want to run the entire test suite, all the tests for
every single mutant is going to take endless. Instead, because we know the coverage, we
can also see if we mutate this one line, we know which tests to discover, so we only need
to execute those few tests. But what if you have tests that actually cover half your code
base? For example, one of the things you can do in Java is if you're doing things with
Spring is you can actually boot up the entire Spring application and start doing acceptance
tests from your unit tests, which is typically not necessarily the worst thing to do, but
you now have a very slow test that does cover half your code base that will be executed
for each single mutant. So these are things you want to get rid of. You want to exclude
this acceptance test because otherwise you're going to be waiting endlessly. So my point
about starting locally and starting small was start just with one package. Start with
the utility package to see if it works, see if the report works for you, and then from
there you can expand, add more packages, and also you can see, oh, now it's taking ten
times as long. Why is this? And you can find the painful packages there. So as I mentioned,
you can exclude some tests, and also there are often candidates, certain pieces of code
you might want to exclude. For example, there's no use in testing generated code, but also
it might be that you have certain domain packages that contain just all your domain objects,
your POJOs, which just setters and getters, something that you also typically want to
exclude to your coverage report. You might also want to exclude this from code mutation,
some of it from mutation testing. And now that's done. So we talked about running it
on your machine. We also can do this in the cloud, of course.
Thank you. So as you can see, there's a pigeon on this slide, and Paco, as we've said, has
a personal vendetta, so I've taken over this section. So here we can see that we're going
to run off our machine. So why would you want to run off your machine rather than on your
machine? Any questions? Any ideas?
What happens in the background?
Yes. So what happens in the background is what we said there. Any other reason you might
want to run non-locally? No. I've got a couple. Oh, oh, hand.
CI.
CI. Yeah, you might want to end your CI system. In fact, that's what we'll be showing you.
So foreshadowing. I like it. So yeah, it takes some time. And if you're using a CI system,
you get to use those cloud resources. And also what's important is that you can, if
you've got code which is maybe dependent on different OSes, might behave differently,
you can specify different versions and platforms to run on as well.
So stop talking. I hear you cry. Well, I'm afraid this is what we're here for, but unfortunately,
I will be keeping talking, but what I will do is show it a bit of an example.
So I applied this to my code base, my own code base myself, into my CI system. So you
can see here, this is GitHub actions. And I've got a piece of YAML, essentially. I've
got this mutation test.YAML file. And what that does is sets up an action for me to use.
So this is something that I manually run. And I can do this here. So I manually run
that. And what it will do is do the mutation test non-locally, and it will produce some
HTML output for me to look at. Now, that seems, you know, I'll go a little bit into what that
YAML does, but it seems like something that should be able for everyone to do themselves
if they want to. So GitHub actions, the reason I show that partly is because what we use,
but also, you know, it's free for open source projects. So, you know, it's been useful for
me because I've not had to pay for it. So, you know, just a heads up.
So, yeah, I'll be showing you this with GitHub actions really quickly. And I'll show you
the YAML. I'll show you what I did. Hopefully by the end of this, the next couple of slides,
you will see how easy it is actually to do this and why actually this is all good and
maybe you want to try this yourself when you get home. So here's some YAML. First of all,
this is our mutation test YAML. It's got one job. It's pretty simple. All we're doing,
we're running on Ubuntu. Running one specific Python version to do this. Depending on what
your test base is, oh, they run a great time in there. Or there is thunder. So basically,
we have, yeah, we're testing on one version for me because my code doesn't vary enough
between versions and OSes, so for me, it's not relevant to do that. But if we look at
this next slide, I'll show you the workflow that goes through when I actually run this
action. So first of all, we check out the code. Then we set up a version of Python with
it. Once we've done that, we actually install our dependencies, including our mutmut as well
as our regular dependencies. So now we've got the new mutation testing framework installed
here as well on this kind of test runner. Then what we do is we run a mutation test.
So we do that with mutmutrun. But because we're running in a CI system, we don't want
insanely long logs and due to how it's outputted, we want a no progress flag there just to show
that we're not seeing every line of output, we just see the important parts. We also have
the CI flag, which is one of my only contributions to actual open source. But I added that and
I'm kind of proud of myself. So that basically means that you get a good sensible output,
like return code, when you run in a CI system. Because the default for mutmut is depending
on the type of mutants that we call, it will give you a different exit code that is non-zero.
So you kind of need to consider that or to suppress that with some scary, scary bash.
That's what I did at first. That's why I wrote the flag. Once we've done that, we save it
as HTML and we upload it so you can access that yourself as well.
So that's it. That's the whole piece of YAML. It's 35 lines. And that set up the entire
mutation test for my suite. So you can see, hopefully, does this seem kind of easy? I
think it seems pretty gentle to do, at least in this sort of scope. If you're a Java dev
with a 20,000 line project, you might want to be a bit more careful. But if you've got
a Python hobby thing, try it out, right? Try it out.
What I would say, there are some more concerns. So first of all, I chose to run this manually
when I want to run it. I chose not to run this on push or PR. I chose to run this manually.
And the reason for that is that I don't expect my code base to sufficiently change between
like small commits. And what I want to do is really not use mutation tests as that kind
of score, that 75%. I don't want that to be a metric for me that I've just turned into
a target. I want it to stay as just a good idea, an indicator of what my tests are doing
and what I could be doing better. So for me, I don't want to run every time, partly because
it takes a blooming long time, especially if I'm using multiple versions, which we also
have to factor in. So you might want to do that. So I didn't. I just ran on Ubuntu and
that was fine for me. But yeah, it depends on what your code is. You might want to run
on different platforms, right? So do factor that in. And that will help you a lot if you're
in a CI system.
So the other question there is, should we run on push or PR? My opinion is no. I think
there will be people in this room who disagree with me. Maybe say on a PR you should run
that or maybe there's some kind of metric you want to associate with score that you
then want to look at in some way. For me, that's not how I use mutation testing. And
I think what I want to get out of this is we don't want a situation where mutation
testing becomes a new target. We've got to get a certain score. Because then we're just
kind of abstracting that problem of code coverage targets. We're just doing that all over again,
right? So we're trying to avoid that.
So the final question here is one I'll ask of Paco to explain. Paco, do you think I should
use mutation testing in my role as an audience member right now? What do you reckon?
Yes. Well, so it was there already. It depends. There are some things you can ask yourself.
Because it needs a question. So mutation testing is, of course, definitely not a silver bullet.
It's something that the reports take quite some time to go through. And of course, it's
quite computationally expensive to run the process.
So the couple of questions that you can ask yourself that are quite obvious are for projects
which have a really high quality goal. When people die or when a lot of money is lost
or a combination of those two. So just to check, how many of you are working on a project
that fits in these three?
Okay, then you need this yesterday.
Yes. But for the rest of the room, including me, there are some other questions we can
ask ourselves. And I think one of the important ones is are you using code coverage? Because
if you're not using code coverage, let's start with that. And let's first get coverage and
get to see how many tests you have.
Then the next question is, is how much value do you put into this? How much value do you
get out of this code coverage? And what I mean with that is, do you make decisions based
on it? Is like a definition of done on your sprint or is it with a built fail if there's
80% coverage or also in the case of due diligence, you're selling a company, not something we
also would do, but you would also want to know how well is the software I'm buying or
how well is the software I'm working on?
So here I would say, if you're using code coverage and you're making decisions based
on that code coverage, then yes, you should at least have a look at mutation testing to
see what the state is. You don't have to do this always. You don't have to put it in CI.
Just once a year or go home rather than your computer once just to see what the current
state of your team is. Because it's going to very well be that you're on a high performing
team which already has their PRs and everything so well and set up that it's not worth the
time maybe. Because apparently the mutation testing report might even confirm that, the
fact that you killed all the mutants. So that would be great.
And there's another question that I like. What's the cost of fixing a bug? And I have
two stories for this. My first example is, and it's the first company I worked for, this
was an enterprise company that built software that was running on premise at the customer
and the customer was often in government. And then you're in the line with all these
big integrators which means you have feature freezes and moments where you can actually
go to the customer and deploy your software. Which is quite expensive. Which also means
that if you get a bug after this feature freezer, after this upgrade window, you have a serious
issue because you need to go to the customer. You need to explain what went wrong. It's
a very costly thing. A very costly issue. So here definitely, again, mutation testing
can be quite interesting because a lot of money can be involved in reputation.
The other example that I had was more of a greenfield project which had more of the start-up
vibes where it was really of a fill fast and fix fast mentality. So this was a project
where rather than focusing on getting our quality monitoring up to speed, we were mostly
focusing on making sure that we could very quickly fix bugs as well. It was of course
running on-premises in the cloud so we could control it. And the most important goal was
there to just click a button and be in production again in 10 minutes and have active monitoring
to see if anything goes wrong. Here the cost of fixing a bug is already a lot lower which
means that the reason to consider it might be a bit less. Especially if you're again
in a, for example, a high-performing team which all work into each other. You know what
you're doing. You know you can trust each other because you're really, you're all professionals.
Maybe it's not worth to also spend half a day going through a mutatist report if you
already know what the outcome is probably going to be. Again still do it once. These
are two things you could consider in when to use it. So those are the things I want
to give away with you is don't go into it blindly. Just ask yourself should I really
use it? And then for the last part.
For the last part I'd just like to sum up. So I think hopefully if we've gotten here
we've kind of shown you what mutation testing is, why you might want to consider using it
and how you could possibly get going starting with running that and also why you should.
So if we're here I just want to summarize first of all I'm sorry I used this penguin
as an evil penguin earlier. It is adorable. I just like that Dali when I asked it to give
it some fake wings it gave it three. It gave it this extra flipper here. I'm not sure what
that was for. But what I'd like to do is just quickly summarize what we've talked about
today. First of all mutation testing is a way to test your tests. It helps you to beat
the problem where you're using good hot slow for coverage. It saves you from trying to
turn coverage into a metric that you don't have as a target. You don't want to have code
coverage. It's got to be above this threshold or we don't merge. That's not where we want
to be. What we want to do is write good tests. So if you are going to do this yourself an
important part is to start small. So start locally on your machine. If you've got a big
code base then what you need to do really is run on a subset of that code base. If you've
got a smaller code base like me you're probably okay. Either way start locally on your machine.
You also want to run if you can. If you want asynchronous reports, if you want to use the
resources available on a CI system you can run mutation testing there. So do consider
that if your stuff is in CI. And finally I just want to say that mutants hopefully we've
demonstrated that mutants are like adorable penguins. They're valuable and they are wonderful.
They're really great to use. They can tell you so much about your code. They're extremely
useful. So don't fear them because you should love them. Thank you very much.
If there are any questions, comments, objections, love mail, hate mail, anything? Shout at me.
So the question there was just if we can give some more examples of the kind of range of
things that are possible to mutate. So essentially the short answer is anything that will still
make the code run. So in the Java case the code compiled, in my case the code run. So
in this situation things like I'll give you some Python examples. For example, changing
a variable from a certain type to another so you might type pass something. You might
with a mathematical expression you might add extra terms to that expression. You might
change return types, error types. You might set things to none at any given time. You
might call something and you have removed parts of it. Set things to zero. There's other
stuff. Paco can you think of any mutation testing job?
So I think the examples you gave for that, it depends on the mutators you use. Of each
framework you can also go through the list of mutators to see what kind of mutators are
out there. What's good to keep in mind is that it does use some basic fundamental strategies
to determine if it can be mutated. Because for example if you have a stream and in this
stream you do some operations which you could in theory cut out, you're still using the
return value which means that the mutatistic framework thinks okay let's keep that intact.
The same goes for if you're using the Spring Reactor framework. You could do lots and lots
of smart mutations in there but it's not really there yet. It's really the fundamental things,
the conditional logic, the mathematical logic I think are the two main things you'll see.
And actually also account for often the most typical programming errors I would say.
Awesome. I mean anything you'd like to mutate? Because I guess a lot of these things are
open source. Anything that you might be good if it did exist? Any ideas?
Question? Answer?
Question? So two questions. The first one, could you comment some framework for C and
C++? And the second, what do you think about the idea to force developers or to require
developers to run those mutation tests as a gate hook before pushing only for the duty
of the tests associated with the code which they have actually changed? Just to save
the computational power on the entire machine. Okay, so the question there just for the livestream
was two things. One is are there any mutation testing frameworks for C or C++? I will say
personally I don't know. I haven't used C++ since my physics degree so I couldn't tell
you. I don't know if you know anything about that, Paco.
I just did a quick Google search. That's all. So I see there are some frames available.
I just want to say there is a project by the University of Luxembourg which is called FAQAS.
FAQAS.
And it's not there quite yet.
So based on the search I see there is something for C and also for a bit more for C++. Regarding
your other question by the way, so should you do it as a gate hook? Given that it's
right, that was the question?
The idea was basically to require developers to run those mutation tests but not the whole
set. The only mutation tests which are touching, which are testing the duty tests, which are
tested in code which was modified in this project.
Yeah, so actually there are some, depending on the framework, some have features which
are incremental reports. So where they can just store the last state, then you can do
a diff and use the results from your last execution to not execute all mutants and not
generate all mutants because it knows I only change these production lines so I only need
to generate mutants for these and I only change these tests so I only need to rerun the tests
for these mutants which can tremendously speed it up.
But still using it as a gate hook, I'm not sure. You can, by the way, use the same logic
in the NCI as well to use the incremental reporting that saves a bit despite an also
supports, I think.
Yeah, so with what you have, you have caching, so you can cache those tests that you've done
already and if those cases aren't touched, then you're sort of good if the changes to
your code don't affect that. So that is an option. I would say, yeah, I, thank you, my
opinion is again that maybe you don't want to explicitly mandate this on every run and
the reason for that is it's kind of like it can then become kind of a metric that you
can try and optimize for or something to look at whereas really I think the nice way to
use it is every now and then is how I would say so. I think if you've got a super critical
project where, you know, if that's really important, you may want to run it like that.
For me, I don't need to but I think that's really up to you, up to you as an implementer,
what you want to do and I think there's definitely a use case to do it in that way if that was
important to you.
Hand over here, hello.
Yes, yes, short answer is yes. Long answer is depending on the actual framework, it might
be that you had a comment to ignore it. Alternatively, there is a config file set up as well in
Python where you can say only mutate these paths, only do these things. So what language
do you use?
That's a striker.
I would say yes, I haven't looked that much at the striker but I think there are some
nice stuff, it's quite generic for all frameworks. Exclude code for mutation, definitely yes.
And depending on the framework, some even have nice things like exclude, do not mutate
any calls to these classes which is interesting for the logging, for example, do not mutate
any calls to this logging class but same you can do for packages, class paths, et cetera.
I would say with striker as well, one of my colleagues uses striker because he maintains
.NET SDK and he's also got mutation testing there in striker and it does seem very performant,
it seems like it does have a lot of those features as well. If you're interested in
TypeScript, I think there is something for you there.
Cool.
I think it might be free on open source reposers. Another question?
Are there specific communities that are reproducible for debugging path process?
Actually not a lot of...
Question?
Oh yeah, so the question is how reproducible are the mutants? So if you find one and the
next one, is it still there? So as far as I know, there shouldn't be any randomness
in these mutant generations. It just goes over the code, any condition that it finds
that it can mutate, it will mutate. So the next time you run it, the same mutant should
be there at the same place. So you could also see whether you killed it the next time. So
yes, it's reproducible.
A hand there. I think this person was first.
That's a good question. I'll repeat that one. That's a good one. So the question there
was, so mutation testing, we've talked all the big game. We've come up here and been
like, hey, look, this is important, right? That's what we've talked about. And the question,
which is a very valid question, is hey, if it's so important, why is no one supporting
this question? Why is this all open source stuff? And you know what? I agree. That's
a really good question. It's one I asked as well, to be honest. So now I totally support
the question. And the question I'll probably say is, yeah, why aren't employers supporting
this? The short answer I think is to do with ROI, unfortunately. And that sucks, honestly,
because I would like us to invest more time in certain things. And I think it's just to
do with company priorities, right? So I would like to spend more time. Honestly, I had
quite a lot of fun adding the one feature I did get to add. I'd quite like to do some
more. But again, I've got this API to implement. So do I have time? Well, no one's funding
me to do it. So unfortunately, it really is like, unless there's an obvious ROI, this
just seems to be the way things go. Unfortunately, that's the way we've kind of structured our
platforms and so on. So I gave a talk earlier on PyPy and malware. And there was actually
the reason that that kind of is so prevalent and so possible on PyPy is because PyPy haven't
really implemented many ways to actually protect against malware being uploaded. So currently,
I've uploaded some malware to PyPy that you can get yourself. And actually, the reason
that they, it's not real malware, to be clear, it's a rick roll. But basically, what I'm
trying to say here is that that project kind of didn't really get off the ground in terms
of protecting users, just because I think originally Facebook were funding it and they
stopped funding and that just didn't then continue. So unfortunately, yeah, this is just
kind of the way that things are in open source right now. And yeah, I do feel your pain. I
do understand. But that's all I can really say, I'm afraid.
Yeah, I would quickly add to this, by the way, Striker, for example, is actually funded,
is backed by a company who, for example, let's work in terms work on it as well. So some
frameworks actually are backed and there are people already investing it. So it's not always
bad, but sorry, let's go to that side.
So you showed some HDMI reports for the results of the mutagenet test.
Yes.
We all know all managers and pretty teams loves your KPIs. So I'm wondering, is there
any integration or bringing to export the mutagenet test result in Sona
or anything that's going to happen over the next year?
Yeah, so let's also ask, you were the maintainer of the other framework. So how does it go
for the other by the framework?
So, okay. So I talked about mut-mut not having that facility that feature.
in cosmic rays that.
Well, not really.
In cosmic ray, the moment is kind of a bit unmaintained.
And so the same kind of supplies.
I don't want to say names, but there is a very, very large
450 maybe vendor that uses it.
And we asked them, can you fund development?
They said, you know, no.
They have shown this around at large events, like in front of
thousands and thousands of people.
But yeah, they're like, OK, we keep all the changes for itself
and find it as it is.
So for the Python frameworks.
So we talk about time and balance and effort that you
need to put in to develop all these features and functionalities.
So the core team doesn't have this.
Yeah, so for the Python frameworks, there's not really
CI plugin support.
I do know that, for example, PyTest, there is support for
Jenkins and Sonar.
And I'm not sure about Striker, but I know it's there.
And usually these things are relatively easy to build
yourself with here as well, because all you have to do is,
if there is a report in some JSON file, you can quite easily
parse it and make a nice HTML form about this.
Because again, they're all open for contributions.
Do we have time for one last?
I want to just add to that a little bit.
OK, really quickly, first of all, with your question, yeah,
when I originally implemented my movement thing, I did do it
on PR, and in that case I got an action that would comment my
coverage in a nice, metric-y way.
And so you can, it's quite simple to do.
So about Cosmic Query, first of all, that sucks, and I'm
sorry, that's blooming awful.
Yeah, sadly, it does seem that a lot of what we've kind of
been discussing on the side of the room is just like, man,
it would be good if some, you know, we all agree this is
important, right, and it's useful for a lot of things.
It would be great if someone funded it.
So I think, unfortunately, with Python, that is the state of
play, and it does suck.
But yes, I get you.
Any other questions, finally?
Yes, hello.
Can you write custom notation to motivate your code, you know,
custom logic?
That's a really good question.
So, sorry?
Repeat it.
That's, I will now repeat your really good question.
The question was, so the question was, if I have a
certain type of mutant that I want to make, can I do that?
So I would say, with the stuff that I used in Python, the
answer is you need to actually, you know, use the version you've
downloaded, edit it yourself, and add that stuff.
So sadly, there's not an easy customizable way.
That would be an awesome enhancement, though, that I would
like to see.
You know, that would be cool.
In other platforms, Paco, any other?
I do know that I think Python does have some extension points,
so it really depends.
I know that the company I work for currently called Picnic,
they're also working on extending it, for example, for
reactive code.
So there are some extension points often.
So, in short, it depends on the framework and how easy it is.
Are we done?
Okay, we're at time.
Thank you so much.
This has been a really nice discussion as well, so thank you
for sharing yours.
Thank you.