So, sorry for the mess. It's a bit impressing all these people and so on. I'm Simon. I'm
working as a research engineer at University of Paris and I will be here to present you
Geeks, to be able to do some reversible research. And there is a group, Geeks HPC, which try
to apply Geeks tooling for scientific context. So, currently we are in a replication and
reproducibility crisis. So, more than 70% of researchers are unable to reproduce the
results of peers or more than half are unable to reproduce their own results. So, we have
a big issue. So, there is many problems of this replication crisis and maybe one solution
is open science. So, what does it mean open science? So, what does it mean science? Science
means being transparent and collective activity. And what is a scientific result? Scientific
result is some experiment, so producing experimental data and then we have some numerical processing.
So, to do that, today we have different way because we need to communicate. So, we need
to write results. So, we need open article to be able to read the results, to share the
data. So, we have open data. We need to share the source code. But there is something that
we never discuss is that all that need to be glued together because there is a numerical
processing. So, we need to glue everything together. So, we need another one. We need
a computational environment. And this is really one of the issue is that if this is not open,
all the other stack is failing. So, that's the topic of today. How do we manage this
computational environment? So, again, a result is a paper, some data and an analysis. And
there is some parts which are, I mean, possible to audit, for example, a paper. You can read
it. A data, you can read the protocol that generates the data. You have analysis, you
can read the script. But there is some part that are opaque. For example, the instrument,
a telescope, a microscope, this is opaque. We don't know how it works. But there is something
that is depend on our collective practice as researchers. And this is something that
we can act on to do a better research. So, the question is to be able to eliminate at
least this dependent and turn this as an auditable task to be really transparent. So, yeah,
from my point of view, a computation and computing is just similar to an instrument. So, we should
apply the same strategy that experimental people are applying for any instrument. And
computing is just an experiment, in fact. So, the challenge about reputible science.
From my point of view, there is two kinds. The first one is controlling the source of
variation. What is different between this and that? So, between this computational environment
and this computational environment. Because as with the telescope, for example, we want
to know what is different between this telescope and this telescope to be sure that what we
are observing is correct. So, from a scientific method, we need that the computational environment
is transparent. And from a scientific knowledge viewpoint, what we are building together need
to be independent. So, what I'm observing, you should observe the same. And this observation
should be sustainable when the time is passing. We should be able to observe the same thing.
Otherwise, it means that maybe we miss something. So, the big question today is with this kind
of context, how do we redo later and elsewhere? So, I did something on my machine and you
have to do this thing on your machine, for example, six months or one year or five years
later with the computer. And this is a big issue and is part of the reputible crisis
in science from my point of view. So, what is a computational environment? Computational
environment implies various points. For example, what is a source code? But, for example, if
say I use Python and this script, okay, we have the source codes of Python is in C and
we have the source code of this Python script, okay. But the Python interpreter require a
C compiler, so we need tools for building. And my script, for example, needs some Python
libraries, so we need also tools for running at runtime. So, each tool has the same issue.
What is the source code? What is the tools for building? And so, this is recursive. So,
this is a bigger issue. And answering all this question is controlling the source of
variation. So, the question is so how do we capture the answer of all this question? So,
the question is not new. We have already tools. Picket manager modifies container. So, for
example, with Picket manager like Appetit for Debian, Yum for Red Hat, you can control
this computational environment. But there is some issue. For example, how do you have
several versions of open blast on the same machine? It doesn't work really easily with
Debian or with Yum and so on. So, there is fixes but it's not really, I mean, practical
is sometimes it's difficult. So, you have to fix this issue, you have environment manager
like Conda, Pip, Modify and so on. But this is really difficult because, for example,
in Conda, how do you know how it is built? What is inside what you install? So, this
is for transparency in science. Modify, how do you use modifies on the laptop? I think
no one. And Docker is for container, Docker, Singularity or whatever is a strategy which
generally based on the previous solution. So, in fact, you have exactly the same problems
and the previous solution. It just helped to move stuff from one place to the other
one but it doesn't help to be able to have the correct thing in the first time. Geeks,
in fact, is all these three solution glued together. So, it tried to fix all the anions
from each to have something, I mean, working, fixing all the issue of everything. So, Geeks
is a package manager like Appetit, Yum, et cetera. It's transactional and declarative.
It means that you can roll back, you can have a concurrent version and so on. It can produce
a Pax which is Docker images, for example. It can produce virtual machines like NCBEL
for deploying on some machine. You can build a complete distribution and it's also a scheme
library so you can extend Geeks. So, okay, the talk is 25 minutes. So, just kind of Appetit
before lunch. So, I don't speak about all that because it's too much. So, I just speak
about how Geeks help in open research from my point of view. So, I think it's really
easy to try. You have just a script and give a look before installing it. It's just a vast
script but check it and you can install Geeks on any recent distribution. So, it's really
easy to try. You are running Debian. You can try Geeks without installing the complete distribution.
You can use Geeks on the top of any distribution and it's really easy to try. Give a try. So,
now, Geeks is just another package manager. So, you have the same command that you have
in any package manager for sharing packages, showing packages, installing packages, removing
packages and so on. It's exactly the same as any package manager. But you have some
more functionality like transactional. So, everything you can do action in the same time.
So, for example, removing and installing in the same transaction or you can roll back.
For example, you install something and you want to roll back to uninstall this thing
without breaking nothing. So, okay, this is another package manager. But is it really
another package manager? So, yeah, we can have a command line. We install remove without
special privilege. So, this is nice. It's transactional. So, there is no broken state.
We have binary substitutes. So, we don't have to wait hours and hours to have our binary.
But this is nice. But what is really, really nice is decorative management. It means that
everything is a configuration file with scheme. But you can declare everything and you can
produce isolated environment on the fly. This is something that's really helpful. And you
can also see Geeks as a factory for the Docker images, for example. So, okay, this is all
interesting feature. But why Geeks is reproducible? Or what does it mean it's reproducible? Reproducible
means, I mean, for reproducibility, we need to talk about what is a version. So, what
is a version? At least say, for example, I use GCC at version 11. Okay, nice. But what
does it mean? Concretely, I use GCC at version 11. It means that you need GCC, the compiler,
but you also need LD, which is a linker. And you know, Benitez, for example, and the Gleepsy
library. But the compiler GCC, it needs, for example, MPC, which is a package that does,
I don't know what exactly, anyway. And you need also MPFR and so on. And you have this
kind of graph. And we can ask the question, is it the same GCC at version 11 if we replace
this MPF4 at version 4.1 by MPF4 at version 4.0? Is it the same GCC or not? And maybe
not. And if it is not the same, maybe we're seeing a difference. How can we show that
we are using the exact same GCC? So this is just an extract of the graph, because the
graph have roots. And yeah, it can be really large. And maybe we can also talk about what
are the roots of this graph. But this is another talk. So when you say that, okay, but I need
to have a version. So what is my version in Geeks? So Geeks describe the state of Geeks.
So in fact, Geeks describe is a version of Geeks. And what it does, in fact, it paints
the complete collection of all the packages and Geeks itself. And because that we are
able to freeze the complete graph, we can move this graph from one place to the other.
So this graph, in fact, describe the nodes of each, the node in this graph specify a
receipt. And this receipt defines the code source, the build time tombs, and the dependency.
So for me, yeah. And this graph can be really, really large. For example, for Skypy, which
is a scientific Python library, there is more than 1,000 nodes. So yeah, it can be really
large. So for when I say GCC at version 11, it means one fixed graph. And providing the
state which describes this complete graph. And I can reproduce this complete graph on
another machine. So this is collaboration in action. So Alice describes the list of
the tools in a manifest declarative way to generate the environment Geeks share and
providing the tools. So this creates an environment containing the tools that are listed in the
manifest file. OK, this is nice. But now she describes the revision of Geeks. So she writes
Geeks describe and this fix the state of Alice. So OK, this Alice is working on her laptop.
But collaboration is share this computational environment. So it's about sharing the state.
To share the state, you need to share one specific graph. To share this graph, you need
to only share these two files. And if Blake has these two files, Blake can create the
exact same computational environment as Alice. So you have the Geeks time machine. You specify
the state of Alice shell and specify the tools that Alice used. And Blake and Alice are running
the exact same computational environment. And for example, if you have Carol who knows
these two files, she also can reproduce the exact same that Alice and Blake. So in fact,
you only need two files. And with these two files, you can reproduce everything from one
place to the other. So in fact, you have this kind of picture. Alice, Blake, Carol are in
different time frame. But they can jump from this time frame, virtually, in different time
frames, to the same place. Because their machines are in different state, but they can temporarily
go to another state to create the computational environment. To make this work when the time
is passing, you need to preserve all the source code. And this is not straightforward. It's
not trivial to preserve all the source code. And you also need some backward compatibility
of the Linux kernel and some compatibility of the hardware. But OK. And when these three
conditions are satisfied, you have the reproducibility. But what is the size of the window, of the
time window, where these three conditions are satisfied? And this is, from my point
of view, unknown. And Geeks is, to my knowledge, a case unique by experimenting to be able,
because we have the tooling to do all that. And now we can know what is the size that
we are able to reproduce the past in the future.
So what is software heritage? So software heritage is an archive. It collects, preserves
software in source code form from a very long term. And Geeks is able to save the source
code of the package and the receipt of the package itself. And Geeks itself is also saved
in software heritage. And Geeks is able to use a software heritage archive to fall back
if a stream disappears. So you have the postdoc working on some GitLab instance. And the account
is closed because the postdoc is moving to other place and so on. And now you have this
paper with this URL with a GitLab package and, oh, no, it doesn't work because the account
is closed. If you were using Geeks, transparently, you can check if the source code is on software
heritage. And this asks really good question about how to fit a software. And do you notice
it only the source? And what about the dependency and the build time options and so on? How
do you fit a software? And how do you fit it? Do you fit with intrinsic identifier,
like checksum, or with intrinsic identifier, like version label? This is not easy. So in
summary, there are three commands. I'm almost done, right? So in summary, you have three
commands. And these three commands, which are Geeks shell, Geeks time machine, and Geeks
time machine. They help you to have a computational environment that you can inspect and collectively
share. So if you have this and two files, manifest and channel files, you are reproducible
over the time. So OK, for offline, because I convinced you that is cool. So here is some
resources to read offline. So Geeks HPC is a group of people trying to apply this Geeks
tooling to scientific research. And we're organizing coffee Geeks, where we drink coffee
and speak about Geeks. There is an article trying to explain this kind of vision of what
Geeks could provide for open research. And for French speaker, there is a one hour tutorial.
And there is a now Geeks is 10 years, so it's kind of ready. So we organized 10 years events
where there is some really nice materials about Geeks. And Geeks is not new at first
time. So here, there is all the number are linked to the previous presentation. So as
you see, there is a 31 presentation about Geeks in first time. So you have a lot of
material about what Geeks can do for your job, for your task. So it ran in production
on big cluster, but also in a lot of laptop and desktop. And here, for example, is two
paper in completely medical and biomedical stuff using Geeks as a tooling, as I presented
about Geeks share time machine and so on. So open science means to be able to trace
and transparent because it's to be able to collectively study bug to bug, to be what
is different from one thing to the other thing. And this is a scientific method. And we have
to apply the scientific method to the computational environment. This is my opinion and the message
that I would like you bring back to home. And if you have Geeks, we can do that by controlling
the environment and compare two different environment to know what is different. So
okay, this is the kind of what we are trying to do with Geeks project. So thank you. And
I'm ready for your question.
Yeah. Yeah. I will try to do my best. Yeah.
Ah, look, look, looking. So the question is, okay, I don't have the root privilege to install
Geeks on the cluster because once Geeks is installed on any cluster, you can, you can
run it without privilege, but you need to install the first time you need to install
Geeks, you need root privilege. And the system administrator of my cluster doesn't mean,
yeah, I need to convince him. So maybe the answer is to say other people are already
doing that. So it's not, I mean, to reduce the scare to provide a new tool. This is what
I would like to try to say, okay, these people are doing it. So maybe it's not so scary.
I think it was after. So yeah.
You mentioned that you're not sure how big the time window is.
Yeah.
If you look today, how far can you back and still reproduce?
So five years, 10 years.
No. So the question is, okay, what is the size of the window and can we go back five
years from now in the past? The issue is that the mechanism to bring back in time or to
travel in time in Geeks had been introduced in 2019. So in fact, with Geeks, we don't
have the tooling to go back earlier. So now, I mean, the zero for Geeks is a version one.
So it's 2019.
Yeah.
A lot of scientists are using Mac OS and not Linux. Is it possible to use all this stuff
even though Geeks can't really run on Mac OS?
So Geeks cannot run on Mac OS, but we can ask the question, is it transparent if we
are running on Mac OS? So is it, are we applying scientific method if we're running on Mac
OS?
I mean, I have not the question, is it a collective decision?
Yeah.
Hello, my name is Ivan. As far as I understand, who is or Geeks provides the same approach
as the Geeks?
Yeah.
I've never used Geeks before, but I have some experience with Nix. Is there any crucial
differences between them?
So from my point of view, sorry, in the slides, there is some appendix. So there is extra
slide and there is one extra slide trying to explain what, from my point of view, the
difference with Nix. So the question is, what is the difference between Nix and Geeks? Because
Geeks use exactly the same package management functional strategy. So what is the difference?
From my point of view, the difference is that you have a continuum in Geeks in the language.
The package I wrote in Scheme and the code of Geeks itself is also wrote in Scheme. The
configuration file I wrote in Scheme. So you have a big continuation with everything. And
because that, you can extend Geeks for your own stuff.
So for example, you can write a package transformation on the fly using, I mean, Geeks as a library.
You cannot do that with Nix because you have a lot of different tooling in C++ and some
patterns. From my point of view, is this unity of the continuum of the language?
As far as I understand, Scheme is a general purpose programming language.
Yeah. But Scheme allow you to write domain specific language. It's a good language to
write domain specific language. So in fact, you have the both of the two worlds. From
my point of view.
Thank you.
Last question.
Oh yeah. Sorry. Last question. Yeah.
That's really tough. In Geeks, we always control the fancy graph even if you're building on
top of it or if you cut the graph.
Yeah. This is a, so when you are running Geeks, for example, on the top of Debian. So how do
we manage the graph and can we cut the graph to reuse a part of the Debian part? I mean,
a part of the graph from Debian. So the question if maybe it could be helpful for some packages.
But when you do that, you are not able to manage the computational environment because
if you have, for example, if I cut the graph on Debian. So I have a state in Debian with
some packages. I cut the graph at some place to use this Debian packages.
If I do that, how my collaborator can cut the graph in the same place with the same
Debian packages. So this is kind of issue of a replaceability. So from a practical point
of view, it could be nice because for example, Debian has some machine learning packages that
are not yet in Geeks. So maybe we can reuse some parts, but from a replaceability point
of view, you lose the property to move from one place to the other.
Thank you.