All right, so I'll start a little bit earlier of the, actually, the 2PM.
Just by saying that, so I'm wearing this t-shirt because I'm one of the Dev Room Manager here
in this room, and I'm taking over, actually, a talk slot that has been cancelled.
So we were supposed to hear a talk by Maya Arias de Reina, who couldn't make it today,
unfortunately.
She was supposed to talk about data flowing in the right way, which is a talk about a
tool called Kauto, which implements data workflows with a low-code, no-code approach.
This is what it looks like, so of course I can't talk about this tool because I don't
know it.
It really looks pretty cool.
So we are very sorry for Maya not being here, and we hope we can host her next time.
So I will speak about a project, a research project, called Ricardo in Digital Maintenance,
which I've done with, oops, sorry, are we going for me?
Yes, I worked with Bertrice de Dangere from Sciences Po, she is a historian, and I am
Paul Girard.
I am from a company called Westware, a small agency, specialized into developing data-oriented
web applications, and we do work a lot with researchers.
Today I'm here to talk about how actually a collaboration between a researcher, Bertrice
and Dangere, myself, can be fostered by using data control systems.
By data control systems, I mean making sure we care about the data we are using in the
research by documentation, version control, and also quality control.
So the research is about the history of trade.
So together with Bertrice, we build a database of trade flows between nations, well, between
geopolitical entities in the world in the 19th century, which means that we have the
main data is we know how much amount of money in different currencies has been exchanged
between different geopolitical entities in the 19th century.
We know important exports, and we know this with a bilateral view, which means that we
know the trade from France to UK, for instance, and the reverse two from two different sources,
which makes quite a nightmare to deal with, but still.
So this is basically the main publication we already achieved.
So we started by releasing in 2016-17 a web exploration tool, I'll show you, and also
a paper about how we build this database.
And then in 2021, we released a new database called Geopol East, which is basically a dataset
that explained trying to track which geopolitical entity.
So I'm using this weird word because we have countries, of course, but also entities that
are part of countries, but we also have trade with entities that were colonies at that time
and all the kind of weird political statuses.
And because of that, we built this Geopoly database where we tried to track which geopolitical
entities were controlled by which other one in time.
And recently, we released a new version of the database, adding 230,000 new trade flows.
And this releasing of new data, because actually Beatriz discovered new archives, new archival
book about trade, this massive updates needed a tool to make sure we can actually release
the data which are clean the structure the way we want it without having to deal with
all those kind of issues manually.
I will speak about that a little bit later.
So this is what the websites, the main website looks like.
It's a web application you can go where you can explore basically the trade of the world
in the 19th century.
So we have different kinds of visualizations.
I will not go through all of them because I don't want to focus too much on this today.
Well if you have questions about this, we can go back to that later.
We also have these websites, Geopoly, that allows you to actually explore the political
evolutions of the links, sovereignty, links between the different entities.
I'll show you a little bit what it's like just afterwards I think.
So just as we totally announced, this slide deck is actually something I already presented
in another conference.
So I wanted to speak about the visual data exploration tools we made, the frictionless
data integration.
So this is the main point I want to speak about today, point two.
And also the third point was how we can actually analyze heterogeneous data in the long run,
like one century of data.
My main, I will try to convince you that actually using data integration is a very nice and
important tool to foster this long lasting collaboration we had between Bertrice, historian,
and I, a data engineer.
So that collaboration I just put a link to a conference I gave a few years ago about
this specific subject.
So visual data exploration, so I will really go quickly on this part to focus more on the
second part.
Our main objective here is to propose basically a tool, a set of interactive data visualizations
on the web that all those researchers are basically people exploring this to change
points of view on the data, looking at, for instance, the total trade of the world, then
focusing on one specific country, then on one specific currency, and to be able to add
all the different ways to look at the data in the same tool.
We also like to offer visual documentation, like visualization is a really nice important
tool to spot issues or surprises or errors in the data and to unfold the complexity of
the whole phenomenon.
So this is, for instance, the world view, so we are able to retrace the world trade
in a century, but as you can see there is more than one curve, so we have different
ways we can calculate that actually from the data.
We can, for instance, take some researchers that did re-estimations of this total trade
by correcting sources and all this kind of stuff, so that's one way to do it.
That's the green curve in this visualization, but we also can actually sum all the totals
we have in our data.
This is the yellow one, and we also have the, so here we are summing all the flows we have,
the yellow, and the red is more, we are summing only the total that were in the archive books,
and it's not the same thing.
If you sum what we have or if you take the sum that's done at the time, you don't have
the same results.
Welcome to the nightmare of dealing with archive data.
In this visualization, for instance, we are focusing on one country, Denmark, and then
we can actually spot the trade on the long run of this specific country, and we can also
visualize, so here is Germany's on the right, we can also depict actually not only the total
trade, but also the difference trade, bilateral trade between Germany and its trade partner
a long time.
Okay, so this is an objective, so geopolysts here, for instance, we see like when we talk
about Germany's overline, what are we talking about?
And we are talking about geopolitical entity that had a different statisticism on time,
you can see here, and then you can see on the bottom line which other parts, all other
geopolitical entities were actually part of Germany through time.
Because sometimes we have trade with only Saxony or Waldeck, and we want to know eventually
if those entities are part of another one.
So frictionless data integration.
So we are using a data package from frictionless data here from the Open Knowledge Foundation.
So actually there is a talk from Evgeny from frictionless team later today in the online
part of our room, we'll talk about the new tool fostering data package, and actually
I'm very interested into that, but I will talk about what I've done myself.
So about this project, the main, yeah sorry, the first thing we do is versioning the data.
So we put data as CSVs into a version control system like a Git, simply.
Here it's on GitHub, and you can see that you can track actually just the same way we
do with code, who changed which data, when and why.
So here for instance is Beatrice who actually corrected a typo in the flow number, adding
the comma at the right place, and we have the commentary here.
This is very important to keep track of what's going on with the, because we have like hundreds
and even thousands of files like that.
So it's very important to have that also to know if we have issues, if that happens, where
it comes from.
So data package.
Data package is a formalism where it's basically a JSON file where you will actually describe
the data you have, adding a documentation.
So the first interest of using data package is to actually document your data set to make
it easier for other people to actually understand what you want it to do.
And it's very important for publication at the end, open science.
So here we have the title of the project, we have the license, the contributors, that's
also very important to have.
And then we describe resources.
Resources can be seen as a data table.
So here from some of the RIC entities, and for each resources, which is a CSV here, we
describe the fields we have in the table.
So we know that the RIC name table is a string, it's unique, and it is required.
So it's really like a relational database schema.
It's really kind of the same spirit, but an images and format.
The reason why you can do that, as I said, is documenting.
The second reason is actually to control your data, so doing right, driving data validation.
So if you have a data package, describe like that, you can then use a Python library, frictionless,
it's called frictionless, which will actually check all your data line if each data line
you have respects the schema you wrote.
And if it's not the case, it will actually provide you with a report with errors like,
for instance, here I have a foreign key error because the modified currency here is not
known in the table that's supposed to have this data.
So it's a very nice way to actually, we get new data, and then we check, okay, where do
we stand about what we want to achieve at the end, which is to respect the data package
formalism we wrote.
So that's very nice.
It's very cool for data engineers, but as I said, our goal with Beatrice is that we
work together and she, because the thing is like when she enters new data in the system,
she has an historian to take decisions on how to interpret the data that were in the
archive.
I count, that's not my job.
I thought about responsibility, I don't have the skills to do it.
So we need something to allow her to actually correct the data, update the data that comes
in into the data package format.
And she can't use a common line tools in Python script and that kind of stuff.
So we need something, we missed a tool here to let actually humanist researchers, in this
case, but people in general, to be able to interact with the data flow with something
else than actually a two-technical interface.
So we built, we developed a specific web application that actually helps Beatrice to integrate
new data by using the data package as a validation system.
So all of this is done in JavaScript.
You also have a JavaScript library for the data package.
So basically, this is the steps.
So the idea is Beatrice will upload a data spreadsheet, so a new data file, transcription
of one new archival book she found, the tool which first checks the spreadsheet format,
saying like, do we have all the columns we want and everything?
If it's correct, then it will go through all the data points, checking all the errors and
grouping them to propose a creation interface for her to correct all source issues through
a form.
And we tried to do, to develop something that makes this process, which is tedious and a
long process, as easy and as fast as we could for her, Beatrice, to actually go through
this.
At the very end, this tool will actually commit to and push, commit it into a Git repository
and push it into the GitHub repository.
It follows that down into a serverless web application, which means that I didn't have
had to introduce Git command line to Beatrice neither.
The tool does that for her.
So this is what it looks like.
So it's a React web application.
Here we have the schema validation summary where we see for the fields, so the different
fields we have for which we have errors, the kind of the error we have.
And at the end, we have the error overview which says how many rows that has an issue.
For instance, here in the source column, we have two different invalid values that impact
169 rows.
The idea here is to correct all this group of 169 rows with only one edit.
So once we have all sorts of errors, basically the process of workflow using this tool will
be to go through the error groups one by one.
The web application will actually generate a form with inputs to actually help Beatrice
to decide.
So in this example, we have a value for a partner.
So partner is a trade partner.
So it's geopolitical entity.
Here it's in French.
It's il de célon.
So we use English-based vocabularies to translate the partner.
So we need to decide what is il de célon in our vocabulary in the rest of the data.
And this is where we have search input where actually Beatrice can actually search for
célon which is called in our vocabulary, scélonca, célon, in parenthesis.
And once she should chose that, actually the tool we correct this column and put the data
at the right place to make sure we will translate il de célon to the scélonca célon.
At the end, once she went through all the process, we have summary here explaining all
the corrections she made.
So in the first line, for instance, a year was misspelled.
All that kind of thing.
We change the source name and everything is fixed.
So once all the errors have been corrected through the form, the data form I just showed
you, then she can move on with the last step which is actually to publish this new data
that is now valid because we know it's valid because we can control it with the data package
into the GitHub repository.
And this is how basically the RAC-to-web application will really prepare the data.
So I could go into details into what does that mean later and make it possible for Beatrice
to actually take the right decisions to adapt the raw data into the data package we worked
with.
So I have a little bit more time.
So this is the analysis.
Maybe I can try to demo a little bit the tool live.
So the very important thing is it's a several or less web application.
So here it's on my local host on my laptop, but actually it's hosted on GitHub directly.
So what is the media lab, actually a lot of this work has been done at the media lab,
my previous employer.
So congrats to them too because they contributed to that work too a lot.
So this is the tool.
It's hosted on GitHub.io because it doesn't need any server.
All the logging process with GitHub is done through a personal token, which is a very
specific long key that you have to produce in your GitHub account for once.
Then you use that as a login mechanism.
So this is what it looks like.
Once I am logged in, I can fetch the data from GitHub to make sure I have the last version
of the data before adding new things.
In here I can prepare the little file here, which normally should have some errors.
So the first thing here you see like this green message here on the bottom says that
actually this CSV file is valid structure wise.
And the errors of the columns are good, which is a good first step.
And then this is the all the errors I have in my file.
This is a nice step because you want to review what kind of mess you are going to on top
of where you are before starting the process.
Because if you have too many, maybe you want to do that later or asking for help.
So once you've seen that, you can start.
So this is basically all the things we have to do.
So this is the first one.
I can move to the next error or go back, even though I haven't corrected it yet.
And here I say like, okay, so the value is parallel to, commercial A, I don't know, whatever.
This character is not actually a unit because the unit should be an integer.
Yeah, it's true.
So it's better with a, oops, sorry.
So better with a one.
And I can confirm this fix.
And now we're good.
Unit is one.
Now I move to the next one.
You see here I am in two on nine.
So all the processors are trying to make that as smooth as we can.
So as soon as I fix it, so here I have, it's written in French, it's Milne-Lafsant-Trent-Witz.
But actually we want that to be an integer again.
I don't want the later version of the year.
So Milne-Lafsant-Trent-Witz has a number.
As soon as I confirm the fix, I move to the next page.
So that's, we can try to make that process as seamless as possible.
So here I have a source, so this is a foreign key.
So in the source, in the data table, the source is actually, it's a key that is referring,
which is referring to the source table.
And say like, so here basically foreign key source violation.
So it means that this sort doesn't exist in our system.
So here I have two choice.
Or I was supposed to, okay, normally I should, oh yeah, sorry.
Can you dad?
No.
So normally, okay, so whatever.
So I can search for it and find it, or, and in which case it will, the edit will be only
replacing the key, or I can create a new item.
And here you can see that, here I'm creating a new source because sometimes the source
doesn't exist yet.
So I have to go through all the, you see this form is much, much longer because here I'm
creating a new line into the source table.
I will not do that because it's too long, I will just give me something please.
And that will make it, okay.
And so on and so forth.
Again, we have an issue with the, sorry, this example is a little bit up.
Okay, here it's a Trini-Dad and Tobago.
It's a duopatical line time, I don't know because it's a Trini-Dad and Tobago, not a.
Okay.
Up.
And we are good.
Australia with a lot of E at the end is not correct.
It's Australia.
Yep.
Sorry, it's very long.
Yeah, whatever.
Dollar.
Let's say it's this, it's this crap.
Don't do that, right?
Okay.
Ah.
Okay, so you see, that's important point is like, so we are based on the data package,
in the data package.
So we are using foreign keys, the specification and so on, but actually we had to add specific
forms for our case.
So the application here is not generic.
You can't just put a new data package of yourself with your data and it will not work because
we had actually for UX and UI reasons to make specific cases like that where the forms are
not exactly as the data package described it.
It was too complex to make it very generic, but actually with more work that could be
achieved maybe at some point.
And actually the talk from the evergreen is this afternoon, we'll talk a little bit about
that kind of stuff.
So here we are.
I'll stop the demo here.
Just to finish, why do we do all kinds of stuffs?
Because we want to analyze trade in the long run.
We have lots of trade values as you can see.
A lot of trading entities, very too much.
And then at the end we try to, this is a visual documentation where we depict the kind of
different source we use in the database.
And at the end we try to do something like that where actually here we have the trade
of the world in 1890.
So each node here, circles, are geopolitical entities.
And the links between them are the trade of that year.
So it's total trade.
We could choose import or export here.
I just summed it up.
The important part here is the color here is based on the type of geopolitical entity
we have.
So in this orange or kind of yellow thing, it's what we call the GPH entity.
It's entities that geopolitical entity we know, mainly countries but not always.
In green, so are colonial areas.
So it's not a colony.
It's not a country which is a colony.
It's like French Africa.
It's like, we know it's a colony.
We don't know which one exactly.
Like here, for instance, we have European Russia, which is a city part of.
It's from Russia, but it's the European part of it.
And this is what we find in the archive books.
So we can't really decide what that means exactly.
So we try to analyze this kind of, so we have this, there is this gap between very heterogeneous
data, very difficult to interpret, but still try to do quantification and analyze this
like this networks on top of this very complex and rich dataset.
I think I'm good with what I wanted to share with you today.
We can move to question if you have.
Yes, please.
There was a slide.
The slide was had a title, which was development of a specific web application to integrate
new data.
Yes.
You might not have time to tell me, but please tell me if you have time at some point, what
was the conversation with your historian?
How did this happen?
What did you actually do to plan?
So the question is like how Beatrice and I ended up, decided to do that.
So basically the whole point is very like a collaboration because we worked without that
for a very long time.
And the process was we had to meet in the same room.
I was doing the script, checking the data, editing the data, because editing the data
in a spreadsheet data wise that doesn't mess up your numbers and everything is not easy
actually.
And we were working together on that.
It was necessary and actually very nice to do because we had to exchange.
So she was explaining to me why she was taking this decision or not.
And she was taking this and I was just putting data.
But at some point we ended up with the fact that we had so much more to add that this
process couldn't scale basically.
So we had to find something else to make sure she could do this process on her own.
And I would intervene once the data is in the GitHub repository, checking myself with
quantification and scripts and everything again because you always need to check everything
many times.
And then it makes the whole process much more smoother.
Yes?
Sorry, I don't get it.
So, the question is like, would it be beneficial or possible to actually commit the data before
checking it and put it in GitHub?
So yes and no.
The reason why we don't do that is because, the first one, because I need Bethz to take
the decision of documenting the raw data to make it compatible with all the nice visualization
I showed you.
And she needs to take the decision.
She needs to do it.
So that's why we put this data into the GitHub after she has done this work of data creation.
We could actually host the data as a raw file first and then do that later on that kind
of stuff.
Still, we still need a web interface that lets Bertris, the historian, take the decision.
So no.
Any more?
Yeah?
Just a few things.
I saw on the last slide that the board gave me the idea of organizing.
Yes.
So, this tool I'm using here is actually brand new.
It's a Giphy but on the web.
We are working on this with my company, Westware.
And we are very close to release it.
It's basically the same thing as the Giphy but lighter version and the web version.
It's already there, but you shouldn't go because it's not live yet.
Thank you.