So, good morning everyone.
So my name is Arvé and I'm French.
Sorry, my English is not very perfect.
It's not my mother tongue.
But I work for an NGO called Open Factor, which is a French NGO.
I'm going to talk about it right now.
So self-funded NGO based in France and we created it in 2019.
Our initial goal was to try to federate the francophone-osint open source intelligence
scene as we noticed that the anglophone one was pretty active and brilliant with Bellincat,
for example, people like that.
So we decided to create this NGO and we wanted to assist the newsrooms and activists on ozint
even investigation.
We also wanted to train journalists about what we knew about and also wanted to promote
young journalists based in France in order to help them to get some skills on ozint,
which is a kind of pragmatical way to find a job in France right now.
And as we are an NGO, a self-funded NGO, we also wanted to set up some philanthropic projects
and we trained investigative journalists from Syria, which are relocated in Europe.
We also did some programs in West Africa, all the francophone area.
The NGO today is about 260 members and it's still counting.
And about me, some of the work first, we participated to some of pretty cool investigations such
as Green Blood for a media called Forbidden Stories.
We also published some things and worked on things for BBC, for the French television,
on the Wagner Group, for example.
And we also won a prize with the Swiss TV for a documentary on war crimes in Ukraine.
And recently we published two recommendable reports on Infoross.
I don't know if you've ever heard about that.
It's a Russian company backed by the Russian intelligence and we also work on that and
try to dismantle their network of disinformation inside their border.
And about me, I'm not a coder, obviously, as you probably see.
I'm the co-founder of the NGO.
I'm a former judicial investigator and I'm an open source software enthusiast.
And I've been compiling, well, I used to compile Linux kernels since 1999 or something like
that.
So I'm an open source software enthusiast and evangelist.
And not a techie, I'm a techie, but not a coder.
And I consider myself rather like a Swiss army knife.
I'm very lazy and believe me, if you want to solve a problem, hire a lazy guy or lazy
woman.
And I'm very curious.
What about this information?
This topic is about disinformation.
So disinformation is, as you probably know, false information that is deliberately spread
by an actor in order to deceive people.
There is a fantastic researcher called Ben Nemo.
He tried to resume this concept using the 4D's acronym.
The first one is dismiss.
The other one is distract.
Distort the truth and also dismay.
So that's a very good way to define disinformation.
It's an art for several actors, several threat actors.
You can compare CTI, for example, CTI, sorry, and disinformation.
There are some overlap between these actors.
And there is a very great investigation.
All the links are on the presentation, but there is a really cool investigation called
Doppelganger by the EU Dizinfo Lab.
And I strongly recommend this report about media clones serving the Russian propaganda.
I'm going to switch from time to time in the presentation.
This information is about war, but also health, politics, economy.
It covers mostly every topic, actually.
And of course, internet and the web are probably the greatest echo chamber that they use.
In France, we have such a problem.
And we have a problem with QAnon.
And there is a website called Cactus in France.
It's called Cactus.
It's a judgment for QAQ2 for news and Cactus the tree.
So QAnon is an American political conspiracy, sorry, and political movement.
I'm pretty sure you heard about it.
And it's mostly far right based.
And it appeared on the net in 2017.
This website, this French website is, of course, Conspiracist.
It's all about anti-vaxx.
And it's also very anti-Semitic.
So it's a problem.
It's present on several platforms, such as, of course, the web, but also Telegram, Twitter,
Gabor, GAB, et cetera, all the network.
It has some kind of translated content.
So as soon as you arrive on a web page, it depends on the language, but you can get the
news automatically in French or in English.
This is via Tor, the Tor browser.
So it's basically in English.
But you can also save it in French, for example.
And most of the readers are French or Francophone.
It publishes five or seven articles a day, mostly crap.
It's always crap.
It has more than two million visitors per month.
So it's not nothing.
It's a lot of people.
I have a personal blog and I have an open factor blog.
And we don't have two million visitors a month.
I can assure you.
And since it was open, it revendicates more than 80 million visitors.
So yeah, it's kind of big things.
It's one of the most productive Q&A websites.
So in order to make the investigation, we needed a methodology on disinformation.
And there is a very good framework called the ABCDE, very easy to remember.
It's a good start.
So A stands for actor.
So who is doing the disinformation campaign?
The behavior, how, the content, what about the content, of course.
The degree, it means the scale of the disinformation campaign.
And the last one, he, the he was added later.
But he means the effect that is looking by the actor.
So if we based our research at open factor for cactus, we would say something like, what
is cactus?
What's its audience?
Its environment, ecosystem, its influence, its motivation above all.
And last but not least, if we can identify who is behind cactus, it's really cool for
us as journalists.
So we decided to approach this by trying to qualify the environment.
And in order to do that, we used three different tools that I mentioned as a sweet combo.
The first one is HIVE, and it's a tool that was made, most of these tools were made by
the Media Lab Sciences Po.
And HIVE is one of the greatest one.
It's a tool that you can download on your computer.
And it mostly scrapes the web starting from a URL.
And you can build a web corpus of all the websites that are connected to this website
by the links inside the article.
So it was very cool to use with cactus because the most important activity of cactus is
writing articles, as I mentioned, but inside they put links to other articles, sometimes
legit, sometimes links that leads you to other conspiracist websites.
So kind of a long process because right now at the moment of the investigation, cactus
had about 8,000 something articles on the website.
So it took me a long time to scrape everything.
And I had to go to the level two in order to scrape the link from the website that were
cited by Kirk too, if I'm clear about it.
So I had to go at a level of two.
It works pretty well with a caveat.
There are some limitations with Hive, especially one that really bothers us.
It's Cloudflare, sorry for the typo, because as soon as you arrive on a Cloudflare website
and a lot of websites are protected by Cloudflare, you cannot scrape it.
You cannot scrape them with Hive.
But it works pretty well.
Actually, not on my computer.
I tried at the hotel yesterday night and it doesn't work, but believe me, it works.
So I scraped the links.
I'm going to show you the result after that.
The first tool that I combined with Hive was, of course, Jefy.
I've been an enthusiast of Jefy since probably 2011 or something like that.
And it's a very interesting tool to explore and analyze graphs.
And especially if you try to use the modularity algorithm to determine sub-communities.
And it's a brilliant tool that I'm sure you already know about.
And the last one was important for us as journalists.
We tried to illustrate our articles with images and graphs, et cetera.
And it's very difficult to render graphs on websites.
So this tool is brand new and one of its authors is in this room, actually, and I'm super happy
to know that.
And it's Retina.
And Retina offers you the opportunity to import a graph inside your website and to dive into
it and to analyze it or at least to help the people try to understand it.
And that's really cool.
So that's what we got.
And I'm going to show you the rendering of the article.
So this is Hive.
And based on the three tools, what I tried to do is to illustrate the environment of
the website.
So the first one at the top level is Cactus.
And all these websites were at least once mentioned in the articles.
And then all the websites also cite the other one.
And here, for example, you can reach the American disinformation network.
You've got the Francophone one here and the Canadian one here.
So it's very interesting to see where Cactus is in the middle of everything.
So I try to illustrate the graph like this.
So it gives you with this three tools a very good idea of the environment of the website.
What you can see inside also are some legitimate websites such as MediaPart, for example, or
YouTube, et cetera, et cetera.
And that's one of their techniques in order to drain some, to lead some activity on the
website, they link regular website and also conspiracies website.
It's in order to increase their SEO, their ranking on Google, for example.
So it's very important to put legitimate and disinformation website.
So that was the first part of the investigation purely made with open source software.
The second one was the influence.
And it's rather usual to do that.
So we needed a good scraper for Twitter.
Our idea was to have an idea on how the disinformation could escape from their traditional networks
such as Gabe or Paner, for example, and to escape from this platform to go to mainstream
platforms.
So Twitter is a really good, used to be a very good platform to analyze.
I don't know what's going on.
I don't know what it's going to be within a few days, but essence scrape is a cool tool
to do that.
I don't know if you heard about it.
It's a scraper for Twitter.
So what we did basically was to extract all the tweets from its creation that had a link
referring to cactus.fr, which was the website.
And we wanted to know about its activity.
So you just basically open a terminal and you copy paste this.
I'm not going to export to it first, but what you receive, I hope my connection is okay.
Yes.
So you get all the tweets.
You can grab a cafe.
You don't have to scroll.
And when you come back, you get all the tweets.
So there are approximately 124,000 tweets that talk about it.
Once again, it's not nothing.
And you can export that as a JSON file.
Here.
So it's going to work.
Blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
I'm going to break it right now.
Once you have these tweets, you have to scrape them and you have to wrangle your data.
And I used another tool called OpenRefine.
You probably know about OpenRefine.
It's a powerful tool to cleanse.
And there is a wow effect for journalists, especially with this tool that I like.
It's how it deals with JSON file.
So this is going to be maybe possible.
So you open the text like this and it knows how to render JSON file in CSV, which is a
format that we all like when we do data journalism.
So you can now analyze all the data that you have.
So that's why I love OpenRefine and also when you want to do some clustering.
And the last one was, of course, R Anti-Diverse.
I'm not going to dive into R Anti-Diverse.
You have had several presentations on that.
But these tools are really easy because R is an easy language for statistics, easy syntax,
very readable when you don't know how to code.
And this is really important for newsroom, for example.
Most of the time, few journalists know how to code.
So having a code that is readable is important.
You get a quick overview.
So we've got 10 minutes, yes.
Thank you.
It's very convenient for prototyping and important also for reproducibility.
But if you want, you can use Python.
I don't want to enter the war between R and Python.
The motivation.
The motivation, we use Firefox and we dive into the source code.
And this one was pretty easy because Cura2 has a Google ad program inside.
So every click that you made on this web page gives you some money.
So this is the main motivation apart from the ideology.
And about the identity, all the tools that we got from GitHub, Hollehey, Gint, and Sherlock.
These are command line tools that are packaged right now by a French company called APOs.
But you can use them on your terminal and it will help you to dive into the nicknames
and the mail combination on websites.
We also use some leaks, but we found out who was Patrick behind this website.
So let's wrap this up.
First of all, I want to talk about the myth of a single tool in Hoseint.
Most of the time when I say to people, well, I'm a journalist and I work on Hoseint, they
say, oh, which tool do you use?
There are several tools.
There is no single tool in Hoseint and you've got to mix everything.
About this investigation, this guy Patrick is a retired IT technician in a lost town
in the middle of France.
He's a completist, but as we saw, he's in the middle of a bubble of completist influence.
He earns approximately $4,000 a month just by writing crap.
So it's very important for us and for the audience to know him and to help him on the
website.
Patrick, we know who you are.
That's my thing.
Why do we use OpenSoup software?
Because they are powerful, adaptable.
They respect your privacy and reproducibility.
I don't ever know how to pronounce this word.
Most of the time, these tools are free, which is really important and I insist on that.
For journalists, we don't have money.
When you go to Africa and train NGOs, for example, or journalists, it's very complicated
to buy software for them.
They don't even have regular machines.
Having OpenSoup software is really important.
Thank you, you all.
If you code for OpenSoup software, it's really important for civil society.
Thank you.
The last one, collaboration.
I didn't talk about collaboration.
You're in the room today and it's important for us to mention that collaboration on how
our investigation is the key, first of all by software, but also in order to share information
and to share indicators of confirmation, for example.
So data capitalization is important.
There is this project called OpenCTI that I hope we will try to impose in Europe as a
tool.
It's an open source tool and we'll try to impose it as a standard with the DISARM matrix.
It's called DISARM.
All the links are in the presentation in order to get some cooperation.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Let's spare a thought for Patrick and on with the questions.
Yes.
You mentioned you used some leaks.
Is that a leaks that you have friends that gave you information or is it that you found
things that had been put inadvertently in the public sphere?
Second one, which we try to do when we do some...
We try to do some leaks and the question was, is this information that some friends give
me or information that is publicly available on the internet?
That was the question.
So the answer is as OpenFactory is an NGO, we don't have friends.
So we use public leaks.
We dive on Telegram, the Darknet, et cetera, and we use basically keywords, passwords and
emails in order to make connection between nicknames and try to identify people like
this.
That's what we do.
We also have a sort of...
I'm a former investigative journalist, an investigator, so what I try to do is sort of judicial methodology.
So we try to open everything in our investigation and we mention all the information that we
get.
So if we link from somewhere on the internet, we will explain where we got the leak every
time.
Transparency is important.
Another question here?
I have a question.
Are you Jewish?
No, I'm not.
Okay.
The question was, I'm a Jewish.
No, I'm not.
I'm not Jewish.
Other question?
Yes.
I mean, you mentioned like one particular question.
That you identified, but I mean, I guess there are more people.
What is the scope of the success of this program?
The question is that we identify one person behind this website and there are probably
more people and more websites like this.
So we are just a bunch of cool people working behind their computer.
So we try to do our best, but at least we have one website which is really influenced.
So we start by the most productive website that we want to investigate, but of course
there are millions, not millions, but thousands and thousands of people doing these kind of
things.
We do what we can and we're trying to inspire other journalists in order to make their own
investigation and to help these kind of people.
Sorry.
How big is the environment of NGO working on this kind of subject?
Are you the only one?
Are you a lot of NGOs and friends working on this information?
The question is, are we a lot of people, for example, in France working on this information?
There are some newspaper and newsroom that start to investigate on these kind of topics.
It's not very popular, not very famous, but I think that the last three or four years,
this information has become a major issue, especially in Europe.
And we see plenty of NGOs such as EU, this info lab, for example.
They are friends of ours and we really like them and we try to collaborate with them.
So yeah, I hope that we'll get more and more people in order to work on that.
Other question?
How can you stop automatic disinformation?
So I'm thinking about chat GPT and bots and stuff like that.
So can you distinguish whether it's being auto-generated or human-generated?
So the question is that, how can we stop automatic disinformation made, for example, by chat GPT?
Chat GPT is going to be a very big issue for influence, which is something pretty obvious.
When I'm saying that, I'm saying obvious thing.
But yeah, it's going to be a problem because websites, especially search engines, they
use, as I mentioned, SEO technique in order to do the ranking of the website.
And one of the biggest issues, for example, for Google will be to figure out if a content
not only is duplicated, which was pretty easy to do, but now automatically connected.
So I don't have any solution for the moment.
We haven't faced this problem so far.
Chat GPT is quite recent, and its use is not widespread right now, but it's going to change
within the next six months.
And I'm sure about that.
As an answer to this gentleman's question, the OpenAIG recently launched a site where
you can give an effect.
It will give you a confidence level if it's human-generated or computer-generated.
Yeah.
Could you please give a red-noth visualization again?
Sorry, sorry.
The height of the page?
Yep.
Sorry.
This one.
Yeah, I was curious about the labeling you did of the notes.
Could you explain more about the color classification?
The label?
Yes.
So the label is basically the title of the website?
Yeah, sorry, the coloring.
Ah, the coloring.
We used the betweenness centrality on this graph.
Okay.
So it's usually what I do on this kind of website in order to figure out the importance
of a node as a distributor of the connections between other sub-communities.
So yeah.
Because American clusters, I'm just curious about your clustering.
Ah, okay.
The distribution, you mean, for example, all the links, it's basically the standard,
Gephi...
No?
No, no, no.
The specialization?
What?
For SATLAS too.
For SATLAS.
So it's this one?
Yeah, this one.
So it's for SATLAS.
So every link that is close to the other one will be packed as itself and a group, a group
cluster that is not very linked to another one will be far away from the other one.
There is a bias in the representation because I wanted Q-A
to be clear.
First of all, when you work on this information, so the question is how can we make the distinction
between misinformation and disinformation?
So basically when you start an investigation, this is the first question that you ask yourself.
Is it going to be disinformation or misinformation?
Misinformation is like something that could be true, but no, that is false, but the person
thinks it's true.
Okay?
But when you see the content of the website, you know that he's talking always on the same
topics, always distributing the same kind of information.
So you know that he does this deliberately.
The motivation is important and that's why in this case it was important to identify
the Google Ads tag because you know for sure that its motivation is probably ideology,
probably, if you see his Facebook wall, for example, but there is the money and the ads
and the Google and the platform are fueling the disinformation with the ad system.
So this is really important to identify.
Okay, last question over there.
I didn't get the question, sorry.
So is there a strategy from, the question is that is there a strategy to tackle disinformation
from authoritarian states?
I think so.
The problem is that everybody, everyone has its own strategy.
So there are millions of strategy and this is the big issue according to me.
So Europe, for example, is trying to organize this by different programs.
EU Dizinfo Lab, like is the leader in trying to federate the Dizinfo structure and activist
in order to make wider and bigger investigation like this.
So I think yes, there is a strategy.
The problem is that for the moment there are multiple strategy, but it's going to change.
Thank you.