Hello, thank you very much for having us here.
I'm Daniel Aguido, together with my colleague, Elizabeth Garrard.
We are coming from the University of Luxembourg, from the Center of Contemporary Digital History,
where we're running this new journal, this new idea of journal, together with a well-known publisher
in the Open Access publication, which is the Groiter.
The idea is the journal of digitalhistory.org, and then the idea is how to bring reproducible
papers in the humanities and in digital history in our specific case.
And then that's why we joined forces with them, so it's a joint venture with them directly,
so the team is relatively small compared to other projects, and then we have two perspectives
that we decided to put together.
On our side, we understand that academic publishing is a bit too traditional, especially in history.
And then our researchers, they currently work on Jupyter Notebook to run their own experiment
and so on, so the idea was, can we pass from experiment on Jupyter Notebook to actual publication,
also in our domain?
And on the other side, they wanted to test out this hypothesis, because they really want
to engage with new publication practices, and this joint venture would just be a good
match.
And well, reproducible papers in digital history means a lot of things, because first of all,
we have now massive digitization process of primary sources and secondary literature and
also new digital-born material, like the Twitter archive that we've been seeing before.
On one side, the detail of the code, Cruz also sharing the dataset is one thing, but
the other thing is really how this data has been created.
So what were the conditions of the production of this data?
So this is very important for us as historians, not for me, for my colleague, and then interpretation.
So how the dataset has been built, which were the limits, all this questions need to be
addressed in a different way.
And then at the same time, we have, of course, new standards, not only digital history, but
also the famous FAIR principle, so findable, accessible, interoperable, and reusable data.
And we need to meet this criteria also with our journal.
And this idea of Moolen is the one of a Braden narrative.
So he advocates for bringing together two things.
One is the narrative of the argumentation of our publication.
The other one is the interpretation of data and say that they can be done in a narrative
way.
This is where we put these so-called multi-layers together.
So this one is like every article published in our journal has a fingerprint sort of identity
where this level, like the narrative, the hermeneutic level, and the data layer are
together.
So this is the representation of one Jupyter notebook, which is normally linear cell by
cell.
We just distorted, we put it in a circle, and here you can test it out.
So this was also a tool, it is also a tool for our authors, which we own them a lot because
they are our primary tester.
It is still an experimental journal.
And there you could tweak with data, you can change the content, and you see how the fingerprint
is changing.
This was just an experiment at the beginning, but then it really becomes integrated into
the main interface of the journal.
And we saw that indeed they were very different.
Okay, yes, I run.
They were very different, and we can see also the code style of every Jupyter notebook,
how they also decided to narrate the arguments.
So I will go quickly, sorry.
And then this is like the basic layer, so the narrative layer that looks like an MV
viewer with steroids in the sense that we have figures, we have tables, we have bibliography.
With Zotero and Site2C.
And then above all, it's a very thin layer on top of the Jupyter notebook because we
use the usual output of the notebook.
So this is very like an augmented MV viewer.
And then we have, as it is a braided narrative, we decided to have this metaphor of this level
one on top of the other.
So this is a sort of animation, so on the left you see the full hermeneutic layer,
and on the other side you can see how it slides through the, like behind the narrative layer.
And the data layer is for the moment the part on top, right top, which we use MyBinder,
fantastic service to publish online your notebooks.
And we wanted this article not only to be a show off of the dataset, but also a small
history lab so that people could just click on a button and get to the data and understand
how the data will be composed.
The good thing is that we decided to keep this, MyBinder, as this source of truth.
So the article that you see published is exactly the same copy, with just a different way of
interacting with this different layer.
So this is how it looks like on MyBinder, so it's a classical Jupyter notebook.
And for every notebook we have a GitHub repo, where we store all the requirements and all
the images in the dataset.
We have to put together the fair metadata, but still, so it's under construction.
Then what does it mean having Jupyter notebooks for publishing?
We see that in the literature there are a lot of critics, shouldn't use Jupyter notebooks
because it's too complex, it's impossible to replicate and so on and so forth.
But then for us, it was really the simplest solution.
So at the same time, to publish with Jupyter, we had to make our pipeline a bit more complex
as usual, so we have a first review directly on the abstract, where we start communicating
with the authors, understanding their needs, creating a writing environment for them that
can be replicated with Docker containers for Python and Air.
And then the first technical review, she's in charge of the first technical review, which
is the most complicated one, because there's a lot of checks.
We saw some projects already, we needed to have checks.
And then we have a lot of other open source software that enters this pipeline, like for
the preview of the notebook, we took it up, and the viewer, we have my binder, and this
is just for the first technical review, because then the article is being sent to the reviewer
for the double banana review.
So before even reviewing, we had to do this huge job because they have to review also
the data and the pertinence of the dataset.
And then finally, there is one important thing, so it's English editing, so how to edit something
that which is already being run, so without running itself.
So this could be a tool for translators, tool for correctors, that they're not into the
Jupyter world, so how to do that?
We have Jupyter text, we're still testing some plugin to see if this could work without
touching the final output.
And then the final technical review, so after all this has been shipped, we have a DOI,
so the article is now published, needs to be indexing, and there is the problem of long-term
archiving, which is a big problem for many reasons.
First of all, libraries that get deprecated, also API that disappeared, so how to really
reproduce this in the future.
And then finally, the dataset needs to be included into, we have dataverse, but we are
looking for Zenodo in order to match the fair metadata.
And time is up, I have a question for you, of course.
Thank you very much, first of all.
And then if you want to contact us, just collaborate or work together on Jupyter publication, jdhadmin
at uni.lu.
And then the question are, how can we actually collaborate on something which is a notebook
that requires quite a threshold of expertise, not only for the researcher, but for the people
that are around, and how to maintain all this and how to make this history lab living for
more than one year.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Yeah, well, I repeat the question, so he asked me if the double blind review, how can we
keep it actually an actual double blind.
So she anonymized the data on GitHub.
So we have specific repository that have been created after the communication with the authors,
where we only have the code without the names, but then you still have the bibliography,
so it's easy to, it's a very small word, one of the digital history.
But still, this is the way to maintain double blind.
And then we're going to send the review where both the MyBinder and the version of the article
on our website with a hidden URL.
So this is the only thing that we can do.
For sure, the double blind, we have the problems that we cannot really use the peer request
directly on the GitHub repository.
In fact, there is some replication between the GitHub repository.
After with the peer review, there is some recursivity that come back to technical review
because there is a revision.
There is this question about how we synchronize the notebook together.
There is some authors that they have good enough with GitHub.
But to review a notebook with the output with the metadata to track what has been changed.
This, it was the question that you have, we are testing with ReviewNB, or also to maybe
use some markdown or just Python script to produce several output in order to not sometimes
touch about these metadata that they are inside the notebook.
And there was another question, but I don't know if we have time.
Yes?
Yes.
Please.
I'm sorry, auto assess?
Yeah, that's the very big, big, big question.
So the idea behind the narrative is then you tell the story around the data on one side,
and on the other side, you keep the data like with the Zenodo metadata coherent, or probably
with what Paul showed us before with Ricardo, so having like an external check on the metadata
and on the dataset itself.
At the same time, the initial, the first technical review is the one where we assess actually
the data.
So if the data sets are complete, coherent, we don't judge them because then we know that
there are conditions of production that needs to be, we try to make this as more explicit
as possible.
Yes, exactly.
And this, like that's why the long term maintenance, so now we only have nine articles, but we
have 28 in the pipeline in the coming year.
So it's really now it's getting up speed, and we have more and more interaction with
all those, which makes things more complicated.
Thank you.
Okay.