Hi everyone.
Well, I'm very impressed to have such a large audience for such a small tool.
But, well, I'm Beatrice.
I work at the French Media Lab.
And today I'm going to present PIMI, which is a tool to study image propagation.
The Media Lab is a lab where social scientists try to, among other things, study the traces
that people leave online.
And from now they are quite well equipped with tools to study text.
But when they ask me, okay, how can I study image propagation?
And I'm still struggling to give them answers.
So what does it mean to study mean propagation?
It means, okay, being able to recognize that some parts of an image are copied or partially
copied.
So what this tool does, it's very simple.
It's able to create clusters of images and group together images that are total or partial
copies of each other.
It's able to deal with image transformation, so if the image is cropped or zoomed.
And it's able to adapt to copper's characteristics.
So it will try to make the best of your data sets, depending on the number of images you
have or the type of images you have.
What PIMI is not able to do is to cluster semantically similar images.
So it's not the tool that you are going to use if you want to create clusters of cats
and clusters of dogs or, I don't know, find images of violence versus images of peace.
And it's not able to do some face recognition.
So again, you will not be able to make some clusters of pictures of Elizabeth II versus
clusters of images of Emmanuel Macron.
What you could imagine doing, and we could imagine also work together if you are a researcher
working on those subjects, is to study the propagation of MIMA on social networks, as
I was saying.
But also you could study the usage of press agency photos in a press corpus or stock photos
as well.
You could also study the dissemination of fake news based on image montage.
Or you could study the editorial choices between different media, depending on whether they
use the same images or not.
So let me do a quick demo of how it looks for now.
It's not on the screen.
OK, let's forget about that.
OK, I'm very sorry.
I'll try to make it work.
OK, well, still not showing totally all clusters.
So we create clusters of images.
So this is a data set that is created by the French INRIA.
And that is presenting some degradation on images.
So they take an original picture and they apply some filters or they crop the images
to see if they are able to put the images together.
So we can see that we have pretty correct results on that data set.
And this is our results on some images that we collected ourselves on Twitter using Ellen
Musk as a query.
And so we try to cluster those images.
So as you can see, we have images of Ellen Musk.
We are able to group together some images that are crops of others.
So this is probably the source image of the montage that has been done here.
But we can also see that we have some problems with the tool.
For example, here we have a cluster with two images that have been assembled together and
we create a cluster of actually two images.
But well, that's the state of the tool for now.
And now I'll try to come back to my slides.
OK.
So how does it work?
For people who work in computer vision, I'm going for a bit to say some things that are
quite basic, but I try to make it clear for people who do not do computer vision.
So it is not based on colors at all.
It's used like the grayscale of images.
And it tries to detect points of interest on a picture.
And then it uses these local key points as vectors.
And then those vectors are indexed in a database that is able to perform some very quick similarity
approach.
you
of the tool as I say there is that problem of parts of images that create
clusters that are bigger than they should be so our plan is to be able to
detect images that are actually those links between two clusters so to be able
that's to detect that this image is actually containing two images and to be
able to to deal with part of images and also what we would like to do is to show
images in their context to be able to show the tweets that that contains those
images or Instagram posts etc or at least to show additional metadata for
the users and also we would like to show you the graph of image similarities so
that the clusters that are resulting from that graph are not like not
interpretable and to improve our tool we need your use cases because for now like
we have those two three databases but but we would be very glad to like do some
partnerships with other researchers to improve the tool thank you very much for
your attention
he she wanted to look at the slides we have the references to all the images
used and to the papers of the algorithms used by teeny I'm open for questions
we had a bit of trouble with the sound stream but it's back online so yeah you
should repeat the question okay I'll do
yes
well trying to find similarities in oh sorry I have to repeat the question so
the question was if I understand well well how to reproduce that that use case
not on images but on other types of documents that would be I guess some
features 3d counterparts and I'd say well as long as you can you like represent
your data in the shape of vectors then you ready to use face to do like do some
some search from for nearest neighbor in your database and then you can go for
the whole pipeline create some graphs find communities in graph and go for it
but I'm not sure PME is your tool but but well the the architecture of PME
could be of course a model
is there any project current or you're going that media labs has used them for
or is it still largely in development it is largely in the development sorry I
repeat the question so are there some projects at the media lab that are
currently using PME and the response is no yes
sorry can you
well yes have you considered other ways of presenting picture similarity or
using picture similarity all the types of image similarity if you understand
well well I'd say that that that was what I was saying in my second slide
there are other types of image similarity for example semantic or
similarity and well maybe in a few months if we have like a robust
architecture we could maybe include some other types of vectorization of images
but for now well they are already tools that do that like there is something
called clip server that that helps you like find similar images from clip
vectors that are like semantical vectors so you you you could use that tool it's
great yes yes
so the question is is the tool really able to distinguish the thing that is of
interest to us the fact that we are talking about a dog so the tool is only
able to find partial copies in an image so the tool would probably be able to
say that all those images contain the same parts of face of a dog so it would
probably be able to group all those images together the problem is that if
there are other images in the database that contain the rest of the images then
they would probably also be grouped in the same cluster so that's why what we
are currently doing about parts of images who let us improve the cluster
so that it's purified from the rest of the images and we could have a cluster
of the face of that specific dog and then a cluster of that taco in the second
cluster yes well for now we have the best result with excuse me what kind of
cluster ization do you use on the graph for now we have our best results using
pure connected components so actually the specification we do on the graph to
reduce the number of links between images is enough to have separated
connected components in the graph and so we take each connected component and
it's our cluster what we would like to do is to try to like mix with some
wrong from detection but actually for now it's not the thing that works best
yes
I'm not sure I understand the question can you try to rephrase it okay what
what things are you looking at to improve the model well there are many
things where we we are looking at for now mainly we we look at techniques to
to do a better graph specification in order to find more coherent clusters we
are not so much working on the on the like local descriptors parts of the
tool for now yes have you considered and used the direct
clique to to the Twitter images or social media images online did I repeat
everything well yes we would like people to be able to to see images in their
context because actually they they won't understand what's happening if they just
have images they need to see okay why was this image published who answered
etc so this would probably mean that we need to to add at least the links to to
the pulse and or maybe some some kind of visualization of it
you