Okay. Hi, everyone. It's a big pleasure to be here. My name is Armin Purnaki, and I'm
a PhD candidate in applied mathematics, and I work on building tools for discourse analysis.
And we build tools for discourse analysis based on methods from graph theory, network
science and natural language processing. And today I want to present a tool called the
Twitter Explorer that is already a bit older, but that was built in the institute in the
Max Planck Institute for Mathematics and the Sciences in my previous group. And the idea
was to build a tool that allows researchers who don't necessarily have programming skills
to collect Twitter data, visualize them using graphs, and explore the data and maybe generate
hypotheses in their pipelines. So this kind of tool building and this research happens
in the field called computational social science. So when I was preparing my slides two days
ago, I thought it would be good to maybe give a little overview of computational social
science, then say why we built the Twitter Explorer and where we saw somehow the need
for a new tool. Of course, introduce the features of the tool because it's kind of a talk on
programming, the architecture, and maybe give some insights on the usage. But when I was
sitting down to make the slides two days ago, I was confronted with this. And of course,
since the tool is essentially an entry point into the free API, there's also a part of
it that uses the research API, which of course led us directly to this question, what happens
to the research API? It's also not entirely clear, right? So I want to maybe instead of
giving this talk the way I was planning to do it, I will do it, but maybe I wanted to
ask a few questions first that we might then discuss maybe in the discussion also. And
I think there is even something planned later, right? So some kind of panel discussion. So
I'm just going to throw some questions out there that I think are really pressing now,
especially in the research field. How serious is this? By this, I don't mean the implications
of it because I know a few people whose thesis is now in jeopardy because they can't collect
data in a way. But how serious is it in the sense? Will it actually happen? Or is it some
scare tactic? So I think this is something that is hard to predict. And then these are
questions also I think that we can discuss here is how, or is there a way for us as users
and not necessarily only as researchers to claim our data or our digital traces that
we use and that we leave on these platforms? And how can things like the Digital Services
Act play a role in this? And the last question is very broad, but how do we move on in the
sense of how can we see this as some kind of wake up call maybe? And how can we use
this new development to maybe on one hand move to different platforms, but on the other
hand also to think about how we do computational social science in the future? So with these
questions that we're going to discuss later, I'm still going to give my original talk.
So in computational social science, a typical pipeline for a project is you have a research
question, then you collect data related to it. And in this case, it may be data from
online social platforms. And then you analyze it and ideally you generated some more insights
on the research question you had in the beginning. And sometimes the exploration and the analysis
of the data can help you maybe refine also the questions you had in the beginning. So
it's some kind of loop that you can see in this way. And the tool that I'm going to present
the Twitter Explorer is precisely made for this second part, for both facilitating the
collection and also the exploration of such data. And this pipeline is that we start with
text. So in our case, it's tweets that are annotated with some kind of metadata. We have
on Twitter different types of interactions. So you can mention someone, you can reply
to someone or retweet. And we choose one type of metadata and cast it into an interaction
network. And then we want to find the most significant, for instance, clusters or the
significant correlations in this data by using 2D spatializations. And typically, these are
done using forced layouts. But today, for instance, in the graph room, there were also
some talks about new methods of node embedding. And so I think this is also something that
we can discuss maybe in the questions section. But one reason why I think forced layouts
are good is that especially if you use them in a context where you work with social science
researchers who don't necessarily have a lot of knowledge about the latest machine learning
algorithms, they are quite straightforward to explain in the sense that you have a spring
system and nodes that are strongly connected tend to attract each other. And especially
if you look at interaction networks on Twitter, since retweeting can be considered endorsement,
clusters in such 2D spatializations can then correspond to something like opinion clusters.
And there's a lot of research being done in that way. But one question that we always
had when we look at these networks is how do we actually go back to the data that generated
them? And this is something that we tried to tackle with building these tools. So why
we built it is firstly to provide an interface for researchers without programming skills
also to collect and visualize the data, because we were working a lot with social scientists
that did not have these programming skills, but had a lot of hypotheses about the data
that they could not test. Then, of course, to facilitate the exploration of controversial
issues on social media. And this is the point that I was making before, is add some layer
of interpretability to these 2D spatializations by providing an access from within the interface
to the actual data that created these node positions. And finally, we see it in the context
of a larger scientific scope of using the network paradigm as something like a sampling
mechanism for the data. Because if you're confronted with a large number of tweets,
for instance, of course, everyone knows that you can't read all of them manually. So you
need some kind of way to get to the tweets that are relevant for you to read. And this
is what we use the network for, essentially. So we can look, when we look at retweet networks,
immediately identify, for instance, the most influential actors in the debate, and then
read precisely those tweets that they made to maybe influence other actors. And we call
this guided close reading, because if you do only close reading, then you have to read
all the text. If you have distant reading, you kind of look only at the network on a
structural level, and this is something in between. So what can the tool do? It collects
tweets. I mean, I think we have like one week left for the V2 and the V1. So far, the V2
academic is safe, but we don't know that. So you can search for it from the past seven
days using the API. In the second part, in the visualizer, you can do, display just a
simple time series of the tweets to see maybe if there's some kind of special activity during
one day. You can build these interaction networks, build co-hashtag networks. So we divide it
into some kind of two types of networks, which we call semantic networks and interaction
networks. And then you can compute the typical measures people compute on networks, and especially
compute clusters like using modularity-based algorithms. And all this happens in some kind
of interactive interface using JavaScript and D3.js. And this is essentially the part
where it gets interesting, because so far, all the other things you can do it with a
lot of other tools, especially like Gefi. I think you can even collect tweets with some
plugins. So I think all of this is not new, and this is kind of where it gets interesting.
And I think this is time for a quick demo. I don't know how much. Okay, I have plenty
of time. I think I talked too fast. Okay, so I've prepared some Python environments
that already have the Twitter Explorer installed, but usually you would do it like this. And
then all you need to do to fire up this interactive interface is type Twitter Explorer collector.
This will open a browser window from which you can choose your API access, choose the
path to which the tweets will be downloaded, and insert your search query, maybe adding
some advanced settings and saving options. So I don't know. This is a question to the
audience now, what we should search for. This is easy. And you're looking into the future.
I already have this network prepared for the last slide. Sorry. Can you look at the reaction
to the Twitter API? We could, but what would we look for then? Is there maybe a hashtag
like API shutdown? Maybe we need to go to Twitter itself. API something like this. Ideally,
we would find some kind of hashtag. Okay, let's just use maybe this as a search query.
Okay. Now it's collecting in the background. Then we can open another browser window here.
Fire up the visualizer. Now we see that while this is still collecting, we can already access
this. There were only 400 tweets, so there seems to be. So we can look at a time series
of tweets, and then we can choose different types of networks to create. We can filter
them by language if we want. And this is the language that the Twitter API returns. So
there's no language detection going on here. We can do some network reduction methods like
taking only the largest connected component of the graph. Then we have this option here
to remove the metadata of nodes that are not what we call public figures. So if you want
to publish some explorable networks, it is advisable to do so. There is not, as far as
I know, not a very distinctive or clear rule after which point one is considered such a
public figure, but within our consortium, we decided that it's 5,000 followers. This
is also something we could discuss. But since Twitter is public by default, in a way, anything
you post is somehow potentially to be used and displayed somewhere. Then you can export
the graph to all sorts of formats. Then you can aggregate nodes. This means that, for
instance, removing them based on how many retweets they have or how many retweets they
did themselves, and remove, for instance, nodes that only retweeted one person. So is
there a chalk? Maybe somewhere? If you have a graph, and then there are some nodes that
only retweet this person. I don't know if everyone can see that, but they tend to clutter
the force-directed algorithm. Structurally, they do not necessarily add anything to the
network. So if you have very, very large graphs, it makes sense to remove these and somehow
englope them into this super node. Then you can do traditional community detection. Then
it will be saved as an HTML that you can then open. So we see here that this is, again,
in a retweet network, every node is a user, and the link is drawn from A to B if A retweets
B. Now we can look at this user, T Chambers, and look at the actual tweets that were made
for them to end up at this part of the visualization. Okay. So the data we collect is kind of sparse,
so this network doesn't look that interesting, but I have prepared some fallback options.
So what we did in a case study a few months ago was to look at the repercussion of some
discussions in the US about red flag laws. And red flag laws are specific kinds of laws
for gun control that allow state level judges to confiscate temporarily guns from people
that are deemed to be a threat to themselves or to the public. And these laws created very
big repercussions, especially on social media and especially in the conservative camps.
And this is one typical example where people then can analyze on Twitter if there's something
like echo chambers or if people then maybe retweet each other only from the similar camps,
and then people draw very quick conclusions very fast. And what we want to do with this
tool is to show that maybe things are not that simple as they seem. So I have prepared
these networks, but I think I will make it a bit smaller. So this is now a bit bigger
than what we had before. We have roughly 25,000 nodes and 90,000 links. And this is already
one limitation of the tool that I think I would also like to discuss in the end is that
you can't display mentally huge graphs. So 100,000 links approximately is kind of the
limit. And I think this is also where integrating it with other tools such as Sigma or Gayfri
might actually make a lot of sense. And so now I can color the nodes by the Luvan community.
We can turn off the light also. And now we can wonder what are these two communities.
And right now the node size is proportional to the indegree, meaning how often a given
node was retweeted. But if we want to, so these may then be considered as something
like the opinion leaders of the given camps. And so if we go here, we see for instance
on this side Donald Trump Jr. And we can then look exactly at the tweets that led the visualization
to put him where he was. So okay, we don't need to go into the details of what he said,
but you see the point. We can also change the node size to the number of followers.
And then we get an immediate view at who the main actors are that in general are also influential
on Twitter. So we have the New York Times here. And Wall Street Journal. So we can see
that we have something like of a more liberal versus a more conservative camp. But if we
look only at the retweet behavior, we might think that okay, these are separated echo
chambers and people do not talk to each other. But what is interesting is if we look at other
types of networks in these examples. So we can look at the replies. I think I will make
it a bit smaller. And all of the sudden we don't see this very strong segregated clustering
anymore that we saw here. Maybe it's easier if I put it in. But we see something more
of a hairball layout. And when we look at the nodes, we see that indeed the path of
going for instance from Donald Trump to Hillary Clinton or New York Times of those people
that were very far apart of the network is maybe not that long in the reply network.
These opposing camps actually maybe do talk to each other. And it might be more interesting
to see how they talk to each other and what they say. And this is something that you can
do when you use this interface and look at the tweets and that actually replies. So it
allows you to then actually go to the parts of the platform that generate this data and
that then generate these networks. And finally as a small example of the semantic networks,
you can look at the hashtags that I used. Again, I'll make it smaller. And you see that
for instance there is one kind of hateful conservative hashtag cluster which and again
maybe I should have said that in the hashtag networks every node is a hashtag and they
are connected if they appear together in the same tweet. So this is a very low level way
of seeing what is going on in the data in a way. You don't need to do some kind of topic
modeling or complicated techniques. You can literally just by looking at the hashtags
already get a hint at how the different camps speak about the same topic. So if you go here
in this area, this is about confiscation laws. So Marxism in this case is also a good example.
Right now we don't really know how it is used, right? And it can be used either by conservatives
or by liberals and it's important to look at it in the context of the data. So then
we would have to, okay, five minutes left. Good. I will go back to the slides. Okay.
So under the hood, this whole backend of the collector and the visualizer is written in
Python and it's using the streamlit Python library to serve it on a local front end.
So this is actually a very convenient library and I guess a lot of people also know it,
but you can write your code in Python and then it essentially serves it in interfaces
that look like this. And the explorer is written in HTML and JavaScript and it uses D3 and
prints the graph on canvas, which is also why it's probably not as fast as Sigma is,
but it has some nice other features that are especially due to this force graph library.
So I think if anyone has questions, I'm going to go into the details and the questions.
So this is how we install it. It's fairly simple. If you have a running Python bigger
than 3.7 and there's also an API. So of course, especially here, probably people will not
be so interested in using the streamlit interface, but you may want to include it into some kind
of existing code pipeline that you have. And this is essentially the API for semantic networks
and interaction networks. So I invite you to try it out yourself while you still can.
You have five days. Of course, if you have the research API, you might be able to use
it for a bit longer, but otherwise go on these websites fast. And I will stop the talk with
some questions. Actually, I came here with more questions than answers and I'm really
hoping for a lively discussion now because I'm not originally a developer, so I kind
of wrote this a bit on my own. And I wonder if this integration of Python and JavaScript
is actually a good idea because in theory it would also be possible to probably do everything
in JavaScript and maybe do it on the client side so you wouldn't have to install all these
libraries. Then, okay, maybe one thing that I would like to show is that I experimented
with temporal networks. So of course, doing temporal force layouts is kind of a non-trivial
task, but we can kind of look a little bit at the temporality of these networks by at
least displaying only the links that are active during a given day. So this is also kind of
nice, I think, but I would like to discuss maybe other visualization paradigms for this
kind of network. Then one thing that would be really interesting, I think, is to dig
deeper into a visualization paradigm for hierarchical structure of communities, meaning
that okay, in theory I can either run stochastic block models or luvain community detections
and stop them at a certain level and then have some kind of hierarchical node structure.
But how to visualize that is another question, but I think it would be very interesting, especially
for very large graphs. Then another question is force layouts. Should we still use them
now that everyone is doing node2vec and all these other things? I think yes, but maybe
there's good arguments against it. And on a more deeper conceptual level is, and this
is a question, the first one is a question for people who already have much more experience
in building tools for the social sciences, is how do you kind of further integrate these
kinds of methods into existing maybe also more qualitative social science pipelines?
So yeah, it's kind of an open question. And how can we devise something like a research
protocol for these kinds of interactive network visualizations? Because as you saw in my demo,
we kind of look at the big nodes, we look at the tweets they made, and it gives us some
kind of intuition of what's going on in the debate. But how can we formalize such kinds
of visual network analysis? And I think, I mean, there's people in the audience who actually
work on this, so it would be very interesting for me to talk about this. And finally, to
end on actually maybe a bit nicer note is that there is the network of firsts as we
had already said in the beginning on this website. So it is updated every 15 minutes
thanks to a data collection done by my colleague, Beatrice. Thank you very much. And so if you
go on this website, you can see the retweet network of firsts. And if you tweet, then
you can find yourself in the network also. So yeah, what do we have here in the middle?
OK, first them itself. Then there was Ubuntu, Debian somewhere. OK, time's up. Thank you.
Do we have questions?
Yes. So the question is, I mentioned that you can only collect tweets from the last
seven days. With the free API, this is a limitation. But the tool itself just writes into existing
CSV. It depends, basically. So if you do the same keyword search multiple times, then it
will just append to a CSV. Yeah, so this is.
Yes, I mean, this is the question right now. It depends because the question is what happens
on Mastodon. I don't know. All these, like if you want to look at political controversies
and such discussions, I don't know if Mastodon is mature enough yet to or adopted enough
yet. I think if you want to look at the first income, it's great. So for this, yes. But
yeah.
I know computer science for more than 40 years. And I am very skeptical of this kind of thing,
I'm one. You don't buy paper, right? Really?
Yes.
You know, dancing.
computers, computers, computers, or many people
visits which we have so often.
So I'm very reactive about this kind of thing.
I don't know what you should think about that.
Well, I don't know which point exactly should I address,
because you raised a lot of.
So are you OK?
If I can rephrase, so you are concerned
about this kind of research also?
Yes, because it can be used to track users
across political camps.
We have problems with computers of a popular section
of population.
There are no computers taking them in account.
I see.
So I think it's more about the representativity of Twitter
data for the wider population, which of course,
you're totally right.
It is kind of a subset of highly politicized, maybe also
a bit more educated than average people.
So you cannot.
But this is not what we're trying to do also.
You're not trying to infer, I don't know,
actual election results based on Twitter data.
So yeah, I don't know if I addressed the point.
Maybe we can take more about it.
To be concerned about this kind of thing.
Right.
Thank you.
Next time.