Okay, thank you for coming to this presentation.
I'm Nicolas Roland from the Gustave Vefel University.
Thank you.
Please.
And I will be presenting some research we did on crowdsource
health data, some analysis we did with a few bunch of software.
I will be presenting the work we did with myself, Pierre Roman, and
Ludovic Moison from the Gustave Vefel University.
So traffic noise is a major health concern.
In Europe, in Western Europe, it's estimated by the World Health Organization that we lost
one million healthy life years each year.
In France, we have estimated the social cost, so the cost to the community of 147 billion
euros per year.
So it has a cost on monetary costs, but also a cost on people and their health.
So the big question is how we can find where noise is problematic.
And so, of course, we can't have direct measure everywhere.
We can't put microphones everywhere.
It will be a cost nightmare, a logistic nightmare, and a privacy nightmare.
Of course, it's not possible.
So the traditional way is to simulate the noise from traffic counts.
So we put counters on roads and counts of vehicles and estimate the vehicles.
We do that on trains, we do that on planes, aircraft, and we simulate those traffic counts.
And we produce this kind of car, for example, noise modeling, which is an application we
developed with the Umarou laboratory that can compute from these counts noise maps.
And this is a legal requirement by the European Commission.
Another way that the Umarou, which is working on environmental acoustics, it's a lab on
another acoustic, is not to simulate, but to get actual data, real data from contributors
using a smartphone application you can install.
It's working on smartphones.
It's available on fDroid.
So it's also free of interest software.
And it measures several things like your position, the sun spectrum, or not the full spectrum,
it's just the third octave.
So you can't understand what people are saying if it's someone speaking.
But you can detect that someone is speaking.
You also have some level and some kind of information.
So it's part of a bigger project, like the noise project.
So we have this noise modeling application that generates noise from open source geo
data, mostly French geo data and open script map.
So when you use street complete to say, OK, this is GROSS and this is MACADAM, we use
that data to generate more precise maps, sound maps.
Noise capture to measure and share some environments.
And all this data is given in a special data infrastructure called Onomap.
And there is also some community maps made by the users.
This is a map of all the recordings we have nearly five years.
So you can see it's worldwide.
It's just not only France or Europe.
It's worldwide.
So the question was, what can you do with all this data we collect?
So there was an extraction in 2021 of the three first years of data collection.
So it's still collecting the data, but there was an extract that contains 260,000 tracks.
So the tracks is recording worldwide with some spectrum, like I said, GPS localization
and also the contributor can provide some tags.
It's an open database license.
So it's free to use.
So the question is, oh, we can characterize the user environment, the sound environment
of the user at the moment of the recording with the collected data.
We think of two possibilities.
One is from the sound spectrum we record.
So it's an ongoing analysis.
And it's not the way, it's the hardest way to do that, because we have to find patterns
on the recordings.
And we have to use machine learning to detect these patterns on all those data.
So it's still going, but there is an easiest way.
And this is the way I use.
It's by using the tags that are provided by the contributors.
So in this concept, like I say, 260,000 tracks, half of them have tags.
So we can use just half of it.
50,000 are where outdoors are not tested.
So we want to work on this sound environment, so we discard indoors and test tagged tracks.
We also remove the very, very small ones, so less than five seconds.
So we remove maybe tracks that might be accidental.
And we also work for just this preliminary works on France, because we are French, and
it's easier for us to understand what's happening.
And it's nearly 12,000 tracks.
And like I said, it's a major, the road noise is a major concern.
And it appears directly in our data, because the more frequent tag is road.
So people are on maybe a third of our subset.
There is the road noise in it.
The second one is chatting, and so we have also things like wiring, animals, sounds,
works.
So there is 12 tags, different tags the user can provide.
So we use quite simple one, a toolkit to analyze the data.
First is the PostgreSQL and PostgreSQL database, because the data is provided as PostgreSQL
dump.
So in order to access it, you have to rebuild the data and the database.
And the other tool we use is R, because we are, in the team, we are mostly R users.
We also have Python, but we are more familiar with R.
So two tools, simple, yes?
Actually not really, because we also use in R a lot of packages, like the tidyverse, the
SF packages for your special, your reason, stats, and so on.
And we also, all those packages use dependencies like pandoc, markdown, rivil.js.
This presentation actually is made with R and rivil.js.
We also use geospatial libraries like Proj, JOS, GLAR, and those are dependencies that
are not handled by R. It just called them.
So what we did in this data set, so let's talk about results.
We got some interesting things to add.
The first thing we looked at was the animal tags, because we know that bird songs can
be heard mostly the first hour before dawn.
So this is a well-known dynamics in ornithology.
And in the sound of the environment, we can't hear it.
And we actually find it also.
So in this graph, you can see on the left part is the time before the sunrise on the
day of recording.
And after, it's an hour after.
So we find this actual dynamics of birds singing one hour before dawn.
So it was a good sign.
And we also find peaks of road noise between 8 to 10 AM and I fixed it, 6 to 8 PM.
And we can say it looks like a much like a commuter's behavior.
But we can't directly link to it.
We can say, it's very similar to.
So we look to physical events in the environment of the contributor.
And we find a very good correlation between the wind force and the present of tags, the
wind tags in the data set.
So it works very well.
We also did that with rainfall.
And the correlation is not so strong.
Not enough.
So it might be a user bias, maybe if the rainfall is too small, the user doesn't hear the rain
or doesn't think to add the tag about it.
And it might be also a special issue because the mean nearest weather station distances
is 16 kilometers.
So maybe the local condition might be different between the weather station and the user
at the moment of the recording.
So not so strong, but actually find data.
I'm not the first one to speak about repossessible science here, actually.
And it's an issue, really an issue.
So for this study, we have some good points, like the data is already available.
The source code, we made it available.
So all SQL script to rebuild the database and the table we use are available.
The R notebooks we made are also available.
The setup broadly is available.
But we also bought things to assess.
So some notebooks were very wide.
And we went very deep on the analysis and the exploratory files.
But at the end, it was very hard to reproduce even in our team.
We actually were able to do it.
But for someone coming from outside, it might be difficult to enter in that.
And so it needs some contractoring and a little bit more commenting, more explanation.
And so there is also a lack of information on software environment.
So it makes it very hard to reuse and reproduce.
So what could we use to have a better tooling?
Since we use R, you can use R-end, which is R package to reproduce.
It's like Py virtual environment.
It worked well, but it worked well just for R. And we used other software like Pajes.
We used JOS, Proj, Jidal.
So it's not perfect.
Docker might be something that can be helpful.
But like Simon said before, it's not perfect for reproducibility.
And I just say, GUIX is on my mind from one year, actually, to say, OK, I need to work
on that.
And I think it'd be a good solution.
I won't talk too much because there was a talk by Simon Tournier just two talks before.
And I go watch it.
I think it might be a very good solution.
In conclusion, so we can use cold source data.
We can use cold source data for science.
We can find even for something quirky, like some environment.
You can use it for science.
This particular data set is usable.
So you can access it and find new things.
We don't have every question.
So we don't have every answer to.
We can answer with this data set.
So it's quite fun to play with it and find some, oh, we can find birds.
I do believe that free open source software are key for reproducible science.
We can't make reproducible science with proprietary software.
It's impossible.
Repulcable science is hard to achieve.
You have to find it as soon as possible before starting your project.
Because when you are too far, you have to refactor things, and it can be very tricky.
And you have maybe working with, this is more sound and physics related study.
But sometimes I work with economists.
I work with geographers.
And they are not so fun, very keen on technologies and computers in general.
So sometimes you need someone, maybe an engineer or someone in the team, that can handle this
reproducible part.
And so you need to get the skills.
So either you get yourself or you have to take someone in the team that can do that
for you.
And notebooks are not enough.
notebooks are great to communicate and explore things, but they are not good enough for reproducible
science.
So there is a link for the data set, the actual data set.
Please go to check noisepleid.org.
You can navigate on the map.
You can see actually tracks and click on things to get what is recorded.
Thank you for your attention.
You can join me by email or on Mastodon.
This presentation is available here.
And everything is accessible on GitHub.
Thank you very much.
Thanks.
That leaves us a bit of time for questions.
So please feel free to take them, repeat them, and then answer them.
Yeah, in the graph with the bird, you had a sort of a dip at zero, which...
Yeah, zero is...
That is a statistical artifact.
We have an explanation to show that the low beam is exactly at the top of the fitted line.
Yeah.
The explanation was about this particular graph, why there is a low beam at the zero,
and the peak is just above the zero, because it smoothed a little bit.
And you can see there is a peak just before, and the line is just smoothing, and there
is little shifting.
And you think, why is there a low?
I don't know.
I'm not sure.
Yeah, please.
So, as you're jumping on the same question, because we are doing crowdsourcing data, so
it's obviously influenced by the users that's collecting the data for us, how do you factor
in or how do you eliminate this source of variance where there could be underlying behavior
of humans that is affecting the results of the data?
For example, summarise time.
So people who get awakened by birds during... before summarise, they would be very annoyed
and they would record more.
People who wake up at the normal times are too busy to even make the recording, then
you kind of have a bias in the data.
Okay.
So the question was about this is crowdsourcing data.
So there is data provided by people willing to provide it, and there is a bias, of course,
because you might be angry at birds waking you up in the morning, and you may be angry
to traffic noise, and actually we don't assess the data.
We take it as it is.
Maybe there will be some... I'm not part of this part of the project, but maybe there
will be some work on it, and we hope that it's so much data that it will smooth a bias.
But of course, it's bias, like OpenSuite map data, and there is someone making a decision
to say, okay, I will record it for a good or bad reason, or to prove a point, okay,
where I'm leaving, it's too noisy, I make a recording.
And it's okay.
But we count... it's very hard to assess this kind of information.
We don't know why people record tracks, because maybe it's a pleasant environment and they
want to share it.
It's not so good, and it's okay for us.
I hope it answers your question.
Yeah, please.
Yeah, so I just wanted to ask, because I think wind is pretty hard to incorporate, because
when somebody records, they probably record it without the pop filter, which makes the
sound really loud of the wind, despite it not being so loud.
Because somebody comes up with the phone and records it, and the wind blows straight
into it, and it's really, really loud, I mean, as kind of like in decibels, when it actually
isn't.
So you can translate these sort of things out, or subtract something from this wind recording
so you can keep them in the noise.
Okay, the question was about the wind recordings, and the fact that smartphone doesn't have
a pop shield, and protect the microphone from the wind.
And so, actually, I'm not an acoustician.
I'm a more JS engineer.
So I don't have the exact question for that, but I do believe when you are using your microphone,
when you're talking smartphone nowadays, it can protect you a little bit from the noise.
But I'm not sure of the question.
Yeah, please.
My question is kind of connected to the bias one, but when you were building the data capture,
like...
So the subsets?
Yeah, did you build the data capture tool where people are inputting data, right?
Or how was that built?
And did you make sure that people could use it in a way that...
Like, how did you make sure that people were comfortable using it in the situations that
you needed recordings for?
So the question was...
Can you simplify it?
So I'm interested in what choices you made in order to have the thing look and function
how it did to capture the data, and again, to bias.
If people are not able to use it, or don't like using it, does that also bias the data?
Ah, okay.
So you're not speaking...
So the question was about how we build the analysis and...
How we build it.
If you are not able to use R to build the...
Sorry.
Actually, we have to make choice, and we are more comfortable with R.
So there is a bias, of course, and we also have some libraries like SunCalc, for example,
that makes life very simpler for us to...
We give it a date and a position, and it gives you the sunrise and...
Sunrise and sunset, thank you.
Sunset tile, for example, so it makes life easier for us.
But of course, there is a bias.
Even when we build the application, there is, of course, a bias.
But I wasn't part of the team that built this application.
And it's more focused on what we want to get, but it's available for everyone, so do whatever we want to do with it.
Thank you.
We have more time, maybe.
On your first slide, you had a really big number in terms of the social costs.
Yeah.
Only in France.
It seems quite egregiously big.
Do you know anything about what includes the social costs?
What are the costs that are incorporated into this number?
As Kim, it's a huge report.
Adam is a French agency, an environmental agency, so it works on noise pollution, but also air pollution and things like that.
So you are working...
Sorry, I didn't repeat the question.
The question is about the social cost and the amount and how it is constructed.
So I just read quickly the report.
And the social cost is mostly about health issues, lack of sleep, and stress related to noise and things like that, and how it affects people,
and how it affects their health, and how it affects less better health as a cost for the society because you have more anxiety.
Big disease in terms of the GDP.
Sorry, we have a short switch.
Thank you very much.
Sorry.