Hello everyone, I'm Dylan Fievez and I'm a research engineer at CERAF Technique Research
Centre in Mons in Belgium.
Today I will present you the software Mephene, which is a graphical tool for modeling and
simulating multiphysics systems.
So the project started with a research project.
It is a collaboration with Thales Alenia Space, so it's a research project funded by the Wallonia,
so a public fund of Belgium.
And the goal of the project is the development of a simulation method to assist in the design
of mechatronic chains with complete multiphysics model.
So in other terms, what are the goals of the project?
It exists different kinds of multiphysics simulation software, the global variable simulation
type like Open Modelica, which simulates a system by an item like a motor, etc.
And we have a local variable simulation like Finite Element Simulation System, Finite Element
Simulation for Multiphysics System.
And both types of simulation are not compatible with each other, so the research project tried
to find another way to simulate a multiphysics model with using electrical analogues modeling.
So the method we want to develop is a simulation in three points.
So the first step is to convert physical system to electrical analogues system.
The second step is to convert those electrical analogues model to numerical model.
And the last step is reducing numerical model with evaluating the inference of each part
of the system to the rest of the system.
And a second point, a more important point for our research is a timescale adaptive model
reduction.
So how to explain that?
In a system, we have a low inertia part in the stem and high inertia.
So low inertia part of the system are a part of the system that evolve quickly in the time
and high inertia evolve slowly with the time.
So when we simulate each one, we don't require the same step size.
Sorry.
When we make a simulation, a physical simulation, we have to find an optimal step size.
If we have a too large step size, the accuracy will decrease.
And if we have a smaller step size, we will have a sufficient accuracy.
But if the step size is too much small, the time to execute the simulation will be increased
for a little gain of accuracy.
So we have multiple inertia part in a multi-physics system.
And we want to find a way to optimize the simulation by using different timesquale in
the system.
So for the project, we have some requirements when we will choose the simulation software.
We need a multi-physics simulation software.
This one must be adaptable.
So it must be able to adapt the model as a function of the condition of simulation, like
the time, et cetera.
And last but not least, the application must be user-friendly.
So we have Simulink with MATLAB or XCOS with Scilab.
That would be a very, very good application for the project.
But Simulink is expensive.
It's a closed source software and not exactly adapted to our requirements.
And it's a closed source software, so we couldn't modify MATLAB like we wanted.
And for XCOS, it's not user-friendly.
And like MATLAB, it doesn't exactly fit with the project requirement.
So we decided to develop our own software that leverages existing powerful Python libraries.
Here is an overview of our application.
It has been used in a regulation system.
And here we have an example of results for this regulation system.
So the software, it's a graphical tool for modeling and simulating multi-physics system.
There is a quick demonstration of how to use the application.
So to build the simulation graph, it's just a drag and drop from a box library to a scheme
drawing.
And then once the simulation graph is done, you can easily launch the simulation.
We can use multiple projects at the same time, save and load projects, et cetera.
So what is the application?
The application is a simulation graph builder.
We have provided some default libraries to use the application if you install it on your
computer.
But you can easily add your own process boxes and can solve all the simulation you've been
building in the application.
We have implemented some default simulation solver.
But you can also add your custom simulation solver.
So here is a list of default boxes in the application.
We have a mat application like addition, multiplication, derivative, et cetera, signal processing with
transfer function, et cetera, sources, and order like a graph display, and also open
model, cache simulation, embedder, et cetera.
So if you want to install the application on your PC and want to create your own library
of boxes, if we want to create our own box, we have to know that a box is defined by two
files.
The first one is a description file written in YAML.
The second one is a code file written in Python.
And there is one condition to make it as a box.
It's that both files must share the same base file name.
So how to create a box?
I will take an example.
I will create a box that is able to display a graphic data in a graph.
So the goal of the box is to display data in a two-axis plot, in the x-axis, the time,
and the y-axis, the value.
The box must be able to display data from one or more sources.
And the graph must be displayed at the end of the simulation.
There is how the box must behave during the simulation and at the end of the simulation.
So how to create the box?
The first step is to define the metadata of the box with the box name, the library name,
version, author, and creation date.
Just metadata of the box.
Then we will define the characteristic of the box.
What I mean by characteristic is all the inputs, all the outputs of the box, and the parameters.
So for the box, for the graphical box, we need three parameters, the title, the label
for y-axis, and the label for x-axis.
We must define the type of the parameter, and we can define a default value.
For the outputs, the box doesn't require any output.
And for the inputs, we have three conditions.
The first one, we have defined a default count of input to one.
So the box, by default, will have one input.
The number of inputs must be unlimited.
So we must write the parameter is infinite to true.
And the number of inputs must be not limited.
That means we can define a range of number of inputs.
So we can limit, for example, the number of inputs from one to five, for example.
But in this case, we won't define any limit.
The next step is to define a behavior.
So how to define the behavior of the box, we write a Python file.
When we write a Python file, we can use all of the available Python libraries.
We have to define three functions.
The first one, an init function.
In our case, this function will init the plot.
The second one is, during the simulation, what will the box do?
What is the process inside the box during the simulation?
In our case, it's saving data.
And what will the box will do after the simulation?
And in our case, it's plot the data.
Then the next step is to connect the description file and the code file, the Python file.
To connect both, you only have to write the name of the associated function.
Then we have created a box.
Now we want to add it in a library.
So a library is just a collection of boxes.
And in practical, a library is just a folder containing a YAML file and a Python file.
For now, a library is a folder that doesn't accept subdirectories.
We can't, at the time, we can't put our file in subdirectories.
It won't be recognized.
So we have our folder, our first box with our two files, second one, et cetera.
And it's how we make a library.
Another feature we added to Muffin is an IPython interaction.
So Muffin can be run in IPython session.
It means that Muffin can access to all the IPython variables, all variables declared
in the IPython environment.
We can use all these variables as simulation parameters.
And the access variable is dynamic.
It means that if we can launch the application at the beginning of the session, declare variables
in the IPython, and use it dynamically.
So if I launch a first simulation with some parameters, I update it after one simulation.
If I launch a second simulation, the second simulation will take the new value into account
for the new simulation.
Or to use it in IPython session, the first step is to load the Muffin extension with
the command loadxt.
And then just run the Muffin command.
There is a demonstration of how it works.
So we have firstly declare our parameter in a notebook.
We will create a simulation with two signed signals.
And then we will configure all the parameters.
We have implemented some information for the user when he writes a wrong variable name,
the application will give the information to the user.
So here we have all of both signals.
The first one at 10 hertz with an amplitude of 10.
And the second one at 5 hertz with an amplitude of 7.
And we will launch the demonstration.
Then we will update the value of the second signal, the amplitude of the second signal
only, and we have a signal with the new values.
We have implemented other control features like saving and loading a project, working
with multiple projects at the same time.
Copy and paste boxes and cut also.
Delete in box.
Then cancel action, etc.
So in conclusion, we have developed our own multi-physics simulation software.
The advantages of this application is that the application is entirely coded in Python.
So we have access to many powerful libraries like NumPy, SciPy, etc. for the application
and for the custom processing boxes and simulation servers.
The application is very adaptive.
What I mean by that is that you can easily implement your own custom boxes and custom
simulation server.
And the application can be associated to an IPython environment.
So Mephene offers an Python alternative to MATLAB plus Simulink.
The disadvantages of the application, it's written in a scripting language.
So we have higher solving times.
It's a young application at the time, so we need more time to offer a lot of features.
And we need more users to improve the experience.
So what's next?
We will have to work on compatibility.
We want to make the transition from PyQT5 to PyQT6.
And we want to add more interactivity with the user to improve the user-friendliness
of the application.
Here is a list of the contributors of the project.
And here is the links of the project.
If you want to read all the source code, you have a link to the GitLab.
And if you want to try the application, we have a package available on PyP.
If you want to try to install it directly in your Python, you can use a pip install
method.
So thank you for your attention.
If you have some more questions.
You said you go through electrical analogy to make the calculation, you use electrical
equation, right?
Sorry?
Can you repeat?
I will repeat after.
You said you come from physical...
We want to make a electronic simulation.
And we want to convert all the parts of the system to electrical analogies.
We don't use any software like...
Sorry, I'm a bit stressed.
Electrical simulation.
I don't remember the name.
But the cons with the software is that the model is not dynamic.
We can't try a lot of sets easily.
But the game of our application is to...
With the time, make a box to create an interface to other multi-physics application.
We don't want to replace those applications.
We just want to create an interface to those applications to use it in our research project.
If I don't want that, because it's important project.
The idea is a lot of process can be simulated with impedance like...
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Thinking, like thermosters, mechanical stuff.
You had already...
And then between the physical aspect and the electrical, the impedance stuff.
So my question was, do you use electrical equation because they are simpler to solve?
Yeah, very good physical equation.
Sorry guys, there is a stream.
People watching on the web, they can hear you.
You have to go through the mic.
Maybe you can go instead and use the mic if you want to answer that question.
Oh, you can repeat maybe.
You can repeat.
Yeah, that would be great if you could at least summarize.
It's probably the user who understand better the problem.
It's maybe just...
Okay, yeah.
The goal of the project, of the application is to improve the comprehension of the system.
Do you plan to make it where and how you work to evaluate the wide process?
Sorry, I don't have heard...
I'm a bit...
I'm a bit deaf.
Because you want to continue to do a real time simulation?
No, the simulation...
Can we do a real time simulation?
For now, it's not possible.
We want to implement that in the future.
For now, the application, we just run the initialization function, then run the simulation
function and the ending function.
And all the functions are run in one time.
So at the time, we don't have implemented a real time overview of the simulation.
But we plan in the future to add this feature.
Go ahead.
So, no, it's...
In the beginning, you talked about the slow paths and the initial high inertia and lower
inertia paths of your simulations.
Yes.
And you said that your software was designed to deal with local viable solutions and global
viable simulations.
How does that translate into what you've shown us?
Where is the global viable part?
So I repeat the question.
I've said that we have in a system low inertia paths and high inertia paths and also local
viable simulation software and global viable software.
And how...
How does this translate into what you've shown us?
Where is the idea?
Or does it implement it in the application?
Yeah, why is it in the application?
How do these concepts translate into the application you've shown us?
What moment it's a purpose?
At the time, it's not implemented...
It's the background of the project.
All right.
But it's too stable a problem.
So the idea is we want to have too stable those.
And I'm sure that this kind of...
You might forget for the...
Discussion can go on in the...
It's a great part of the first time.
So go on with the discussion.
We should switch speakers now.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Can we go for the video today?
Yes.
Sure.
Thank you.