Hello everyone, glad to be here. I am Etienne Combe, I am a researcher at Guast-Avester
University and I will talk about a site project that I have from several times ago and try
to tell the story of this site project with concern of web mapping and statistical data
and how quickly, how the OpenStreetMap stack have changed the way we show and diffuse statistical
data. Okay, so this is a background that I will skip and I will go back in time eight
years ago. I was on a project and I was working on a massive, great statistical data set that
are called Doné-Caroé in French and these data are derived from text sheets and they
are given at a very detailed spatial scale, so pixels of 200 meters by 200 meters on all
the French territories and you have several variables like population structures, number
of people under 10, above 17 and so on and you have also information about the revenue
of the people and this data set reached the statistical limit of statistical secret, so
in some of the pixels there are less than 11 households, so the data are aggregated
in order to be above this threshold which is forced by the law. So the more precise
data set that we may have on the French population. Okay, and the distribution of this data set
at this time was like this, so the first step was to go on the INSE website, find this page,
it was already quite hard because it was in a very deep part of the website and you have
to download two files in a very specific file format like DBF and MIFF-MID which were coming
from a map for software, so a G software from the 80s and you have to deal with that. Okay,
so not very easy, you already have a QG way to read that, so there is already an open
source software to read the data but the exploration was not very easy and friendly. Okay, so this
is the help page to read the data, load them in QGs and so on but if you are not a G specialist,
it was quite difficult to deal with that. Okay, and I was working with my student on
this data set and at the end of the thesis we had the idea to try to improve a little
bit that and we seen an opportunity. So the context I have already given, EV file, tricky
file format and also projection problem in the data set at this time, usable with a lot
of pain and with dedicated software like Map and Faux, ArcGIS or QGs. And the opportunity
that we have seen at this time was the web mapping stack that was developed around the
OSM project. So OpenLayer was already there, Leaflet also and Mapbox tools were also on
the rise with at this time, this was a tiny platform that allowed to build custom maps,
web maps. Okay, and we had second that this will allow to renew the data diffusion, which
is visualization approaches. Okay, we were not alone, Oliver O'Brien in UK did a quite
similar proposal in 2015 with DataShine, this is a screen of DataShine at this time, which
was built using OpenLayer and he had to build one stack of types for each features he wanted
to be visible on the map. So in all of this interface you may choose between several features,
so more than 50, less than 10, the revenue or so on and he had to build all these types,
so a lot of work. And at the same time there was a technology that was coming which is
called vector ties, so the ties that were used to build the map are no more images but
are vector file format solutions, so it was the very beginning of this approach and I
have recovered some of the first tech notes about some solutions from the open source
community about vector ties and for statistical data this was a massive advantage because
you may put all the data in the tile and add up the visualization on the front end and
you didn't have to produce one tile set for every feature, so it was very advantageous
and very interesting and we tried to build something around that and the tools were not
existing completely at this time, so the first tool was something like some earth creep to
process the data and export vector ties in geo-gizom format, a leaflet map to draw the
map and a detour hook to render the vector ties on the canvas and to animate all this
and some tricks to try something with interactivity because if you draw something on canvas it's
not so easy to know on which part of the map you are and we tried to put some love in the
details about the color scales, some background on the labels and the data that were produced
by the French administrations were square, so there is one unknown problem with statistical
data, special statistical data which is called the modifiable area unit problem which says
that when you change the elevation levels you will see different things and you may
find different patterns and we see that this can be an opportunity in fact and we will
try to aggregate the raw data at different scales and link these scales with the zoom
levels, so this will solve two problems, we need to keep the vector ties a little bit
small because we are on the web so we did not want to download 10 mega and so on, so
this will be solved by the aggregations and because of the map we want to explore several
aggregations scales so this was a possibility that were interesting, so this first solution
is still usable eight years ago and it's already cool, so you have a map you may zoom, you
may look for a place and so on and you may find a precise location, you may switch the
features that you want to look at and you didn't have to download the big file open
energy software and it's quite more easy.
Okay so this was the first project and we get some feedback from the INSE so we are
speaking with the producer of the data, also from journalists, some journalists were interested
on specific topics and used the tools for example to study segregation on school or
districting, your banists also use some of the your banists use that for territorial
diagnosis, transportation research and curious people so it was cool and since this first
version the technology has quite matured and there is now a very standard way to deliver
vector types which is an NVTA format, Mapbox vector types with specifications and Pojis,
all known database can produce these type of vector types and there is also new frontend
solutions like Mapbox gel which is now a normal and open source but the open source project
is used by MapTrib now and that's also, we have a new tool chain and some successors
and if you have questions and if you want details about some of these successors it
will be a pleasure.
Excuse me but I am completely disconnected from one point, vector types in French what
is the translation?
It's how you split so the question was about vector types and the meaning of vector types
so when mapping is based on a pyramid of types and when you zoom, a type is a tool in French.
Yes but it's because in web mapping, so to draw the map you have to build tiles that
are 100 in a pyramid and when you zoom you download only the parts of the zoom level
that is concerned by the current view so it's to optimize the usage of the bandwidth and
to send only the relevant part of the data to the frontend during the exploration of
the map.
From Inse they are trying to build something similar but from some time now and it's still
not online so I have worked on a prototype for them so the next version of the solution
was built with Inse and the didn't have sufficiently people inside to deal with this type of project
I think but it's still not there but if you look at that I shine so almost the same project
with similar tools and in the UK that I shine is now available in for the census of the
UK it's a new version of that I shine that is used.
So I have some hope that at one point in time we will have an official portal in Inse that
will look like that but still not.
Yes but not in the web mapping exploration tools for everybody but I had one version
for your buddies for example where they can upload their own shape files to add more layers
of information.
Yes there is a European initiative I have forgotten the name but it's all derived from
the Inspear directive which gives some guidelines for delivering statistical data, special statistical
data sets and there is also a library from Eurostat which is called GrideViz.
You may find the links but there is a JavaScript library now which is developed by Eurostat
to show grided data, statistical data.
Thank you, we have to get here.
Thank you.