Okay, so basically we had this extra slot of time in our physical session.
Actually, the, well, we want to use that time to engage the session with you, the audience,
about this open research track here at FOSDEM.
Before opening the stage for basically questions and discussions, just wanted to very briefly
say a few words about how we ended up creating this space.
So basically we've been with a few colleagues at S
Poppari, for instance, doing a few conferences here at FOSDEM in other dev rooms, using this
FOSDEM conference as a venue to actually talk about technical realizations we were doing
in the lab.
And it was not so, it was a very good opportunity for us because it's not easy to do a scientific
publication about technical things, more specifically into the social sciences.
So after a few years of doing that, we thought that actually we could try to go a step further
on this by organizing this track, which is definitely about open source software and
research.
And so we had, as you've seen, we understand research with a very broad way.
Any kind of inquiry is, we think, interesting to discuss because the share, a journalist
investigator, we had an open factor, for instance, our social scientists, our natural scientists,
all share kind of the same engagement with data about inquiry.
So we created this room four years ago.
Actually at the time we merged with another initiative from two people from neuroscience.
And it was nice also to have these different disciplines.
Of course, then the COVID came, so we succeeded into keeping the room online.
And now, so we have a crew of five, six people.
We have two people who are online, Yohudi and Celia Grison-Daniel, who will actually
monitor from their home the online session, which will start in 20 minutes.
And basically we are a bunch of people working in academia or not, or in an open knowledge
foundation.
And I have no more in academia myself.
And so the first thing I would like to say is like volunteers to help us out organizing
this space are more than welcome.
Basically the work of this starts in the autumn where we submit a proposal to first them to
organize this room again.
So each year we do that.
We wait for the answer.
And once we have it, we have to do a call of proposal for something very, very classic
about organizing a conference.
So reviewing papers, actually getting the papers in.
So we actually contact people for asking them to come to our conference.
And then, as you've seen, what we did today, mining the door, putting signs on people and
that kind of stuff, which is fun.
And yeah, so I will finish with that.
And maybe some other people won't say other things.
I will finish this with one thing.
The other thing is it's important for us to try to augment diversity of our group.
Gender but also disciplines.
We'd like to open up as much discipline as we can.
So yeah.
Sorry?
Less French people.
Less, yeah, and diversity.
So there is a question about, yes, yes, also less French people.
We tried that, we succeeded a little bit, but not that much.
So yes, please.
Matthew.
Yeah, I just wanted to say a few things.
But basically, the reason we need you is also to increase this diversity in the papers submitted.
Because for instance, if you look at the gender balance, the committee is basically gender
balanced.
But the submissions are completely dominated by males.
And also, the deaf room in the beginning had one leg firmly into the hard sciences.
But then we've kind of drifted towards the social sciences.
And it's not just us, it's also the demand.
So we try to prompt something.
But it's kind of a balance game to try to have this variety in the proposals in the
first place.
Because if we don't have any proposition, for instance, in hard sciences, we're not
going to have any.
So the audience, which is like, if you submit papers, or if you come to the committee and
then become a bridge to contact other people to submit papers, that's how we can kind of
ensure that it remains diverse.
It's not a lot of work to participate, also because we are many, and we are probably going
to get even more people.
And it's not a problem to be many, because the real job beyond managing the day is, as
you said, to contact the people and then to review, but mostly to contact them.
So please come in and join us about that.
But we could also have this discussion about what the scope of that should be.
Because I think that the figure of the tool maker was kind of at the center of what we
had in mind.
But as we see, it's not just about tools.
It can also be about infrastructure in ways that is not tools, like institutions.
I don't know.
I'm thinking of the journal of open source software that we had a few years back.
Infrastructure is not just tools.
So now it's clear.
It's not just the tool makers.
They said the infrastructure maker.
And what could it be like common and shape the profile of the room with us?
Can I just to emphasize what you said, can I just share my experience from this?
Go ahead.
Take the mic.
Since my first time at First
Time, and I went to talk about it.
But just to emphasize what Matt just said, this was my first time at First Time.
And as I told you, I'm not a coder.
So I was pretty scared about what I was going to say and share, et cetera, et cetera.
So please do it.
Because why I came here was to share knowledge, of course, but to retrieve some different
experience from what I do every day and who the people are with whom I work every day.
So thank you for this.
And please submit papers.
Yeah.
You want the mic?
I think one challenge for the diversity is that there's also the good way to use open
ITK solutions and design on them.
And it's about how we can find how to tweak a real type of
hey, we also use Excel.
It's sort of a bad thing for a practice
that people look at strangely, or even if it's
like LibreOffice, which I think is a good source.
But it's not the death wave.
And I guess that vibe that people catch that
would make also a lot of people that
would be very interesting for this community
to also see how it's done in the real world in a very messy way
very often.
So may stem not by that.
And if we could get to a place where this would be legit
and people would be curious and interested
in those non-perfect, chaotic, and not 100% open source ways,
I think that would increase diversity law.
So just for the stream, the idea that a challenge to diversity
could be that there are good ways and bad ways
to do open source.
And where I say that, I forgot the last part of your speech.
The Excel LibreOffice part is important.
He's going to come back later.
I'm sorry.
I'm so tired.
It was for the stream.
Yeah, that's what the point was.
But I mean, you were very right that it's about us
to cultivate that.
Yeah, it comes back to me now.
It's really important to show how
it's being done in the real world.
That's something that I think we all
appreciate very much about the first dimension in general.
You don't see some people talking from a distance
about how it's supposed to be.
You have real people who are from actually doing stuff, which
also means that sometimes they are not
really good at communicating.
And that's something that I really appreciate,
because you hear the voices.
I think the first dimension is somehow a safe space for people
who are not primarily good at communicating,
contrary to academics, for instance,
but who are really doing the stuff.
And we can hear them.
And we can identify to them and realize
that anyone can get involved in open science and open source
design.
We want very much to keep cultivating that.
That's why also we try to have a blend of people showing off
the tools they've made, but also people
having a different kind of talk.
I don't know what the right balance is,
but we want to preserve this voice.
It's one question.
During my research, at some point during my PhD,
I was part of a training workshop
led by PhD students in product training of cells
with best practices in mind and also
to have a grassroots initiative, which
I think is a good example of what
works in a particular field.
Is this kind of stories of what works in a particular domain
would that be a thing interesting for this level?
So are stories that work in a particular domain
interesting for the dev room?
Well, for me, I think it totally is.
So the answer is yes.
And I think we've somehow done that.
But sometimes what it looks, once it's in the slides
and here, it looks different.
But that is very much the case.
I think we do not have a clear typology of the kind of talks
we accept.
One very clear kind is the tool talk.
I've done something, I show you that to you.
Another kind would be experiment feedback.
So I'm not going to show my tool.
But for instance, I have engaged with that open source stack.
And I've met issues.
I'm going to talk about that.
This is a little bit of that kind somehow.
Do you think it would be good to add the small track dedicated
to very short talks like lightning talks,
but dedicated to?
Repeat the question.
So a question like, would it be a good idea
to organize lightning, very short lightning talks
about open research?
So actually, we try to do that a little bit.
Like, the three last talks were lightning.
OK, lightning's 15 minutes.
But I think it's, yeah.
So we try.
Actually, so the format lightning or not
depends on the time we have.
And what the speaker wants.
So it basically is a tool.
If you don't know how it works, people
propose if they want a lightning talk or a normal talk.
And then so we can also ask them to expand or reduce
if we think it fits better.
So we try to negotiate.
But it's kind of unpredictable how many lightning talks
we're going to have.
So the proposals decide if there is enough for a tracker or not.
From the two last questions, there
is one thing that's very important that's emerging.
So the form of things should be in question.
And there is a sort of standardization associated
with a conference.
And as we receive talk, we perceive diversity,
even in the form and or experiences, tools, or maybe
talk.
We do have a classifications.
But seeing things here, it's sort of standardized.
And maybe we should work together,
so you're in this with us, on the form of things,
on maybe other forms of presentations.
We're not that constrained by the first them.
So that's one way we could work forward into.
But there are many things we could do.
And I am Todd.
I do have very much.
I am part of your special community.
And on the two side of the conference,
we have the same programs.
We have lots of developers who want to speak of their own.
And the new teams and the new stuff,
they have to do the program to have users who are speaking
of how they use the tools and use KADs around.
And it's very difficult. And it's pretty hard
to keep the academic.
We do have a colleague.
I asked her for a film.
And she put out her book.
And she put it here.
I asked her for the movie.
And I came here on the area.
She said, I don't speak.
I'm not a developer.
It's not the kind of meeting for me.
So maybe we can speak a little bit.
And she said, it's very open to everyone, not just the number.
And I don't have the answer.
the question in the comment was that in the,
Nicolas says that in the Joe special,
the dev room or community,
they also have this issue of having users come
because they don't feel welcome
or they don't feel like they fit.
So I want to give the mic to Maya
because Maya was first,
before she got in the committee for the room,
she was presenting a talk here two years ago, I think.
2020.
As a user, so now you are in.
So what would you give as an advice to those guys?
Don't be scared, they're really nice.
I understand your colleague perfectly,
especially coming from academia,
which is also my case.
Academia is extremely segmented
and we're taught to fear each other deeply.
And so it can be really scary
to push those boundaries a little bit.
It can also be very rewarding.
So you said she did come in 2020 or she didn't come?
Okay.
I tried two concurrency for them
and the one I organized and the...
Okay, so despite trying, there was no success yet.
Maybe if you show them this replay,
it will change everything.
I got a question for you,
which is, so one of our ideas or objective organizations
was also to bring folks from academia here at the first time
so that they can actually benefit
from the other conference in all the dev rooms.
So here's my questions like,
do you consider seeing talks in other dev rooms
and this one here, yourselves?
Can you raise your hand if you do?
Yeah, it's good.
Yes.
I'd like to.
Yeah.
So much, I think there is a lot of talk
in the dev room.
Yeah, yeah.
It's difficult to see all the talks that we want to see,
even though the offer is large.
But, and conversely, who is here now,
but who didn't come to the FOSDEM specifically for that?
Okay, raise your hands.
So it works also the other way around.
Okay.
Yeah, it's good.
Thank you.
Amazing.
Okay.
Is it time?
No, not yet.
So we still have 10 minutes.
Then we'll actually watch the stream here,
if you want to stay.
Just a quick question.
What is the acceptance rate here?
That's a very good question.
So the question is, what is the acceptance rate?
I don't know.
We haven't calculated it, but I think.
It's not a rate, but it hasn't happened.
I guess we...
I would say that there is a part of the papers
that are not good.
I mean, they're out of focus for the dev room.
And what we can do, actually,
we can reroute a paper to other dev rooms.
So it doesn't matter much.
But also some people just submit to multiple dev rooms
for the same speech, right?
So, and it's okay, right?
The boundaries are not super open.
There are kind of buggy proposals.
What we would consider not acceptable would be,
is that something that is clearly for someone else,
and we don't know why it's been submitted here,
or something that has just a title.
When that happened, we would kind of send an email.
Sometimes we don't even have an answer.
We don't know what happens.
So if you remove those,
the ones that we actually refuse,
I think is like one third, one quarter, maybe,
with not too much.
So we are always, it's been always working for us.
We need to have enough to fill the day,
if we want to have a full day.
But not too much that we have to refuse a lot of good talks.
But to be honest, we've been refusing good talks every year.
Just because there's not enough room.
So basically, we decide about the balance
when it's the case.
So we have like too many or not enough tool talks.
We will try to adjust this way.
I can remember that one kind of a talk
that we tend to reject are talks about tools
that have been developed somewhere in research,
but which is very specific.
In a very specific domain, without any abstract,
without any issues about what does open source side
of the thing actually change anything in the story.
So I mean, just a paper about the tool,
which is in research,
depends out of the quality of the abstract,
but yeah, it's not enough in a way.
Submitting is very, the abstract to submit is like,
so a few paragraphs long, so it's really easy to submit.
It's very easy to submit, please do. Yes?
I did write about the young receptionist organization.
So I was the first member of the Italian
and PhD student association.
Okay.
You mentioned they, maybe.
Good idea.
So the question is like, have we tried PhD associations,
a session of PhD students to email them,
to propose them to submit a talk?
No, we haven't.
And we are not very good at communication.
Well, I'm bad, but they are good.
Yep.
Yeah, I should say as an academic,
I feel, well, as an academic and a developer,
I feel like there is a tendency for academic labs
to have sort of a rotation of conferences that they present at.
And it typically is difficult to get added to that
as a new conference,
and especially if it's something that's sort of
outside of the norm.
And so it's something that I do think,
I think most of the time that's not sort of intentional.
It's just there's so much else going on,
people don't really think about it.
So I would second the suggestion of talking
to PhD student associations
if you're reaching out to universities,
especially universities that might have also to say,
hey, this is an opportunity for interdisciplinary work.
I'm going to do to talk to people who are more technical,
if you're less technical,
or people who are more in open disciplines,
because that sort of stuff is in vogue right now as well.
Interdisciplinary is very important right now.
Collaboration is very important right now.
So I think that once you're on the radar,
it's going to be easier to get people,
it's just getting on the radar.
So the comment was that actually,
it's not easy for labs members
to actually add one more communication conference
in the list of an already existing kind of standard
publication venue.
And above all, when this venue like here
is really not standard, I can't really speaking.
But actually, the interdisciplinary of this room
will be actually a good way to attract notably PhD students
and to make it clear for academia
what the space is basically.
I'm really curious about in the room
and whether anybody else in the room,
other than myself and the people that I know,
would identify as like UX designers,
not developers or academics.
Okay, so that's a very good question.
The question is like, who would in this room
define him or herself as a UX designer?
Can you raise your hand?
There's one there.
So not many, not many.
Are you trying to get the open design room?
The room?
We're doing research into how usable research
and design is to pick some sort of software
so we're trying to figure out like usability
and design and design to figure out.
Okay, cool.
Here, we're just going to open it
and using our designer brains to use events.
Okay, so the comment was, are you aware
that actually there is an open design dev room?
And so then says, yes, actually you co-organize it.
And actually this room is here tomorrow morning,
I think, afternoon, sorry.
And my personal comment on this is that
actually in my career and what I've done,
my experience, UX is very common stone
to go beyond the big, big issue of mixing
qualitative and quantitative approach on data
as my talk tried a little bit to explain.
And that yes, we need designers
and we have one here who talked about it
and in our previous lab, that was very important
so good to discover the mini-rat
is a very place where they try to do this mix.
Fair enough.
I think that, no, it's even less than.
Maybe you want to elaborate.
We should try to not overlap.
It's good this year, the years before
and it's annoying, I think we have kind of
the same public or partially.
So if we could, I don't know if we can do that,
we should ask at least there or whatever.
It's better if we can maintain it separate.
Oh yeah, not at the same time.
We can do that.
Actually we could also talk about what we do.
Right, one last comment is Mike,
if you want after the online session,
we can have drinks together in a place which is.
Tavarnier.
Tavarnier, Tavarnier.
It's close to here.
We are going to write that on the board, Tavarnier.
And I'm going to set up the stream here
so you can stay here and watch it with us if you want.
So it will be only, we are going to stream the video
and the interaction.
If you want to ask questions to the speakers,
you have to go through the chat room
on the first day website, right?
Thank you all.
Applause