So, thank you Paul, welcome everybody.
So we will today present to you the Cortex platform, which is open platform for research
in social sciences and it's a collective presentation where all the team is here but we have three
of us will be presenting today out of the team that you see on the picture.
So what is the Cortex?
It's an online platform built on top of an architecture and its main goal is to help
the social scientists with the research question to actually find the benefit of a computational
method to fit a specific question.
So it has been founded in 2009 and it's driven by social science research and supported by
several French national institutes at the beginning, in particular INRA and then later
on some funding, some research funding and some European project called RISIS, European
project of infrastructure.
We are now at our second version of this online platform called Cortex Manager, so this is
the part that you can actually go online.
It has been designed from the very beginning, as I said, for the social scientists.
So we took the point of departure was that the social scientist doesn't have any IT capabilities,
doesn't have any, on average, doesn't have any resource on the computer, especially 15
years ago.
So one of the main benefits of the platform would have to be empowering him with the power
of computing and of methods.
It's a collaborative platform so a lot of projects can be shared between scientists
and there is, is it a web interface connected to a workspace online?
You don't have to, of course, have it on your computer which was, again, quite new at the
time.
And it's very important that it's very permissive, so it's a bunch of methods that you can apply
on all kinds of data that we will detail later.
And this was one of the main foundations of our platform in the beginning, that all the
methods are runnable on all the viable that you have at your disposal.
So how is it going from 10, 10, 12 years after that?
So we have over 250 peer-reviewed publications that we are counting from now.
And of them 75 documents in 2022.
So it's growing and it's growing quite fast the last few years.
50K, so 50,000 analysis, so 50,000 jobs have been done on the platform by scientists last
year by over 1,000 active users, 400 institutions and in 50 countries, so it's pretty worldwide.
The team we have now in 2022.3 is consisted of eight technical persons, so engineers mainly,
two researchers, one trainee and two close collaborators in companies are independent.
Very important is located at University of Gustave Eiffel in Paris, near and the greater
Paris, so near Montla Valley.
So you have this island not far away.
And this infrastructure is composed of a classic web-oriented application and infrastructure.
So obviously we have the web interface that you can go to as a regular user that encloses
a lot of web services, so the main interface, but also an API that you can go and act upon
from outside.
So this allows us to open all our methods and services to external applications and
the specifically external projects that we are part of.
We are built on an infrastructure of servers that are hosted at Montla Valley, so in our
university, so everything is local.
We don't have anything hosted online, which is 300 CPU, 3.5 terabytes of RAM and 40 terabytes
of storage, which is big and not big at the same time nowadays, but it's enough for our
needs.
We have two main services that we are providing.
First is the storage of big database that we are collecting and curating, like for example
the patents, the European patents.
We have several other databases that we are putting inside some projects, so we can help
specific projects with this data that we have stored in the infrastructure.
The second part is the processing that we offer, so the method, the scientific methods
that I will talk about later, that are run inside of projects on the platform directly
by the researcher.
The researcher are actually actioning those methods directly from the web interface with
the parameters and their data.
We of course have this monitoring of the whole infrastructure, so it stays online.
Once you have an infrastructure, it has to do something for scientists, and that's the
goal of the platform.
How does it do and what does it do for science?
First, what?
This is the right part of the previous diagram.
We have a bunch of heterogeneous methods, so from scientific metrics, the study of publications,
scientific publications and tracks, natural language processing, so terms extraction,
name recognition and stuff like that, social network analysis, so the study of all the
interactions found inside publications and text in between actors, keywords, etc.
Stochastic block models, then I will end that.
Where is Ali?
Okay, somewhere in the room.
We'll talk to you about later.
Knowledge dynamics, so through time, the study of the knowledge through time, and the special
analysis, which is a big part of our infrastructure now, because we have geocoding, geolocating
inside publications, and geomapping from framework.
Okay, next will be, I will give Joéneu the mic to talk to you about how to cite cortex.
This is one of the big...
I will try to know.
Okay.
It's here.
Then as a cortex is a research software being used mainly by researchers, then supposed
to be cited, besides the fact that there is no yet strong culture of citing software properly
inside academic works, it's expected to be done.
Then according to that in 2022, we documented how cortex must be cited inside academic works.
And here we have just an example.
For example, if I am writing a paper and if I cite cortex, this is how cortex will be
hand-read at the end of the paper in the reference section, for example.
And with this, we can give, for example, the credit to the developers, like, for example,
Philip, Ali, and many others who is contributing with this software for a long time, and must
be recognized by this work academically speaking, then this is important, then that's what we
did.
And nowadays, we are lucky because a few years ago, we are missing the infrastructure to
how to define, how to document, and how to cite software.
And now we have, for example, the citation.cff, that is a citation file format.
It's been adopted a lot, and I think it will be the standard way to do it.
And on top of it, we have many tools.
Here is one example, CFF convert tool, where we can convert the CSCF file format, for example,
to bib.tech, to bib.l.tech, or to APA format, and many other formats.
Then we can keep all the metadata about the software important for citation in one single
file, and from this file, we can deliver it to many others, and it's really an easy way
to do it.
And then in Cortex, it's a solved problem, but we still have an issue, is about how to
identify permanently this object.
I say object as a digital object.
It's a software, but it's a digital object from the point of view of science.
And how we can identify it permanently, for example, for papers, we have a DOI, that is
very well known, and so it's very well for papers, PDF.
But for software, we have a problem to...
We can need to cite software in many different levels of granularity, for example.
We can cite the software, just the software name, or a specific version of the software,
or a specific line of a specific file inside the source code of the software.
And this is still an open question, because, for example, we have a proposition from the
community to solve it, but there is no one single kind of permanent ID that covers out
the levels of granularity, for example.
We have the proposition from the software heritage project, that it's the suite, the
software heritage ID, that we can use it to cite software in the very specific code fragment
to the snapshot of the full source code.
But for example, we can't use software ID to cite software in a high level, like the
software version of only this project name.
For that, we should use another kind of ID.
That's it.
And it's an open question that we should work on this year or next year.
Then that's it.
So it's the time for a new one.
I don't know if you will.
So one question we've been asking ourselves is how to open the platform fully.
What did we do to do that until now, and what to do in the future?
So there is no platform, web platform, without free open source software today.
And we are using a lot already.
And I just put some of them on this page.
You can see here from any layer of the infrastructure, from the virtual machine, the containers,
the scripts, the operating systems, et cetera, et cetera, until the actual methods and the
interface that you produce to the user.
We are using free and open source software, or at least open source software, because
I don't want to start a debate here.
But that's the general idea.
Now this is not Cortex producing that.
Cortex is wrapping around this open source software.
And it's open access for now.
So it's free and open to everybody to use as an interface.
But the code is not entirely free.
We've been trying to do that a little bit more than the last few years.
Hopefully in the next few years even more.
And Ale will talk to you about how to do that and what are the challenges to actually produce
a good open source software and methods.
Hello, everybody.
I'm Ale.
I work with the guys and go within Cortex.
So this is not really a talk about Cortex.
I'm not going to do a demo or something.
We thought of this talk as a moment to discuss what's going on with us, what is going on
in the platform.
Because up to now, like Philippe just explained, everybody can come and use.
But most of the software in Cortex has been developed without, well, with open source
in mind, but not in practice.
For practical reasons.
So are we missing one slide?
No.
So everything from the methods, the interfaces, the back ends, everything has.
So even our documentation is on WordPress or Q&A also.
So everything is based on open source.
But up to now we didn't have real open source practices.
So how are we managing this transition from a project that is very aligned with open source
community but that doesn't manage to do open source to start doing open source?
So there was really a big part was just getting even more open source into this project.
So starting to use project management tools that we were using, some of them, but not
as much, not as systematically.
So this is a real common problem with research software.
They don't always have the effects to go into GitLab or GitHub or wherever and use issues
and use dashboards and project management, sometimes not even a thing in their head.
And that's kind of the background that we were facing, years and years of researchers
developing stuff, using open source software, but using version control because, well, it
was still the infrastructure guys really needed that to work with, but it was really like
the bare minimum.
So how do you start to get people more involved?
So we just, the first step was really pushing everybody to start using the usual tools,
and sometimes force moving some projects and moving the discussion into issues on GitLab
and all that.
And then, also adopting for discussions more open source software like Matrix.
So it's like, I don't know if anybody knows Matrix here, maybe today everybody already
knows Matrix.
It wasn't really a given last year.
And then once we had adopted the general workflow, most of the projects were still private, but
they had the workflow of an open source project.
So it helped get people into a better mindset.
And the people who would arrive and start working with us would more easily recognize
the pattern of working with open source.
Then because we had this system that runs the jobs and everything, and the old scripts,
they would just use the structure that was in the system directly, and it was pretty
hard to adapt and evolve them.
Then we developed some kind of intermediate library so that it gets easier to, so making
it easier to develop new methods in the platform.
So we had to develop this intermediate.
I won't have time to go into show the details, but just getting the idea that we have to
get people into the workflow, develop libraries and interfaces and intermediate layers that
help and automate some of the processes, give people more freedom to work.
We also started integrating containers in the job manager and everything so that we
could have done with this intermediate layer so that people could have more freedom to
make it easier for them to keep doing their non-standard, non-advisable, non-best practices
stuff.
But that works for them because their researchers are not coders.
They're not always coders.
And finally, and even for the people in the team that are more skilled programmers, of
course they want to have the possibility to do all this stuff.
And finally, one thing that's very important is at the management level, because this is
like a kind of already intermediate, kind of big-ish thing where we have hundreds of
users every month, blah, blah, blah.
So we had to discuss this in the strategic planning so that our institutional partners
could get it.
So basically, just get it everywhere as soon as possible and then start.
Once you can show some of the benefits, we also work at the institutional level.
So these are some of the challenges.
Because part of the team didn't have the know-how, part of the researchers we work with, people
have limited resources, they have priorities.
And I'm just reading out of there, but that's it.
It's not very surprising.
There's this learning curve of open source and everything.
And there's always doubts about why is this going to lead us.
There's licensing doubts.
So there's part of, like, next thing I'm going to quickly show is that we're starting to
open up stuff.
And there's lots of stuff that hasn't been opened yet simply because somewhere, we know
that somewhere in some file somebody used an extract from a software library that is
not clearly documented where it has been used and we need to find it and check if the license
is compatible.
So yeah.
And so we're always like, okay, where are we going?
But getting things to as close as possible on every dimension is what's keeping us moving.
Just keeping the feeling that something is moving even if we're not seeing everything.
But then we, well, through this effort eventually we managed to open source already a good part
of the, specifically the science part.
So the infrastructure, the dashboard, the interfaces, the front end of the web application
and the job managing part, all those parts not necessarily, it's taking longer because
has been like, it's also another part of the infrastructure.
But the main, most important short term part is to let the scientific part of it be available.
So here's just some examples.
I'm not going to, but yeah.
So there's two parsers, an importer for a big database of scientific publications, a
kind of generic parser that we use for, we're in the sociology of science lab.
So even though the tools are more like general humanities and social sciences, we have a
lot of interesting things that come from PubMed, data that comes from PubMed and similar databases.
So this is like also a parser for that.
And here's one example of a project that's in progress because even though we reworked
the project, parts of it still use libraries that we're not sure, so we have to check,
take the time to check if we need to change anything or replace.
Let's quickly show what some, some, one of these things look like.
Well, this is just a repository for one of the projects.
I have the source code, some documentation, blah, blah, blah.
It makes pretty graphs and you have to use it like this, like this.
So just getting, getting things into what we all know about, what you know as an open
source format, how do I go back to the, to the presentation?
F, no, no.
There you go.
What else there's to say?
That's it.
So thank you.
I think, I mean, if you, if you, if you're experiencing, I don't know, if you, if you,
any of you work in a similar institution where open source is not an evidence, but it's something
that you have to struggle with.
We're very happy to exchange after, during or after the conference.
Did you skip the, ah, no, no, no.
You have no more time.
Thank you.
Any questions next?
Question next.
Yep.
Thank you a lot.
I like your time because there is a lot of nice teachers and you just said that you have
a
lot of time.
Yeah.
So, yeah, so the question was, what, what was preventing us to opening it from the beginning
and to make open source software from the beginning?
So as, as Ali was saying, the first thing I think is just the lack of no-hold, especially
15 years ago when we started.
The second thing I would say is that we, we basically didn't have a precise idea of what
we were building.
We just went basically script by script, project by project.
And this, this is how we built slowly the platform.
Then it became a platform, proper platform, I mean, with the, with the resources and everything.
And then, then it was already used and, and we trained people on those methods already.
So the problem of opening, of doing open source software is you have to think about it from
the beginning or at least refactor enough the, the, the code.
So it's, it's, it has no problem of, of license and stuff like that.
So this is, this is just, you know, an ongoing streak.
Yeah.
I speak loud.
Sorry.
I can't, I can't hear you.
Yeah, it's about, yeah, some, some people upload software to Zenodo or upload a documentation
or that's, that creates one kind of identifier, which you could also make a, some people just
make a publication related to the software so people can cite a DOI.
Zenodo is going to give a DOI, so it's the same, pretty much the same thing.
The problem is, I think, like, Jania was explaining is that sometimes you need, want to cite a
specific version of the software or a specific file in a specific version, or you want to
cite the software without mentioning a specific version.
And, and you don't want to upload one version to Zenodo for every possible thing.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, I, I don't know exactly deep what Zenodo offer, but I know that Zenodo
offers a way to manage a many different kind of digital objects, data, images, software,
etc. and not only Zenodo.
In our case, what is missing is to study all the options to see which fits better in, in,
in our case, you know, is more to, to understand because in fact, inside the, the, the software
engineering community discussing this topic is still an open question, exactly how to
do it.
And when we, we search about this topic, it's quite difficult to find tutorials or someone
teaching you how to, what kind of permanent indentifier you should use, for example, software
heritage ID, for example, here is an example of the type of persistent indentifier that
named as intrinsic persistent indentifier.
What means it doesn't, doesn't depend on, on a service, has history where you need to
ask a new ID to first to use it.
It's like a hash, a hash ID of a commit is this kind of a, interesting key, a, a, a,
persistent indentifier that we can generate by the source code itself.
Another option is to use maybe Zenodo or maybe any other thing to generate a DUI.
Then for that we are, we are gonna ask to the hazard, the, the DUI server to generate
a DUI for us.
Then we have many options.
We don't know yet, deep and maybe Zenodo could be really interesting.
I would be happy to, to learn with you, your experience because it's a lot of thing to,
to learn.
Sorry.
Okay, thanks everybody for stopping here.
Thank you.
cat