Okay, hi everyone. Thank you for being here and thank you for the invitation. I'm going
to speak maybe in a less technical way, in more realistic way of the thing I am trying
to do for the last year. I'm Émio Anschulze. I'm a postdoctoral researcher in sociology
of science and health in France, both in Medialab and in the SES team in Marseille. I'm going
to say something about the way we are doing scientific programming in Python in social
sciences and the way we can improve it. I gave this presentation a provocative title
that is so wide to speak about what are the specifics of social sciences and how can we
improve all this kind of environment, make computing and data analysis in relation directly
to open science. So, yes, it's kind of humble presentation. If I want to summary it in one
sentence, my point is to say that social sciences need more scientific programming. And it is
three points. First, that scientific programming has, I think, the right flexibility to equip
the very diverse practices that exist right now in social sciences. For the moment, we
have the landscape, especially in France, with main based on the air language and Python
could benefit of some impulse and I think he needs it. And the gateway will be to develop
very specific disciplinary packages that are still missing for Python in social sciences,
which I can call disciplinary API for the language and to move beyond open source treatment.
So, just a quick disclosure. I've been trained physics, but I moved in sociology and now
I'm speaking as sociologist or social scientist here. I'm trying to give some feedback of
what we are using in our community and I'm trying to answer two questions in one which
are not very well delineated, which is first, how to improve Python in social sciences and
in a more general way, what are the different uses of scientific programming right now because
we don't have a very clear look of what's going on in all the different ways we can
use scientific programming. So, it's a work in progress, so it's mainly to make an exchange
with you. To be clear about my title, I'm not saying that we are under equipped in a
pejorative way. Social sciences have a well established open source software platform
and some of them are going to be presented today and usually give a warm welcome to new
strategies for data analysis and its own field work are expanding to numeric and software
data. So, we are using and studying all those software tools and open source tools, but
it is a general point of view from sociologists. We have in general a low tech practice and
we are using software applications programming for very discrete, meaning punctual or kind
of unseen operations and if you want to have a look, there is a very nice article from
Caroline Muller, Fredrik Laver, about how historians are changing their practices and
putting some more numerical analysis inside their work, but still conserving the global
way of doing their work. So, we need flexibility to adapt to individualized practices or topics
which are very personal to research. So, I need to say a word about the specificity
of social sciences because I don't think we are very numerous today. There are a variety
of disciplines, this very different way of dealing with data and analyzing archives and
interviews and within each disciplines there is a huge variety of methodologies, school
of arts, theoretical approaches and from an organizational point of view there is a very
weak functional dependency between all the researchers in our different fields and moreover
there are very important national specificities and moreover each research, each research
trend is very conceptually laden, meaning that there is very important given to the
trend that each researcher is using to collect data and to analyzing it. There are no global
rules of how to do it. So, there is a very huge limit of one size fits all instruments
in our disciplines and besides there are very harsh critics against standardization and
normalization because it is seen as a way to erase plurality which is some kind of base
of what are social sciences. So, there is a huge fight between individualization and
standardization of practices. Nevertheless, shared instruments are important especially
software instruments and science studies which is a field of sociology and topology of science
are shown the crucial role of instruments for the functioning of scientific communities.
It is very important for conceptual changes because it allows us to look at other stuff
at different scales, at different topology like the microscopes change the way we are
doing biology. They are very important for disciplinary identity, the way we present
ourselves in our research communities and how we define our activity and they are very
important for coordination between specialties and standardization of practices beyond a
small group of researchers and to transfer surgical agencies and meteorological changes.
And there is a lot of studies about how electron microscopes change biophysics has to put second
cell for change medicines and the way we are dealing with data but there are very few studies
on the way software is changing and standardizing practices especially for social sciences.
That has a value, social sciences are kind of divided regarding standardization especially
imposed standardization because it usually reflects some kind of relationship or one
specific kind of thought which try to impose its way of doing things against others especially
in sociology or political sciences. So there is a goal of to define what is a good scale
of creating software instruments for social sciences. Scientific programming is what I
want to say today is a solution which both favor new, the Raman new scientific instruments
within the specialties and to improve some kind of second hard generation standardization
by using the same way of doing scientific programming and it's a good entry point for
new open source practices which are not existing or very little existing within social sciences
like those linked to as we've just seen other open science, reproducibility and collaboration
beyond the small disciplines which compose social sciences and to import new cool stuff
like coming from the computer science, AI stuff and machine learning. Nevertheless for
the moment scientific programming as a global frame is not very common in social sciences.
Of course there are always cool kids so there are people doing it and computational social
sciences are the thing and expand very quickly in our field but for the common people it
is not very developed and we have a lot of users of air which has an intermediate status
between a programming language and a statistical language which kind of dual status. What I
mean as scientific programming so very quick but it's a diversity of practices they have
in common the fact that it's interactivity, exploratory and based on packages and the
priority is given to usefulness for researchers to explore certain questions they want to
address and all the questions just we have seen are not the primary aim of the researchers
who are using scientific programming so stability, design and also very important question of
software development are not what is in the first front of the uses of scientific programming
but when you are looking at what researchers are doing, they are doing different one of
the steps of the different scale and they are not all of them developing and creating
new packages so the diversity of practices were existing. If you look on what are currently
the software uses for researchers in social sciences so it's a kind of a exploratory mapping
because it comes from non-representative survey conducted by Mariana Iglebechik in France
in a study called State of Open Science Practices in France and we ask for researchers in different
field what kind of tools are using their research and they can answer different for producing
data, analyzing data so just a small network of all the tools that researchers are saying
they are using for social sciences and humanities also and if you look to this huge diversity
what just the main result as there is a diversity of software and profile of researchers nothing
new about that you will find the centrality of standard office software like Word, Calc,
LibreOffice etc. and the main scientific programming language used is air with 22% of users that
are using it and then a geographical software QG 10% for SPSS which is a statistical software
and only 6% using Python in this broad field of social science community and if you look
just to the quotation the reality of the work is usually just using at some point some software
and there is no global glue of open source tools in the workflow of the researchers. So even when
you look at the small part of the social scientist who are doing quantitative analysis so it's a sub
part of it there are also a huge diversity, diverse tools, divisions so we are looking to a very
very fragmented communities and there is a need to create some glue between them. What you can say
that 22% of researchers once saw the survey said they are using air as a statistical and scientific
programming language and the observation is important because air developed for good reason
for social sciences. It developed because there is an afflicted affinity between the diversity
of practices existing and the flexibility of the tools that air allows that allows to develop very
specific packages which can continue the work of small communities. You probably all know about
air, it's a script-oriented language. You can build very quickly small packages with data about a
specific research project and there is a lot of support from the French community with there is a
lot of packages in French for instance. But this leads to limits. It creates a huge diversity of
types of package. Some of them are not very easy to understand. Some of them are not very well
documented and there are functions that exist only in air which creates some kind of, we increase
the diversity of tools social sciences community are using. Depending on what packages you look
like there is a very low documentation and very low standardization of the code and there is still
this ambiguity between what is the statistical languages and what is the programming language.
For the main topic of what I want to say, what is the state of the Python uses in social sciences?
Let's say there are not a lot of people using it. There are more and more human researchers
interested to leverage machine learning in their research. So they are coming to Python to try to
understand how they can use it in their research. But for the moment it's difficult to get to realize
the basic steps of social scientists work in Python. So it means all the tools that we are using
on a daily basis like making logistic regression with a clear presentation of the results. And we
need what I want to say, dedicated community packages as a middle ground for researchers to
access friendship programming and then being perceived aware of all the open source and open
science practices they can add in their research. So for that there is a need to go beyond application
development itself and beyond one specific package. It's a whole process to implement.
Just what are the expected positive benefits of Python broad adoption? Just a small snippet. It
will enhance scientific programming practices especially with the importation of the whole
ecosystem of Python, especially notebooks. They have the potential flexibility and they will allow
to create common language with other communities especially computer sciences. The question is
still we in the social sciences have already aired as a main language. What's the future of
the collaboration between the student language? Reject the idea to develop Python to advocate
the polyglotism between and Python or start a transition with Python. In France we decided to
teach Python as a first language for students in high school. So maybe there is a change going on
on what kind of languages students are going to practice in the future. So it creates a shared
language. It's a leap of faith to decide what kind of tools we will need. Mine here is the Python but
I'm here to speak about the place of a central programming. So both of them are going to be
together. I just want to say a word about what I'm trying to do in France for social sciences,
especially in sociology, to enable this practice of Python and this kind of by social humanities
social and science package. I need to achieve a double constraint first to achieve some
standardization because we need some shared tools to be able to work together especially to train
students and to create collaboration projects. But we can't sacrifice our disciplinary and
subdisciplinary specificities so we need to find the good level of flexibility. It's a four-step
process. Nothing very new and it's very common I guess in every development of packages and tools.
The first one is to identify what kind of practices can be called co-assist standard even
if they are not completely standard. The second step is to build easy to use packages. I can
find place in the specific workflow. The third one is to prove it can be useful because there
is no way to create something. There is no proof that it makes some positive advantage in research
processes and then the first step is to train colleagues and develop practices. Step one, to
uncover standard practices and we need to and I'm speaking about social science to understand better
what is a common sense of our daily job. For instance not all social scientists are doing
machine learning or statistics but a lot of them still do it a bit especially basic statistics.
So there are some co-assist standard operations for instance for survey, analyzing surveys with
questionnaire and samples. So we need more like descriptive statistics for survey, different
tools for transformation of file formats to generate and modify tables to create
intermediate documents and to produce visualizations the way we use it in our work. For instance,
France we are using a lot of work from Bordeaux, Pierre Bordeaux, sociology and he has very specific
way to present the result of factorial analysis and you can find it in the Python universe. So
you need to start to work with those existing workflow to build more adoption. The second step
is to facilitate the disciplinary use and nitride a small package which is in French and it's the
choice to be able to be close to students and researchers who don't usually use Python to be
a one-liner which is the first step to use some kind of easy tools to move quicker to results close
to the common sense in the way tables are organized and based to facilitate the complete workflow from
the data to some results that can be published or presented to students and it's based on the
basic packages of the Python communities like Bordeaux so it allows to move swiftly from one
specific disciplinary package to the more general practices. The third step is to show the usefulness
of both Python and this specific package and for that there is a need of public demonstration in
context. No research tools can be used will be used if it's not direct advantage to use it for
research and doing stuff. So notebooks are kind of perfect vector to prove and display some,
I can see the figures in this, yes it can be derived polarizing but it's a good way to present
a complete state of research and we developed with the collaboration between Humanoon which is
platform for software and data analysis in French and a cooperative detective ist, five notebooks
for machine learning as a starting point to show how Python can be used like from the beginning to
the end to analyze a survey and the survey we just discussed before about the state of practice
of open source science in France. And the fourth step is a very important step is to train
colleagues and students so you just can put something out there in the world so the tools
need to find the place in research workflow so there is some kind of translation to the tools,
to the practices and we are doing it in different steps, writing books and academic examples
to stabilize a sharp practice in France. I am interviewing laboratories to show how its
usefulness to use some Python even if you don't, my colleagues don't usually do a central programming
to train more new students especially PhD candidates to those new approaches and all the
world around Python like Git and using Git Hub or Git Lab and creating spaces to discuss
our specific practices which for the moment doesn't exist. I will conclude just
from very quick computer ideas. My point today is to say that
central programming especially in Python but not specific in Python is a third way that between
the use of application which is the daily basis of a lot of social sciences especially in sociology
and not using at all code which is also as the daily basis of a lot of qualitative researchers
in social sciences. In scientific programming we allow to promote the productivity and open
source practices because it is the gate to all the practices from the open source communities
and we promote inter-disciplinarity collaboration with colleagues outside the scope of sociology
for instance. Nevertheless, we need to excavate and make this process of understanding what are
standard practices that can be standardized at some point to find early users and creating
code developers that can come along with this work of reflectivity and to demonstrate more
the concrete efficiency of those tools. The limits are the focus on disciplinary specificities
is also drawbacks because it can increase the expression from libraries and it's something
which is real and maybe there are better languages to promote than Python or IR to do that.
But I started with Python. So thank you for listening to me and it's my message.
Thank you. If you could take questions please do repeat the following for the stream. Thanks.
So in recent years we have a lot of conference that one special track for tools and one is
request or kind of a stamp on the paper that the paper is so it comes with a software repository
where you can rerun the experiment. Do you think that will be helpful also to propose
this on social sites? The question is that there is a lot of problems in similar problems
going on in social sciences and even the possibility to make a paper is not here right now in the
social science communities because the logic of central programming is the logic of automatizing
steps and not using directly excel to make that analysis is not yet here in the basic practices
of our communities. Some of my colleagues are doing it but there are very few that are usually
kind of the youngest one. So what I'm saying that is not so clear in what I said is we need to
use more what has been developed from computer sciences and to try to find a way, a gate to
import them at some point in our practices. So to look more what's good to understand what's
going on in computer science we need also a better culture what are all those tools and
it's still not here. Thanks.
So I was trying to set up tutorials
that's important for social science people. This is my presentation actually for those people
who are going to learn these things they're going to learn the new social science. For people who
are not going to learn them not going to learn anything. So this is not very helpful in my own
property architecture experience. Okay a question is that there is a division between people who
wants to train to those tools and those who doesn't want. The fact is we are more and more
working projects in cryptography and the basic culture of what's going on what's possible to do
is something we need to share to everyone. Otherwise our new division which are going to
exist and to reproduce. So I'm quite sure that that's why I've put this kind of very small
diagram first. Semi-programming can start with reading a script and a single language not
policing it by yourself and it is those steps that I think are useful for everyone so global
computer literacy for social scientists even if they don't want to move to other
more advanced tools. But this one is in theory for instance working on project with statisticians
that people were doing scrapping for data to know what is possible to do. Thanks.
You you you speak about the software cap and trees.
They have a section dedicated for social science.
They have a specific context for specific fields like social science and
recently social science and maybe they are totally totally driving everything is open source the workshops material is open and everyone can collaborate with integration at a structure it creates a
yeah a job for you. Yeah of course for the question it is they are already a very
important intensive existing the cap and trees especially in different disciplines. For what I
know in France there are very little visible in social sciences so I use the content they create
they are creating but for what I can see very far from the daily questions social scientists are
having in the daily analysis and there is still you know transition to make and I can I agree
completely with what you said there is a need to make this the jointer but it's a working process
and I will try to contact find someone who wants to do it with me at some point but I've been
trained at some point for software cap and tree but I never completed my training but yes I'm aware of that thank you.
You're right. I have no data about why and sorry for the question the question is how
how much do we know why people are using specific software tools in social sciences. My answer is
and it's with my heart of social scientists interested in science is that I know very little
work studying how researchers are using software and tools there are some work starting to be
developed but I have no answer for instance for air exists because statisticians used it a lot and
so it has been touched in sociological sources and then students became researchers and now
they're using in France so there is an historical past dependency on the specific kind of use but
I'm quite sure it's a huge avenue for research thank you.
I'm quite sure you're right the question is then is how people change
from one software to another and this is the unresolved question so thank you.
Thank you.
Here you go you can put that in your pocket.
Yes wherever you want.