So, good morning everyone. I am Adrian, a PhD candidate from Laijian University in the
Netherlands and I'm going to today, I'm going to talk about my project or my software, so
called Red Defense Station, which is a weird thing, an interstellar social simulation framework
and a turn-based strategy game as well. And I hope this can be an interesting start of
today's schedule. So, before I go into the details of my thingy, I would like to do a
bit of self-introduction because it relates to my overall open source development experience.
And I was educated in physics, I did my graduate in physics, I did some master's research on
so-called gravitational waves and their delightful collaboration. And I must say, like before
my master's research, I was a kind of mathematical student, I didn't really like computer, I
liked pen and papers more. But my research forced me to appreciate computer because I
was forced to do things like supercomputers, Linux, terminals and writing programming language,
programming like C or Python. So, I started to appreciate software or open source software
in general, so that's why I get into this world. And after my master, I decided to kind
of switch my field to do something social science, so that's why I came to Lydie University
to do something called quantitative science study. And I'm supposed to work on social
modeling simulation or data analysis on some kind of social data, or actually more specifically
for academic system. And as a hobby, I kept contributing to open source software because
I think it's fun to work on just the software and you find something wrong and you just
submit a PR or a great issue for that. And I learned a lot from that kind of process.
And then, because I started my PhD right before the pandemic, as you can imagine, things went
quite wrong because I partially blamed the pandemic because, for example, the data that
I'm supposed to use is still not ready even now. And the whole collaboration became mass,
the infrastructure is mass. So, I partially also blamed the engineer in my collaboration
because they are so annoying to work with. So, I have to rescue my PhD, right? I can't
wait for the things to happen. So, I need something to work it out. I can work it out
by myself because it's pandemic, so I have to work from home. And I was also traumatized
by the collaboration that I experienced. And I know something about physics because of
a background. I know something about social modeling. And I'm also kind of familiar with
software engineering. I'm not trained in that field, but I learned a lot from my hobby.
So, it is natural for me to try to combine these things together to create something
for a weird thing, interstellar social simulation. And perhaps some of you guys are a fan of
science fiction, movies, or games. And you may ask these kind of big questions like,
will human civilization become interstellar one day in the future? Or does alien exist
or not? And if they exist, or if we become interstellar, we will be curious about what
is the form of society of those interstellar civilizations, right? And of course, it's
very hard to study those kind of things rigorously in academic settings. But perhaps one way,
at least I claim, I argue that one way to try to explore this is to assume that some
social theory we know nowadays can still be a good approximation for that kind of society,
like perhaps we expect that they should also be utility seeking, or there are some collective
actions there. And of course, we can't study that rigorously because we don't have the
data or we don't have the observations, but we can try to explore this kind of domain
by simulation. And in case if you're not familiar with social modeling or like...
No, no, no. Please.
Sorry. So, in case if you're not familiar with social modeling, nowadays when people
talk about social simulation, it's made maturity like they're talking about agent-based modeling.
So social scientists design some behavior rules based on the understanding of how human
works are based on some experiments to design computational rule for agents, and they put
the agents into a world just like machine learning people do, and to see how they interact
with each other and interpret the overall simulation outcome from that. And there are
many existing framework that can help us to do this kind of simulation, but I have to
create my own framework because for social simulation, for existing social simulation
framework, they don't support the physics well. I mean, because we have been working
on like in the status society, and it is a scale that is not on the earth, so it's not
easy to deal with, it's possible, but it's not trivial. And there are also some kind
of physics simulation framework out there as well, but they are not built for social
scientists, so it's also a bit hard to work with. So that's why I have to create my own
framework. I think it's interesting and useful if I want to create something meaningful for
this thing. And when I talk about the physics for interstellar society, I am talking about
special relativity, which is simple undergraduate level physics, because it is sufficient when
we consider a scale like 100 light years, 10s or 10s of light years, I think it's a
good starting point of trying to imagine about this kind of thing. And special relativity
tells us that there is an intrinsic time delay out there, so everything cannot travel faster
than the speed of light. And also, special relativity tells us that there is a time-direction
effect, so if you move very fast, close to the speed of light, you are close to the speed
of light, so experience the slower time, essentially. And in the setting of social simulation, we
have to deal with problems like what can you see or what can an agent see, and how agents
interact with other agents because of time delay, and how we change the state of the
light. I will go into this one by one in the following slides. Because of the time delay,
information travels at the speed of light, so we are not seeing each other instantaneously.
We are seeing the path of each other because of the delay. So here, the red people here
see the path of the blue agents of people because they have time delay, and it depends
on the distance. And technically, they see the path light comb of the universe at that point.
The second problem is how the agents interact with each other. I mean, if you're a programmer,
you're probably familiar with the command design pattern, and this is used for dealing with,
if you have something you might execute, but if you have a delay, then you have to create a command,
wait for a delay, and send it to your target. This is what I used in this framework, so that
some agents need to interact with each other. They can't just do that directly. They have to
send the command and the command travels at the speed of light in the universe. And lastly,
the last problem, how we change the state of the agents. We defined here a mechanism,
which is essentially dynamics of the model. It changed the state of the agents and sent commands
out, so I defined how the model actually works scientifically. And recall that because clock takes
the order for moving agents, so I define this into two types of mechanism. A regular mechanism
executes a process once per turn, and a direct mechanism process once per end turn, because
the end depends on the speed, because if it is moving faster, then some time is lower there,
so the execution is lower there. So for convenience, if you model your things based on these two types
of mechanism, then it's easier to follow the physics. And as an example, regular mechanism
could be something like you observe things and update your information, and it's not something
that it actually takes time, so it can be executed once per turn. And for dialectic mechanism,
it can be something like manufacturing. It actually takes time to produce some product
and to make it and send it out. So if you have a slower time, then you manufacture that.
So to deal with these kind of problems, as I said, I created framework, and the framework is written
in Kotlin. There are many reasons behind that. I'm not going to give you that. And basically,
the framework enforces a specific way to model your social model, so that it can automatically
account for the physics. And it also provides some functionalities to help you to develop the
so-called in-depth data social model. And it deals with some technical support like
parallelization of the simulation, and how do you serialize things into data, or how do you make
deterministic simulation using under parallel process. And this is the core of the framework,
and you can check my archive. Rupina actually is going to be a proceeding for some other conference
and for the algorithmic details and for the mathematics details.
You can find it in the last slide. Anyway, I was not a very experienced programmer when I started
this project, so I made some decision that perhaps I would change if I do it in another way.
It started for now. Anyway, I made some decision here on how we should use this framework. For
example, I decided that this should be used as a- OK. OK, here it works. So there are some
technical reasons behind why I made this decision, because I think it's always easier to provide
libraries for people to use that. Because the reason behind it is that I tried to keep it in a
pure Kotlin project, and it is not possible to do things like deserializing string into objects,
because the diffraction library of Kotlin is not very powerful. And anyway, this is the decision
I made. I may change in the future, but it's how it's now working. And to use this, you have to
create a template using the source code and build your model based on the template.
I have created a few effect samples on how to use this framework. I will do a very brief
illustration on the results, because it's always interesting to see how things actually
work out. So the first example is the Flocking model, which is the standard of the 101
HMA modeling. It is a very simple model. The bird follows a very simple alignment bruise, and they
align with each other, and it creates some interesting microscopic pattern
as shown in the figure. And here, we are interested in Intestila Flock. I mean,
it's a very hypothetical scenario, but it is kind of a group of spaceships, and they try to align
with each other in the universe, or some kind of mysterious creature living in space. And I
assume, for the sake of physical realism, I assume they are propelled by some kind of
proton rocket, and we can measure how well the Flock align. And this is the simulation result.
I'm also not going into details of this young thing, but you can see some interesting things,
like if you can adjust the speed of light because it is a simulation, and if the speed of light is
lower, then it takes more time, it takes longer to communicate, and they're less well-ordered.
And you can also tune the perturbation on the Flock, and so it takes more, it's harder to align
with each other, and it takes more energy to do so. And you can see in the figure on the left-hand
side, or in the right-hand side in alignment, then it takes half the mass of the population
to align with each other for one year, for one turn. So it's not a very
environmental-friendly way of traveling, I would say.
And the second example is some kind of knowledge dynamics, which is closer to what I'm supposed
to do in my PhD. So we study how, I try to model how research or knowledge is generated
in the interstellar setting, and there are some assumptions that are made, like cooperation takes
time to, we need cooperation to stimulate innovation, but cooperation takes time to
process, right? You have to invite people to cooperate with you, and you have to wait for
the response, and if it is very far away, then it takes a long time to work with people.
So this thing is affected by the time delay. And also there are some other factors, like
if there's a small time delay, and so you have a more rapid information exchange, then it
essentially creates a more competitive environment, because when I do something and you want to
compete with me, and you update the information very frequently, then it creates a kind of stress
to work your research out. And also, like research, the next time, it is a dilated mechanism,
it is affected by the time delay if you want to move. So there's a cause if you want to move
closer to each other to do research, or there's a cause if you want to move from your home country
to this place to work with each other. So this is also some kind of simulation results.
I would say it's kind of interesting. So if the, you can also tune the speed of light,
and as you see in the figure on the left-hand side, the blue curve
was lower at the beginning, and it becomes higher eventually. It is because like, this is a curve
when you have a very slow information travel. So if you have, because the innovation,
or the cooperation started very slowly at the very beginning, so it rises very slowly,
but at the finals, ultimately, because it is less competitive than the overall results,
overall research outcome becomes better eventually. I think it's interesting results.
And the figure on the right-hand side shows that there are two kinds of strategies, right? You can
stay in your home country and do all the things remotely, or you can move the conference
physically to work with each other. And the orange curve represents the moving strategy,
and the blue curve represents the remote strategy. Because the move, there's a cause
imposed by speech-related fitting, because there's time generation. So it starts out lower,
and then eventually pays off in the future. So I think it's an interesting result to
show off here. And I mean, this is kind of interesting, but you can always criticize
about this kind of model, because this two hypothetical, I mean, we're studying something
that is not happening in the real world, and perhaps we are getting nothing out of that.
I kind of agree with the kind of criticism, but I'm just trying to get something out of
the framework. And if people are not interested in this kind of model, or I also feel like this
is not interesting enough, and then I made the decision that perhaps I can make a game out of
this to make it more interesting. And the reason why I decided to make a game is also because I
like simulation game, and simulation game is kind of similar to modeling or
simulation, or HMA modeling in a sense. And also, I have many things I want to test out. I mean,
the model that I have presented are kind of simple models, but they are more complicated
mechanisms that you can implement, but you can't do this for a regular state, because they are
so complex, you can't get anything adequate or interpretable from those ideas. So a game provides
an environment for me to test things out and to just explore what I can do in a statistical model.
And also, perhaps this is one of the sensible ways to get something actually useful from the
framework. I mean, it's not very academically interesting, at least I have a game for that.
Right. So the game. And for a game, it can be very complex, and I try to address many,
many different things in the game. And I try to ask very great question. And for example,
we can try to ask, how should the economy looks like in the international society? Does
private-based economy work? Because nowadays, we're relying on currency, credit card, but those
kind of currency relies on some fundamental building blocks of the society, which might not
work in an interstellar setting, because the time delay, how do you exchange money, and how do you
define the exchange rate? I mean, perhaps a simple bottom economy that we use historically is a better
choice for those kinds of society. And perhaps we can use some kind of fuel or energy as the
money instead of credit card. And also, we can ask how the political system work. Does democracy
work there? Because how do you folk, if you have to wait for 100 years for it to receive the
floating results from the other planet? And also, we can also ask how we can optimize
the research in this kind of system. So I have my own ideas on how these things work.
So I put all the things into the game, including population dynamics, politics,
diplomacy, economics, warfare, scientific technology. I mean, some of them are typical
elements in strategy games, and some of them are not that typical, but I still get inspired from
some other games. And I try to get this to work on PC and Android, because that's one of the reasons
why I choose Kotlin to implement this kind of thing. And I hope this can be a multi-player game
in the future or like now. So I implemented some kind of server-kind architecture. And for a game,
for a game, you have to limit how a human can can or how a client can connect, because you can't
allow them to do everything that they are going to cheat in the game. So what they can do is
essentially receive a field of the universe, and you can send a command to do action. And I also
created a utility-based or dual utility-based AI for the game. And this is the bigger architecture
that's built on top of the framework. And this is the screenshot of the game. I know this is not
graphically attractive, but this is like, oh, I can do an ops. Where is it? And I'm losing my side.
Okay.
And this is how the game actually looks like. The interface. I mean, you can click on things here
to do something and add some command. And I mean, this is a complex interface. And so I'm not going
to actually show everything here, but you know something is working here.
It's the scale.
Sorry?
You mean the spatial scale. For this, it's like three times three light years cube.
This is a very small universe. It can be larger. At least it can handle a thousand light year cube
game without crashing my computer. So thanks for the open source ecosystem. I can rely on all
kinds of open source library to build my game. I use deep gdx for the graphical interface. I use
coroutine for the parallelization. And also thanks for the open art community. Because I'm not an
artist, I can't create all the art by myself. So I can rely on creating company license assets.
And I can use open source software like Inscape to definitely draw something.
So it's going to be the end of my presentation. But I would like to have a bit of reflection on
my project. So I think I've learned a lot by contributing to open source software. And the
ecosystem gave me plenty of building blocks from my own project. And of course, because of this,
it's natural for me to also open source my project. And at least I've created some interesting.
But there are also some problems that I face during the development of this project. For example,
there's a lack of open source culture in my workplace. I mean, some people there do use
open source software, but most of them do not care that much. So most of the time, I'm by myself.
And as a one-man project, it's a bit too ambitious, I would say. So I don't have time to polish all
the things like graphic interface, documentation. And I can't ensure that things are fun to play.
And I just don't have time to work on the translation. I did try, but I just simply
don't have time to do to work on all kinds of things. Because I'm also doing my picture here.
I have to write papers and do presentation. And I decided to go fully open source. So I choose
those libraries. It depends on. But perhaps, I mean, there are some kind of industry standard
solutions. Like if you're creating a game, people just use Unity for that. And perhaps
it was better for the project. So I have more time for other things. I don't know. But it's
just some other thing that perhaps there's a price to pay for if you decided to go open source.
And actually, I did try a bit to commercial my process, because it's possible to sell
open source game. I know it's possible. But it's also very hard to do so. I mean,
it takes time to advertise it. So I gave up. Eventually, I didn't have time for now to push
it forward. So this is the summary of my presentation. I have created a framework
for industry-asocial model. And I've created some model based on the framework. I've also
created a game on top of that. And perhaps it's lacking some immediate practical value. And that's
not so tall as that. Tall as that, like, it didn't exist tomorrow. But I think it's not going to
happen in the short route. So perhaps there's no immediate practical value. But I still believe
this kind of meaningful and educational exploration, you can if the game is fun to play,
eventually, then you can ask your kids to pay for that. And perhaps they can learn some physics
from the game. And at the very least, at the most important, I feel like I've achieved something in
my PhD. I'm not wasting my time in my pandemic. So that's all my presentation. And this is the
link of the project. And if you like, you can give it a star. Just check it out. And the thing that
I show is I think you can find those things in the read me file of this page. So thanks a lot for
attention.
We'll give you a few questions while the next speaker will come and.
Okay. Okay.
In your simulations, when you said that the civilizations then cluster,
how many years was simulated into simulation before you got to sort of resolve?
Yeah, I'm talking like that. Sorry. Can you repeat? Okay. Okay.
So the question was like, how many years did I simulate for the for the for the for the for the
model that I presented here? I typically I simulate for for for 1000 or 2000 years. And because of the
spatial scale is like 10 times 10 times 10 light year. So it takes the test of action time for the
spaceship to move towards each other and then to do the clustering.
Because I assume that they move as a sub light sphere of light philosophy. And you have a question.
Yes. I guess it's more technical. So your framework is written in Kotlin. Does it support any form of
extension like in another JVM language? I mean, in principle, you can use Kotlin with other JVM
language. For instance, or, I guess, customize agents, maybe even maybe the physics model that
says I want to fasten the light and travel or something like that.
Um, I so the question was like, I can can you use other JVM language to to to extend it? I think in
principle, it is possible because you can always I the way to use this is to is to create something
from a source code, right? And you can always work with JVM other JVM language in the source code.
But I am not entirely sure because I use some Kotlin feature like inline function to simplify
the code. So I'm not sure what that kind of thing. Can you can use it nicely with other JVM language?
I know you didn't go into that. Why not? Why not? Like, I want to work on what I want to work on
Android. And you know, Android Java support is not great. Okay, sure.