So, this is the second talk related to open projects. I don't know if anyone went to the
talk about integrations yesterday. Anybody? All right. Designers, I get it. So, this is
Practical UX at open projects. So, I've been working there for a year and a half, and these
are musings about the things I've learned, things we've gone through. It will all become
clearer in a second. I'm Pyremol, and that's a very elaborate site to tell you my name is
Pyremol, and I'm a UX designer at open projects. So, I think we can start with, I think we can
all agree that the UX in open source could use a little bit of work. I think it's fair enough to
say that, right? We know the reasons, but very quickly, some of the challenges we've had. Data
design. When you have data design in software, and open source tends to have this sometimes,
it is not necessarily intuitive, which makes it less attractive to new users, because they're
comparing with a lot of other newer tools, and they tend to have all this shiny stuff, right?
There tends to all sometimes be inconsistent behavior. The good thing about having contributors,
all sorts of contributors over the years, is that it's open. Anyone can do things, can add new
features, but if you lack a consistent coherent design language, then you do have the problem of
inconsistency over time. There's also a lack of investment in designers. Now, this is, I think,
in general, an open source has a lack of resources in general, right? Not always, but there tends to
be this problem, and design does not tend to also be the priority for a lot of projects.
There's also this tendency of open source projects being engineering driven. Not necessarily a problem,
because this can generally mean a very fully functional, very feature-rich software, I'd say,
but that does not necessarily translate to beginner-friendly software, because we don't
manage to, again, attract new users, and UX and accessibility tend not to be immediate concerns
of developers if they're not necessarily topics that concern them directly, and this also means
that these tend to not be prioritized for that same reason. However, there are some positives to
UX and open source, and that's that UX has also taken this dark turn through all the sort of
Facebooks and the Microsofts and the Googles, where there's a lot of dark patterns, and UX
designers and a lot of companies are encouraged to produce these dark patterns. We tend to not have
this in open source, because we tend to want to create things that people like, and we're sort of
bound by these values, though I think the fact that we're in of Fosse means we sort of have these
values, and there's a spirit of sharing, which is why we're all here, and things are getting better,
and I think that some of the talks at Fosse are showing us this. So that's the sort of point of
which we're starting, but then we joined Mark and I, he's not here, but hi Mark, we joined Open
Project in August 2021, and we were quite impressed, because Open Project, for quite a small company,
decided to invest in two UX designers, which was quite a big deal for an open source project of
about 30 developers. So we have a product team of the two UX designers and the CEO, so we take
product decisions, but then we also try to work on the user experience. And the reason I joined
Open Projects, because I come from a background of working in agencies, communication agencies,
different world, with all the values that you guys share, that we all share, and seeing that
a company was willing to put the resources in, and the goal was to improve user experience.
What does this mean for Open Projects? To tell you this, I'd like to tell you a little bit about
Open Project, because otherwise you won't know what I'm talking about. So Open Project is an
open source project management and collaboration software that looks, I'll show you the screenshots
in a bit, but I thought I'd tell you how we organize, so you get a sense of perhaps
compared to other open source projects. We have about, I said we're a team of 30, about 15 devs,
full stack, front, back, all that. We've got three product people, like I just said. We've got one QA,
which I'll sort of connect to user experience a little bit, because if you can't test it doesn't
quite work. A bit of marketing, some HR, and then sales and support. That's it, that's our entire
ship. We've got two versions, the free community version that you can just download and install
anywhere, and the enterprise with the support, quite a classic model. And you can install it
on premises, on the cloud. We also offer hosting within the EU if you don't want your data sent
anywhere else, and you can see some of our major clients, including Burshipban, who spoke earlier.
Right, and the values that are very important to us are sort of the privacy, the data security,
digital sovereignty. These are things that we're very, very passionate about, as are a lot of other
projects who are speaking today. Something looks like that. List of work packages, tasks. This is
actually what we're using to work on the new version that we're going to release in a couple of,
well, we'll see when it gets released. It's been released this month, and so we work publicly,
using open projects, obviously. And so you can see a bunch of some features, some epics we're
working on. You could filter by priority, by status. I think you get the idea. You could go
into a bug report that I submitted. And this is all public, by the way. And if you find a bug,
you can also submit one. And you can see the description there, the activity, where you can
really exchange with other users. You can tag them. That's very important to us as well. Connect
to other files. We talked about integrations. We have an integration with Next Cloud. So if you
upload files in Next Cloud, you can link to tasks and work packages in open projects.
And I think that's a very common view, sort of a Kanban Scrum view, if you want to drag things
around. We have that too. And we have a team planner. So if you want to organize your
team and see who's doing what and reassign tasks, you can do that.
So that gives you a sense of what the product is. Let's go to UX at open projects. Some things
have happened since I joined, since Mark and I joined. We now have a design team. Previously,
we didn't have one. Wasn't the priority. It was quite normal as well. Now we have two UX designers
and a test person, a QA person, Ivana. We used to do Markups in PowerPoint. It did the job.
But now we're working in Figma. And hopefully we can move to Penfot at some point.
So we had a rudimentary style guide of HTML elements. And now we have a growing design system
with reusable components that we're going to look at in a bit. It was quite engineering-driven.
So the design, you can see that in the design as well. And now we're working alongside devs
to get some early feedback. And we're not at loggerheads. It's not devs versus designers.
We're trying to work from scratch and get early feedback. So these are things that we are changing
within our way of working. Now, we all know the benefits of better UX. But for us, we've
realized that even clients that have used our software for a very, very long time, if we can
offer optimizations, even mine now, that's worth the time and effort. And of course, attracting
new users is very important to us. Because we're not trying to only be the open source project
management tool. We're also trying to compete as an alternative to the proprietary tools.
So the challenge is, if you read the abstract, that was something I promised. And I will try to deliver.
So, designers, us designers have a temptation to want to say, be helicopter into a project
and design everything from scratch. I see that. I'll put something on Figma. Let's do this.
It's not that easy. I think you guys know this. Because when you're working with an open source
project, there are certain contextual constraints, let's say. Let's put it that way. It tends to be
quite large open source applications. So you can't just change one thing and propagate it throughout
the whole application. Because for example, the same element, say a drop down or a button,
can appear very differently in different parts of the application. But not just visually. It might
be implemented differently in all those places as well. Because again, multiple contributors over
the years, no coherent design language. Sometimes you can even have different code layers. In our
case, we have Angular and Ruby, which means the views aren't rendered quite the same way, everywhere.
And the time, if you come up with a new design, it has then to be developed. And that time,
that's time and effort that's competing with new feature developments, with maintenance,
with bug fixing, and general dev time. So you can't just say, I've designed this, implement it,
and we'll move on. You've got to balance it with all these other things. And of course, we realize
that when you design a new feature, the requirements are very different between pro users and new users
who are used to certain ways of working. And you say, oh, no, we're going to change something
completely. The risk of that is, of course, the classic XKCD. I don't know if you know this one.
There are 14 competing standards. And you're like, oh, you can't have that. We need to develop a one
universal standard that works with everybody. And then you end up with 15 standards. We don't want
that. So of course, data analytics helps often. It helps you get a sense of what users are doing,
what they want, where they're getting stuck. And you could use Google Analytics. Or you could not
use Google Analytics like we do and not have the data. Because it's very important for us not to
track our users. So that makes our work slightly complicated because we don't quite know what people
are doing. But it's very important to us that we don't do this, especially because, again, the data
would not necessarily be within the EU. Having said that, we managed to ship our first big feature
when we joined, Mark and I. It was a notification center. We were very proud of it because we didn't
have any process, no UX process. And we still managed to do it. And because before this, all
notifications in OpenProject were email based. If you sort of had a new package, a feature,
someone answered it, added a new requirement, you'd get an email alert. You couldn't follow it
within the application. So we designed this. Extremely proud of it. But it did ruffle some
feathers because we said, all right, now the emails are only going to be digests, not for every single
notification. But some people were used to this. So we're extremely proud of this feature. But we
also learned that you've got to ease users in with these big changes. Perhaps we need to start small.
Small means sort of manageable, developable, maintainable, testable, don't scare existing
usable. That's sort of what we mean by small, reasonable, in other words. So when you want to
change these things, there's a couple of different ways to go about it. You can change one thing
everywhere in the application. So let's say a button. The button that we had doesn't quite
work. We want to change it. We want to make it better. You could make that button the same,
the new version, everywhere. But then individual pages would not be consistent, right? Or you could
change everything in one page. It takes the settings page. We're going to update it with new
components. We're going to make it standard. But then that standard, it's not across pages,
it's not very standard, is it? You just changed the problem a little bit.
So the approach we've gone with is we want to standardize the elements first. Remember how I
told you that the same elements could be implemented in different ways in different places?
Well, what if we first standardize the implementation, the HTML, the actual code of
that element, and then we can modify it, can't we, once we come up with some sort of consistent way
of doing it. That'll also help us understand how these elements are being used and the different
variations we'll need. I'll give you an example. For a design presentation, it's been a lot of
words, hasn't it? More images, please. This is the date picker that we used to have, and that's the
date picker we have now. We changed it because we introduced a new feature which was taking work
week into account. So sort of being able to say that Saturday and Sunday are holidays or could be
a Friday depends on your company. So when we did this, we took the opportunity to upgrade it,
and beyond this sort of aesthetic change, you'll notice that was an opportunity for us to then
work on all these elements to try to better define what a button should look like, what an
action bar should look like, what the blue when you tab across the application and you're changing
the focus, what that should look like, because that wasn't very consistent either. So we took
this opportunity, sort of new feature development to create these components, and not just things
that are visible, but also things that are invisible like this, which we didn't quite have
in the past. So that does mean that for now, you won't find this in all across the application.
There are parts of the application that don't respect some of the things we've defined,
but we are going iteratively one step at a time. And to do that, we need a design system.
We call it the single point of truth, spot. And if there's a component that has not been
included in the design system, we say it's not been Spotifyed. They can't really sue us.
So what is a design system? For instance, sort of a consistent, dependable, reusable,
reusable and documented set of things. These things could be styles, colors, spacing,
things I showed you. Could be components, like buttons or text boxes, any of the little
components that bigger interfaces are built out of. And then patterns that are a combination of
these things. And the last bit is very important. You've got to then document it and tell people
how to use it, when to use it, what to do, what not to do. And of course, as being an open source
company, we publish all of it in our website. So anybody can go and look at it. So now when we say
spacing two, everybody knows the developers, designers and the testers know what that spacing
should look like. Same thing for action bars with a different variance. And then we go to our
website, and then we try to explain those variants and how to use it. And this is public in our
website. It's not complete yet. We're still working on our design system. So not all elements are
there. But we are working on it. How's the speed? Am I speaking too fast for anyone? It's all right.
Okay, well, I'll take a bit of a break and bring some water. You can appreciate our design system.
So in some startups, they say, build fast and break things. We can't afford to do that. That's
not our mantra. Our mantra is to build slow, iterate and test things. I say test things. We've
not quite done it yet. That's our goal for this year. So we want to balance UX optimizations with
feature dev. But like I showed you with the date picker, perhaps if we spend 40% of our time with
feature development, we take that as an opportunity as well to optimize and maybe choose five core
elements and then sort of fold them into our design system and try to make those consistent.
Which requires sort of that means that there will be imperfection and there will be inconsistencies
within the application. Our goal is to accept that imperfection and to keep moving. Because again,
the developer doesn't like when things are inconsistent or some developers want it to be
pixel perfect. Well, sometimes it's not going to be. And for those of you who speak French,
the better is sometimes the enemy of the good. And sometimes you've got to accept the good enough
to move forward to where you want to be. Very philosophic, I know. So the learnings for the past
year and a half. It's very happy to be able to put that half symbol there. I thought it looked quite
cool. So the first thing is you can't just join a project, be helicoptered in and magic wand the
whole thing and say, great, we want to just change everything. Let's do it upgraded to 2024. You need
incremental upgrades because you need everybody in the company to believe in what you're doing, be
convinced it's worth the effort. And luckily, we have that sort of projects. But it's not an easy
thing to do because there are competing competing requirements, competing priorities and how
companies should use its time. So that's important to accept incremental, standardizing things now
means a lot of time spent now. But down the road, it gives us more time to do that. And
down the road, it gives us more time to do more relevant work. It's less time because things are
already standardized. If we change a color, if we change the design, it'll change all across the
application. We need to be pragmatic, try to make something a little better with every release, not
go for everything in one release. But sometimes we do want to go for those big changes like we did
with Notification Center. It might ruffle some feathers. But those changes are required because
we have a vision for where the product needs to be. However, we've learned, perhaps the hard way,
that we need to ease our users in who are used to the old system, help them understand why we're
doing it. And in that regard, we also plan on communicating more from the product team,
perhaps publishing the why and the how of how we work, why we take certain decisions. And finally,
we could learn from other open source projects as designers. I mean, because developers do it
quite a fair bit, I don't think we quite have that culture amongst designers. And we're currently
working on theming. And I saw a presentation by Mathieu, Mathieu Brouet from Proton, who was
in Paris where he was last year. And he was explaining how his company worked on theming,
and all the things that he did that were wrong and what he learned from. And we were able to use that
and learn from it. And that helped us save us time, sort of get a better sense of what we were
doing. So thanks to Mathieu, who's not here, but I think that sort of sharing is very important.
We should do more of that. And we really hope that this presentation maybe,
hopefully, one day can help someone as well. So what are plans for 2023 then? More UX.
Shocking, I know. So more UX, so more work on the design system, continue working on it, rather.
More testing, because we've not really done any testing now. We haven't had the resources.
But that's one of our plans. Even a basic hallway test where we ask five people what they think and
if they understand the feature, is some input. We want to integrate more with other tools.
Part of doing that is to take the design system and make it easy for someone creating a plugin
or trying to integrate with Open Project to use those design elements as well. So that's one of
the reasons we're working on the design system as well. And of course, better theming, like I just
mentioned. And accessibility is something that we have in mind, but we could do a lot more.
We could be a lot better at that. So that's one of our goals. And of course, we've got the usual
suspects, the ongoing optimizations, and new features along the way. The goal, of course,
then is to have more users who say they picked up Open Project for the UX. Not just because it's
open source. Of course, we want them to pick up Open Project because it's open source. Of course.
But if they say, we tried a bunch of tools, we think you guys have really good UX, that's our goal.
But why stop there? Let's go further. A broader goal is to build an alternative to Microsoft 365
with all the other actors, some of whom were here, Fostom. So Next Cloud, Open Exchange,
Elements, Exmikki, Collabora, with all these other players. Let's give users an alternative
that's respectful of their privacy, that is open source, and that respects data sovereignty.
And if you're passionate about these things, I'm certainly not telling you that you should,
you know, whether these companies are hiring, but they might be. Just saying.
Thank you very much for giving me some time. And if you have any questions, I'll take them now.
Yes.
A lot of what you said reminds me of when I was at the Open Food Network doing similar things.
This move was built on like Spree, and it was very like component messy, change it here,
but not change it here. All those things. My question is, how beneficial or not is having your CEO
on your product team to do things? That's a great question, actually, because for us,
designers can also go too far. Because we want to change things very, very quickly,
but there are some very pragmatic questions that are also development related, but also,
let's say, related to the product roadmap. We think it's quite helpful, because then we can
have the discussion internally and align ourselves rather than be at loggerheads again with, like,
you can have designer versus developer, you can also have designer versus product. So we try to
avoid that. So we think it works well. Yeah. Yes. Sorry.
So the organization I work for, my university, have been paying enterprise users through project
probably like a year and a half, two years. Glad to hear it. So I use it like every day. I really
like it. Universally, 100% of the negative feedback I've received from my colleagues
on open project have been explicitly related to the UX. Yeah. And so, and then pretty much all
the positive feedback I've gotten from my colleagues have been related to specifically
the UX improvements that you showed last 10 minutes. So these improvements are really
important to us as an organization, but I realize that especially in open source products
that are oftentimes very privacy focused, from my perspective, it seems like usually it's a very
lab first adopters that have a priority among all of their customers, regardless, because there's
just not an easy way to measure. Do you have any suggestions as like an organization that's
paying for the product that really appreciates this work and wants it to be known by, I don't
know, like your boss or something like that, that this work is important to us and matters?
Okay. So I'll try to repeat the question. Yeah. So you said that one of the biggest complaints with
open project was the UX and some of the positives in the recent times have been related to UX.
And the question is, sometimes the early adopters tend to be the loudest and tend to get heard the
most. So how do we get better at listening to the community in general? Yeah. Like what
recommendations do you have for maybe customers? Yeah. Okay. Customers of open projects. So what
recommendations would we have to them? Well, we have two things we can say. First of all,
our community discussions are open. So if you feel very passionate, be passionate about a feature
or a certain optimization, we really welcome that feedback and we will engage with you.
It can be sometimes a bit tough to be on all fronts. So sometimes it's true that feedback
can be a bit lost. We tend to track it with both an open project, but our biggest, perhaps a
recommendation would be to engage with the community directly via community. And also,
if you have an idea of some of the pull requests, that's also very, but that's not fair for a lot
of people because, yeah. Well, thank you for using our project. Yeah. Yes. We will, we will test more.
We'll start small with how we test and this quarter actually we have quarterly goes and
so I'll go to test more. And there's a question back there. Perhaps it's the last one. Hi.
Oh, other designers contribute. Oh, we've not had that yet. That's a good question. We might
have to talk about it. So we have our design system that's quite open and everything. I mean,
you could submit a pull request for pretty much anything, including our design system,
but we've not quite had external developers. We are, we are obviously interested so we can talk.
Yeah. Thank you. Do we have time for more questions or are we one more question if there is.
Oh, hi. Thank you.
That's that's yeah, that's good question. When we first arrived, there was a question of what
the priorities should be. But there are a lot of issues with open project through feedback. We've
got from our users that we already know about. We already have a backlog. That's I wouldn't say
considerable, but we do have a backlog of known issues. So we thought we'll work on those first
because we know that customers have told us that there were certain improvements and notification
center, which was a passion project actually initially within the company. But it was also
because we got some feedback about improvements that we could do and was also a feature that I
think was quite required. It's quite a basic feature as well. So we were very happy to work on that.
Thank you everybody. And if you have any questions, you can get there.