Okay.
Hello, everybody.
Welcome.
Thank you for coming to my talk.
My name is Brian Duggan.
I'm going to be talking today about something called Termi, which is practical and fun automation
for all your terminal sessions.
I'd like to thank my employer, Instacart, and the Pro Foundation for helping me to be
here.
I'm on the logistics team at Instacart.
Okay.
So here's an outline of the talk.
I'm going to give a quick overview of the concept of Termi.
What it does, what it's all about.
Go through some of the features.
Explain the scripting capabilities.
And then a little bit about why it's written in Raku, which is usually the first question
I get, but I'm saving it for last.
Okay.
So here's the basic concept of Termi.
It works like this.
So you have your shell.
You type Termi to start the session.
It starts a T-Mux session.
How many T-Mux users in here?
Oh, good.
Okay.
Screen.
You guys can fight it later.
Okay.
So it starts a T-Mux session.
It puts you in the bottom half.
And basically anything that you type into the bottom half goes into both the bottom
half and the top half.
Okay.
So you type, what is Termi?
And it sends it to the bash shell session at the top, which doesn't know what what means.
Depending on your environment, you'll get some strange error messages about what command
are you trying to type.
So I did this.
And since this is the automation room, I thought, probably, maybe I could just automate this
talk completely.
So I found a command line version of chat GPT on the internet.
And that had a command line wrapper.
I thought maybe I could just get chat GPT to write my entire talk for me, automate it
away, and then I would be done.
Okay.
So I did the pip install, which sends a lot of things to the terminal, as everybody probably
knows.
Lots of recommendations about what to upgrade.
Finally, I have the chat GPT executable.
So I typed that.
And I said, what is Termi?
But did not get very much information.
Since it didn't know about the talk that I hadn't given yet.
So then I said, you know, Termi is being presented at Fostem, which was a little bit better,
but still I had to add a little more substance to the talk.
And then the program hung.
So I had to interrupt it with Control C. And the way you do that with Termi is you use
a backslash, which starts the command.
Everything starts with a backslash, kind of like the Postgres command line interface is
a directive to Termi.
So stop says send a Control C signal to the other pane.
So I got keyboard interrupt, but that wasn't enough to stop it, because that was trapped
by the Python interpreter.
So then I sent another one.
And then that finally gave me a stack trace, which everybody who uses Python sees a lot.
And then finally, I was done with this session.
So the basic concept here is simple.
You have something on the top, something on the bottom.
It's the same.
And the things on the bottom go to the top.
So you have kind of an interactive session.
And then you can also send these additional commands to the top.
So now I'm going to go through some of the features.
So as you saw from the last one, you have everything sort of organized on the bottom,
and if you have stack traces and things on the top, you still have a nice little session
that shows you what you're doing.
And you can set up macros.
You can run scripts.
You can wait for things.
And I'm going to go through a few more of these in detail now in the next few minutes.
So it has GNU read line built in.
It has a few ways of getting history.
Read line is a last command.
There's also fuzzy find, fzf.
You can use fuzzy find for things.
So you can search your history for that.
And it searches right, even if you have several different sessions on the top.
Maybe you're on different machines, or maybe part of it is in some other application.
Some of it is in a shell.
It'll search your local history.
So for instance, let's say you're using a PSQL.
You're connected to a remote database, and you have your local history, and maybe you
run some SQL that's going to show you the long-running queries.
So you can write a macro to send all of this.
And the way you do that is you say slash edit.
Then you have a text editor.
Put your file in an SQL file.
And then slash alias will create a macro that says, you set the name of the macro.
And then slash run says run this little script, which will send it to the other console.
And then after that, you can just type slash find queries, and the top will get the SQL
that you put into the file.
So it can be convenient for things like that.
Or you could use it with Redis, or doing your kernel testing, as we saw in the first talk,
or whatever.
Just any sort of session, you can just make a macro and send it.
So here's another example.
In this case, instead of using a macro, we're going to send standard out from a command
that we run locally to the other pane.
So on the bottom, I say delay three, which means wait three seconds between every line
that you send to the top.
And then slash shell means just run this command, and then show me the output.
So I say slash shell cat eg simple.bash.
And here you can see my bash script, which does an echo, echo docker run.
And then echo hostname.
So then it runs that command.
When I say slash do, it runs that command.
And the output from that command gets sent to the top.
And it's sent after every line, it waits three seconds.
So it sort of throttles the output, which we might need, because it might take docker
a few seconds to start before you run the hostname command on the shell inside the container.
So the bottom is what you're typing.
The top is what you see.
So here's another feature.
So in addition to standard out, you can take the output of the top and send it to standard
in of anything that you write.
So in this example, I'm using the nl command, which basically takes standard in and outputs
line numbers for the commands that are coming in.
So I say sleep three and head user share addict words.
The reason I do sleep three, if you think about it for a second, is because when I do
the exec command, I need time to type it.
So I type sleep three and head, and that gets sent immediately to the shell, which waits
a few seconds.
Then I type exec nl, and then standard in comes in, and then it prints out what goes
out.
So in the real world, you probably won't have to sleep, because there will be constantly
stuff coming through the top terminal.
A few other interesting commands.
So await will just wait for either a string or a regular expression to appear in the top.
In queue is a way to enqueue a command after you've finished awaiting it.
Grep, repeat, send the same thing over and over, maybe add an interval, send a file,
and we already saw what delay does, setting the delay.
And there are actually a lot of commands.
There are 43.
Whenever I needed to do something, I added a new one.
If you have any ideas, send me a PR or send a request.
There are 43 different commands right now.
Actually, 44.
I think I added one this morning.
Okay, so script.
Anybody here use expect?
A few people.
Okay, so expect has been around for a long time, 1993, but it's still pretty useful if
you have to interact with a program that requires a TTY.
So here is an example of an expect script on the left.
In this case, what we're going to do is we're going to start a Docker container again, and
then we're going to run user add to add a user, and then we'd like to set a password
for the user.
So we're going to run the password command, and we're also going to look for the prompts
that are coming back.
Okay, so on the left, we see the way expect works is you say spawn, and then expect takes
a pattern, so root at is what comes back in the prompt.
And then you send user add termee.
We're going to add a user name to termee.
Then it has a regular expression, expect-re, that you can then capture with expect out.
And then finally at the bottom, we're going to print out what we caught.
We captured the fact that the host name was something that was in the prompt.
So you can do the same thing in termee.
You can say user bin end termee, and then set it to be an executable file.
The default is to just send everything, so it's just kind of like you're interacting
from the console.
All the lines just get sent directly to the other pane.
So you just say docker run, and then backslash expect is kind of like the expect command.
There's a little subtlety in there that you usually don't think about, because it's sort
of intuitive as a human.
You type it and you're expecting something, but really there's a race condition there,
right?
Because between the time that you send your command and the time you send the expect command,
the output might have already happened.
So the way that expect deals with it is it keeps track of the stream, and then it kind
of goes back and there's sort of this running, you know, a pointer to the output stream.
And the way we do that with termee is we basically run the expect before we run the command.
So it'll basically say now I'm starting to watch the output, and then it'll send the
output, and then it'll capture it.
So when we run this, and it runs interactively in tmux, so you can see on the top it sends
docker run, pulls the image, and it's waiting now to see the prompt.
So it waits for the route.
And then after that it sends the user add, waits for new password, and then finishes
successfully.
So the output here is in the test anything protocol.
You may or may not be familiar with it.
It's just okay, and then the number of the test.
And then currently if it doesn't get what it expects, then it aborts the tests.
Okay, so quickly I'm just going to say why it's written in Raku.
And the main idea here is that Raku has a lot of very nice ways to do asynchronous programming
and also interact with other commands.
So you can quickly open a pipe to tmux and interact with it using asynchronous processes.
You can run things synchronously.
It's got good not just interprocess but interthread communication.
It has built-in constructs like supplies and channels and promises, which you may be familiar
with from other languages.
So this is like an example of how you could tail a file and create a supply, which is
a built-in type in Raku.
And finally, this is kind of like the implementation of expect.
So it's really pretty straightforward.
You can basically set up an event loop in a separate thread using this construct.
Starts a thread, reacts whenever it says here's an event loop.
And then if it's a string, we look to see if it contains a target.
If it's a regex, then we send it to a channel so that then we can have it available to use
locally.
So even if you're not interested in using termi, you might find some value in using
Raku for automation.
That's the end.
Thank you for listening.
Questions?
I think I have a few minutes.
Okay.
Yeah, that's a good question.
So different shells do different things that you kind of are not really aware of, even
just the simple printing of a prompt.
They don't always send a newline character.
Sometimes they'll send escape sequences that go to the beginning of the line and then go
down the line, or sometimes they'll even redraw the line above it.
So it works fine.
But you just have to be aware of the idiosyncrasies of the various shells in terms of what they
do to the terminal.
It does interfere.
You can, one of the commands is to buffer the lines, and it does get tricky to split
up the lines when there's a lot of cursor movement.
Yeah.
One more.
Does it also work with serial consoles?
With serial consoles.
So that aspect is basically taken care of by TMUX.
So it doesn't do the direct communication with the serial console the way that expect
would.
Yep.
We have one more minute.
Last question.
Who wants to do the honors?
Nobody.
No.
Okay, I'll do the honors.
Are you aware of current users?
So we only have a handful of users, so now is your opportunity to request features.
We don't have to worry too much about backwards compatibility.
That's it.
Thank you.
Okay.