So, hello, welcome everybody. I'm Announcer Zwinfritilanes, but I should also announce
Emily Trump. We did this project together, and unfortunately she couldn't make it today
because of problems with public transportation. So, she's now at home watching this presentation,
and I hope I can make her proud. I'm Zwinfritilanes. I'm just a privacy expert, and usually making
totally dual, bad design presentations. Emily is a designer, really working with design
thinking and really likes to reframe things. And she's also the one who is responsible
for this really great presentation. I'm totally happy with it. So, failure-driven design.
This is about a case study, and it has been really successful privately by design projects.
But we did a lot wrong, and we make a lot of failures. Unfortunately, we learned from
it, and we went wrong. And so, this presentation will be the story about that one. But before
I really dive deep into it, I want to ask you a question. When you think about privacy,
this concept, do you think it's modulated? Is it about the requirements the technicians
to have to build this system in a private way? Is it about the trust of the end users?
Or is it about agency, about their ability of end users to make their own choices? So,
what do you think? Let's make a little poll of it. I hope it works. This is the first
time I use Nextcloud for a poll. It goes to a domain totally owned by me, so you have
to trust me. So, you already answered the question.
It's also an IPv6 that might be a problem. Are you connected to the dual stack?
Yeah, let's... Wait. Yeah. So, who thinks it's about requirements?
To one hand. Who thinks it's about trust? A little bit more than half of it. Who thinks
it's about agency? Quite close, we said. But requirements are down the list, I believe.
All right. This is what I will be talking about. The design challenge, the thing we
had to design. Then three perspectives on privacy. The approach we did in the design
project and what we learned from it. So, the design challenge was promoting agency with
an open source ecosystem for e-hals. There are some things that are really important
here. First of all, it had to be about a digital open source exchange standard. The idea that
was envisioned for all different kind of e-hals apps, all kind of health professionals, all
working together in unpredictable ways, in unpredictable combinations, and that had to
cooperate. So, we had to find a way to make standards to have them communicate. And another
starting point of the project was user agency. The idea was when people have to control about
their own path in the healthcare system or in the care system, then they make same choices.
They choose what's good for them. And that makes the healthcare system better and better
affordable. So, agency was not only just because we like to be ourselves and to have the possibility
to be ourselves. No, it was really at the heart of the project the question. Another
part of it is, I'm already told a bit, it's really about the ecosystem of care applications
and blending with health applications. So, more informal care, more social work, comparing
with really hard medical care. And these have different security levels. And they need different
levels of trust. And trusting your neighbor is something else than trusting your doctor.
So, we all had to design for this. Well, then we started. And we discovered that there was
three perspectives on privacy that were really causing havoc in the project. Confusion,
misunderstandings, everything. So, the three perspectives was really a theoretical perspective.
I told I'm the privacy expert. We like to make the presentations with lots of text.
And I really like to think about what means privacy, how does it relate to agency. And
I came up with talking with peers on relational view on privacy. And that relational view
is really focusing on the choices we make. I'm standing here in certain clothes, are
you feeling certain things about myself? Not feeling other things about myself. Those
choices about how we feel create how I relate to you and how I appear to you. And also that
creates a relation. And we all make these choices. Just look around and see how we are.
There's no process all this time. And by these choices, we create agency. By these choices,
we can determine who we are and who we are in certain contexts. So, that's really the
theoretical thought we had about it. And then we had to end you with a perspective. And
we really went into neighborhood centers, talked with users, gave them an app, asked
how do you experience this. And they were totally somewhere different. What's this?
This is complicated. Don't know how to handle it. And I have to enter this data. What's
why? And where does it go? And I don't trust this thing. And then we were sitting at the
table with developers from the companies making the ELs and the care apps. And they were asking,
well, tell us what to do. What are the requirements? So, all talking different languages.
So, we had to find a way to get on. To get this big misunderstanding solved and to get
something that got everything together. And we had to test it with users. Which might
be a problem because we were creating an abstract exchange standard and not an app or something
like that. So, we had to bridge a gap. And we took a step back. We're thinking, what
are the common failures? What are they talking about? What are the things that they share
and what they all want to have in the system? And that's where the trust in the agency came
in. That's where when we noticed users really wanted to see experience that they could trust
the system and experience that they could make changes. And the developers, well, they're
not bad guys. They don't want to violate everybody's privacy. They're working in health apps so
they know that this is important. So, we talked with them about what's needed in such an ecosystem.
They very well understand this also trust in agency. It's really important to give the
choices and to make sure that you are trusted. So, we translated these principles of these
common failures into design principles. Tell more about it later. And, of course, I was
there also. And I helped to trick them, give my own input to the design principles. So,
that's how we came to a set of design principles that were bridging this gap. And then we came
to the next problem. I already mentioned it. How to use a test. Yeah. How to use a test
as a standard abstract thing that can have totally different traces and all different
kind of apps. And, you know, when we literally went to neighborhoods and talked about trust
in agency and everybody was, what are you talking about? So, we came up with a privacy
game. And it was a small game, small simulation. And we used that to envision abstract scenarios.
And we made a scenario about you're in this situation and you want to share this with
somebody with who you want to share it or you're in this situation, you're talking to
this person, what do you share? Then we changed in the twist of the game. Turned the page
around and then there was a new part of it. For example, somebody else or some changing
your information, what you maybe made want to share. And based on that, we got into a
discussion, talks with the users about how they made the choices. And if we could validate
the principles, we formulated. So, by playing this game, we made it, creating this game,
we really made it possible to see visible how the abstract principles, design principles
worked out. So, what did we learn? What are the things we got out of this? First of all,
trust is iterative process. You don't even when you go in at the doctor, it would be
totally strange to have a shield at the door of the doctor. Please undress yourself in
the waiting room. You know, you first want to make contact, want to see, well, is this
a doctor I like to see? And then slowly you start to trust the doctor and then slowly
you say, well, now it's appropriate to undress. And the same happens between a human and a
machine. Or when you interact with an app. It's not just, well, there are many apps where
you have to first page you see, create an account, and you have to tell everything about
yourself. And you're looking at it, well, why should I trust this app with all this
information? Maybe the apps you show that it's useful and there's some nice interaction
with you. So, next thing is, reciprocity of the information or what happens. I share,
you share. It's not one way around. Everyone wants to know everything about you. It doesn't
give you anything back. It doesn't show what it is. Maybe you say I want to donate information
about myself because I can help somebody else. But it has to be made visible. It has to be
two-way thing. So, really, I share, you share. People are willing to trust if there's balance.
And then the last one, and that one was really important for the designers. We tell them
these principles, they must be backed with your technical solution. The first thing they
said, well, identify in the system. Well, let's use the email address because it's easy
and everybody has it and then you can use it everywhere. But then people lose control
about where the data goes. Because somebody can link all the email addresses across all
applications. So, if you want to give people really agency, really the possibility to make
choices on a technical level also, then you have to say to the developers, well, for each
link between two apps, you use a unique identifier. And if you want to share a piece of information
across several apps, you have to create a star and make a deliberate decision to share
it and really back that up in your technical architecture. So, we really could tell that
the developers, well, this is what you should do. And it was really nice because we had
many meetings with the developers, different developers, they were really, oh, we don't
understand this. And then we came with these principles. Oh, and then we said, oh, then
can do this and this. And then it all piece together for them. And then they really drafted
in several days and first version of a standard. So, there was these are the principles we
found. Well, I have another poll, but let's do it manual. I have five minutes left in
my talk and five minutes for questions and I want to lengthen this. I'm a bit wondering,
curious, and let's just shout out the way it ends, whatever. What do you take away from
this presentation? What did you learn? Because I told about what we learned, but I'm wondering
what you did learn.
So, the interactive, I repeat it a bit because the device is not on the video. So, it's the
interactive building of trust. Yeah.
I might be projecting here a little bit, but some of the struggles you mentioned remind
me of when I worked in the aid sector where many people would try to apply design principles
like human centered design to develop a solution for certain people. But it's very difficult
to ignore these larger economic contexts. So, when you talk about privacy and people
not being engaged with it, maybe they aren't politically engaged with the topic, educating
them and figuring out how to mediate that, it reminded me of looking in the aid sector
where funding is.
You've experienced in a similar sector and you run into really the commercial barriers
of parties who didn't think that way, didn't want to implement it. So, it's interesting
because we were with lots of commercial organizations around the table and they were willing to
cooperate and they were willing to change something. They had some idealism there too.
But it is a problem in the care sector because it is a huge economic sector with lots of
money and lots of people who try to get a bit of the money. So, I feel your problem.
Any other takeaways?
I have a quick abstract question. How did you come up with the user testing as a game?
It was not a game you can win, but it might be played a bit as a party game and it might
be nice. We have lots of games, card games from this.
Was it an issue that the users were anonymous or was it the case that you managed to get
the users? You knew what the user was.
It was a paper game. We literally went to neighborhood centers and sat with people visiting
there around the table and played the game with them and interviewed them afterwards
about even before and after about how they even influenced.
I was curious, I find it really interesting how open source projects make decisions about
which methodology to use or which tool to use. How did you guys make the decision to
use the game? It is a tool I have never heard of before.
I am very open to learning. The question is how did you make the choice for the game for
testing? Well, we didn't make a choice. We tried lots of things. We had many sessions
in neighborhood centers that were totally filled. Then we had a feeling we need a way
to discuss more. Then we came up with the game. We noticed this works.
Now when we are looking back, we can make a nice story about it.
We had a game and it worked. I left out about a dozen of failures there.
I can give you more information about the game. I have both a paper on it and a game
available too.
The question is how do you include the GDPR in front-end design?
I love it. I have once been introduced at the conference as a person who laughs about
the GDPR. The point is when you work like this, let's move on. We are now here. When
you work like this, you have a far better way of handling privacy of your users than
the GDPR says. For example, part of the pattern is that in the iterative pattern, you only
ask for information when needed. Then you make clear why you need it.
That is already awfully close to an official privacy question you may have to ask according
to the GDPR. Maybe add a link to some additional information with all legal stuff in it. But
they are already there. Then you have asked a meaningful consent question. That is just
logical to do that when you are designing this way. Just design for privacy and then
GDPR should be included already. Good to know. You are the dark side.
Can you give a clear example of how you use reciprocity in information exchange?
For example, there are two levels. Between humans, you can deliberately support, and
we also had some design patterns, but they were UI design patterns, so they couldn't
be forced on all apps. You can really support two-way communication before telling somebody
something. You can really support, well, I asked you this, but I want to ask you this
because then I know I can do this for you. You can support in your design of the chat
interaction messages, patterns like that. You can also do that in human to machine things.
The app asking, well, I really like, if you like to, then we can arrange it if you come
back that I remember what you did. But to do so, I need an account.
It's essentially about telling what you are doing.
Exactly.
Any time you ask for something, tell us about it.
Exactly. Don't ask before it is already clear what you can give back for it. Start, for
example, with anonymous accounts. Then people can see what the app is doing.
Well, at a certain point, you can say, maybe it's interesting if I remember this. Tell
which you like to make an account. Don't ask the account. Then for the account, ask only
what is needed for the account. Don't ask anything more.
One final question. For example, try to make a really taxonomy and architecture that would
support all fine grained type of privacy patterns. That became a huge picture with lots of drawings
and lines and data model that was really exploding on all sides. Nobody understood it anymore.
And it was bonkers to even think about implementing it.
Spend some days on drawing all the boxes. No, that's not the way to go. To give one
example. Exactly. Yeah.