you
Thank you.
No?
Better?
Okay.
Yeah.
Perfect.
And then let's say the new generations, they moved to this VM-based scheme where they
have an entire VM isolated from the, from the user.
You cut the hypervisor, you create a completely isolated VM and everything that's inside,
like the firmware, the BIOS, the kernel and so forth, is everything is part of that confidential
context.
That means, of course, more code that needs to be trusted that's running in the same kind
of privileged layer.
But you don't have the problem of this restricted system interface.
So you can directly access, do any kind of syscalls, pretty much behave like any other
application inside any other operating system.
And those are these, these two worlds.
And both could be an option for protecting the variety at runtime.
As I said, Rebuild interface, in, in case of the confidential VMs, there's nothing really
we have to change.
And in case of the, the Intel SGX, the process-based world, we have this weird thing where we need
to forward those syscalls to, to the host.
And I guess it's, it's fair to say that the, the right side is probably a lot faster.
But you have this bit more of a stack that you need to trust that has, that's running
inside the same, same context.
Yeah, so, so SGX and process-based limitations.
It's currently, I think it's fair to say it's an Intel-only solution.
You're pretty much locked in with Intel at that point.
Any kind of context switch is expensive.
That means IO is, is expensive.
Any other interrupt is expensive.
And InnoDB, I have to say I'm not a MariaDB expert whatsoever, but for some reason I
know that InnoDB is a, is a problem.
People use different kinds of storage backends, like RocksDB, for example.
So you can just move the, I guess the, the off-the-shelf MariaDB into an SGX.
There's some, some things you have need to fiddle with and then you can make it work.
The upside is you have a very small trusted computing base, a very small amount of code
that you need to trust that runs inside this, this context.
On the other hand, SEV, confidential VM, larger TCB, well that, that means you are more, it's
more lift and shift.
And yeah, Intel is currently not an, it doesn't really have a solution out there that you
can use, but there's Intel TDX coming that's more or less the same as AMD SEV.
There's other stuff coming from ARM and, and, and Riskv and so forth.
Huge attack surface just means, yeah, you have the kernel, you have the firmware, the
bootloader, everything inside the, inside that, that context.
So if you have any kind of vulnerabilities there, you could be potentially attacked even
though you're isolated.
Right.
Apart from memory encryption, I think an important aspect of confidential computing is, is attestation.
That means, remoted attestation just means you get a statement from the chip, from the
CPU about what's running, what code was loaded inside your enclave, your, or your confidential
VM.
And that you, that's, that's signed with a key from the CPU and this key has a certificate
chain back to the hardware vendor so that you can send such a statement about, for example,
this is a MariahDB enclave, a MariahDB container that was loaded inside this enclave.
You can send it to a, to a remote party and establish a secure channel.
For example, exchanging a key, bootstrapping a TLS connection, and then you have a secure
channel through that, through the database.
You can exchange data to your select statements and so forth.
And with SGX, this needs, for example, you can do that by, by having like a small, small
stab that runs before your, before your actual code or next to your actual code that does
that interaction with the CPU and provides you with a attestation statement and then
you can use that.
Felix gave a talk last year, Felix was at the MariahDB dev room about HlessDB.
That's essentially a, that builds up on MariahDB and tries to bring that confidential computing
concept even, even, even closer or even more into the, the, the use case.
After slides from Felix, let me quickly show.
Because what, what we've seen so far is essentially just lift and shift of MariahDB on top of
SGX or top of AMD-SDB.
What HlessDB does, essentially it uses RoxDB for the reasons mentioned and also for, it
has some neat features about the encryption.
So the way it writes blocks makes it very good for the, for the confidential computer
and the attacker model, you can switch things around, you can't do any, any modifications.
And the interesting part is, why I'm showing this, they added a confidential computing
front end.
That means you not only have attestation that your MariahDB runs inside confidential computing
environment, they also give you an attestation about what the database is and who has access
to it.
Essentially when you, when you set it up, you define a small manifest that just gives
the initial database layout like the users, the initial tables, who can modify what with
access to what tables.
And they add that to the, to the attestation statements.
So then you can give, do a remote attestation and you know this is, this is not only MariahDB
running there, but this is MariahDB with those user credentials, those tables.
I think that's integrating this concept of confidential computing more with, with the,
the concept of a confidential database, if you will.
So interesting, as well as DBs also open source, so you can check it out, but if that's, that's
interesting for you, but it's SJ specific.
Let me go back to Arvid's slides.
Yeah, it's his slides, his, his emojis don't take responsibility, but yeah.
The problem with SCV and confidential VMs currently is that you can, you can just lift
and shift MariahDB inside, it will work.
The problem with the current way hypervisors and other cloud providers offer confidential
VMs is that they don't give you full access to the entire stack that runs inside the confidential
VM.
That means they have a firmware shim, you don't know, you can't really verify that loads
your bootloader US and then MariahDB, that breaks the chain of verification from the
hardware essentially.
That's what the slide tries to tell you.
And what we like to have is having the full chain inside this, in this VM verifiable from
the, from the firmware, like from the hyperstatement to the firmware and then up to MariahDB itself.
So yeah, this is a practical problem right now, but hopefully it's going to be solved
soon.
Can you start the hypervisor with your own virus?
Because the virus is on the lowest level.
Currently you can, for example, on Azure you can start on a AMD SCV machine on Hyper-V.
They set the firmware.
But there's a preview where you can define your own firmware.
You can either use direct Linux boot or you define your own UAFI base firmware.
And then you boot the image, the image starts MariahDB and then you go from there.
Yeah, if you want to try that, yeah, of course there's the AMD documentation and stuff.
It's a company called Cloud offers confidential VMs based on SCV.
Apparently there's some, some solution to try it out.
And yeah, EdgelessDB is open source.
You can also try that.
I think that's the last slide.
So not sure if I hit those 20 minutes, but yeah.
Any questions?
What type of usage do you see using this?
Yeah, mostly people that currently want to process sensitive regulated data in the cloud,
like healthcare, telecommunication, this kind of stuff.
They store, they do that on-prem with the database.
They want to move that to the cloud, but they can't because it's not enough that data is
protected at rest and in transit they also need to protect data at runtime.
Or as the EdgelessDB gives guarantees on who has access to the data.
Yeah.
The AMD based question, I'm interested in it after.
What is the reason why it's not compatible?
Is it the asynchronous IO?
To be honest, I am not the best person to answer the question, but I think it's part
of the syscalls that happen when you use InnoDB.
I'm not sure what syscalls are in the problem.
And then you have this context switches and you have a lot more context switches than
when you use RocksDB and that makes it super slow.
That's at least one problem.
I would imagine that RocksDB, well I don't know any detail, but I would assume that it
is synchronous IO for writing those LSM3s so it could be simpler syscalls.
Yeah, yeah.
I think that's...
There was something on Felix's slides along those lines.
But yeah, by the way, if you...
I think this is from last year.
I think there's a recording and Felix speaks about why RocksDB is a better performance
than the InnoDB.
I have a bunch of questions.
First of all, the first slide mentioned the Ponzi schema, some virtual training and touch
this.
What is it?
To be honest...
You can't keep this if you...
I don't know.
This would be a great question for Avid here, something right...
Yeah, at the end.
Yeah.
I'm not sure if Avid is in the chat or if there's a chat, but maybe he can answer that
question.
Okay, the next question is, there was a slide, two slides from the end, there was an object
called SP.
Yes.
Yes, what on the bottom right?
What would it mean?
What would it mean in a chain of trust?
Which one?
This SP?
Yes.
So, this is specific for how AMD implements that.
Essentially, they add a chip, the secure processor.
Yeah, and this basically holds the keys, holds the information, and then you communicate
as the guest, you communicate, you can establish a secure connection to that, go through the
hypervisor to the SP and obtain an annotation statement, for example.
So this is explicitly trusted, right?
So the SP has a firmware, if the firmware has a bug, you could potentially exploit it
and so forth.
Yeah, yeah, I understand.
Okay, okay, okay.
The question is, how do you actually verify and what is the verifiable minimal unit of
the code?
So yeah, in the case of a confidential VM, depending on the hardware, you essentially
can verify, you create measurements of the entire boot chain.
So it's similar to a TPM case, like a measured boot, where you have a statement of the initial
memory layout, the firmware, and then a statement of all the other components in the boot chain.
And the statement just says, this is an isolated VM, this was the boot chain, and this is signed
by AMD.
And this is what you get.
So the VM is okay, but what about process runtime?
How do you lower the code itself and how do you verify it?
Yeah.
So the process space, exactly, so your untrusted host creates the process, loads the memory
pages and then says, okay, I'm done.
And then the secure processor that's part of the CPU will create a hash over those pages
and compare that to the expected measurement that's signed by you as the author of the
enclave.
So you assign, when you build an enclave, you essentially build the expected memory
layout, you assign that, and part of the attestation statement is always this measurement of the
initial memory layout plus your signature.
I see, this is the way to authenticate the actual code before it runs.
Right.
So you somehow think of this with a runtime code, I mean, there are persons who were able
to change the top D, the kernel version on the running machine.
So what's the protection from such?
I mean, yeah, that's part of why you can say this is a bit more fuzzy in terms of what
the attestation statement says, right?
Basically anything that happens after this boot, modifying the memory layout, modifying
what's running there, you can only derive from the initial statement.
So what people do is they use read-only, file a immutable image, this kind of stuff to make
it more locked down.
For example, if you just want Mariah to be, you could bring this to a microkernel that
just is able to run a Mariah to be container, for example.
Still there's a lot of things that can happen at runtime but trying to minimize the TCP
or the trust.
So at this point it looks like a state of defense is at the entrance.
I mean, there is a path to go for sure and there will be a path to also a way to authenticate
the dynamic, the code dynamically or the runtime dynamically.
But at this point I see that this is an entrance defense.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, if you can derive all the states you will end up in from the initial state, you
will have perfect verification but this is not feasible, of course.
Thanks for answering my question.
Sure.
What memory is encrypted?
The main memory, if you're referring to caches, I'm not sure which cache is.
But you started by saying it's important to have encrypted memory.
Yes.
So what here is encrypted?
So in the confidential VM case, anything off that VM, right, from the firmware layer upwards,
anything that's above the hypervisor, for the process-based, anything that's part of
that process.
So what's the performance course for that?
Yeah, for process-based, with the latest generation, I think it's around 10%, something like that.
The bigger problem are the context switches by far.
For the right-hand side, AMD did measurements and I think they are around, worst case, like
4% to 8%.
What kind of instructions do we use to switch the context to use the Win 0?
What are the instructions that you actually need from the CPU to raise the privileges
on the CPU?
You mean if I want to?
The context switch is usually speaking to raise the CPU operation privilege.
So you want to go into kernel space?
Yes.
There are more than these for hypervisors, for the things that we have to use.
Yeah, so on a process-based, what will just happen if, let's say, you do a write syscall,
the process will trap, you will have an interrupt, and it will automatically...
Save your registers, your state, encrypted, and then clear those registers.
There were some problems in the past, but clear those registers and go to kernel space.
For the VM, they both have additional instructions for doing those confidential computing specifics,
like getting a remote attestation statement or for the confidential VM connecting through
the secure processor.
There's an instruction set addition.
As I said this week, if you do a write call for a block, the kernel, kernel will see it
unencrypted.
If you've got more questions, you need to leave them in the third order.
That's what I'm talking about.
I'll put you on the side.
Thank you.