Now, we already spoke here a little bit about developers,
and especially the front-end developers.
One purpose of this talk for me is to
really start with this bridge of the gap,
which I often see between the people who
really have a databases of
a center of their at least professional life.
Any people who are writing application and
databases of them like a thing.
It's like a toilet. You do your business anymore in your life.
I mean something like that.
For those people, the database is typically like a black box.
There is this black box,
and what I want is I
connect to the service point which is provided to me.
I connect it quickly, I run my queries,
and that's all I care about.
All that change buffer combia, never heard about it.
What about queries?
What would you as a developer think about queries?
Well, these are actually pretty simple things.
When you connect it to a service point,
you add queries you want them to complete if no errors.
You want them to provide you correct results set,
because if you wouldn't,
we could alter all the MySQL tables to
black hole and get a fantastic performance.
No errors too.
Also, you want them to make sure that they complete in
that response time what your application expects.
I think that is a very important thing to understand.
If you look at from the individual developer standpoint,
like writing application, hey,
performance response time for my queries is all I care about,
and how that's internal database kitchen works,
somebody else's problem.
Now, if you think about response time from
their database point of view,
that is often seen like,
well, I see that response time for a query
is an average or whatever distribution.
We'll talk about that later.
But that is different from what business cares about.
If you think about the business point of view,
you think about, well,
do my user have outstanding experience
in terms of performance if all of the application interactions.
That means like a search should work and place
an order should work and whatever.
Database is important part of that,
of course, but not is there a complete part.
What is interesting in this case is what as
database engineers who often talk about
those different events like a bad performance and the downtime.
Say, well, no, no, no. We weren't down.
It just was taking 50 minutes to run my very basic query.
Well, from user standpoint,
the bad performance,
very bad performance isn't distinguishable from downtime.
Because A, we don't have variance,
but then even if people are very patient,
then the browser write or some other time out will happen,
and nobody gives a shit about that query which
may still continue to be running.
Another thing to understand about
query performance is you do not want to focus on the averages.
I like this one saying,
but there was one silly demand who tried to cross
the river in the average one meter deep.
That is same applies to the query.
If your average query time is x,
well, that means pretty much nothing.
You need to understand more about that.
I like in this case to look at
their percentiles and even more to make sure you can look at
a specific distribution of a query response time.
If you're that, that gives you a lot more insight.
Now, one thing to understand about the percentile,
you may be looking at it and saying,
well, great, my queries have this decent 99 percentile.
But that does not mean on a business side,
what 99 percent of your users have a good or
like acceptable experience. Why is that?
Well, because guess what?
The single user interaction can
correspond to a lot of queries sequentially,
which all adapt and typically through
their joining user has a number of those interactions.
So I would say even 99 percentile,
that may all well depending on your application,
only correspond to 50 percent of user session.
So if you really see their complicated,
larger environments, they are really focused on
either relatively short SLA for rather high percentiles.
Another thing that I would encourage to pay attention to
is errors and make sure you
are measuring response time for those as well.
Because errors actually can be offered two kinds.
Fast errors and slow errors.
In certain cases, let's say if your table doesn't exist,
you may be like get the response time straight away.
If you put all your error queries
and actually normal queries in the same bucket,
you may say, oh my gosh,
my response times are doing so well.
But on the other hand, if your query is, for example,
error is a lock-weight timeout,
then that is a slow error.
It actually will have a high response time than the normal cases.
That is why I always suggest to make sure we
measure response time for normal queries
and for queries of problems differently.
Another thing which is very important is looking at
response time over time because traffic changes,
a lot of things are going on in the system and just saying,
hey, I'll have a response time of x over some long period of time.
It's not very helpful.
Also, what you would see in many cases,
if you still start those like a small performance problems,
like SLA violations which are if unfixed,
they convert in the downtime.
Like for example, in my SQL world,
you may say, well, I have forgotten this runaway query.
And my history accumulates.
It will slowly increase and increase your response time.
If you measure that over time and say, well,
something is not trending in the right directions,
you probably can fix it before that will
be seen as a downtime by your users.
If you are not, then not so much.
This is example what we have here.
You often may see something like this as well
for where all the queries have like a spike in the response time,
which you often make a response to
something external happening in the environment.
I think here is what is very interesting,
especially for us running in the Cloud,
we only have limited observability to environment.
If there's some shit going on on
an Amazon backend, they're not going to tell us that.
You know what, we had let's say some free hard drives failed,
which back our EBS and we had to some rebalance yada yada.
The another question I would ask is where we want to
measure response time from queries.
In my opinion, both application view and database view
in the combinations are very
helpful because the application can see real thing.
If your network, for example,
is adding some latency or whatever,
then you will see that from application,
not so much from a database,
because it's only sees from,
hey, I got response to then it's sent the data back.
But the database view allows you often to see
a lot more insight about what had been going on inside,
where from application side,
we often can just capture the query time,
maybe some very basic additional parameters. So,
what is spoke from our business view?
Well, we already said what that all users have
outstanding performance experience of
all the application interactions.
Let's now try to break it down a little bit
more to what that may mean.
In this case, I want to introduce
this little project of Laga from you.
This is SQL Commendure project by Google,
which is pretty cool in terms of what it's
allows to pass you the metadata,
which you understand as developer all the way to SQL query.
They implemented that support
from a number of frameworks,
and it's also supported in
their Google Cloud monitoring environment.
I would very much see that developed more,
and for at least ask them to some shared standards
between the databases or whatever,
how we can augment query information with tags,
values which users care about.
So, what are the possibilities which can be
quite helpful in this regard?
Well, finding, for example,
who is our actual user attendant,
who is query corresponds because we often may
have different performance issues.
Finding the application,
like some subset of application functionality
where many of them may be hitting the application.
Version information, maybe information about
their engineer of a team who is responsible.
I often see DBAs or SRAs team having problem like,
oh, I see this nasty query which was shipped yesterday.
I know because it was shipped today
because I know it wasn't fair yesterday,
but now having to find out who
a hell introduced that stupid query,
maybe problematic in a large environment.
Now, a lot of focus and I think the core of
a query based observability may be about the query.
By query, I mean obviously like a query with
the same except different parameters.
That is very helpful because well,
obviously they have a different complexity,
different expected SLA and so on and so forth.
The next way also to break things down for me would be to
look at the schema or database.
Why is that interesting?
I just noticed right now what it's been cut a bit.
See? Well, anyway, life is life.
I'm just not going to be lucky in this room right here.
But well, we can blame our windows, right?
On this conference, we can and should blame windows.
Well, why schema and database are also good?
Because often you would separate in
a multi-tenant applications different tenants by schema.
In that case, that gives us a good profiling for performance
of different schemas like we can see here.
An example of this PMM tool.
Another thing what I found is very helpful to find
a way to separate the data by different tables.
In many cases, you want to say, hey, you know what?
How queries hitting given table is affected,
especially if it did some change which relates to a table.
Hey, you know what? I changed the indexing on this table.
Let me see how all the queries hitting this table is impacted.
Very helpful because there may be some surprising differences.
Database users, that is another thing which is quite
helpful because that often allows us to
identify the service application.
If you're following good security practices,
you would not let all your applications
just use one username, not a good idea.
Also find human troublemakers which are
doing having direct access.
So many times you'll find somebody running
a query and say, okay, well, yeah,
it's slow but wherever I'll go for lunch,
I have time. Well, you may have time,
but your database may not.
Here's an example how we provide that.
I also mentioned database host and indexes in
many instances in many cases that is very helpful
because even if you may think,
oh, my different database instance should perform the same.
Well, world is a messy place and world in the Cloud is even
messy place, they may not exactly have
the same performance due to
some strange configuration differently,
having a bad day or even maybe having a different load.
That is a good to be able to break it down.
Right then you see some of your queries are not
performing very well. I would also look at
the same stuff from a web server or application server instance.
Because again, if you have maybe like a 100 nodes,
you deploy this application, you may think, hey,
we're all going to perform the same,
hitting the database, well,
that is not always the case.
They have seen changes from people saying,
one of them is misconfigured or for some reason
cannot connect the cache.
So it's hitting 10 times more queries
right on the database than it should be,
or the application rollout didn't go well,
where you've eliminated nasty query on 99 of application instance,
but not some others.
It's very good to actually be able to validate that.
Because what you would see,
or like I gave from a DBA standpoint,
developers, sysad means storage people,
they are going to tell you shit,
but they are going to lie.
They are going to lie.
Maybe not intentionally,
maybe cause of a ignorance and limitation of fair tool,
but as a DBA, a CD or something,
you want to point them out to where you can say,
look, this, I have evidence.
Evidence is good.
So clients cost.
Custom tags is very helpful if you can extend.
That is what we spoke about SQL commenters,
something else, which I find very helpful,
which we cannot quite easily get with MySQL,
but being able to separate the query by the query plans.
Often you may have a query which looks the same,
but it may take different execution plans.
And often that may be correlated to its performance.
In certain cases, it is totally fine,
very different situations.
Sometimes MySQL optimizer may get a little bit crazy
just and have that optimizer plan brief for no good reason,
which may not be very easy to catch,
and it would be helpful to do.
What I also would like to highlight
is when you find the specific query and say,
hey, this query has nasty performance,
you often want to understand
where that query response time comes from.
And that is some of the things where it can come from.
Surin-FM are relatively easy to find out.
Surin are not very well.
For example, wherever query has waited on available CPU
because system was overly saturated,
well, you can't really see on per query basics.
You can only see those things, well,
my CPU was kind of like a super packed
right on a period of time.
Okay, here are a couple of other things
to consider when you're looking at the queries.
One, you want to really look separately at the bad queries
versus victims, because sometimes you will see,
oh, queries are getting slower,
but it's not because of them.
It's about some other nasty queries.
Maybe that is your Java developer who thought,
well, to solve my problems,
I will just launch with stuff with 200 threads,
and make sure I am good,
but everything else is kind of slowed down.
And that's maybe tricky.
One thing is what you should not forget
the currently running queries.
In many cases, like if you look in performance schema queries
by digest, that gives you what happened in the past.
But believe me, if you started 50 instances
of some very bad query, which continues to run,
well, that may be the reason of your problem, not the past.
And to connect to that, I think it is less problem
in my school right now if you're using query timeouts,
which is a very good practice,
because if you say, hey, you know what,
for all my interactive queries, by default,
I set the timeout of, let's say, 15 seconds,
then you should not care too much about your past queries,
because, well, you know what,
everything gets killed after 15 minutes.
Also, 50 seconds, right?
You should not ignore the stuff which is invisible
from a query standpoint, right?
Databases do a lot of shit in the background.
You may also do things, or your operation teams,
like, well, backups, or provisioning
another node for cloning, right?
Or the clouds, or wherever your VM system
need to do something in the background,
it may not be directly visible,
but that can impact your query performance, right?
So sometimes, well, when you observe a query impact,
and you can't really see what is causing that,
it's possible.
I also would encourage to avoid
what I would call a biased something.
I see people sometimes would say, hey, you know what,
we will set long query time to one second,
and only look at the queries
which are more than one second in length.
Well, you may be only focusing on the outliers, right?
And missing the possibility to optimize other queries, right?
Or actually even focusing on the queries
which a response of providing that experience, right,
for your users.
Okay, we find another thing,
like a last minute I have, or something.
I wanted to say, hey, what I would like to see
from my school to do better.
Who is Kenny?
No Kenny?
Yes, he's always hiding, right?
He probably wanted to get another sandwich, damn it.
Okay, so here are some things that I would like to see.
One is better support of prepared statements, right?
And right now, right, it's kind of,
not done in the same way, right?
Which is, I think is a problem, right?
Now, I would say consider grouping data by time.
In certain cases right now, you get like
all the statements in one table, right?
And you have a lot of statement variety,
that table tends to overflow, right?
Which is not really helpful, right?
And if you have to kind of reset your queries all the time,
that is not very good practice in my opinion.
Provide list of tables query touches, right?
That is very helpful because, well,
my school parser already knows it, right?
It knows tables query touches,
but it's very hard to parse it out from a query,
especially if you consider views, right?
I don't know by looking at the query alone,
wherever something is a table or a view, right?
So in this case, information about plan ID, right?
I would like to see for the query, right?
Some sort of plan hash or something so I know
then query is using something like that.
And also what I would call like a top weight summary, right?
Right now we have information about the weights
in MySQL performance query and about query,
but I cannot see and say, oh, that query was slow
because it spent XYZ amount of weight on something
or whatever, right?
Or at least kind of like a small class of queries, right?
I don't think that's convenient.
Well, with that, that's all I had to say.
Hope that will help you to avoid tuning your indexes
by the credit card.
And yes.
Oh, I have a time for questions.
You told me like Peter, five minutes.
Oh, to answer I have a time for questions.
Yes, any questions?
No, oh yeah.
What's the difference or advantages
of this SQL command of things
compared to what open tracing standard
as because task of tracing the whole thing?
What's the difference of SQL command?
Well, what I would say in this case, yes.
I mean, there is obviously open tracing framework, right?
Which you can use.
This gets specifically to the database
and specifically in every query, right?
If you look at the open tracing framework,
I think, you know, getting every query, right?
Maybe a lot of volume out there, right?
And again, I also think, well, the good thing
if also SQL command, right, is what that does
it automatically, if you will, right?
That does not require to take an extra integration.
Okay, anybody else?
The PMN tool, is it like, it works also with MariaDB?
Yeah, I mean, it works with MariaDB as well.
Yes?
Are there some good practices you can do
to avoid your query just randomly going
down a different plan?
Well, there are practices, there are no good practices.
Like, you can, there is a lot of optimizer hints
you can use, right?
So you can actually force the query to go
like this particular stuff, right?
But that also prevents optimizer choosing different plan
if better plan becomes available.
Yeah?
Never use forced index, always use ignore index
and you will mostly avoid what Peter just warned you about.
Okay.
Okay, well, then thank you folks.
Thank you.