Okay, thank you. It's great to be here for the first time. Really in person, I really
feel...
Yes, you're a regular feature actually.
So far only online, it was so sad always, always in my small little room. So here I
am. I want to talk about fusion again, like the last years. What I want to talk about
here is about algebraic effects and types and what has changed in the last year in that
respect in the fusion language.
Short background to me, I did a lot on compilers and mostly in the Java area in the past for
about 30 years and also did quite a bit on garbage collection. So I enjoyed the previous
talks here quite a lot. But now to the fusion language, which is what I'm currently working
on, the main idea behind the fusion language is that we see more and more language getting
more and more overloaded with more and more features and concepts and new things being
introduced while in fusion we try to reduce this to one single concept, which is a fusion
feature. That's basically an abstraction for things like classes, methods, interfaces and
so on.
Instead of having the developer to choose what to write, whether to write a method or
a class or so, have the compiler, have the implementation make these decisions, what
we actually need to implement those features.
And also we see that more and more systems become safety critical, so we need a simple
language and we need tools to analyze that simple language to ensure the correctness.
So that's what we keep in mind when we work on fusion. Fusion is on GitHub. I don't give
any tutorial in the language also here in this talk. This is all online, so I will just
basically throw you in the water and let you learn to swim bringing fusion code in this
talk, but I hope, I think you will do fine. Fusion is backed by a small company, Tokiba.
Now to this talk. No, before I forget, for those who only came for the fusion stickers,
I have some here, so you can maybe give them around, whoever once can take one.
So now what I want to talk about here is basically three points. I start with explaining what
algebraic effects are and how they are implemented or how they are used in fusion. Then I want
to talk a bit about types and how types can be used as first class features and type values
can be used in fusion. And then I bring these two together because that brings a big advantage
when working with algebraic effects. So what do we need effects for? Fusion, in fusion
a feature is a pure function, so there is no side effects, no mutation of data by default.
And algebraic effects are used in fusion now to model all the non-functional effects like
state changes, I owe, any threat communication or mechanisms like exceptions. So let me first
define what are algebraic effects. An algebraic effect is actually a set of operations. You
could think of operations like reading data, so performing some I owe, getting the time
or doing something like a panic, so causing an error in the application to stop, or logging
some data somewhere. Typically these operations in an algebraic effect model some non-functional
aspect that is kind of orthogonal to the actual computation of your function. These operations
have basically two things that they can mainly do. They could either resume and produce a
result like reading that is successful, or they can abort, which is like throwing an
exception, you just get out of that, you don't get anything from this. And an effect can
be implemented by different effect handlers. So one effect type could have different implementations.
And to run code that uses an effect, this code has to be executed while a corresponding
handler for that effect is installed. Now the effects allow static analysis of the code
that we can analyze what effects any feature has. And we require that for all library code
the full set of effects is documented in the signature of those features. So effects that
are not presented are not affected are used that will cause a compile time error. I start
with a small example of a hello world feature. We use this exclamation mark syntax to mark
that this code actually uses an effect and the effect or requires an effect. And that
is I ordered out in this case because the library function say requires that effect.
And I run this code now, of course it prints hello world. And if I analyze the code for
the effects that it has, I see that I ordered out is an effect required by this small example.
Now I want to run the same code, the hello world hasn't changed, using my own handler.
So I've defined a handler here which is a feature inherited thing from can print and
it redefines the print operation to print to IO error instead and to replace the exclamation
mark by many exclamation marks. And now to run this we need to first install this handler
as the IO out handler. The IO out here is just a convenience function that installs
the first handler and executes the code given in the lambda as a second argument. And when
I run this now, of course, I see the print out is the modified string because we've replaced
the exclamation mark here. And if I analyze this for effects, I now see this no longer
depends on the IO out effect but the IO error because we have kind of diverted the code
to depend on the other effect. We could also implement a handler that doesn't do anything
then the hello world executed in that environment would not require any effect at all anymore.
That much to effects now let me talk about types as first class features in fusion. To
make it a bit easier for you to understand what's happening, I give first an example
of generics in Java where I have a generic method here that takes an argument A of any
generic type T and prints out the value. Doing that in fusion, we have type parameters which
are actually at the same level as value parameters. So we have a function with two arguments,
T which is a type and A which is a value of that type. And this is not just syntactic
sugar that this looks the same but it's also internally the type parameters feature, our
state features just as the arguments itself. Of course, we can now call this function with
two different type parameters and two different value arguments and print these two values.
That's pretty standard for generic for type parametric functions. Fusion uses a lot of
type inferencing. So in such a case where the types are obvious from the arguments,
they don't need to be given. So we have the rule that type parameters always have to precede
the value arguments and they can be left out if they can be inferred. So the code can be
written like this.
The next we could constrain type parameters. So we could say in this case we want a type
that must be numeric. And if you have such a constraint, we could use operations that
are only provided by the type like the plus operator that is defined on numerics. And
if you run this now, we can also output the double value. Still pretty standard for generics.
But what we can also do is we can use the type parameter itself and call features that
the type parameter provides. Every type provides its name. So we can run this code and print
those names.
And we can go even further with that. And I want to show you in an implementation of
a feature that calculates the sum of a list of some numeric elements. The implementation
of that feature would distinguish the case of an empty list or a list consisting out
of a head and a tail where we can recursively calculate the sum. The question now is what
do we do in the case of the empty list? In languages like Java, we would have no way
to produce any value here. What we can do is we can call a feature that is defined in
the type numeric and redefined by all concrete implementations to provide the zero value
for that actual numeric type. So numeric itself is defined as a feature with its corresponding
type defining zero as an instance of exactly this type. And then something like an I32,
a 32-bit integer, defines an implementation of type.zero to return the integer zero.
And we can now use that function to print the sums of different lists here. And when
I do this, we have a list of floating point values, a list of fractions. We have an empty
list of floating point values and an empty list of fractions. So we get the corresponding
zero values from the types of the corresponding types. So that much to types. And now coming
back to effects, I want to use these types and type parameters to give names to effects
or to reference user-defined effects. And I'll give you an example using a code that
creates a linked ring. So a ring structure. To create a ring structure with references,
you need mutation because at some point you have to close the ring. So that code require
is mutable, is not easily pure. Then, so we will see that this depends on the mutate effect.
And then we want to re-implement this or extend this to use local mutable state, local mutability
to make this function pure. So I start by code to create a ring that uses the mutate
effect. You don't need to understand the whole code. The important thing is that every element
in that ring has a pointer to the next element. And there's a reference to the very last because
if you extend the ring, you have to update the next of the last element in the ring to
point to the newly added element in the ring. And here for next we create a mutable value
which is done by a base library function mut, which use the mutate effect. And to update
the next, we use this error operation to update that. Now we create, in a small demo, we create
a ring with elements ABC. And then we run 10 times through the ring to print them. So
we do that. We see that it circles around in that ring. But if you now analyze this
for effects, what we see is that we have a mutate effect in, used by the code. There's
lots of other effects as well, the out effect because we print something. But there's also
error handling in the library code that shows up here. But what I'm interested in is here
is now this has the mutate effect because the code mutates the next element while building
the ring. And now we want to get rid of this mutability in the code. I know. I think I'll
make it in five minutes. And the way to do this is we define a local instance of the
mutate effect. And to do that, I first need a bit more space in the code. And I'll add
a type parameter, M of type mutate, to the code here. And also pass this on calls, on
types of ring used in here. And now when we create an instance of a mutable reference
to the next element, instead we take the instance of the mutate effect M, which we got as a
parameter here, from the current environment. The syntax we use in Fusion there is type.n,
which is the effect from the environment, plus dot and the operation new create a new
mutable variable. And now we can define our own mutate effect. Here mm is the local mutate
effect defined here, which is just inheriting from mutate. And is nothing follows after
the is, so it doesn't do anything special. It is just a new subfeature inheriting from
mutate. So it basically only has the purpose of giving a new name to this is my local mutate
here. And now we can pass this sub instance of mutate, or the subtype of mutate, to the
ring here, which means that all the mutable values that are created are created locally
to the mm to our own mutate effect. Now we still have to create this effect and execute
the code within the context of this effect. And this happens in the bottom here. So we
create an instance of mm and use it to execute the demo code. And that means that the m.f
nf call here will then take the instance of mm from the current environment to create
the new mutable value. And when we run the demo, the same output. If we analyze it for
effects now, we see it's the same effect apart from the mutate is gone, because the mutate
is completely local here. So we can create code that locally, to perform some calculation,
creates mutable data and mutates data structures. But the result is a pure function anyway,
because the mutation is only done locally. So I'm coming to the end. Fusion status is
still under-developing. It's a very experimental language, but the language definition is slowly
getting more stable. There's still a lot of work on the base library that is ongoing.
There are currently, the current implementation has two backends. One is a very slow interpreter
running on a JVM. And the other is a C backend, which also used the BMD-Mviser garbage collector,
which we just learned about as a garbage collector right now. But I would like to have a precise
garbage collector and add a lot there as well. And basic analysis tools, like you've seen
for the effects here, are available. And yes, those who remember Ellie might wonder who's
disturbing me now while I'm working on this is Felix. That's it. That's coming to the
end. So maybe one more sentence. I hope I could show you that algebraic effects and
types as first-class features are something that complements one another pretty well.
And it helps to create code, then encapsulates non-functional effects. And yes, it makes
it possible to work with this and work even with code that is not pure, but to manage
this in a nice way. You find some links here to resources related to Fusion. We're happy
for everyone who gets involved. Please have a look. Join us. We have a small team currently
from three working on this. We can, there should be more. Thank you very much. Can I
pick? Yeah. Thank you.
So earlier you said that a particular type can implement numeric. Is that a word terminology
you use, but is it a numeric interface? And then you were able to say A plus B. If you
didn't say that it's a numeric, what would happen if you tried to compile that program?
The question was if a particular type would not implement numeric and you would use the
plus in there, what would happen then? You would get a compile-time error. It's completely
strict typing. So if you call a function that requires a numeric type parameter and you
call it with, say, a string, well, a string happens to have a plus, but not the numeric
plus, you will get an error that type, the actual type parameter is not compatible to
the type constraint in the code features. So that will not be excellent.
And the same example you were converting the value to string in order to print it. Is the
string operation implied to be present for every value?
There's a two-string operation in our any, which is the parent of any feature. So a two-string
is always available, yes. It's not very helpful if you don't define anything because you just
have to do it. I'm contributing to the language code name,
which also have an effect types and I have one for people who are generic code. One problem
that I've seen in combining these features is that when you have generic code, you often
don't, you can create instantiations when you trigger different effects. So how do you
approach this kind of syntactically or even simultaneously the language?
The question was that actual code can actually trigger all sorts of different actual effects
at runtime. So you could have, one example I think of, you could have a function converting
in an object to a string that maybe performs some logging and some other code printing
that value would not expect that. My answer to that is that must be part of the static
analysis. We need to analyze the whole application and see what is happening there. Library functions
can do this to a certain extent, but they cannot predict if you have a dynamic value
coming in, what the actual type will be. So we need a whole program analysis in the end
there. Do we have time for one more? We will.
So the question was, in Haskell you have multiple
monads which have a similar role like the effects, but you have them always explicitly,
you have to carry them around and mark them. The answer is here, this is actually, it's
on purpose. We don't want to have the hassle of wrapping everything into a monad and carrying
it around all the time. So the idea is to get rid of this as much as possible without
losing the information you get from the effects. Thank you for all the questions.