I'm Marco Makkala. I've been working on E-NODB code for 20 years almost and today I will
talk about one of my pet heads in E-NODB, this change buffer, which I long time suspected
that it's causing bugs but I couldn't prove all of them. So I took a car analogies because
some software people like car analogies are unsafe at any speed. It's from the 1960s.
I'm a bicycle person myself. So what was the change buffer good for? It was something developed
in the times of the spinning raster, hard disks. The idea was that when you are doing
sequential I-O, like page reads or page writes, sequentially then the read-write head will
move less on the hard disk. If you are doing random CX it could take a long time to position
the head to the correct track and then wait for the sector to come under the track when
it's rotating. So the idea of the change buffer was that instead of reading something
from a page and then applying a change to that page, you would write a buffer change
to somewhere else. So if a B3 secondary in a sleeve page is not in the memory, in that
case we could, instead of reading the page to perform an insert, originally it was only
insert buffering, we would write that insert operation into a separate insert buffer tree
and then later when some other operation needs to read the page it would merge the changes
in that buffer to the page. And these structures are persistent, so even the insert buffering
could happen years ago and then at some point years later somebody wants to access that
page and then you get the trouble. This was extended in MySQL 5.5 to cover delete operations
and purge operations. Deleting in InnoDB only marks the record for deletion, same for update
of a key in a secondary index, it will do delete marking and insert. So the purge is
what is actually removing the record. Those operations could be buffered but not rollback
of an insert, that was never buffered. And this leads to lots of problems like the change
buffer is located in the InnoDB system tablespace and up to this time there is no mechanism
to shrink the system tablespace. If you at some point use the change buffer a lot, the
system tablespace will grow by some hundreds of gigabytes, there is no way to reclaim that
space. In MariaDB we are working on something to help with that but it's not done yet. And
then this obvious right amplification, if you are doing an insert, that's rather fine.
Instead of doing just one insert, you are doing two inserts, you are doubling the write,
plus you have to write some metadata, some index information so that the contents of
the page can be interpreted correctly because the change buffer doesn't have access to the
data dictionary. But for delete or delete marking, if you apply the change directly
to the page, you would write one byte or a couple of bytes, now you have to copy the
entire record which you are going to delete or delete mark to the change buffer and the
metadata and then at some point it will be merged. And then there is some overhead, even
if you are disabling the change buffer you still have some overhead, you have to maintain
some metadata saying how full your pages are. If somebody is going to enable the change
buffering or insert buffering later, this data has to be accurate otherwise you would
get a page overflow. The insert buffering must know that the page will not get too full
when you are buffering the insert and merging later. And then we got lots of nice corruptions
where the secondary index gets out of sync with the primary key index. And these are
very hard to reproduce. So why is it hard to reproduce? Well, the first part is the
same as on the previous slide. It is exactly this that you cannot easily control when the
change buffer merge happens. It's like the Spanish Inquisition in the month is Python
Sketch. Nobody expects a change buffer merge. And to reproduce something, either as a user
you are unlucky and as a tester you are lucky if you can reproduce this and you need lots
of luck to get that because especially this purging of the history which is deleting records
from the index, it can be blocked by reviews. If you have long-running transactions which
are holding a review open, that will prevent purge from running. And then at some point
that review will be closed and purge can start running. And then there is also this buffer
pool. If a page is locked by something, it can't be written out and it can be evicted
from the buffer pool. So the change buffer can't be used. And we have a debug setting
that forces that, okay, user is asking for operation that could use the change buffer
and we see the page is in the buffer pool. We are going to the evil and we evict the
page. But we cannot do that because somebody could be holding a latch on that page or the
current thread is holding a latch and the page was modified. And we cannot wait for
page writes to happen because this latch is blocking the page write. So this is really
difficult to test. And there was a recent fix to some hangs which were introduced in
MySQL 5.7. We have that fix in the release that is coming up out next week. That one
will make it even more tricky, this debug option. So in order for this to be effective, they
have to do some smart tricks like abandon some tables for a while and let them cool
down, use some other tables meanwhile and then come back.
Well, we got some nice magic tools as well. We have this random query generator. It's
also used at MySQL. And a grammar simplifier. We could start with the huge grammar of all
of the SQL covering all the features and let it run. If the crash was frequent enough,
then we could use this grammar simplifier. But in this case, this is very hard to reproduce
back. We cannot use the simplifier. We cannot get any simpler grammar. We just have to run
it all and hope for the best. But then we got this debugger, rr, record and replay.
That one is really a huge productivity boost. We started using it maybe two or three years
ago. So when you are able to reproduce a problem while running it under rr, what you would
do is that you will save a trace, a deterministic trace of an execution that is interleaving
processes or threads that are being monitored by it. It saves the system calls and the results
and so on. And these threads can be debugged as many times as you want. You just need the
same binaries, same libraries and compatible processor. Then you can run it. And you can
set break points. You can set data watch points. And you can execute in forward and backward
direction. You can see what happened before the bad thing was observed. And this can also
be used for optimized code. You are debugging an optimized executable, then the debugger
complains that some variable has been optimized out. Well, then you can just single step some
instructions and get it from the registers because you can go backwards in time.
So now I'm coming to describe one bug that we found last year. And actually there was
a support customer last week who hit this bug or a consequence of this bug. So we had
a bug that was doing this change buffer merge. It would hang because the change buffer got
corrupted and we were testing some fixes in a branch for that. And then we got this assertion
failure. This assertion failure essentially means that when it tried to insert a record
that was insert buffered, it ran out of space in the page. And what was the reason? Well,
there were some extra records in the page. And it turned out that, well, this is partly
by design. Heik Kitori, the creator of InnoDB, he was a friend of lazy deletion or lazy operations.
So drop index wouldn't clear anything from the change buffer. It would leave the garbage
behind. And later on, if the same page is allocated for something else, then we would
pay the price and free the space from the change buffer, delete the records. And in
MySQL 5.7, there was a new feature, bulk insert creation or building indexes faster.
And that codebase didn't do this adjustment correctly. It only cleared some bit, but it
didn't remove the records. And there was a mandatory Oracle security thing I took several
years ago before switching to MariaDB. It said something like, complexity is the friend
of security bugs. I found it somehow fitting here. So the immediate root cause of this
failure was that this new code cleared a bit that says that there are buffer changes for
this page. So when somebody is going to use that page, he will see that, okay, there's
nothing to do. I don't have to care about the change buffer. And then later on, something
adds records to the page. And then these old records from the change buffer will come to
the page as part of a merge. And how can we prove this using this RR tool? By the way,
you can download the slides from the first in page. And you can also download an attachment
that has a script replay recording of the RR session. So I'm only showing some high
level view here, but you can download a debugger session that shows the exact commands and
the output, which I'm going to present in the next slides. So the short version, how
we can prove these claims in the debugger, we let it continue from the start to the crash
or the assertion failure. Then we set the break point on a function that was the last
one to access the change buffer bitmap bits. And from that function, we get the address
of the bitmap bits for this page. And we can set the data watch point on that. And I found
this hardware watch points are very powerful tool. It's really much easier for some things
when you don't have an idea which code is going to modify or read something. And then
based on this watch point, we get some call stacks where this change buffer bits were
last changed. And then we set the break points on functions that insert records into the
change buffer and delete records from there. And then we observe that, okay, there was
nothing to delete records from the, for this page and basically proving this claim. So
we are printing the index ID and index name to get some more detail to this proof.
Oh, sorry. Okay, so we were unable to reproduce this with a small grammar. We just took something
and we got lucky and got the trace and debugged it. A possible consequences of this bug are
the wrong results. And that's of course, very difficult to prove. We don't have any testing
tools to prove that really, or not many tools, or you could get the crash on change buffer
merge. Like here we got, and that change buffer merge could happen anytime, even if you are
running check table or check if your table is okay, then before my skull, my, my, maybe
10.6, your server would crash because of this change buffer corruption. So in our case,
it's what was a page overflow when applying an insert and change buffer doesn't allow
any pages splitting. It must fit in the page. In the support case I mentioned one week ago,
the case was that the page split failed. It ran out of space. You are taking one page,
you are trying to copy part of the records to a new page and it ran out of space. How
can that be? It turned out that the page content records for some other index, which apparently
had been dropped earlier and that index apparently had not null columns. So the length of a variable
length field was interpreted, was stored there for that index where this correct index would
have the null bitmap. And then we would read the length of the record from a previous byte
and that's how we would get this too long records being copied. Oh, five minutes left.
I have to hurry up. So this, the parking, how it goes in detail, we continue to the
end of the execution from the start, which, and then we reverse continue to go back from
the abort signal. Then we set the temporary break point to this bitmap page access. Then
we get, get to that break point and we get the, in a register we happen to have the byte
address of the bitmap byte, which we are interested in. And then we reverse continue the, to the
changes of that bit byte. So the last occurrence of that was for an insert that was buffered
after the add index. And we continue from that. We see that this, the previous occurrence
is the add index that is clearing the flag. And from that we can get the page number,
which is affected and we can get the index ID and index name and the SQL statement, which
is alter table. And then we set some more break points on this insert buffer delete
and insert operations, set the condition that we want it only for this page. And then we
reverse continue, we get the insert that was buffered before this add index. Apparently
there was a drop index in between, but I didn't add statements to get a break point there
this time. So the index name is different after the add index and index ID is different.
And there was no call to the change buffer deletion. When we continue from this point
to the end of the execution, we just reach the assertion failure again without any change
buffer record deletion in between. So I'm quoting this finished ski jumper, who apparently
was confusing to French phrases. He was wishing him a good trip when he is starting to do
the ski jumping. And I'm wishing good trip for anybody who is using the change buffer.
So, and the deja vu, yes, we have seen this shutdown hang actually earlier. There was
a 10.1, MariaDB 10.1 support customer case. They got this hang and we had to do something
to fix that. But in MariaDB 10.5, we made an other change, hopefully to reduce the chances
of getting like random change buffer merge bugs because basically after this change buffer
merge only happens when SQL statement needs that change buffer merge to happen. No background
operation. So we had to adjust that previous fix for the 10.5 code base, but that was not
adjusted correctly. And we were not able to reproduce this corruption or this hang earlier.
So only quite lately we were able to reproduce it and then we were able to debug it properly.
There are some other corruption caused by the change buffer. And one thing I want to
notice that in MariaDB 10.6 recently there was a fix that we should not crash on any
page corruption. If there are any cases where we are still crashing, I would be interested
in details. And this includes a check table when there is a crash, when there is a failure
during change buffer merge, it will not cause a crash. There was a mystery bug filed like
12 years ago, MySQL bug. The customer got a crash during change buffer merge because
the page got empty as a result of applying a purge operation. I can think of several
bugs that have been fixed in MariaDB that could be the explanation. The last one, this
one from the previous example, that cannot apply because that only was introduced in
MySQL 5.7 which they didn't use. And of this list, the 30422, it's a clone of MySQL fix
which is applicable to MariaDB 10.3 and 10.4. Others I don't think have been fixed in MySQL
yet. So this teaches us that it really pays off to analyze any obscure failure you get
from running with RR because there are games in there. And I think that assertions are
like lottery tickets. If you don't write assertions in your code, then you can't win
these kind of bug findings. And if you sometimes you can lose, you can write a bogus assertion,
okay, you make mistake, you correct it and improve the assertion and then hopefully you
will get something better later. Yeah, we have some mitigation for this in MariaDB.
We don't access the data file when executing drop table. So in that case, we are avoiding
maybe more crashes on drop table. And there was a bug in Unity with slow shutdown that
the change buffer merge wouldn't check for log file overflow. So if the user got impatient
and killed the server because it's taken too long time, then they could end up with unrecoverable
database. And some more mitigation that we did, we disabled this change buffer by default,
we deprecated the parameter and we removed the change buffer in the 11.0 release. The
upgrade code for handling it, it was tested and I hope that if there is some corruption
notice during the upgrade, it should still be possible to go back to the earlier version
and then do something to correct. Yes, if there are any records in the change buffer,
we ignore, we don't trust these bitmap bits. We go through the change buffer records and
if there are any, we will apply them. Yeah, so that was basically what I wanted to say.
And maybe this last slide, it's a good thing to have a nice layer design. If you optimize
things by breaking this layer boundaries, then you're asking for trouble. That's basically
what we can learn from this. Question. You said that you fixed a few things in MariaDB
and they're not yet fixed in upstream. Are there bugs open upstream for fixing these
things? I haven't filed any. I lost my skull bug account when I resigned Oracle. Okay,
well, I'll velocity that with you so we can get this fixed in upstream file. Yeah, you
are welcome to file bugs and maybe they will be fixed. Especially if it's a crashing bug.
Yeah, but you can't repeat them so you have a hard time proving that. Well, there are
tools obviously now to do that which weren't obvious before. I'm very persistent. Like
once we know it exists in MariaDB and it has been fixed, somebody that is persistent enough
should be able to. Yeah, but Oracle is not allowed to look at Oracle. Yes, I know. So
how can they know how we can do it? I am so I can open the bug and I can't. You can't
copy the code because then they're not allowed to see it. I'll find a bug report. Yes. How
bad is the RR over 10? It is very bad. I mean, it's running, if you have multiple threats
or processes, it's running them in a single on a single CPU core at the time. So that's
why we are running hundreds of servers in parallel on a single server for several hours
to get these traces. For normal debugging, maybe twice as slow as that. Actually also
for normal debugging, there have been cases like if you have lots of conditional branches
in your code, like this debug library or performance schema, that's causing those branches are
never taken, but because RR is interested in conditional branches, I have seen a case
where if I compile without these things, I get a crash or problem in, let's say like
three seconds. And then I was curious, how long does it take if I use this stupid compilation
options with this extra conditions for that particular thing, I interrupted it after two
hours. So it was 7,000 seconds versus three seconds. So don't use conditional branches
or unnecessary like debugging. Turn off all the code that you don't need. The conditional
branches are evil for RR. But I have only four ways to debug code. There are no problems.
But maybe you are not using it on like multi-threaded with context, switches and so on. Yeah, for
single thread, there is basically no overhead.