Hello everyone.
Alright, thank you.
So I am Harshit Gangal.
I work for PlanetScale and I am a maintainer of VITAS and today I am going to talk about
life of a query.
Why not?
Because I work in query serving team in VITAS.
So what is VITAS basically?
VITAS is nothing but it is used to scale out your MySQL and it also manages your MySQL
for you.
It is a CNCF gadget project and it is open source with Apache license 2.0.
So this is the architecture of VITAS which is basically there are so many components
but today we will just focus on few of them which is one is VT gate where your application
connects to and then we have VT tablet where once the application connects to VT gate then
the queries are sent over there and then you have the MySQL where actually your data are
getting stored.
Let us talk about few terminologies which I will be using across my presentation which
is one is Keyspace.
Keyspace is a logical representation of a database and it is basically a collection
of your physical databases.
Shard, it is basically a subset of your data which resides in a Keyspace and there is some
term called Windex.
Windex is similar to your MySQL indexes which is basically it is maintained by the VITAS
and there is a thing called primary Windexes which means it will decide where your row
actually live in a particular shard or in particular table.
So once your query comes in then it decides like okay this row while inserting where it
should actually which shard it should actually go to.
So let us take some query right then we will go further.
So let us say we have two tables customer and order table and what we want to do is
we want to find a customer who has at least a spend of 1000 rupees, 1000 bucks basically
in their whole order history.
So we have to take two tables we take a join and do grouping on them and take a filter
on top of it.
So first thing first, so now the clients want to send a query to you how they will do it.
So first the client has to connect to something called VIT gates and so they can use MySQL
protocol.
You have your vanilla, you have all the MySQL drivers like in different languages you have
and you can use the already available MySQL driver to connect directly to VIT gate.
VIT gate supports the MySQL protocol so you do not have to do anything on that front.
But it also supports GRPC and it was supported earlier before we implemented the MySQL protocol
but it still stays here for its own benefits.
And the reason is like in MySQL protocol once you connect it is like your session is tied
which means if you open a transaction you have to commit transaction using that.
But in GRPC what the initial benefit you get is you can connect to any VIT gate and you
start a transaction over there and then you can connect to any other VIT gate and you
can commit a transaction using that VIT gate.
So let's talk about the different phases that we have to go through.
Once the query is now received by the VIT gate it has to go through parsing, rewriting,
planning and execution and we'll talk in details about each of the phases but this
is what the VIT gate does once it receives the query on its end.
So in the parsing phase now you receive the query now basically it will parse it to know
the whether the operaries syntactically correct or not and once it is syntactically correct
then it construct the abstract syntax free output of it.
So it will have the select expression from clauses, group by and the having for the query
we mentioned before.
Now once it's parsed it goes into the rewriting phase and it's very important to have this
rewriting phase because we are trying to mimic a thing like as a single data store though
your data is distributed across multiple shards and this rewriting phase what we try to do
is basically we first try to see oh is there any literals is anything which you can parameterize.
So once we are done with the planning phase we don't have to plan again and again similar
kind of query.
So what we do is we say okay here's I see 1000 but I don't need to plan specifically
for 1000 so I just make it a parameter and then I plan for this kind of query rather
than planning with the 1000.
The other thing we do is we do some replacement functions.
So like if you want to get last insert ID you cannot just send it to any MySQL and
get a last insert ID.
So we do a session management at the VTGet level where for each session we have to know
what was the last insert ID inserted so you cannot send directly so we need rewriting
phase for these kind of functions they are multiple but I just talking about one of them
which is last insert ID so you have to do it at the VTGet level so then you know then
you are replacing that function with a value and you know what that value is for that session.
And the third is you might have to add another SQL node like after you construct the AST
so this is like if on the session you said my I cannot select more than 100 rows so in
the after AST we have in the rewriting phase we will add a limit clause as well so the
planning happens with the limit in place in it.
So before so after rewriting and the AST generation before we go into the planning the planner
needs some additional information which is it should know what are the key spaces that
exist and what are the shard that the key space map to and in the key spaces what are
the tables that exist and what is the primary way what are the in Windexes that you use
for those tables and those these information is basically cached in the VTGate and you
have an event watcher which watches and this information comes from actually we have something
called topo server which is zookeeper HCD sim which is this metadata kind of information
stored and let us see what the sharding information looks like that we get from that zookeeper
so what we call is called V schema and here it is saying that there is one thing called
commerce and it sharded this is the Windex that exists and these are the two tables customer
and the order table which use and they uses the CID column and they use this Windex function
to shard their table.
So now the VTGate knows about everything that now it can go into the planning phase and
the first thing that it does is does the semantic analysis which is it does basically scoping
binding and typing which is like it is validating not validated your syntactic thing before
and now it is trying to validate whether you are using the right columns in the right places
or not whether they are actually scoped correctly or not is the visibility correct or not for
those the operations the operations you are using and then once it validates that then
it goes into the binding phase where it binds those columns to the table that it belongs
to and then it also does the typing which means it try to understand that okay once
the results come back we know that what type it will be of.
The second is once the semantic analysis happens then your AST is converted into an operator
tree which is basically it is basically a logical operator like you have joints and
then you have tables and stuff so it convert into those logical operators and then once
those logical operator are converted it then goes into the optimization phase.
So in the optimization phase we basically make a decision that how the plan should look
like and in the innovators basically what we do is we get the sequel and ultimately
after the planning phase we will get another sequel because the data does not reside on
the VT gate it resides on the MySQL and we want to optimize on the way that we should
get less and less information back on the VT gate to process your data.
So we try to push as much as down to the query to the MySQL so that that can resolve much
faster for us than we do it at the VT gate.
So in the optimization phase basically after the optimization completes we call something
like routes which tell us that okay this query will go to which all shards so that is what
the ultimate step becomes and that is where we call it as a physical operator and then
once we have the physical operators we transform the plan into an execution plan and the execution
plan is nothing but a collection of engine primitives that we call.
So let us look at how the plan looks like or how the execution plan looks like.
So if both the tables which I showed in the V schema were using same sharding key, sharding
function so that is why we were able to basically make it as a single route which is telling
you that okay just go scatter to all the shards and just gather the result at the VT gate
level and send it back to the user.
But if both the tables the customer table and the order table were using some different
sharding functions then you cannot merge it like that then it says basically it will look
something like that like you will have now because it gets very complex enough to show
everything over here so I am just showing that there will be two routes that will happen
and then ultimately the join will also happen at the VT gate level sorting and projecting
and aggregation and then finally the filtering based on how much customers have spent those
thousand bucks so everything happens on the VT gate.
Let's just look at the two routes that I showed on the left.
So first one will do is basically doing a scatter and it's trying to do on the order
table that okay give me for all the customer IDs what is the spend they have done and then
on the right hand side we need the customer email so for every customer ID I need to get
their email IDs and because the customer ID was the sharding key the primary index for
that table we are able to send the second query as a only to a specific shard we don't
have to do again go to all the shards.
So what all steps happen in the execution?
So first thing is once we get the route we resolve it using those indexes and so that
it can go to the specific correct shard.
Another is then basically then we take it decide okay now we know which shard we have
to go to then it then it will also decide okay this is a query that we have to send
it to something that we call the VT tablets which basically in the shard we have VT tablets
in MySQL so it sent it to the VT tablet and then it once you receive the result back you
gather the information but sometimes you also have to do transaction so if transaction is
needed then the VT gate will also tell VT tablets go and also open the transaction when
you execute this query and then the session the transactions will be managed by the VT
gate that will know in which shard what is the transaction being opened so that when
you do the commit it knows which all shard it has to send the commit information as well
too.
And the third and the last thing that execution also handles is basically if you have a select
query and you want to read it on the replicas then it also does the load balancing for you
so it doesn't overload a specific a single replica.
And yeah right so now the query is been sent to VT tablets and now the VT job is to basically
get the result back to the VT gate so what are the things that goes in the VT tablet
it's exactly similar thing that goes in the VT tablets as well but what are different
reasons so first thing is VT gate has some view of the VT tablet of what the state is
but the first thing that the once the query received by the VT tablet it does this okay
let me validate whether that's current am I able to serve this query or not if any view
has changed before after sending the query and before it reads the VT tablet so it validates
if everything is okay then let's go and do the parsing so it will parse the query and
the reason is it has to parse the queries because VT tablet has its checks and balances
over here where it tries to put some limitation like it says that don't overload the MySQL
resource so it will basically add its own limits on the query so that it doesn't overload
your MySQL that's that you can configure and do things and then it goes into the planning
phase and in the planning field it basically tries to see whether did you have did you
have put any query rules which means like any bad query if you put like okay somebody
does select star and without a where condition and stuff so it should it should it basically
says okay this query cannot be executed because it's a bad query so those kind of query rules
you can put and and and the second and another thing that we check in in the planning phase
is basically it will say okay this is the user that send this query but is the user
allowed to even access that tables or not so if if it's not allowed then we throw the
error back after the planning phase also we detail it does this again and all these are
there to just not to load a MySQL so another thing that it does is query consolidation
which is basically it's it's it checks whether any similar same query or some exact same
query is running on the MySQL or not if it's already running then it put it just waits
for that query to return the result and all the threads which are waiting for the same
query will get the result and it will return back so only one query ultimately gets executed
on the MySQL and not all the queries get executed with the same exact same same query
yes so once it thinks okay nothing can be done like it it has to finally send it to
MySQL then it will use the one of the connection from the connection pool to send the query
to MySQL and once the results are written back it will send it to vtgate if it has to
do some operations will do it and finally the client will receive the query so yeah
so that that's what the life of queries but then there are some customized operations
which also affect your query path and which is like when there's a plan maintenance going
like you are promoting one replica to primary for some reason and so and the other is basically
if you are splitting your data like you have some n shards and you want to go to 2n shards
or n plus 1 shards or such thing like that so while doing those operations what vt tablet
does is it notifies to topo that some operation is going vtgate understands it so it doesn't
send query to the vt tablet it basically buffers for certain duration and once everything comes
back right then it the queries start going to the vt tablet or it times out and vtgate
does the time out from itself rather than sending it down so yeah thank you questions
so currently we we don't do cross shard transactions we do it but in the best effort way but it's
currently on the application to know that they are doing cross shard transactions but
we allow it but the application should know that they are going cross shard.
Yes.
So join I already showed in how we have the two routes and then from one we get the two
routes and then the other one this is join so we have hash joins available but then it
will consume your memory and other yes otherwise it's yes it's like from one you will get the
result and then you send it to the other one so it's just sequential yes
aggregation happens at the vtgate level we he has a sorting layer so before aggregation
we have to sort yes that's what it was there in the diagram as well that after join there
was sort layer because you have to sort so we have a in-memory sort so that there are
multiple against sort based on what we can do the best so there's a merge sort also and
then you have a complete sort as well based on what can we do best and then sorting then
it goes to the aggregation what do you make certain operation yes yes so yes so that's
why we said we try to push as much as to my sequel so we actually push the sort as well
to my sequel if possible for the most sort but if you do it in the memory then we still
sorted so that like we can it depends whether we can push it down or not if you are able
to push it down we push as much as to the my sequel yes thank you all right I think
you have nothing thank you thank you