All right, everyone. Good morning. So my name is Andrew Hutchings. I'm also known as kind
of Linux Jedi everywhere. Long story behind that another time. I'm the chief contributions
officer for Marie DB foundation. And I want to start out by kind of saying what all the
different really these are because when someone uses them to read a beer can mean a lot of
different things. So there's really be server which is the software kind of everyone knows.
There's really be corporation which is the kind of for profit entity that does all the
support consulting they do Sky SQL max scale etc. Then there's the foundation which is
a nonprofit entity with funded by kind of lots of different third party companies. And
we are there to essentially continue the read to be source code for the community, essentially.
So bit of a weird job title to contributions officer. So I'm going to explain it using
the pillars of the Marine DB foundation and how they apply to my role. So the pillars
of the Marine DB foundation are openness, adoption and continuity. And on the continuity
sides I try and make all the kinds of different contributions easier for the community to
contribute by reducing the kind of time between opening closing pull requests, but not the
cost of quality or the communications to the contributor. On the openness side we create
and publish metrics. I'll be talking about those a little bit. But essentially it's so
that you can see exactly what is going on with community contributions. And on the adoption
side we work with communities such as operating systems and also end users such as well end
applications such as WordPress that use Marine DB to make sure that we can integrate well
with them and grow adoption that way. So there are lots of different types of contributions.
When people hear about contribution they usually think of code contributions. And those are
the ones I'm mostly going to be talking about today. But there are lots of others that are
important. Funding for a non-profit kind of foundation is really important. It helps us
kind of grow the community around everything. Documentation is really important. If you
can't contribute code, then contributing documentation is quite useful for us. Community. I say this
because we have a Zulip, we have people asking questions on StackOverflow, Reddit, we have
a community Slack, we have mailing lists, etc. And the small foundation can't get to
everyone and everywhere. So if you know how to answer a question then it's a contribution
to reply and would love you for it. Translations. So I grew up in England. We suck at languages.
I barely speak English. It's terrible. So any help we can get with translating error
messages, things like that is really useful to us. And we're working on making that a
bit easier on a workflow point of view. And then usage. Bug reports, feature requests,
actually using the thing and telling us what you like, you don't like, what's broken, what's
not broken, what you want in there. That's a contribution and that's really useful to
us as well, just as much as a code contribution is. So going a bit further into non-code contributions,
I'm going to talk a little bit about Intel, who's a sponsor of ours. They do lots of non-code
contributions, sorry, morning. And they can't really do that many code contributions due
to some legal stuff that they have to go through every time they contribute code. But they
are doing things like they're constantly benchmarking readDB against their current and upcoming
hardware and feeding back the information to us of what's working, what's not working,
what hardware combinations are working, what's not working. And when they do spot some kind
of regression or some new hardware or something like that or there's a release that's caused
a regression on their hardware, they will tell us, they will dig deep and tell us where
to look in the code, what they've spotted and then our engineers can then work on improving
that. So they've worked a lot with Marco on inADB, I'm sure he's in here somewhere, to
improve the performance certainly in 10.6 recently. They do supply speed hardware to
test against, so a lot of the buildbot infrastructure is on Intel hardware. They've given us financial
support and Steve Shaw from Intel is on the board for the MariaDB Foundation. So there
always be things you can do to contribute even if you can't contribute code to MariaDB.
Why contribution is important? Well, so we get a more diverse input from our life experiences.
So if a project is built by one team in one country, in one office for example, you're
not going to get a diverse feel of not just culture but use cases, etc. So I think it's
really important to get contributions for a wide group of people. You get to direct
the project the way the users want rather than being led by one single entity, one single
corporation. So if a corporation says, okay, all money is here, they're going to put all
the resources to develop those features and it might not be what someone is using WordPress
wants, for example. You're fixing bugs and things that are important to you, and I think
that's quite important, and you're building a real community around the project. So it
wouldn't be a first-time if I don't talk about Drizzle. For those who don't know, Drizzle
was a database, a fork in MySQL 6 back in 2009. It started in some microsystems and
it was designed to be a microkernel fork with loads of different plug-ins optimized for
web and cloud usage. It eventually died, so that's why you probably haven't heard of it.
But in 2009, we had a talk where we said we want 50% of the code contributions to come
outside of some microsystems, and we kind of met this goal in a unique way. Oracle bought
Sun and fired everybody. So we did meet the goal and everyone went to Rackspace, but my
point is MariaDB Server has more external contributors than internal contributors. So
the corporation has in 2022 36 code contributors, there's eight from the MariaDB Foundation,
and there was 68 code contributors elsewhere. Now obviously those contributors are not working
full-time on the code base, but it does mean that they kind of fix the problems that are
important to them, and it's a pretty impressive stat, I think. And we had some stats in 2019,
you know, kind of something happened in 2020, can't think what, that kind of, of course,
it was kind of implied, but yes, COVID.
Also, many of the contributions come from China, and that was recently a lot before the
COVID. If you don't see that in the Thursday packet.
Exactly, yeah, so as Monty said, COVID hit, China kind of caused the stats to dip a little
bit, things like that. They started to get back up again in 2021, and 2022 has probably
been our best year ever, and I think we got some really big stuff lined up for 2023 as
well. So the actual stats for 2022 are on screen right now. So Corporation obviously
is the biggest contributor, they pay a lot of full-time developers to work on it. We
have a smaller number in the foundation of full-time developers and some people who work
part-time on the code and things like that as well. So even I contribute a little bit,
but knowing near as much as everyone else, you know, at most one day a week, so it's
not a huge amount. And then other contributors kind of outside of the MariaDB circle, pretty
much on par with what the foundation contributes, so pretty good.
So we use Git DM, which is called Git Data Miner, to actually process the Git commit
stream to generate this, and I've actually open sourced the tooling that does all this,
and it has all the kind of metadata in there to generate this. So you can actually break
it down by user, by entity they work for, etc. And if you find that I've made a mistake
on identifying someone, you can actually open a pull request on that and change the data
accordingly. So it's kind of open in that respect as well, if you see what I mean.
Git Data Miner was something that was created for the Linux kernel. We tweaked it a little
bit so we can count hackers and things like that, but yeah, it's essentially the same
thing. We have a script to generate pull requests. I know this chart is going to be difficult
to see on the screen, but kind of the trend is the important part. So this scrapes GitHub
for weekly pull request metrics. So the x axis here is weak numbers, and then the y
axis is the number of open pull requests. So the bottom is 80, the top is 120. Part of
my job is to help bring this down. I have been failing. I will be working on that quite
a bit in 2023. So I'd run.
You should also add how many actually close to that one. Now you have no open.
I do have that, but showing that on this chart was getting very messy. So it's hard enough
to show this. See, we do close a hell of a lot of pull requests as well. And we don't
just go in and say, no, that's rubbish close. We tend to talk to people through the pull
requests, and that's why some of them stay open quite a long time.
So in the metrics future, I kind of want to break down the commit contributions by module,
engine, et cetera. So we know how many contributions are coming to NODB, how many to Connect Engine,
how many to RocksDB, et cetera, so that we can track that kind of usage. I want to track
the average time to merge pull requests, median and mean, I guess. Probably median because
we've got some that have been open a couple of years and some that only stay open a week
or two, for example. So, but we'll track that. We'll bring it down.
Buildbot contribution metrics. So we use Buildbot for continuous integration. We do get pull
requests through that contributions through that. So we'd love to track that kind of stuff.
More community wide metrics. So we're talking JIRA, we're talking Stack Overflow, Reddit
metrics, et cetera, like that, capturing those kind of things and publishing along with the
quarterly stats that I already publish on meridb.org. And if there's any other metrics
you want to see, let us know. Contact us because we are more than happy to generate them.
So I want to talk about how to contribute code to meridb. I wrote a blog post about
this on meridb.org, but there are some basic steps you can follow. And it kind of helps
reduce the round trip time during review. And also, I don't want you to spend hours, days
working on something and opening a portal question saying, sorry, this doesn't really
fit with what we're doing at all or someone else has already done this. And I have to
say no, because I don't want to crush people's hopes or anything like that. So if you follow
these steps, it will kind of help reduce that quite a bit.
So first step is communication, talking to us. We can guide you through kind of every
step of the way. The meridb team are quite approachable, preferably via Jira and Zulit,
but there are other ways to talk to us as well. In particular, for Cento, Daniel and
me at the foundation, there are a list of people at the corporation I'm sure you can
talk to as well. Tell us what you want to work on. And if you don't know what you want
to work on, there is a beginner-friendly tag on Jira where we've tagged tickets that are
should be relatively easy to pick up and work on. And we can talk you through these. If
there's no Jira for what you want to work on yet, open one and again talk to us and
we can figure out the best solution for it.
Next step is hacking. Write some codes. If you are making a bug fix, it needs to be against
the oldest affected version of meridb. So if it affects 10.5 upwards, then against 10.5.
What is the biggest active release? Yes, active release. Always check the end
of life as well for the releases when you do this. We're in this weird phase right now
where we have got weird, we changed release cycles a couple of years ago. So some releases
are on the old release cycle and some are on the new release cycle. So some in the middle
are end of life, but some are. So it's a bit funny right now. But again, you can talk to
us about this and we can help point you in the right direction. But new features always
go in the latest development version which currently is 11.0 for the next couple of weeks.
We're now Hest, G8, there'll be another release you can bolt things on.
Please stick to the coding standards, to the surrounding code. You'll find that different
engines have different coding standards because they've come from different places. Connect
Engine was originally a MySQL contribution that came through to meridb and that's got
a different coding standard to say inodb and the core server code. I've put together a
coding standards document which should be merged shortly and that's just for the core
server and at the moment it's kind of descriptive, un-prescriptive. But we're going to kind of
improve on that over time.
As some test cases, we don't want you to kind of write something, us merge it and then us
break it later. So if you have some test cases in there, A, it proves exactly what you're
doing and B, it means that it will stay like that in the future.
Run the MTR test suite locally because otherwise you might get build bot errors that you don't
expect and it just kind of reduces the cycle a little bit there. If it's a new feature,
help us write some documentation or at least describe what it does in the Jira tickets
so that we can kind of put that into the knowledge base at a later date.
Next up, pull requests. When you open a pull request, a form will pop up and filling this
in will help us triage the pull request essentially. So it will ask you questions about whether
this is a bug or a feature, have you added a test, does this break things, stuff like
that. If it's your first time doing a pull request, something called the CLA Assistant
will pop up. It's not 100% intuitive right now, it's something we need to improve on,
but right now it will pop up and ask you to sign the CLA. You can click through that and
either sign the CLA or tick to say, I want to contribute under the three clause BSD license,
or you can just literally put a comment in and say, I'm contributing this under the three
clause BSD license and then we can take it from there.
Build bot will run on the pull request automatically, lots and lots of different builders. The most
important ones will report back to GitHub and show you that if anything has failed during
compiling or testing on lots of different platforms we support. When we actually go
to review it, we'll actually look at the full build bot list where there might be some obscure
platforms that might have broken in weird ways. At least it gives you some idea of what's
gone wrong and you can click through and look at the cause. Again, if you don't understand
the error that popped up, we can look at it for you and point you in the right direction.
And then code review process. The Meridib engineers, both at the foundation and corporation,
will review, give feedback, advice. If we think the code is ready, we'll approve it
and merge it. Community members are also welcome to come look at the codes that people have
contributed, review it, comment on it. It's another way you can contribute. If we are
taking time to get to your pull request and we're dropping the ball or something like
that or you need advice, you can tag me, at learnersjedi, on GitHub and I will take a
look at it for you. I'm lagging a bit behind on that because I'm at FOSM right now, but
I will try and keep up with that. We have a large backlog right now, so it is very easy
for us to miss things. And that is all I have. Any questions from anyone? Yes.
Is the foundation and the corporation have different release cycles?
Is foundation and corporation different release cycles? So, no. At the moment, the corporation
are generating the releases. So, the engineers at the corporation are generating the releases,
if you see what I mean. So, the releases you get are generated by the corporation.
Built by the foundation, yeah. There's a lot of synergies between the two, which is a good
thing. We want to be working closely with them, if you see what I mean. But if anything,
God forbid, happens to the corporation, the foundation existing means that MariaDB Server
will still exist, will still be developed, et cetera.
All right. Thank you very much.