I'm going to talk today about MySQL 8 and MariaDB 10.10.
Original talk says 10.11, but I wanted to make sure we're sticking to the latest GA
or stable version, so it had to go down a bit.
And let me start by congratulating MariaDB team with MariaDB Corporation going public.
In particular, Monty, congrats if driving two very impactful open source database companies
to exit.
That's quite an achievement.
I think you people in the universe have that.
That's one step on the road.
So what are we going to talk about first?
I think which we need to recognize.
Where MariaDB and MySQL started from the same route, they have diverged substantially.
So I think it was interesting then on the previous talk, Jean-Français was talking about
upstream.
I was thinking, hey, does MariaDB really consider MySQL upstream at this point?
Or not quite.
Right in this case.
I think there is enough diversity right with this is our ancestors, maybe monkeys for humans,
something of this regard.
Now in this case, I am trying to be fair the best way I can, which for me always means
offense everybody equally.
So if Monty is not screaming at me saying, you are fucking moron Peter, that is not how
it is, then probably I'm not doing my job properly.
No, no, no, but you see, yes, yes, yes.
Of course, of course.
You always do everything with loving your heart, right?
And you don't use bad words as I do.
That is wonderful.
So let's talk about development model first.
Obviously MySQL is developed by their Oracle corporations.
We can see what the contributions are accepted, but I wouldn't say they are encouraged in
the same way as MariaDB does.
And we also have open source as I would say like a drop ship open source.
We have those release coming, but we do not really have a tree there over developers changes
that happen as we can see.
That I think can be particularly problematic, for example, for security bugs where it can
be hard to track like what exactly change fixes that particular issue, right?
Which is different from MariaDB, which has a server released by MariaDB Foundation.
Though there is a lot of work for actual new features done by MariaDB corporations.
Though foundations ensure what the contributions are encouraged and developers really done
in the public, right?
As I would say true open source project.
One thing I wanted to point out, which I think is interesting is also changes from Oracle
side, right?
For years I've been actually defender of Oracle in regards to saying, hey, you know, besides
all this kind of stuff that Oracle is looking to kill MySQL, they have actually been doing
a pretty good job in releasing majority features of open source and a property enterprise features
have been kind of well isolated, abstracted through API and it was relatively easy for
companies as well, especially like Percona to implement the equivalent.
Now things have been changing.
Last couple of years, right?
We can see what's, everybody knows this guy?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Well, like we can see what Larry actually discovered, what MySQL exists in the last
couple of years, right?
And he only seems to care about MySQL as a heatwave because we all know heatwave is supposed
to melt so no flake, right?
And we can see a lot of focus getting on this snowflake development, which is sort of a
cloud only and of course, you know, proprietary version of MySQL.
So far it is only analytic extension, right?
But I think it's all questions to us, hey, could there be some other critical features
which will be only property, right?
Maybe Oracle somewhere in the bellies developing something like transparent sharding for MySQL,
maybe that is going to be proprietary first, right?
So that is, I think, a question what a lot of people in MySQL community are asking.
Now, with my, with MariaDB, I think what is interesting compared to like a MySQL, there
are actually two companies, MariaDB, well, two entities probably better work, MariaDB
Foundation and MariaDB Corporation, right?
That is the latest mission, which I just grabbed a couple of days ago from MariaDB Foundation
side, right?
And I think that is a very good to understand relationship with those companies to understand
this, right?
Now if you think in this case is what MariaDBation is really at large focusing on serving MariaDB
community, MariaDB ecosystem, right?
It develops open source software around MySQL, where MariaDB Corporation that is now public
company, right, which is providing the property solutions and commercializing MariaDB software,
right?
That is, I think, is the interest way, right?
Now relationship sometimes can be a little bit complicated, though I would say there
have been some more complicated installments in which I mentioned in my previous talks,
right?
And some of them have been made more clear, which I think is a great progress.
So if you think about this, what is interesting is MariaDB Foundation has responsibility,
kind of relatively narrow to the MariaDB server, right?
And we can see what number of other components which are very valuable in MySQL ecosystem
are owned by MariaDB Corporation, right?
Not by the foundation and also a lot of development roadmap is driven by the Corporation.
I also find it interesting what we see in MySQL, knowledge base, which is kind of built
by community, but is hosted by MariaDB Corporation.
I find not in a very good sense for like an open source software, there's also entanglement
on the website level, right?
So if I'm downloading MariaDB software from.org, right, then I am kind of redirected
next to the MariaDB Corporation knowledge base, right?
And encouraged to fill out the lead which will go to their MariaDB Corporation, which
is not totally transparent, right?
I think that's kind of, I may be still looking like, oh, I am engaging with a nonprofit while
actually I am giving my connections to somewhere else.
Now, I wouldn't say though that that is completely unfair in this case because MariaDB does carry
the largest wealth, the way to development and promoting MariaDB, right?
And they do also get the largest rewards compared to other sponsors of MariaDB Foundation.
Now let's look quickly at what is really open source between those versions.
Now in MySQL, what we can see, it's a very clear open core platform and we have Maria
MySQL community, right?
And router, cluster, wherever, all that comes which comes in open source edition and there
is also enterprise version.
Plus, as I mentioned, the addition we have increasing focus on the cloud only solution
as a heatwave.
In terms of MariaDB, there are a lot more nuance in this case, right?
Because there are certain things coming from MariaDB Foundation which are completely open
source right now.
The things in MariaDB Corporation space, they can be with a variety of licenses.
Now if you look at the- Peter, let's correct your mistakes.
Okay.
In Mac scale, all the versions are open source.
What's that?
You need to say that all the versions in Mac scale is open source.
Yes, yeah.
The latest is BSL.
Well, okay, yes.
So the latest version of Mac scale is BSL.
All the versions are open source, buggy, insecure and unsupported, right?
What?
Okay.
Well, okay, well, you see- No, no.
Not open source at all.
Okay.
That's fair.
Let's move on, right?
But I would actually check on the Mac scale in terms of how much changes there are.
I did check a couple of years ago, right, to be honest, right?
And the old versions at that time, they really converted to abandoned there.
That changed, right?
And there is actually, you know, they are being maintained beyond the BSL cutoff.
Maybe not.
Okay.
The next thing, right?
If you look at the MySQL enterprise is a super set of community, right?
And I think in this case you have everything that runs in community runs on enterprise.
If MariaDB, you can see MariaDB Enterprise is an extended subset of community, meaning
there are some things in which exist in community which has not been included.
Everything we do for enterprise is part of the community.
I think there are two small features that we see enterprise we don't know.
Well, I mean, so all the storage engines which exist in community are also supported under
enterprise agreements?
No.
Well, that is what I'm saying, right?
I think the first sentence.
What?
It is not a really extended subset.
It has two features.
Well, what about expand?
It's not part of MariaDB Enterprise Server anymore.
It's a different project.
Oh, okay.
Okay.
Let me correct.
So there is a cool feature available from MariaDB Corporation, but it's not part of
MariaDB Enterprise product anymore.
Okay.
Sounds good.
Let me move faster or we will need much more time if you have a wonderful and productive
discussion with Manji.
Okay.
So now in terms of cloud native, we have a finding new MySQL operator available from
Oracle and both for MySQL and MariaDB, there is also a bunch of third-party operators available,
including one for MySQL from Percona.
If you look at from MariaDB Corporation, there is a lot of focus on SkySQL as a way to run
MariaDB in the clouds, right?
Like there was MariaDB Corporation operator ones, right?
But that is nowhere to be found, but there is an effort for MariaDB Foundation to have
their operator created, though I couldn't find what if that's GA yet.
Database as a service, right?
Obviously, there is a lot of database as a service available for both databases standpoint,
right?
In this case, I think what is also interesting is what a lot of folks are relying on this
sort of community versions right there.
You would say Oracle has MySQL enterprise with HitWave available on Oracle Cloud and
now increasing some other clouds and also MariaDB has partnerships with other set of
folks.
In terms of analytics, we have a column store, right, in MariaDB ecosystem, right?
In MySQL ecosystem, right, there is no really integrated open source solution.
We have only cloud only HitWave as I mentioned.
I also think there is a significantly different focus within MariaDB and MySQL, right?
And I'm not going to read through all of that, but I think it's also interesting what the
architecture approach, right, has been substantially different, right?
If you look at MariaDB has been really having much more, you know, incremental iterative
approach, right?
In terms of MySQL, you can say a very big change with MySQL 8.
A lot of things has been written, made not quite comparable.
And also there's also a lot of focus in MySQL making it work better in the cloud, right,
in how Oracle sees operating database in the cloud.
Release frequency, that is something which I think is very interesting, which changed
from the last year, right, where we can see MariaDB recently moved to even more frequent
releases, right, which are with shorter maintenance cycle, right, as well as LTS releases every
two years, right?
So we can see what's starting with a February last year, the major MariaDB releases are
coming out as quickly as minor MySQL releases, right?
So I think that is a very interesting difference in this case, right?
And as I mentioned, there is quite a few differences in this case, right?
If MySQL 8 is kind of has this evergreen release, right, where you have a lot of features introduced
in mind in Maria releases, also a lot of bugs, right?
In particular, I think in the last few releases there have been some, you know, pretty nasty
corruption bugs, which people did not appreciate.
And also this concept, but now it's only a forward comparability, right, that once you
move to the new MySQL 8 release, right, you are not going to be able to run a previous
version, right?
So if you really want a safe rollback, you need to dump and restore, which is not appreciated
by many.
So what you can do from, let's say, 10.5 to 10.10, right?
I see.
So you can upgrade.
That is a good...
I just made 5.7 MySQL to MariaDB 10.
I think 10.10 also.
Okay.
Well, yeah, let's move quickly.
Right?
So some of the changes in MariaDB and MySQL, which I think is worth it.
One is like a protocol.
But MySQL hasn't pushed a lot on their new X protocol, while MariaDB has been making
classical protocol better.
We also have different interfaces support right there.
Well, something else, Manji?
You guys want to know how much do you see uses on X protocol?
I've seen almost non-uses.
Well, yeah.
I hear using X protocol.
It's used for group replication configuration.
Yeah, but they're using it natively.
If you manage group replication configuration, you use it.
Sorry, I have to restart the file.
Sorry, you need to lose slides for a minute.
Oh, okay.
Okay, yes.
So the box needs to be...
Well anyway, do guys have a good human generation?
Yes, okay.
So JSON, imagine JSON.
Can you all imagine JSON?
Yeah, so that is very significant difference also exists.
In MySQL, they designed native JSON data type and have some pretty cool things like a partial
updates.
And also, I think from usability standpoint, JSON shortcuts, which makes things nicer and
cleaner, with MariaDB, JSON is really stored as a text, where it has improved JSON partial
speed significantly.
And what is cool in the latest MySQL versions, it cut up a lot in JSON features in MySQL.
I think two years ago, I could say, hey, MySQL is a lot further in terms of what it can do
with JSON, most of that gap has been covered.
Now imagine replication.
Well, that is also, there are things substantially different, right?
MySQL has built out a group replication, which gets a lot of focus in MySQL 8, specifically
with MySQL in a DB cluster, right?
You now have kind of cluster set, like how you can replicate between two clusters, a
lot of focus on that.
There MariaDB has been focusing on both supporting classical replication as well as Galera replication.
And also, even if you look at classical replication, MariaDB, GTID, and MySQL, GTIDs are conceptually
different, right?
They both move to that versus binary logs alone.
You should be able to stream it to you.
Okay, well, you want me to try?
Yes.
One minute.
Yeah.
Minus one minute, right?
Okay.
What?
You broke it.
Now, it doesn't work at all.
You see?
I think it's seen something, but it doesn't see.
Okay.
The good news is you can't blame me.
What?
Good news, you can't blame me.
For change for once in a lifetime.
Did you see the external display?
Well, I think as you see, it's kind of blinks, right?
What it gets, the external display, right, like, hello?
You see?
It gets.
Yeah, that's what it says it's seen, external display.
Well, that's lovely.
Well, look, I mean, I have a couple of slides in minus two minutes, so let me just finish.
And then you can, you know, troubleshoot it during the lunch, right?
Sorry.
Yeah.
So, okay.
Let's see what else.
Couple of things which are different, right, significantly.
I would say is, A, security is very different, right?
There have been a lot of approach to making security better, both in my school and my
ADB, but approach is essentially different.
So if that is area you focus on and you immigrate in one way or another, make sure you give
it separate special attention.
Optimizer is another area, right, which things diverted specifically, right?
So again, make sure to check your query plans, especially for complicated queries, and go
in one way or another, right?
Now I wanted to also pick up in the latest release a couple of unique MariaDB goodness,
which speak to me in particular, right?
One is I like your, your ID data type, right?
Because all that kind of MySQL, post, well, you know what?
You can actually do this and then you're going to store your ID efficiently.
That is not a good way, you know, just provide the user convenient, your ID data type and
functions, right?
And so they don't have to deal with that shit.
Log-free alter table for replication, I think it's also very cool, right?
Pain, double for essentially time for alter table.
That is, I think was log, log problem in I scroll, right?
That's fixed.
And I also like this concept of grant to public concept, which is being added in 10.11.
Okay.
And now I want you to imagine mountains.
Well, because this slide was supposed to show what there is a nice conference, current whole
bunch of databases called Per Corner Live coming in May.
It will be in, in Denver, right?
And copper papers is open.
We want, you know, if you have something to talk, please submit.
And also some other unique opportunity, right?
Some of you are probably running MariaDB, right?
Anyone?
Okay.
Well, this is your opportunity not to just run MariaDB, but run for MariaDB.
We will put together a like relay team for the Denver Marathon, right?
Which will take place one day before Per Corner Live, right?
And so if you guys want to attend and run about 8K as a part of MariaDB team, then let
me know.
That's all I have to say in this, you should imagine this slide, which says thanks to all
of you to be in such a wonderful audience and come and listen to my talk.