I'm Matthias, I work at the Pincap.
We are doing a distributed SQL database called the TIDB.
It's MySQL compatible,
so for the clients it's just looks the same.
I do have a short talk about online schematics at scale in TIDB.
Compared to MySQL,
a distributed database is slightly different.
MySQL does a metadata lock,
so it basically needs to stop the world.
No transaction can go through the metadata lock,
just to change the metadata.
That means that it's a short lock when you do any kind of DDL.
It also means that when you're doing replication,
these metadata locks actually stops replication a bit.
So if it's not an instant DDL,
you would start getting replication delay when the DDL goes through.
So a distributed database is of course different.
From the client perspective,
you should just see a normal database.
You should just expect that it to be transactional,
it should be an asset compliant query with your normal SQL queries.
For the user, you shouldn't see any changes.
But of course, underneath,
it's distributed on multiple nodes, etc.
So if you take add index as an example of a DDL,
we can't do the synchronous stop the world scenario
with SMDL example in MySQL.
So that's something that we need to solve.
During that, we do need to copy and create
all the index entries for creating a new index while normal traffic comes in.
So in the beginning,
MySQL did more or less stop the full table and
copied everything over and then it released it again.
Nowadays, they are much better on the online and only keeping the metadata lock.
But that's something we need to do better in a distributed database.
So the proposed solution is to version the schema.
So every change you're doing to a schema or a table,
you do with that as a specific version.
You would need to allow sessions to use either the most up-to-date version,
the current version of the schema or a previous version.
So then you can do transitions in between these states or versions.
We need to guarantee that
the states between the previous version and the current version are compatible.
So that basically means we need to create some kind of states from
the before or the start states to the public state where it's usable.
I think it's easy to go backwards to actually see what kind of states are needed.
So here the VN,
it's the current version and we start by the public.
It's the end state, everyone sees the index.
So select goes there, insert updates, everything goes there.
The previous version, we can actually remove the selects,
but it still needs to do all the updates, insert some deletes there.
As you see, regardless,
the time here can be a bit confusing.
So the transactions are of course using the real-time, current time,
but it might see a different version of the schema because we
can't require all transactions to
constantly check for the new schema and stop the world for that.
Let's then move and say we are in this right only states.
Before state for that,
then of course we cannot do selects.
Do we need to do inserts before to make them compatible?
Well, we don't actually serve the reads.
So we do not need to do the inserts in this state.
Backfill will handle it.
Then of course comes the question,
how would backfill handle it?
So for backfill to handle this correctly,
we actually need to have another state between
public and the right only state.
As you see, state-wise for transactions,
it doesn't really change anything,
but it gives time for doing this backfilling.
Because when we enter the right reorganization state,
then we know that the state before,
it's the right only.
So all changes will be double right.
That means that updates can be a bit tricky
because we say we're not doing insert,
but how do we handle updates?
So we need to go a bit deeper to see how that's handled.
In the add index example,
we do have the table data that's public.
So everyone should be able to read
the directly from the table without the index.
So let's say we have at time zero,
a session that sees this new right only state,
and it doesn't insert,
it inserts into the road,
into the table, and it updates the index.
So you can find the row through the index.
Then later on, another session comes in,
but that session has not yet
transitioned to this right only state.
So it's in the state before,
and it wants to update this.
So it goes to the table and updates the row.
That's public, so that's what it needs to do.
But then how about the index?
We don't actually need to insert into the index here,
because that will be handled by
the backfill in the right row organization stage.
But the trick here is that we actually need to
remove the old entry as a part of the update.
So update actually means that we need to propagate
the deletes into this new index object,
but we do not need to do with inserts.
So we need to propagate updates as delete only,
and that also makes it easy to handle the deletes.
So we do need to handle deletes in the new index.
That also gives a name for the state,
so delete only state.
That's when you're reading this,
it's inspired by a paper from Google about
the online asynchronous schema changes in F1,
so on top of Spanner.
Then it takes some time before you understand exactly why
you do need a delete state,
but this is the reason to be
able to move through the different stages.
By not inserting the new row in the index,
or the new entry in the index,
does that not mean that nothing else in
the system can use it because you
have to wait for the backfill to complete?
Yeah, so you don't read from the index until it goes public.
It has to complete, okay, so you have to wait for it to
read it so it doesn't matter either way.
Yeah.
It just delays that you could have done it at
the same time while you're alternating.
So if you would insert it,
then it would more or less be overwritten by
the reorg phase anyway because the reorg needs to
read from a snapshot and take all that data.
So a snapshot taken somewhere
when everything were on the right only.
Just simply to do it that way.
So it would just be overhead to doing the insert.
It wouldn't actually mess up anything.
It will still be correct,
but it will just be unnecessary.
Then if we move on from the delete only state,
the previous version can actually be the start state
because as long as deletes are done,
the previous version does not need to
do anything with previous states.
So there we have the different states
that it needs to transition through.
For keeping transactions running without being blocked.
So here we do have the full part of
the asynchronous DDL in online.
That's done online in a distributed database.
Do you support distributed transactions?
If you do, what transactions in XA prepare state?
So we do not support XA transactions right now.
But of course, if you're connecting to
different SQL nodes, it looks just like it is a master,
or a primary wherever.
So full read and write in however you connect.
So I suppose all this happens
when the remote transaction is committed.
These changes are only then being applied to the.
So transaction is a bit slightly different.
So you cannot have transactions
spanning more than two versions.
So you need to either wait or you need to block,
stop and fail transactions that are too long-running.
Okay. These versions, you have
several versions associated with
a single all-night schema change.
Did I get it right?
Yes. So a single DDL goes through multiple stages.
Okay. I'm calling the inversions.
Thank you. Currently, I'm actually working with
partitioning and for all the table,
reorganized partition will take one set of partitions into a new set.
Then there's another thing.
So during the reorganized phase,
when you're copying data,
you do select from the old one.
Then you go to public.
So you select from this one,
which means that if someone is actually on the right reorganization state,
then they will select from that that's not updated in this one.
So you need to add an additional state between
the right reorganization and the public state just for moving the select.
So it's a double right while moving the reads.
All this is done in TIDB,
and I'm not sure how many is familiar with TIDB.
Okay. Good. Then let's do a quick introduction to this.
TIDB is mainly architecture around three different components.
You have PD, which stands for placement driver.
It creates the timestamps for
transaction handling and it knows about the data locations.
So it knows on which nodes the data are.
Then we have an SQL layer that is stateless.
So it's very easy to spin up or scale in the different number of nodes.
Here we have re-implemented the MySQL protocol.
So this is actually written in Go,
and all of it is in Apache 2 license.
So we do not share any code from MySQL or Maria.
It's completely new since 2015 when the project started.
Then we have a storage layer.
The base storage layer is TIDB,
so it's a distributed key value store.
We even have people that runs that as a distributed key value store and
don't bother about the SQL part.
So that's what you can do as well.
Then we do also have an additional and optional way of
storing the data in what we call TIE flash.
That's a column store.
So by connecting it here,
you can actually do analytics like aggregations and so on,
on the same data within the same transaction even.
The optimizer here would choose what is the fastest way,
what has the lowest cost for executing the query.
So you don't have any ETL or anything like that in between.
It's very easy to just add.
You're doing all the tables and set the TIE flash replica equals one or two,
or if you add more than one,
then you also get the MPPs or massive parallel processing part of it.
We do have, you can run Spark on it as well.
Let's just go down slightly deeper on how we actually store the data.
So we take all this data and split it into ranges about 100 megabytes,
and each such range is stored in three,
or it's configurable, let's say three copies in the TIE KV storage nodes.
Each such region is forming a raft group.
So that's how it keeps the HA and high availability.
TIE KV is using RoxDB as a lower level storage.
So it's an LSM tree.
It's similar as MyRox in Percona or MariaDB.
So it's not B-tree based.
Through this raft protocol,
that's how we also can connect the column store.
So that's how we also have it.
So you can run it in the same transaction.
Even if you have a join,
maybe it's faster to execute parts of it through an index in the row store,
and then do some of the table scans and aggregation in TIE flash in the column store.
This is optional, but this is not, this is the base.
You always need to have the row store and you can have this as an option.
There's a lot of tooling that works.
So first of all, I would say that the data migration.
So it's easy to have a TIE DB cluster to read the binary logs,
or you have to set it up for dumping an upstream MySQL instance,
or even several instances into the same cluster.
So you can combine all the data back.
We have the backup and restore very good dump story.
I think that even works with MySQL, right?
Yes.
You have a tool for us to do a diff between the different instances,
the change data capture that can go to either another TIE DB cluster,
or MySQL instance go through Kafka as well if you want.
TIE up, that's a way for managing and deploying TIE DB,
and all components you want.
You can even use it as a playground to start it in your laptop.
It will download the binaries and start everything,
including monitoring everything.
So it's very easy to just try out.
We have an operator if you want to run it in Kubernetes as well in the cloud.
So we even have it as a cloud service.
You can do anything from on-prem up to cloud service in many different ways.
And we also have Lightning, which is an optimized import tool.
And that's what I will actually use in the next slide soon.
A year ago, we started a project because we heard and compared
the add index performance in TIE DB cluster versus, for example,
Cassandra or Aurora.
And at that time, we were basically three times slower because we hadn't
optimized that it was just stable, proven, and it worked, but it was not fast.
And that's especially when you're doing proof of concept or loading the data.
That's where it's really beneficial to speed it up.
And the way it worked, it would just do a data copying through small transaction
batches, more or less.
So that also creates a lot of overhead with transaction handling, etc.
That's not actually needed when you're doing a backfill,
because during backfill process, copying the data,
it doesn't actually need to be transactional.
And it's only a single node that does this, a single TIE DB node that orchestrates it.
I'm not going to go deep into this.
It basically just shows how you're creating a command in one TIE DB node.
And it goes into a table.
A TIE DB owner will do it, go through the different steps,
and do the data migrations and data copying.
So what we did first was create a feature with this feature flag.
It uses this lightning, the import tool technology.
It's completely built in in TIE DB cluster, so it's not the external tool.
But it reads the data, and then it creates these SSD files for ingestion in Rokslib.
So it's not a single node.
It's a single node.
And it's a single node.
It creates these SSD files for ingestion in Rokslib.
So it's very efficient load, and it has very low impact on the storage side.
It just moves these files into the storage and takes them into the Rokslib levels.
The result was around three times speed up,
and of course, a lot less impact on normal load in the cluster.
Even if you have a highly loaded cluster, you can do this almost without impacting it.
And then we did a bit of analysis of where we could improve even more.
And there was things like the scheduling could be improved just to shorten the time.
Instead of reading directly from the key value store,
we could use these co-processors for removing columns that's not needed, for example,
for doing optimized scans, etc.
We disconnected the read and write dependencies
so they could run in parallel in synchronous, and a lot of other small optimization.
And that created yet another three to five times speed up.
So all in all, during the last year, we had done 10 times improvement in speed.
While we're still only using a single TIDB node,
and now we're three times faster than the baseline of the other implementations
in Cockroach and Aurora that we have compared with.
And there's a bit more to do, so we're currently looking into how we even can distribute this
instead of running it on a single TIDB node,
and also being able to autotune the priority.
So if you have load that goes a bit up and a bit down, so the DDL work can adjust to that.
And that is if you depend on a single time, if that breaks for any reason,
then you basically just go back to the previous stages.
Yeah, so we have a state state, so we go back a little bit,
but you don't need to redo the whole feeling of the index or anything like that.
And yeah, it's all on GitHub.
If you're interested a bit in how it actually works,
I would recommend go to OSS Insights.
I would say it's a demo site.
It runs TIDB in the background, and it's a simple web UI,
well, quite nice UI on top, but it has all of the events from GitHub.
Currently, it's 5.5 billion records, and we store it in a single table.
It's a bit other things there as well.
And you can compare for your own GitHub ID or your own project,
your own repository, compare it and so on, and check some different frameworks, etc.
It's quite cool, actually.
Tie-up is very useful if you want to try it on your own laptop or in your own data center.
Of course, you can go to TIDB Cloud as well,
but I didn't mention that here because that's our commercial offer.
Something else that we have that is not directly connected, it's Chaos Mesh.
So if you have a system on Kubernetes and you want to see how it handles different errors,
you can use that for injecting errors.
That's something that we used for stabilizing and testing out the TIDB cluster.
Then I think I'm out of time.
Perfect timing, so you have time to answer questions.
Yeah?
I have a bunch.
First of all, I'm very interested in how do you organize the H step transitioning.
I mean, you have both storages, and I missed the way you move the data from row into column of format.
I believe you do a double copy.
You have double copies of the data itself.
So we always have the copy here,
and the Raft leader of the group is always here.
So you do have Raft leader and Raft follower in the TIDB,
and then we extended the Raft protocol so we have learner states here,
so they can never become leaders.
So this is a must, and this is optional.
Yeah?
What about the optimizer model?
How do you calculate the cost?
Yes.
To understand which storage format we use.
Yeah, and it's also the influence of the volcano optimizer model,
so that's how you more or less pipeline the different things and can move parts of the pipeline into an MPP framework that handles the column store.
I wonder if this model and the optimizer are at least dispersed across the multiple portions of the TIDB or it's in a single.
So the optimizer that's in the TIDB project, in the TIDB repository, so the SQL node.
And when it executes, it's a push down this co-processor request and also through the MPP framework for pushing down query fragments or the co-processor request into either TIDB or a TICB or to TIFlash.
So, for example, if you're doing a join where one part of the table can be resolved the fast by an index lookup, then it will go here for that part of the table.
And for another table, it might be a big table scan or aggregation that will be faster here.
So then it actually can combine that.
I'm not sure I don't know the details deep enough for answer that.
Yeah. So we are only we don't have on any own connectors or anything like that.
We asked relying on MySQL connectors or MariaDB connectors and that's what we're using when we're testing.
So you basically have the students that tries different kinds of queries and after the passes you understand that they are somehow equal.
Yeah. And of course there are differences.
But I would say the compatibility with the MySQL dialect.
It's very, very high. But of course, like management commands for replication doesn't work because we don't do replication.
We have internal replication or we use change data capture for transfer to another cluster.
Thank you.
Last question.
What TIFlash does when there is high rate of single cell updates like how it handles this like the writing the whole file.
So it's a it's a derivative of Clickhouse.
So it's the caches the changes and then it updates it partially or rewrites the whole.
It can. But if it's behind then it will more or less fall back here.
You have some tweaking options. You can even do it as optimizer hints that you want to use either end in for example, etc.
If there are more questions, I'm sure Mattias.
Yeah, I'm here. Even Daniel is here as well.
Thank you.