So, hello everyone.
A pleasure to be here.
I'm Ithamar Holder and I'm a senior software engineer working for Red Hat.
And this is a talk about the journey through supporting VMs with dedicated CPUs on Kubernetes.
And the reason that there's a journey word in the subject is that this was a true journey
for me.
And I'm going to guide you through the journey until we reach the actual problems and solutions.
And there are two reasons for that.
So first reason is that we need to understand the problems and solutions.
So we need to understand the background for it.
But the second reason is that I've gained a lot of insights and takeaways during that
journey.
And I think that I hope that you could find this also valuable for your journeys.
And that you can take the same takeaways for whatever you're doing and whatever you're
interested in.
So we're going to talk about all sorts of stuff like dedicated CPUs and CPU manager,
C groups, pod isolation and name spaces, Kubernetes resource allocation.
And so let's begin.
So first of all, an introduction to Kubernetes.
So Kubernetes is designed to run containers which are designed very differently than VMs.
And running VMs on one platform and containers on another platform is not the best approach.
And this is where Kubernetes comes into play.
This is basically an add-on or extension to Kubernetes which lets you run VMs on top of
Kubernetes as a first-class citizen, as a completely cloud native.
And I'm not going to dive into all the architectural details here, but the trick is basically to
run a VM within a container like this picture tries to illustrate.
And that's basically what you need to know for this talk.
So what's the deal with dedicated CPUs?
So basically the key word here is avoiding preemption or context switches.
Right?
So this is crucial for certain use cases like real-time VMs or VMs that depend on very low
latency.
So as a naive example, let's think about a VM that hot loops over some condition.
And when this condition becomes true, it has to react really, really fast.
So if we context switch this workload out, then it would take more time because once
the condition becomes true, it would take time to context switch back and only then
the VM could react.
So this is very crucial for some use cases.
Also it's supported by most hypervisors and it's a pretty standard feature.
And we aim to bring this also to Kubernetes.
So a question to the crowd.
Who recognizes this section?
Who knows what this is?
Okay.
So most of you.
And another question, who can say that he's confident about how this is implemented behind
the scenes or how Kubernetes actually does that?
A lot less of you, right?
So that's good.
It means that this is relevant, right?
So obviously this is the part, this is taken from the Pause manifest.
This is the place when we specify resources.
We have of course requests and limits.
We can specify CPU, memory, ephemeral storage and a bunch of other stuff.
And so let's talk about containers for a second.
So containers are actually a conceptual concept that could be implemented in many ways.
So from the kernels, the Linux kernel perspective, there isn't such a thing as a container really.
There are basically a couple of main kernel features that serve as the building blocks
for containers.
One of them is C groups.
C groups is very important and is one of the main building blocks for containers.
So let's talk about C groups a bit.
So basically the idea is that the architecture is a tree of resources, right?
We have the root C group, which is basically all of the resources on the node.
So for example, 100 CPUs.
And then we divide them into groups.
Like for example, 70 CPUs, 20 CPUs, 10 CPUs, and so on.
The idea is that every process on the system is attached to a C group.
And that basically the C groups limits the resources for this group of processes.
And in Kubernetes, there is usually one C group per container.
This actually depends on the CRI that you're using.
But the most common approach is to use one C group per container.
So in Kubernetes, all of the values are always absolute, right?
When we specify CPU, for example, we can specify 100M, which stands for mill CPUs, which is
similar to 0.1 CPUs, 1.3, whatever.
But these are always absolute values.
In C groups, it's all relative, right?
It's called CPU shares.
The default is 1024, but it doesn't really matter.
So if we will look on a very naive example again, let's say that we have a node with
two pods running on the system, pod A and pod B.
And let's say that pod A has one CPU share and pod B has two CPU shares.
What it would mean is that pod B would have twice as CPU time as pod A.
It doesn't really matter how many CPUs the nodes have, because this is all relative,
right?
So how does Kubernetes convert between the absolute values and the relative shares?
So we can think about one CPU as 1024 shares, just because it's the default in C groups.
So let's say that a pod asks for 200 mill CPUs.
So this is actually a fifth of a CPU.
So what we can do is divide 1024 by 5, and we get approximately 205 shares.
And this would work, but remember that shares are still relative.
So what happens, for example, if the node has 100 CPUs and one pod with 200 mill CPUs
requests runs on that pod?
Since it's relative, it would just use all of the nodes' resources, right?
So this has a nice side effect.
The spare resources on the node can be used by the pod relatively to their requests.
So basically, the request is the minimum amount that is actually allocated, and all of the
spare resources are being split relatively to the request.
So let's talk about Kubernetes QoS for a second.
There are three quality of service levels.
The first one is best effort.
That means that I don't specify anything.
I don't have requests.
I don't have limits, not for memory and not for CPU.
The last one, guaranteed, is kind of the opposite from that.
I specify both requests and limits to both CPUs and memory, and the requests and limits
are equal.
Now if you're not best effort and you're not guaranteed, you'd be burstable.
So this is just an example, but the idea is that you can specify either only requests,
only limits, you can specify them both, but they're not equal.
So any other than best effort and guarantee.
Now basically, the trade-off here is predictability in order to get stability.
So basically, Kubernetes tells you, if you want me to guarantee you stability, you have
to be predictable.
Or if you will be more predictable, you'll gain more stability.
Like one example for that, if we're talking about memory, for example, are node pressures.
So when the node would have high memory pressure, it would evict guaranteed QoS pods less.
And after that, it would get to burstable, and after that, it would get to best efforts.
So this is true, by the way, as long as you keep your promises.
If you say that you're limited to a certain amount of memory and then you exceed this
memory, then Kubernetes is, on most CRIs, will just kill the pod.
So can we use dedicated CPUs in Kubernetes?
So the answer is yes.
This is possible with CPU manager.
And in order to do that, we have two requirements.
Now, first of all, the pod needs to be of guaranteed QoS.
First of all, the CPU request, which equals the limit because it's a guaranteed QoS, has
to be an integer.
It cannot be a floating point value.
Also, an interesting fact is that only a single container or some of the containers in a pod
can have dedicated CPUs, but the whole pod needs to be of a guaranteed QoS.
So let's talk about namespaces for a second.
So remember this little diagram from before.
So namespaces is another building block for containers, and it basically is responsible
for the isolation of the containers.
So when I'm picturing a pod, this is what I think about.
Like it's a box with some containers in it.
The containers are absolutely isolated from one another.
And as we said, container is a concept.
So if we will take some of the namespaces out and we will break some of the isolations
between the containers, are there still containers?
How layers of isolation do we need to strip before it stops being a container?
This is more of a philosophical question, but is it possible on Kubernetes?
And the answer is yes.
So for example, it's possible to share the PID namespace between containers or the process
namespace between containers.
And what it means is that inside a container, if you will do something like PS, you would
see all of the processes from all of the containers.
This isolation will not exist anymore.
Another interesting fact is that as a side effect, the file systems are also shared.
Now, they're not shared directly, but you can use Datric to use them indirectly.
So, slash proc slash PID slash root will get you to the root file system of another process
that now can be in another container.
So to actually enable that, that's what you need to do in the pod, in the spec, share
process namespace through, and that's it.
So now a word about KVM.
So who knows KVM, by the way?
Oh, a lot of you.
Okay.
So we have a kernel model which turns the Linux into a hypervisor.
Basically we have two kinds of hypervisors, type one and type two.
Type one means that it's also called a bare metal hypervisor because it's being installed
on a bare metal.
There's no OS benefit.
And what it means is that it's really fast, but the downside is that it has to implement
stuff like the scheduler and virtual memory and a lot of stuff that already exists on
every OS.
Type two hypervisors are being installed on top of the OS, so they don't have to re-implement
all of those stuff, but they're usually a lot slower.
So KVM is really incredible because it turns Linux into a type one hypervisor.
And this is what QVRT is using to gain near to native performance.
Now, an interesting fact about the KVM is that its main purpose is CPU virtualization
because this is a performance part.
It's also backed by QEMU, which does things like IO and stuff like that, which are usually
are less related to performance.
So how does KVM actually work?
So from the guest perspective, it will have, for example, four CPUs.
But these aren't real CPUs, right?
They are virtual CPUs or vCPUs.
And from the kernel perspective, these are just threads, vCPU threads.
So what the guest sees as a physical CPU is actually from the host perspective is just
another thread on the system.
Okay, so now back to QVRT after all of these introductions.
In QVRT, we have the VRT launcher pod.
It has some containers in it.
The compute container is the main container.
Inside the compute container, we run the QEMU process, which actually runs the guest.
And this is the main container that we're using.
So first attempt to support dedicated CPUs.
So the idea was let's allocate the compute container that we talked about with dedicated
CPUs.
So this is possible with CPU manager, as we talked about.
All we need is to do is to have a pod that's guaranteed QS and to have an integer amount
of CPUs on the compute container.
So by the way, is it a good approach, do you think?
This is a problem, and let me explain you why.
So let's zoom into the compute container for a second.
The list here is all of the processes and threads that run inside the compute container.
Now, you don't need to understand everything that's running here.
But let me show you the interesting part.
So you see the QEMU KVM process.
All of the red ones are its threads.
Now as you can see, we have two threads, which are the actual vCPU threads, like I said earlier.
And so the problem is that we have a lot of threads with different priorities.
And basically, if we let all of the compute container run with dedicated CPUs, these aren't
really dedicated CPUs, because we said that the key word here is avoiding preemption.
But with the previous setting, we will context switch out the vCPUs in order for other threads
inside the compute containers.
So the vCPUs aren't running on dedicated CPUs, really.
We actually lied to the guest.
So that's a problem.
Now the second approach is called the housekeeping cgroup.
And the idea is that we will make a child cgroup for all of the low priority threads
or processes.
So how would it work?
So let's say that the user asks for x CPUs.
We would actually allocate x plus 1 dedicated CPUs.
And one dedicated CPU will serve all of the housekeeping tasks.
And when I say housekeeping tasks, I basically mean everything but the vCPUs themselves.
Then what we can do is move all of the threads that aren't vCPUs into the housekeeping cgroups.
And then the vCPUs would be with true dedicated CPUs.
So this is how it looks like.
We have the BERT launcher pod.
How do we have the compute container with x plus 1 dedicated CPUs?
One dedicated CPU is for everything but the vCPUs themselves.
And the x dedicated CPUs are for the vCPUs.
So this approach is much better because this basically supports true dedicated CPUs for
the vCPUs.
But this also has a problem.
So first problem is that we waste one dedicated CPU for stuff that are of low priority.
This is a huge waste.
Ideally we would have wanted to do something like give me a 4 or x amount of dedicated
CPUs and another amount of shared CPUs for everything else.
And this is actually possible on cgroups, but it's not possible on Kubernetes because
of what we said earlier.
If we're going to ask like 3.2 CPUs or something like that, they won't be dedicated.
They would be all shared.
So basically Kubernetes goes for an all or nothing approach.
Either all of the CPUs are dedicated or all of the CPUs are shared.
Another problem, which is more of a design problem, is that we're focused around the
lowest priority processes.
And this kind of should be reversed, right?
I mean, we want to configure the vCPUs to have dedicated CPUs, so we configure everything
that is not the vCPUs.
And this is problematic because we would ideally want to only change the vCPU threads and leave
everything as is to keep it open for extensions in the future and stuff like that.
There are more problems related to cgroups v1 and v2.
I'll not dive into details here, but two words about it is, for example, in v2, we have the
threaded cgroup concept, which doesn't exist in v1.
And in a threaded cgroup, we have a lot of limitations.
Some of the controllers or some systems of cgroups cannot work at all.
So just know that there are more problems with this solution.
So a third attempt.
This is, I'm calling it the dedicated CPU cgroup approach.
And here's the idea.
So the compute container stays completely as it is.
We won't touch it at all.
We would allocate it with CPUs that are not guaranteed, not dedicated, sorry, they are
shared CPUs.
But remember that the pod still needs to be with guaranteed QS, and I'll explain why.
So what we will do is add another container, which is basically a blank container with
x dedicated CPUs.
And as I said, every container creates a new cgroup.
So it will create a new cgroup for us.
So what do I mean by a blank container?
I mean, a container doesn't really run anything.
It could run, for example, a slip forever process just to keep the container alive, but
that's it.
It would be entirely blank.
And then what we'll do is move only the vCPUs into another container, right, into another
cgroup.
All of the compute containers stays as is, and only the vCPUs are configured.
So this is how it looks like.
So as the VM starts, or before it starts, we have the VRT launcher.
Now we have two different containers.
One of them is the compute container with Y shared CPUs.
These are not dedicated CPUs.
The other one is a container with dedicated CPUs.
X dedicated CPUs, exactly the amount we need, not x plus 1 as before.
So in the compute container, everything is being run when the VM is being started.
But right after it's being started, or right before it's being started, what we will do
is move the vCPUs into the different container.
And that basically solves the problem, because now all of the housekeeping tasks are being
run with shared CPUs.
The vCPUs are running on dedicated CPUs.
So can we actually do that?
I mean, we actually moved some threads of a process to another container.
This looks extremely weird, right?
But this is possible because we shared the PID namespace.
So you can think about it like the processes are not isolated anymore.
They're not really being moved from one container to another, because the container does not
isolate processes anymore.
So we only change C groups.
So from the vCPUs perspective, they just stay the same.
They can communicate with all of the threads and processes in the system.
So only the relevant threads are being configured, as I said.
Shared CPUs for the housekeeping tasks, so we don't waste one dedicated core anymore.
And we keep things open for extensions in the future.
Maybe we would want to do more plays with C groups in the future.
So we want everything in the compute container to stay completely as is.
OK, so summary and takeaways.
There were a lot of introductions here.
And I've scratched the surface of a lot of cool facts and technologies that I've seen
along the way.
So we've seen CPU allocation, implementation in Kubernetes, how C group uses relative shares
and not absolute values, and how the CPUs and the resources are being spread along the
pods relatively to their requests.
We've seen how to enable dedicated CPUs in Kubernetes.
We've seen namespaces and how to break the isolation within a pod.
We've talked a bit about KVM and how it uses threads to run the actual CPUs.
And of course, we talked about Kubernetes.
And again, I really hope that these takeaways will serve you in your journeys in the future.
And I hope that you find this interesting.
So thanks a lot, and you're always welcome to send questions or feedback or anything
else to my mail.
And I'll also be outside for questions.
OK, so thank you.
And if you have any questions.
OK, so the question is, do we need to do a
virtual answer pod, or is it being done by the virtual handler?
And the answer is, it's being done by the virtual handler.
So just a bit of context.
Virtual handler is another pod that Kubernetes uses.
It's a pod with high privileges, and therefore we don't need any extra privileges for it
to configure that.
Yeah.
Does this allow for easier networking communication if you talk in service to service communication
in the Kubernetes sense?
You can do it VM to VM, presumably the exact same mechanism, so resolving service names
from what VM is for another VM, which uses Kubernetes.
Does that work at the moment?
So that's a question about Kubernetes in general, right?
In Kubernetes I can do it, but presumably I can do the same thing from a VM running
inside the pod in the same fashion.
Right.
Yeah, so the answer is yes.
Okay, cool.
Any other question?
Yeah.
So this is an early IELTS.
Right.
So the question is what about IELTS threads or network related threads, what about them?
And actually in the VM manifest we have configurations for that.
So you can ask for example for an IELTS thread to run on a dedicated CPU.
That is also supported.
Yeah, I focused solely on the CPUs themselves, but this is entirely possible in Kubernetes
today.
Yes.
So the question is can we support NUMA with this?
The answer is yes.
I'm not sure if it works right now outside of the box, but I think it should be possible
especially with C groups V2, but this is an interesting question.
I will have to think about it a little more, but I think it is possible.
Anyone else?
Time's up.
Sorry, but I'll be out here if you want to ask further questions.
Thank you.