Hello everyone, my name is Andrea and today I'm going to tell you about the
what we need to do to pass in the digital resume map.
This presentation is not about passing the detail, but rather how we failed at it.
So before I start, I need the details of passing, I will continue to teach about passing the detail.
I hope some of you already know about it, I don't have a lot of time.
So I'm going to go ahead and talk about the
how to pass in the details.
So passing is basically an automated testing technique.
The idea is to just send random inputs to a program to see how it behaves in that case.
And how it works is that you use typically a tool like a buzzer
that is going to generate random input for you, and then you're going to call some functions with that random input.
And the buzzer is going to record some findings, and if it finds any interesting input files, it's going to write them to where it works.
Findings in this case can have crashes, can be hands, but can also be timeouts.
So for fuzzing, when you first do it, you typically start from an empty corpus,
but as you run fuzzing, you're going to generate some interesting input,
which is helpful because in the int and int ones, you can just reuse those inputs and start from scratch.
This helps with finding interesting things faster.
So in RoseVMEM, we implemented fuzzing for VM-Bert.io.
We have three fuzz targets, one for the BERT.io queue,
one for the serialization of the BERT.io queue, and one for the BERT.io ISOG.
In the RoseVMEM project, we all have implementation for the packet, so that's what we fuzzed.
During fuzzing, we discovered three crashes, and only one of them is triggerable by a partition malicious driver.
And what we have right now is that we are able to un-fuzz in for a very rest-heter-soment into the rescue method.
To the name BERT.io repository, the fuzzing is implemented using libfuzzer.
And besides the fuzzing that is happening in RoseVMEM itself,
the folks from the hypervisor are also running fuzzing, and they also discover a timeout in the
server.
So this actually brings me to our first intro.
So, what is it we want? It should be the output, so it's the entry.
Afterwards.
It's a people, and that is me.
The first people is that you actually have to run the timeout
that is appropriate for what you're doing fuzzing for.
Because the people, for example, for the fuzzing that we are using is actually 20 minutes,
and since we are just working with BERT.io, we have to choose,
and there's nothing that can possibly take 20 minutes to process,
so we have to adjust the timeout to 60 seconds in our case,
and this is something that was written in by the folks from the hypervisor.
Now, how we run fuzzing in RoseVMEM is at the library level.
The advantages of this is that it's easy to set up.
So, it's really important that it's easy to set up.
It is a good thing. People are like,
oh, but you're running fuzzing at the library level, so you don't have the kernel that's so easy,
so simple, so they're like, yeah, it's great, right?
And easy is a good thing.
Yeah, it's a good thing because you can also run almost any host.
You just have to have a fuzzer installed, and the repository,
and then you just run fuzzer.
And it also runs in a user space.
There's also the disadvantages, of course, the first one being that
you cannot cover the whole of what they have set up,
so that means that you're going to have some things that are great to replace.
And then, because you are fuzzing in user space, we need to do some more things for the driver.
And this is, this is basically a bit complicated.
And also, you can find false positives.
With the false positives, the idea is that you will find
crashes that otherwise would not be triggered by a driver,
because maybe you have some other JSON trace.
I don't think that it's really important to fix these ones as well,
because you never know how you're going to change your code,
and how it might end up actually triggering those findings in the future.
And for the mocking of the driver, how it works,
we already simplified here, but the idea is that the driver is writing something in memory,
and then the device reads what the driver wrote in memory,
and thus stops the data.
The part that we want to fuzz in the machine,
and the part that we want to fuzz in the machine is this side of the device,
and then what we need to mock is actually the driver side of the application.
And in the machine, what we did is that we started this mocking of the driver from the beginning,
so we needed it anyway to run some unit tests,
we needed for other tests as well.
So we had an initial mock interface from the beginning,
and when we wanted to fuzz, we just evolved a mock driver in order to support that as well.
Okay, so at the high level, how it happens right now in Rasfira is that we parse the random bytes,
we initialize the mock driver with the data that was parsed by fuzzer,
so high level it ends up with some descriptors and some functions that have some random input
that we need to process, and then we create a QM equal these random functions with random input.
And yeah, the second big point is that if you are trying to do fuzzing
and you just start when the project is already mature,
what is going to happen is that's going to be a bit difficult,
you might find it very complicated to retrofit it,
so instead, I know that it's not necessarily viable to start fuzzing when you start a project,
but what you can do instead is that you can keep fuzzing in the back of your head,
and then when you create some mock objects or some unit tests,
you can think about how you can actually reuse them in fuzzing as well.
Which is what we did, but not very well.
So one of the crashes that we actually found was that the mock driver was crashing on invalid input,
so we had to adapt these actually to return errors,
even though it was just one test, we couldn't just crash on invalid input anymore,
so the idea is to return errors at the level where you want to be fuzzing,
that can be processed at higher levels, and so the fuzzing can crash.
And now for structural fuzzing.
So without structural fuzzing, how it works is that the fuzzer is going to generate some random bytes,
and then you have to interpret this as the bytes that you have to do for your library.
With structural fuzzing it's really nice because there are some tools that are just going to basically
interpret the random bytes as a structure that you actually need.
So it's super nice.
What it does is that it significantly reduces the code that you need to write,
and even in Resfier and Risme, it's efficiently arbitrary.
Now, we had to change it, unfortunately,
but before we did that we had only 270 lines of code,
and now we have around 740 lines of code for the fuzzer,
and unfortunately it came with some problems, so that's why we had to actually fix it.
The most important part is that it's not going to produce a fuzz,
so you can't reuse the core fuzz that you had in previous runs,
which was a big problem for us,
because basically what happens is that arbitrary is introducing some randomness in the library,
because it's writing the input,
and that basically means that it cannot be used to purposeful for previous runs.
The big point here is that we can rewrite the incremental improvements for the fuzzer,
and we didn't check that what we want to implement can actually be integrated to the end.
So instead, a better point would have been to make it if we can actually reuse the problems that we generated.
Okay, and now about when fuzzing actually fails.
So we had a PR, University of Man.
At this point we were already running fuzzing for pull request,
and there was a PR that was introducing actually an overflow.
So here the overflow is that the packet header size addition to the packet length can actually overflow,
because the packet length is set up by the driver.
This bug, I actually found it during code review,
so it was a bit unexpected because I was hoping that fuzzer is going to find it, which was not the case.
So after some dive deep, I realized that writing fuzzer for just 15 minutes might not actually be enough,
because the fuzzing, this bug was triggered twice in the government for 14 minutes instead.
So how we fix that is that we had the fuzzing session that is optional and that runs for 24 hours.
This one needs to be started manually by the University of Man maintainers,
and should only be started when there are pull requests that actually impact the whole fuzzing situation.
This is because we are also consuming a lot of resources.
When doing fuzzing, you don't want to block all the pull requests for 24 hours.
So typically the recipe on the site is based on the
page that we use to execute.
So blocking it for one day might not be reasonable for all the pull requests.
So the people here were not planning fuzzing for long enough.
And instead, we had to work our way to find a way to not block pull requests,
but at the same time to provide for fuzzing.
Put coverage for Rust.
So in Rust, you can actually get coverage information by running a LLVM talk.
In Rust, unfortunately, you only get live coverage.
So basically, this was the starting point of the presentation.
I was thinking I'm going to come here, and I'm going to show you how great it is to run fuzzing for 15 minutes,
and then more minutes, and then the purpose, and all these really extravagant things.
And so we ended up with fuzzing for 15 minutes, generating them for these regions,
and the coverage of an early 2%.
So I was like, well, that's okay. That's good.
So then let's just run with some email purposes as well.
So this is some purpose that we generated from unit tests.
Let's just feed the fuzzer and see how this changed.
There was no change, actually.
So I was like, okay, it's not bad, not bad.
Let's just run for two weeks.
So what do you think is going to happen now?
So actually, it's starting.
It's starting, yeah.
At this point, I was like, I have to change my presentation.
It's not what I expected.
But instead, I learned something, right?
So you can't actually use coverage to decide when to stop fuzzing.
So instead, what you can do is that you can use coverage information
to see what parts of your code are not actually covered.
And yeah, well, that's about it, actually.
This is a summary of the people that we ran into,
and I hope now we have a lot of questions.
Yeah?
Did you look at how the fuzzer works and then what areas were not covered
and trying to figure out why it was the fuzzer areas?
Yeah, so the question was if we looked at how the fuzzer works
and what areas were not covered.
Yes, we did, and I have a slide for that.
Thanks for the question.
Okay, so actually, I have two slides for that.
There were some functions that we were not calling on purpose.
So because on the Word.io queue, for example,
we have some functions that are just iterating over the scriptor chains
and then they're doing something with the data.
And at the Word.io queue level, you can't do something with the data.
So it's like, okay, this needs to be fuzzed at a higher level
like at the device implementation level.
So it's like, okay, we're not going to call these functions,
which is a bit hilarious because that's where
Trump hypervisor actually found the time-out problem,
which we were not able to reproduce with Word.io queue, but still.
And we actually did this one function that shouldn't be called during fuzzing.
And then I reran the fuzzing, and, you know, it's a bit better,
but it's still not great.
And then I looked into what, well, actually, you can't see very well.
That's unfortunate.
Yeah, so I looked into what actually is not covered,
and you're not seeing, so you have to trust me,
that these are actually errors, so the printing of errors to files.
So since in the fuzzer, we are not actually initializing
a logger, these things cannot be triggered by files,
so there's lots of this printing to a file that's kept really fuzzing.
Yeah.
Yeah?
What's the truth taken to actually make sure the coverage
goes everywhere, which needs to be covered,
and so just covering sub-values, which clearly aren't good?
I didn't understand the question.
But what's the truth taken to make sure the errors that weren't covered
are going to be covered in the future for me?
Oh, okay, so the question was what measures are we taking
in order to make sure that code that was covered
before is going to still get covered in the next three issues?
Yeah.
None?
So right now we're not doing anything, this whole coverage thing
is just something that I need for the presentation,
and it's not automatic in any way.
This is actually a good point for future investment
to make sure that we're still covering code,
because what will help with as well is that we will make sure
that new functions that we are adding to the code
are also covered by the coverage.
So it's a great point to make the way in your survival.
Yeah?
We're talking about the structure of our fuzzing,
and you mentioned that you cannot use the code
to expand a bit more, thank you.
Yeah, okay, so the question was about structural well fuzzing
and just that you cannot use them for this.
Let me see if I actually have it over here.
No, okay, so the idea is that what we were using,
which is arbitrary, when it was taking the input from it,
fuzzer was also adding some randomness to it.
So because it was random, basically every time it was writing
the purpose of the file, it was introducing some randomness to it,
so when the same people would get the read again,
it would not have been the same.
Where did the randomness come from?
This is just how arbitrary decided we implemented it.
There is actually an issue in arbitrary that they are aware of the problem,
but they are not actually...
It doesn't seem like they are interested in fixing it for some reason.
So what we ended up doing is that we ended up doing some custom serialization
with input, which is also very well known for us to track each other.
It's not much more into the latest part, and it doesn't produce.
Yeah, okay.
When you discovered what we did,
does it transform into a unit test afterwards?
The question is, when we discovered about the...
So yeah, the way that we are fixing these kind of problems
is that they are always adding a regression test for them,
just to make sure that they don't do the information.
And it was not a question.
I was wondering about the computational requirements.
So how many cores are you using?
How many cores are you using?
Are you using the exciting?
So when we went for two weeks, we actually used 96 cores.
In a unit test, when you are running on 20 cores,
I don't know exactly how many.
I think that's one? Maybe?
I don't know, but I think we will be running on 96 cores as well.
There was another one.
Can I see that one?
One minute.
If you find a cover case, as I try to shrink the case into smaller cover case steps,
it's making it a very long step.
I'm sorry.
All right.
This is... I'm not going to...
No, I need a little less chat afterwards.
Yeah, I'll leave it there.
Thanks.