Welcome to the virtualization room.
Similarly, we'll talk about OPD virtualization.
Enjoy.
So, hi-hole.
Nice to see you here.
Today, we're going to talk about OPD virtualization.
We're going to have just a quick intro
for who doesn't really know what OPD virtualization is,
just to get a bit of context.
Then, we are going to see how you can use
a CSC to play with OPD virtualization at home
in a really small footprint just if you want to try it,
or if you want to start developing on OPD virtualization.
We're going to see a couple of new features.
I chose this one because they are cloud-native.
I think that they are a bit different from what you use
to see in a related kind of products.
And then, we are going to see next challenges for us.
So, let's start from OPD.
What OPD is?
OPD is a distribution of Kubernetes.
It's a sibling distribution of OpenShift container platform,
which is the data distribution of Kubernetes.
OPD is the community of the upstream release of a VET.
It's based on physical machines that can be virtual or virtual
machines on a hyperscaler.
In our case, it would be better to use
virtualized nodes just because we are talking
about a virtualization solution.
Then, we are going to have hosts there.
But nowadays, based on Fedora, Kuberos,
but then we are going to see that this is going to change.
Then, we have all the Kubernetes stack.
And you can use it to start your application.
Now, what is kubectl?
Kubernetl is a set of virtualization APIs
for Kubernetes.
So, you can extend the Kubernetes
in order to be able to run virtual machines that
are in containers on your Kubernetes infrastructure.
At the end, it's still using the KVM hypervisor.
It's able to schedule and manage virtual machines
as if they are native Kubernetes objects.
What is its main advantage is that it's cloud-native.
It means that you can use all the Kubernetes stack.
So, the container networking interface for the network,
the container storage interface that you are already
using a Kubernetes for the storage,
it's based on customer source definition and customer
source that are a way to extend Kubernetes with a new API.
It can schedule virtual machine as a native Kubernetes object.
Then, you can manage them to talk with what you already
developed as a microservice.
So, in an ideal world, you are going
to rewrite your application from scratch,
completely splitted into microservices.
In the real world, probably you have a bit of legacy code
or something that is already running in a virtual machine.
When are you supposed to schedule it
on an external hypervisor or on the same infrastructure
that you're using for your microservices with the capability
to have them talking natively to your virtual machines?
Kubernetes is the response for this challenge.
Now, how can you test it at home?
You can easily try it with CSC.
CSC is a really quick way to start playing, debugging,
hacking on OpenShift in general.
CSC is a microdistribution of OpenShift that runs in a virtual
machine that can be executed on your laptop.
It's absolutely not intended for production usage.
It's going to be executed in a virtual machine.
So, it's a single-node cluster.
It's not going to scale out.
It's not going to support upgrades.
It's just a test platform.
In order, here, just a few instructions
if you want to try it at home.
Since we are talking about virtualization product
and you are running it in CSC, which is a virtual machine
as well, you need to enable nested virtualization
on your laptop in order to be able to start virtual machines
inside the CSC one.
Then you can tune the configuration.
Normally, CSC comes with a real-time configuration.
If I'm not wrong, it's about 9 gigs of RAM,
which is not that small, but it's just enough
to run the OKD by itself.
If you want to think about playing with a couple
of virtual machines and so on, it's
better to extend the memory up to at least 20 gigs
in order to be able to do something realistic.
It's also nice that CSC already comes with a kubeviato
host path provision, which is a way to dynamically provision
persistent volumes for your virtual machines.
Because as you can imagine, a pod is something
a female while your virtual machine
needs a persistent volume.
You need a way to provide persistent volumes
for your virtual machines.
CSC is just a virtual machine where
you can run other virtual machines inside,
but you still need a mechanism to provide
persistent volumes for that.
It's already integrated in CSC, but you
have to extend its disk in order to have a bit of space
to create disks.
At the end, you have just to execute a couple of commands,
CSC setup and CSC start.
After a few minutes, you are going
to gain the access to your environment.
You can connect, of course, you can do everything
also from the command line.
Probably much of you are going to prefer using the command
line here using a touch of the screen shot
to the presentation just because they are nicer.
So you can connect to the user interface,
to the admin user interface where you have the operator
AB page.
In the operator AB page, you are going
to find already there because it's
a distributed via the operator AB mechanism.
You are going to find the cube of your type
that converts the cluster operator.
As I mentioned, you don't need to configure the storage.
So you only support it to install the operator
and create a CR to trigger the operator,
but the storage is already pre-configured.
After a while, you will be asked to create the first CR
for the operator in order to configure it.
Here, you can fine tune the configuration
of OKD virtualization for your specific cluster.
In particular, we have a stance called the feature gates
where you can enable optional features.
In the here, we are going to talk about two features.
One of them is already enabled by default,
which is enable common boot image input.
And the other is deploy tech-tone task resources.
This one is not enabled by default.
But if you want to do a tome of what you are going to see now,
you have to enable it.
You can enable it also today, too.
So after a few minutes, the operator is installed.
It's going to also extend the UI with a new tab
where you can see what you can do with your virtual machines.
So now, let's start talking about one of the,
in the last year, we introduced a lot of features.
But today, I want to talk about two of them.
The first one is golden images.
Why?
I think that it's interesting.
Nowadays, if you think to any public round environment
on a public hyperscaler, you are going to find,
it's really used to use them.
Why?
Because you can find their images
for your third operative system.
So they are enabled.
You have just to select one of them, click.
And in a matter of minutes, you are
going to get a virtual machine that it's running.
You don't need to upload your disk.
You don't need to upload eventually an easel.
Start defining virtual machine and so on.
They are really convenient.
We want to have the same experience also in CubeVirt.
So we introduced this feature.
The whole idea is that we are going to have,
or we, sorry, we already have a container registry, which
contains some images with the disk image for virtual machines
that are going to be periodically refreshed
to include a new feature of their operative systems
or security fixes.
Then we have this new object called the data import
persona, which is going to say that you want to periodically
pull an image from that container registry
with a schedule and import it in your cluster.
There is some mechanism in order to configure
the gathered collecting, the attention policy.
But at the end, the idea is that you
are going to find images for popular operative systems
out of the box already available in your cluster.
And they are going to be refreshed over the time.
So each time you, now let's see.
This is the catalog in order to create virtual machines
in the user interface of OKD virtualization.
We have a catalog with objects.
The whole feature is here.
As you can see, for popular operative systems,
we already have a nice label saying that the source is
already available.
It means that this new feature automatically imported
for you a golden image of that operative system.
And it's going to continuously keep it up to date.
The benefit is that when you want to start a virtual machine,
you will be able to do it with a single click.
You can customize the name.
You can say in which namespace it's going to be executed.
But everything is already ready.
With one click, you are going to start your virtual machine.
What is going to happen on the storage side?
We see that we have some existing persistent volume claims
for the disk that got automatically imported.
One of them is going to be cloned
to be your virtual machine.
Depending on the CSI implementation,
this can be even completely flow added to the CSI provider.
It can be really fast.
After a few minutes, your virtual machine is there.
And as you can see, through CloudInit or SysPipe
or whatever, it can be also customized
to use a custom name and so on.
So our data import kernel looks like.
We are saying that we want to have a data source named
Fedora with a schedule with the usual context.
We want to periodically consume images
that are available on Quay, which is a Docker register.
Here, you can see the status and the image is up to date,
meaning that the most fresh version of Fedora
got automatically imported in your cluster.
The important thing is that if you look here,
you see that Fedora, the tag for the Fedora image, is the latest.
It means then when the next release of Fedora
is going to come out, it's going to be automatically
available in your cluster.
Of course, we are providing images for Fedora for centers,
but you can use the same mechanism
and the same infrastructure to import on your cluster
your own images.
You can create custom data source, sorry,
custom data import kernels.
Now I want to talk about an additional really nice feature,
which is Kubernetes Effect on task pipelines.
In the previous section, we see that we
are able to import images for popular operative system,
but maybe there is some other operative system
that requires to create a virtual machine starting
a terminizer and installing it.
So how can we automate it?
We cannot expect that the provider of all the operative
systems in the world are going to use this mechanism
and publish images for us.
We need a way to be able to automate
the creation of the images for other operative systems.
In this case, we are going to use a Tekton pipeline
to automate this.
What Tekton is?
Tekton, also known as OpenShift pipelines,
is a cloud-native continuous integration, continuous
delivery solution.
It's also cloud-native, and it's fully
based on Kubernetes resources.
It uses what are called Tekton blocks
to automate tasks, a structuring the infrastructures.
In the Tekton world, we have tasks.
A task is something that defines a set of a build step,
like compiling a code, and tests,
or building and deploying images.
In our case, we are now interested in deploying
images, but as you can imagine, you
can combine it with other tasks.
Then you can define a pipeline.
A pipeline is a set of orchestrated tasks.
And then you can use a pipeline source, which
is a set of inputs that are going
to be injected into the execution of your pipeline, which
is a pipeline run.
On kubewitt Tekton Task Operator,
we introduced some specific tasks
to create, update, and manage the specific kubewitt
sources, so virtual machines, data volumes, data sources,
templates, and so on.
You are able to populate these images,
even with the libgestfs to inject files, and so on.
You are able to execute scripts, bash, or PowerShell,
and whatever.
We have a set of tasks I don't want to give you,
but some are already available.
We are extending one.
And we have an operator that is going
to populate the task for you on the end of your cluster.
Now we want to see an example pipeline.
This pipeline is going to, we have
two pipelines that are going to be injected by the Tekton Task
Operator.
The first one is called the Windows 10 installer.
It's going to populate a golden image for Windows 10
according to some input that you are going to provide.
The idea is that it's going to copy a template.
It's going to modify a template.
And it's going to start installing Windows from the ISO.
And it's going to create a virtual machine for you.
We can see a small demo.
So here is the pipeline.
We have to provide a few inputs in particular.
We have to provide the ease of the Windows
that we want to install.
And it's the first, yes, there, perfect.
Here we see the pipeline.
The pipeline is going to copy the template.
It's going to modify it.
It's going to create a first VM that
is used in order to install Windows
and then create the Windows image from that VM.
Here is a, now we are simply going to see what is happening.
But everything is fully automated.
You don't really have to watch it.
But if you like, you can also see it live.
Here it's our virtual machine.
And as you can see, it's starting, it's booting.
And it's going to install Windows.
We have also a second pipeline.
I have a demo for that.
It's called Windows Customize.
Probably we are a bit already over time.
The idea of the second pipeline is
that you can customize the image,
running additional steps like installing the software
that you need, modifying the image that it's
going to be one of the golden images
that you are going to provide in your cluster.
So let's move back.
This is the second one.
I'm going to skip the demo.
But if you have any questions, please reach me.
The idea is that we can use this pipeline in this case
to install SQL Server and so on.
What's next?
OKD is going to change.
Now in the beginning, I told you that now it's OKD.
It's based on Fedora CoreOS.
We are going to have a big change there, which
is called OKD centralized streams, which
means that the nodes of OKD are going
to be based on center stream.
And so it's going to be a really upstream for OpenShift Container
Platform, where the nodes are based on Redat CoreOS.
Center stream is the upstream of Redat CoreOS.
Everything on center stream is going
to be built as well using Tekton pipelines,
just because we really believe in that project.
On OKD visualization side, we are
going to introduce many features.
We are going to add more pipelines, more automation.
We are working on our support.
We are working on better the capacity APIs.
We are working to reduce the privileges of the parts
that really execute the virtual machines.
We are working on the real-time area.
And here, a few links if you want to reach us.
Thank you.
There's already OpenStack and Kata containers.
And I wonder how does OKD compares or integrates
or overlaps with these two projects?
So the question is, we already have other projects
like OpenStack, Kata containers.
I want to understand how kube-vert compares to them.
So the first idea is that in kube-vert,
we are managing virtual machines as first-class citizens
on Kubernetes.
You can define a virtual machine with a customer source
because Kubernetes provide a mechanism called
the customer source definition to provide
customer new APIs.
You can use them to define a virtual machine
as a really native object that is
going to be scheduled by the Kubernetes orchestral
alongside the ports and other sources.
The main benefit is that you can expose,
you can use the same storage that you are using for your ports.
You can have your ports talking at a network level
with the virtual machine, natively,
without the need to configure TANs and so on,
because virtual machines are running on the lower stack,
like if you have OpenStack and Kubernetes.
The virtual machine is going to be a first-class citizen
of this infrastructure.
So you think it breaks with OpenStack?
So not really integrated.
If we go here, OK.
Here the idea is that we have something here, which
in our case probably is going to be the metanodes,
but it can be also another hyperscaler.
But in that case, you need nested virtualization,
which is not always the best idea.
Then you have Linux host nodes.
Now we've federated the device, but in the future,
we've sent those streams.
And here you have the Kubernetes stack.
Kubernetes is going to schedule ports as containers
on those nodes and virtual machines there.
So you don't really care of what you have on the last level.
Yeah, you showed how to install Windows and prepare
image decisions from pipelines.
Isn't it easier to use simple doctor file
and if it's possible to use just a doctor file?
Enjoy that on the way that children understand
their own decisions.
OK, so he asked the question, is you
showed how to use a pipeline in order
to prepare an image for Windows?
Isn't it simpler to direct the user doctor file
to create a container?
So in theory, it is.
But you have to start from another running virtual machine
and take the disk because Microsoft is providing
an ISO with a tool that you have to execute.
But you can use the same built-in test and guess
which tools to install Windows inside the doctor file.
But you have to execute it.
I mean, you have to execute the binary of the installer.
So you have to, at the end, you are manually running something
that it's going to install Windows.
And at the end, you need to take a snapshot, which
is going to be your image.
You want to automate it.
You want to continuously execute it
in order to fetch up data.
How we solved this, we automated it with a pipeline
because we have a set of tasks.
And so the pipeline is the most smart way
to execute and monitor them.
Sure.
Last one.
Which format are the golden image disks using?
Which format are the user for the operative system disks?
No.
Oh, do we support other format?
So just a little.
Thank you.
Time is up.
But if you want, please reach me outside.
Thank you.