The next session will be by Dami-en about the SDK with its end. So enjoy the session.
We are facing granular. So that is one of the most often to come in the end of the project.
It's been a very good resource. It's a pre-precision platform based on them.
And we want to do better with what we have.
So my focus is on the storage visualization part of the supervisor.
And we currently have a very modernized approach to the storage platform.
So if you can see on the left that we have a per-metal storage.
And when we had the presentation from inside of the end, we lost 300% of the power of the end inside.
What we want to do is to support the security given by the 10 providers, even the scratch team.
We want to have less impact as possible in some user.
So we want to minimize impact to users. So we want them to have to minimize things too much in the machine.
So what we are proposing is to use... So first I have to introduce the problem.
Then we have to take the pipeline and provide the units seen with storage.
So the tutorials I've drawn first will be on the album.
And to be able to use storage platform and network, we have to use the
system to make sure that the storage is important.
Because it has the responsibility of sharing the network and storage for everything.
And we want to focus on the environment. So NVMe is a new storage protocol.
So that's giving us a lot of preferences inside of the system.
So we have all done zero virtual machines.
That means we can share the storage for other virtual machines.
And to do that, we have what we call a split driver.
So we have a specialized protocol called VFX in the
VFX system. So it's already in place since a long time.
So it's an option in the VFX Linux. So it's not...
And the backend, if you're interested in the XBNG, the backend is TARDIS.
That is a new space program that takes multiple requests and gives you the IOT transfer results with non-zero plot error.
In that we have a special interface to share memory between VMs that is used in the VFX protocol.
We share plot requests from the return machines to the R.0.
This interface is mediated by the new provider. So it's already in place.
We have the return machine that we usually call W in the same time.
Explicitly telling the improvisers that the memory will be granted access to by a 2.0.
And the
W0 need to ask the supervisor to map this memory into its own memory via W0 access.
So I have already replaced TARDIS in our limitation because we want to use SDK in place of TARDIS.
Be able to directly detect the current request and transmit it to the ID and the access.
So to talk a little bit about more about TARDIS,
TARDIS SDK is the storage performance of the backend kit.
But it's originally created by W0, which is used by a user, by a user like Muten.
It's a driver for the
ambient devices running on the workspace in our case in terms of work.
And it's used in the in-line ves
So it's part of the same project as the TPG.
But it's a great tip as ever.
I'll take a look at the camera.
Yeah, this is from the mobile device.
Okay, thank you.
So here we have the current state.
So we have two times the block layers that need to be traversed for one request.
It's one of the costs that is adding to the difference we have with the metal.
So our proposal is to use SPDK to directly transmit BL carry requests from a virtual machine to a storage platform,
a storage device, and to reduce the cost by bypassing the kernel in the in-dom zero.
It's completely transparent for the virtual machine because we already use a lot of the infrastructure already present.
So to take a BLK request, it's a simple part of structure in a shared memory in a ring.
It's not very much different from virtual in this aspect.
And we have multiple request types.
So read, write or discard.
Everything I'm going to focus on read, write because it's a minimum we need to put on to be able to share a request.
And we just have to use it to transfer them to what SPDK to SPDK interface.
So SPDK needs to use a special memory to be able to transmit it to the device.
So we need to use the SPDK allocator, memory allocator, to be able to have a buffer that will be used to go from the device.
So we need to have the data copied from the virtual machine to our DOM zero.
Then we can transfer it to the disk.
So it's pretty simple.
We allocate memory.
We copy the data using the grand stable interface into our memory.
Then we just write it on the disk.
SPDK will call the callbacks that we've given it when it is finished.
And then we can do the same for the read requests.
So it's working great for now.
So as you can see, the read requests, the first and the second call and not read requests, is because the implementation is not finished.
And in this case, I'm doing more grand calls to the epivisors that are on the read or the write requests.
So it's a big cost of our implementation.
But for now, it's done and we'll look into improving it.
But we are doing better than that.
That is on the right.
And the blue column is that this is your current status.
And our implementation is the read on the left.
So same for block size and throughput.
So we are able to improve the performance of our storage stack in a transparent manner for VM because they can use a normal VMs at boot today on the top disk in the current infrastructure of the stage and still make it work.
The problem we have to use NVMe dedicated to the SPDK platform, but NVMe is pretty much everywhere nowadays, even in data centers, especially in data centers.
We are still capable of using the security of the grand table because we keep the state of where the VM only share data that want to be returned to the disk with the back end in SPDK.
And then is still doing the mediator for this.
What we want to do is, of course, having the read request being better than the write request, than the tab disk, which since we are in some case, for example here at the same level with this optimization, I'm not very worried about that.
But we want to be able to not have copy to copy data from VM into DOM0 then having it being handled by the NVMe and use directly the guest memory as source and destination for the email request from the NVMe drive.
And we want to take a look at the grand table interface to see if it can be improved for modern days computing. So I'm finished.
Thank you.
I know from the cloud that it is very hard to install an implement.
How hard is it to implement SPDK?
This question is very quickly.
Is your work somehow can be applied to a KVM virtualization tool?
So the question is if SPDK is hard to use like DPDK and if it can be used in the KVM infrastructure.
So it has always been used in the KVM infrastructure to be as a storage platform for VIT.io guest.
And just that our case is crucial because of the different architecture between KVM and them.
So it's already done by the SPDK community in this whole way.
I would say that this is not very hard to install in our case.
It would be given with the app advisor and the install of XAPNG.
But it's not very hard to install.
We just have to have a special configuration for our DOM0 because this is relying on super page.
So we have to have the support and it's not available in the basic configuration of DOM0.
Yes?
Does your implementation survive the crash of the SPDK process on the host?
The question is if the application is surviving the crash of the SPDK process.
So the virtual machine would be able to survive SPDK not being available.
We would lose the disk in the virtual machine.
It would be hung in the virtual machine for the disk but the virtual machine would still be able to run with the problem.
Any other questions?
Thank you.