Welcome.
Welcome everyone.
We are going to talk about first the schematics checksums.
So, who am I?
I'm a long-time contributor to this of the projects.
And I worked for way that more than nine years on obvious storage.
Who knows obvious?
And I focused on incremental backup, image transfer and anybody tools.
And this project is continuous.
They work on first the checksum in obvious that is available for all.
So we're going to talk about why do we need this schematics checksums and why we cannot
use the standard tools for these schematics.
And we'll introduce the blocksum command which is optimized for these schematics.
And the blockash library which is used by the blocksum command.
And you can also use it in your program.
And a good example of this usage is the new checksum command in QEMO image which is work
in progress using the blockash library.
And we see a live demo, we'll play with the tools.
And finally the most important stuff you can contribute to this project.
So what is the issue with disk images?
Why the additional standard images?
Let's say we want to upload a disk to, we have disk cube up to image.
Usually it's compressed because it's the best format to publish images.
We want to upload it to OVILT or maybe to OKD.
Maybe Simon want to upload it to OKD.
So what we have to do is get the data from the disk image.
And we need to upload it to some server on the virtualization system.
And this server will write in some disk.
Now the disk can be many things.
It can be just an if a server with, we'll have a file similar to the file we uploaded,
but not the same.
It can be all sparse image.
It will not be compressed.
While we have Q2 compressed image.
Or it can be a small block device.
If it's OVILT, it can be a small block device.
Just large enough to fit the guess data that we uploaded.
Some is C
server.
Or it can be a safe image stored in many nodes in a cluster in many disks.
So we have very different shapes on the two sides.
Like disk image on one side, something completely different on the other side, different formats,
different way of storage.
One thing must be the same.
The bits must be the same.
The guess data must be the same.
So if we start the guess with the disk image or with the virtual disk, we must get the
same bits.
So we can verify this operation by creating the checksum of the disk image.
The guess data inside the disk image.
And the guess data inside the virtual disk.
Whatever the format and shape.
And the checksum must be the same.
The nonic image is mostly the same problem.
We have some shape of disk on the other side, some shape of disk on the other side, different
formats.
But the guess data must be the same.
And the checksum must be the same.
Another interesting problem is intermetal backup.
In this case, the backup system will copy only changed blocks on each backup if it wants
to be efficient.
So let's say two days ago we did a full backup and we stored it on this full Q2.
This is just one way that we can store backups.
It can be many other things.
And yesterday we did another backup and we stored it in one file which is sitting on
top of the full Q2.
And this is the backing file.
So we created a chain.
And today we did another backup.
We copied more data from the virtual disk.
We created another layer.
So also in this case, the guess data inside the virtual disk must be the same as the guess
data inside this entire chain.
So if we know how to read the guess data from the entire chain like a guess does, we can
create a checksum and we can compare it to the checksum with the virtual disk at the
time of the backup.
And we know if our backup is correct.
So if we will restore this chain to another virtual disk, we'll get the same data.
So what is the issue with the standard tools?
Can we use Shasom to create checksum of this chain?
So first we have the issue of image format.
Standard tools do not understand image format.
So if we have the whole image, everything is fine.
But if we have Q-cap to image, which is identical, and here I compare the image of system QM which
compare, which access the guess data and compare it bit by bit.
So the images are identical, but we get this in checksum from Shasom.
Image compression, even with the same format, both images are Q-calm.
But one of them compressed, we'll get this in checksum.
Because the host clusters are compressed and Shasom is looking at the host data, not at
the guess data.
Even if we have the same image format without compression, everything is the same, right?
I just converted one image to the other image.
Images are identical, but we get this in checksum.
Why?
I used the dash W flag and this allows on all the rights.
So the order of the cluster on the host can be different.
The guess data is the same.
Finally the issue of spouseness.
Standard tools do not understand spouseness.
So here we have six gigabyte image, but only little more than one gigabyte of data.
But Shasom must read the entire image.
So it will read this much of the data, complete the hash from this one gigabyte, and then read
almost five gigabyte of zeros.
Because anything which is not allocated is read as zeros.
So it must do a lot of work, which is pretty slow.
For example, if we take a bigger image, here I created the 100 gigabyte image.
But there is no data in this image.
It's completely empty.
Just a big one.
And computing checksum took more than three minutes.
So do we really want to use this for one terabyte image?
It's not the best tool for this job.
And let's introduce the bloxom command, which is optimized for this case.
So first it looks just like the standard tools.
If you want to use the standard tools, you know how to use it.
Just run it and you get the checksum.
It understands the image format.
So if you use identical image, you will get the same checksum.
Although the images are different.
The size is different.
They do not look the same on the host.
Of course, it supports compressed Q-Cal because it reads the Q-Cal to image, which the compressor
data and it gets the actual guess data.
So we get the same checksum.
And it also supports snapshot.
So if I create a snapshot, here I created either the snapshot, this snapshot Q-Cal, on
top of the SADOAS-LT5 image.
SADOAS-LT5 is the backing file of your snapshot.
And if I compute the checksum of the snapshot, I actually compute the snapshot against it.
I installed it in a time chain.
Note of the tiny snapshot file, which has no data yet.
And we also support NBD-ORL.
For example, if I start NBD server, this QM-NBD is NBD server.
Here I started exposing this Q-Cal 2 file using this NBD-ORL.
And if you compute a checksum with the ORL, the access to NBD will get the guess data
and compute the checksum.
And actually, this is the way we always access images.
Here we always run QM-NBD and use NBD-ORL internally to access images.
This is the reason it works.
We also support reading for pipe, like the standard tools.
But in this case, we cannot support any format, just raw format.
And this is less efficient because we must read the entire image.
In other cases, we can read only the data.
But it works.
So it's not enough to get tools to get correct snapshot checksums.
You want it to be much faster than the standard tools because we are dealing with huge images,
which are usually empty.
Usually, when you start to use an image, it's completely empty.
Then you install an operating system, add some files.
Everything starts really empty.
And then goes.
So here we tested this 6 gigabyte image with about 1 gigabit of data.
And in this case, blocks was about 16 times faster.
And another example, can we compute the checksum for 8 terabyte image?
Is it practical?
It is.
It took only 2.5 or 2.6 seconds.
And if we do it with a stress room, it's not practical to actually do it.
So I tested the 100 gigabyte image.
It took about 200 seconds.
So the estimated time is 4 hours and 29 minutes.
It means in this case, we are 6,000 times faster.
And of course, we get a different checksum.
It's probably obvious, but any tool has its own checksum because they use different algorithms.
So blocks room is using, under the hood, some cryptographic hash function, but it's a different
construction.
So we don't get the same checksum.
Now, it's not available everywhere, anywhere.
But I believe in copper.
So if you have a Fedora or CentOS or well system, you can enable the copper repo and
then you can install the package and play with the tool.
So the block hash library.
Basically blocks room is just using the library to compute the hash.
So you can also use the library to integrate this functionality in your program.
The library is very simple.
This is the entire API.
It gives you the standard interface to create a new hash, to update it, and to get the result,
find an interface, and of course, to free the resources they used.
So if you use any cryptographic hash libraries, maybe hashlib or OpenSSL, you know these interfaces.
Now the important difference is that when you update, when you give it a buffer with
this data, this API will detect zeros in the data.
And if you find a zero block, we hash it much, much faster.
So this increases the support by one order of magnitude or something like this.
Even if you read from the file, you give it a buffer with zeros, we can hash it much faster.
But the most important API is the zero API, which is new API that no other library supports.
So if you know that the range in a file is not allocated, let's say empty 8 terabyte
image, you check the file, you see that you have 8 terabyte whole.
So you can just input this range to the library, and it will hash it really, really quickly.
Much, much faster than any other way.
And you don't have to read anything for this.
So how fast is it?
For that, we can process about 2 gigabytes of data.
If you give it a buffer with zeros, we can process almost 50 gigabytes per second.
And the real cache zero API can process almost 3 terabytes per second.
And this is on this laptop, if you try on FLM1, and this is the first M1 from two years
ago, it's almost 3 times faster for data, and almost 5 times faster for zero, up to
13 terabytes per second.
And I didn't try the newer M1s or M2.
So if you want to use this library, we install the develop packages, we install the headers
and the library package, the libs package, and your application will depend on the libs
package.
And everything should be automatic using RPM.
Now the most important stuff is integrating this into your image, because this is the
natural tool to consume this functionality.
So I have patches in review for adding this new command.
It's pretty simple.
You give it the sign name, you have progress, you can control caching, and you can force
the image format.
And with this, you can compute the checksum of anything that your image can access.
You get the same checksum.
It uses the block cache library using the same configuration.
So both tools are compatible.
You can check my QM4 if you want to see the details.
So what is the difference if you compare to blocksum?
Usually it runs almost the same, a little faster, maybe 5% faster.
In some cases, it can be 45% faster, like in this special case, image full of zeros.
I think because QM4 image is closer to the data, it does not have to copy the data to
QM-BD and then read it over the socket.
So this is really the best place to use this technology.
So let's see a small live demo.
So I have several images.
Let's try to look at 35 images.
I think we have 6 gigabyte image, a little more than 1 gigabyte of data.
And we have this QK2 image, again, similar size.
And we can compare them.
And of course, they are identical, and we can create checksum with Birkash, Birkashum.
And we'll get the same checksum pretty quickly.
So let's try a bigger image.
This time, we'll use the pogus flag to make it more fun.
This is 50 gigabyte file with 24 gigabyte of data.
So it will take some time to compute it.
You can see that the pogus jumps really quickly when we find a big hole.
So it took 12 seconds, and we will not try to use Shasum now.
And let's try the 8-terabyte image, which is really fast.
And let's try the same use QM-BD image with the new checksum command.
OK, takes more time to type than to compute it.
OK, so this is all for the demo.
And the last part is how you can contribute to the project.
So the easiest stuff is just install it and play with it and test it, and if you find
any issue, report it.
If you have interesting machines, benchmark it and send the results to the project.
We have some results in the readme now.
Probably should be in a better place.
To run the benchmarks, you need to build it on your system.
It should be easy enough.
The most important stuff is packaging and hardware.
Packaging for Fedora and central central is mostly done.
I just need to get this into Fedora.
There is some review process that I probably need some help on this.
Other Linux resource, if you want to package it for Debian or whatever, please do and contribute
to the project.
I like to keep all packaging upstream, so I will be very happy to add whatever you need
to make it transparent.
So it will not break when I change something upstream.
Make OS and FreeBSD, I tested it on this platform without LibnBD because we don't have LibnBD
there.
We also cannot port it before we port LibnBD and package it.
But we can package only the library part, which is really useful for QM.
Missing features, there are a lot of stuff that can be added.
You can look at the site.
We have on the issue track a lot of issues that we can add, like supporting any image
format because currently we support only Q2 and O.
CheckSoom, multiple image, use the file to verify CheckSoom using what we recorded before
and stuff like this.
Improve the CI.
And even more important, but of course much more work, integrate this into your system.
So Oveot already supports CheckSoom API using all the implementation.
This rest project uses this API to verify the back-ups.
It can be upgraded to the new tool.
Oveot can use it.
For example, when you import image to using CDI importer or many for storage operation,
Oveot can verify operation with this tool.
And running a port connected to the disk and reading the image and measuring it.
Maybe other systems.
I don't know.
If you like other systems and think that it can be useful, you can contact me to discuss
it.
If I want to see the project links, we have the project in GitLab.
Also the issue track in the project and the copy of the project I showed before.
So that's all.
How much time?
How much time do we have?
Your question.
Five minutes for question four.
Okay.
Yes.
I have a question about the special case with block hash and block, I'm sorry, zero.
How do you handle it under the hood?
I have a specific one, but how is that done?
How do we handle zeros?
How do we do it efficiently?
So I have a bonus section at the end of the slides that you can get from the site.
Basically the idea is that we split the image to blocks using fixed size.
The last block can be smaller, but it doesn't matter.
Then we compute the hash for each block, but for zero blocks, we don't need to compute
anything because we know that like we compute basically when you start operation, we compute
the hash of the zero block based on the configuration.
Then each time we see a zero block, we can use the per computed hash, so it's cost nothing.
Then we compute the hash from the list of hashes.
This is called a hash list.
It's not really new.
This cost something, you need to pay something for computing the hashes, but they are much,
much smaller.
Like whatever's magnitude smaller than the actual data.
To make it even faster, we also use multiple threads.
The previous slide show actually what's done in each worker.
We split the blocks and we map them to multiple workers in the same time and send them to
the worker queue and the workers go and compute this combined hash, this block hash.
Finally we create the hash from the worker and hashes.
Yes.
I have a question, so how hard is it for you to add a new checksum algorithm instead of
SHA-1?
How hard is it to use?
Can we use another checksum algorithm?
Yes, in blocks, you have the parameter, you can specify another algorithm.
You can use SHA-1 or MD5 or whatever, but anything that OpenSSL supports, it also supports.
I'm not sure if this is the best option, maybe we limit it because SHA-1 is considered broken.
But currently this is what we support.
Anything that OpenSSL provides.
Yes.
How do you identify zero blocks?
What?
How do we identify zero blocks?
We use the very popular method that somebody ought to block about it, someone from the
kernel a few years ago.
You can use MenComp with an offset to compare the file against itself.
You check the first 16 bytes and then you can just check the two pointers, the start
of the image and the start of the image plus 16th and it can process up to 50 gigabytes
per second on this machine.
Very efficient.
Yes.
I have a short question.
That's a question.
Okay.
I didn't get the question.
Basically, you support the second algorithm.
Yes.
Did you try un-cryptographic algorithm?
We didn't try because we tried to use something secure.
We tried to get something which is secure with the original hash function.
We can try other algorithms.
It's interesting stuff that we can try.
Thank you.
You can mute the microphone.