Right, so welcome.
My name is Remko and I'm here to talk about two very undeclarative but very minimal and
hopefully useful languages.
So the first one is FOURTH.
FOURTH is a very minimal programming language that's been around since the 70s.
It's had mostly applications in low-level contexts such as embedded systems, spacecraft
controllers and so on, but it's had some other applications as well.
If you look at FOURTH, the most obvious thing to notice is that it's stack-based.
So it uses a reverse polish notation where you first put something on the stack and then
you call a function.
But other than that, it looks like a regular high-level language with syntax for constant
variables for comments, syntax for function definitions, loops and conditions and so on.
But actually that's an illusion.
FOURTH has almost no syntax.
So FOURTH executes through a very simple interpreter loop.
So what it does is it reads something up until the next space and then decides, is it a number?
I'm going to put it on the stack.
Is it something else?
Then I assume it's a function which is called a word in FOURTH and it's going to execute
it.
So symbols is just like any normal word, so it's just a function of FOURTH.
Same goes for the colon.
Colon starts a new definition of a word.
Colon when it executes, it puts the interpreter into a special mode called compilation mode.
Now in this compilation mode, the interpreter still advances token by token, but when it
encounters a number instead of putting it on the stack, what it does is it generates
some codes that will put that number on the stack later when this word is executed.
Same for another symbol.
Instead of calling this function, what it's going to do is it's going to compile some
code that will call this function when this word is executed.
So the same goes actually another, sorry, so it's going to compile.
The exception for this is that there is a thing called immediate words.
Immediate words are always executed even if your interpreter is in compiler mode.
So an example of such an immediate word is the opening parenthesis which starts a comment.
When it executes, what it will do is it will actually consume all the input.
Another immediate word is the semicolon.
So the semicolon is what you see when you end the definition.
What this will do is it will put your interpreter back out of compilation mode into interpretation
mode.
Other of these immediate words are the loops and the ifs and the nels.
You can actually create your own immediate words and as such extend the compiler because
these are executed at compile time.
So you extend the compiler and you create your own language.
So in summary, fourth is actually nothing but a very simple interpreter loop with an
integrated compiler.
There is no syntax, almost to fourth, just space delimited tokens.
All the behavior of the language is in the execution of these definitions.
And you can actually extend the compiler yourself.
This combination of super simplicity and power has actually made fourth a very attractive
language to implement on a new piece of hardware and a restricted piece of hardware.
Typically these fourth implementations are targeted at hardware assembly but you can
actually do this in any low level language.
Which brings me to the second language of my talk, WebAssembly.
So I think everybody here knows WebAssembly.
It's an open standard for portable binary code.
Most browsers can execute WebAssembly.
Many languages can compile to WebAssembly so the result is that you can run all these
languages in a browser.
Although WebAssembly was designed for the web, there's actually nothing web specific
about WebAssembly.
It's just an open standard of portable code.
Most of the information you find online about WebAssembly is about how you compile your
favorite language to WebAssembly or how you run WebAssembly in your browser.
So a few years ago I wanted to figure out what was actually under the hood of WebAssembly.
And at the same time I came across fourth so what I did was I combined both hoping that
I would learn something about both.
So that's why I created WA fourth.
WA fourth is a small fourth system.
It's completely handwritten in WebAssembly and it compiles to WebAssembly.
So goals are, WebAssembly tries to, WA fourth tries to do as much as possible in WebAssembly.
Now the problem is WebAssembly is a portable standard so you cannot do everything in WebAssembly.
For example, it needs to do very few things outside of WebAssembly.
For example, reading or writing a character to the output or reading from the input.
WA fourth tries to be simple.
So it's just one big WebAssembly file handwritten.
There are no dependencies, no complex tools.
The compiler is very simply written.
It still tries to be complete enough to be useful.
There's an ANS standard that defines what a fourth interpreter needs to implement, the
minimal set of words.
WA fourth implements these and implements a bunch of other words as well.
What isn't the goal is speed.
So of course, because WA fourth is implemented in WebAssembly, you're going to get some speed
for free.
But still the compiler is very naive so I don't expect it to be very fast.
Same goes for binary size of the system.
It's written in WebAssembly so it's going to be naturally very small.
In fact, it's about 14 kilobytes of WebAssembly compiled binary WebAssembly.
However, I'm not doing any code golfing or something like that to keep the system small
because I want to keep it simple.
And as most fourths are not really known to be very user friendly and WA fourth is not
different, although it does emit some debugging information to make debugging easier, as you
will see.
So what can you do with WA fourth?
Well, you can embed it in any JavaScript application, which means you can run fourth code inside
your JavaScript and you get bidirectional bindings to the system and back to JavaScript.
To illustrate this, I have a few example applications.
So the first one is the standard fourth console that always exists where you can interactively
execute fourth code and you can even interactively compile code and then run this compiled code.
So it's a repple actually.
I also have a small graphical programming environment where you can create some graphics
using a logo like turtle graphics language, but it uses fourth.
It looks a lot like logo, but it's actually fourth.
And I took this a bit further and then I created a notebook extension, a VS Code extension
to create VS Code notebooks.
So these are actually formatted markdown files interleaved with runnable code.
So you can run this code.
This is ideal for tutorials because you can have the code directly there.
You can execute it.
You can change some parameters and then see what the effect is by rerunning the program.
Now, because this is just WebAssembly and it's just a very small system, there's also
a script that converts these notebooks into a standalone, small standalone HTML file with
all the functionality, but you don't actually need VS Code anymore to run it.
Now let's have a look under the hood.
Like most WebAssembly formats, WebAssembly has a text-based format which is much easier
to read than the binary format for humans.
So this text-based format is based on S expressions, so it looks a lot like Lisp.
So this right part here is the entire fourth interpreter that I described earlier, but
it comes straight out of WA fourth.
It's actually quite easy to understand.
So first it starts by parsing something, parsing the token, and then it's going to either execute
it if it's a function or it's going to compile it if you're in compiler mode.
Or if it's a number, then it's going to put it on the stack or it's going to compile it.
So this tree-like code structure is then transformed to binary WebAssembly using a tool from WebIt.
WebIt is the WebAssembly binary toolkit.
This is actually a toolkit with a lot of tools to work with WebAssembly files.
It's a very interesting project to look at.
So this is the entire interpreter.
The interpreter is actually quite simple.
The interesting part is the part where you have to compile something.
So you have to compile a call when you're in compiler mode.
So how does this work?
Well somewhere in memory there is a hard-coded binary header of a WebAssembly module with
one function in it.
So when a new word definition starts, what happens is some values in this header are
reset and the pointer is initialized to start at the end of the header.
So each time the interpreter, this is the piece of the interpreter, needs to compile
a call to a function.
What it does is it generates some raw WebAssembly hex codes and puts it at the end of the header.
So for example if it needs to do a call, what it does is it generates a hex code for a const
instruction with the index of the function to call and then an indirect call instruction.
And so the compiler keeps on adding binary code to the end of this module.
Now once you reach the end of the definition, this binary piece of code needs to be loaded
into the system.
So WebAssembly doesn't support anything for this yet.
So there's no support for just-in-time compilation, although there are some discussions about it.
So what WA4 does is it takes a pointer to this piece in memory of binary code and it
passes it to the host system.
So in this case it's JavaScript.
And JavaScript has a small piece of code here running.
What it does is it takes this binary, it uses the WebAssembly API to create a new WebAssembly
module and then it instantiates it.
That's all JavaScript has to do.
The rest is tracked by WA4.
It keeps track of which module corresponds to which function that it needs to call or
compile later on.
So here you can see the system in action.
So what's happening here is now you start at a definition, you start by compiling something,
so you're still in compilation mode.
And so it's only when you reach the end of the definition that suddenly you're going
to see a new entry in your WebAssembly debugger with a function that has been loaded.
So this is the generated WebAssembly code that's been generated by the compiler.
You can get even more control over this compilation process by writing your own WebAssembly inside
forth.
So this is actually, this is again no new syntax.
This is just standard forth with some user-defined words.
And there's a direct one-to-one mapping from this to this, if you can read it, that probably
can from there.
The last thing I want to note about implementation detail is that most forts have very efficient
execution by using a system they call threaded code.
So threaded code is actually called doing jump instructions all over the place using
values that come from memory or from registers.
Now this is something you can do in WebAssembly.
WebAssembly only allows structured jumps.
So WebAssembly is actually a structured programming language.
What WebAssembly does have is function tables.
So these are dynamic tables where you can put functions, function references in, and
then it comes with a special instruction where you can say jump to the function at this index.
This is a system that WA-4th uses for calling the words.
Now the downside is that this is a very inefficient system compared to direct calls or jumps.
So I said that speed wasn't really a goal for WA-4th, but it's still interesting to
get some idea of ballpark numbers of speed and size involved.
So I did some very unscientific thing, and I took an algorithm, in this case the SEVE
algorithm to compute prime numbers.
I took a fourth implementation, ported it to JavaScript, CE, WebAssembly, and then ran
it a few times and see what the result was.
Again, this is not a very representative benchmark, but it's just here to get a feel for some
numbers.
So if you look at the execution times, WA-4th is about 10 times faster than a JavaScript
4th version.
This is to be expected.
JavaScript 4th versions do pure interpretation.
WA-4th uses compilation, so there's no surprise there.
What is a bit surprising is that G-4th, which is a native 4th, is not much faster than WA-4th.
I have no idea why this is.
I'm suspicious about this result.
Maybe it's because I'm using an architecture that G-4th isn't optimized for.
JavaScript is 10 times faster than WA-4th, which is also normal because WA-4th needs
to do these constant indirect jumps, and JavaScript doesn't have this problem.
It doesn't need to do any function calling at all.
And then finally, if you have the C version and you compile it to WebAssembly using Mscripton,
it's about as fast as running the raw WebAssembly, and the native version of the algorithm is
slightly faster.
Although you have to say the WebAssembly engine is pretty good at running this code compared
to native code.
So if we look at the size of the runtime and the code that is executed, the main takeaway
here is that WA-4th is actually a very small system.
It's like about 15K, but you need a complete browser to run it.
So that's, of course, huge to run.
So the question is, can we improve this situation?
So actually, there are several standalone implementations of WebAssembly.
In different languages, for example, Webit has a reference implementation in C++.
There's wasm time, which is security focused and speed focused in Rust, but there are several
others.
But these only do the WebAssembly part, so there's still this small piece of code that
is the small pieces that are outside of the system that we need to call out to.
If you wanted to use all these engines and try this out and create a standalone version,
you would need to write this little piece of code in all these languages against all
these APIs.
Luckily, there's something called WebAssembly C API.
And this is a standardized black box API that most of these systems implement.
So actually, the only thing you have to do is write these 200 lines of implementation
in dependency, and then I could drop in any engine I wanted and then have a standalone
version of my system.
Now if we look at the same benchmark again, we can see that speed wise Webit is about
100 times slower than the browser version, which is normal.
I mean, this version in Webit, that's a reference implementation.
It's very naive.
It just does what it needs to do to be functional.
What is a bit weird is that wasn't time which is supposed to be fast.
It's still about 10 times faster than the browser version, and there is no good reason
for this.
So I don't know why this is.
I haven't tried other engines yet.
Now if you look at size, you see that if you use a relatively optimizing system, you still
have 90 megabytes, which is a lot smaller than a browser.
But still, if you have a system of about 15K, this is still big.
Can we do something about this?
Well, you need the WebAssembly runtime to be able to run your fourth code and to compile
your code and load it.
But typically most programs, once you did the first pass and you did all the compilation
necessary, you no longer need a compiler if you want to run the program again.
So you can do some ahead of time compiling.
And this is where WA4C comes in.
So what it does is it takes your fourth program, it uses WA4C to run your program once.
And at the end of the cycle, it's going to look at all the modules that you created.
It's going to combine them all, combine the final state, and then create one big WebAssembly
module out of this.
And it's going to take this big module and then use another tool from Webit.
Webit is really a cool tool set.
It's going to use another tool from Webit called WA4C to transform this big module into
C. And then it's going to use your host compiler to create a native executable.
So the end result is that you have a fourth code to native compiler and your native binary
is your fourth code with the rest of the fourth system still in there, but the compiler left
out.
And the cool thing is that because this is all platform independent stuff up until the
native compiler, you can actually do cross compiling easily.
So you can just do cross compiling from fourth to any architecture you want.
And all this code is about 500 lines and uses a lot of stuff from Webit actually.
And Webit is the only dependency here.
So if you look at our final table of benchmarks, we see that the speed is slightly better than
it was before in the browser version and the binary is becoming a lot smaller.
So the entire system is only about 116K in the end of native code.
Now there's still room for improvement here.
So what WA4C does is it just throws together all these modules and then generates the big
module.
Now this big module, there are no cross module calls anymore.
So what you could do is actually do some post processing.
You could change all these indirect calls into direct calls, which could speed up a
lot because the calls are really the bottleneck here.
Another thing you could do is throw away code that you don't need.
So in conclusion, this was a very fast talk.
I could only touch upon things very briefly.
And what I did was I used fourth to explore low level language implementation in WebAssembly.
Those fourth is so minimal, I was able to keep things very simple, try out a lot of
things and go a lot of places.
But I think a lot of the things that I've shown here are actually applicable to other
languages, so more declarative languages if you want to compare to WebAssembly.
Although I have to say if you don't know fourth yet, I can really recommend having a look
at it because I find that there's some interesting philosophies and concepts behind it.
Thank you.
I have a question.
We seem to be dealing in rather old languages today.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I always have been.
So list is sixties, I think, or fifties even.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yes.
So yes, I.
Okay, one question.
Yeah, one thing is that there was a potentially you could, I'm not sure, one potential direction
is that you could also consider doing the code generation in JavaScript as in you can
just create function out of binary and out of text in JavaScript.
And the same thing, I'm not sure the infrastructure how much can be shared, but the same thing
could happen also JavaScript side as in the thing of compiling the code JavaScript side
and then it's, so it could get to JavaScript.
I'm not sure if it's interesting or.
So the question is, can I reach the same perform?
Can you reach the same performance if you do it in JavaScript?
Potentially there is this thing passing through WebAssembly and this J4, the GSPort you mentioned,
but potentially it's also possible to do code generation in JavaScript.
So yes.
So the question is, can you do also this code generation JavaScript?
Yes, of course you can.
Potentially you can.
So typically what you will see is the handy part because I'm working in WebAssembly is
that I have all the WebAssembly low levels at my disposal.
So the hard part if you go to the other languages is that you're going to be, need to have something
to manipulate these, for example, this function table is very critical.
So you need to be able to talk to that and hook into that.
That's going to be the tricky part, but it's definitely possible.
But it's easier if you do a directing job in WebAssembly, of course, you would never
write a complex language directly in WebAssembly that that's madness.
So you can do it with fourth, but I would not recommend it with anything.
Thank you.
One more question.
Yes.
I'm interested because you also use it with SMG to see combi.
I didn't know I used the WebAssembly to see compared to performance was quite on par with
the.
So if I took the C algorithm, it was a little it was about it's a bad, bad benchmark.
So the performance was about 10 percent slower.
So it was not much, much slower than pure the native binary.
So it's C compiled to native and C compiled to WebAssembly was only a little bit.
So of course you are running.
That's not the number.
OK.
But you are running in a WebAssembly.
You are running in and still running in a virtual machine.
So the fact that the performance is going to be maybe a little bit slower, but it's
I thought it was still OK, given that you're still in a in a V.M.
We need to solve.
OK.
So senator Meyer, thank you for NOUpFkeep.