I'm going to talk a little bit about Guy and Zig.
So I prepared two talks.
One talk you can download online.
There was kind of an overview of why I made these choices and why we're doing this.
But I think it's better just to hit the command line or a shell.
So many people will recognize this Emacs.
The letters fall off on the side, but it shouldn't matter too much.
And then I'm going to run in a shell.
So I don't know if everyone is aware, but a GIG shell is a proper container.
So only the tools are pulled in that we define.
This is done in the GIG.scheme file.
Oh man.
In the GIG.scheme file we define the dependency we want.
So Guile is there and Zig is there.
So in the file we find Zig version.
So that's in the container and then Guile minus V is also there.
But VI, for example, is not.
And if this was properly running on Debian it would be visible.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to run Zig to build my library.
It's a dynamic library.
And then I use package config to pick up the Guile compile switches.
I'm going to compile it against a little C library.
Sorry, yeah, C file.
Uh oh.
Yeah, um.
Right, yeah, I missed the second line I see, yeah.
Right.
So Guile is almost designed for linking against C. Right, so I wrote a little C program to
show you that.
And it can, it calls Guile functions.
So scheme from int is a Guile function.
So it switches, it turns test into a Guile integer essentially.
And then a boolean.
And then I call this function here in C. Right, my increment and function.
You can see that it uses Guile objects to pass into the function.
And there's also a Guile object returned.
Right.
So it's very minimalistic code.
Now I just need to get a compile it.
Now it did compile.
But now it doesn't find the library.
So I need to add the library path.
So I'm just doing this raw so you can see what is happening.
You know, I mean if you had a proper build script you can account for all this.
But you can see it says hello world from three to four.
Right, so that's what the C function does.
Now I want to do the same thing in Zig.
Right, so I created, actually what I want to do is I want to call Zig from, you know,
the same library that I'm using.
I want to call it from Guile.
Right.
So let's try that.
So I'm in Guile now and I added the local search path for the library.
Right.
So here we load the shared library libmy.so.
Right, it loads into Guile.
I want to try something like, and it says it doesn't find the procedure because I haven't
defined it.
So that doesn't work very well.
Nope.
Let me see where we are.
Yes, I call it thing Zig.
With an underscore.
All right.
It's not very Guile-like.
Yeah, so that's some conventions and I already ignored it.
So Guile has a wide range of C functions in the library.
And these can be called, you know, so if you look for the C function, which one did we
use before?
Yeah, or Scheme from Int you can see here, right?
Scheme from Int.
So in the Guile reference manual.
You see in the reference manual almost on every page you see the sort of the C functions
that you could also call as Lisp functions.
You know, and the Scheme from Int should be there.
It's a long list, but that's the idea.
So when you actually use the Guile manual, you will see the C interface to the C A B
I.
Now, the interesting thing about Zig is that it faithfully, you know, uses the C A B I.
So, you know, anything you can define in Zig, you can essentially access from Guile.
So let's look at my Zig file and I say ping.
Yeah, so this is the, you know, sort of the equivalent C function, sorry, Zig Vinc function
that we had defined in C earlier.
Yeah, you have a ping Zig.
It takes a Scheme object as an input and it returns a Scheme object, right?
And it just pings it back.
So how come I can see the Scheme object as it is defined now?
And as a matter of fact, Zig can export, sorry, can import C include files.
Yeah, it's actually one command.
Yeah, so you say Zig translate C, right?
Then the path to the include file, then the include file itself and it turns into, you
know, it turns into a proper Zig file.
And this Zig file you can just import and it will work.
So all the functions that are defined by Guile that are exported for, that you could use
from C in principle are now available in Zig, including the objects.
Yeah, so if you look at this Zig file, it doesn't look very nice, right?
But it's all there and it actually just worked in one go.
I didn't have, I had to delete one line in it.
All right, so yeah, the other thing of course that is that I'm using ping Zig 1 right now.
Okay, so let's try hello.
And it pings back hello, right?
I mean, that's what we see in the Zig function here.
And Guile is not a strictly typed language.
I mean, it's typed, but it's not in the sense that here we have a variable that you can,
you know, in the one case I'm using an integer, in the next case I'm using a string.
And this makes for, apart from the fact that I'm using a grapple where I'm actually talking
to the, you know, to the Zig back end, it also gives me a lot of flexibility in what,
you know, how I define these functions and these variables that get passed.
Okay, so let's do something a little bit more complex.
So the, you know, this exploration that I had with Zig and Z and Guile, it's also all
online.
You can just read it.
It's in a GitLab repository.
Yeah, so if you define a function in Zig, you know, just naively like ping Zig here,
it won't be immediately visible to Guile.
You need to create a mapping for that.
Yeah, and this is in the Guile documentation.
It's exactly the same thing in C. See if I can find it.
Yeah, here it is.
So when you initialise the module, which means when you load the shared library, right, it
will call this function and you will define a sub, sorry, it will, yeah, define the function
call here.
So in Grand Zig here is ping Zig, right?
Ping Zig and it has one argument.
All right?
You need to do that to make the symbol visible to the Guile interpreter.
That's basically what you have to do.
There's nothing more to it.
Which is kind of boring.
So yeah, I'm of the opinion that, you know, that we need multiple programming languages.
You know, when you talk about Zig, there's often, or even C++, you know, there's often
the elephant in the room.
I'm not going to name it.
But this is a language that tries to be everything.
You know, and you end up with a very complex language.
Also the compiler is dog slow.
I don't know if anyone is using the unnamed language.
And then it has, you know, it has a borrow checker which acts like, you know, a nagging
wife.
You know, it keeps talking to you.
And I tried it, and I tried to love it because it's a functional language, a functional programming
language.
But it kept talking to me and it kept going me out of my flow.
I just couldn't keep moving.
So I think it's probably wiser to have a language like C, which is, you know, you have to realize
that most of the code in the world today is written in C++ still.
If you want a type of performance, you will end up with a strictly typed language, which
is imperative to some degree because CPUs are imperative.
We don't have functional programming CPUs.
So to optimize that stuff, you end up with the type of language that has to cater for
that.
But nobody loves programming in C++, and C programming is also hard to shoot yourself
in the food language, I call it.
So it's nice if you can have a language that has somewhat stronger guarantees, but it's
still blazingly fast and still kind of imperative.
And then have something like guile, which actually allows you to be productive, right?
And do functional programming when you want to.
So you end up with this type of mixture.
Have I got five minutes?
Five minutes to questions.
So one additional thing I would like to show you.
Sorry, that's mine.
So you can, I mean, using the guile libraries, you can essentially build up lists, which
is the fundamental for many lists like programming efforts, but when you talk about performance,
you'd like to deal with arrays of data.
So continuous blocks of memory where you have integers in a row or doubles in a row, and
you're able to address these integers and doubles.
Of course, you can do that from guile, but if you write high performance code like we
do, you want to be able to use it as a vector in Zig.
So you have an index, the base pointer to the vector, and then you have an index, and
you should be able to fetch out the data object that you want.
So just wrote a little example here.
So this is the list example.
Let me see if I can find the vector array.
So you have, I wrote a little, let me move that down.
A little Zig function, which says my increment in floating points 64 bits vector Zig.
I'm very good at naming, apparently.
You pass in a guile vector, which is again a scheme object.
It returns a scheme object, which is again a vector, right?
And then it calls this guile function, scheme F64, that's where the naming came from.
Came from guile.
So I said X, so I said in the vector, I set at position one, so index one, I set the value
3.7.
So this is kind of happening in guile-ish C code.
So it's calling essentially guile C functions.
And I proved that it works.
You can look it up.
But here, I'm using a proper index.
I think, let me see.
Yeah.
So you increment the F64 vector, right?
This is the old version.
Here I get a handle on the array.
And then I get data.
So I get a vector here.
If our data is a vector, of the elements of the vector array, right?
And then I index the data points based on the vector of the floating point and show
zero, one, and number two.
And that's what it shows.
So I'm not going to do that live, but that's the idea.
Yeah, I'm done.
Yeah, so it's in a nutshell.
The code and the slides are online, so you can have a look, have a go.
Any questions?
Yes.
I'm trying to learn the same language that we cannot name right now.
And I was wondering, how long did you try to log the board?
I checked the computer.
I tried quite long, actually.
So I read five books.
I probably took two months and wrote a thousand lines of code or so to decide it wasn't for
me.
But yeah, I hear quite a few stories like this, which are very similar.
I think it's a language for masochists.
A language for masochists.
You have to be a brilliant person.
A brilliant masochist.
Let's put it that way.
You have to be brilliant to keep that all in your head.
You're going to get garbage collectors soon again, they say.
Yeah, so see.
Yeah, I'm not complaining about it because people who program in Rust, they do better
than in C++.
So the compiler does help a lot.
I think it does lead to better code.
I've given students work in Rust and they do write better code because the compiler
actually helps you.
But it also takes them a long time to get something done.
So it depends on what your goals are.
If you have to write perfect software to launch your rocket, you might want to do it that
way.
But if it's just like me, in my job we write mostly throwaway code.
It doesn't pay.
What kind of applications do you want for it?
Bioinformatics.
I'm in science.
Yeah, we do have long-lived code, but it's usually by accident.
So you write something.
People start using it and then 10 years later it becomes mainstream.
It actually happens to one of our projects.
And then it's too late to do better.
So at one point you showed us how to convert the Zig file to C, right?
And it wasn't really necessary in order to call the style stuff from within Zig?
No.
The guy that adheres to the C ABI, right?
So it has a C calling interface.
But I use the scheme object.
So that came from there.
But actually the scheme object is really simple when you look at it.
So it could be that you can just roll your own.
Yeah?
So you created the language from scratch.
So why did you decide to use the semicolons and curly braces in it?
Well, I didn't design Zig.
I should have been clearer.
Sorry.
Nor have I any input on Guile.
Unlike other people here.
But yeah, I dabble in languages.
I use people who often ask me what is the language of the year.
I think at that point it was Scala.
I'm embarrassed to say.
But I think Zig does appeal to me.
Yeah?
So Fortran is a bit difficult because the very different languages Fortran and Julia.
But I think Zig tries to be in the space of C.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's a general purpose, systems programming and uncompromising speed.
And it is fast.
The compiler itself compiles itself in 10 minutes on a standard machine.
But I think, for example, it doesn't have exception handling.
Yeah, it uses a different approach, which is more like a maybe monad.
And even C++, typically you'll have exception handling, which every time you call a function,
it has to carry state with it to be able to unroll the stack.
And this causes overheads.
That's one thing.
With C++, the other thing is that in the background there's often a lot of memory allocation going on.
Especially when it's kind of unavoidable to use SCL these days as best practice.
And I find that in Zig, because it's closer to the C philosophy, it's actually much faster.
So, oh hey.
Are you planning to write a tutorial in the guide manual for how to do this?
Yeah, we should.
I think the next speaker needs to go on.
No?
How much time do you have?
Two minutes to go on, one and a half.
Yeah, you can.
It's good to switch.
Straight on.