So, my name is Marie de Brumais, consulting for digital humanists, the cultural shock
be developing tools and pedagogy.
This talk is given on behalf of the Center for Digital Humanities in Uppsala, which is
where I work.
Here you have my contact.
You can contact me via email, mastodon, as well as my website.
I'm an engineer in digital humanities.
We'll come back on that later.
What you need to know is that I'm located in two countries in the city of Leland, France,
and in Uppsala, where my work and university is.
From my spare time, I'm a activist in Uppsala women's coding, as well as sometimes in Ulug
and Raoul in Uppsala.
So, I'm not the first digital humanist you are encountering in the first day.
I did a little bit of a survey.
And so, at least four people I could identify as digital humanists in the past, as the name
of Jan Jonsson, Van Eeley, Guido, Ollie, Obert, Antoine, Fauchet.
Thank you to them for opening the path and just being pure near and indirectly making
me feel welcome in coming to your community.
So, without further introduction, what is digital humanities?
It's a pretty new field and it's a blurry term.
I'm not going to have the talk of three days and three nights without sleeping about how
to define it.
What you need to know is that it's the field in the intersections between computer science
and humanities, all sorts of humanities.
And what in this context an engineer in digital humanities is, it's someone technical that
will have expertise in one or several domains of computer science and whose mission is to
help humanists in their project.
By humanists we can mean a philosopher, literature analyst, historian, sociology, archaeology,
etc. etc.
I thought to give you a bit of context, examples would talk more than a long discourse.
So if you're an engineer in digital humanities, you could be helping a theologist mapping
all the colors of the Bible to show the color ambiance of the New Testament.
You could be also building an online database to help an art historian broadcasting their
un-psychopedical knowledge about some engravings of books, etc.
You do not need to read this complicated table, but I will attract your attention to a couple
of things.
First, observe the subjects.
The subjects are pretty academics, academical subjects, things that computer scientists
will normally not be very familiar to, like literature, Scandinavian languages, linguistics,
here the ALM means the archives, etc. etc.
We have an audience of very academic people, people that have no contact with the corporate
world, that have been in academia and stayed in academia after.
Look at this, we have a pretty gender balanced group and slightly actually female dominated.
I counted 16 women here in this room, including me.
So that's an interesting contrast.
Actually the title probably doesn't speak to you too much because it's a pretty specialized
topic.
Could we even say niche topics?
I had fun making a table of the differences between the engineering world and the humanistic
world.
By the way, I have a background in classics before going to natural language processing,
so I'm accustomed to this switch of culture.
Additionally, to the remarks I have made, I will add that among engineers and computer
scientists, the programming is the norm and often as an operating system you will see
Linux or Mac, or at least when I was in the department of natural language processing
that was what I was seeing, you would use in an academic context later, you would exchange
terminal apps, etc. etc.
Whereas if you land in the department of humanities, you will have a point and click as a norm
and offer proprietary tools as a norm.
Windows Mac pour a point where I have been asked in conferences to give pour a point
PPTX files and Word documents and no one gets offended by that.
So yeah, industry influence, I can make a good job.
And I think finally the most important is that in computer science we are very metrics
oriented, optimizing maybe speed or quantified performances, whereas the humanists are very
question oriented.
So between those two different audience that we need to gather in digital humanities, how
do we help each other?
And to be able to continue my talk or end my talk in something positive, I will start
in the, let's say, more obstacles or negative points of trying this marriage between the
two fields.
I think if you want to have free software, computer science and free software in the
digital humanities, you need to overcome a lack of visibility from the free software
world towards the humanist.
And I think this Versa, and I thought of taking short example of technical tools we are working
with.
So in digital humanities, I'm specialized in web scraping and NLP.
And as engineers, we tend to use, I would say, open source tools like Python, Dutiful
Soup and Spacey, whereas people that will be less computer savvy in digital humanities
will use more proprietary softwares such as WebScraper.io or NSCONC, which has the advantage
to be point and click tools, to be simpler, more straightforward, to have less functionalities
as well.
And yes, another remark is that I noticed recently while giving courses to digital humanists
that people are asking me if I can teach them GitHub.
And I say, no, I can teach you Git, not GitHub.
So it's very revealing the fact that they don't even know the difference or what it
means.
It's very revealing that they know GitHub before understanding the notion of Git.
So I think this is, to stress my point, about lack of visibility of the open source world,
or maybe the over visibility of the freeware world.
The second obstacle to bringing free software to digital humanists is maybe a lack of cohesion.
I mean, digital humanities is an essence topic where we have a lot of groups already spread
with different languages, digital historians, digital literature analysts, et cetera, et
cetera.
And so they have already had time gathering together.
So in this context, it's hard to make as well a community of open source enthusiasts.
So it's not yet built this community in this context.
The next point or obstacle is, I would say, the lack of common references, or I would
say that not of common values.
So it's hard to find a language to understand each other's.
We'll come back on that in the positive points.
And yeah, that's it for the obstacles I can see.
Then on the positive points, or on what could make this Maria Josephus, we have first, I
think humanists will be a very receptive audience to the philosophy of free software.
I mean, enlightenment philosophy existed before and was at least a student in humanities and
was a student in humanities before, which has started and was born.
And so they have those references and those references to philosophy and value of spreading
the knowledge of sharing.
They have a lot of activism in them.
I mean, half of my department is vegan, so it reveals something about them.
They are an nascent but varied community.
I think that's a positive point.
It's a crowd that is diverse, very unusual for a dev crowd.
Even non-neglectable, they have financial means.
The humanities in general do not have much financial needs, not as much as science.
But digital humanists are attracting grants and subsidies for projects.
And that's an indirect way to finance open source and free software.
I'm an engineer developing tools for digital humanists, and my salary is paid by the government
because digital humanities is such a buzzword.
It's finally one very interesting thing about this crowd is that they know about domains
that maybe engineers and computer scientists have interest on but do not have a formal
training on.
Part of them have access easily to training on communication, science of education, ethics,
and are trained to think critically all the time.
I will end my presentation not in certitudes but in doubts and questions.
The questions we could have are ideas to reach better this community and how to make them
feel welcome.
That was it for my talk.
After I just kept for illustration purpose in case I have questions that I happen to
have prepared, and references here all in the slides.
Thank you.
We can have questions.
Yes, I will open the floor to questions.
Are you aware of the research software engineering movement that's been going on for about the
last 10 years?
Are you aware of the research software engineering movement that's been going on for about 10
years now?
There's quite an active group in the Nordic countries and in the UK that have a lot of
common issues with what you've just been talking about.
There will be a very good community for you to get involved with.
Aware like this, no research.
Is it any link to the dev room of yesterday about the research tools?
I don't know.
I wasn't in that dev room.
No.
Okay.
But thank you for your remark.
Please come to me after and I will write that down.
We have one minute left.
Yes.
On the other side.
Thank you.
How could you, would you suggest to approach someone in the humanities sector that maybe
needs a hand with the project but doesn't really know what can IT do for it?
Does it really know what we do?
I had a set of questions when I do consulting.
I can read them to you.
First, context.
What is your domain?
What does your domain focus on?
Because they can be very varied.
What is the problem you try to solve?
Eventually, what did you already try to solve your problem?
What tools did you use?
That will give you an idea because they will be very blurry about what they want.
That will help anchoring.
What are the data you have and hope to collect and they rarely think about it.
And finally, and the most important, can you present me your data?
Screenshots.
Probably they have an Excel file or something, whatever.
Size, format.
How has it been collected?
And things you think are as a computer scientist quantification, they don't think like that.
They just think questions.
So I think that could help.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Thanks everyone.
We'll give you all another close.
A big round of applause.