Now is the time for the Yoshimalize.
And he speaks about breaking the code of inclusion, the designing micro materials based on principles
for accessible programming education.
Very difficult title.
So, okay, the stage is yours.
Thank you.
So, my name is Yoshie.
My name is Yoshie.
I'm a PhD student at the Ray University at Bristol.
And today I'll be giving a talk about how we can design more open.
Sorry for that.
Okay, okay, okay, good.
Just, all right.
So, I'm Yoshie and I'll be giving a talk about how we can design more open and inclusive
pedagogical material to teach programming.
I'll first like to start a bit with a small introduction to tell you why we think this
talk is important.
So, I've always been passionate both by programming but also by education.
I joined CoderDojo from a very young age helping kids to learn how to code.
And I also went for an internship abroad in Kenya to build software for schools in less
fortunate areas where I could firsthand experience what technology can do to help education.
Upon graduating, I joined Hack Your Future Belgium for those of you that don't know.
It's a small nonprofit organization in Brussels that organizes coding boot camps for refugees
that are trying to find a job in the tech sector here.
So, before we go on to the meat of the presentation, let's take a look at some of the background
information we need.
I'm pretty sure most of you remember your first programming classes where you had to
install a weird-looking editor with hundreds of buttons.
You had to type in some text.
You tried to press the play button or a compile button, and you would see a weird error message
that you didn't really understand.
This can be very demotivating.
And it's actually even worse when it happens to people from already underrepresented groups
because if they encounter these types of errors, they internalize it, and they feel like it's
a confirmation that, yes, maybe they do not belong in such a classroom, which is, of course,
not the message they want to send.
Now, in the past years, there has been a new methodology of teaching programming that tries
to limit this issue, and it's based called the PRIM principles.
Now, the idea is instead of starting to write your program from scratch from day one, you
basically start with a simple exercise predict.
In this stage, you look at some existing code, you download it, and you're going to try to
predict what will the result be if I run this piece of code.
Then in the next stage, you're actually going to download the code and execute it, and going
to verify whether your prediction is correct or not.
Then in the third stage, we're going to ask you to actually make exercises on the problem.
This can be label all the variables, or can you tell me which variables are updated at
some point in the code.
Now, up until this point, the learner hasn't changed anything about that code itself, and
as such, he also doesn't feel like it's a personal failure if something goes wrong in
the process.
We're going to try to change this in the fourth step, modify, where we're still not going
to ask the student to write code from scratch, but we're going to give them a functioning
program, and we're going to ask them, hey, can you make some small modifications?
Like instead of running this loop three times, run it six times.
It's only in the last stage where we're going to ask them to actually write a new program
from scratch using the same principles he developed earlier.
Now, this is a new methodology in teaching and programming education, but it's based
on a very well-known pedagogical concept called the zone of proximal development, where the
idea is quite simple.
If you're only doing tasks you can do by yourself, you're not actually learning anything, you're
just repeating stuff.
But if I give you a task that you cannot do yourself, even with some help, you're actually
just going to get demotivated and lose all motivation to continue learning.
So that's also not good.
So we should always strive to give exercises in this yellow zone, where the student cannot
easily do it on their own, but with some proper guidance they can get there.
Which brings us to micromaterials.
Now a micromaterial is an open education resource, so anybody can easily include it in their
curriculum, but it should also provide some sort of automated feedback so that even though
the teacher is not there directly to guide the student, they can still get something
away from it.
Ideally, you also want some kind of automatically generated content, because managing all the
content for exercises can be a very time-consuming exercise for teachers.
So now we'll discuss some small examples that we within our lab have built to experiment
with these ideas.
So the first sample we'd like to discuss is an online environment to practice the use
of HTML.
It is designed for engineering students, where we do not really expect to be able to develop
HTML websites on their own, but they should be able to grasp the core concepts of what
the elements are about.
So we have a stepwise progress that they can follow level by level, and we always start
with a small presentation of the core HTML concepts that they need to know.
Now once it's time to actually practice their HTML, we do not just give them an editor,
but instead we make use of Google's Blockly library to show this kind of HTML blocks that
already contain the syntax so they can focus on what the text represents and not on the
syntax itself.
And here we analyze sample HTML code to generate the blocks, so adding new levels is as simple
as providing a new website we want them to recreate.
We also dynamically create links for every element, like hints for every element that
they will need to use in the page.
We have a similar environment for the practice of databases for the same engineering students.
We used to have a lot of problems where they had to install databases locally, database
files could get corrupt and they could turn into issues, so we developed a fully online
environment with the use of SQL.js, which is an open source project based on SQLite
compiled to WebAssembly using Enscriptum.
So in this simple application they would get to see a description of a database, and on
this database they would get to run queries.
The queries would be typed into an online code editor based on atom, so they get syntax
highlighting, they get code completion, and whenever they were to execute the queries
they could see the results directly in their browsers, and this they would use to answer
questions about the data.
Similarly if it was more about inserting or updating the data, we could no longer do with
simply having a simple fill-in-the-answer type of question.
So instead we're going to run checks to see at which step did they fail, so they can stepwise
go back and modify the code until they get it right for all the constraints.
Similarly as well if they want to create new tickets we would also generate test cases
for those.
Another problem that's very often looked at is can the students interpret codes, and
a common tool for these are trace tables.
Now for those of you that don't know, a trace table is just away for example here where
you can look through your program line by line and note down what happens at each line.
For example this trace table is designed to look at which variables are declared or initialized
or updated at certain moments in time.
Different type of trace tables would be the operators trace table which gives the student
a view of which operators are used at which points in the program.
A third one would be these variable values which is basically a way to see which variables
are updated at which point in time, which is a way that we can know is the student actually
reasoning about this code correctly.
Lastly we have a very basic trace table for advanced users where they can just keep track
of the latest state of the program.
Now to this trace table application we added some export functionality so teachers could
import the JSON from the student so we could run some diagnostics to see if students were
understanding the codes correctly.
Then we add more of a social game, a coding card conundrum.
It's basically a kind of card game where there are three types of cards.
We have goal cards that say in a certain condition that needs to be true.
We have environment cards that initialize five variables and we have code cards that
would execute some codes to update the global state of the program.
It's a multiplayer game.
It can be played from one to four people.
We get this field where each player gets a handful of cards and there will be three heaps
in the center.
During their turn students could select a card from their hand and place it on one of
the environments.
If they were doing so they would have to update this state table to reflect the new latest
state after executing the code on their card.
And if they manage to achieve the goal on their goal card they will get awarded some
points for it.
So it's a social game where they can still practice their trace tables.
Then the final one we're going to discuss is King scroll.
Even here we tried to make it a bit more silly, we added like a fantasy theme where the idea
was that we live in a kingdom but the kingdom is going to be attacked by an evil dragon
and it's up to us to find out which of the heroes will be able to stop the dragon.
Now there are 16 heroes randomly generated based on four essential variables of the equipment
they are wearing and two extra variables to increase the inclusiveness of our application.
Students would be shown a scroll that would be randomly generated based on essential JavaScript
features that would update the state of those four variables and it's up to the students
to predict after the program has run which of the heroes matches the final description.
Students were able to automatically select which elements of JavaScript they know or
didn't know so they could always participate even though they hadn't seen everything.
Then we gave them a state table to of course keep track of the state changes as they went
through the scroll.
So those were some of the examples that we developed but now we'd like to take a step
back and look at what did we learn from it and what kind of guidelines can we give you
if you were to try to implement something on your own.
So the first piece of advice we'd like to give you is embrace the themes.
I know it might look silly at first but just having a silly team takes a lot of the stress
away from students and they no longer feel like they can fail doing an exercise because
they're just playing a game in this kind of team world.
But when we want to design those themes we also shouldn't forget the principle of skill
transfer which basically states that the context in which you learn something becomes an important
part of how you will be able to apply those skills in different contexts.
So the closer your environment is to a realistic use case the more useful their skills will
directly be when they need to apply them to a realistic environment.
So it's still good that in your silly team world there is a real life kind of application.
Also definitely invite a social aspect.
One of the main reasons people stop learning how to code is because they don't really feel
like they belong in the world or they feel discouraged and just having this kind of social
aspect it can be slightly competitive but also collaborative really takes away this
barrier and pushes people to continue learning in a welcoming environment.
Also you should strive to keep the setup minimal as possible and I know this sounds really
straightforward but when you're designing an application that needs to be installed
on a desktop and even two out of twenty students are facing issues that takes away at least
five minutes of the teacher's time that they cannot be helping students.
So if at all possible try to make it work just within the browser.
Now we should also make sure that our micro materials only focus on one specific learning
goal.
A lot of content is created like for example the Heidi programming language which there
is a great talk tomorrow and these are all like great tools but they kind of expect you
to focus on them for your whole semester.
A lot of teachers already have a curriculum they need to follow so they do not have the
flexibility to really go with something else.
Your tools should really be something they can introduce and use in one or two of their
lessons without needing to change their overall curriculum.
Otherwise it will just not be adapted.
We also have the expertise reversal principle.
Now the idea here is if you're new to something you really like to be guided and get a lot
of hints on what can I do, what shouldn't I do but as you gain more experience if you
keep having to go to the same guidance it actually becomes a hindrance.
So ideally your application should be designed in such a way that they contain multiple layers
where first at the outer layer there is a lot of help available for your students but
as they move on and become more experienced and become more experts they can take away
those layers and start operating the tool without getting all that extra help that's
getting in the way of learning.
Then also of course try to do something with automatic content generation.
Whenever you try to develop a tool on your own you'll quickly discover that having to
update the content yourself or even asking teachers to create the content themselves
it takes a very long time and they will not do it.
Our idea is to make it easier for teachers to use those tools not to give them more work.
So the final principle is if at all possible try to make things mobile compatible especially
with the adults I've been teaching.
They are very busy work lives.
They're trying to learn programming while still taking care of the families.
If they have a simple tool they can use for example while on public transport that's a
huge quality of life improvement for them.
So let me finish this presentation by telling you all like I know you're all a community
of builders if you think like hey these kind of tools you discussed I can build those feel
free to reach out to any learning environment close to you and try to ask how you can contribute.
Thank you all for listening.
Thank you.