Okay, the next speaker is Miquel Tameni, which has a talk about coffee or coffee osmo.
It's an upper state map, it's received at a time.
So check it and add shop on the map with the receipt.
So the stage is yours.
Hello everyone and thank you to be here.
It's really nice to be here after attending like 10 additional post-em so it's my first talk.
It's really great to be here.
So I want to talk to you today about a little project that I started like five months ago, I think.
And it basically wanted to be a new, different and hopefully easier way to add place,
in particular business place to open a street map.
And to give you a little bit of perspective, the usual process to insert a new place or
a business into open street map usually involves with check if the place is already on open street map.
So open the map and look for the location or where you want to add the place.
Gather all the information needed.
So the name, the position, the address, maybe the phone number, the website.
Then open your preferred editor, the website or, you know, osmond or something like that.
Insert all the information, check if it's correct and then save it.
And it became easier over the time, but it's anyway a time-consuming task.
And especially I found myself sometimes having problems on the updated information about a business,
like the phone number or the website.
Sometimes you find the incorrect information online.
So I think it's quite hard sometimes to insert a new place.
And so I got this idea that I'll tell you later how it's come.
But to validate the idea, before coming to FOSNAM, we took a little bit longer way.
We went to Zagreb with my friends to drink some beer for a sales purpose, obviously.
And when you are in a new city that you don't know, you usually open them up
and have a look where the majority of perhaps a restaurant or something like that, where they are.
And when you see something like that, you know that on that street maybe it's a good place to be
or on the other side of the city there is something else.
But what you usually do is looking for restaurants, pubs, bars, etc.
So it's quite important for me having this kind of information on the map.
Open Street map, I think it's improved a lot over the last years, especially Europe maybe.
But sometimes it's lacking the biggest information, I think.
So we went to Zagreb, we tried to find as many bars as possible for this research.
And what we found out is that there is so much more pubs and drinking place than what we spot on the map at first time.
So our question is how we can improve this.
Obviously, we can do more travel like this one.
And instead of the information that we gather traveling,
fortunately there is so many volunteers around the world that do this kind of stuff
and insert all the kind of place that nowadays we can find on Open Street map.
But as I told you before, it's a time consuming task and you have always to find the correct information
about the business you want to add.
So what we can do?
We can do the things that they already said or do something like Bob does that is seated over there.
I think he do a quite smart thing.
He call it on the site that we get over our drinking nights.
And after he check if the place where we went is already on the map or not.
And it's not that it's in open street map.
With all the information already there, no need to look everywhere because usually the receipt have the business name,
the address, the location, the numbers, sometimes the website.
So I think it's quite smart things to do something like this.
Maybe it's not that smart that Bob usually do this after too many years.
That's another problem and to avoid his mistakes like type or something like that.
I think this could be interesting to try to automate the processor and the access information from the receipt.
And basically the idea.
So it's like to use not a picture of your receipt and you get all the information that you need to insert the place.
And eventually you insert the place already if the place is not on open street map.
So coffee or some basically do these things.
Exeter the text from the receipt.
Try to tokenize and label the data that you can find.
Check if the existence of the place is the place is already on open street map.
And if not, maybe we happen because it's not actually possible.
You can insert it already on open street map or at least copy and paste all the information you need.
And actually the project is quite small.
It's just a proof of concept.
And I thought a little bit about the architecture of this project.
And maybe I started to try to do a standalone app.
But I think that maybe it's better to have something that can be easily integrated in other application.
There is something like street complete or other projects that do a great job to improve and make easy to be able to contribute to open street map.
So I think it can be really, really interesting to maybe integrate a function like this in those apps.
So I just mock it up a small Python API based on fast API that expose an endpoint where you can just upload an image.
And then the software tried to understand what is on the site, label the data and just return it.
Actually, the front end is just really, really small application that show as more form and visualize the information that the mechanic will extract.
As I said, future integration for the editors, I think it will be the way to use this kind of function if it's probably to be interesting and useful and available.
Or maybe it can be just a standalone app or a PVO. I actually don't know.
It's something open and I'm here to discuss it actually.
So how it works, actually, the receiver is allowed to a server.
I removed the exit data just to have a little bit of privacy because can be there like the location, the time where you went in a place.
And I think it's not something that you want to share.
The image is a little bit pre-processed before the OCR.
Actually, it's something really basic. I think it can be improved really a lot.
And there is OCR with test out OCR that work quite good, but I think it can be a little bit better, maybe processing a little bit more an image before.
Then I tried several ways to parse the data with Live Postal that actually I think is what I found the most available for this task with PASI.
And maybe it could be interesting to train a custom model because I found some open source model that can understand what our receiver and invoice say.
But it's usually trained about the product that you buy and find the price and the total and not the business name.
So it doesn't work really well, actually.
Then the beacon just look with nomination with the place already on the open street or not.
If we can find the exact name, I try a location search with the WordPress API.
So I look at the address, have a look at all the business of that type that is around and show a list to the user to just to make sure that the place is not there with a little bit different name.
So what can be done different or better?
I have in my to the list improved the text section.
As I said before, the OCR actually works good. I tried the like the Google Vision API that worked much better, but I don't want to use it actually.
So I think that maybe with a little bit more proper processing on the major, all the data started could be a little bit more accurate.
As I said, the front end, actually, it's a really, really small application that just shows some information.
It's maybe better to do on the client side all the stuff for privacy reasons.
So I just can read the text, keep it on my device and just upload or save the new place to open street bumper and choosing what information I want to share.
Integration. So as I said, use of the place directly from the app will be great or integrated with some other editor.
More safe to test and improve because what we spot in the agrib, so our trip is not useful, actually, is that there is not a clear standard of obviously for a sieve and can change a little bit from place to place.
In Italy, almost they are all the same. We didn't find this true for like the agrib.
So maybe call it more information about how their sieve look all around the world could be great.
What we can do, we don't know different because this is the step that I thought is the easiest.
But maybe like I said, having a custom model that can label a little bit better information could be interesting,
at least because sometimes you find not the name of the place on the receipt, but the name of the business that is sometimes different or sometimes you find both and actually post that they use, get confused.
So you don't have a rebel over time.
So why we don't use to find more pub, more beer, more fun, help Bob to drink some more good beer?
And absolutely to improve open street maps together and just having an easier way to add place and so we can call it more information.
So thank you. This is the website where you can find the source code.
I asked the temporary playground where you can upload your sieve to test.
And that's it. I just want to know if you find this idea interesting.
If it could be good to go on with this project if you have some suggestions.
So I asked question. It doesn't actually you to have questions.
So thank you.
Any?
OK.
the mic. Why don't you expect GPS coordinates from the X-ray?
Because maybe you haven't snapped the photo when you just went out from the place, the
first reason. And the second reason is for privacy, as I said before. But I think it
will be great to offer the users the possible to choose if you want to share information.
It's much easier because if you have the X-ray coordinates, you can just have a look in a
really small area around and just easily found if the place is already on OpenState map or not.
And even be more accurate when you insert it. So it's obviously a nice idea. I haven't done it
just because sometimes, like Bob, he doesn't do the insert right away, but the day after the
angle there, so like... Yep.
Question, normally on the receipts, it always shows like the time when the receipt was printed or given to the customer.
Can you repeat the question? Okay, I repeat the question.
Could you somehow combine it? Maybe we scanned the pictures taken to think, maybe the picture was taken as the question or at the button or...
That's a nice idea. Yes, sir.