The stage is yours.
Thank you.
I'm here for quite a short time.
My head may not have switched completely to English, so if that happens, maybe someone
of the audience can help me out.
So my talk is about Web access.
And in the last time I had a talk, after the talk, people said to me, you need to tell
more about Web access, so that's what I'll be doing.
First wake up.
Some color.
What is Web access?
Web access, I'm a manager of a workshop in Berlin, in a university.
Some people call me the product owner or the father of Web access.
It's not really the case.
I'll tell later why.
Using machines in a workshop sounds easy.
You switch one bit on, machine is on, switch one bit off, reset the bit, and the machine
is off.
But it's not that easy.
First thing, why do we need to switch off machines?
In a workshop you have two kinds of machines, the one who tear off parts of the body of
the users if they do not know how to use the machine, and the not so interesting ones who
are not hurting people.
And there are two kinds of people in your workshop.
There are the ones who know how to clean up their place after they leave the workshop,
and there are the ones who leave the mess to you.
And if you need to get along with this combination of people and machines, you need to get some
structure in the workshop.
And I'm the only one working aesthetically in that workshop, so I'm not enough people
to get structure.
And 30 people are using the workshop, so I need support, and I need the wonder of the
digitalization.
So I do not like good luck, have fun, that's why we began to work in FabExcess in 2019.
I won't read all of that.
These are requirements which are coming into software if you want to switch on machines
and off machines.
That's why it wasn't that easy.
And next thing is we saw a lot of projects who began working in that area.
But when we realized there are a lot of these, no, where's the picture?
There are a lot of these projects.
I think most of you know that XKCD, we tried to avoid that by becoming modular and getting
more than works for me.
Technology readiness level nine, maybe some of you know what that means.
And that's one more thing we wanted to reach, we wanted to reach the technical for Federation
in the future.
Not right now, we'll get there in September this year maybe.
That's what it is, FabExcess.
In the last talk they said, talk about what is FabExcess, that's it.
We have users and the machines can be switched on by the user, not by the manager of the
FabLab, but the manager of the FabLab has the user database and the machine database
and can say who was allowed to switch on which machine.
And in the next step here, can see which one of the users switched on which machine in
the last time.
And that's it, we do not follow our users or make surveillance of what they are doing,
we want to know who left that mess.
And that's it.
There are, in the time, there are some perspectives which need to be implemented in such software.
First is the workspace manager.
I won't read because time is running.
For the workspace manager, the software we are implementing should fit into his workspace
and not press his workspace into our software.
That's one of the most important things for us.
And for the user, it should be easy to use and that's it, fast and clear as, and at,
no, English word is missing.
So that's how we approached to, well, you know what I mean.
Sorry.
How to consider the wishes of the FabLab manager, yes, of me.
I think it's too much text for nine minutes.
Are there some questions for that slide?
I think the most important is the last one, attaching new machines is easy for Python
and bash because we are not able to implement as a project each and every machine in each
and every workshop, so we need to enable the workshop users and managers to work as a community
project.
In the middle, GUI would be great if there is anyone in the audience who is willing and
able to build a GUI which takes machines and throws out to them and files, feel free.
That's some things in the back end that are important.
It's written in Rust.
So the language and the compiler guarantees some sort of stability.
And in between the back end and Rust, there is the CaptainProto API which enables the
guys who are not working in the back end and in the core of the server to get a stable
API where they can throw against with Python or I think easier languages which are, there
are more people who can write code in these languages.
We have two to three core developers who are having a guarantee of a very, very stable
API and this is also important because the FabLab manager doesn't want to take care of
software updates.
They should happen without any effort.
Accessibility for the users, the app which we have, I showed in the slides before, should
be really accessible for the users because if you have a workshop, it doesn't help you
if a third of your users say, sorry, I can't access the app, I can't use your workshop
machines.
The last line there is one more step to accessibility because not everyone has a mobile phone and
not everyone wants to take his mobile phone and get the app and when he wants to just
use a machine, so NFC is a thing in that case.
Supported hardware devices out of the box, this is what the core developers have been
working at right now and the accessibility are not only the core developers developing
modules for Fab Access, that's where the community comes in.
I think the list on the top will grow with time but the developers have an eye on stability
so it's not growing that fast as the community wishes so it gives community unrights.
I don't know the English word, sorry.
That's where we are right now.
We're in the beta and I think the beginning of March there's a deadline for 1.0 which
will be the first release which can be used by workspace without having software engineering
guys in the background.
These are targets which will be addressed in 1.0 of my connectors which by a lot of
the guys in the community as most of the German workspaces in the
Wachstäppen switched to a key cloak in the background.
I'm good in time.
The Federation, I already talked to the people of Matrix and I think there will be some interfaces
between Fab Access and Matrix to realize Federation.
Coming to the end of the presentation, the most important are the community members.
We have 64 number growing, we have a community manager, thank you.
We have four people in Berlin, first the core developers, then me, sorry, and one guy in
Bohold who is doing a really good job in alpha testing and documentation because if developers
create documentation it's better when there is someone outside of the developer circle.
Nobody in the team does anything with blockchain, sorry.
These are organizations who supported us and are carrying the project.
Yes, the lower even spent some amounts of money, thank you.
These are the URLs you need to get involved and give it a try.
I think we have three minutes, are there questions?
Yeah.
Did you guys think about interoperating with all the existing authorization schemes like
Free IDA for example?
Yes of course, right now they are implementing a summer and there will be many many more.
It's part of the modular design of Fab Access because we do not want to press you into what
we are using if there are authentication systems which are in the market we will implement
them one after the other but if you have wishes feel free to talk to us.
Yeah.
This is maybe a little out of scope but how do you stop people from just unplugging the
shelly?
Ah, very good question, thank you.
You are not able to solve social problems with technology.
Unplugging plugs which switch on and off the machines is I think for me it's a part of
a social problem but there is a technical aspect.
Of course the shellies say I am here, I am here, I am here, they have a heartbeat and
if that heartbeat is away so you are in the core of Fab Access realizes all that shelly
is unplugged.
So it's a technical and social problem.
So Fab Access does log a lightness of the shell.
Inside the kernel, yes, inside the backend, yes.
It throws out in the normal configuration into the memory so it's gone and the time
is thrown out a log file and if you need to follow what your users are doing then you
may take that log file and configure Fab Access, give me the log file and push that log file
to ERP systems or whatever you want.
But that's not in the scope of Fab Access.
Any more questions?
One and a half minutes?
Do you have the possibility to also get a signal from the machine to say it's working
or it's voicing?
Next good question, thank you.
It depends, sorry.
Sometimes if the information from the machine is important for Fab Access to switch on and
off machines then we're taking the data into Fab Access.
Normally when there are data from the machine which are not needed to switch on and off
machines because the core point of Fab Access is switching on and off machines and that's
what we are doing good.
If there are any other data in our package there is a MQTT server and maybe a, um, far
by the MQTT server and Fab Access does not need that data, yeah?
37 seconds.
Since you talked about invoicing, next door or laser cut up we have a paper book where
you wrote down like I used it for like one minute and 30 seconds.
Is this something you can do with that?
This is something you can do with the log file which is coming out of Fab Access and
your own software, you writing or maybe a duo or any other ERP system which needs to
be filled with structured data from that log file.
So you don't want it in Fab Access?
No we are not an ERP system, we are not gaining money from people using our machines.
That's in the scope of different software packages.
Yep.