Okay. Hello, everyone, and welcome to the last lightning talk of the conference. I hope
you've enjoyed yourselves. This will be the FOSDIM infrastructure review, same as every
year presented by Richard and Basti.
So normally I do this thing, but Basti has been helping a ton, and the ball of spaghetti
and spit and duct tape which I left him turned into something usable. So I'm just going to
sit here on the side, and I'm here around for the Q&A. But for the rest, it's Basti,
and it's his first public talk for realty, so give him a big round of applause.
Thank you. I hope I will not screw this one up. Okay. So we'll have about 15 minutes,
10 minutes of talk, and five minutes for Q&A, and I hope it's somewhat interesting to you.
First the facts. The core infrastructure hasn't changed that much since the last FOSDIM 2020.
We're still running on its Cisco ASR 10K for routing ACLs, NAT64, and DHCP. We have already
reused several switches that we are already here from the last FOSDIM. They're on by FOSDIM.
These are Cisco C3750 switches. We had our old servers which are now turning 10 this
year. They were still here, and they will be replaced next year. We have done, like
all the years before, everything with Prometheus, Loki, and Grafana for monitoring our infrastructure,
because that's what helps us running all the conference here. And we've built some public
dashboards, and we just put it out to a VM outside of ULB because we were running out
of bandwidth like the years before, and I'll come to that back later.
We have a quite beefy video infrastructure. You might have seen this one here. It's a
video capturing device. It's called a video box here at FOSDIM. It's all public. It's
all open source except one piece that's in there. You can find it on GitHub if you try
to build it yourself. Go ahead. Just grab the GitHub repo and clone it. These devices,
there's two of them, one at the camera, one here for the presenter's laptop. They sent
their streams to a big render farm that we have over in the K building where every year
our render farm is running on some laptops. So laptops sent the streams off to the cloud
from Hetzner, and from there we just distribute it to the world so everyone at home can see
the talks. We have some sort of semi-automatic rev up on cutting process. Those of you have
been talking here, maybe have known S-Review for years. This is the first time it's running
on Kubernetes. So we are trying to go cloud native as well with our infrastructure just
to show how all has been held together. This is our video boxes. I don't know if you can
see it. We got those black magic encoders here that are turning the signals that we
get, like SDI, HDMI, into a useful signal that we can process with our banana pie that
we have in there. Everything is wired up to a dump switch here and then we go out like
here and have our own switching infrastructure inside those boxes. There's some SSD below
here where we just, in case of network failure, dump everything to the SSD as well. So hopefully
everything that has been talked about at the conference is still captured and available
in case of a network breakdown. Those boxes also have a nice display for the speaker so
we can see if everything is running or it's not running, which makes it easy for people
to operate these boxes here. You don't have to be a video pro. You just have to wire yourself
up to the box. You see a nice Fostom logo and see, okay, everything is working and you're
done and everything gets set out. This is like how the video system is actually working.
All this can be found on the GitHub. You don't have to take screenshots for that. If you
like to see it, we will tear down this room afterwards so everyone can have a look at
the infrastructure we're using because it's not being used after this talk. You see it's
quite some interesting things to do. This is the instructions that all our volunteers
get when they wire up the whole buildings here on one day on Friday. They're not here,
but they should be given some round of applause because they're volunteers that are doing
really the hard work and building up on one day the complete Fostom. Maybe it's time for
a round of applause for them. Here we have another thing. This is also on the GitHub
rapid where you can see where's something coming from. We have the room sound system.
This is what you're hearing me through. We have a camera with audio gear, speaker laptops,
that's all getting pushed down until someone reaches your device down here. There's a ton
of services processing it in between. This is almost all done with open source software.
Expect for the encoder that's running in there, which is from Blackmagic Design. How is it
used? We have a rendering farm. This is the laptops. It's 27 this year. For those of you
who don't know, those laptops are being sold after Fostom. If you want one, you can grab
one. This year they're already gone. For next year, maybe you want to have a cheap device.
You can have them with everything that's on them because we literally don't care for that.
You can have it because everything's been processed after the Fostom. You can see it.
We have some racks where we just put them four-wise. We have 27 of them. We have some
switch infrastructure that is used for processing all that stuff. This one's not running out
of bandwidth, but we're coming back to what's running out of bandwidth. You might see this
mess over here. This is our Internet. Looks like every common Internet on the planet.
This is our safety net. We have a big box here where all the streams go. This will be
sent out to Bulgaria, to the video team right after Fostom. We have a really off-site copy
of everything. The challenges for this year. DNS64. All the
years we've been running on Bind 9 since ages. We switched to Cordian S, just testing it
on Sunday of Fostom 2020. We really saw a significant reduction in CPU usage. That's
why we stuck to Cordian S since then. This year we also replaced the remaining Bind installations
that we handled for all the internal DNS and all other recursive stuff that's been used
here to provide you Internet access. Richie always used to give you some timelines,
and that's what I'm trying to do as well. There were times when it was mentally challenging
for people building up Fostom. We got better by year by year by year by doing some sort
of automation and getting people used to know what to do and have everything set up before
that. We installed routers. You see that? There's a slide. It's getting better year
of the year. This year we had a very... We thought it would be okay from what we know.
We just set it up in January, and everything worked. We came here on the 5th of January,
I think, put everything up, and it just worked, which is great, which gives you some sort
of things not to care about, because there were other things to care about. The network
to have it up and running here took us a bit longer this year than the last years, because
we were playing around with the second uplink that we got. We used to have one gigabit uplink.
Last week we got a 10 gigabit uplink, and we thought, okay, just enable that and play
with it, and it turned out to be not that easy to getting up both of the BGP sessions
running and doing it properly. That's why it took us a bit longer this year. The monitoring
was also one thing, which really helps us to understand if FOSDIM is ready to go or
if something has to stay very, very late here. The last years we've been very, very good
at that. Basically, in January everything was done, like the last of January, but it's
January. This time in the first half of January everything was set up and was running, and
it worked. It was really great, because some people actually got some sleep at FOSDIM.
They didn't need to stay here very long, because everything was all pre-made, and they just
go and look at the dashboard, okay, this is missing, this is missing, and just say, okay,
just have them all checked. The video build-up took a bit longer this year, because of getting
old and rusty at that. Also, very many new faces that have never built up such a great
conference. This is why we took it a bit longer, and the video team also, yeah, I think they
got the least amount of sleep of all of the stuff that was running the conference. This
was the story so far. We closed FOSDIM 2020, I was also there at 2020. 2020 was really
one of the best ones we ever had from a technical perspective. We had everything running via
Ansible, just like one command, and then wait an hour until everything is deployed and you're
gone. Cool, have some beer, some latte in between, and everything was cool. Then we had this
pandemic, just for me, like a week after FOSDIM, everything went down. You had FOSDIM 2021
and 2022, there were no conference here at the UB, so we had no infrastructure to manage,
which was quite okay. We had to do some other things, like most of you have learned that
we have a big metrics installation to run the FOSDIM conference and help you with communicating
during the conference. Then there was this bad thing that the maintainer of the infrastructure
left FOSDIM between these years. So Richie searched for someone who was dumb enough to
do that. That's me. So this year we're back again in persona. Sorry? Yeah, thanks.
Yeah. So after two years, we came looking for the two machines after almost two years,
like no one touched them. They rebooted one or two times due to power outages in the server
cabinet. But we had a working SSH key. We had tons of updates to install after literally
three years. I wonder, nobody broke into the machines because they were public exposed
on the Internet. But only SSH and I think a three-year-old or three-and-a-half-year-old
Prometheus installation which was full of bugs. Yeah. We noticed that the battery controllers,
the battery packs of the rate controllers have been depleted, so this was the only thing
that actually happened in the three years. The batteries went to zero and didn't set
themselves on fire, so everything was okay. The machines worked. Just a bit of performance
degradation, but everything seemed to be okay. And then we tried to run this Ansible thing
from the last years. And three years later, Ansible has done a lot of things in the time
and you want to use a current version of Ansible with that old stuff. You end up like this.
This is me. Start from scratch or fix all the Ansible roles. You can have a look at
them. They're also on GitHub. So when we saw, okay, how do we do this and said, okay, then
just be gone. Ansible be gone. We just fix it after the first time because we will have
to renew the service anyway and everything will change. So the service timeline, we had
them service alive at the 8th of January. Services, DNS, we had centralized all our
locks. This was something Richie was looking for since ages that we had easy accessible
lock files for everything that's running here at FOSDEM, which was good that we had them
because we could see things like, oh, the Internet line that was proposed to be there
actually came. Nobody told us, but it came up. You see that? We, thanks to the centralized
logging, we were aware of things like that. And then we could go and fire up our BGP sessions.
Then two days later, we noticed, okay, firing up the BGP sessions wasn't that a good idea
because we lost almost all connectivity. Stop it, Seth, but I don't care. I just keep talking.
We lost all our connectivity and said, okay, damn it. We're in some sort of panic mode
because the reason for looking at the service was like this bind security issue that was
been, I read the mail at the morning of January 28th and said, okay, we have to fix the bind
installations and then you suddenly can't reach the service anymore. So, okay, are they
already hacked or what's going on? And doing some back and forth with our centralized logging,
you see that? This is Grafana Loki that we leveraged for that. We were kind of like,
yeah, it's been really nice to debug things like that. We also noticed that there was
an interface constantly flapping to our backbone, which we also could fix within that session.
And after that, we said, okay, there are some MTU problems. We have to restart BGP and so
on and back and forth. And then we finally agreed to just throw away the BGP sessions,
go with the one gigabit line. And yesterday evening, we switched to the 10 gigabit line
because we had the congested uplink like since 11 in the morning. So many people using too
much bandwidth. And since yesterday evening, everything is okay. It's better. And we are
on the 10 gigabit link due to the fact that there are not so many people here today. Yesterday
there were quite a bit more. The link was not fully saturated. But you can tell we this
is the place where we could use some more bandwidth was like, I don't know, this is
usually time for something to eat. But at 330, we could actually use something of the
new bandwidth that we had available. So if you want to look at all of the things, we
have a dashboard put out there publicly. If you want to have a look at the infrastructure
and the Ansible repo that will be fixed to work with current Ansible versions within
the next few days, just clone our infrastructure, clone everything. And if you have any questions,
I'll be glad to take them. Yeah, fire away. As I don't see any questions, then we are
about to tear down this room after this. So please don't leave anything in here because
it will be cleaned and everything will be torn out. If anyone else has a question, just
there's one. We use the question is why do you use laptops for rendering because they
have a built in USB called battery. So in place of the power outage, we can easily run
with them. Also, they're very cheap for us. We can just use the computing power and sell
it at the same price that we bought it to the people here. You get a cheap laptop. We
get some computing time on them before and that's the main reason for running it on laptops.
Well, actually, the question was why you were using banana pie. That's a good question.
The thing is that the capabilities of the banana pie were a bit better than the Raspberry
Pi. The times the decision was made. If you see there's a big LCD screen in front of the
boxes where you can see that thing, I think it was driving those LCD panels and also the
computing power available on the banana pie. But actually, we have to look that up in the
repo. There's everything documented. Okay? Yeah, there's another one in the front. So
the question was if there are any public dashboards out there. Yeah, we've put some public dashboards
on dashboard.grafana.org. Oh, dashboard.fosdom.org. Sorry. Which you can have a look at the infrastructure.
We used to have some more dashboards like the t-shirts that have been sold. But due
to the fact that we changed the shop, we converted to something that we bought to an open source
solution. And the thing is we totally forgot to monitor that. But there are some dashboards
out there to monitor it. And if you want to see something more, just come to me after
the talk and I'll show you something more here at the laptop. Okay? Yeah, another one.
What was the biggest issue that you faced with this year? The biggest one standing here.
No. Actually, the biggest issues we had was like running all that stuff after three years
and not having set up everything properly was quite challenging. Like on Saturday morning,
we had to run and redo the whole video installation on the K building because of you see those
transmitters here. They were not plugged properly. And so we had no audio on the stream. This
was one thing. And then another very challenging thing was like when we played around and I
said play, we did not engineer anything properly. When we played around with the BGP sessions,
it was not clear how long it would take till things distributed to the whole net. And we
were literally just trying to get information. Is it working? Is it working not? And till
this BGP information propagates from here to the rest of the planet like Brazil, it
takes quite some time. And so you can't be sure that you're setting up the BGP session,
everything works because we'll hit the fan after 10, 20, 30 minutes and not instantly.
And so it's quite a problem to have instant recognition if things are going well or not.
So the question was if the problems with the Wi-Fi that we had here on site were due to
the BGP playing or was it due to something else, solar flares or so. The thing is that
we had some issues. We've been given access to the WLC, the wireless controllers. You
see these boxes over there, they're centrally controlled and we have to dig in that. We
have some visibility of the infrastructure that's owned by the ULB. They've given us
access to that so we can engineer that. But we're not quite sure why it was that. Most
of the time, FOSDIM, which is an IPv6 only, was working quite good except for some Apple
devices that do tend to just set up an IPv4 address even if there's no proper IPv4. And
things get complicated then. FOSDIM dual stack, which is dual stack, usually worked for most
of the Apple devices. But we're not very certain. Yeah. Yeah. You will see that. There's another
one. So the question is if the live streams will be made, yeah, this is rewindable or
not. Honestly, I can't tell you that. I don't know. I can ask the video guys if they're
planning that for next year. But there's no plan of that as far as I know. The biggest
challenge was to redo things with HDMI over VGA, which we had the last year. But there's
another one. Yeah. So the question is that we're planning to use service. Do we know
what and what's planned for next year? We'll have a talk about that next week, I think.
And then we go through the post-mortem, which is usually a week after FOSDIM. And then we
decide on things to be bought for next year because switches are old and routers are also
old, I think. And we have one more year on the route to go that should be fine for next
year. But what after that? We have to make some decisions and some investments for next
year to run this stuff. And this will be done next week when we're all a bit cooled down
and refreshed after this FOSDIM. Anyone else? Yeah. Come.
So the question was what part of the infrastructure are being reused and what do we bring for
the event? Well, in numbers, I think it was three truckloads of stuff. No, three because
the video arrived in the second year. We bring mainly cameras and those boxes here. Switches
stay at the ULB. Most of them stay here. But the one that didn't stay here, they won't
be here next year because ULB is planning to do some tidying up and giving us here some
video ports for our VLANs. They're very, very good at working with us. We get access to
most of the infrastructure. We just say, tell them what we like to use and they just throw
it on their controllers and bridge it to our servers and we can use it and make fun with
it. And they will be replacing part of the network infrastructure next year. And we then
will have to bring even less gear here. Yeah. Which one first?
Yeah. So the question was what's about all the other stuff that FOSDIM is doing through
the year that we hosted on our own hardware? Is it in the cloud or somewhere? We used,
yeah, we have another company called T-Gron here. It's a Belgian provider and there's
most of the stuff is running at T-Gron during the year. During FOSDIM, we also spin up some
VMs at Hetzner in Germany and they are only for during the event and short time after
the event. So like cutting videos and so on in the cloud. And they will be turned off
for like two or three weeks and then everything is running on T-Gron on our own hardware there
as well. So there was another question.
What are you using to communicate with volunteers?
So the question was what is being used for the communication between volunteers? We have
that matrix set up. I don't know who's aware of matrix. It's a real time communication
tool like, yeah, like Slack or something like that. We use matrix since 2020 internal for
our video team for communicating and then we expanded that for 2020 and then with the
pandemic we opened it up for all of the people and now the volunteers are being coordinated
to that. And we also have our own trunk chair still that we have here, especially for this
event set up. And volunteers are also can be reached via those radios.
And my correct volunteers. Yes, yes. Okay. We have two volunteers here. So yeah. Yeah.
Is there anything else you want to know or any where's the money? The question is where's
the money Lebowski? That's the real phrase from the film. I don't actually know. I'm
not yet a member of Fostum stuff. So you have to ask someone in a yellow shirt. There happens
to be one next to me. Just throw him the microphone. We have a money box and a bank account. Anyone
else? Three to one. Thank you very much.