I'm going to be presented by two amazing researchers, Iraklis and Christos.
Good morning, thank you for the introduction, thank you for being here and attending our
presentation.
So I'm Iraklis Varlamis and here is Christos Cronis.
We come from Harakopi University but here we are also representing the Open Technology
Alliance, the Greek Open Technology Alliance for Open Source Software.
So we will present today Fosbot which is a project that started a couple of years ago
in terms of the Google Summer of Code as an open design, an open source software robot
and gradually it evolved to what you see here which is a more concrete, let's say, robot,
a more concrete design that is specifically targeted to educators in our educational levels.
So together with me I have Christos and I will give a follow-up to Christos Cronis who
is the lead developer of the team, Fosbot, and also the designer of this robot.
So Christos, the floor is yours.
Thank you.
Hello, I'm Christos.
I would like first to introduce the team behind the Fosbot.
Let's start with my PhD supervisor, Professor Iraklis Varlamis, who is the coordinator of
the project, me as the designer of the robot including the hardware and the software, Elisari
and Vanay who are front-end and backend developers and past Google Summer of Code contributors
of the project, Dimitris and Jorvos are backend developers and assemblers of the physical
robot, and finally Manusos who is a backend developer and also the developer of the Fosbot
simulator.
Now, so this is the Fosbot, also we have a physical version of the robot in the table.
Let's start with an overview of the hardware and design aspects of the Fosbot.
On the front side of the robot we have a multi-core RGB lead on the top left, a photo resistor
on the top right and ultrasonic sensor in the middle.
The entire body of the robot is 3D printable in any FDM printer with bed size 220 by 220
millimeters.
The design is customizable and easy to assemble.
At the bottom of the robot there are three IR optical sensors suitable for line following
or edge detection application.
The robot moves based on two DC motors and the free rotor on the back side.
This motor have odometers to measure the movement of the robot and there is also a
three axis accelerometer and gyroscope sensor inside.
At the back of the robot there is a speaker and an off switch charging port and the robot
powered by three lithium ion rechargeable batteries.
On the top of the robot there are some unique features, a pulling component in the back
side of the robot.
That component gives the opportunity to user to attach small object, let's say using a
rope, in order to measure how the extra weight affects the movement of the robot.
Also we have a large detachable cover.
It's the white circular piece on the top.
That component is Lego brick compatible and also have a hole in the front side.
This hole drives to the bottom of the robot and allowing the market to be attached for
programmatic drawing.
Now let's summarize the key features from the hardware design aspects.
The robot is 3D readable and offers repairability and customization.
Can be designed to be used with common electronics.
In the current version the brain of the robot is based on the Raspberry Pi but we already
see some variation of the robot with Arduino or micro bit inside.
It's open source and open design of course and it comes in a low cost around 90 to 120
euros.
In the slide you can see our lab on Her
Her
University and some pictures from let's say the assembly line of the robot, from the physical
robot or also have some pictures from different assembly phases of the robot.
Now we'll speak about the software.
We have created the custom platform built in the robot with three modes.
The Gitter Carder mode, the Elementor School mode and the High School or Advanced mode.
The Gitter Carder mode features a friendly UI with card blocks based on Google's Blockly.
Additionally it's expandable with the options to add new cards to execute Python or Blockly
scripts.
For the Elementor School we have a custom user interface once again based on more complicated
Google's Blockly version that uses custom code blocks for all the sensors of the robot.
The experience is similar to Scratch and that makes the robot to be easy, that offers easy
direction with the robot.
Finally we have the High School or Advanced mode.
This mode based on Jupyter Notebooks and the native Python language.
This mode is under construction but will be available soon.
Now let's take a look to the platform UI.
The platform, this is the platform's home screen.
That home screen allows the creation of multiple projects.
Also we have the ability to import or import export of shared project between users.
Also using the little cog in the top right we can modify the behaviors on some blocks
such as the default distance, let's say for one step movement.
The icon with the three ABC cubes in the lower right offers access to the Kitter Kardon mode.
Now we see the Kitter Kardon mode.
The Kitter Kardon mode utilizes a simplified version of Blockly using card based blocks
for basic actions.
In the bottom right corner we can see an example of how this mode can be used in a classroom
setting.
In this example we are trying to teach students the numbers through a greeted carpet with
numbers on it.
In the elementary school mode we have as already said a fully custom version of Blockly.
On the left side we have different categories of blocks including mathematics, programming,
movement and sensing.
On the right there are some control buttons and a terminal window for printing real time
measurements and messages.
Now for the advanced mode.
The advanced mode of the robot is based in Jupiter.
The user can directly program the robot using native Python language combined with our custom
robot library and the code can be combined with text and images.
Then the whole page can be exported including the result of the program execution as an
experimental report in a class.
Now for the action.
This is a line following program written using Blockly.
It's a very common task for students when we teach them robotics.
We have some videos to present you.
On the left you see a video of the robot line following a line and stopping when it detects
an obstacle in front of it.
On the right we have a video of the robot running the same code but this time following
the line in the loop.
When a colleague puts her hand in front of the robot it stops and waits until no obstacle
is detected.
Additionally, the physical robot will also have a simulated environment.
We have developed a library and a custom simulation environment for our robot using CopleiaSim.
This was a crucial step for us because it eliminates the need for a physical robot and
that means that the experimentation with the robot comes in no cost.
Our software platform works seamlessly in both the physical and the simulated environment
allowing the project to run identically in either setting.
On the left you can see a video of a simple example of our platform combined with the
simulator.
Here are more examples of our virtual environment.
Those examples created for different teaching scenarios.
Also we have a video in the top right that demonstrates a line following project inside
the simulator.
We are trying to constantly improve the robot and we have received strong interest from
our university students.
We have already students creating educational material and developing new features such
as the real-time graphs and soon we will hope to integrate the new features to the main
platform.
Now let's dig deeper into the workings of our platform.
Firstly we have created a custom library to simplify the process of controlling the electronic
parts of the robot.
That library is based of my 2019 Google Summer of Code contribution.
The platform was built using Flask, Socket.io, Python, Blockly and can be deployed to the
robot via token containers for easy distribution and maintenance.
The robot after powering up tried to connect to a non-WiFi and if that is not possible
then the robot creates its own wireless access point.
The access to the platform can be gained through a user preferred browser such as Chromium
and finally all the necessary tools are already pre-installed inside the robot.
This allows a hassle-free experience as the user never needs to install anything to their
computer.
In this slide we present a brief overview of how users can be accessed at multiple levels
of the robot.
The top level is designed for less experienced users and is where the platform resides inside
multiple docker containers.
The access to this layer can be achieved through a web browser.
The second and third levels are designed for advanced users with knowledge of Python language
and bus and can be accessed through SSH.
Before concluding I would like to present the future prospects for the robot and its
potential use in higher education.
In Herakopio University we have already started to examine the potential of using the force
boot as a machine learning robotics platform by combining the custom high-level library,
the simulated environment and the physical robot with advanced algorithms.
With this combination the force boot has the potential to be used in various ways, for
example, reinforcement learning.
Additionally, if attached to the robot some advanced sensors such as cameras or lighters,
it can be used as a self-driving platform or a computer vision platform.
So that brings us to the end of our presentation.
I hope you enjoyed it.
Before closing I want to add a couple of things to this excellent presentation of Christos.
First of all I have to say that technology wouldn't be successful without content, first
of all, and without people.
With the help of Open Technologies Alliance we also managed to have a great group of educators,
primary and secondary education, that currently are creating or developing educational activities
and educational content for teachers in Greece.
They are currently running some seminars for force boot and they are currently educating
them on programming and using force boot in their teaching activities.
Over 1,000 or almost 1,000 teachers around Greece.
So the benefit is that we have the virtual simulation environment of force boot so they
can start working in the simulation environment and then everything that they have created
there, they can directly apply it to force boot, they can print the force boot, assemble
it and use it in the actual process.
Another thing that I would like to add to the higher education part of this presentation
of this work is that we are currently working with some colleagues in the university in
order to develop a short term curriculum, let's say one year curriculum with basic IT
courses such as data management courses, IoT programming, basic Python programming, machine
learning and AI as Christo said, in order to develop content that in most of the activities
we'll use force boot as its main demonstration platform.
So this is another effort that we are trying to do, we are working on at the moment and
we hope that it will soon bring us some results.
And I would like to thank you once again for your attendance.