Hello, everybody. Today I'm going to talk about something I've been hacking on for quite
some time now. It is called Galia and it is an extendable pen testing framework mainly
in the automotive domain. My talk is structured like this. It is divided into four parts.
I will start with some metadata about me and the project. Then I will give you an overview
of the status quo. I will conclude with an outlook and I hope we have some time for a
little short demo. So that's me. On the left-hand side you see my avatar and you might have
spotted me on GitHub. I'm Stefan and I'm a security researcher and I'm the maintainer
of Galia. So what is Galia? Galia stems from the SAC4COS project. It was a research project
and we received some funding. On the YouTube link you can see a little demo we prepared
last year. Galia is implemented in the Python programming language and we support the latest
version minus one that is currently the 3.10 release. It is free software and it is available
on GitHub. It is licensed under Apache 2. And we have two maintainers. The second maintainer
hides in the audience. If you have questions we have been around here for some time. And
it aims to be a modular tool for automotive penetration tests. So what is this? According
to Wikipedia, a penetration test is an authorized simulated cyber attack on a computer system
performed to evaluate the security of the system. And that basically means we connect
our computer to a car or an automotive ECU and we send some data. And we keep on sending
data until it breaks. And hopefully it breaks and then we try to figure out what we did
in order to break it. And after such tests the lab usually looks like this. What are
the challenges to actually achieve this? The reason why Galia exists is that we were doing
some penetration testing and we needed a protocol stack for this. And in the automotive domain
there is usually the UDS protocol that stands for unified diagnostic services. And you can
think of it as the HTTP of automotive with the difference that UDS is stateful in contrast
to a stateless protocol. Of course we need post processing which means machine readable
logs in order to analyze data. Everything needs to be reproducible. We solve this by
a defined directory structure for artifacts. And of course the automotive guys are very
very creative in implementing network protocols. That means if you do expect an answer, the
ECU doesn't answer. If you expect no answer, the ECU does answer. And that's quite a challenge
and that's why we decided to write our own protocol stack. Since the automotive industry
loves proprietary software and we do want to release the core of Galia, we created a
plugin interface where we maintain our own proprietary plugins in our own infrastructure
which plugs nicely into the GitHub code. And of course we need the whole software stack
to achieve these goals. So we did write a whole implementation of the UDS stack and
the status quo is like this. Usually you plug it in into the OBD port of your vehicle. OBD
stands for onboard diagnosis and several ECUs might be exposed on that port and you can
use Galia to discover this whole tree. For example, there might be three ECUs available
and each ECU has different modes of operation. These are called UDS sessions. Galia can also
discover these. And each session might also provide different UDS services. And what a
UDS service does is up to the manufacturer of the ECU. It can be getting parameters.
It might be setting parameters. It might even be software updating. The UDS standard defines
just some basic facts what this actually is. And it could be everything basically.
Galia came as a CLI tool and you can think of it as the nmap for cars. We provide some
ready to use scanning modules. For example, the discovery I already showed and there are
also modules to investigate these modules further. We have an UDS stack including DYP
or ISOTP. These are little transport protocols beneath UDS since UDS is on the application
layer. DYP, for example, is on top of TCP. ISOTP is on top of the CAN bus. You can use
all these setups. The next one is that we are able to do some automation. If you're
testing some ECU on its own, you can power cycle it during a scan. We power cycle the
whole setup before each scan and so on. And of course, we have machine readable logging
which comes as JSON logging and SQL logging. The SQL module is quite interesting since
it can be used to query logging information across different or multiple ECUs. And for
development we offer a virtual ECU module. The core concept of Galia is a test run. It
is basically the invocation on the command line until it finishes. And it always creates
a directory structure which is always the same and which contains some artifacts which
can be used for scripting or similar. And the artifacts still always contains log files,
always contains PCAP files and it might contain something else. The software is basically
structured like this. There's a core module which can be extended via plug-ins. And you
can build standalone modules or you can integrate into the CLI system. Basically, the architecture
is like this. The main entry point is the scanner on top which contains a module for
optionally controlling power supplies and it contains an abstraction module for an ECU
which uses the whole UDS protocol stack. And the protocol stack also can be extended via
plug-ins. And these plug-ins might look like this. This is a Hello Work module. Basically,
you create a class in Python. You need to implement the main method which could be basically
anything and then you plug it in into an entry point and that's basically it. Some random
facts. We use poetry for dependency management and in order to maintain a modern Python code
base, async.io, and async. await is used everywhere. It is fully typed. It passes my py strict.
It is extendable as mentioned via the Python entry point API. And for configuring the protocol
stack, we use some URL strings which are verified by the Pythonic module. Yesterday, there was
a great talk about the Pythonic module if you're interested in this. So, let's give
us some little outlook. Of course, we need more power supplies. We need more transport
modules. We need also more scanner modules. And also, we need extending the scope. We
need more plug-ins, scanning techniques, and so on. And of course, more breakage and more
memes and more testing. And we need more packages. Currently, there is a package for the Arch Linux
distribution. We have a UAR package and it is included in the Nix OS distribution in
the unstable branch. And if you're a package maintainer and interested in this, just create
a package file ticket on GitHub and we will include this in the file. I will conclude
with a short demo. It can be downloaded on this link, but I brought it here and I will
play it. Sorry. Okay. What we can see here is a Team
Manager. And on the second tab, we have the command line invocation. Here we have the
configuration of the network stack. We have a transport module called TCP lines, which
basically sends ASCII strings as TCP. On top of TCP. We use this for debugging and testing.
We have an artifact here where all the logging is placed. And we try to discover what actual
UDS services this ECU exposes. When you start it, it starts dump cap, which records all
the network traffic. Then it synchronizes with the ECU, which means it sends a present
packet that's something like a ping message. And when the pong arrives, the scanner starts
and it iterates over the ECU. And in this example, we have found a mode of operation.
This session, hex 52. And several services are exposed in this session, which can be
scanned further with other scanning modules. Now I have finished with my talk. Thank you
very much for your attention. And if there are any questions, I will help you to answer
them.
Yes, thank you, Stefan. So we have sometimes four questions here.
Hi, thank you for your talk. Can you say anything about fuzzing or memory scan? What you did
there? We have some very basic fuzzer. It is included in the GitHub code. It is PDU
fuzzing. But it just generates random data. And you don't have any feedback loop for this
since this is quite complicated to implement for a car in a generic manner. Internally,
we have some more sophisticated fuzzing modules, but we are not allowed to publish them because
of the NDA stuff, unfortunately. For the memory scan, there are a few services, blah, blah,
blah, by memory address. We have discovery modules for this published on GitHub. But
they actually discover endpoints. And that's basically it.
So I have done a lot of testing and reverse engineering. And you need a matrix of tests
of what you are testing against. And I was just wondering, for fits and giggles, is this
virtual CPU sufficient to actually plug it into the bus and actually run the car?
Maybe not.
Maybe not. Because then it would be accurate enough to be able to be tested as a real world
MCU.
I hope I did understand the question correctly. But our virtual ECU module offers a possibility
to clone ECUs so we can just record traffic and store this in the database. And it just
answers what it has seen recently. But it does not cover any state.
The idea was that the virtual CPU is actually sufficient to replace the ECU in the car and
run drive the car. And that would give the enough accuracy of the ECU to be able to be
tested.
Maybe it's a bit too much.
That's not in the scope of the data I feel.
Okay. Thank you, Stefan. Thank you for listening. And feel free to ask questions outside. Full
speaker there.
Thank you.