Bonjour. It's a great honor to be present among you. I'm sorry I speak English like
an average French. And I asked, obviously, I asked ChatGPT and Google Translate to write
me my speech. So if it doesn't work for you, it's the algorithm fault, obviously. My name
is Alexis Kofmann, and I'm going to present to you a Forge project for all teachers and
students in France. So a Forge project that forced them, so what? Nothing less original.
But three points in which, in my opinion, distinguish this Forge from other classical
forges. Users are teachers and K-12 students, so up to 18 years old for school, not for
the university. Shared content is educational, pedagogical content, and there's more text
in markup languages than code. And last but not least, the project is supported by the
French state. A few words about me. Basically, I'm a high school math teacher for 25 years,
but also a kind of screen software activist having founded the
French. And for years, we hoped, we, from ourself, we hoped for a real free software
policy in French education, and elsewhere and worldwide, obviously. But that did not
real come. I remember 10 years ago, as a president of from ourself, I wrote an article titled
My Ministry Drives Me to Despair, where I said this, either my ministry doesn't know
that free software exists and then it is irresponsible and incompetent, or it knows it and does nothing
and then it is guilty. By having such remarks publicly, you can well imagine that I would
never have thought of funding myself one day in the ministry. But today, times have changed.
I was invited to join the ministry a year ago and I accepted the challenge. This is
the first time that there is such free software and open educational resources project manager
in the institution and quite high in the organization chart. And I think it's a good sign. Another
good sign, we don't just use free software, we also contribute. For example, we found
a development for the open source video conferencing tool, BigBlueButton, and it's unusual to read
this in a project repose. And we contribute to other free software projects like NextCloud,
Future or Moodle. So, another positive move, this Forge project. It responds to two needs
expressed by the teachers. The first is a classic one. We are nearly a million teachers
in France and among them there are those who develop free software application for education.
And some of which have a great potential. But all these projects are scattered and it is
difficult to spot them and then it's difficult to support them. And for ethical and GDPR reasons,
we cannot also tell our teachers to go to Microsoft GitHub. So, let's bring them together
in a sovereign and secure space. And as we have computers courses from high school now
in France, this also concerns students. Firstly, the second need corresponds to new uses. Here
we share a lot more formatted text, markdown, LaTeX, than code to create educational content
together. And here we create content in the dark mode image which will then be pushed
into web pages, print PDF for a Jupyter Notebook. By using the pages function of the Forge, you
can work collaboratively on the Forge to produce web pages, websites with quality educational
content as in this project with computer science teachers. And you can do this without leaving
the web environment, without knowing git pull, git push, etc. Another example in CI, in
continuous integration, we can also push markdown into a pretty mind map as a philosophy teacher
suggests here. Just to emphasize that it's not just science teachers who work this way.
So, two needs expressed by teachers for a Forge of code and text. So, let's do it. And
the Forge already exists as a proof of concept since last September with 200 projects or
300 accounts. It's a GitLab instance powered by a French PE platform as a service, CleverCloud,
who have a stand here at first then. And administered by the, an association, a teacher's
association, the association of computer science teacher of France, the R-O-E-F. The big news
just from 10 days ago is that the project has been validated by the ministry which has
integrated it into its big strategy, the digital strategy for education 2023, 2027. So, the
prototype Forge will join the IT services of the ministry. I cannot give you more details
because the project is just beginning, so no road map, etc. But we have at least five
years to move forward. To move forward and convince of its interests more and more teachers
and students. This is the big challenge. Succeed in enlarging the cycle of users. This will
require support, training, animation, and promotion of the projects submitted. Here,
you can see a quick and dirty sweat and eyelashes. The most important thing for me is that the
project is supported by the institution and that it has values close to an event like
the post-dem. So, I have just one minute, huh? Okay. So, I don't detail the strengths,
opportunities, or weaknesses. So, thank you. I came to post-dem to present this project,
but also despite my terrible level of English to discuss and see if other countries, other
ministry of education in Europe, for instance, are engaged in similar projects to pull and
share our experiences. Okay. Don't hesitate to talk about it around you if you think the
project is interesting. And, thank you.
Thanks for your attention. If there is anyone who has a question, is there anyone who has
a question? In French, in English, also in chat GPT language.
No, but I can, if we have time, I can read with you a first list of positive points and
risks. So, obviously, the main thing is that it's an institutional project that carries
values, openness, sharing, ethics, sovereignty. Sovereignty is important here and sustainability.
It encourages teachers and students to work together and so increase digital and computer
skills, I think. And by gathering our force, join the force in the same place, it's easier
to make community and obtainment. It's easier to ask money. And doing so, I hope we will
have a big, a large bank of open educational content with free license available to the
entire school community. There is also a point with what in France we call it so britais
numéry, the digital sobriety. I think it's not a good translation. But because we use
light and open format, we can work offline, it's improving existing rather than beginning
from scratch, et cetera, et cetera. And important, the project for us is a commons. So, it's governance
and policy is shared with the users. That's very important because we did a lot of projects,
a lot of top-down projects in the French Ministry of Education. These want to be more horizontal.
Not very expensive, but at first, at the beginning. But if there is a lot more and more users
with CICD, it can be different. And the threats, maybe it's too complex tool for our teachers
and students if we want more and more users. So, great news for documentation training,
animation. And convents, great teachers who are already on forges to migrate to our forges.
That's a point because super teachers are already on GitHub, for instance. A copyright
stuff. This is not clear if the content belongs to the agents or the teacher or to the states.
So, there is a thing to end the evolution of GitLab offer. And the competition with
Microsoft GitHub, with Copilot and Chattera with more and more new functions. Voila.
Thank you.