Hello, good morning everyone.
I'm Christopher Peters and I'm going to present you Grotto Center.
So first a bit about me.
I'm from Belgium.
I'm mostly working as a trainer and consultant in open source and DevOps.
And in my free time, I'm spending quite a lot of time doing outdoor adventure stuff
such as, for example, I go into caves.
By the way, for the people who like to enjoy the pictures of my slides, this is the only
picture that I didn't take.
So it's a bit difficult to take it when you're posing for it.
So first a bit about caving or spalliology.
So what does it actually mean?
It's mostly a scientific study where we are going into caves or outdoors and explore cast
phenomena or caves in particular.
If we are going into caves to study what is happening over there, there are different
sciences that are involved.
There is geology, there is biology, there is also a lot of physics and chemistry involved.
But in general, to get to the place that we want to study, we need to go and pass certain
obstacles.
We have to crawl through some small passages.
We have to descend into pits.
And for that we need a certain physical activity to get there.
So there are some people who do this for science, to actually research things that are happening
down there.
There are other people who just like to do the physical activity.
And so it's also a bit of a sport.
For the people who are a bit familiar with other terminologies, in English it's also
known as caving, potholing, spallunking.
So they're different words for it.
But in general, the idea is we go into caves.
Now if we go into caves, of course there are a few things that we have to keep in mind.
And one of the things that I would like to present to you today is a problem that we
often have to deal with.
So when we go into caves, on this picture you can see a person who is descending into
a pit on a rope.
And this is something you don't do just like, okay, you know, it's 10 o'clock, let's go
and see what's in this hole.
We actually do some preparations.
For that we are using a lot of information that we are consulting to make sure that we
have the adequate equipment with us.
We have also made sure that we are using the right tools that we are also making sure that
we're not going in the wrong moments.
Because sometimes also weather conditions can make a very bad influence on the conditions
in a cave.
Here you see an example of a survey, we have quite a lot of surveys that provide us with
information on how the cave looks like, if it has already been explored.
And we can use these surveys to also make sure that we have all the rigging material
with us, that we make sure that we know where we are going, what we are going to do, and
what kind of dangers that could be involved in this trip.
For this we have the surveys, they provide us with this information, there is also sometimes
a description that is added to the survey which provides us more information of, for
example, how to get to the entrance, maybe some particularities, special things we would
like to see or special things we would like to avoid.
And sometimes also separately we have rigging information.
That's not always the case, but depending on how well a cave has been researched and
explored, these documents are available.
On this survey there is also, over here you can see that there is an indication which
actually also tells that this is a pit of 20 meters, and so sometimes also this information
is only available on the survey.
Except for that we also have other information which is not very necessary to just facilitate
the trip itself, but which can give us some more background.
For example, scientific research that has been performed, some information about the
region that could be geologically, that could be biologically, that could also be, for example,
information about how rivers are flowing above and underground.
There is also other kind of research that can have been performed that isn't necessarily
limited to this specific cave we are going to visit, but that could be more broad and
give more information about also the region or maybe a particular kind of cave.
And other documentation, like for example, when they made this survey they also took
measurements.
This survey has been made probably with compass and just measuring tape, and thus they might
have taken notes of that.
They might have also saved them somewhere.
These days we are also using more modern technologies such as radar and 3D scanners, and also those
data points that can be saved and they can also be archived.
All this kind of information is available at a certain location most of the time.
It is the person who has actually, who has generated this information, who owns this
information.
But if we want to share this, we are very much scattered around the world and there
is not such a thing as a central database.
That is the actual problem we have to deal with.
So if you look at how we are going to share this information these days, a lot of this
happens by email or by websites or blogs, sometimes also some file transfer services.
But in general all the information is at one specific organization, one specific person
or group of persons, and you have to know where you have to go to if you want to actually
access the information.
There are some countries who do have their central databases, but this is not something
which is also standardized or generalized.
If we then have the information about the cave, like for example the survey, how also
are we going to link this with scientific research that has been performed around this
cave?
That is also one of the problems we have to deal with.
If we are contacting someone because we want to visit the cave, very often we get a survey
or we get a description or we get a combination of both, but we don't get all the information
that is available.
Also because very often this information is not centralized in one sort of group of people.
Some people have one part of the information, other people have another part of the information.
And then when I contact someone to obtain this information and if I have been using
it for a while and then afterwards an update has been provided on this information, how
am I going to make sure that I'm also getting this update?
Because also in this world science is still moving on, we are still exploring new places
underground, we're still finding new places, new caves, and so all these kinds of information
need to be shared as well because the survey that I was showing before is a very old one.
There are already several newer versions of that available right now.
And so if I get this survey one day and a newer version is made the other day, how am
I going to make sure that I also get this if the person who sent me the first one is
forgetting to also send me updates?
For that there is a solution and this solution is Grotto Center.
So what is Grotto Center?
It is a sort of wiki database which is made for cavers and also mostly made by cavers.
So there are a few people in France, they have been starting developing a database which
they use to store all the information and it is made public available so that everyone
can use it.
It is supported by the European Caving Federation and it is also supported by the International
Caving Federation who also officially hosts some parts of this.
The idea is to have a global source of all kinds of information about caves and caste
phenomena and to have it with an open access so that everyone can access this information.
Also with the idea to use standards so that all the information is saved in the same way
and it is very easy for everyone to also add information and also query this.
And because we are using standards we are also making it very easy to make it accessible
by machines as well so that you can query this using APIs.
How are we going to then use these kind of standards to make sure that everyone can access
this information?
For this we made a standard which is called Cast Link and which enables us to link all
the different documents to caves.
For this we didn't really try to reinvent the wheel, we just extended a tool which is
from the W3C Linked Data and Semantic Web.
This enables us to store the information in such a way that it is very easy to access
also using machine readable sort of ways such as APIs.
And then you have Grotto Center itself.
So here you see the front page of the website where you have on the side menu bar which
you can easily use to browse the information.
If we then go, you can see there is a quick search and advanced search.
I'm going to skip those for a moment.
I'm going to skip to the map and then here you see a screenshot of a part of Belgium
where you can also see all the hexagons which are indicating where are caves or cluster
of caves.
So these are just sort of caves bundled together.
If you further zoom in then you can actually see over here you can see that there are also
a switch point where you can find certain caves and then you also have over there the
pop-up which appears when you click on one of those points which provides us with some
information like for example here which cave has been found at that location and then also
a link to the data sheet of this cave.
So this is the data sheet of that exact cave.
You can see then where it is on the map.
You can get some basic information such as for example the exact GPS coordinates, some
information about how deep and how long the cave is when it's been discovered and then
if you browse down here you can also find some information about for example the location.
If you go down a bit more in the description you can also find documents such as the cave
survey.
Not all this information is of course very extended.
It depends very much on the people who add this information.
So this is one that has been created automatically using an import which is done during migration
of Grotto Center from version 2 to version 3.
But most of this information is being provided by users.
It's just like Wikipedia.
If I don't write a webpage, a Wikipedia page about Grotto Center then there is no Wikipedia
page available about Grotto Center.
So this is information that can be shared by everyone.
On the top there is also a login which enables you to add to your information yourselves.
How are we making this possible?
We are using different technologies.
The complete infrastructure is running on AWS and Microsoft Azure and we're using Docker
to also host our application.
For the rest we're using quite a lot of JavaScript so there is a node involved, there is Sales
JS, React.
We are also using GitHub to host our code so you can also browse the code freely because
this is of course an open source project so the GitHub project is freely available.
You can check out the code over there.
For the rest you can also get in touch using our Slack channel.
There is a wiki which explains how you can use this tool if you want to add information
and then for the rest a few other links.
For example here you have the WikiCaves Foundation.
The WikiCaves Foundation is the foundation which is responsible for the project so Grotto
Center is being officially organized by WikiCaves.
They are also making sure that all the funding and all the partners are being addressed.
Then a link to what is called the Documentation Center of the International Caving Federation
where you can find all the scientific documents.
They have been imported into Grotto Center so these days if you are browsing information
about specific caves then you can also find all the scientific bulletins linked to specific
caves.
Last link is one to the CastLink project page where you can find more information as well
as the current standard.
We are building this mostly with people who are doing spelology and who are by accident
also IT people.
We are also very grateful that we from time to time get some interns from different schools
that want to build on specific parts of our project to make it better and to also add
more functionality.
For that we can rely on interns from the Polytech of Montpellier as well as the Epitech from
Montpellier and the University of Grenoble.
Many thanks to them as well.
Some of our partners, I didn't list all of them because then my slide would be very full
but there are quite a lot of clubs and caving associations, federations who are sponsoring
the project and who are making it possible that we can build this and we can host this
on an infrastructure that is also made it, that makes it possible that everyone can access
this.
So here by I would like to conclude my presentation.
If there are any questions then I'm very eager to answer them and if you have any questions
later you can also reach out to us on our Slack or GitHub or project pages.
Thank you very much.