Hi everyone, this is I2P major changes of the Peer2Peer network by Konrad Bächler.
Almost close enough.
Enjoy.
Hello everyone.
Thank you for being here.
That's my third I2P talk at Fosstem.
First one was about DNS.
That was the most difficult for me personally.
That was JavaScript which was also difficult for me and now a major changes of the Peer2Peer
network of a bunch of programmers which are creating I2P which is an overlay network.
I'm an independent researcher and software architect and developer and I'm developing
libraries and I'm working full time for D.W.Xchange which is a small non-profit association in
the world.
There is nothing like a centralized model involved because I'm totally living in the
Peer2Peer I2P world because I really love what the I2P developers and the open-source
space are doing since the last 20 years.
I suggest we're looking now at the agenda.
I give you a short introduction of I2P and then we're looking at what the developers
did as the latest changes of the code and we'll focus since I'm an application developer
based on the I2P network, what is the impact?
We're looking at the summary and I understood that there are no questions so if you have
questions I'll be outside in the hall for a few minutes and I'm happy to get in touch
with you if you have critical and skeptical questions.
Sure thing, what is the role of D.W.Xchange within I2P?
I2P is a developer team, D.W.Xchange is a developer team and the I2P developers are
spread all over the world.
The D.W. developers are spread all over the world.
We're cooperating friendly but we're not the same.
D.W.Xchange is primarily a library developer and is supporting so-called official open
source to Docker images.
That's what we're doing.
Myself, since I'm a researcher I'm cooperating with Swiss universities and I'm open for all
corporations with any university to take a very skeptical perspective towards our own
work.
Now what is the I2P network?
I2P network is an overlay network.
An overlay network and now please jump to the very last line of this slide.
I2P gives you privacy by design, serious privacy by design.
It means you get confidentiality and total anonymity.
Just an example, this statement that the network gives you total anonymity is something which
we do research in Switzerland whether we can break this anonymity and that's one of our
research approaches.
But currently, at the current stage of knowledge and since I2P is existing since 20 years,
we can say it's confidential and anonymous.
Now a question, whoever in this room in the past presentations there was around 5% of
the audience have ever got in touch and used I2P in their life.
Please hands up.
Wow, that's close to 20%.
Cool, thank you.
For the others which do not know it, anonymity has a cost attached and this cost is called
latency.
When I'm talking about an anonymous network which gives you full confidentiality, then
these messages are multiple time encrypted and hop from peer to peer to its destination
and through another tunnel they hop back, the reply hops back.
And this is giving anonymity on a very, very, very high level.
A word to be clear here, I2P has no storage capability by itself.
It's a transport layer.
Now how to get I2P?
Those which got in touch with it, they know that.
There are the Linux Red Pose and then there are PPAs and then there are the container
maintained by DevoExchange which you find on Docker.
Now why is there I2P and why is there I2PD?
Because there are two versions available from two development teams.
In short, I2P is written in Java, it has a user interface and there are a lot of fans
around there which really like that and then there is a smaller version which is I2PD which
is written in C++ and which is a daemon only so it's rather a bit more for odd means.
Devo uses I2PD and there's also the image maintainer on Docker for this version.
From my point of view, both are equally valid.
Bit of warning, please don't trust any binaries which are floating around here and there which
you can't reproduce locally by yourself.
Please build it yourself if you can and sure you can because this gives power to the open
source developers.
If you just consume some binaries, please don't.
It's also dangerous because you have a router running on your local machine.
The whole thing here is it's a peer-to-peer network without any central authority, without
any trust involved.
Now the latest changes.
Since 20 years, I2P is existing and gets developed and there are two transport protocols, TCP
and UDP.
TCP is also used within other overlay networks.
Was along a while so around four years already upgraded to so-called NTCP2 which is much
modernized so the TCP communication was already pretty well done in the last four years.
But UDP which is something where you just blow out messages to the network and I'll
talk about that in a minute which is fast for I2P in an I2P context was not modernized
since 15 years.
The developer of I2P, they worked one full year on modernizing UDP and they call it SSU2.
When you hear SSU2 in the context of I2P, it's UDP.
If you want to dig deeper, deeper, then please take a look at noiseprotocol.org.
That's very important also for other overlay networks you might heard of.
The developer team of I2P has borrowed quite some things from WireGuard, VPN and also from
Quick and there are some RFCs around so please dig deeper by using these hints.
Then the cryptography had to be updated too.
There will be more work coming in the upcoming years I know for sure.
But it's now already on a quite good state.
Right, seven minutes to go.
What were the goals?
UDP, the performance, is simply much better in an overlay network than TCP.
Me as an application developer which is creating a fully distributed storage layer on top of
the I2P network, performance to communicate between the notes in the peer-to-peer network
is an issue.
For me it was always the choice to take UDP and I implemented a gossiping protocol to
realize this fully anonymous blockchain.
This distributed storage layer.
I needed UDP so that the peers could communicate within each other.
For me this was really an important goal that they could improve the performance a lot.
Additionally, as you know, there are countries in this world where communication is not that
easy as we have the luck to be here in Europe.
So obfuscation is a topic.
For all those people, for all the whistleblowers and the journalists which are using I2P in
critical countries, they must not be detected.
And I2P is one of the premier solutions for such people which need communication on a
very confidential level.
The obfuscation was a big topic and additionally UDP is easily attackable so the developers
had to look into the security problems they had.
And they did a good job.
There are a few other challenges of UDP like the fragmentation of messages.
You have a long message, you want to send it through the network but it gets chopped
up into pieces and UDP is not reliable so the developers really had some challenges
to solve in the last 12 months.
But the fact is they have implemented strong solutions and today if you look at the release
notes of I2P, I2P is in a much better state.
And this is what I want you as a core take out of this presentation.
I2P gives users 20 years real privacy by design and the developers did a good job the last
20 years.
But now with this performance improvement and that's my personal view on their work,
they really made a major step forward.
Because UDP is for application developers really important within the I2P network.
That's my personal view on it.
Please feel free to criticize me afterwards in the Q&A session outside if you see this
differently or if you have a different view on it, I'm happy to hear that.
But these reductions, they are relevant.
For us as application developers we directly felt this performance impact.
In November when the release was, so four months ago or three and a half months ago,
the performance in our blockchain test network improved very much.
And although I believe from research point of view we have quite some work ahead of us
to skeptically and very critically looking at the latest changes to see whether some
weird box have been introduced, the first impression of the two months is woohoo, that's
a new generation of I2P.
So for me the performance impact is really, really relevant.
Okay, we're on the target, we're seeing the target line.
Takeouts.
After 20 years of development I2P is the leading peer to peer privacy by design network which
is a transport layer only which gives you today very modern cryptography, very modern
possibilities to use as an application developer.
The performance increased significantly since last November and if you feel as a researcher
too or as an application developer to take a closer look at I2P I believe now it's a
good time.
Either you can invest as a researcher trying to break the anonymity and present it at
an upcoming conference or you try to create some applications on top of it.
I believe currently it's a good point to take a look again at I2P because now it's really
quite fast to use and it's also fun to use.
On GitHub, so that's in the lower right corner and you'll find it online on GitHub, you'll
find Docker images which help you to get started with I2P really quickly.
Because a peer to peer network to create it as a test network is quite complex but we
created here simple images for you which you can start with Docker Compose, you have all
the containers running and tada, you're a member of the I2P network and you can write
your application on top of this network.
Here is a list of sources.
Please do your own research too because privacy by design also means that we hope to motivate
US developers to take a look, a very close look at the documentation, a very close look
at the source code to be sceptical because privacy is such an important topic for us
as developers.
So we're always very, very pleased if we get critical feedbacks on the development of the
stuff we're doing.
Thank you very much for your time.
Have a great Fostem.
Thank you.
Thanks, Corin.
Really nice talk.
Again, if you have questions, please grab them outside and I'd be happy to answer.
I hope.
Thank you.