Let's entire talk is inspired by a single remark by a former co-worker of mine who just
casually dropped the line that Yama was so simple that nobody could ever attain master
ship in it.
So a question towards the audience, also slight audience participation, sorry, who would tend
to agree?
That is almost nobody.
That's a shame because you would be in good company.
This is in the goat section of every speck of Yama there is.
So let's get a bit into detail.
And the very cool Yama exists to provide printable text presentation of structured data.
And in that regard it is a rival to things like JSON, XML and other formats.
It's been around for quite a while.
We're almost looking into 20 years of Yama now.
It is somewhat interwoven with JSON since version 1.2.
Actually all of JSON is also valid Yama.
That is, they're just introducing an interesting relation because now since I think 2018 JSON
is a strict subset of JavaScript, there's an intersection of Yama and JavaScript now
that is precisely JSON.
Let's not get into the argument if that's good or not.
It's a thing.
If you write a lot of Yama, all of the examples, most of the examples, most of the real life
specimens they will let you believe that there are no real types in Yama.
Actually the opposite is true.
Yama is heavily typed.
Almost everything in a Yama document has a type.
Here's a selection.
They're nothing surprising.
All of the times you see here they are also present in JSON.
That's also inspiring an interesting question.
Let's say you have a Yama document.
Could you just change the syntax to JSON and have a valid presentation?
Would that work?
Oh, you're too good.
I see I affected the wrong audience because no, that doesn't work.
Actually it falls apart with the map type.
The map type in Yama is really, really wide.
It does allow for such things as composite keys to its entries.
If you're really interested, they're introduced by your, what's the token, Crested Mark Space.
So that's a thing.
There are not so basic types.
OMAP is an audit map.
The regular mapping is not ordered.
That is somewhat special.
There's not a complete list, by the way.
There's a way to have Yama inside Yama.
That's nice.
Then there's a type specifically for binary data.
This one is really, really useful provided it actually works.
Try it.
The problem really is in JSON, XML, also in Yama is you can't have certain bytemarks.
So the first 16, I believe, character points, they are off limits.
They are controlled signals.
They can't be part of the stream.
With this type, you can just base 64 everything.
Once your Yama is being passed, that is being expanded into the raw binary.
First example, this is not minimal Yama, but it does help to illustrate a few points.
I suppose a lot of you got a lot to do with say OpenShift, Kubernetes, something like.
You've seen three hyphens a lot, haven't you?
Okay.
Who knows what that does?
It's not the beginning of the document.
Come again.
Not quite, no.
It's not the beginning of the document.
What this is is a document separator.
So what you see here is not actually a Yama document.
It's a Yama stream.
Yama is meant to be streamed, possibly.
Don't do that unless you have a solid message framing because our truncated Yama tends also
to be earlier to Yama.
So I think twice before you do that.
Thing is, most of the tools that you have with Yama will assume there's only one document
ever.
You need to do some convincing to get all the documents out of a stream.
By the way, do you know what happens if you omit those three hyphens?
You do.
Okay.
Pretty much everything you see here, if it's missing, it's implied.
Great, eh?
It's a folder version number.
There's also a bit of homework for you.
There's a chance this is going to break your tools because they do not understand version
1.2.
The majority of the tools are still stuck at 1.1.
Ah, yeah.
Let's get into time a bit.
This is something you see quite common.
What do we have here?
It's a mapping with a single entry, which shares the key variables.
Inside is another mapping for the key app version.
We've got something in it.
Now there's no indication to what data type that is.
It's an integer, right?
You agree?
Depends on your schema.
It depends on your schema.
We're not quite there yet.
This is for most pure YAML.
This is an integer, we agree for the time being.
This is a float, right?
This is a string.
This is still a string.
You may have noticed I omitted a few things.
What's three points?
It depends on your schema.
No.
Yes, it does.
The regular expression for float says three point is a float.
What is point one then?
It's also a float.
If you want to make sure this is really always a string, you may be tempted to do something
like this.
Quota strings are a thing, also in YAML.
Big supplies.
Single quoted also.
The professional may do something like this.
This is a tag.
The two exclamation marks means it's a global tag.
There's global meaning.
I'm running out of time.
It's a string.
I have my word for it.
The true professional who lost a plot made to something like this.
Tags are identified by URNs.
Also there's a name spacing mechanism in YAML.
That's the part where you go, yay, name spaces.
Most features, this is something you do not commonly see.
Most users of YAML are probably unaware this exists.
But you have some tools to reduce duplication, redundancy within your structures.
One is anchors.
They're basically marker.
One are alliances that do invoke those anchors.
Pretty nifty.
So these do give way for an attack known as one brilliant loss.
It's basically you can set an anchor to an array or list of alliances who themselves
contain a lot of anchors.
This allows for a very complex presentation of a very complex structure that quickly expands
plenty of code.
So if you happen to consume YAML from untrusted sources, this is something you should know.
Magic operator, this is another really nifty tool.
It's only valid in 1.1 of YAML.
It got immediately deprecated in 1.2.
And also it's a data type.
It's there to basically merge mappings into other mappings.
Great stuff.
So these are examples that really happened.
Do you see, I should explain this.
This is part of the GitLab setup as a script.
This is expected to be a sequence of strings to be executed on the shell.
That's not what it is.
Who sees the issue?
No?
Oh, very good, yes.
That's not a string.
It's a mapping.
Because of the single pass design of YAML, the algorithm is very, very greedy.
So it sees that colon there and says, oh, great.
This is a mapping.
And completely ignores the cretations.
So how do you fix this?
There's a bunch of ways.
Yes, I think the third one is my favorite.
The fourth is really unsafe because once again, raw binary data.
I'm sorry to know that.
This is another favorite.
So again, GitLab CI, we have a mapping.
We tried to set some variables for GitLab to expand.
What is the content of bar?
I must remind you, mappings don't have order.
Oh, who knows?
I thought the answer was fast.
Oh, no.
It's going to be empty.
The mapping doesn't have an order.
The YAML implementation in GitLab has other ideas.
So it takes that mapping and applies an order on it.
So bar goes top because of the order.
And then there's a single round of interpolations.
And foo at that point is empty as a variable.
So how do you fix that?
Either way out is you rename your variables or this.
Thank you.
Oh, this never happened to me, but it's been too good to pass.
What do we have here?
What does languages contain?
It's a sequence of?
We all need to drink.
It's one string and one Boolean.
Because no, which is supposed to present Norwegian here, is accepted as a Boolean.
So you need to tag that or quote it.
How are you, you wish?
So my observations, because of the cases of the hidden complexity, there's huge disparity
in features that various tools actually support.
They also show different behavior.
It's one hot mess.
I can't put it in other words.
Also if you're writing YAML, it is admittedly really a pleasure.
It's easy to type, but you can never let your guard down.
YAML would try to do a lot of lag for you, being very accommodating in sometimes the
worst way possible.
Some proposals I have, because with the versions of YAML really do different behavior, you
should start to tag your streams accordingly.
You should see that the tools you use for consuming YAML are properly configured.
Things like language specific extensions.
Part of the YAML streams could be evaluated in the process, read, execute it.
That's a bit scary.
As most of YAML is relatively simple, the complexity is mostly because it's deeply nested
and you can't properly edit it.
Strict YAML may be a solution.
It's a strict subset of YAML with a lot of the ambiguity removed.
Way easier, safer, way easier.
Turning support is so-so.
I teased a question with this talk.
The question could be, YAML is exactly then the answer if all you wanted was JSON with
comments.
Some other niceties as well, but that's pretty much it.
This concludes my talk.
Thank you very much.
You've been terrific.
Is there any questions?
Please repeat the questions.
We've got four seconds.
Is JSON any better?
There you have it.
It depends on what your use case is really.
Repeat the question please.
Oh yes, the question was, was JSON any better?
So yes.
Thank you very much again.