Hello, I'm Konstantinos Pabadimitriou.
I'm the web developer and analyst from GeForce Open Technology Salients.
I will show you how we combine these appointments with JITC for online appointment management.
In COVID, a lot of private and public services switched to online appointments.
Most of them used closed source services for the online part.
We at GeForce adapted the easy appointments, which is an online software platform for appointment
management in JITC.
An online open source meeting with audio and video, and combined them into a seamless integration
for booking an appointment that will take place online rather than physically.
About our organization, we established in 2008, we are a non-profit organization, and
also we have shareholders, universities, research centers, and public beneficial organizations.
Our objectives are development and promotion of open standards, open software, open content,
open data, open government, open educational resources, creative common license of open
material and design technologies, and also open hardware and design.
We contribute to openness in education, in public sector, and also in private sector.
We have thematic working groups on open software and open standards, open technologies and
education, open governance and open data, open design, open hardware, wireless networks,
information, system security, and personal data protection, and also innovation and entrepreneurship.
Well, the easy appointments part, it's a web application for appointment management.
It has a very easy installation on a web server, and also configuration is simple.
Workers can use it directly without having to install any applications.
The operation is using a web browser, and it works on a computer, on tablet, or mobile
phones since the design is responsive.
It's a really simple and fast operation, optimized without unnecessary options.
Also easy to use environment for managing the appointments from the service side.
It supports over 25 languages, and also since it's open source, anyone can contribute more
languages.
It's written by Greek developer Alex Chelegidis, which actively continues development.
It's open software, open source, and also it has already hundreds of installations around
the world.
It's written in PHP.
It requires PHP 7.4 or above.
It uses MySQL or MariaDB for the database part, runs on N-Zincs or Apache web server,
and uses PDO extensions for JSON, M-B-String, OpenSSL, and PDO.
It's a developer friendly with clean source code.
Now the JITC part.
JITC is a set of open source projects that allow easy teleconferencing.
It's written in Java and JavaScript.
It's compatible with web by RTC.
JITC VideoBridges transmits video and audio to all participants separately, rather than
combining them first.
And of course it's open software.
The platform now, on the first page, if that seems Greek to you, actually it is Greeks.
In the first menu, the user can select the service he wants.
After that, he selects specific agent or any available from the service.
And finally, some information appears about the selected service, the duration of the
appointment.
On the bottom you can select also the interface language.
We added the part that you can also arrange an online appointment.
That's why we, maybe it's the same service, but rather than physically you want to do
it online.
On the second step, you choose the available dates and times of the service you choose.
Or if you select a specific agent, you see his availability or any other agent available,
you will see the calendar here.
And the third step, a user inserts its information, first name, last name, and email, which in
this email you will receive the details of the appointment and also the option to change
or to cancel the appointment.
The fourth step, all the details gathered for the appointment.
And finally, when he submits the appointment, two emails are, he sees a confirmation message
on the browser.
Also the system generates two emails, one for the user with details and also from the
selected agent to the selected service.
The email he receives, again, the confirmation, the details, and also in case it's an online
appointment, on the location field it will appear the unique video link to the DTC service.
Also the user will receive an as an attachment and an ICS file which he can import it to
the calendar.
On the administration side, the agent sees all his meetings with information in an easy
management environment.
Also you have roles in the system so you can have directors of the service which they will
see all the appointments.
Some technical details about our prototype.
We did minimal changes to easy appointments source code.
So it will be also easy to use it.
If the administrator doesn't set a physical location of a service because it's a service
so you say the appointment is on this address or this building, this office.
If this is empty, then the change we did, they generate a unique DTC link using the
appointments hash.
Each appointment has a unique hash in the database so we use this also as a link for
the conference.
We use the native location field to store the DTC link.
We added the location field in the email the user receives.
And administer to some settings.
We also wanted to show some text with information on the homepage which wasn't an option in
the appointment so we also added this and we wanted to change also the appearance.
So we inserted a CSS file which from there you can change colors and some design of the
pages.
The source code is available on the GitHub you see here.
That was our project.
Thank you for coming.
Does anyone have any questions?
Because once further information.
Yes.
I understand that this is a port from the official DTF endpoint.
So how do you manage with the new versions?
Do you provide something like automatic combination to add some patches to the main project?
This is a prototype.
We spoke with the developer of his appointments.
He has a system for plug-ins.
So it could be written as a plug-in to his appointments.
At the moment, no.
You change the actual code.
That's why also we wanted to make minimal changes.
Thank you, Konstantinos.
That was fantastic.
Thank you.