Welcome, everyone. Thank you. We start with a small introduction to have a bit of context
about Jupyco. I'm Maciej Goeche. I'm a flamethrower. And I'm working. My main client is a Kuwix
project. And for there, I'm the lead developer of L
eaMse. What is Kuwix? Kuwix is a project to provide
content where the Internet is not there. And the question we try to answer and we have
answer is how to distribute static websites. And, for example, if you don't know all Wikipedia
in English, it's 95 gigabytes and six billion article and media. And to do that, we use
the ZIM format. It's an archive format for web content. And content is partially compressed.
So you can compress textual content or not compress images or videos. And you can do
random access without initial decompression so you can access the content inside the archive
directly. It works well and pretty efficient. But there is a few flaws in the design and
the archive is really tied to web content and to Kuwix. And you cannot add another metadata.
So the question I try to answer is could we reuse the ZIM format, the good idea of the
ZIM format, and do better and more generic? So here is Jupyco. Jupyco is a Japanese name
for the bento boxes. And it's more boxes you can compress the way you want depending on
your needs. And Jupyco is a new format independent of Kuwix project. And this is a good idea
of the ZIM format but generic. And Jupyco is a meta-container. It tells you how to store
things but it's up to you to decide what do you want to store and how do you want to organize
them. And there is a reference library written in Rust. The feature of Jupyco, it's mainly
read-only archive or mainly read-only. This is selective compression so you can compress
the content or not. No initial decompression needed and you can do random access on the
archive. It's configurable so you can decide which property you want on the entries. There
is an extension system so your user can download an archive and they can download extra content
to add content to the archive you provide. It's embeddable in other files and it's composable
so you can compose different kinds of entries together in the same container. So it checks
them. And a few features to do, signature and encryption, direct access to uncompressed
content, content deduplication, modification, different patch between archive and overlay.
Let's have a quick tour on the internal structure. The Jupyco container are organized about a
round packs. There is three kinds of packs, the manifest pack, the content and the directory.
Each pack can be stored individually in the file system or they can be put together in
one file and then you distribute this file to your user. The manifest pack is the main
pack. This is a pack you will try to open when you want to open the Jupyco container
and it's mainly a list of all the other packs of the container. The content pack is a pack
which contains the raw content, compressed or not, and without any metadata. And the
directory pack is where you store the entries and the entries can point to content in the
content pack. This is a configural part of Jupyco. And inside directory pack there is
entries with a specific schema. So you have to define the schema and the schema is the
series of properties and their types. The content is just a property. It's a link to
the content in the content pack so you can have entries that point to several contents
or no content at all. And each schema can contain violence. It's kind of in your own
in pre-commission. You can have different kind of entry inside one directory pack. Which
use case? Why you would like to use Jupyco? The first use case is one archive. There is
a tool, ARX, which is an equivalent of tar. And here we have one kind of entry with three
variants, file, simlink and directory. All three variants share two common properties.
And for example, the file variants add the pointer to a content. Simlink, tar.get.link
and the directory just stores the first entry and the number of entries in the directory.
So it's a kind of a nogization and a three structure as a file system. There is no index
property for now but just mainly because ARX is pretty young and I don't want to bother
with them while testing ARX and Jupyco. But is it hard? It's a fun archive so we can compile
bits of ARX with tar to see how Jupyco and ARX perform. If we take the Linux source code,
the full Linux source code is more than one gigabytes and both tar and ARX are compressing
the source code is about 130 or 140 megabytes. Creation time is a bit faster than tar and
extraction time we are pretty close. ARX is a bit slower but we have someone pretty close,
both tools are pretty close. What is interesting is when we try to list the content of the
archive, tar took almost the same time that expression because to list the content in
the tar archive you need to uncompress all the content. ARX is very faster because the
list of the entry are separated from the content itself. If you want to extract only one content
from the archive and we try to dump a third of all the entries you can see that ARX is
really, really, really faster. The same way extracting one entry from the tar is pretty
close from the time of listing the content the same way as you need to uncompress all
the content of the archive and ARX you can locate the content and do a direct access
to the content without compressing the content. Once a few things that we can do is mount
the archive, directly mount the archive on the file system and if you mount the archive
and you do a diff of the content between the original source and what is mounted, if you
do a diff between two plain directories it's a bit less than a second, with ARX it's four
seconds and half and tar is an estimation it will take something like ten hours to do
the comparison. You can do something even more interesting with a mounted file system
with a mounting Linux source is compiling the kernel. So if you compile the kernel on
the plain file system it's a bit more than half an hour and if you compile the kernel
using the mounted archive is a bit less than an hour. What is interesting here is that
the compilation is made with G8, so there is eight processes and ARX is monosplated
so there is a huge bottleneck for now but if we move to a multithreaded system it should
be even better. Another use case is the GIMM, it's an equivalent of, kind of equivalent
of the GIMM format, there is two variants only and here we are storing the entries as
a playlist, there is no tree structure and the GIMM by now we just integrate a small
HTTP server looking for the entries. What we can do also is we could replace for example
a PM and deb with ARX or a thing based on Jupyco so you could download your package
and not extract it on the file system just open it directly and even a Jevil or Debug
Info that could be put in specific content pack of the same archive so it could simplify
the management and you will not need to have different package to different subtype of
content of your packages. OCI-Conner are based on Tor, you need to extract them on the file
system before running a container so you could just use ARX among them or you can even use
directe to put different layer in different content pack and so the whole image will be
one Jupyco container. File format, almost all file formats are in fact container for
the content so you could use Jupyco to just organize the content you want to store what
you want for your own project and your own file format. Website, Jupyco is written in
REST, you could run it in Wasm and so Jupyco could load your Jupyco archive in the browser
once and just open it directly in the browser. Backups, Jupyco is almost incremental by design
if you reuse the content pack of the backups, previous backup this is incremental and you
can decide which property you want to add so for example you can add a checksum on each
entry to do a comparison between the content store in the backup and what you have on the
file system. Embedding resources, Jupyco can be embedded in the executor program or even
more this presentation you can download this presentation at this address and you will
have a file and this file is an ARX archive so you can just use the ARX tool to list the
content extract on the archive and you will have access to all the files in this presentation
it is rebuilt yes and it's HTML content but the same file is also a GIM archive so you
can just use the GIM tool to just serve the content and open a browser to the local host
it's not and the same files is also a program so if you make it executable you can run the
program itself to extract or serve the content what is interesting is that between the content
is not shared it is an ARX and GIM archive but it's just a view to the same content there
is no duplication it's not two archives put together it's really one archive with two
kind of view of the same content and the last line is the exact command used to serve this
actual presentation.
Conclusion, this is a new way of thinking we could extract you could use the archive
directly instead of extracting it so we can reinvent the wall without thinking about using
directly the archive it's a new way of thinking it's generic it's a common base tool that
can add that can adapt to different usage but it's pretty new maybe some crash and you
can expect maybe some change in the specification.
Thank you.
Are there any questions?
How do you compare to GramFS?
Can you repeat the question?
Okay.
How does your format compare to GramFS?
I don't know.
I know about SquashFS.
The thing is that Jupyco is not a file system.
ARX is an archive to store files but Jupyco is not so Jupyco is more generic than GramFS
or SquashFS probably and ARX compared to SquashFS is half slower than SquashFS.
On the size ARX is better but on the performance is slower.
Any ideas on implementing this in other languages?
We could implement that in other languages.
Repeat the question because for the...
Could we re-implement this in other languages?
You could.
The specification is language-anoustic but I've just implemented the reference library
in Rust but the specification is public.
Sorry?
Jupyco is much slower than ARX in almost any kind of operation and is bigger than ARX also.
Thank you.