Okay, Yarmul Makenbach, his next talk is K-OX-SIT, the Refinery-lined Identity of this
Characterography.
Welcome him.
All right.
Is this working?
All right, awesome.
Thank you all for coming.
So, yeah, I'm Yarmul Makenbach.
I'm a scientist.
And I would like to give you a little non-technical introduction to my project called K-OX-SIT,
which is all about verifying online identity with cryptography.
And to start us off, I would actually like to review very quickly, like, how traditional
passports work.
So, yeah, you walk around with your little passport and you give it to the person who
needs to verify it.
And they will do their little verification with a computer.
And then, of course, after that, you can do whatever you came to do with your passport.
So, what I would like to briefly touch on is this third step, where a passport needs
to be verified by contacting the government that issued it.
In and of itself, the passport doesn't do that much.
It's just a piece of paper with maybe a little picture to identify the person, but not that
much more.
And, in fact, even if you do verify with the government, it checks the validity of the
document.
Is it still valid?
But it doesn't actually link it to the person, again, except for maybe the picture, but still.
So if we were...
So the online world, of course, is becoming more and more part of our lives.
So, how would identity work on the Internet online?
So, for me, of course, I would like to have it secure.
And with that, I actually mean verifiable, so that I can present my online passport and
prove to people that it's me and that not someone else is trying to claim that they're
me or anything like that.
I would like it to be anonymous.
We don't actually need this online identity to be the same as our real... in real life
identity.
In fact, I would go even further than that.
Fine, we can be multiple persons.
We can be a certain person that works in a certain domain.
We can be a person with a certain hobby.
And all these personas, they don't need to match a real identity.
And they should have their own identities that need to be maintained and be cared for
and be presented separately as identities.
I would like to be self-sovereign.
So people should be able to make their own passport.
They should be able to create it, update it, delete it, distribute it or keep it private
as much as they would like to... as they see fit.
And of course, I would like to see it decentralized.
There shouldn't be any gatekeepers.
It shouldn't run through a single big instances.
It should just be...
If you verify someone's identity, you need to be able to do it yourself on the spot without
having to trust another entity in the middle as much as possible.
And if you combine all this, I think it should represent what you do on the internet online
and not just like the traditional passport where you were born mostly.
So let's envision a little scenario.
Again, I said that this would be non-technical.
So we start off with Alice.
And if there's Alice, then of course there's Bob.
And they've spoken to each other for years now with, let's say Matrix, I don't know.
So they know who they are.
And again, they don't need to be...
These don't need to be like in real life identities.
They could be pseudonyms.
But they know who they are.
And on a certain day, Alice gets a message from a certain Bob 91 through a 7 network.
And of course Alice wants to know, you know, is this Bob?
Why are they using...
And if it is, you know, why are they using a different username?
That could have many reasons.
But again, is this the same actual person?
So luckily for Alice, in this case, she could ask Kieuxide.
And Kieuxide actually did a little check on both Bob on the Matrix networks and Bob on
91 on the XYZ network.
And it could actually verify that they were the same person.
So that's really a rough explanation.
So let's actually look at what happens to get to this point.
So what Bob did is he created a cryptographic key.
So cryptographic keys are represented by a fingerprint, a large string.
In this case, let's simplify it.
We'll just call it key 42.
And he treats the cryptographic key as like a sort of vault.
So he can put arbitrary data in there.
So in this case, he puts two links.
In this case, I use different accounts.
So maybe he refers to a Fediverse account.
And he refers to a Liberapay account.
Again, this could be any number of services that he chooses to enter in the vault.
And then he uploads a public key version of this to a so-called key server.
So a public key in this context, we can view it as like a glass vault.
Everybody can look inside, but no one can actually modify the contents.
Only Bob can, and Bob secured it through cryptography.
But everyone can actually look at this vault and look at the links that are inside.
And on that fateful day that we just discussed, Alice, so she went to this Kewksite page.
And she entered the number 42 because she knows that that's Bob's cryptographic key
identifier.
Again, they must have talked about this before or anything like that.
But so beforehand, she knew that this was Bob's key.
And so, well, Kewksite then goes and fetch this key from the key server, displays the
data.
But again, it's just displaying this as a list.
It doesn't know yet if it's actually verified because just claiming that you are someone,
a certain account on the internet, you know, that's not sufficient.
So what Kewksite then continues to do is that it will actually fetch some basic data, profile
data from this Fediverse account.
And inside this Fediverse account, it will actually find a link back to the key, in this
case the number 42.
And with this confirmation, it actually like knows that it verifies the identity.
This really is the basis on how Kewksite determines identity through bidirectional verification.
So the key links to a certain account on the internet and the account on the internet links
back to the key.
It does the same verification for the LiberiPay account.
It finds a link back to the key.
And so it has to be the same person that did both actions, put the link to the account
in the key and put the link to the key back in the account.
So that's how it looks in the stick figure mode.
This is an example of my account, for example.
And so, yeah, so this big string, that's actually what the 42 were presented in the stick figures.
And below are like all my identities, all my accounts that I linked in my profile.
And that actually have been verified by this website.
So what this website does, kewksite.org, in the end is basically just like a little automation
layer.
You could verify it yourself.
You could go to each of these profiles.
You could go to each of these links and just look for the reference back to my key, which
is written up there.
But yeah, that is kind of a tedious task.
So that's what Kewksite is designed to automate for you.
But Kewksite will always give you the option to verify for yourself.
So currently we do have a Kewksite mobile app.
It's available on FTROID for now only.
And it only does this profile verification mode functionality.
It doesn't do process profile creation yet.
For now, it requires you to use the command line, the GPG command line tool.
So that's not for everyone.
But yeah, we're working on making sure that the app can just make it, just like eBay's
used to do back in the day.
And of course, we would like to release it on different Play Store so that it's more
widely available.
But you can already play around with it right now.
I would like to briefly touch on what is next for Kewksite.
So we are trying to create this more easy kind of way to create profiles, not only using
openPGP.
Right now, everything is openPGP within Kewksite.
But soon you'll be able to use, like it says, minisign keys or SSH keys or whatever keys
we can find.
As I said before, I would also like to have more apps that can actually help you and guide
you in creating profiles so that it's not just for the very technical people among us,
but also just more general that people can enjoy online identity verification.
Another thing is for each website that we support, it needs to be programmed in manually.
We need to know the right APIs for every service.
So there's a lot of work that goes into finding out how to do that.
And of course, if a certain bird's-eye decides to close the API, well, yeah, that is overdone
for those verifications.
But that is their problem.
So we need to add support for more services and websites.
And we should also play around with creating new websites, creating more clients.
Clients can do a lot more things than just display a list of profiles.
And these are things that should be explored, like different ways of using identity online.
Actually I did so myself.
I created my own competitor, in this case named Kewksite Blue.
And I just, yeah, like it says, I built this in an afternoon.
And it's just that easy to get started with this ID, because in the end, it's just an
automation layer.
And yeah, it was just a little quick test for myself to see how easy it is to create
a new client.
So if anyone feels like playing around with this, go ahead.
It's a little fun, I guess.
And the other thing that I quickly wanted to mention is to go further and just display
a nice list of profiles and of online identities would be, what else can we do with online
identity?
And actually a few hours ago, there was this presentation by Pablo, where he discussed
creating CVs for developers, or in the end, for more people.
For now, developers, how can they share what they do online?
How can they share their free open source contributions on different platforms, on different
websites?
So that is something that maybe we could explore using Kewksite as a backend to know who has
done what and make a nice little CV of anyone's contributions to the open source world.
And with that, I would like to thank Victor and Berger and all the other people who have
contributed to the project so far and now for their funding.
And if you like the idea behind this, do reach out.
It's fun.
And we're always looking for more people to get this field further.
Thank you.
Thank you a lot for a nice presentation.
So you have now almost three minutes for questions.
And after that, you will ask them outside.
Anyone?
Questions?
So is the system dependent on a key server?
No.
So the question was, is it dependent on key servers?
In the end, no.
So key servers are just one way of promoting, distributing keys.
But there's also like WKD, WebKey directory where you can put keys on your own server.
You can also share keys directly, of course, between people.
Brilliant.
Okay.
So have you also included key signing so that you can create a web of trust?
No.
There have been talks about that, no?
Because it will be good.
Yeah, of course, like the web of trust discussion, you know, that's, yeah, people like it, people
don't like it.
If you can make that socially easy for people, it's a big deal.
Yeah.
That is also something to explore, the social aspect between having identities and, yeah,
because in the end, that's just another verification.
New people know each other and that generates trust.
Thanks.
There was a few questions there.
Yeah.
Is there a last question?
Because also in that direction, do you have support for blockchain names or something
like that, where the public key is on a chain?
It should probably be feasible.
We haven't looked that much into it yet.
For now, we're just focusing on the basic platforms where people are and where you can
just create an account and then, yeah, get some data back from an API.
It should probably be feasible as long as you can.
As long as you have an online entity where you can put arbitrary data and you have a
way of querying that data, everything's possible.
It's just a matter of, yeah, send us a PR or send us an issue and let's discuss and
we'll get it sorted.
Okay.
Thank you, Yarma.
Thank you for listening.