Okay.
A Libri-Saw project is creating free and open source ship design for a family of system
and ship products for powering routers, cell phones, laptops, your laptop maybe in the
future.
So it uses the power source set, augmented with 3D upcodes, 3D graphics and also video
acceleration upcodes and audio decoders and encoders.
So we need it for avoiding proprietary binary blobs and drivers and no reverse engineering
needed for supporting our hardware.
And well, it is hard to do so we do it by grants and donations.
We use a pool of community experts on Usenet, IRC, academia and also commercial partners
which will produce our ship as you see later.
So it is architecture is a traditional fetch the code issue and execute pipeline but to
increase performance use parallel decoders to decode instructions in advance, a vector
issue.
So one instruction can generate many results at one time utilizing the functions units
of the ship with the parallel execution units and managing all things scoreboard, dependency
tracking design.
Well we started from zero from the Power Inza instruction set specification as published
by the OpenPower Foundation which is open standard.
You can submit extensions to it and that is one of the reasons we chose the Power Architecture.
So the Power has this big manual with all the assembly instructions and all these formats
and we take these formats, these tables and auto generate from by Python, a Python decoder
from these specifications.
And the specification of the Power Architecture also has a pseudo code and with this pseudo
code which is for humans but we use it for auto translation to a simulator, Python simulator.
And we start from the beginning just simulating instructions in software then you use the
simulator to test against this one, the last one and the harder simulator will verify against
the software simulator and finally FPGA and even an ASIC.
Let's jump here.
So this is like an, imagine you have an adding instruction coming in and the LU has to process
it but before processing it, it has to receive operands like add what?
A and B. But A and B can be the result of a previous instruction which is still being
processed.
So it has to wait, wait where?
In here and here and here and when it has to have a read the transaction, read the transaction,
and it will fill the buffers then the adding instructions can proceed and it will generate
a result and condition codes but maybe you cannot write them right now because you'll
overwrite another instruction so we wait here and here also and this has to be managed.
So one of my tasks is to simulate this to see if it works well and do what?
Formal verification which is so, so good, so, so interesting.
With normal simulation you just throw random inputs maybe on some test cases but how do
you know that you didn't hit a corner case?
Well informal verification is like it's try everything at once.
Usually it starts from a bad result that you don't want to have and it shows you the input
which reaches that bad result.
Yes.
So that's the beauty of the thing.
We get a simple core.
First we do not do these function units all in parallel.
We just use one to test all of this is working.
Put it here and then we read the instruction, decode the instruction and then run the instruction.
Terribly slowly but we validate the function units and the decoder.
Next step which we did already is we vectorize it.
So we put a read 64 because there are 32 instructions.
You add a vector prefix to them and this vector prefix will tell you to read a predicate so
from the vector you say no I don't want all of them.
I want the even ones or the odd ones or the ones with pass the test like if then else
but vectorized.
And then you run the vector loop.
So one instruction again can generate many can take the place of many many instructions.
And well now we go to the next steps.
We have these working now we have to do it in parallel.
We want to have performance.
It is working now performance.
So to be performant we need to while we execute in one instruction you are decoding the next
one and you are fetching the next next one.
And there is a jump instruction by chance and it doesn't match what you are fetching
you have to reset the pipeline.
Yes.
Test well where you are right now we have a development environment that any of you
can download and test in your computer you can do it is run in a shoot and you can do
make test to run the tests and if you have an FPGA board you can compile the bit stream
and put it to a supported board and we even did a execute.
Well for the execute we need the PDK which is a process development kit that the factories
don't give it to you freely so that part is done by a third party we don't touch property
stuff but while it was done yes and we hope in the future to have a FPGA with it.
So the FPGA is booted we have a bare metal like Arduino like FPGA running Zephyr quite
fast was ported with network so networking was proved and the Linux with a serial console.
Yes.
We have the test silicon with that little simple core and it is being carefully tested
because you have few chips produced not to burn them so they are tested in our app.
Yes the new tools part is on the way with the new instructions vector instructions already
and the new instructions been submitted to the open power foundation for standardization
and we are being are parting algorithms cryptographic algorithms and multimedia etc.
So what you aim you aim to port and boot a Linux distro in the future eventually we want
to have a filter change this is seen in the new tools with vectorization they find these
stations to include the text your app codes for 3D acceleration so you notice there will
not be a GPU the instructions the CPU will be the GPU and well we need the hardware and
software developers and testers and also well documentation optional no OK.
So who will build the chips well you just have research money right.
Well we'll produce thousands of chips for the market.
Well we are partner with red semiconductor which is have the mission of producing these
chips producing a powerful power efficient chip with our car.
So if you see some of them and some of us some of them with this logo on the shirts
you can talk to them here.
Hello David hello people.
So that's it thank you very much.
Thank you for the stone.
Thank you very much for the presentation there's a few minutes left for questions.
So in the back of the room I see someone waving just a moment.
Thanks for your presentation.
You said that you had some test chips going on.
What's the status of the bring up like how far did you get in the bring up process.
OK we know the clock is working it has well the ASEQ it's not only for Libri-SOC but for
the academic institution to test their design so they are testing this clock generation
and well we know the clock generation works.
Just that.
So maybe anyone else with a question.
OK thank you for your attention.