Thank you. I'm Aurora from the University of Murcia.
And I'm Michael from the University of Passau.
And we will be presenting the NDSR 10-up Web Search.U projects.
Two sister initiatives for a paradigm change in open search and discovery on the internet.
We will have a common introduction and then each of us will delve into projects that we
are involved in. And a short disclaimer before we start.
In the last two days at Fosten we have heard a lot about personal lifetime projects.
This is quite different because it's not personal.
These are European institutions involved and it's not lifetime.
But these projects they are just starting up and have nice ideas and require your attention
and contribution. So NDSR 10-up Web Search is a European project
that will welcome entrepreneurs, tech tapes, developers and socially engaged people that
have challenging ideas about the way that we will search and discover information and
data on the internet. So basically we will fund projects that are
focusing on several topics that I will explain in a minute.
And they are compliant with the European values of openness, transparency, privacy and trust.
The applicants can be natural persons and organizations and they can apply individually
or as a consortium of three members per team.
Open Web Search is a project funded by the EU and has the goal of developing an open
European infrastructure for a Web Search. There are several research and computing centers
involved and the project started in September last year and has a timeframe of three years.
It's quite interesting that it's the first project which is funded by the EU and has
the goal of developing Europe's own Web Index. And for those who don't know, a Web Index
is a data structure which allows the vast access of Web Data.
It is the fundamental core of all current search engines.
And it enables the development of all kind of Web Search and Web Data retrieval services.
So for us, let me present you the project partners. We are Link Novane, Aarhus University,
the University of Murcia, OWU2 and Family Box. These are some of our faces.
We will organize five different open calls and we welcome these innovative projects.
We will provide them financial support up to €150,000.
As well, we will not only provide financial but also technical business and innovation
support and the projects are expected to take 12 months.
The first open call, which is already closed, the evaluation is ongoing and it was a technological-based
call, meaning that we were looking for products, finalized products.
And then we will select 9 to 10 projects in the topics that you see on the screen, based
voice assistants, NLP, semantic analysis, social computing and data visualization.
But let me delve a little bit more on the second open call topics which may cut your
attention. I hope you can resonate with some of them.
The second open call will open in April, 1 April.
It's a little bit more research-oriented but please have a look because we have plenty
of space for everything.
And let me explain each topic. The first one is power cognitive search by reinforcement
learning. Basically, we look for mechanisms of self-learning
and all kinds of algorithms that can contribute to a reinforcement learning system that is
able to learn with the interactions how to choose the right data and algorithms in order
to make any search more relevant towards the objective of it.
Then the second topic is machine-based data, Internet of Things data.
Basically we look for algorithms for search and pattern discovery that are adapted or
that can adapt to IoT characteristics which means we will look for edge computing, algorithms
that can deal with time series, with events, with different geo-localizations and so on.
We have also AI-based taxonomies. We look for the automatic creation and expansion of
existing taxonomies that are machine-based, machine interpretable semantics by using AI
techniques. Basically, we want to model the interdependency
among new concepts so we want to adapt to the dynamic and the dynamicity of the data.
The next topic is network analysis. Basically, we want to find other ways to create knowledge
graphs which are an interlinked network of distributed resources that can be searched.
We can do this looking for the objective can be to make them more scalable, to test the
quality of the creative models, to create different semantics, to make them compliant
with diversity and dynamicity of data and so on.
Then we have AI-based search tools and content generators. As you know, nowadays AI-based
content generators are quite popular. Here I have some names that have been coming up
in FOSM many times, CheckTPT, GitHub Copilot, CopyAI. We welcome projects that can help
evaluate the privacy of these kind of tools. Also, look for research and technological
gaps on them as well as the completeness of their answers.
Then we have the topic of ethics in search and discovery. We want to have projects that
specifically focus on testing that the developments of search and discovery are compliant with
human rights, that they are not biased towards minorities, towards gender, so that they promote
equality but also private and they take care of the confidentiality.
Finally we have new ways of discovering and accessing information which can be a broad
topic so that we don't leave anything behind. How are we going to do that? We are going
to provide technology mentoring and advice on technologies to access store managed data
and also on algorithms and platforms that are tailored to the projects. We are going
to leverage the ReachOut beta testing platform for beta testing campaigns. Then we are going
to link the projects to different standards and promote the conversations with different
foundations that will be related to them. We will have a program for market readiness.
We will create workshops for pitch training so that they can try to pitch their solution
or their project to potential investors and users. Business modeling, advice and coaching.
As for innovation, we will give information about which kind of open source license they
can have, they can use, how to manage it and how to make their research and their solutions
reproducible, so following open science principles. So as to conclude from my part, the next three
years there will be five open calls that will challenge the way that we search and discover
information on the internet. We have synergies with the NDI mission of looking for a more
human centric internet. These are our core values, open source, contributions to the
wider community, collaboration and open science principles as well as transfer challenges
that include sustainability and equality. I give the floor to my colleague.
So now switching to the second system project, Open Web Search. As I said before, there are
several computing and research centers involved in the project and it's good this way because
all of these have different competences like universities or businesses and this underlines
one specific point about the project. In a contrary to the web index which is operated
by Google for example, this project does not follow a centralized approach but it tries
to build up a web index collaboratively and distributed among several European institutions.
Otherwise, it would just not be possible to build up a web index from scratch. I will
keep the motivation short because it should be clear why it is a good idea to have own
a web index in Europe. The first thing is the imbalance in the search engine market.
There are four big global web indexes out there from big tech companies and this dominance
of these companies has a lot of negative effects on the critical infrastructure web search
so to say. The solution is to strive for more plurality. Another thing is that web data
is a driver for innovations. An example, just one out of many examples that has drawn a
lot of attention lately is the training of large language models such as JetGPT which
works on its basis with web data. The project goals are developing the core of an open web
index so two remarks on this point. This will be done with open source and open configuration
and it is not expected that at the end of the three years of the project there will
be a production ready index. But the goal is to have an index which contains at least
50% of all text web pages and then that can be worked on and that shows as a prototype
that it is possible to create it collaboratively and distribute it among several institutions.
Another goal is to build an ecosystem around the index and make it publicly available in
this way. As I said before, it serves as a feasibility study in some way to show that
it is possible to do it collaboratively and that is why along the way it should be established
a network among European infrastructure partners. The overall vision of the project is to give
open access for innovators and businesses and researchers on web data to enable them
to build new business ideas for example or to work on their ideas on web search and web
analysis. As for the NGI search project, there are also ways to contribute to openwebsearch.eu
through third party calls. There will be three public calls with a fixed amount of funding
and the first of them focuses on the legal aspects of the project. There are two tracks.
The first one focuses contributions on legal and business and social aspects of web search
in general and the second track focuses on the legal compliance of the crawling so the
acquisition of the data from the internet which is then stored in the index. This call
will open on the first of March this year. There are also other opportunities to contribute
which is covered by the upcoming calls and this course overview of the architecture should
just give you a hint on where these contributions can be located. If you have an idea on how
to develop a search and discovery application, this can be done for example as a vertical
search engine on top of the web index infrastructure or it can be a content analysis method which
enriches the data which is then stored in the index. As a conclusion, the openwebsearch.eu
project wants to open up web search and strides for more plurality to give new business ideas
a chance and new alternative search engines a chance. Therefore, the project partners
collaborate and build up a European open web index which is then publicly available. For
researchers, innovators and businesses there is the possibility to contribute either by
developing your own business model which sets upon the open web index or by involving in
one of the three public calls. The first one of them, as I said, opens on the first of
March. So thanks for your attention and we're open for questions.