So the next presentation is a NimixNet from Yoon Hockblood.
So welcome, Yoon.
Yeah, thank you very much.
It's great to be here.
The presentation all seems to be working.
Right, so I'll talk about Nim, title is Intro to a New Anonymous Communication Network.
It's quite a lot of overlap with the previous presentation about the concepts involved.
And who am I?
My name is Yoon Hockblood, or sometimes I go by just John for simplicity.
I'm a Sweden developer, I spend my days writing Rust, backend type things.
I used to do C++ and scientific computing in a previous life.
Yeah, live in Stockholm.
Yeah, that's me.
Right, so the NimixNet.
What's the NimixNet?
So the basics, I mean, this is obviously free software.
The source code is available on GitHub over there.
It's a Apache license, it's mostly written in Rust.
All the backend stuff is written in Rust.
Some of the frontend things is TypeScript.
This was in the past, this has been funded by some EU projects.
And currently there is a Switzerland-based startup who does the majority of the development.
But yeah, it's an open project and of course we welcome public contributions.
And yeah, it's quite deeply rooted in university as well, in university research.
We have some work-class researchers associated with the project.
So the concepts aren't things that we came up with ourselves.
This is state-of-the-art research.
Right, so what is the problem that we're trying to solve?
We had the usual suspects, the government surveillance and surveillance capitalism.
And wish of these two is a problem, very much depends on where in the world you are.
In some parts of the world these things aren't that big of a concern.
For other people this is serious matter.
This is with grave concern to some people, depending on who you are and where you live.
And what is the aspect that we try to tackle here?
Because there's a lot of privacy platforms that sort of...
...to sort of...
...tries to attack this challenge from different perspectives.
The Nim-Max Net is a network layer or a transport layer thing.
And the main challenge to be focused on is that it has become clear in the sort of the last 10 years that...
...there's now so much surveillance going on and there are some entities that collect so much data...
...on a global scale that they almost get some sort of like a god's eye view of the network.
They can monitor the network on a planet scale and they can correlate.
They can correlate using leaked metadata, your transmission patterns, your packet sizes, timings.
They can do end-to-end correlations even though your data is sent entirely encrypted the whole way or obfuscated.
But still if you can sort of monitor at all endpoints, you can sort of still draw conclusions.
You can identify who talks to who and as we know who talks to who is sometimes more important than what they say from a sort of surveillance perspective.
So that's the sort of the angle, the challenge that we try to tackle with this.
So now I'm sort of taking a step back here. So I'm referring to the Nim platform.
So which is then I use this quote here, a decentralized incentivized mixnet plus prior credentials.
And sort of yeah, my talk here will be to try to unpack what all of this means.
And we're going to start and with what I think is sort of the core part is the mixnet, the word in the middle there.
I think if you use something like Tor as a starting point, that's sort of a very good first step to understand what it is.
And just like Tor and just like the previous talk, it's an overlay network in the same way as ITP uses...
onion routing where all packets are wrapped in layers of encryption to sort of to hide the fact, to hide the end destination of each packet.
It's based on the Lupix design. If you know a little bit of mixnets, you probably have heard about Lupix.
I put in a few citations here at the bottom if you want to read a bit more about these things.
It uses Sphinx packets so that the idea is that all packets are wrapped into these identically looking and identically behaving packets.
To sort of to hide some sizes and timings and also each packet as it moves through because you know,
mixnet is very much what it sounds. It's data, you send through data, multiple hops, you mix data as much as you can through a cloud of nodes.
At each node, I'm going to have some pictures on the next slide to illustrate it better, but yeah, on each hop in the network,
you add things like random timings which effectively reorders traffic, you add cover traffic,
which cover traffic can appear in many ways either like between nodes, but also for example,
if you use a client to connect to network to transmit data, you emit Sphinx packets at a
steady average rate. So it's not a steady rate, but it's like this is probabilistic how you send the
packets, but you send a steady stream of packets either fake or real ones. So when you have real
data to send, you just fill up the packet stream, the packet they send out fill up with real data.
So from the outside, you can't tell when you're actually sending, when you're bursting data.
You attach Serbs or single use reply blocks in your packets so that when you if you make a request
across the network to get something back, you attach these headers, these metadata so that
the response can be sort of layer encrypted and sent back so that the other side, the server
doesn't know where the end destination is. So you hide your identity, but you still allow the other
side to reply back to you. It's a picture, the first step here, the first one there, ordinary VPN,
and a VPN doesn't give you any anonymity, it just moves trust. So the guy in the middle there,
you can still see where data is coming from, where data is going. The second one, you have things
like Tor where you have these nodes in the middle where you open up a circuit through the sort of
swarm of nodes and you pump data through. And here you have MixNet set up where you, in each
packet is mixed individually so you don't open up a circuit like Tor for example, you send up,
each packet is sent as an individual pass-through. And the idea here, the crucial thing is that the
on the other side, you see these packets there, they are colored white now instead of red and
they're the same size. And you shouldn't be able to tell, you can't correlate who's like the data
on the other side compared to on the sender side, which you can in many other systems, because you
can't correlate transmission patterns, timing, sizes. So even if you can monitor all the data,
all the exit data from this MixNet cloud, you still can't correlate who talks to who.
That's sort of the key thing here. And yeah, so if we go back then to this quote,
so decentralized, incentivized MixNet plus price credentials, what do we mean by incentivized?
By incentivized, we mean that the network directory which keeps track of all the
MixNodes and the gateways are a bit like exit nodes in Tor. They are constantly being monitored.
Oh yeah, so the network directory is effectively a set of validators running a consensus protocol
and they keep track of all the MixNodes, how well they mix traffic, how well they
contribute capacity to network, giving them limbs for it, which in turn can be turned around and
used to acquire bandwidth credentials, coconut credentials, is the academic term.
And the idea is that we also, because this is always a problem when you have something like this,
with volunteers you only get so far, anonymity or privacy loves company, you want to disappear in
crowds. So you want to encourage people to provide capacity to the network at the same time as they're
using it. That's the idea. Because otherwise it becomes difficult to scale up above a sort of
various base level. But if you want to make this available for the broader public, you need more
capacity. And this is a way that we hope we can achieve this. And these price credentials,
the idea is that you break the linkability between your identity and your right to use the service.
And it's a very deep topic on its own. Here's the citation. There are some cryptographic
buzzwords here as well, listed and re-randomizable means that if you use the same bandwidth
credential multiple times, it's indistinguishable from multiple people using different credentials
from the person redeeming this. But yeah, the idea is you want to break the link between
your identity and your right to use something. And yeah, okay, so the first word there, decentralized.
It's not too much to add there. I mean, we have a running network. It's 500 mex nodes currently.
And yeah, the vision is that this becomes sort of self-running. It should be like,
it shouldn't happen. We won't have an anti-fragile funding model. We don't want it to be reliant on
a specific company or some funding body or donations or anything. We want this to have robust,
robustly running on its own, run by the community entirely, long-term. That's sort of the
division here. Even though currently we have a startup that sort of does the most of the
development, we should in turn, like long-term, we should be able to hand this off as sort of the ID.
There's a picture. So this is all running currently. This thing that is currently sort of in
deployment or sort of being rolled out or these credentials currently is free to use the main
network. We have all these clients, there's a client, there's a Wasm client, there's a
native running client exposing a WebSocket, the mixed nodes up there. When you use a user,
you connect to the gateway, which is like entry and exit nodes for Tor. You mix the traffic,
you exit on the gateway, you can have service providers. There's the set of validators keeping
track of the other nodes in the system. Yeah. There's a lot of taking here, probably a lot of
a lot of details there. I'm not sure it's all visible towards the end, but yeah, that's pretty
much it. Thank you for your time. Yeah, thank you a lot for a nice talk. Yeah, thank you for
listening. And I think that have some time. So theoretically, they could spend it asking a
question at least for two minutes here and then after it, we can discuss it outside.
Hi, can you imagine the NIMP framework also to be integrated into another proof of stake based
cryptocurrency as a backend in the future? Maybe what did he say first?
Can you imagine that the main part of the NIMP framework, like the mixed nodes and everything
around it can also be attached to an existing proof of stake based other cryptocurrency that
is not currently part of your ecosystem? Well, so I mean, a big use case of this is that
it's this is sort of on the network layer. So that means it's a big use case is you have all
these other privacy systems where in this crypto space where they have this privacy preserving
services, but they still leak metadata at the bottom layer, you still leak metadata when you
broadcast transactions and things like this. So I think if this were like to integrate this in other
systems in this space, then it will be in that that layer, sort of the transport layer. So yeah,
so there's a lot of potential for integrating with other privacy platforms, I think. And
then in general with these, I mean, there are a lot of privacy platforms. And I think what we need
is a sort of a robust ecosystem. There is no single solution that solves all our problems.
We need a robust ecosystem for different solutions for different types of problems or different
categories of problems. So I mean, I don't see this as a competitor to other systems. It's more
they complement each other. For example, like when you had this, you had random delays, for example,
that of course, you know, you have means you sort of compromise, you give up a bit of latency,
which is, you know, works very well for asynchronous communication, but
might not work so well for other categories of applications. So I think sometimes like this,
this is also the complement store, it doesn't replace the store, it sort of complements it.
Yeah. Okay.
There's any more questions? Just grab me afterwards.
Just go there and ask questions.