We're all good.
Sorry.
Yeah, I remember.
Hit the button when you're ready.
Yeah.
And help yourself to water as well.
Yeah, sure.
Check, check, check.
All right, all right, all right.
Hello, everyone.
First time actually I'm talking about this project on a conference.
So, FOSDAM here is it first.
The images are generated with Mid-Journey.
So I'm going to talk about this self-hosting for non-crowders.
Somewhat of a click-by title, but we'll get there.
I have a question for you all.
Did anyone try?
Raise your hand if you tried hosting Mastodon on your own.
A Mastodon server.
All right, all right.
We have a couple of hands.
Now, keep your hand up.
Only lower your hand if you think the process was easy or simple or enjoyable.
Okay.
All right.
So, this is the Mastodon docs on how to host it.
This is just one page.
This is actually not even the hosting part.
This is just preparing the machine.
So, out of this room here, I guess three or four people tried that,
and I can understand them.
It's not easy.
And this doesn't just apply to Mastodon.
It applies to many apps, actually, that you would want to self-host,
many open source apps, because apps are getting complex.
Does this not work?
Yeah, you're working for the sex.
I'm sorry.
The other one is much better.
Oh, really?
Should that try it?
Will there be...
Thank you.
Does this work better?
Yes, it works better.
Okay, all right.
So, yeah, so you saw the huge instruction.
You know, what we want is everyone to be able to host Mastodon,
because that's kind of the point of Mastodon, right?
It's decentralized.
There's Docker out there that many, many projects use to simplify
this process of hosting something.
Maybe we could host Mastodon with Docker.
So this would be the Docker setup.
I guess it doesn't look that much easier.
And I mean, imagine...
I assume that most of us here are technical people,
but imagine if you don't know how to use a command line.
That would just be impossible.
You can forget about it.
You would use someone else's Mastodon server.
So what if I tell you there is a way, actually,
for people who don't even know how to use a command line
to spin up a Mastodon instance?
And this is how it would look like.
This GIF is a bit sped up,
but it actually is close to the normal speed.
What's happening here is I'm entering a couple config values.
The Mastodon is deployed on my machine anywhere I want,
where I have this garden set.
Mastodon is deployed.
Streaming service is deployed.
Configured.
Sitekick service is deployed.
Postgres database is deployed.
Configured.
Redis service is deployed.
As you see, Mastodon has a lot of services.
And we're done.
We have a Mastodon instance now.
This would be the...
It's actually open on the Internet.
I host a couple of those myself with this method.
And this would be the URL that I end up having.
And of course, you can have it on your own domain.
If you own a domain, you would have it in Mastodon,
let's say, on your domain.
So the process, without regard to me speeding out the GIF,
took one minute and 44 seconds.
I counted.
And you can do this locally on your own machine.
If you want, you can do this in the cloud.
If you do this in the cloud, that would be even a bit easier,
but we'll talk about it.
So this is called Gardens.
It's an app.
It's a platform that I'm making.
It's open source under AGPL.3.
And it's not the only one.
Not the only self-hosting platform out there
that really simplifies deployments.
Actually, this project is based on another one called CapRower.
I don't know if anyone in the room knows it.
Okay.
It has 100 million plus Docker pools.
So a very established project.
It's out there for many years already.
It was called Captain Duck Duck previously.
But CapRower was meant for hobbyists
and kind of for testing.
Our aim with Gardens is to bring it more to the organizations.
So get it to a level where it's actually the stuff that you deploy,
like Mastodon or anything,
is you can use it instead of a SaaS service, for example,
in an organizational setting.
So the technical part of this is roughly this.
It's a web app.
The web app, actually, you deploy on your own server.
So even the web app is on your own server.
We have a website for non-technical people
where they can connect their cloud account
to deploy to their server.
But after they do that, everything else happens on their machine.
This web app talks to Docker API.
It uses Docker Compose, which actually you cannot use via API.
So there is some processing there to deploy containers for these apps.
So, for example, like I was showing,
these various services that Mastodon spins up,
they're all in separate containers.
And, of course, you can not just have Mastodon deployed like this.
You can deploy Gitsy Meet.
You can deploy WordPress.
I'm going to show a couple more examples.
And then we use Nginx to show these apps on the web
and allow the actual end user to interact with them.
Now, what I mentioned, for non-technical users,
right now we support DigitalOcean.
If, let's say, you don't know how to use a command line,
but you want to have gardens on your, let's say, VPS or your machine,
you just, there's an old flow.
You connect to DigitalOcean,
and then there's a no-code process where you spin up gardens,
and then from gardens you can use it.
But there's also a local process where you just run one line in the CLI.
You pull basically the gardens container,
and then gardens does everything from there.
It doesn't actually, yeah.
I mean, it talks back to us to get the list of apps available,
but our end goal is for it not even to talk back,
to kind of really be isolated in your environment.
So these are just some examples of the apps we have in gardens.
There's really a lot of good open source products that are coming out recently.
Of course, there are established players like WordPress.
There is stuff to replace social media, like PeerTube.
Here are just some examples of what those replace.
Of course, with Mastodon you can replace something like Twitter.
Penpot here at the bottom left, you can replace Figma.
They actually had to talk previously at the conference.
Bizro or No-code DB can replace Airtable.
GtMute can replace Zoom.
Outline and replace Confluence.
And there's actually other alternatives there.
So you can choose whatever open source product you want to host.
We have about 130 apps, a bit more, available right now
that you can self-host with one click.
But there is also an option to deploy your own apps
or even connect to GitLab, let's say, have a bit of CI CD going,
if you're more technical.
As I mentioned, the process of spinning up those apps
is based on Docker Compose mostly.
There are options to even spin up from Tar Archive and so on,
but this is like the main method.
Yeah, we do some processing of Docker Compose files
that are taken from official repositories of these app developers
and then we just spin this up for you.
So, Gardens is just one example.
I'm talking about it because I'm making it.
Capraour is what we forked because it's very reliable,
very nice service.
Coolify is a newer service, similar to that.
The main difference, I'd say, is for the proxy,
we use Nginx, they use traffic.
And Unihost is a bit different,
but it covers the same use case to self-host stuff.
It's a bit different because it's a Debian distribution,
so you have that on kind of replace your operating system,
whereas Gardens, Capraour, and Caulify,
they are all apps that you can put right now on Ubuntu, Debian,
I think on CentOS, it works as well.
I actually got it working on macOS,
but that's more experimental.
So why do we even want to self-host?
Let's go back to that.
I'd say actually, if we want software freedom,
which is, I guess, the point of open source in a lot of ways,
you have to be able to self-host.
But as we can see from here, you know,
just several people hosted Mastodon, let's say.
I imagine many more here use Mastodon.
It's kind of like if you're not using this freedom
or if you're not able to because you can't handle the technical side
because it's too difficult, that kind of defeats the purpose, right?
So if you cannot host, you don't really have freedom
if you have it technically or formally, let's say.
So I'd argue that this not having freedom is bad,
but also bad not just in a kind of ideological way,
but also in a competitive way.
If open source wants to be able to compete with all these SaaS apps out there,
because this is like something that open source has
that proprietary apps just don't have,
and it's an unfair advantage.
I think, I believe that right now, organizations,
how they use it is they use proprietary SaaS by default.
They self-host when they are really worried about privacy
or there's some kind of sovereignty concerns or something.
They don't care about open source.
And how it should be is you self-host instead of SaaS by default,
but then you choose a SaaS where it's too complex
or you want the scale or there's some specific requirements
or if you want to support developers because that's one way they earn
and they can financially support the development.
So to bring some numbers in there,
I've been hanging out on Reddit self-hosted, sub-Reddit,
and I found the statistics.
So for the past like seven years,
the number of people there skyrocketed
to more than 200,000 people on the sub-Reddit.
So it looks like people are interested actually in hosting their stuff.
But I also run a poll with 1,250 participants about that number
where I found out that people on that sub-Reddit,
they don't really self-host, you know, anything business critical, so to say,
or anything for their organization, anything for productive use,
or at least not a lot of them.
So about only 100 people self-host, let's say, Nextcloud or something,
but most of them self-host for media,
so let's say for movies or something, or for personal use.
So maybe something for their smart home.
So that I think is a pity,
but I cannot understand that, why people are not self-hosting.
Because it's complex, like we discussed, for organizations.
Because it's complex, but also because of these issues.
You don't just want to spin up an app.
There's also a part that comes after you deploy,
which is about maintenance,
which is about making sure that your instance is secure,
and if you get a lot of users, you also want to scale.
You want to have an option to scale.
So how we deal with that is for maintenance,
for each app, for each service that I was showing you,
let's say for Macedon, you can view logs in the graphical interface,
so you don't have to accession to your instance to view logs.
We keep a version history.
We track analytics for instance with net data,
so you can see, let's say, how much CPU is utilized,
how much RAM is utilized, so you can kind of check the health,
and net data actually provides nice notifications,
so you can even get notifications where you want,
or have a webhook to get updated when, let's say,
you're running out of CPU or RAM.
For security, we covered that with automatic SSL for all apps.
You can force it. You can force HTTPS.
We have basic auth, so that we do with Let's Encrypt.
For scalability, actually, that's the part I love the most.
If you have a lot of users, you can scale,
either by adding more instances of the same app on the same machine,
and Nardance will redistribute automatically the load,
or you can scale by adding more machines into a Docker Swarm.
So we support Docker Swarm. This is the same for Caprover.
So I'd say people want to self-host, but it's hard,
and we need to help them.
So otherwise, they just use SaaS, like currently,
and this is one way to do it.
You can help this effort by, if you're a developer,
maintaining Docker Compose files, or documentation,
just a way to self-host for your application.
If you're a sysadmin or a DevOps, you can think about providing
a platform like this to your organization,
so that people in your organization can spin something up
without having to bother you.
And you can, everyone here, of course,
should use open source instead of SaaS,
and you should try self-hosting.
If you find self-hosting hard,
you can check out some of those self-hosting platforms.
You can, of course, host not on AWS or something,
but you can use some of those hosters.
Cloud68 had been giving a talk here a bit earlier.
Chateauans is a French network of good hosters.
Librehost is another one.
So look at other hosting solutions.
Thank you, and yeah, have a good rest of the conference.
Thank you.