Thank you.
So, it's time. Okay. Hello, everyone. So we have here
Benjamin Jamie who will be sharing should there be a
standard and Libra localization. Ideas on how to make it easy
for translators to contribute to any FOSS project they like.
Thank you, Benjamin.
Thank you.
Thank you for the applause. I didn't deserve that yet.
Definitely. Thank you for being in such a large count here.
So, I'm Benjamin. I work in Weblade. I do the talking there.
And you can also meet Michal in this lovely hoodie here.
And he's the mind behind the coat and everything. And the
founder.
I won't be talking much about Weblade here. That's the talk
tomorrow in translation's dev room. Here I would like to share
a story and kick off something probably that could become a
standard in Libra localization.
Because at the moment, it's nothing like that there.
At first, I would like to talk a short start of Weblade story.
It doesn't start like a master minded start-up plan that will
get a lot of money and conquer the world of the localization.
No, that's other companies. We are Libra software from the
start. And Michal actually started it when he was working
at SUSE. And now SUSE people are very proud that they started
it during the SUSE hack week 12 years ago. Sorry, 11 years ago.
And for a long time, this is the office. It was actually the
office at the top of the building of those large concrete
buildings you have around the Czech Republic built in
socialism. And when you needed an elevator there, there was
those like small on some side of the building. And then you
put all the machinery for your elevator. But it's not needed
now. So all the machinery is downstairs in the shaft. And
Michal had his office on the top of the building. And it's like
three to four meters or something like that. And that's
how he started it. And it was not aimed to do something that
will be master minded and well-
supported. And it was a very good idea to do that. And it
was a very good idea to do that. And it was a very good idea to
do that. And it was a very good idea to do that. And it was
master minded and well-prepared for all the use cases. It was
just in the start, the use case that Michal wanted something
better than Puthu, which was very popular tool but no longer
maintained. And something that's very tightly integrated with
Puthu is that much of the money will work. And you are a
developer. So you connect Weblight to your version control
system and it just works. You don't have to care about
anything. And then everything is in the editor. And you know
localization editors from Weblight and from other similar
tools. And then more and more big open source projects and
other companies went to ask Michal, hey, we would like to use
it. Can we pay you for supporting it? And yeah, that's
how Weblight started getting bigger. And these days there
are large or small Libra projects that are using Weblight.
And oh, sorry, I forgot to put a pen pot logo there. We'll do
tomorrow. But there is Kaledis. And more and more Libra
projects started using it. And it became some sort of a go
for tool. And then Fedora came, I think, three years back to
us and migrated all their stuff from Xanata, from their
original platform they created to Weblight because Xanata was
like we don't have time for that. That's not our core of
business. So we won't use Weblight. And that's how we
realized that this is maybe the thing that will be happening
more. And it became our responsibility. We took very
seriously to give the tool to the communities that they can
use happily and they can contribute to. But it's still
just one platform. It's Weblight. And we created last
year a page called Discover Weblight. So if you are on a
hosted Weblight, if you have your projects on a hosted Weblight
which is the largest instance of Weblight on the Internet, it's
easier to search there. And it will be even easier throughout
this year because of the development. And if you host
yourself your instance, we wanted to give the users a place
where they can come and search through all the Weblight
instances that are open to contribute to this page. So at
the end of the project, you can find if the project is using
Weblight, you have this place and you can search for your
project name, let's say, and you will be guided to the right
place. And you can contribute to the localizations there. But
what about if the project, because there are so many
projects in the world that are not using Weblight yet or they
are not using Weblight, it's always your choice. What do you
use in your community? Sorry. So there became an idea. And I
think two years back, and that's really important to say, the
time frame, I was speaking with Dwayne. Dwayne is a wonderful
guy who works with the Weblight. And he is a great developer
to translate toolkit, which is one of the core components that
Weblight uses to work with translation files. And Dwayne
is, yeah, very talkative like I am. So we were talking a lot.
And then I told him, yeah, and maybe there should be a way for
like one place possibly federated,
so it's not in one central place,
where I as a translator of a Libra software,
that's not technically savvy,
and I want to contribute the time
to the project of my choice,
but I don't want to search through readme's and wikis
because every project has its own different way,
or there is no information,
and you have to really dig hard to find it,
or if you are at FOSDEM,
you can walk around the booth
and see a little bit like a little advertisement
or small stand that says this project
is localized on WebLite,
but if you are in the online world,
you will spend usually a lot of time to find
where is the right place
to localize your favorite software,
and I told that to Dwayne,
and Dwayne said, oh yeah, I had that idea a while before,
and I have it very roughly specified,
and we were talking more,
and then he sent like nine pages long,
nice specification of how it could look like
and how it could work,
and there are so many other features
that we would like to have there,
but that was two years ago,
and nothing happened,
because there is no time to do that
in WebLite team,
and it should be a community thing.
It shouldn't be something that WebLite says,
this is the thing, how you should do it,
and everybody should use it.
It can be like that,
but we are at FOSDEM,
there are so many wonderfully skilled people
that may be interested in not only helping
with the actual development,
but also sharing their ideas,
and maybe they,
because it's such obvious thing that's missing,
maybe there are so many people
that already have similar ideas
or some kind of specification,
and I would like to use this talk
if you have an idea,
I just want to kick it off,
we are not working on it yet,
we just want to connect,
we want to discuss,
and maybe in a year on next FOSDEM,
we will have something like that,
and a lot of projects could use that,
or every project on FOSDEM,
and it shouldn't be just about WebLite,
it should be maybe a file,
like you have a license file in your repository,
or a readme file,
that can be indexed by some tool,
so if I want to have an instance,
a server where I could guide,
let's say I'm a localization lab,
or some other lovely group of people
that wants to localize open source software,
they can use some kind of tool,
put it on their website on their own server,
and tell if you have your time,
select a language you want to contribute to,
and find your project,
and this might should index those readmes,
or translation MD files,
from not only GitHub and GitLab,
but probably more and more.
Can it be done?
Probably yes, it will have some limits,
it probably won't scan all the repositories in the world,
that's not possible,
but maybe we can make something bigger
than Discover Web Light,
that's universal use for everyone.
What should it do is to guide the translator
to the right platform, to the right place,
because if I'm a translator,
I don't know all the technical way of the localization,
which can be made easier
by localization management software like Web Light.
I just want to translate my hello to hello,
and that's it.
It should be unified, so everybody can use it.
It should be possible to index it somehow,
to search through it,
and yeah, that's a start,
and probably there is much more that it should do it,
but in a start, this would be nice.
And yeah, let's discuss.
If you go, not right now,
because I have to add a link once I finish the talk,
but this is the place where you can go
and search through Web Light schedule.
I just double check.
Yeah, it's right, there is no misclick.
So if you go there, you can see all the schedule,
all the plans as Web Light have for this post-em,
I will add their link to the discussion,
and you can join, you can share it with your friends
that are interested in such things,
and maybe we will come up with something interesting
for every possible translator in the Libre community,
or in ideal way, this tool,
or this localization file,
or translation entity, whatever we will call it,
can welcome new translators
that don't feel I'm a translator
and then don't know how to get there,
maybe to make it easy for everyone.
So that's it, that's what I wanted to share with you,
and yeah, I'm interested in what do you think,
maybe we still have three minutes
so we can talk something.
Right now, you can also, if you go to that link,
you can also find our BO stickers, T-shirts,
and yeah, other things,
and you can share your ideas there about Web Light
and what we should include,
and if you don't like something, just come there and tell us,
or you can join the online discussion
that will be ready in a few minutes,
and yeah, thank you for your attention,
and if anybody has a question or anything,
just raise your hand or come here and tell it to us.
Thank you for your time, and enjoy your first time.
Thank you.