Hello, everybody. My name is Bruce Mamjin. I am from Philadelphia. I am one of the Post
Course Core Team members, and I'm going to talk for the next 30 minutes about some of
the nuts and bolts of building open source teams. I know the previous talk was more of
a little more high level. This is definitely trench level activity here because that's
what I've done for a long time. I'm basically a co-founder of the Post Course Internet Development
Group. We have a dev room downstairs. We had a big conference on Friday at a local hotel.
We have a whole bunch of events coming up, Paris, Stockholm, Malta. We got one in Chicago.
We're going to be at scale in a couple weeks. We have Ottawa and hopefully one in Singapore
coming up. A whole bunch of stuff going on. I travel a lot. I've been a Core Team member
since the community started in 1996, and I've worked for three open source companies. I've
been around the block, and I have some insights into how we've built Postgres and some of
the things that work for us. What I want to talk about first is motivation.
This is something a lot of people are going to talk about. We take it for granted that
people are going to come to us, but why do they come to us? Why do they want to be involved
in open source? What interests them? Why are they even giving their time to us? It's a
trench question. Talk a little bit about open source management and how we manage open source
projects. I'll talk a little bit about the development process.
Open source motivations. This is actually from a study done in 2002 published in the
register URL here right at the bottom. By the way, these slides are actually on my website.
If you want to go here, feel free to get the slides and do whatever you want with them.
What they basically did is a survey, and they found that the major motivations for people
getting involved with open source were professional advancement, learning new skills. That's probably
what got me involved in new skills. Practical need for the software. Maybe they
have a business need for the software to be enhanced. There's a lot of people in the Postgres
community like that. Or their business wants the software to thrive. Now that's my employer,
EDB, wants Postgres to thrive, so they pay me to do my crazy thing.
Professional stimulation is actually a valid reason to get involved. That was actually
one of my also reasons for getting involved. I was always curious how a relational database
worked, and Postgres was open source so I could actually see it work. It was exciting
to me. Finally, the belief in open source, the belief
that open source is a good, and therefore I want to invest in that. These are the four
big ones. I'll tell you the real thing that nobody talks about is if you go up to somebody
who works in open source, you say, which one of these are you? They may not even know.
They may not even know. The weird part of it is that they all work together.
I love the mental stimulation aspect. I actually have a need for it. I'm learning new skills
and everybody helped me in my career. The open source stuff is cool. I like helping
them. Which one is it? It's all of them mushed together. I may be able to give you percentages
a little bit, but that's part of the beauty of it. Usually, if I say somebody, go dig
a ditch, they're going to say, okay, how much are you going to give me for digging a ditch?
They know what's motivating them because they just don't want to dig a ditch. For open source
software, it's like multiple motivations all working together and flowing together. Healthy
open source projects are able to have all of those aspects working at the same time.
If you focus on just one of them, which I know some projects do, you're really not taking
advantage of the full spectrum of ways of attracting developers. I know this is kind
of, I never heard anybody talk of before, but when you see it in writing, you're like,
yeah, I guess that does kind of make sense because that's kind of how I got involved.
That's what motivates me. There's all this kind of stuff that doesn't really make sense,
but actually it actually does. I mentioned mental stimulation. Programming is where there's
unusual activities that does not require any upfront money. As long as you have a computer,
you can do as much programming as you want. You're not paying per hour or paying per
piece or paying for wire or paying for fabrication of some kind of equipment. It's basically
a malleable and a cost-free medium that you can continue changing. That cost-free aspect
actually helps people get involved. With Postgres particularly, it's kind of a puzzle to solve
some of the problems we have to do. How many people like puzzles? It's kind of fun. Postgres
has a ton of puzzles that are really hard and a whole bunch of people would love to
work together to solve them. That's one of the things that attracts people. It kind of
makes sense. They wouldn't say it this way, but when you look at the people and they look
at the way they talk and you kind of look, it kind of squint your eye a little bit. You're
like, yeah, that's really what's kind of... Oh, and the other parts as well because they have
a good paying job. They like helping people and they like open source and it's helping
their business. There's a whole bunch of things all going at the same time. They enjoy learning.
There's just a whole bunch of stuff. Actually, this comes out of a book from I think the
70s, the mythical man month. We're going way, way back here in terms of understanding why
programming is interesting. We're kind of, I feel as open source people and of course
the Postgres person, we're kind of... There's a term in English, you're running on all cylinders.
All of you have an engine and all of the cylinders are working in the same way in a uniform fashion
for the same purpose. That's kind of what we have here and that's kind of what we have
here. What I'm saying is that to build open source projects, you're not going to open
with these things, but be aware that these are aspects and aspects that you're going
to attract different people who have different focuses and different things that motivate
them. Let's talk a little bit about management.
Obviously managing an open source project is incredibly complicated. Having done it
for so long and having done it really when open source was much smaller. Obviously, communication
is a key aspect, the ability to send free email. We didn't have chat back then really,
but the ability to send communication freely across the globe and harness the capabilities
of people who are very far away from me is incredibly important. You are going to have
issues with just being able to communicate potentially with email. You may not meet the
people that you're working with. You have travel distance challenges. You have time
zone distance challenges. When I was working on the port of Postgres to Windows, I had
one person in Stockholm who's actually at the conference and another person in Sydney,
Australia. Based on their availability, I would wake up in the morning and I would work
with the person in Stockholm because he would prefer to work in his evening time. Then I
would go through the day and then at night I would work with the person in Sydney because
that person liked to work in their daytime. I had this weird thing where I'd work really
hard from seven to nine in the morning and from 10 to midnight. The rest of the day was
kind of like, yeah. The culture is going to be different. Different cultures are going
to have different focuses. One of the things I try to do is to make fit into the culture
I'm visiting or the people I'm working with. Sometimes that's uncomfortable, but I think
it's important. Language, obviously, that's a huge challenge. I'm speaking in English.
You're understanding English, but I realize, A, I'm not sure how successful I would have
been if I had to do everything in French or Flemish or German. I don't know if I would
have been capable of being the communicator I am if I had to go learn another language
to be involved. How can we bridge that gap? I feel I'm very lucky and blessed to be able
to speak in English and you have to understand English, but that's not everybody. How can
we work with people who have trouble learning languages or just don't have the opportunity
to learn languages? How can we show what we value their contributions and we want to then
be part of our community and how to... I could have a whole talk just on that. You
can imagine. Funding, I'll talk about that in a minute. Communication, so I'm pretty
good at that. One of the people, one of our community members said, early on they said
to get new people in the community, we just need Bruce Monchene telephone. I used to call
people just in the middle of the day and talk to them about whatever they wanted to talk
about who are regular community members. I may be calling Germany, I may be calling the
other side of the country, the United States, but that personal contact meant a lot. It
showed you I care about what you're doing, I want to know you. I don't necessarily want
to know what you're doing for the community. I want to know you as you. If you want to
do something for the community, that's fine, but that's not my focus. When I go to visit
and I travel quite a bit, maybe 30 some events a year, I'm not there to tell you about our
software. I'm not here to tell you about my software either. I am here to get to know
you. I am here to understand how we can help you and how we can work together in whatever
you feel you want to work on. I don't have an agenda. My employer fortunately doesn't
have an agenda for me. My title is evangelist and postgres evangelist or open source evangelist,
whatever you want to call it. I am not here to sell you to use anything. I'm not even
here to tell you to use postgres. I remember I was in Sri Lanka once and somebody held
up his hand and said, why would I use postgres instead of MySQL? This was like 20 years
ago. I said, I don't know. Maybe, I don't know. If you want to use it, fine. I'm not
here to tell you. I'm not here to tell you why it has some features you might like. I'm
not here to convince you. I'm here to get you involved if you want to be involved. Instant
messaging, I've actually found it to be really almost better sometimes in the phone now because
everyone's on. Typically, Telegram is huge. If you're not using Telegram, that's usually
what I use for Europe, Russia. Asia's a little harder. There's WeChat in China. I'm not sure
I do a whole lot of chatting with Japan or Korea. I have a couple of Korea guys on Telegram
now that I think of it. I mean, Google Chat. We don't do too much with Facebook or at least
I don't. I'm sure some of my people do. Being able to just chat somebody and say, hey, did
you look at this or how you doing or did this problem in your country cause you a problem
or how you feeling or... Wow, that was an amazing email you sent or I loved it, that
patch you did. These little things, it doesn't cost you anything. I might send him $100.
I'm just talking to him and I'm saying, you did a great job. Frankly, I was down there
at the Postgres booth just before I came up here. I said, this booth looks great. I said
the dev room we have looks fantastic. We got a Postgres banner out front of the building.
There's a banner right near the entrance to the room. We've got people in blue vests that
say elephant herd are on the back. They're sort of helping people get into the room.
I'm like, we look like a million bucks here. I don't know what you guys are doing. This
is great. Didn't cost me anything, but they did a lot of work. Somebody had to make those
requests. These people are volunteering their time. Somebody had to bring the banners. They
got to put them in their car and bring them here. Nothing worse than doing something and
have nobody care about it. There's a lot of people who do stuff and nobody cares. Even
if people appreciate it, nobody tells them they appreciate it. It does not cost you anything
to tell somebody you appreciate what they do. It doesn't diminish you. It doesn't make
you look foolish. They're probably going to thank you and it's going to mean a lot to
them. That's a key aspect of building any type of community, particularly a community
where nobody gets paid. I know this sounds obvious, but a lot of people don't do it. That's
my soapbox. I'm sorry about that. I travel a lot and there's a lot of people who help
me get to where I am and help me find things and help me in the hotels and airports and
stuff. I say thank you. Thank you for helping me. Thank you for working on Sunday. I know
you'd rather be home. I think it makes a big difference. It's a mind change. It's a mind
change of what type of person you want to be. It's not just an open source. It's basically
what type of person. You want to be a grateful person who thanks others for helping them.
You just want to worry about yourself and just get your thing done. Whatever happens
to those other people who helped you, right? A lot of people that way, but you're not going
to be a leader if you're that way. That's not the type of leader. In fact, there's a
really interesting... I go to a lot of leader conferences and there's basically seven, six
type of leaders. There's the innovative leader. There's the managerial leader. There's the
sort of organizational leader. One of them is probably most important for open source
is the servant leader. The leader who is a servant to the people who report to them and
wants the best to happen to everyone who's reporting to them. That's the type of leader
you have to be an open source because you have no money. You have no control over these
people. They are helping you out of their own voluntary. If they stop doing it, there's
nothing you can do. A lot of management focuses on rewarding people and paying them and stuff,
but honestly, servant leader for open source, you can search for it. There's a lot of talks
about it. It's actually really interesting. One of the things I found in terms of conferences,
and this is a good example, I travel about 90 days a year when COVID isn't happening.
I found that going to somebody's country and spending time with them and staying an extra
day after the conference and just hanging out with them and doing whatever they want
to do is gold. The conference itself, yeah, okay, people hear me talk and I'm talking
about Postgres features and blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah. Okay, yeah, maybe I'm good
at that or maybe, yeah, they can see my slides online and it's not the same maybe, but a
lot of what I do is not just peaking to small groups but spending time with individuals
in their countries just doing whatever they want to do. Hey, let's go to the park. Let's
go to the zoo. Let's show me something interesting and it's unbelievable some of the stuff I've
seen by just asking somebody, hey, I'm here for an extra day after the conference. If
you want to do anything, let me know. You don't know what's going to happen to you.
Honestly, it's a little scary. You'll notice I have shoes on but they actually have high
top shoes because a lot of times when I'm traveling, I don't know what climb I'm going
to be going up. Particularly in Russia, I seem to be ending up on top of a mountain
or in a forest or covered in snow or just places I never would have thought I'd go.
But again, I have to be flexible. I can't be this weird. Anyway, it's actually kind
of crazy and that investment pays back. It really does. One of the issues I had is, yeah,
email is nice. Talking to somebody on chat is better. Talking to somebody by voice is
better than that. Going to them is the best. I'll tell you a story. Shirley, are you here
or are you left? Shirley's here? No. I have shoes right back. In 2000, I want to say three,
I was at a show. I used to work for OSCON. I went to OSCON in San Diego. I fly out there.
I didn't travel very much at that point. I fly out to San Diego and it was in a hotel
right on the water. I had a tutorial and a talk. I gave my tutorial. There's probably
like 40 people there. Then I gave my talk the next day and there's like 30 people there.
I'm like, okay, so I talked to like 70 people. I'm on the plane flying home. I'm like, that
was a waste of time. I sent an email. Thousands of people see it. I just flew across the country,
spent like four days, five days to talk to 70 people. I'm telling my wife, we're not
doing the same one. It's 2003. I think I've traveled like 1200 days since then, but anyway.
The stats are on my website. What I found out is the next week when I was looking at
the Postgres email list, there was a lot of activity that wasn't there the week that I
left. The week before OSCON, the week after OSCON, I had a lot more activity after the
week. What I realized was the people I had lunch with at OSCON were now the people who
were actively working in Postgres. I don't know how it happened. I don't know what magic
words I said. Who knows? The point is it wasn't, I'm not even sure it was the people in my
talk. I think it was the people I talked to at lunch. I talked to them. I got to know
them. I talked about, I guess I must have said something about Postgres or they asked
me something about Postgres. I talked about it. All of a sudden, we were going. I don't
know. Magnus Huygendur, who was actually one of the core team members as well, he's here.
I went to a conference early on, probably 2004 in... It was in Denmark, Sta. Copenhagen.
Yeah, I had my clock right here. I'm good. Away at Copenhagen. Again, it was a very early
trip. I remember flying... It was a crazy flight out at JFK in the snow. I remember
arriving. I don't know. I talked to the guy. It was Magnus. I don't know. I didn't even
know what Magnus meant. I didn't know Magnus was a name because I'm from the United States.
I'm talking to him and he's talking to me about stuff and okay, whatever. I talked to
a bunch of other people. Then I came back from Copenhagen. All of a sudden, Magnus is
involved and he's working an email list. I'm like, oh, this is great. Little did I know,
he would end up being the president of Postgres. You're up and a core team member. You don't
know. You don't know who you're going to talk to. I will tell you, travel is time consuming.
There's only a few people in any one location, but if you can do it and you have the time
to invest in a long-term goal, it pays off tremendously. Time zones, obviously, we all
work in multiple time zones. I've always worked from home, so I don't have it nine to five.
My days have always been very long. I work in the morning and then I work through the
day, but I may take two hours off, three hours off in the middle of the day to go shopping
or go visit somebody or go to church. I don't know, whatever. I never really worried about
it because the work's always there. The people in Asia are awake. It's actually kind of a
long-term. Having a cell phone is nice because you can communicate when you're not home,
but it is a 24-hour cycle. There's something happening all the time and that is a little
hard to get used to.
Culture show interest in other cultures. Don't be the person who, oh, I don't do it that
way or that's wrong that you do it that way. We had a case where there was an inappropriate
something at a conference in Russia years ago and I had to call somebody up in the middle
of the night. I called him at his 1 a.m. and he answered the phone. I kind of talked to
him about the issue and he was able to resolve it by the time everyone got up the next day.
Again, I already had personal contact with that individual. That individual had already
sent his daughter to live with me for a summer to learn English. I knew him and his family
very well. He answered my phone at 1 a.m. I said there's concern about this thing that
happened at the conference. I got all the information I need. I talked to the court
committee and we handled it very cleanly. Again, I had already invested in that relationship
long before I needed to call that person at 1 a.m. to get an answer so that things didn't
get out of hand. Turned out they didn't understand. This was part of the package they bought and
we're like what country has a package like that? But whatever. You have to be culturally
understanding sometimes. I spoke at a Russia conference in June and people were saying
don't do that. We don't discriminate against where somebody lives. How do I do that? I
start the talk and I said I want to say something before I talk about my material. I said I
know it's a very hard time for people in Russia but it's an even harder time for people in
Ukraine and the people and the Ukrainians. I said I work for a project that does not have
boundaries between individuals. We don't discriminate on where somebody lives. It's in that spirit
I'd like to talk to you today. I said the one sad thing is that I have been in Russia
many times and I have. I said I'm sad to think it's going to be a long time until I can come
back and see you again in Russia. The feedback I got from them was they really appreciated
me saying that. I was able to talk about Ukraine. I was able to talk about Russia at the same
time and I think in a balanced way and they appreciated somebody was willing to talk about
that. Again I spent a lot of time thinking about what am I going to say to them and how
am I going to make sure that I say the right words. They appreciated it and I continued
to have a regular dialogue with them. We had a lot of developers in Russia still who continue
to work on our project. We don't discriminate against them basically. Language can be an
issue. We do have some cases where we try and do per language. Remember I talked about
the language barrier. We have a French email list. We have a Spanish email list. We have
a Japanese email list, a Chinese email list. There's a whole bunch of per language lists
to get people started. We have per language I believe it's telegram channels. I know we
have a big Russian telegram channel. I don't remember what other languages we have. I know
we have Slack channels for particular languages. We have obviously conferences all over the
world. Many of them are in some of them are native languages. Some of them are in English.
Some of them are both are translated. So when I go to Japan there's typically a translator
there. When I go to Russia often there's a translator China as well. So again depending
we have different documentation in different languages. Funding we don't have any. So just
get over that. Hopefully you'll find a company like mine who's worried about the health of
the community as willing to invest in somebody as crazy as me who just says these things
and goes around and does whatever. And the reason is because they're investing so that
if there's a problem he already knows everyone who can get the problem fixed real cleanly
and that's again one of the investments. Development process we try and involve everybody. Find
each person's motivation. Remember different people are motivated by different things so
figure out what the motivator then and try and put them into position where they're going
to be strong. I don't know how to put this but none of us is perfect. We all have problems
things we do wrong. So I try and look at a person say what is your strength and what
are the weaknesses. How can I put them in a place where your strengths are going to shine
and we kind of have somebody backstopping the weaknesses so that doesn't become a problem.
Reach out to individuals again that personal contact is important. Harvest the strength
of the team. There's always somebody smaller than you. I learned that early on there was
a guy in Krasnoyarsk Russia who was so smart early on not only could not answer his questions
I didn't even understand why he'd answer the question. So I'd say I don't know the answer
but why are you asking the question. Oh because of this and this. Oh okay I understand it
but now I at least understand why he asked the question. Produce work that people are
proud of. I'm not always Mr. Sunshine sometimes if I think if I'm embarrassed by something
my community members will hear about it. In fact somebody just told me today I railed
against how our website looked. It was kind of stuck in an ugly years ago in Dallas. He
remembered where it was and what year it was and he said you didn't like the website and
you basically said you were going to yell at everybody. He said I don't care what you
do to the website do something because we were stuck and we couldn't we were stuck
trying to look for something perfect. I said just do something and that kind of like got
us over the hill. Produce clean code. Remember we're not paying people to code so we better
make it easy. All right. And finally let manage the team lead by example not from authority.
This is a big thing. I didn't realize it myself but but if the leadership the leadership really
has an unspoken control over how the project and how the team works. If you have toxic
leadership at the top you're not going to have a role on team at the bottom. If you
have a servant leadership at the top you're you're the people underneath you will be servants
to those below and so forth and will continue promoting people up and up into more powerful
positions. That is absolutely a key aspect. I've been surprised at how well that works
except failure gracefully when I make mistakes I'm like I'm sorry and when I say I'm sorry
and I say I made a mistake it opens the door for other people when they make mistakes to
also say I made a mistake because if if Bruce can say he was wrong about this thing and
basically take the lumps on it then oh I guess look it didn't hurt I guess I can do that
too. Right. If I'm the type of person who ignores any mistake I make then that's going
to that's how other people are going to do it. So see consensus the post community does
that a lot. OK. Let me take some questions. We have one minute for one question. Who would
like to be our one question in our one minute. I see a hand. I look. It's here. Yeah she's
there. She's she's she's she's going to give me an easy one I'm sure. Hi Bruce. Hey. So
here's my question. How do you find balance. I mean you said you take calls at 1 a.m. travel
three months a year. You have wife you have children. How do you do that. Right. So the
question is how do you find balance. Basically basically you have to just accept your failures.
You have to accept that I'm not going to be everywhere that I'm not going to be able to
fix every problem. I'm not going to be able to do everything. Right. And you now rely
on your leaders. So for example a great example when I'm here at the conference I have no
idea what's happening in the community. No idea because I trust all of our people who
have been working for years on this. So when I travel I don't even bother reading the community
email list. When I get back I'll take a look at it and you know nothing bad happens when
I'm gone. So what I realize is not to be anxious about things to trust the people who are part
of your organization to handle it. And we're by showing by showing confidence in them they
become confident. If you show you're not confident then they will not be confident. It's kind
of natural. Thank you. Appreciate it. Bye bye.