We are getting there.
We are almost there.
I keep encouraging everybody to take more Haribo, but I don't think we have enough left
to encourage massive runs on the Haribo.
We also have Ritter Sport, if you need it.
Wonderful humans, I live in the town where they make the Haribo gummy candies, so please
take the gummy candies.
I can get more easily.
Do not need the extras to go back on the train with me to Germany.
While we are getting set up and having a little bit of additional technical difficulty, all
of us are getting ready to go back on the train.
I am getting very happy over here because we have our next generation of Fosdomers hanging
out and getting candy now too.
Yeah, that's right.
Sadly I couldn't bring my daughter with me, but when she was all of 33 days old, she went
to her first Fosdom.
I am looking forward to her next Fosdom.
No, although I did get one conference to make her a lanyard that said future speaker, so
that made me feel happy.
I think I am going to try and bring her to DevConf this year if at all possible.
The German school system is very rigorous about thou shalt not miss school time, so
it's a little more difficult.
We'll.
La la la la.
If you want to la la la la la, you totally can.
There may be karaoke coming on.
I know you're going to leave.
It's worth the risk to me to entertain our adoring public, Mr. Prophet, but we will try
and avoid it because we care for you.
Is everybody both enjoying their Fosdom and exhausted and ready to go home?
Yes, okay, that's all right.
Sometimes exhaustion is where we end up, but in the good way, in the we're full of happiness
and good ideas way and filled with delicious candy.
Welcome, welcome, welcome, lovely people who are just joining us.
We're still working on convincing the, watch me go.
Everybody centering DEI in your open source project.
Okay, on the topics, good.
Hi, everybody.
It's great to be here and it's great to see people.
I'm Matt German-Prey and I'm one of the co-founders of the Chaos Project and I'm also a professor
by day at the University of Nebraska Omaha in the College of Information Science and
Technology and it's really great to be here.
So just real briefly, I'm going to be giving this talk with Justin and Kristi so they can
kind of introduce themselves when they come up and we also have a slide that introduces
them as well.
So the Chaos Project, as Dawn was actually alluding to in her last talk, which was a
great segue, is a project that's focused on open source health and sustainability.
So creating metrics and software as well as programs because there are a lot of metrics
that can't necessarily be determined through software that require qualitative and human
efforts to understand.
So we develop those types of metrics and software and programs.
As part of what we do in the Chaos Project, diversity, equity and inclusion is a key component
to understand with respect to the health and sustainability of projects.
And for ourselves, we looked at the Chaos Project and thought how can we not only help
others think about diversity, equity and inclusion with respect to their projects, but also reflect
ourselves about our own diversity, equity and inclusion.
So how can we as a project better center diversity, equity and inclusion within the Chaos Project
and then subsequently help others do the same from our experience?
So I would like to first say thanks to the Ford Foundation who has provided support for
this reflection over the last, it's been a year and a half now, and it'll complete in
about two, it'll complete in about another six months.
And so through the support from the Ford Foundation, it's been really great because we've been
able to have consistency in our team of people helping us do the reflection, including Kristi
and Justin, as well as come to places like FOSDIM and talk about our experience and what
we've learned and share that with other people.
So the team, oh that got cut off a little, it's close.
So the team, Celia got cut off, so we have Kristi, we have Justin, we have Sean, Guy,
and
Gagans, we have Georgia Bulin, who's there in the center, we have Elizabeth Barron, who
is the Chaos Community Manager, we have Ruth Ikega, who couldn't come, she's on the right,
and then in the upper right corner I think you only see a very small part of Cela, but
it's Cela Yang, who is also part of the team for this reflection, and then myself in the
lower right hand corner.
So it's been an amazing group of people, and like I said, through the Ford Foundation
support we've been able to stay together as a team throughout the entire reflection.
So here are the speakers, again, Justin you're cut off.
That's okay, hopefully there aren't a lot of words that get cut off there when we show
what we're showing.
But again, I'm Matt Gerwinpre, we have Kristi Progrie and Justin Flori, and I think Justin's
going to talk kind of about our first, we have four things that we're going to talk
about that were part of this reflection, and Justin will talk about two of them, and Kristi
will also talk about two of them, and then we'd really love to kind of hear from you
all and answer questions the best that we can or any thoughts that you might have.
So Justin, I'm going to turn it over to you.
Should we do quick round introductions too of all of us?
I'm done, I met Gerwinpre.
I'm Justin Flori, so I'm currently with Red Hat as the Fedora community architect, so
I'm working in the Fedora community day by day, but I've also been involved with the
Chaos Project that we're going to be talking a little bit about here for the last five
years, and then working with our awesome group of folks on this DEI review for the last two.
Hello everyone, so I'm Kristi Progrie, I'm currently the program manager for the GNOME
Foundation, and I'm also part of the Chaos community for around one year and a half now,
and also contributing in their diversity and inclusion working group.
I'm going to go sit down.
Yes.
All right, so let's look at the first two points of our reflection.
So again, this was just the background context again.
So this was work that we started about two years ago, and we were coming into this reflection.
We were starting really from the very beginning.
We were going to take a look at the Chaos Project to understand where could we better
focus our efforts and spend our time and energy and resources to make things better.
So over that journey, the four points that we're going to be sharing here are basically
the outcomes of this journey that we've been on for the last two years.
So you're getting a little bit more of the polished end result of this, so it'll be
nice bullet point list.
But you can also keep in mind that when we started with this reflection, we were kind
of like, where do we begin?
And this was a lot of conversations that brought us to this point and engaging with our community
to learn some of these things that helped us define some of our efforts.
So without further ado, the four highlights.
Whoops, there's a little bit of a lag.
Okay, we didn't get it all cut off.
So I'll be talking a little bit around our newcomer initiatives and engagements, and
also talk a little bit around our global efforts.
So across the span of the last two years, no, I guess I kind of already covered this.
So the first part on the newcomer experience.
So with the creation of new support structures, along with an increased emphasis on mentoring,
the chaos project has grown a lot, really tremendously with new contributors in the
last couple of years.
New onboarding pathways were developed, and we prioritize the refinement of these pathways
too.
I might say part of this was also kind of the right time at the right place, because
I think as we were kind of going into COVID as well, and everything was really shifting
into a virtual format, as we were spending more time thinking about the newcomer experience,
I also think there was more of an interest in folks trying to get involved with open
source projects, which also opened the door for lots of folks that we ended up engaging
with from countries and places all over the world.
So ultimately, many of us long time FOSS contributors remember well what it is like to get involved
in a new project, and trying to figure out where do you begin.
It's easy to get overwhelmed.
And ultimately, many of us long time FOSS contributors remember well what it's like,
or at the same time, ensuring newcomers have a clear pathway to get onboarded is important
for project sustainability and keeping things going.
So new faces should always be coming and going, as well as mingling with the older faces and
people that have been in the community.
So keeping those signs of folks who have been around for a long while while also still having
new faces coming into the fold and the mix is important for community growth and sustainability.
Additionally, newcomers have that unique perspective as a first time observer to your community.
And you can learn a lot by listening actively to them and their perspectives that they're
bringing to your community.
So one key takeaway here is helping newcomers see and understand the impact of their work.
It's important to validate the small contributions.
In a way, you almost need to hype people up on their participation.
It feels great, actually kind of like what Don was just talking about in the last talk,
it feels great when you know your efforts are appreciated and made a difference to someone
else, all that soft squishy human stuff.
So one wish list item for developing metrics or measurements in a FOSS project is showing
and measuring the impact of a newcomer contribution.
So both trying to come up with a way to measure and understand that, but also kind of around
this recognition piece of making sure that the people making that contribution also understand
that impact of their contribution.
Additionally, newcomers need to feel safe and welcome in the community.
They need space to try out new ideas and more importantly, to make mistakes and mess up
because that's where you really learn.
So having a safe environment is important for people to test and validate their wildest
ideas and a welcoming community gives them the opportunity to bounce back when something
doesn't work out.
So one key part of unlocking creativity and innovation is making sure that people bring
their best and that a newcomer has the space that they need to bring their best while they're
learning more about the project and the community.
In short, avoid this tendency to over-celebrate your long-term contributors.
We also want to recognize those folks, but I really like, I think it was someone in our
group who put it as the emphasis is really to share the spotlight.
So making sure that there's an equitable focus of how you're recognizing and validating people's
contributions in your community.
And also kind of a side point, or not only side point, but the importance of diversity
and leadership I think is a tie-in here with that newcomer experience.
So it's kind of an unwritten point in the slide deck here, but in our Chaos DEI review
team we have one of the people who we really wanted to be here, Ruth Akega, who has done
a lot with that newcomer onboarding in the Chaos Project.
She was really hands-on with the mentoring and onboarding of the new contributors, especially
across Western Africa where she's originally from.
And Ruth worked directly with the newcomers, but also brought visibility to the challenges
and issues, but also the success points for the people she was working with to our group,
to the DEI review team.
So in the same way, she was very hands-on with engaging with those people, but she was
also sharing these experiences back with our review team so that we had better visibility
and insight to that.
So at the more, I guess a higher level in the project, we could think how could we align,
again, our time, resources, and energy to make sure that we're supporting and welcoming
in all these new people to the project community.
So the takeaway on this point is to choose folks from regions, especially with less representation,
to try to encourage them into these leadership roles or find somewhere in the project where
they can make that impact.
It makes it easier to build relationships with those newcomers to the project.
I think, oh, global efforts, right.
So when you're trying to fix things, challenges are going to come up.
It's important to have this persistence in the face of challenges when necessary.
And when you're trying to pivot a project's focus toward DEI challenges, or towards DEI,
these challenges are going to be inevitable.
The work is a kind of cultural, organizational culture work, and that stuff is really hard.
So again, there's kind of this piece that there's a historical resistance to change.
Change is hard.
We don't like it.
Sometimes there's a, I read this, there's actually a comic I was reading a while back
that we have this part in our brain that when we, there's something that's challenging our
beliefs or ideals that we kind of freeze up.
It's almost as if someone was threatening us with something violent, but it might just
be changing our mindset or ideas.
And what I'm going with this is that the change is really hard.
And so we can help make it easier to evolve and adapt to change.
So I think one part of this as well is that we're not also in a, you know, escape room
or echo chamber doing this work.
We're kind of all in this together.
One of the data points to mention here as well is again, coming back to both the chaos
Africa piece, which is where we had a lot of that newcomer growth was we had over 200,
over 200 new community members who joined into our project.
And that was across five different focus groups of development and design and research and
technical writing and community management.
I think it also ties into one of the efforts around our new website, which is underway
for the chaos project, which has been a huge contribution from all these newcomers who
have helped shape and influence how we're kind of opening or presenting the front door
of our project and making it easier for people to find the things they're looking for.
And also the over 900 plus folks following the new chaos Africa Twitter account as another
data point.
And our folks in the Asia Pacific community, there's also been a ongoing connection with
the to do group supported by the Linux Foundation and GitHub.
Or sorry, I misread that.
So this they're doing work with the to do group around trying to support some of these
efforts and grow the community there as well.
So I think from here I will pass it over to Kristi to take us into the last two points
of our what we're here to share with you today for the reflection.
Great.
Thank you, Justin.
One other important, very important part of our community and one of the most successful
initiatives, let's say, has been the badging.
So the badging is meant the badging review is meant for self reflection and improvement
on how many different communities and how many different conferences are implementing
and are centering diversity, equity and inclusion.
This initiative uses chaos matrix.
And the way that it works is that we have an organizer of a conference applying on our
website.
We have two forms.
One application is for all online events and the other application is for in person events.
And the person who is applying actually goes through all the application, answers different
questions.
And we have two reviews, two reviewers that actually go through the application.
And then by the end of the review, we also give the badge to the to the specific conference
or the community that has applied for this.
And it's also like this badging review has four different levels.
And depending on how you're centering, we also give the reviews.
In our community, we also give support and lessons learned from many people on how you
can improve and how you can actually work more in your community to center diversity,
equity and inclusion.
Another initiative, let's say, in our community has been the survey.
We started the community survey by October 20, 22nd.
So in this survey, the idea was to get a general idea of how the experience of the community
is going, what we are doing well, what needs more improvement.
So by collecting all this data, we were able to work more on the things that we want to
see more improved for the next years.
The idea of this survey was to create a structure that could help also other communities to
implement it.
And we have asked many demographic questions.
When the results will come out, we would like to give or to publicize this survey online
with all the structures so everyone that would like to implement it in their respective communities,
they can do so.
It's a very demanding work.
It takes a lot of energy and time.
So we would love to give this work to others to make their lives better.
And for a quick summary, so for our two years journey, there are definitely surprises going
on.
And we had things that we need to do during this whole process.
So it's not, you know, sometimes things don't really go in the way that we have planned
it, but the most important thing is to actually finish with the results that we wanted to
and to accomplish the goals that we set ourselves to.
Another main idea and another big lesson that we have learned throughout our journey is
that supporting contributors and making onboarding process smooth actually helps us to have a
better community, to have a healthier community, and to be able to get as many contributors
as possible.
And also the other last takeaway is that the community surveys are actually very important
because it is a very good way to understand what is going on in your community, how can
you help, and what other things that you can appreciate or that you can feel proud of,
let's say.
So this was all the presentation that we had for today.
Thank you all for joining our talk.
And feel free, if you have any questions, we'd be happy to answer you.
Thank you.
I'm going to put that QR code on the live survey.
I'll do that.
If I know how.
Yeah, it gets got here.
Yeah, can I?
You can also upload the PDFs to the post-op site.
Hi.
Are you finished?
What's that?
Yeah.
Are you finished?
Yeah, we're done.
Okay.
Should we take any questions?
So I think, yeah, we have about eight minutes left.
Do we have, yeah, I see one question here from the audience.
Yeah, it's an issue.
Thanks, guys.
It was a great talk and great insight.
One of the questions that I had was, so you mentioned that improving the onboarding process
made it easier to retain contributors down the line.
Do you have any insight as to why you think that one might have contributed to the other?
Because oftentimes I've seen in other projects where we've done work to help improve the
on-ramps and we do see a large influx of people, but over time as well, there's still a fair
amount of attrition.
So I was just wondering what your insights were based on what you saw from the work you've
done.
Sure.
Thanks.
Yeah, thank you for that.
So as far as a lot of our newcomer experience, I can tell you about a couple things that
we've been doing just in that regard, and then I'll speak to kind of how I think it
has helped retain people as well.
So from the newcomer experience, a lot of the work that we have done are open office
hours, which have worked really quite well.
They're unstructured hours every week.
We also have one hour a week of kind of structured talk about the project itself.
So it's usually led by Ruth or by Elizabeth, who's the community manager, using a slide
deck.
You know what I mean?
That's a little bit more structured in time.
The other thing that we had to reflect on was in terms of the newcomer experience, for
a lot of us, it was not actually going out as far as how to make a commit or how to do
a PR, but they were usually easier things like, here's the meeting to attend, and we
encourage you to attend this meeting twice.
And this would be, say, our general meeting.
And then once you've attended the general meeting twice, we encourage you to attend
a working group meeting, kind of a smaller level meeting, say four times.
And what we find is that by doing this, it helps create the vocabulary for folks to understand
what it is.
So sometimes the commit is kind of far out there.
A poll request is kind of far out there.
So in doing that, we also had a better opportunity to understand why people were joining.
So it was kind of on us to understand why.
And then the earlier talk about the different types of contributions, I don't know if you
were here, there was one that was like not just technical contributions, but all the
different types of contributions.
It then becomes kind of our responsibility as the community folk, you know, like the
community managers, to identify what those hopes are from people and how to contribute,
and then really try to focus in on pairing that.
So hopefully that helps a little bit.
So it's not just putting out documents that are for the newcomer experience, but you have
to be really active along that path as well.
Did you want to comment, too?
I'll just do one more callout to something that I thought worked really well in this
as well.
It was Elizabeth Barron, I think, Ruth, too.
We're doing kind of like individualized like mentor sessions with folks who wanted like
some extra guidance or had questions and weren't really sure where to go.
Talking to a real human being and getting some of that individualized support, I think,
also made it easier for folks to feel connected to the project.
And so when things got hard or things weren't clear, there was always a way that they could
they had like kind of a buddy in the community to help kind of help them through.
And I think that was also kind of a big part of the retention piece.
I also think that an important part of the onboarding process and to make it as easier
as possible is to also have a good documentation on how people at least can get started.
And by having some very specific steps, it makes people more comfortable and it makes
people feel that they know where they're actually going.
So having actionable items helps you with the path forward.
Do we have other questions for our fine speakers?
We have about three minutes.
How many?
Three minutes.
Three seconds.
Ah, I see.
Is it helpful to have an onboarding buddy for each person, a mentor for their first
stage?
I think that assigning someone specific to every new commerce may be a little bit too
demanding because there might be like a certain amount of people coming all at the same time
and maybe we don't have the manpower to assist each one with an individual mentor.
But I think that having one mentor for three or four people, for a set group of people,
would be easier to coordinate and to organize.
It's a good question.
I don't think we've sorted it out yet, but in terms of having a one-on-one, to Christie's
point would be a lot of work.
So how we sort that out, I don't think we have that quite clear yet.
Maybe just one corollary point to that is I think in Fedora, we have also like a join
special interest group of folks who kind of buddy up with folks.
I think what's helped with that to make it scale is that there's a process that anyone
who wants to even do that mentoring work knows how they can help people.
So it makes it easier not just for newcomers to find someone to get kind of help buddy
up with them, but there's also a way for the people who want to be buddies to help connect
with the newcomers too.
So I think that might be one way to help make it easier to scale because one-to-one is,
it only goes, it only reach, can go so far with that before you hit your limit.
Anyone else have a question for our wonderful presenters?
Very good.
On my way.
Hi.
I was wondering if after the two years of research, do you review your metrics process to have
another understanding what does health in the community mean?
Yeah.
So as part of this process.
So the CAS project also publishes metrics.
So as part of what we're learning, that's going right into the development of new metrics.
So that would be the publishing that we're doing in part.
I think we're also in the stage right now of how we.