Before we get started, we actually have an empty chair.
So anybody want to raise their hand to be a panelist?
Contestant?
Contestant.
Come on.
Woo!
Awesome.
Catch his name.
George.
Alrighty.
Guess we'll just get started.
Hi, I'm Shirley and this is the first time we thought we'd try this out in the community
dev room because everyone's sort of sitting around all day learning things, which is a
great thing, but we thought we'd try to have some fun as well and engagement.
So we'll see how it goes.
A little bit weak in here.
It is lunchtime, but maybe nobody likes to have fun.
We'll see.
So just a community minute.
Some of you might have heard of the game show just a minute.
It's a British game show from the 60s.
It's a radio comedy show with a panel of folks and essentially you have a couple of topics
that you'll throw at them and our esteemed panelists will have to answer 60 seconds to
answer or talk to the topic that they're going to be presented with.
So if you have heard of just a minute, it was originally hosted by Nicholas Parsons.
He hosted it for about 50 something years before he unfortunately passed away.
And then Sue Perkins has recently taken over.
You might recognize her from the great British Bake Off.
But again, rules of the game.
Each person goes when it's their turn.
They get one minute.
They have to answer on the topic with no hesitation at all.
So the full three golden rules, no hesitation, no repetition, no deviation.
So for example, if the topic provided is bananas, Dawn would have to talk about bananas for
full 60 seconds, never repeating the word banana, never deviating and talking about
pineapples and not hesitating.
If any of those three things are met, her fellow contestants hit the buzzer.
And unfortunately, this was the cheapest thing I could find that didn't have wires.
So you can test your buzzers now.
By the way, those are children's learning tools.
$24 on Amazon.
So I should say, sorry, George, I didn't have you in time.
We're not quite sitting in order, but we have spot in the middle sort of ish, Dawn, Ray
and George at the end.
So let's get started.
We'll start with Dawn.
Once I see the topic, we'll start.
Can you hear me?
Yes.
I'm good.
All right.
Okay.
So Dawn, your topic is things that make people crazy.
Things that make people crazy.
There are lots of things that make people crazy.
Spiders are one of mine.
Absolutely bonkers.
And I think a lot of people, crowds, like we've got here at FOSDEM, I think those often
make people, not the word I'm going to repeat.
And there are lots of others too.
I think maybe birds.
You know, there was that movie, The Birds, that I think also makes people kind of bonkers.
More movies.
Yep.
It does.
Okay.
All right.
Very good.
I'm glad I'm done.
So now, so the mic goes to George to continue the rest of the...
Yes.
Crowsball, you have the remaining time to, on the topic, things that make people crazy.
Well, I was thinking about things that make developers crazy is when you do a lock and
you don't do an unlock, that makes you crazy.
It makes you crazy.
You said crazy.
Oh, you can't say crazy?
Yes.
You can't say more than once.
If it's the topic, you can't say it more than once.
Seven seconds remaining.
I think the other thing that drive me crazy is long lines.
Okay.
Done, right?
Yep.
All right.
Mic goes to spot.
Your topic is beer.
Beer.
So, last night I went out and had far too much of this liquid goodness that is flowing
all over Brussels.
And unfortunately, no one bothered to tell me how strong some of them were.
And I may be feeling some of the repercussions of my experiences.
And I apologize in advance if this has impeded the verbosity of what I've been able to deliver
to you fine fellows.
And I want you all to know that you should not take my example as an action not to mirror.
Because I think it's important that you go out and you try all of that beer because you
will not know what you're missing if you do not take this opportunity.
So I actually don't drink that tasty beverage.
It's one of the only things that I will not drink.
Alcohol is fine.
For some reason, I just can't get into it.
So being here, I think is maybe kind of wasted on me.
My partner, though, comes with me.
And he certainly imbibes in all of it.
Ooh.
Way closer to that.
Well done.
Since you don't drink beer.
All right.
The mic goes to Ray.
So just to switch things up, we're going to have the audience pick a topic.
Anybody want to throw away a topic?
Books.
I enjoy reading them.
But my problem is I have a short attention span.
So it takes me a long time to finish consuming the content.
I wrote one of these ones a long time ago.
And one of the things that I learned from that experience was that having an incredibly
good editor is key to success.
And if you don't have one of those, then you find yourself in a position where you hate
everything about it.
You don't want to look at the computer.
You don't want to look at the horrible interface that O'Reilly has built for you to put these
words into play.
There's so much pain and suffering and you wake up in the morning and you think, why
in the world did I ever agree to this and why did I sneak into the O'Reilly party in
the first place?
What is wrong with me?
But I think that that should not discourage any of you from the audience from doing that.
You should take the time to write.
Well done.
All right.
George, you're up.
Your topic is DevRel.
DevRel is a thing which I just heard about today as I was looking at what a developer
advocate was.
But I've been in community management for a long time and I think certainly it's an
important topic.
Developers are very important.
And it can often be frustrating when you have new developers.
I'm going to say developers in more time.
I mean, it's a scam and I'm here to tell you that.
We need to put a stop to this before it takes out any more innocent people.
The victims are crying in the streets.
Why do we continue to perpetuate the idea that this is something that anyone should
be trying to do in any sense?
Because it's not.
It's bad.
It's harmful.
And I'm not afraid to say it on video.
I think that we need more people who are willing to speak up against this.
Stop the madness right now.
Nobody wants to fall in.
I'm still having problems figuring out what the delineation is between DevRel marketing
community.
Easy point for Ray.
I'm not fired by the way.
All right.
We're going to go back to Don.
How to cook eggs.
So I'm a vegan.
And so I don't actually cook eggs.
But I have seen people cook these things.
When our friends come over, so my partner has been friends with people who went to uni
with 20 some years ago.
They all come over on New Year's Eve.
And we did make eggs and sausage for the team.
And my partner cooked these things in the microwave, which I thought was maybe a little
bit weird because I'd always seen people.
You know, you see people on TV.
And they put them in a pan.
And they cook them for a while.
And then halfway through, they flip them over.
And then, you know, they wait a little bit longer.
And then they put them on a plate with some toast and some probably meat.
I don't know.
Because like I said, I don't actually eat these things.
But I think that when you cook them, you also put like oil or butter in the pan.
And I think that's part of the process.
And then you can also serve them.
Oh, good.
I'm like, grrr.
I'm really slow.
Did she get the home in it?
Yep.
Well done.
I could say eggs twice.
I was waiting for it right after I said it the second time.
All right, Spot.
Anything about not cheating?
You have to catch one another.
We're all verified to follow up.
Spot, you're up.
The internet.
I keep this in a box on my desk because if I didn't, then what would the repercussions be?
Will no one think of the children?
I know I'm harping on this today.
But it's important that we all factor in the youth when we look at the applications of the internet.
I mean, really, what good has it brought us?
It did not bring us here together.
Well, maybe it did.
But it did not give us ideas.
Well, it could have.
But these things are not important.
What is important is that there is a square feature that involves cables and blinking lights.
And if we don't have those blinking lights, come on, you all beat me up.
I'm trying.
Thank you.
Good thing or a bad thing, I haven't figured it out.
It's been around.
Everybody uses them all the time.
Are we addicted?
I'm not sure.
It's basically a series of tubes that go from one place to another, and they're full of data and goodness and also...
You did it.
I've heard that times.
Well done, George.
So are the internet.
All right, Lee, it's back to you.
A technology you love.
Technology I love.
Wheels.
Shoes.
Lights.
Electricity.
Cars.
Batteries.
I've been fascinated with...
I went to an energy track yesterday, and they were talking about, like, EVs.
It was pretty interesting about how you can not only charge your car, but discharge and make money.
And it was amazing that this person only spent in the Netherlands 200 euros to charge his car for, like, over 10 months.
And the Netherlands is not a place that you think of that has a lot of solar energy supply,
but I was pretty impressed with something.
I just bought a vehicle with the battery, so it's something I'll have to think about.
But he did have to do a lot of hacking with open source software, but I thought it was pretty amazing and commendable.
But hopefully that kind of platform will be available for a lot of people.
So is that a minute?
Oh, wow.
I think we're getting a little tired.
George, yours is free software.
Just sing the song.
Apparently there's a song about free software, which I had never heard, and I'm hoping maybe someone will sing to me at some point.
But this way of developing software is based on the idea that everybody has a right to modify the software that they're using,
which I've always thought is kind of a strange thing to say it's a right, that it's wrong somehow to withhold software from somebody.
But I do believe that it is a better way to start making software, and we wouldn't be here at this conference if we didn't all believe that.
And now I'm trying to think of something else to say, and I'm hoping someone will beat me off or something, maybe.
No, but it's the song.
I think it goes something like this.
I asked Chat GPT to write me a free software song.
So without free software, I guess I wouldn't have a job.
So obviously I'm glad I got to meet a lot of cool people, made good friends.
So back to you, Don.
I will not give you any other food-related topics.
How about FOSDEM?
I have a love-hate relationship with FOSDEM.
I come here every year.
On the one hand, we have the crowds, which is on the less of things that I like about this particular event.
On the other hand, it's the place where everyone I know finally comes together.
So I go to lots of different conferences.
But this is the place where the whole community is in one place.
And we have a community dev room, and Leslie always makes me delicious vegan cake for while we're here.
And it's a lot of fun.
I get to see people.
There are lots of really good places to eat in Brussels, so I don't drink the beer, as discussed earlier.
But there are two really good Ethiopian restaurants and an African tapas restaurant,
all of which are high on my list of delicious places to eat in Brussels while I'm here at this event.
And I spend a lot of my time at fringe parts of the conference, so ChaosCon on Friday was a lot of fun.
And I like to go out to dinner.
Oh, good.
Spot.
Bob Dylan.
No one wants me to sing.
I promise you this.
I can give you 150 reasons why.
The first reason is that I actually can do a really good impression, and no one needs to hear it.
But if I have more of that beer that I was talking about previously, it might come out.
And I apologize in advance because...
It's not.
I know a lot of people are a huge fan of the artists.
I don't happen to be one of them, but obviously I have a lot of respect.
Cultural icon, epic performer from what I've seen and heard, and a lot of followers.
No one's people...
No one wants a part of this.
So fun fact, I was raised by hippies, so there was a fair amount of this artist playing around the home because they liked sort of that folksy guitar.
Oh, good.
So Dawn and Ray are tied, points-wise.
Followed up.
And so Spot and George.
Tied for a laugh.
Bob, open topic. Go ahead.
I didn't hear the free software song.
Is there a free software song? I haven't heard it.
I don't know if it's just made up or maybe there should be one.
And maybe it should be...somebody should start a GitHub repo for free open source software song.
And maybe somebody can compose it. We can contribute to it.
Make it a medley.
And what kind of license should it be under if there is a song?
I don't know if there is a license even for songs, but maybe somebody knows.
But maybe there should even be a legal aspect.
I know a lot of repetition of the word song.
I don't know if we have one. There was that SUSE Chameleon one a while ago where they dressed up and there was a video and everything.
And it was based on what does the fox say, I think.
So there is that melody floating around.
But I also don't know of a particular musical number.
Oh, sorry. Is that pausing?
What's that pausing? Okay.
What kind of would this be? Would it be like those communist ditties that they...
Alright, George, since you're holding the mic anyway, freets. Like fives.
Fence. Fives. Otherwise...
So freets are made from potatoes and they are fried.
And I'm not sure if they were invented in France.
But I do remember that one time I was driving, I'm from the US, I was driving across the country from Michigan to Oregon.
And I stopped at a place in the middle of Wyoming and looked at the menu and on the menu they had freedom fries.
They said menu twice.
Well, you never know what the story was.
But I get a good point about whoever invented the food. I mean, I always wonder the same thing.
Whichever civilization first invented this...
Now I'm from the South.
That was a good win.
Alright, mic goes back to Dahon.
The topic is open source.
I have made a career out of the stock technology and have been working in it for more than 20 years.
So it's been a really, really long time. I really like it. Big companies just pay me to do this.
So I get to hang out with really cool, fun people.
I get to travel the world and go to conferences and give talks and hang out at places like this.
And I get to work on software that anybody can see. It's fun. The people are fantastic.
It's an amazing community.
I get to come to this dev room every year at this event. I get to go to other events.
I don't understand what the big deal about open source is.
I mean, I went to the doctor and my doctor was very clear that this was not something that I should keep having.
And I really ought to use the cream to just clear it up.
So it's holding the mic anyway. Penguins.
A penguin bit me once and it made me want to go and write code.
And I don't know why that is, but I think it might have been sick.
And I'm not an expert in animal diseases in any real sense, but I don't that doesn't seem like it makes any real logical progression.
How would that animal infect me with the desire to be at my keyboard?
But I really I need to spend less time at the zoo.
And if I was able to, you know, be in other places, maybe a museum, maybe a bookstore, possibly a restaurant,
there would be less risk of being attacked by a feral creature.
I find myself in these situations far too often.
And I think that my life choices are generally poor and I really regret so many things that I have done.
And this is becoming a confessional.
And I hope that you all can appreciate that I'm bearing my soul to you right now, all because of a black and white thing and its tendencies.
All right. We're getting closer to the end.
Don and Ray still tied, spot catching up with one point behind Don and Ray.
So once we get to George, we'll do one last round.
Oops, did we drop a.
That's good that I have no idea how the points are scored.
Every time you test someone challenges somebody else and they get the challenge and they finish the time.
It's one point if you get your if you do the full minute like you have, you get two points.
Yeah. All right.
Community building community building.
So I've been in this since 2014 when I started.
I think there was a lot of discussion about why does this job need to even exist.
People didn't understand what the value was.
And I think that's obviously changed.
I don't have to justify my existence anymore like I used to.
But now the challenge is like where in the organization does it belong.
It's like existential question.
I think the contribution to the company and the bottom line is pretty clear.
But people don't know like who my boss should be.
What the what the metrics should be.
But like everything else I think it's just constantly evolving and hopefully we'll continue to grow.
It's nice to see like a dev rooms like this that are very popular and people want to talk about him and discuss him and debate him.
Wow.
I think I said that.
All right. Does anyone have a topic suggestion for George.
Okay.
All right. The cloud.
The cloud is a very fuzzy concept that was invented.
It was first described my understanding was in 2006 with Amazon Web servers using Zen which was the first open source virtual hypervisor which was available for them to use.
And it spread from there and it spread from computing to data and storing data on someone else's hard drive instead of using someone else's computer.
And then to cloud documents like Google Docs and then everyone thought that software as a service was a great thing and a way to lock people in and prevented free software.
So now you can't modify the software that you're using.
All right. Last round.
Don your topic is traveling by plane.
Traveling by plane. This is one of one of my favorite things to do.
I actually probably prefer traveling by train.
But sadly so I live in the UK. We have lots of rail transportation but I can't get back to see my family.
I can't get back to the U.S. where a lot of the cool conferences are without traveling by air.
So I fly Delta a lot which is nice because I have status and so I get extra things I get to sit in the lounge and drink free champagne which is pretty cool.
And I spend a lot of my time in these these little tubes where I still wear a mask because they are just gigantic germ factories with people breathing all over each other for 10 hours straight.
The food is terrible. But on those international ones they give you.
OK. Spot crabs.
Well my doctor. No I'm not going to do that.
Recently I was in the position of having a lot of money at my disposal.
And of course the first thing that came to my mind was crabs.
So I went on a quest to find a vendor who would be able to take a design that I had found on the Internet that was very popular.
It was very orange and pinchy. And I said to them can you make a lot of these.
And then they responded. Who is this. And I said it does not matter. I have money. Just do it.
And they did. And a year later these boxes started to show up in the warehouse and they were full of plushy goodness.
The kind that makes you think am I at a seafood restaurant by mistake but you're not.
You're in this place where there's shelves and inside the plastic wrap its little eyes look at you and you can't help but feel abject terror because you know that this should not exist.
And you have done something that is against the laws of nature.
All right.
And get up.
So what a lot of things to say about this.
I've been using it for the past two years and before that I worked at a competing platform get lab.
So it took me a long time to get used to the new like interface.
And I struggle quite a bit with it. But now I guess you know after two years it's it's I can't even tell the difference between the two platforms.
It's kind of ironic. A lot of open source software are hosted on this on this on this platform but the platform itself is not open source.
So the irony continues.
But you know I'm not a really I'm not a I don't get religious about a lot of things including like whether it's something should be freely available with source code or not because I use a I use a lot of Apple products and they're obviously not open source.
Well that kind of concludes unless you want to keep going. People need to like start throwing some topics at our panelists. If not our winner today is Dawn followed very closely by Ray and Scott who caught up.
Oh sorry. Sorry George. So yep.
One more. You're right you're right you're right. Absolutely. On the topic of that how about lunch. Not us going to lunch which we could but topic is lunch.
Yesterday for lunch at Fos
Dem. I knew that there would be long queues and so I went to the grocery store and bought some food ahead of time.
And that was very lovely. I when I became hungry I went outside and I opened my bag and I opened the packages and I consumed what was inside the packages and I didn't.
Well where I come from there's this thing that we do when we're hungry and it's important that you get the deep fryer out to start with because if he ain't gonna burn your neighborhood down you're doing it wrong.
So what you've got to do is you've got to put the oil in and then you find the food and then you put the food in and then you.
However I was unable to go to the establishment that that sold nourishment.
Well done George.
Well thank you all for playing along. We thought we'd try something different this year. We'll see how if we do this again next year but Dawn's still the winner.
Tied by Spot and Ray. I did. I did buy a prize for each of you however yours isn't vegan. So I'll have to get you something or there's more cake.
Otherwise thank you for playing along. I know that we ended a bit early but maybe.