So you are almost having like asynchronous Q&A session.
And I, you know, that just makes life easier for a lot of people, including presenters,
right?
Because you know what to sort of expect.
The last one is sort of similar.
I saw this, like, Linux Foundation did this like a few years ago.
I made a presentation, again, with Sophia on documentation.
And then there was like a Slack channel for Q&A's.
And after our presentation, we were on there for like 30, 45 minutes, which I thought was
great.
Because typically, like when you're at a convention center, you kind of get shoot out after your
presentation.
So people only have like a five minute window to ask you questions, like if you ran out
of time, right?
This just gave us a lot more time to answer questions.
And also for people to be, you know, vocal with their comments and feedback, which I
thought was great.
And I made sure that I let a lot of people know that I thought that was pretty awesome.
So I know I'm almost out of time.
So I think I've covered most of these.
So it's not either or.
The virtual events can complement what you're doing, like, in person.
And you know, just remember that we've been doing like a virtual collaboration for a long
time.
And this is definitely an important toolkit to help community members.
And then especially for people who can't always travel for whatever reason, financial or otherwise.
And the final point I want to make, actually, we did platforms that we're using for online
events, like including Hoppin.
I mean, I'm not saying that's my favorite tool, but even Hoppin has really evolved over
time.
And one of the things I noticed when I talked to event manager and vendors is that they'll
give a list of here the virtual event platforms that we support.
One company, they provided like 15 logos, including like Hoppin.
So there are just more alternatives available.
So I think we have better platforms and tools to run events virtually.
And yeah, I just I think that's it.
I just want to make sure I have time for questions.
Hopefully you were able to hear me out there.
Great, because it's you, you can do one question, even though we're over time, because we think
you're awesome.
All right, thank you.
Anyone want to ask a question?
I see a hand.
Off we go.
You are the final question of the community, Deborah, for FOSDAM 2023.
Congratulations.
Well, thank you very much for the talk.
We have a global market, but obviously we don't have big resources like big companies.
So I wonder how much it is to put up with not to set up the whole logistic of the virtual
event live streaming.
Yeah, because we definitely have a global market.
So obviously you can't be relying on everyone assistant to your event if you do it in person.
But I'm thinking probably best thing is to just record it and then put it available online
a week later or something like that, rather than having to live stream it as a proper
hybrid event.
What do you think?
Yeah, well, I mean, so the question for people online, you know, because even Zoom is not
free, right?
And then, you know, is it okay to sort of, you know, prerecord things and make content
available for people to like consume and ask questions to?
I think that's completely valid.
Actually, one of the things I learned from these vendors, they don't, on a virtual platform,
they actually don't encourage you to have like a live presentation and a Q&A because
there's just a lot more technical difficulty you can run through.
So they call it senior lives.
They prefer that they have the presenter record and be available for 10 minutes of questioning
as an example.
But, you know, if you don't want to have person available 10 minutes online for questioning,
you can still have like a creative Google Doc, like here's a recording, please submit
your questions over this period of time and the presenter or other people can answer them.
So there's all documented, right?
So I think that's completely valid.
So you don't have to use Zoom.
I mean, I just happened to be, I've been using Zoom for the past few years so that's what
I'm comfortable with, but you can do live streaming from Google Hangout.
I haven't tried it hands on myself, but I know it's doable.
So that's an option.
By having something prerecorded available on YouTube channel, but here's a documentation,
it could be a Wiki page or Google Docs, please submit your questions.
We'll close the questioning in like seven days and, you know, whoever the presenter
was, whoever the content expert is, we'll get back to you with their answers.
So I think that's a completely valid thing to do.
It doesn't have to be like 100% interactive.