Here today at FOSDEM I am going to be talking about contributor growth strategies, how to
get more contributors for your open source project.
Today I'll start by talking about the factors that can impact contributor growth and why
it can be so incredibly challenging before moving into some strategies for growing your
contributor base, using contributor ladders to help people move into leadership positions.
Then finally I'll talk about some metrics you can use to measure project sustainability.
Then we'll look at a few resources and give you some final thoughts.
First, I'll tell you a teeny tiny bit about me.
I've been in the technology industry for well over 20 years, working mostly on open source
projects from within companies like Intel, Puppet, and now VMware, I'm responsible for
our open source community strategy within the open source program office.
I'm a board member of Open UK, I'm a governing board member and maintainer for the Linux
Foundation's Chaos Metrics project, I'm co-chair of the CNCF contributor strategy technical
advisory group, and I also have a PhD from the University of Greenwich where I researched
how people collaborate within the Linux kernel.
Let's start by talking more about why it can be so hard to achieve contributor growth.
In this section we'll talk about some of the issues people face that can impact the sustainability
of contributions along with the vicious cycle that people often face when trying to balance
the time required to maintain the project versus the time to onboard new contributors.
The reality is we are not mindless automatons.
We have feelings, we have bad days, we have other commitments and personal challenges
in our lives that are often invisible to the other contributors within the project and
they can get in the way of our contributions to open source projects.
Maybe it can be squishy, we can be unpredictable and irrational, especially when we're stressed
out, when we're overworked, when we're burnt out.
But you can't have an open source project without actually having people to maintain
it, so you need to be able to encourage people to participate in ways that are sustainable
not just for the project but also for those people as human beings.
Many projects struggle to find people who will actively participate in their projects
and continue to participate over the long term.
If it was easy, you would all have all of the people you needed to maintain your project
and I'd be in an empty room and none of you would be watching this talk.
But we're in a situation now where there are lots of open source projects and just frankly
not enough contributors.
Maintainers are burning out and are in desperate need of help.
And sometimes it can be really difficult to get people to contribute to your project.
And unfortunately there's no magic behind this, there's no one size fits all solution.
But throughout this talk I will focus on some things that you can do to increase the chances
of successfully building a community and then growing more contributors for your project.
Building an open source project is hard work and it extends out over many years.
And maintainer burnout is common with an open source project.
Even the really big successful projects like Kubernetes struggle with maintainer burnout
and growing the contributor community.
It can be hard for already overworked maintainers to balance the day to day work required to
keep the project running while also investing in additional activity to increase future
community sustainability.
So this creates a vicious cycle where maintainers don't have enough time to onboard new contributors
leading to fewer contributors which leads back to no time to onboard new contributors.
And while it takes a bit more time up front, if you can invest some time in activities
that will help onboard new contributors like onboarding documentation for example, you
can increase the chances that you can break out of this vicious cycle.
Another way to free up some time for maintainers to break out of this cycle is by getting help
for different types of contributions that take up valuable time and are required to
make an open source project successful.
So think about things like documentation, marketing, community management and loads
of other things.
And for projects with really complex code bases, it can sometimes be a lot easier to
onboard people into some of these roles first to help free up some time to onboard other
contributors later.
Now next up, let's talk about developing and executing on a long-term contributor growth
strategy including motivation, governance, new contributor onboarding, mentoring and
leadership.
People's motivations for contributing to your project vary widely.
Some people are contributing as part of their job while others might contribute to gain
experience or maybe learn more about a particular technology.
And you don't really have any control whatsoever over what motivated people to show up.
But there are things that you can do to motivate them to stick around regardless of why they
showed up in the first place.
Clear communication and reducing friction are key to helping people stick around.
And I'll talk more in upcoming slides about the importance of explicit and clearly communicated
governance along with solid onboarding docs and fostering a welcoming and inclusive community.
But there are other things you can do to help motivate people to contribute.
Having good first issues or help wanted labels are excellent places to start because these
help contributors find something that they can work on while they learn more about the
project.
So good first issues should be targeted as something very simple that a brand new contributor
can just pick up and do in a very quick amount of time.
It helps them learn more about the contribution process.
And then help wanted labels are for issues that maybe are a little bit more complicated
and take a little bit more time so that people who've already started to contribute can find
something else to work on next.
And good first issues and help wanted labels are passive requests for help, right?
But I also encourage maintainers to be proactive and specific about ways that people can help.
Asking someone specific to review a PR or maybe answer a question in Slack or some other
forum from a user demonstrates that you recognize their expertise and that you want their help
specifically.
And going back to the discussion about squishy humans, knowing that we're appreciated makes
us feel good, right?
Which can be a strong motivator to participate in an open SARS project.
Now I know a lot of people like to really hate on governance.
It's just paperwork, it's busy work, nobody likes it, it just gets in the way of doing
the real work on the project.
But this really isn't true of good governance.
And good governance is really about setting expectations and getting all of the people
in the community collaborating together.
And ultimately the focus of open source project governance is on people.
The roles we play, our responsibilities, how we make decisions, and what we should expect
from each other as participating in the community.
The goal should be to make the processes for participation as obvious as possible.
Even for people who are brand new to the community.
So having clear rules about how collaboration occurs, how decisions are made, and what types
of contributions are in or out of scope really helps community members make contributions
that are likely to be accepted and embraced by the project.
This helps avoid wasting maintainers' time for contributions that just aren't aligned
with the project at all.
And a healthy project with clear governance makes contributors happy and helps set the
project up for success and future growth.
Now another aspect of governance is about making it easier for people to move into positions
of increasing responsibility to help reduce the load on existing maintainers.
We'll talk more about this later in the section about contributor ladders and leadership.
But the good news is you don't have to start from scratch.
We have some good templates with instructions that we've developed at the CNCF.
But they apply to most projects so they can help you quickly and easily build out some
really basic governance for your project.
Now I suspect that some of you are still thinking that you really don't need to spend time on
governance.
But think about this from the perspective of the new contributor.
It's a lot more difficult to participate in a project or participate in a community if
you don't know anything about the role that you might play, the expectations, the key
players, or the roles for participating.
So explicit documented governance gives new and existing contributors a clear path to
guide them through your project.
And spending a bit of time, you don't spend a lot but just a bit of time documenting governance
up front can help save you time later with fewer questions about how things work.
And it gives you a document that you can point people to if they have questions.
Now when I start contributing to a new open source project, I want to know how decisions
are made and who makes those decisions which helps me understand whether decisions are
likely to be made fairly by people with the expertise to make those decisions.
And I also want to see a clear path into leadership for me or for my colleagues if we decide to
stick around in the project over the long term.
But the bottom line is that if the process for collaboration and decision making are
not clearly documented as part of the project governance, this introduces a lot of uncertainty
and increases the barrier to contribution while also jeopardizing the long term health
and viability of the project.
I see so many open source projects with contributing guides that don't actually provide any useful
information about contributing to the project.
At a minimum, a new contributor needs to understand how to spin up an environment where they can
do their development, the expectations for testing and how to run those tests, any processes
or expectations you have around things like pull requests or issues, and instructions
for other requirements like maybe they need to sign a CLA or sign their commits using
the DCO process.
Now if this is well documented, contributors can get started with a minimal amount of help
from existing maintainers which can save you a lot of time in the long run.
And when a project doesn't have good onboarding docs, maintainers can get frustrated by the
amount of time they spend on new contributor questions.
And it can make it hard for contributors to feel welcome and take them longer to become
productive.
Now this does not mean that you need to spend days and days and weeks and weeks writing
the perfect onboarding documentation for your project.
Anything is better than nothing.
And if you just start with a few things that can help people get started quickly, new contributors
can actually help make the onboarding documents better by adding more details and additional
instructions for things that they found confusing or that they had struggled with.
Your project should also be designed to keep diversity, equity and inclusion top of mind.
Building a diverse community where people feel welcome and included doesn't just happen.
It does require putting at least some thought into it.
But it's really time well spent providing an environment where everyone including people
from marginalized populations feel safe is the first step toward building a diverse community
for your project.
Ideally having programs that give people opportunities for things like shadowing, mentoring, sponsoring
new potential leaders can help you grow a diverse set of people into new leadership
within your project.
The Kubernetes contributor experience SIG is a great place to see some examples of how
to implement some of these programs for things like shadowing and mentoring.
Projects that make a concerted effort to bring in new people from a variety of backgrounds
and have programs in place to help them grow into leadership positions are more likely
to benefit from increased innovation and just have a healthier contributor community.
And by having a diverse and welcoming community, you have the advantage of getting contributors
that might not feel welcome in other projects.
Now this, I gave it its own section but it's really still kind of part of the strategy
section but it's important enough to call out separately since moving people into leadership
positions really is a key part of growing your contributor base and scaling your project.
So I'll talk about this in the context of contributor ladders which is a good way to
do this.
Defining the roles and responsibilities for contributors, reviewers, maintainers can help
with recruiting new people into these roles.
It can help to really think of this as a ladder where contributors can climb up to become
reviewers and those reviewers can become maintainers and what's important is to document it and
make sure that people understand how they can climb this ladder and move into positions
with more responsibility within the project.
A contributor ladder usually outlines the different roles within the project along with
responsibilities and privileges that come with them.
Community members generally start at the first levels of the ladder and then they advance
up as their involvement in the project grows.
So for each rung of the ladder you can define responsibilities which are the things that
a contributor is expected to do.
Requirements are the qualifications that a person needs to be put in that role.
And then privileges are maybe some things that those contributors are entitled to do
as a part of that position.
And all of this helps set expectations for roles and encourages people to think about
how they might take on additional responsibilities within the project.
And as you get more people moving into maintainer roles you can reduce the load of the existing
maintainers.
Now the good news is that there is like with many things also a template so you can avoid
building this from scratch.
Now this template has probably more roles than most projects need but it's intended
to be simplified and customized for your project.
Project leadership is one of the key elements of good governance and this is how you scale
your project.
So you should have some kind of documentation about your leadership.
For small projects maybe you just have a list of maintainers that indicates which people
are responsible for which things.
And there are quite a few different options for selecting leaders as part of defining
your governance and the ideal is to have a process that provides a fair and level playing
field that defines how contributors can become leaders and this should be documented so that
all participants can clearly understand the criteria and the process for moving into leadership
positions.
Now some of the bigger projects like Kubernetes for example have an election process at least
for the top levels of leadership like a steering committee.
But only the biggest projects actually need something that complicated.
Most projects have a relatively simple process where the existing leaders or existing maintainers
get to select the new ones.
So for example new maintainers are often nominated by existing maintainers and maybe approved
after a certain number of maintainers have agreed to it or maybe there's a voting process.
And there are loads of different options for selecting leaders for a project so I won't
go into all of them but there is a wrote a document for the CNCF that kind of describes
some different options.
But the key is to spend some time thinking about this as you document your governance
and as you build your contributor ladder so that you can bring new people into leadership
positions and reduce the load on the existing maintainers to help scale your project by
growing your contributor base.
Now granted mentoring takes a bit more time but it's a good way to help existing contributors
become even better with an eye toward moving them into leadership positions.
So for busy maintainers one good approach is to focus on mentoring people who've already
been around a while and are unlikely to disappear and help them learn to do maybe some more
complex time consuming tasks.
Like with many things mentoring isn't something that's all or nothing and you can time by
box it to whatever time you can fit in your schedule.
So this doesn't have to be hours and hours and hours every week.
Even spending an hour, a month or an hour a week to help someone quickly become productive
in some part of your project can be time well spent if that person can then take on a few
tasks that help you reduce your load as a maintainer.
You can even structure this as shadowing and allow them to watch you and learn while you
do some maintainer tasks that you're going to do anyways.
And if you focus this on helping someone learn to do something that can free up your time
later then this will be time well spent.
Now the strategic part of all of this comes in to thinking about where your time would
be best spent.
I've given a lot of suggestions so far in this presentation and you should not try to
do everything at once.
So I recommend you think strategically about where you start.
If you know you've had people interested in contributing but they've given up when they
couldn't get started then maybe you focus on onboarding docs.
If you have a lot of casual contributors who come around occasionally and contribute things
maybe you focus on the contributor ladder and governance to help some of them move up
to take on more responsibility and eventually move into leadership positions.
One way to figure out the best place to start is by using metrics.
So I'm a big fan of metrics and data for those who know me but this can help you find problem
areas and figure out where you should be spending your time.
Time is precious right?
So it's important to identify problem areas so that you can focus on the right things
while avoiding wasting time on things that maybe are already going okay or going really
well.
However metrics do need to be interpreted in light of how you operate as a community
and the other things happening in your project and there's no one size fits all interpretation
for metrics but I will talk in this section about what some trends might indicate and
how you can think about addressing them.
One key area to look at for your project is responsiveness.
So in this project in this graph you can see that there are times when they have a lot
of PRs in the backlog that need to be merged or closed.
Now if these PRs are coming from several regular contributors who aren't maintainers maybe
it's a good time to look at how you can promote some of those contributors to become maybe
reviewers, approvers, maintainers to help with the workload.
Now as with any metrics you need to interpret them in light of your project.
So there are other things that can cause an increase in the backlog like everyone preparing
for a big release or maybe there's a big conference coming up or it's vacation season in Europe
that just are not resolved by moving people into leadership roles.
So you have to think about maybe why you have this backlog and what might help resolve it.
It can also help to look at the types of contributors that you have.
So in this case casual contributors are those drive-through contributors who make just a
handful of contributions and then you never see them again.
Regular contributors are the ones that make some contributions and stick around so they
continue to make some contributions but maybe not a ton of contributions and then core contributors
are usually the maintainers who make most of the contributions and stick around over
the long term.
Now you can really learn a lot from this graph actually.
If you have a very small number of casual and regular contributors this can mean that
people don't have the information needed to become productive and contribute.
So in some cases onboarding docs can help solve this issue.
Another thing that this graph can indicate is whether maybe you have some fundamental
issues within your project that are driving people away.
So if you see the total number of contributors declining or the number of regular contributors
declining this can indicate some deeper issues maybe with toxic community members or an unwelcoming
environment that probably needs to be resolved before you take any other actions to grow
the community.
Or it could mean people are leaving your community for some other reasons.
Maybe lack of responsiveness is another one.
Now this metric is often called the bus factor, pony factor, lottery factor based on the idea
that if one person or a small number of people disappeared maybe after winning the lottery
that the project would possibly be completely screwed because they're making all of the
contributions.
So I recommend measuring this because there are a couple of things I can tell you.
So first of all it tells you how big of an issue this is for your current contributor
situation.
If it's like this one, this is a big issue and you should focus on getting some more
contributors that can be moved into leadership roles.
You might also find that there are people contributing more than you realized which
is the other reason that this is a good metric.
This can help you think about who you can encourage to contribute more or maybe find
someone who can move up the ladder into a leadership role and reaching out to someone
and acknowledging their work while encouraging them to do a bit more can help quite a bit
with contributor growth.
Sometimes people just need a bit of encouragement.
As I mentioned earlier you can ask people for specific things that you know they're
good at.
There are several communities that I've gotten more involved in or involved in in the first
place because someone asked for my specific help and kind of made me feel wanted within
that community.
Now before I wrap up this talk I'm going to leave you with a few resources that you might
find useful.
I've mentioned the CNCF contributor strategy technical advisory group a couple of times.
We have a governance working group and a contributor growth working group which provide templates
and guidance about contributor experience, sustainability, governance, that sort of thing
to help people develop strategies for maintaining healthy projects.
So resources are designed for CNCF projects but most of what we talk about applies just
about any open source project.
The open source way guidebook has loads of really great details about building and maintaining
open source projects.
The chaos project has loads of metrics definitions and software which you could see in my metric
slides that you can use to measure the health of your open source community.
And these are all great starting places for understanding how to grow your contributor
community.
And I just mentioned the contributor strategy tag on the resources slide but I wanted to
put in a really quick recruiting plug.
Like with most open source projects we're also looking for help.
We don't have enough people to contribute.
And anyone's welcome to join our meetings if you want to learn about us or even better
if you're passionate about contributor growth, governance, or related topics and want to
help CNCF projects improve in those areas.
We'd love to have you join us and help us develop resources and provide advice to projects.
And this slide has several ways to find us and get involved.
So with that said let me leave you with just a few final thoughts.
Maintaining an open source project is so much work and there are so many maintainers who
are overworked, exhausted, burning out.
And the best way to address this challenge is by growing your contributor base.
But it's hard work.
It takes time away from the day to day activities now which can be really hard to justify when
you feel like you're barely keeping up as it is.
But in the longer term spending at least a little time on things that can help you recruit
and keep new contributors will be worth it in the long run.
And hopefully some of the templates and resources that I provided will help you get started
with some of this work.
And as I've mentioned before you don't need to do everything at once.
Taking just a little time on something to grow your contributor base is a great way
to start.
Thank you for coming to my talk and we can open it up for questions.
That was very easy.
Thank you Don.
I have a question about the lottery factor.
Do you have any advice on how to measure or how to take into account quality not just
enumerating the quantity of commits that various contributions make?
So the question is how to take into account quality versus quantity.
Just quantity, yeah.
Yeah I think that that's something you have to, so you're not going to be able to measure
the quality really well instead of a quantitative way, right?
But I think it's something, again it gets at interpretation.
So I think it's something that you need to really think about.
So there might be somebody that has loads of commits for some particular reason, but
maybe they're not a major contributor to the project for some other reason.
Maybe they're not a maintainer.
Maybe it wouldn't be a big deal if they left tomorrow.
Maybe they're working on something that's fairly niche that not a lot of people use,
for example.
So I think you really do need to interpret those graphs.
And you can think about the quality of what someone does.
If you've got someone who makes a ton of commits and they're kind of crap, then that's not
as important as someone who makes a lot of commits that are really great.
So you just need to, I think, apply a reality filter on top of it.
But I don't think it's something that you can really easily measure quantitatively,
but you need to just think about and kind of put a qualitative filter on top of it.
Yeah.
Other questions?
Hi.
First off, great talk.
The question about the governance side, because I work on a pretty big open source project,
but the problem there is that it's owned by a company that doesn't really necessarily
value open sources, like one of their core reasons why they do it.
So do you have any recommendations for how to advocate for governance in big open source
projects or company-owned projects?
Yeah.
It's really hard to advocate for governance in company-owned projects.
I've tried to do it and failed in certain projects in the past.
What I found is usually the best way to approach it is to get them to document the way things
work now.
So not worry about changing all of the governance, not worry about coming up with some big elaborate
governance structure, but how do people get moved into committed roles now?
How do they get moved up?
And try to encourage companies.
And this is something I have this discussion internally within VMware all the time, too,
is we hire people to work on certain open source projects.
And so they get commit or status kind of automatically.
And we should be as transparent as possible about that in our governance materials, for
example, that they do get special treatment as of the fact that it's a VMware open source
project and we're paying them to do the work.
So they're going to be able to commit from day one.
So I think being transparent about that, as transparent as possible, can help.
But I would say work with them to document what they have right now.
And then maybe people will start to see the gaps and you can try to build on it.
But it's hard.
It's really hard to get good governance for company on projects.
It's a tough problem.
Thanks for your talk.
About the lottery factor.
I'm not sure if you mentioned it or anything.
But I'm going to see.
All right.