Thank you so much, Ray.
Can we get a round of applause for Ray, please?
Thank you.
You figured something would go wrong, but this was resolved pretty quickly.
So thanks for sticking around.
Last session of the dev room.
It's really good to be back in person, and I realize the irony of talking about virtual events when we're all together,
but bear with me.
So my name is Ray Paik.
Currently, we have a community at CUBE.
If you're not familiar with CUBE, we're in the semantic layer space of data analytics.
So if you want to find out more, check out our website at cube.dev.
And you can, for now, I'm still on Twitter.
I'm like a lot of people trying to figure out what to do with Twitter,
but you can reach out to me on Twitter or LinkedIn or other social platforms where you can find me.
And if you came to my session like three years ago in 2020, back then I was working at GitLab,
where I also done a lot of virtual activities.
So in addition to having a lot of experience along with all of you with virtual events,
I went to sort of share what we all collectively learned about getting together in virtual formats.
So what we'll talk about is, I mean, first of all, I wanted to sort of step back and talk about why we even have events in open source.
I mean, a lot of us are, you know, even before pandemic, we work really well across different time zones,
different cultures, asynchronously.
But we invest a lot of time and money in events.
And I just want to briefly talk about why.
And then what we learned, especially in the early days of the pandemic, like the experience was in, you know,
I think universally not great with virtual events, but I wanted to sort of discuss what we learned over the past couple of years.
And I also want to talk about events that actually work relatively well in a virtual format.
And I think that's why virtual events aren't necessarily going away.
It'll be in a different, you know, improved format.
But I want to talk about some topics or formats where, you know, virtual events actually setting actually works pretty well.
And how can you even complement or enhance the in-person events like this one?
So I think all of these photos are from pre-pandemic.
I just looked at like a different events, like, you know, one on your top left, I guess, on your top left.
That's from CubeCon. It's like a huge event that gets more than 10,000 people typically. Right.
I don't know what the number was in Detroit last year, but, you know, it's like a huge event, you know, almost a week long.
And the other picture, it's sort of the other end of the spectrum. I mean, in that picture somewhere, I can't remember where I am because it's been like four years.
But that's KDE Academy. They get together like once a year for almost a week.
And I mean, this was like a sort of good way for me to get introduced to the community.
I didn't know anything about KDE or what even, you know, what the difference was between KDE and GNOME.
But they really made me feel welcome. And it was a good way for me to get sort of onboarded and introduce to people in the community.
So I definitely enjoy that. And even at large conferences like CubeCon or like OpenStack, you know, I mean, I get I need to remember to call them Open Infrastructure Foundation.
But one of the things I like about a lot of these conferences is that they have like a developer hacking room.
So like a hacking lounge. So even if you've been contributing or working on something for a long time, you get a chance to sort of work together with somebody like in person in a more intimate setting.
And I mean, I find myself sort of hiding in like a developer lounges with a lot of other developers.
So like, you know, all these sessions are great.
You know, ability to sort of interact with other people in person and collaborating are obviously a great benefit of these large events.
But I think what like a lot of people, what I appreciate the most is, I mean, Bruce just talked about it, the ability to sort of form personal relationship with somebody in person.
This is really difficult to do virtually. Like, you know, you can work with somebody collaboratively for years.
But, you know, you're not going to go much beyond like having a great professional relationship with somebody.
I made a lot of good friends in Open Source over the past several years. And I guarantee you some of that happened in very informal settings.
Like there's something intimate about sharing a beer or sharing a meal with somebody and that you can't get over Zoom or whatever platform you use to collaborate with somebody.
And especially if you had like, you know, maybe you had some conflict with somebody over meetings, like the direction of the project, how you're implementing something.
Those tend to all go away if you share a meal with somebody. I mean, I had so many instances of that happening.
So, you know, being able to meet with somebody and in a more relaxed setting is something I really look forward to.
And I took a picture, I found this picture of a hallway because I think the great benefit of these conferences is a hallway track.
And then I don't know if you did the same thing. When I was putting together my schedule for FOSM, like I was trying to look at which sessions that I'm going to,
I also reached out to the friends that I knew who were going to be here and tried to decide when am I going to meet you for lunch?
When am I going to go get together for, you know, for a beer at our favorite bar near Grand Place?
So that hallway track is, you know, obviously it's probably the one of the most important tracks that I look forward to in every conference.
Unfortunately, this all came crashing to a halt like three years ago.
I mean, I don't know if you were here at FOSM in 2020. I mean, shortly after that sort of world stopped, right?
And then, you know, a lot of people made herculean efforts to move events online.
I remember, like I presented at an event like in April. I mean, this is something that was sort of a local large meetup kind of thing in the Bay Area.
They were scheduling for a while for devl people. And I mean, they did a wonderful job like moving everything onto like Hoppin.
Like, I mean, I think before then, I didn't even know what Hoppin was.
They had some technical difficulties, even though I went through some speaker training on a platform.
But despite all that, they did a wonderful job of sort of moving things quickly online in about, I mean, they only had about a month to do it.
Having said all that, what were our experiences with virtual events in the early days?
And I mean, I found these pictures, and this is probably how a lot of us felt when events moved online.
And it's not just because we missed the hallway track or, you know, networking session over beer.
A lot of people, I think, talked about Zoom fatigue. They were just tired of, you know, having more interactions with Zoom.
I don't think I struggled with that as much because I was used to having a lot of Zoom meeting anyways.
What I struggled with, what I found out was that I'll attend a session. There'll be like a 45-minute session,
and then they give you a 10-15 minute break because that's how the events were used to run,
because you need to move to a different room to get to the next session.
During those 10-15 minutes, like, I didn't have anything else to do.
So what I do is I'll check, like, Slack or email from work, right?
I mean, when I'm at a conference like this, I'm pretty good at compartmentalizing.
I tell myself, I'm not going to check Slack until, like, lunchtime or morning break or whatever it is.
But when I was sitting at home, same place where I work at all day, I can get easily distracted and I'll check a Slack message.
It wasn't urgent, but I'll respond to it, and then I realize, like, 20 minutes later, oh, shoot, this other session I was going to go to,
I'm 10 minutes late to it. So I might as well just watch the recording then, right?
So I was, I think I was getting, like, really confused.
Like, am I at work or am I at a conference?
Because I couldn't tell because I'm just my same home office.
That's what I struggled with, and I think that's why the experience was really bad because they were trying to force-fit in-person event
and they were trying to keep the same format but move it onto whatever platform that people were using.
And that obviously didn't work very well.
Because, you know, I think what we realize now is that you don't need a 15-minute break, right?
You can just move to a next session.
I mean, you don't want to do that for eight hours, but you don't want people to be, like, switching to a different mode all of a sudden,
like, because you have a 15-minute break.
So I think that's one of the things that I really struggle with in the early days.
But if you think about, like, because I think when we thought of events before the pandemic,
we always thought about these, like, almost week-long conferences like KubeCon, or even, like, KD Academy that's almost a week long.
You're away at a different location for about almost a week.
But if you think about it, before the pandemic, a lot of us in open source were doing a lot of collaboration work, like, on a virtual platform
and not necessarily in person.
Like, Hackathon is a good example.
I mean, this is something, you know, I helped start, like, when I was at GitLab.
We once a quarter, community members will get together for two days, and then we'll just, you know,
you don't have to commit to be, you know, at the Hackathon for 48 hours, but whatever time you can commit to in those two days,
like, we're willing to encourage, like, contributions from the community.
So obviously, the metrics we looked at was how many contributions we're getting.
Those are, like, this is something that we can count and measure.
But what was more gratifying, I mean, at the end of my, like, two-plus years at GitLab,
what I noticed during Hackathon is that there's just a lot more chatter on our online, like, chat platform,
like, we're using GitLab at the time, and more people are helping each other,
and then community members are forming connections and bonds, right?
So that was very gratifying in addition to the lot of contributions that we're getting.
So that's one example.
The other example on the top right, this is my presentation from two years ago with my friend Sophia.
So this is about documentation, like, how, you know, how to, like, really accelerate, you know,
documentation on open source projects.
And the example I gave was that, so, what I was, let me step back.
I was working at Linux Foundation at the time, and Sophia is at Ericsson.
So a lot of the networking projects in DLF, they had set release cycles,
like, either three months or six months release cycle,
and if your subproject wants to be part of the release,
there are a couple of documentation-related milestones that you need to hit.
Like, if you don't have stuff documented, sorry, you're not going to be part of the release.
That's sort of one way of us forcing documentation milestones to be met.
And first, documentation milestone is relatively simple.
You just basically, in your repo, create a subdirectory for the release.
For Project ABC, you need to have documentation structure sort of laid out with some header information and labeling.
So it's sort of a routine task, but it's not something that gets you up in the morning necessarily, but it just has to be done.
So what I suggested to Sophia was that let's make a, like, a, you know, fun event out of this.
Like, we're doing a sort of like a household chore, but let's sort of, you know, almost like gamifying it.
Let's all get together virtually for a couple of hours,
and people have people complete their documentation milestone for that release.
And then first, like, a documentation milestone for that particular release for OPNFV project happened to be like a week before FOSM.
So I contacted Sophia. I said, I'm coming to Europe anyways.
Why don't I come to Erikson in Sweden?
Because she's a documentation lead for OPNFV, but there are a couple of other Erikson people that were leading other subprojects in OPNFV.
So we'll get together in a conference room. We'll set up a bridge so people can join if they want to.
And to my surprise, like, when we started at like 10 in the morning in Stockholm, people dialed in from Nokia, like an hour ahead in Finland.
That I sort of expected because the technical steering committee chairs at Nokia, because I was pretty sure that he'd be able to sort of twist some people's arms at Nokia.
But what we found out on the audio bridge was on GoToMeeting at the time was people from Japan joined.
Like, they all got together at like an NEC office in Tokyo, and they were just going to spend 30 to 45 minutes doing the documentation work, and they were just going to go for beers.
Which was perfect, right? And so got a chance for people to get together.
And the same thing happened with some people from China.
So, I mean, we worked for like an hour and a half, two hours in Stockholm, went for lunch, and had another session.
So people from rest of Europe that were late starters, and then North American could sort of join in.
And then we saw the same thing happen, so that was pretty fun.
And then that sort of became sort of a tradition for a lot of the documentation milestones.
They just made it fun.
You don't have to be in the same city at the same time, but it gave people a chance to bond and work together.
The other example that I wanted to add, you see a lot of open source communities or commercial open source companies do this.
They do these workshops, and we did the same thing at Cube.
This is a way for us to sort of provide educational content to people, because they'll ask questions about,
we want to understand your caching feature better. How do we do data modeling?
And one of our stars, a webinar, is sitting there, odd none.
So this gave us a, not just way for us to reach people synchronously through webinar, this helped us build a content on our YouTube channel.
And this really helped. I think, I can't remember what speaker it was.
I can't remember it was Bruce, or maybe it was other speaker.
Content is really king, right? So you want to provide resources for community members that can use.
And yeah, we've been doing this even before the pandemic.
And this is something that's always been an arsenal and something that we need to take advantage of.
And there are definitely a lot of benefits of virtual events, and here are a few of them.
One is something like a webinar, it takes almost no effort to spin this up.
Like if you have a Zoom account, I guess you'll have to upgrade to Zoom webinar.
But if you're not going to have more than 100% on your training sessions,
you can just get away with your regular Zoom account for up to 100 people.
So it's pretty easy to set up and start, because it doesn't cost very much.
It allows you to do a lot of experimentation. Like a documentation is a good example.
The only cost was really setting up another audio bridge on GoToMeeting at that point.
But if you compare that to what people consider a pretty lightweight in-person event, like a meetup.
Let's say you want to schedule a meetup at one of your local community members' company for a couple of hours.
You have to figure out a room, maybe you have to order food and drinks to encourage people to come and actually feed them while they're there.
But also you may have to deal with security at your company so that people can come have access to your conference facilities.
So that's not a trivial amount of work. And it's supposedly not a full industry event.
It's a casual in-person meetup, but even that takes several hours to plan and organize.
And not just for organizers, even for community members.
If you force everything to be in person, you're going to end up incurring some costs.
I remember going to a local meetup in the Bay Area where I live.
I should have been without traffic. I should have been able to get there in 15, 20 minutes.
This was at noon on Thursday. You wouldn't necessarily expect traffic.
But for whatever reason, it took me 40 minutes to get there.
I was just rolling my eyes as I was driving. This is not good use of my time.
I'm actually commuting to go to a 2R event.
So compared to a lot of in-person stuff that we've traditionally been doing, you can do this at very low cost.
The other thing I like about the virtual events, and this is an observation. I don't know if this is scientifically true.
A lot of the virtual events, event materials seem to be available a lot quicker.
Because what happens is that if you're doing a YouTube live stream, unless you have to do an edit, it's available right away.
Even if you weren't able to join the session synchronously.
Unless you insist on doing a professional editing of the live stream, it's available right away to people in the community.
Or even people outside of the community. I think with Adna and other colleagues, we've done 15 to 20 workshops over the past year and a half.
I only had to edit one of our live stream video once.
That's because we had some technical difficulties like I did today early on with one of the panelists.
All I did was cut out the first three minutes of the video because we were just struggling with buttons.
I think that's another reason why I'm a big proponent of trying to see if you can move stuff online versus doing it in person.
I talked about documentation already. There are other things that work pretty well in open source communities in a virtual setting.
One is GitLab used to do this. I think they stopped this for a while.
Over the weekend, they do issue triaging.
If you have an open source project of decent size, you're going to have thousands and thousands of issues.
Labeling them, putting priority on them is a mundane task that's not necessarily fun.
But if you want to give people an opportunity, I think GitLab used to do this over the weekend.
You don't have to spend the whole weekend.
But any amount of time that you can contribute to helping triage issues, the big one is finding duplicate issues and merging them,
which is a great house cleaning type of thing to do.
That's another type of activity that you don't necessarily do this in person.
That's another example.
The other one is testing.
They're talking about a unit testing or functional testing.
If you have a UI team or a UX team that want to get community feedback, this doesn't have to be done in person.
This is pretty simple to do, set up online.
Pause for the other picture. That's supposed to be a tape cutting thing.
If you're doing your inaugural event, rather than insisting on trying to do this in person,
try to experiment with the content and the format, like online, because it's going to cost you a lot less.
At KEEU, we're thinking about doing our first conference sometime in September,
and we already decided this is going to be done virtually.
If we were to secure a venue all day in San Francisco, that alone is going to be pretty expensive,
and logistical challenge is going to be a lot worse.
We're going to start online and make sure that validate the format and the content
and the type of the audience that we're going after.
Then, at some point, if we're large enough to do it in person, we will have built the audience,
and then we already tested it out in a more cost-effective manner.
I talked briefly about complementing in-person events.
As we're putting together this conference later this year,
I talked to several event management vendors that have experience in both in-person, hybrid, and online events.
Every single one of them, I started talking to them in October, November last year.
One of the questions I asked is that a lot of the events are going back in person.
Are people like a bandling, like virtual or hybrid events, the answer from every single one of them was no.
There seems to be still a market for virtual events.
Then, one good example, a few of them provided was that this isn't just like broadcasting
or live streaming an in-person session that's happening like it is now.
What's happening is that a lot of companies or communities are moving things virtual almost as a separate track.
A good example was a lot of conferences have day zero events.
If you have an event that's officially starting on Tuesday, they might have something else going on on Monday.
It could be a local meetup, it could be a project team meeting,
or some open source communities do this. OpenStack used to do this. They'll have an orientation for new members.
If you want to get a good introductory overview of all the projects in OpenStack
and learning how to contribute, like submitting your first patch, for example,
they actually did this over the weekend before their conference starts on Monday.
A lot of the day zero events, I think they're moving them virtual
so that even if you can't travel on site to that conference, you can still participate.
You're broadening the audience and allowing more people to participate,
at least some portion of the event, even if you can't travel.
My suggestion, if you're going to do, I'm all for the day zero events.
I would even make this happen the week before.
Let's say that if your day zero traditionally was on Monday,
I would do this virtually on Thursday or Wednesday the week before.
The reason why I say that is that rather than people having to arrive on Sunday
to go to those days or even on Monday, they can just stay home.
They can just watch this virtually and they can just spend Monday traveling
so they spend less time away from home.
I'm sure a lot of you have children and kids like I do.
If you have to be gone for a whole week, that just creates a lot of logistical challenges.
Who's going to take her to soccer practice, etc., etc.
The less time you're away from home, I think it's a bonus.
I think you're doing your community members a big favor too.
The other thing that I like about this virtual format,
and I see this happening with FOSM too with some of the developer dev rooms,
is you're basically increasing the capacity of a lot of the talk sessions
because you're creating a parallel track that's what's happening in person.
I'd be on both sides of the CFP process.
Unfortunately, you're going to have to make some hard decisions about not accepting a talk,
which is always a hard thing to do.
By increasing the capacity, you have to deal with less of that.
Especially for first-time speakers, a lot of the conference has gotten pretty competitive
in terms of how difficult it is to get your talk accepted.
This helps potentially increase your capacity for more speakers and more discussion topics.
A couple of quick dos and don'ts.
I sort of mentioned the first one in terms of the don'ts.
When you're moving things to a virtual format,
don't do the same thing that you would have done in person.
You don't need a 10-15 minute break between every session.
You want to have some break during your conference,
but you don't want people to be distracted
because they're just watching it from their home office
or even if they're in the office, they're watching it from their desk.
They don't need the 10 minutes to walk through a different room to talk to a session.
When you have people's attention, make the most of that opportunity.
I've also seen some communities do this.
Let's say you have five, six hours of content.
You don't need to do it in one single day.
You can even split it up over two days.
I've seen some companies do this over three days.
You only have an hour to two-hour chunk that you need to schedule for
over the two-three-day period.
That might make it easier to fit stuff into your schedule.
Although that's not...
I'd be a little worried about that because
how do you make sure that people don't drop off after day one?
You have to manage that,
but that's another thing I've seen some communities and companies do.
The second one, this is the one that really drives me crazy
and I mentioned this too.
If you have stuff live-streaming,
make it available on your YouTube channel right away.
Don't have people registered to get content.
You're basically asking for people's email address so they can watch the video.
I hated one that happens.
I went to a conference a couple of months ago because our CPL was presenting.
They told us the video should be available within a week.
I said, great.
Then I went back to the event website.
They said, oh, if you want to watch the recording,
please register by providing your email address.
I think I was diplomatic.
I sent them an email and I said,
this doesn't seem very open source to me,
like if you're asking for an email.
Actually, they came back to their credit and said,
actually, if you go to the YouTube channel, you'll find it here.
It's like, why don't you then tell people that on the website?
It's like, why are you kind of hiding that fact?
It just drove me nuts.
Please don't do that.
Put a wall around your content.
Please provide your email address to download this white paper.
That doesn't sound like a white paper then.
Anyhow, I guess that's my soapbox.
If you're doing the event virtually,
don't force people to participate synchronously
because you have time zone issues.
This is why I like the model we had at GitLab.
You have a two-day window.
You can participate any time you want.
We're not asking you to spend 48 hours unless you want to.
Even if you can spend just 30 minutes over a two-day period,
that's great.
I'm not going to judge you because you have better things to do.
On the other side of the slide here,
and I was really good at this.
I'm not just saying this because you bought me beer last night.
When we did our workshop,
I was really good at putting materials available like a week in advance.
People can check out the slides.
They can prep the content.
We also have hands-on workshop on our Cloud instance called Q-Cloud.
People can actually tie it up to their data sources
and start experimenting with it.
The sooner we put it up, our scores were actually better.
Even if the slides change over the next several days,
having the content available ahead of time so that people can prep,
it just provides a lot better experience.
It also allows people to ask questions ahead of time.
You're almost having asynchronous Q&A session.
That just makes life easier for a lot of people, including presenters,
because you know what to expect.
The last one is similar.
I saw this, like Linux Foundation did this a few years ago.
I made a presentation, again with Sophia on documentation,
and then there's a Slack channel for Q&As.
After our presentation, we were on there for like 30, 45 minutes,
which I thought was great.
Typically, when you're at a convention center,
you get kind of get shoot out after your presentation,
so people only have like a five minute window to ask you questions,
like if you ran out of time.
This just gave us a lot more time to answer questions.
Also, for people to be vocal with their comments and feedback,
which I thought was great,
and I made sure that I let a lot of people know that I thought that was pretty awesome.
I know I'm almost out of time, so I think I've covered most of these.
It's not either or.
The virtual events can complement what you're doing in person.
Just remember that we've been doing a virtual collaboration for a long time,
and this is definitely an important toolkit to help community members,
especially for people who can't always travel for whatever reason,
financial or otherwise.
The final point I want to make,
actually, the platforms that we're using for online events, including Hopin,
I'm not saying that's my favorite tool,
but even Hopin has really evolved over time.
One of the things I noticed when I talked to event manager and vendors is that
they'll give a list of here the virtual event platforms that we support.
One company, they provided like 15 logos, including like Hopin,
so there are just more alternatives available.
So I think we have better platforms and tools to run events virtually.
Yeah, I think that's it.
I just want to make sure I have time for questions.
Hopefully you're able to hear me out there. Thank you.
Ray, because it's you, you can do one question, even though we're over time,
because we think you're awesome.
All right, thank you.
Anyone want to ask a question?
I see a hand.
Off we go.
You are the final question of the community, Deborah, for FOSDAM 2023.
Congratulations.
Well, thank you very much for the talk.
Thank you.
We have a global market, but obviously we don't have big resources like big companies.
So I wonder how much it is to set up the whole logistic of the virtual event
live streaming, because we definitely have a global market.
So obviously you can't be relying on everyone,
assistant to your event if you do it in person.
But I'm thinking probably best thing is to just record it and then put it
available online a week later or something like that,
rather than having to live stream it as a proper hybrid event.
What do you think?
Well, I mean, so the question for people online, you know,
because even Zooms aren't free, right?
And then, you know, is it okay to sort of prerecord things and make content
available for people to consume and ask questions to?
I think that's completely valid.
Actually, one of the things I learned from these vendors, they don't,
on a virtual platform, they actually don't encourage you to have a live
presentation in the Q&A, because there's just a lot more technical
difficulty you can run through.
So they call it single lives.
They prefer that they have the presenter record and be available for
10 minutes of questioning as an example.
But, you know, if you don't want to have person available 10 minutes
online for questioning, you can still have like a creative Google Doc,
like here's a recording, please submit your questions over this period
of time and the presenter or other people can answer them.
So it's all documented, right?
So I think that's completely valid.
So you don't have to use Zoom.
I mean, I just happened to be, I've been using Zoom for the past few years
so that's what I'm comfortable with.
But you can do live streaming from Google Hangout.
But I haven't tried it hands-on myself, but I know that's doable.
So that's an option.
But having something prerecorded available on YouTube channel,
but here's a documentation.
It could be a Wiki page or Google Docs.
Please submit your questions.
We'll close the questioning in like seven days and, you know,
whoever the presenter was or the content expert is,
we'll get back to you with their answers.
So I think that's a completely valid thing to do.
It doesn't have to be like 100% interactive.
So thank you.
Applause.