We don't yet have the text. So there was a call for input and people have responded to
this so we did have some chance to give input to the Commission already but that was at
the stage where we didn't see what is actually being proposed. We still have not seen it.
It will be published in April of this year but at this stage we are already planning
because we know this is going to be a big topic. So what you're going to see right now
is the early stage planning of what a campaign that could help free software deal with software
patents could look like in the coming months. And to start it's going to be my colleague
here Panos from N Software Patents. Yeah so hi everyone I am Panos Algropoulos. I have
been working on the N Software Patents campaign for a while for about two years approximately.
Just to give an overview of the presentation today I am going to talk about in general
what's the deal with SAPs and FRAND and a rough overview of case law and then Kiaran
will present the free software's toughest problem and five fixes we can think about
it. So what's the deal with SAPs and FRAND? Two words that are probably unknown to many.
SAP stands for Standard Essential Patent and FRAND stands for Fair, Reasonable and
Non-Discriminatory. Just to illustrate what's going on here. As we all know that in technology
standards are very important so if we want devices to work with each other and we want
them to be incompatible we need to use a standard right. So these standards are usually the
rules for these standards are going to be set up by standard setting organizations.
So what happens is that for a known standard there are usually patents that are very important
for the standard to work. So those standards are called standard essential patents and
if one wants to participate in the standard they need to use the patent so that person
is called implementer and they have to get a license from the SAP holder. Now of course
as we all know a patent is very restrictive to everyone so here's what standard setting
organizations do. They require from the SAP holders to license their patents their SAPs
under FRAND licenses. Now it sounds great but there are issues. As we said FRAND stands
for Fair, Reasonable and Non-Discriminatory but that's a very very very vague term. First
of all it can affect everyone that's working with standards and that includes network protocols,
Internet of Things, audio video codecs, the automotive industry and so on and on. The
problem is that when the implementers have to use the patents they have to come under
agreements with the SAP holders and the SAP holders they try to charge as much money as
possible and most likely the implementers are not very satisfied with that. So the real
problem is that there's a potential abuse of dominant power, of dominant position by
the SAP holders and the high transaction costs for implementers are simply unsustainable
for SMEs, for small and medium enterprises. And that in general adds up to the legal uncertainty
regarding software patents. So to be more specific on the way this has been reflected
in the courts because what happens is that when you have an implementer and they come
into a disagreement with a patent holder what happens is that litigation happens. So they
go to the courts and what do the courts say? Well they should try to help as much as possible.
I have a layout here of the courts, of the court decisions that have been relevant and
have been basically the landmark decisions in Europe. First of all it all started with
the German Federal Supreme Court and it started with a very strict and conservative stance
very pro-ACP holder stance because it basically had a very strict test for a front defence
and the front defence is basically when the implementer says yes you are the SAP holder
but the money that you charge for that are way too high for me to actually participate
in the market and that is an abuse of your dominant position. And the German Federal
Supreme Court was more in favour of the patent holders and that was in 2009. But then what
happened is that we had a very important decision from the European Court of Justice that concerned
competition law and it took a more balanced approach. And then in 2020 there was another
decision, actually there was no decision, there was a German lower court which asked
for more clarifications from the European Court of Justice and unfortunately for everyone
the decision was, there was no decision, it was settled out of court so the court had
no chance to answer those questions. To be more specific on what the German Federal Supreme
Court said back in 2009, it had a very strict test and it said the alleged infringer can
rely on a competition law defence only if it does the following two steps, only if it
unconditionally offers to enter into a licence agreement with the SAP holder and more importantly
if it behaves as if it were an actual licensee so that would mean that it would have to act
as if there is already a licence and pay royalties and it was up to the defendant to prove that
the conditions above are fulfilled. What happened though is that in 2014 there were two important
commission decisions about anti-trust issues with Motorola and Samsung and the European
Commission stated that a patent holder abuses its domain position when having given a front
commitment over an SAP to a standard setting organisation, it seeks injunction against
a willing licensee and a willing licensee remains free to challenge the validity of the
patent or its infringement. That was very important because the German courts didn't
recognise that, they didn't expect the defendant to give up some fundamental rights like this.
So in about 2015 the European Court of Justice responded to a lower German court because
the German courts recognised that there is a difference between what the German Federal
Supreme Court says and what the European Commission is doing. So the European Court of Justice
came in and clarified what's going on and it said there is a very broad test here but
it's helpful enough for national courts to expand it further. The SAP holder must alert
the implementer in writing of the infringement complaint of by noting the relevant SAP and
how it shall is to be infringed. The implementer must express a willingness to conclude a licensing
agreement on front terms. The SAP holder must provide a specific written offer for a licence
on front terms. The implementer must diligently respond to that offer in accordance with recognised
commercial practices and in good faith. And if the implementer does not accept the offer
made to it, a counter offer that corresponds to front terms should be made. So based on
that language you can probably figure out that the courts didn't really solve any problems.
What they basically helped is to help the companies negotiate better on what front really
is. And you might suggest from the name of the campaign and so forth the patents what
we're trying to do. But it's important to follow decisions like this because it's important
to understand how patents work and how front can actually affect standards. And finally
just for good information there are more cases that should be studied but we don't have the
time to represent them here. It's the United Kingdom Supreme Court Unwired, Planet versus
Broadway in 2020 that concerns the UK. And there are two more decisions from the German
Federal Supreme Court in 2020 that are also of great importance. So with that I conclude
my presentation and I give the floor to Kia.
So the first time I came to Brussels was in 2002 and it was to come to Fostem. And at
that time Richard Stallman gave the keynote address in the Johnson Theatre and it inspired
me to work on free software policy topics as a priority. So a few months later then
I got interested in software patents in particular. A lot of people looked at the topic and saw
it was a bit daunting and after years people said to me you've been working on this for
ten years and there's no progress, how do you keep your motivation? And then they said
after fifteen years how do you keep your motivation? And finally I stuck with it and now I can make
the joke that after twenty years all of the software patents that I was worried about
have now become invalid. But of course there are now a new generation of software patents.
When I said I was giving this talk I was asked, oh can you talk about the unified patent court?
No I can't. Very important but there's no time sorry. Can you talk about software patents
coming into India via the AI law? No I'm sorry I can't. Can you talk about the idea of AI
writing software patents? Because I think patent applications are such nonsense I think
AI is the perfect thing to write the next generation of them. But no I can't. Can you
talk about the cyber resilience act? We all should be, this is going to be massive but
no it's got nothing to do with patents. So audio video patents are the worst case scenario
for software because you have to form a standard first off. You then have to convince all of
the manufacturers of hardware that this is worth putting into their hardware because
you cannot do audio video with just software. Audio video software used to be optimised
for decoding because encoding would happen on some mainframe somewhere and you'd download
the video and you'd watch it. But now with video chat you have to do real time encoding,
transmission so you need a small file size and then decoding and it should be almost
real time. You convince these hardware manufacturers to put it onto their hardware and then you
have to wait five years because then you have to wait for everyone, a whole world of computer
users to throw out their current hardware and buy a new generation of hardware. So after
five years finally the standard will be hardware accelerated on everyone's computer and then
you can really use it. If at that point somebody comes along with a patent and says actually
I own a bit of that software, there is very little you can do. You can no longer innovate
around the problem. So software patents on standards are the worst type of patents for
software and on video patent standards they are the worst of the worst. This is happening
already. We have an audio format Opus which is not very famous however it is successor
to the AUG audio format. It is used in a lot of hardware devices. There is currently a
patent pool being formed to threaten the Opus audio format. We have the AV1 video format
which is being developed to be freely implementable and already there has been a request sent
to the European Commission to investigate the people working on this for anti-competitive
practices because trying to help each other avoid patent problems might be a bad thing
for some companies. Before I get into it I saw yesterday there was published a paper
by Andrew Katz and four other researchers. I didn't get their names but it is on the
implementing the HEVC standard in software so I expect that is very interesting but I
will not be talking about it. There are a lot of topics here. So there was a commission
call for input last year. There were responses from Open Forum Europe who I currently work
for and from Open Source Initiative. However these comments were sent based on not actually
knowing what text is going to be presented. So they were kind of general comments on what
patent policy could be like. We still haven't seen the text that is going to be presented
by the European Commission but as I said this is early stage planning for a campaign. We
have to start thinking about what possibilities we have to fix this. What different form can
it take? Because when we are talking about policy makers the way it works is you have
to give them a list of different fixes that you are looking for and then they will say
which ones are politically possible and then you have to start trying to maximise each
of the ones that are politically possible. So I have found five starting ideas but this
is a discussion document basically. We can discuss them further in the coming weeks.
The first idea would be a carve out specific to free software. A few years ago this might
have sounded a bit overly optimistic but now in the Cyber Resilience Act and the Product
Liability Directive there is this text and when we first saw it we were amazed to see
free and open source software should not be covered. Excellent. Of course once you start
reading it then you realise well there is an objective limitation here. You can use
this exemption if you are trying to do innovation or research. There is a commercial activity
limitation and we all know that commercial activity has never been defined and is an
endless source of clarity for what exactly that means for software and online activities
and it should be exempted. So a judge will have to interpret whether or not you are allowed
to use this exemption which basically means that nobody can confidently make use of this
exemption so it is not very useful. However the fact that this is in a document from the
Commission in two proposals for regulations tells us that inside the Commission something
along these lines is acceptable. They didn't get the wording quite right at this time but
they are not completely opposed to this kind of thing. So this is a starting point maybe
we can do something along these lines. The second possibility would be a similar end
result but from a different starting point and would be to try and carve industry into
two sections. For example we might find that small and medium business in the manufacturing
and pharmaceutical areas might be perfectly happy with having more patents and might want
help from the Commission to apply for patents and use their patents. We happen to not like
that so maybe we should have a different regime for them and one for us. There is already
as part of this patent package there is a regulation that is specific to pharmaceutical
patents so the Commission is not opposed to singling out sector by sector. Our argument
can be that our sector is different because we have collaborative models and we have market
solutions. If you look at the patent clauses of the GPL and the Apache 2.0 license we already
have market solutions so maybe we can tell the European Commission don't interfere with
what we are already fixing. A third fix and this is still quite early stage is the idea
of competition law. I have always believed that there is not enough discussion of how
competition law is weakened by the existence of patents. The European Commission loves
to work on patent law and it is a big topic in the European Commission but it just seems
that there is not enough dialogue between people who are enforcing competition law and
people who are working on patent policy. So I think maybe if we could find a way to make
it clearer to the European Commission and European institutions in general that how
these two topics interact maybe we could help make them understand what we are trying to
achieve. The fourth one, there are only five, I am not going to go on all night, the fourth
one is something that we will definitely be discussed because the Commission has mentioned
this in their documents. So Fran, at times we think the idea of non-discriminatory that
must help us because we don't want regimes that discriminate against free software. We
need patent regimes that allow for royalty free use of patents. However, non-discriminatory
currently the standard meaning for this is that you don't discriminate between individuals.
If you have a certain system for working out how much royalties you are going to ask for
you have to apply the same system to each potential licensee. However, maybe we can
expand this, maybe we can work with this term and find a way to talk about non-discriminatory
so that it is not just, so that it prevents the patent regime from discriminating against
free software which cannot pay royalty fees because we cannot count the copies. If that
doesn't work then of course the word fair, it's an even more vague word but maybe we
can do something with this word to just talk about how fair should apply to free software.
There is also as part of this package there is a regulation coming on compulsory licensing
so maybe that angle can also be used there to ask for something that works with free
software so that would have to be a royalty free sub-licensible patent licence with no
domain limit. And the last fix being presented for the first time. So the whole problem with
software patents in Europe has always been that we have a patent law that says software
is not patentable as such and the policy makers, when we complained we don't want software
patents, they said but it's not patentable, look software is not patentable as such. The
problem was that of course the patent applications were always written as patent on a limited
resource device which interacts with this and there is always a way to make software
sound like it's more than just software as such. What if we asked them to give an example?
What if we asked them to put this into a patent law on standard essential patents? Software
which reads, transmits or puts data into a data format standard is an example of software
as such. If we could do this, and this is a crazy idea, maybe we could find a way to
get software as such to be defined in a concrete way and we could actually start using the
idea that software as such is not patentable. Now, when we used to campaign against software
patents, the commission, because this software is not patentable as such language is there,
they said don't worry, there's not going to be American style software patents, it's not
going to happen. I would like to try and find out the documents they used to use and I want
to find any statements, anything that they ever said that explained what their motivation
was, if they were saying that their intention was that data formats for example or compatibility
interoperability, which is a massive buzzword now in the European institutions, if these
things were not meant to be hampered by software patents, then maybe we can say, well, please
clarify this. Your regulation says you want to reduce the unclarity, give us some clarity
on what exactly software as such is and maybe we can put this into law. Those are my five
fixes. I don't have a favourite one, we don't know which one is going to be acceptable,
we don't know what text even we have to insert any of these into, but this is something that
we will be continuing to hold a dialogue on in the coming weeks and months and I hope
this topic gets lots of attention and lots of you get involved. With that, we do have
a tool for coordinating work on this and Panos will brief you.
I have a microphone. You probably guessed it from the whole presentation. There's so
much information to be digested and it's extremely difficult to talk about all of this in 25
minutes, but what we are trying to do with our websites and software patents is to have
the central resource for everything for software patents. That includes case law, legislation
and that includes the whole world. We want to make people not forget software patents
like they forgot them probably the last 15 years and we try to make everything about
software patents, let's make them the headlines, let's make software patents something that
everyone should be concerned and not make the copyright the only issue that concerns
free software because patents actually concern not only free software but software in general.
With that, we would like to thank you for your attention.
Please try to contribute to these resources. It's extremely valuable.
We have time for one question and this is going to Simon.
Thank you very much. I'll try and frame this in the form of a question if I can. One thing
I'd like to point out about all of your comments about Fran is that all of those lawsuits that
you displayed included Etsy as a co-respondent because the Fran expectation is not a part
of law, it's a part of the way the specification of the standard is written. As a consequence,
anything based on Fran commitments is on very shifty ground because there's no real proof
that anybody is actually forced to do things on Fran terms anyway. I don't like number
four. Number two, your carve out, I've written a paper on that for OFE and I think that's
the one to go for because there is actually a division between standards that are done
that are implementation based and ones that are requirements based where monetisation
depends on patents. You can find a compromise that will work there and I'd like to invite
you to come with me to an Etsy meeting and meet the people who think we are all crazy,
batshit crazy idiots who want to destroy the European economy because that's what they
say to me when I say anything you just said. We're not going to get anywhere with the commission
unless we understand their position and appear to accommodate it even if we think they're
the ones that are crazy. Then that implementation paper from Andrew Katz you saw, the important
thing to know about it is it says it's impossible for an open source implementation to get any
licenses to any patents in any standards because they went and tried for the standard that's
mentioned in the title. That paper isn't a general paper about the topic. They went and
tried to go and get Fran licenses and they found it was impossible for them to go and
secure Fran licenses to any of those standards. This whole thing is based on a false premise
that anyone is going to actually fairly get licenses. This is all about entrapping implementers
into the universe of the companies that have rigged the standards at the regulatory captured
standards organisations.
Okay, cool. So let's move to Kota Zugel.
The term Fran is in the commission's call for input. So it seems, although it is not
in European law at the moment, there is a regulation from 2012 that has some reference
to it, but it's not in general European law, but it's in the commission's call for input.
So it may be defined and if it is going to be defined, then let's define it ourselves.
Thank you.