Dr. Rodjinska.
Raise your hand if you think that open source projects have too much money.
I hope that there will be someone here who raises their hand and they can come and do
the talk instead of me because they know better.
But unfortunately none of you.
I'm going to convince yourself, convince, no myself I'm already convinced, convince
yourself that we can find us open source by small companies.
We are giving 1% of the income to open source projects.
I'm going to convince you that all of the small companies in open source can do that.
And we can change, we can change much in the open source world with that.
Do you know what it can be?
23.1 million.
Huh?
Hard question.
That's the number of small companies in the European Union.
Wow.
How many of them do the computer science, how many of them use open source every day?
How many use open source every day?
I would say half probably.
But how many are contributing and are constant users of open source?
Way harder to ask.
I would assume that at least 5,000.
Imagine now that 5,000 companies which is not that optimistic estimate, each of them
giving 1,000 euros per year.
The total budget you get is 5 million.
What we can do for 5 million europe?
Quite much.
And 1,000 euros per company, it's not high number, it's really a pessimistic estimate.
So we can do way better than that.
Before we get to the details of the Prod.
Smart Dictionary Check, we are in Europe, all of us talking about taxes, incomes and
financial things.
We are using our own languages.
And we need to have a dictionary check when we are switching to English.
So turnover, income, grocery venue, same thing, it's all sales of a company over a
period of time, usually a year.
And profit, it's earning minus all of the expenses that you have.
What I'm convincing you that you can give one person of the income so all sales a year.
Now my personal point of view.
SyslineBit is a company running multiple economic activities under one roof and we are helping
new activities and new people to be the activities.
It's a pretty specific type of a company under the Fetch Law called CIO.
We are concentrating on embedded and open source.
So we are strong supporters of open source.
Currently in our model, everyone is a consultant but we welcome production, system admins and
all the types of activities.
And now currently every consultant gives one person of their income to open source project.
As we hold multiple independent activities, every person decides on their own to which
project they want to give because we have different preferences.
And I started that when it was a one person show when I started a company two years ago.
A small reminder, one person of income means 1000 euros for every 100,000 of income.
The idea of one person is not a new one, you have probably seen about one person for the
planet.
There have been a few initiatives of giving to open source but I think it's good to bring
the idea back because we are always, as always, missing money in open source.
Now when a company gives a donation, what it needs, invoice.
I will shout it too much, I think.
When you're running a company, you need an invoice for every single expense you have.
And if you pay first and then wait for the invoice, you have a risk of not getting it
at all or getting after a long time.
Last year I have given to one of the organizations in open source, everyone here knows and I'm
not going to name because.
And it took me like four or five months of email exchanges with a person who was very
sorry that they cannot get to the person doing the invoices, they cannot give me a invoice,
they are going to send them a message yet again and I was a month again, I was sending
the message again.
Somebody got my voice like five months later.
That is risky, I was already thinking how to explain that to my accountant.
A company can go through a method used by big companies, purchase order that the company
gives, then the recipient of the money gives the invoice and then you pay.
Problem, it's a burden.
It's a burden to the organization you give and it's a burden for the company giving the
money.
But that's the solution I use for bigger donations when I cannot risk of not getting the invoice.
For individuals, they are all the ways to donate.
If a company wants to give money to an individual, that's complicated.
For the tax reasons, for the legal reasons, so we are avoiding giving money directly to
individuals.
For cryptocurrencies, some projects accept cryptocurrencies.
I leave you the question to ask your accountant and then you need to be sure you can run away
from the place.
The reaction varies but may be drastic when you talk to accountant about cryptocurrencies.
So no, if you do not want to run into trouble, you do not donate in cryptocurrencies when
you are running a company.
Now, typical open source organizations supporting projects, what they offer for companies?
Either yearly sponsoring or even sponsoring.
That is something that exists for most organizations, typically sponsoring is from 1000 to 25,000
euros depending on the level.
Even sponsoring is between 500 to around 10,000 euros.
Now we compare that with what a small company can give.
In a small company, I have an alternative.
Either I give 1000 euros to one project eventually too or I give 100 euros to way more projects.
For people who live in open source, we know that if I give to project X, someone will
ask, but why you are not giving to project Y and Z and some more, right?
Because if you are going to one project, it's fair to give to all others.
Opinions differ inside the company who is using which project in their products.
Exactly.
At the end, what happens is you want to give smaller amounts to more projects.
That is exactly not in line with what the organization supporting open source have as
an offer.
Our way of doing the donation is giving directly to organizations.
We establish the way of how to do the payment.
Either they have an account that you can create and then donate or you need to contact some
email address and figure out the details.
Things vary.
Then when we have the method set up, we have that organization now, a database, and every
transaction later, it goes the same way and it works.
There are other ways using aggregators like GitHub sponsors, Open Source Collective, or
Phoenix Foundation crowdfunding.
And there has been a talk about the subject by Wolfgang at the Open Source Summit Europe
last year.
He had a pretty different approach because that was from the approach of a big company
with more internal difficulties of having the donations done than we have in small companies,
but still his analysis of the ways you can donate is pretty interesting.
Now is it hard to donate to an open source project by a company?
Financially the amount of money, one person, if you compare it to different expenses you
have in a company, accounting, rent, internet access, electricity of whatever you have,
it will be in the small things that you have on the company bill.
So it's not really that hard to do.
What is a little bit more complicated is the organization.
And what I found out is most complex is actually deciding to which project you want to give,
even in a company when everyone agrees, we want to give.
A lot of discussions and decision making on how to do that.
And then important thing, collect and document the payment procedure if you're not going
through an aggregate.
Now you have to ask why.
Project work as they can.
And when you are already doing open source you can say that you are already contributing
and there's a kind of donation you are already doing.
I would say that this is an addition to the work you are doing because you cannot take
maintainership in every single project you are using in your product.
That is just not possible.
And this is the maintainers work, infrastructure, all those hard to sell us new features that
need financing the most.
In my opinion that works easiest with the money because you can just pay someone spending
their time on doing those tasks.
And then a subject related to the presentation before, currently quite many organizations
I was involved with, they in reality depend on donation from a small number of big companies.
Give a part of individual donations that they receive.
So if you can break that dependency and make sure that those projects have more stable
and more diversified way of getting the income, that is going to improve the stability and
at the end is going to improve the quality of the code we all depend on.
So are you ready to try it out in your company?
Or do you have any questions, subjects for discussions?
In the meantime we try to fix the microphone.
So take a bit of time as a question then.
What can open source projects do to make this easier?
For example, something that I run a scientific open source project we are looking at trying
to incorporate as a nonprofit because we think that will be more attractive and we are trying
to figure out where to do that and deal with all of the international stuff.
It's a whole thing.
So I guess what do you see from the small business perspective as to what projects can
do to make your giving us money easier?
Maybe we collect some questions first and then in between we can fix the mic issue.
Would it be fine for you?
So that's why maybe we collect some questions?
The question is how a project can make it easier.
For me it's very simple.
Have a legal entity that can create invoices or any legal proof of payment for the amount
and make it easy for a company to do that.
Make it easy in such a way that when you get a message that we want to give you 500 euros,
we get a response rapidly that increases confidence that's going to work.
And then you can, if you are ready to send an invoice just at the moment of payment,
that helps.
If you have a system that generates invoices it's even better.
You can use online invoice generation systems that exist.
If you can use it it's even easier for everyone.
But it's really simple fast reaction time and getting the invoice easily.
If I have those two I will be willing to donate again.
So we have another question over here.
So mainly the perspective on this was by a company's perspective.
And this topic has been discussed by the technical committee just recently as I'm part of that.
And Node.js is part of the foundation and money is actually not an issue.
That's not the main problem.
What we need is actually people donating their time and effort into projects.
And that is way more valuable as such.
So if a company instead of investing money because it's really difficult even for an
organization you have to decide who's actually going to get that money.
Do we pay someone?
What is with the others who contributed?
It's a really tough question to answer if it's not a single contributor to this open
source project.
And therefore if you pay someone from your company to work on that project that is mostly
really really valuable.
Thank you.
That was a pretty important subject.
In a situation where the money is not really an issue people are an issue.
And my answer here will depend on the type of the development we are on.
In my case for most of the projects we donate small amounts like 100 euros per year to 100
euros per year.
That amount of money doesn't allow you to hire anyone to work on the project.
What would be possible would be to donate to an organization that will hire that person
and have multiple companies donate to that person and then hire.
Also hiring someone for a small company it's an important risk if you don't have funding.
Hiring someone for me is more of an approach.
Either you have a business model closely related with the project.
If you are really doing money with that specific project then it makes sense.
Or if you are a company of like 50 then you can probably allow that.
For small companies I think it's a little bit more complicated unfortunately.
We also try to...
We have another question over there.
I'd like to highlight a service by a small NGO from Berlin.
It's called the Center for Cultivation of Technology which is like a back end to open
source projects so they're registered non-profits in Berlin.
If you are a small open source project which doesn't have a company somewhere or a legal
name to yourself you can go there and say hey I'm an open source project and they could
act as a trustee.
They receive donations and they can hold that for your project so companies can get invoices
or checks that the money has been sent there and the software devs don't have to care about
all the financial stuff for that.
So there is like a back end to support open source projects and to make invoicing more
easier and at no cost.
You want to respond to that?
Just a comment.
A small comment for that.
Thank you for doing this.
If you could send me details of the financial
initiatives that allow that aggregating payments for different projects.
Okay.
Test one, two.
My question is well I thank you for mentioning fiscal sponsorship organizations and I want
to give a yes software freedom conservancy is a fiscal sponsor organization as well as
there are many others.
I know that several of us are very interested in making sure that the projects we accept
and therefore take donations for have great governance and so there can be trust as far
as making sure that funds are donated or used for the project and are used wisely.
How do you evaluate governance for these donations or do you not because there's smaller donations?
I think we are trying to test.
It's working.
Okay.
The question was how we evaluate that the money is going to be well spent.
I'm taking a shortcut.
We are donating to the projects we know very well.
So that's easy.
We know the governance.
We know how they work.
So the check is easy.
Getting to projects that we know less I would definitely agree that getting to a project
that is in some aggregator that has policies on the governments that's an additional plus
something point for this project to actually donate it then to a project that we just absolutely
do not know how they work.
What's going to happen.
The answer to an email after a month and things like that.
That's definitely a bonus point for the projects to getting a donation.
Absolutely.
Okay.
So we have another question over here.
So coming back to what you said earlier, like at least when you're a computer company, then
you can definitely let someone work at least part time on open source.
That would be something really valuable again.
I encourage people in my company that are working to work on open source and we have
dedicated time that they may invest into that.
And even as a small company, I was able to work on open source because we used open source
and we ran into bugs, for example, while developing things and then I discussed that with the
leadership at that point of time.
Instead of having a workaround built into the application that we are currently building
as a closed source, hey, why am I not going to fix that bug in that open source library
that we are currently using?
And that's what I did.
One more, right?
I think you have my mic.
I have my mic.
Sure.
I completely agree.
The money part for me is in addition to all the other open source work you do.
We as an open source company, we propose to our customers to upstream they code that we
tell them we can upstream the patches that you have, the fixes that you have.
We can help you with working with the open source work for your project.
The money part is in addition to that, if you are already open source citizen, that's
already great.
But what I found out is that quite many projects.
I'm involved in York store, so that's I have a lot of experience in that.
That's the maintenance part that requires time and convincing customers to have people
working and maintainers.
It's even a problem for the Linux kernel.
So it's a bigger problem.
And I think that without financing people separately from that, it's not really going
to happen.
It's already happened with different funding for different open source projects for the
maintenance part.
And if you can go forward with that, that's going to help.
Time's up.
I'm happy to discuss with all of you in the corridors.