All right, everybody, I'd like to introduce you to Sarah-Jane Whitfield.
Hi, everyone.
As you know now, my name is Sarah-Jane Whitfield.
I'm an open source advisor at Google.
This is my very first FOSDEM, very first in-person speaking engagement, so please bear with
me through the nerves.
I'm the jetlash.
Thank you.
Everyone I've met so far has been so nice, so gracious, so understanding.
I really, really appreciate it.
And I'll also say that while I'm going to nerd out quite a bit on this topic that I
find super interesting, if you came here for answers about what exactly is the unauthorized
practice of law, I regret to inform you that you will not be leaving with answers.
You will be leaving with lots and lots of questions.
And I hope that that will spur some discussion and we can think through some of the very
fuzzy lines that determine what is or isn't the practice of law.
Let's see.
Hopefully this works.
All right, so in light of the subject matter that I'm covering today, I wanted to just
clarify that this is not legal advice.
I am not your lawyer.
This is for general informational purposes only.
Likewise I have a few housekeeping notes.
So typical American, I know, mostly going to be focusing, well exclusively going to
be focusing on US law today, mostly because that's where most of the action is with regard
to software at this time.
It's also what I'm most familiar with when it comes to unauthorized practice of law.
I absolutely acknowledge that basically every other jurisdiction around the world regulates
the practice of law.
And based on the research that I did before this talk, it appears that most other countries
really distinguish and emphasize regulating the practice in a courtroom setting where
you're actually representing a client in front of a judge way more than out of law practice.
And it's less distinguished in the US.
Finally, wanted to let you all know in the interest of time and everything that I want
to cover, I'm going to be giving you high level summaries of various rules and three
cases that I'll cover.
And as I mentioned before, I'm going to leave you with some open-ended questions to consider.
So to get started, by show of hands, is anyone familiar with a company called Do Not Pay?
Okay, just a few of you.
So Do Not Pay is a US-based company that was launched in 2015 initially providing a chatbot
service that would help users fight traffic tickets.
They expanded their services to deal with other consumer disputes like if your flight
was canceled and you were eligible for a refund, the chatbot would help you through that process.
If you wanted to cancel your free trial before you got charged, it would help you through
that process.
In 2018, they relaunched their app to integrate AI.
I believe that they say that they're relying on IBM Watson.
And they dubbed it the world's first robot lawyer.
And they included various legal actions and legal document generation as part of their
services.
So if any of you are maybe in the future interested in getting involved more in the legal tech
Twitter space, you'll see things pop up like this all the time.
So in the past month, this happened after I had submitted this talk.
So this worked out well for me.
Do Not Pay announced in early January that their AI was going to actually represent someone
live in court, in traffic court, to dispute a $200 traffic ticket.
A few days later, they offered a million dollars to anyone who was willing to leverage their
AI exclusively in arguing case in front of the Supreme Court.
About a week later, it announced some additional legal products that it was releasing where
it would summarize terms of service and lease agreement terms highlighting the terms that
were not standard so that the consumer had a better understanding and more insight into
what they were agreeing to and whether it was standard or not market if they were being
taken advantage of.
And they then confirmed that their case in the traffic court was actually supposed to
take place on February 22.
Everything was good to go.
Three days after that announcement, they regretted to inform all of their followers that they
were indefinitely postponing going live in any courtroom.
And they were also going to roll back any of the legal services that their website offered.
So what happened exactly?
Lawyers, lawyers happened.
Lawyers in the regulatory bodies in the US, the state bar associations said, ah, no, I
think that's our job.
This looks and smells a lot like the unauthorized practice of law.
And along those lines, penalties across the board can include civil penalties, fines.
It could also include jail time being incarcerated for the unauthorized practice of law.
So Do Not Pay was not interested in pursuing that and waiting to see what might happen.
The founder said he was surprised he had underestimated how seriously lawyers in the US would take
a $200 speeding ticket.
So again, I said that you're likely going to leave with more questions and answers today.
I would love to give you a clear definition for what the practice of law actually is.
But unfortunately, there is not one unifying definition.
Each state regulates the practice of law.
So each state has their own definition for what the practice of law is.
And they very much like keeping it vague instead of enumerating every possible action or type
of speech that may constitute the practice of law, which means that you kind of have
to wait and see what happens in court or take a very conservative approach and just leave
it to the lawyers.
So along those lines, I've already mentioned that there are lots of different penalties
that anyone may face.
But I also want to emphasize that this doesn't just apply to lawyers.
This covers non-lawyers as well.
So if anyone is familiar with the US TV show Suits, which is what made Meghan Markle quite
famous, at least in the States, the main character is the quintessential case of the unauthorized
practice of law.
Someone that did not have a law license, didn't go to law school, and he pretended to be a
lawyer.
Surprise, surprise, he was brilliant.
He does a great job.
But there's always this looming specter that someone's going to find out and he's going
to be in a lot of trouble for the unauthorized practice of law.
So that's the typical case.
But it also applies to lawyers.
So just wanted to clarify that.
Now I tried to distill the common elements.
I read tons of cases, tons of articles and law journal notes and articles about this
topic.
And I was able to divide the most common elements of unauthorized practice of law or UPL into
these two main buckets.
And they're going to look nearly identical.
But I'll talk through some of the distinctions in a moment.
So the first bucket deals with legal advice that's given by a person or entity that does
not have a law license in the relevant jurisdiction.
Sounds like a bunch of nonsense and legalese.
The second bucket is legal services for compensation given by a person or entity that does not
have a law license in the relevant jurisdiction.
So the clearest delineation that anyone could draw just by looking at the two of these is
the first two bullet points.
In particular, the legal services tends to specify that it's for compensation, whereas
legal advice does not.
So does that mean that if I provide legal services for free that I'm not liable for
unauthorized practice of law?
Unfortunately not, because some states will then deem or may deem your provision of legal
services as also providing legal advice.
And they don't distinguish in most cases giving legal advice.
You can give that away for free and still be held liable.
So isn't great.
There are also a bunch of other nuanced distinctions that hopefully you'll start to see come through
as I discuss the cases in how courts look at and distinguish between what is legal advice
and what legal services are.
So since I can't give you a definition for the practice of law, and we couldn't really
back into it from looking at what constitutes the unauthorized practice of law, let's talk
about the public policy rationale for why this exists at all.
This quote is from a 1952 Missouri Supreme Court case.
And despite its age, I think it sums up the gist of the public policy rationale pretty
well.
At the end of the day, it comes down to consumer protection.
This theoretically is not supposed to be about protecting lawyers and their livelihoods,
creating a monopoly over who can give legal advice and provide legal services.
What it's really supposed to do is protect the public and make sure that if they're getting
advice, if they're relying on someone else, that it's actually reliable, that it's competent
advice and that maybe there's some repercussions if that doesn't hold water.
So in light of that great public policy theory, what does that actually look like in practice?
The options for legal representation in the US come down to, well, you can do it yourself,
all alone.
You can do it through research, fill out your own forms, draft your own documents, file your
own things.
That's what we call pro se representation.
Or you can hire a lawyer, which tends to be expensive.
And if you don't already have a connection through family or friends to a lawyer, it
can be really hard to track down the right person.
And additionally, your claim may not be worth their time since they charge by the hour.
And finally, in very limited circumstances, mostly confined to criminal cases, a court
may actually appoint a lawyer to you.
But that's not really a viable option for the vast majority of especially civil cases
that deal with consumer protection.
So how's that public policy rationale looking in practice?
Clearly there's a bit of a disconnect.
Additionally, the US is currently suffering from what many call a crisis in terms of access
to justice, access to efficient, affordable, reasonable expectation of justice and the
ability to interact with the justice system.
And based on this quote and all of the other relevant demographics and statistics about
this issue, it largely impacts low and middle income individuals who can't afford legal
services.
So to get back to the unauthorized practice of law, again, I wanted to try and find a
way to describe the various ways that a court may consider, since we don't have clear definitions,
what may bump over into the category, what may cross that fuzzy line into the unauthorized
practice.
And so these are various high level categories of what may tip the scales.
But again, to clarify, there's no clear set framework that anyone is following.
There's no set determination that, oh, well, if they disclaimed that they're not a lawyer
and it's not legal advice like I did earlier, then it's clearly outside the realm and can't
be held liable.
There's no clear line drawn.
If I am giving you legal advice for free, again, as I said, it very well may not be
exempt from liability.
So you'll see some of those factors come up again in these cases in the interest of time.
Again, I want to kickstart the first case.
So this is Janssen versus LegalZoom.
Quite some time ago, 2011, this was a case that took place in Missouri.
And LegalZoom, for anyone who's not familiar, is a website that offers legal services throughout
the United States.
When they initially started, it was just their basic legal forms that someone could buy,
print out, and fill in themselves and do whatever they wanted with.
That's what the court considered the goods that LegalZoom offered.
They expanded into building out a program, essentially a decision tree, where they provided
questionnaires to their customers, and then would generate legal documents based on the
user input.
That's what the court, in this case, deemed the services that were provided for sale.
Sorry, lost my place.
So LegalZoom did make a lot of statements that they were not a law firm, they were not
providing legal advice.
This was meant to be self-help services, and no actual harm was cited in the case as being
done to the public or to the actual customers of LegalZoom.
Despite all of this, the court still found that the sale of the services constituted
unauthorized practice of law.
In particular, I wanted to call this to your attention, the court specifically honed in
on the fact that a human had programmed the software to generate the legal documents.
Since the human that programmed it was not a Missouri licensed attorney, but they had
to have relied on Missouri law in order to generate documents that would affect a Missouri
resident, that they clearly must have been making legal determinations, just like a Missouri
licensed attorney would do a client intake and ask a series of questions of the client,
and then use that to inform what documents they would choose and what content made it
into those documents.
The first open-ended question that I want you all to consider is this was decided just
over 10 years ago now.
How might the court have viewed this human programmer input if this were an AI model
instead, based on where technology has come and where the layperson understanding of what
technology is capable of doing?
How might that affect how courts look at this?
Let's fast forward 10 years to 2021.
This is a Miami-based startup called Ticked.
They were sued by the Florida Bar Association for allegedly violating the unauthorized practice
of law regulations.
Ticked had developed an app that would connect anyone who had gotten a traffic ticket with
a licensed Florida attorney to resolve the case, and they did it for an upfront flat
fee based on a percentage of the total violation fee on the face value of that ticket.
It built an algorithm.
This is the main business model.
They built an algorithm that used court data on the likelihood of ticket being dismissed
in court or being charged fees or accruing points in excess of the face value of the
ticket to come up with what was actually going to be profitable, kind of like an insurance
company will calculate the risk that you as a young, healthy person are going to suffer
some catastrophic loss and they're going to have to pay big.
It's probably a low likelihood, so they charge you, at least in the United States.
Forgive the example.
In the U.S., we get charged a lot of money to pay for our health insurance and usually
don't see a return on that unless something really bad happens.
That's a story for another time.
To get back to the ticked case, they made it very, very clear in all of their website
communications in their terms of service, everywhere on their site, that they were not
providing legal services.
They were going to connect you with a licensed attorney who would take over and handle the
case for you.
Their sole responsibility would be determining whether or not your case was a good fit, referring
to a licensed attorney, and then negotiating that flat fee on your behalf with the attorney.
They would take care of all the payments.
Once the connection was made between the customer and the attorney, ticked removed itself from
that relationship other than providing the financing to pay the attorney at any related
costs.
Likewise, the lawyers were not employees.
I'm running out of time.
To skip ahead, no harm was done.
There were two groups that filed amicus briefs, one in support of the Florida Bar, one in
support of ticked.
Surprise surprise, they were at odds.
One was a group of private practice attorneys in competition with ticked.
The other was a group of consumer rights activists and legal aid services.
Back to that public policy rationale.
In a 4-3 decision in the Florida Supreme Court, they found that ticked was engaged in the
unauthorized practice of law and cited a number of potential harms that may befall their customers,
but no actual harm.
This was enough justification.
The majority had even said that they lauded the idea that technology was lowering the
barrier of entry to getting legal services, to having public benefit and public convenience,
but that still was not enough to knock out the unauthorized practice of law claims.
The minority dissent, I'm not going to have time to cover it in full, but it's great if
you have a chance to read it.
I have citations in my slides.
Essentially, they say, hey, this is a hedge.
This is purely financial.
It has nothing to do with law.
All you're getting is certainty of this is the flat fee that I pay and that's all that
I'm going to pay.
It has nothing to do with legal, lawyers handle all of the legal stuff.
This should not have been considered unauthorized practice of law.
In Ray Peterson involved, I'm going to skip through this, forgive me, the nonprofit called
Upsolve.
Upsolve provides free legal services to low-income individuals to file for personal bankruptcy
in the US.
Again, no harm done.
No fees charged.
Upsolve was still found to be engaged in the unauthorized practice of law despite plenty
of disclaimers relying on government issued forms and instruction sheets and publicly
available information, making sure that they were only serving clients that had very basic
cases that didn't require additional legal advice or input.
Had a lot of controls in place, but unfortunately, it was not enough.
Fortunately, unlike TIC, Upsolve was able to work with the bankruptcy court to make
changes.
They're currently working with the bankruptcy court to make changes to their program so
that they can continue their services, whereas TIC actually had to shut down.
They are no longer active and able to conduct business in the state of Florida.
This is a handy chart.
Again, forgive me for the time.
We won't be able to get to everything, but I did want to note here in the three cases
that I talked about, Upsolve is the only one that did not charge for their services, and
yet they were still found to be in violation of unauthorized practice of law.
In the legal Zoom case, I didn't cover this, but they were providing some direct filings
on behalf of their customers, which in the case law is considered in court, which usually
is a higher threshold.
Everywhere else was out of court.
There was no interaction with judges.
There was no in-person representation.
Finally, I wanted to distinguish the decisions.
All three were unauthorized practice of law.
Legal Zoom is still operating in Missouri.
They settled the class action lawsuit, and they worked out a deal with the state in order
to change some of their services and disclaimers and get around any future claims of unauthorized
practice of law.
Same in Upsolve, at least for now, but TIC did have to discontinue their services.
One thing that I left out is that Upsolve, I found out this morning, which is why it's
at the very end, Upsolve has released publicly some of their software on their GitHub org.
I don't know.
It wasn't cited in the case.
It is free and available under open source licenses.
I don't know if this was the software that was involved or at issue in the case.
It wasn't specified, but interesting to note that open source software is involved.
The reason that I'm bringing this up at the very end, I know I'm at time, is these are
some additional open questions.
In light of the various facts and elements that a court will consider in terms of what
is the unauthorized practice of law, where it falls down, I wanted to address what effects
this may have on FOSS projects.
Everyone knows I'm not a lawyer, but I'm going to give you my opinion about something.
Licenses contain warranties and disclaimers, et cetera.
I don't have time to cover all of this.
Forgive me again.
You've been a great audience.
I really appreciate your patience with me.
Please check out the slides.
They're already uploaded.
This is CC by 4.