I am now going to get out of Pablo's way so that he can begin his excellent presentation.
Thank you for being here, Pablo.
Thank you.
Will you give Pablo a round of applause?
Okay.
Hello, my name is Pablo.
Okay, I'm going to talk about the frequent OCD, okay, as an open source idea to show
the community your contributions, okay?
And the first question is, you have to think yourself, does your OCD follow one standard,
okay?
And the main goal of this talk, okay, is to create a community to give a project to solve
the main question, okay?
The community has already started on that link, so feel free to go there.
And the question is, how do we show our contributions to the free culture communities?
Okay, in my opinion, we need like a free culture OCD and we will talk about it.
This talk is not to show a project, okay?
It's not a demo and it's not to show the latest updates of something.
This talk is to discuss about the creation of an open OCD standard, to get more environmental
sustainability within papers, and to show how and where to collaborate, okay?
Because the thing is, if you have our profile with the communities that we are contributing
to, if someone sees our profile, you can find out more communities that maybe you don't
know, okay?
So the main goal, as I said, is to create a community and improve the relationship between
the candidates and the regulators, because this relationship currently, I guess, needs
to improve.
So one important thing is to have more control over your personal data, okay?
We will see.
This talk is based on four parts.
The first part is a comparison between the 20th century OCD, like the old CVs, and the
20th century CVs, the CVs that we want to create today.
Then we will see the current standard that we in the European Union, we currently have.
As you will see, it's going to be amazing.
Then we will see more about my identity, like the idea of my free-code OCD.
And then we will see things for inspiration in the community to create, to discuss, to
decide, and to build that community.
Okay first, the old CVs are usually not standard, okay?
So each one has a different template, and this is a mess.
We currently have an European standard, but this should be the input.
Linked-in is, we don't want to be at the standard, you know, because currently it has a lot of
users, but it's not the way I think.
And on the other hand, we need to create a standard TV to get all the benefits of the
standard things in terms of the format, the fields, and the features that our CVs should
have.
Then the old CVs are static.
So we have a CV, we print it, and each time you get a new job, you have to create like
a new version or whatever.
So sometimes it happens that our creator asks you, hey, I have your CV, but it's not the
latest one, okay?
So I need the latest one.
So we want that our CV, the 21st century CV, should be dynamic, okay?
Should be a link where, okay, this is my identity, this is my profile, my CV, and then you each
time is referenced by itself.
I mean, you don't have a file that you have to update.
And instead of being asked about, hey, please send you the CV, my link is here, and it will
be always there.
The current CVs, okay, are not searchable and not indexable, okay?
So when the creators have tons of CVs, it's difficult to search inside the papers, and
it's hard to find CVs because they are just papers, you know?
So for example, it's a problem for the recruiters how to find that people between the older
CVs that they have who has a Linux skills, for example.
There is no way because they are just papers.
And so the CV that we want must be searchable and indexable, so our recruiter can say, okay,
please, show me the people with Linux skills, okay?
Current CVs don't have validations, no configurations.
So I can say I am a Harvard student.
I put on my CV, and it's supposed that I am a Harvard student, but I'm not, you know?
So we need a CVs, validable and configurable, with APIs, with links, with whatever, to validate
that the information that we are providing is true, okay?
And then a paper, okay?
We are our current CVs.
Now we are using the PDF, you know, but the paper, it has a problem, and it's how we show
how do we show the multimedia information, right?
We have to create a multimedia CV where we can add our portfolio, our videos, our pictures,
and whatever.
So we get a better portfolio, our CV is not going to trust, because sometimes due to data
protection rights, you have to drop to the CVs, and we get a happy environment, because
we need to, okay?
The second part is the amazing WordPress journey, and as I said, currently we have an open standard
CV that is named E
Uropas, and it's the E Uropan commission project.
So this is starting like this, and I don't know if you can see it, oh, okay.
Looked at it, it's a micro support template, so as you can imagine, this is going to be
...
As you can see, this is not the way, you know, everyone should feel the E Uropas CV, but it's
a nice list of standard things that a CV should have, you know?
So we will see negative things, but also positive things, okay?
A good idea is to add additional information with your publications, your presentations,
and so on.
But I guess just, it's not enough to show that, you know, maybe I'm linked to the presentation
or the event, you know?
And also maybe I can say that I was on the whatever conference, and who knows that it's
true, you know?
It's hard to find out that.
So we need another way to feel the E Uropas CV, okay?
The E Uropas started in 2024, I don't know, but the thing is that they realized that they
need a portpad, okay?
Because the word template was not enough, and nobody was feeling the CV.
So they create an E Uropas portpad, okay, and let's see the simulation journey where
you are feeling your personal information, then you have your work experience, and you
feel your personal skills.
For example, one personal skill important is the language, okay?
It should be also standard.
There is a current European standard, and you have your digital skills, and there are
suggestions when you are feeling the digital skills, and as you can see, all this is Microsoft
Office digital skill, Microsoft Word, Microsoft Excel.
I don't know if it's on purpose or not, but many Microsoft things, as you can see, and
I said, okay, I'm going to feel all of them because I'm a practical engineer, you know,
and let's feel all of them.
And then another suggestion started, okay, and as you can see, soon, okay, it's my digital
skill, then Outlook instead of email.
Google, Facebook as an important digital skill on your city.
PowerPoint, okay, and then it started, I feel all of them again, and then some, it turns
to more personal skills like motivated teamwork, and with the skills, and I said, I'm going
to keep continuing with my feeling all of them, and then the amazing digital skill,
I am an internet user, all right?
So this is my CV, as you can see, I am a pretty amazing engineer.
And suddenly I saw, oh, I can create a CV based on this information, this is what I
want, I want to create my CV with my profile, okay, so you feel, again, some information,
let's feel a professional CV.
You can add the statement at the bottom of your CV, and I started to add, we will see
later on, but I started to add all my free culture profiles, I don't know why, but I
want that information in there, okay?
We will see later on the reason.
I created, okay, and there is another feature, it's that you can upload it to AWS network,
okay, this is the most positive thing about the WordPress, and it's like AWS, it's like
a shared network between the European Union countries, where people from other countries
can ask for CV for other countries, and if they are available, you can see their CV,
okay, so a common database, I think it's a good idea, but I don't know if AWS is used,
you can check which countries are you willing to work at, you can feed your occupation,
suddenly, okay, my CV is on AWS, so I don't know if that is sending my live app, it's
there, I have the open question if it's a good idea, just to discuss on the community,
okay, but it's a good idea to have an European Union shared CV database, and then this is
to bring show up that it's tell your digitalest case, so as you can imagine before, let's
see this, I mean same thing, I don't know if you can see the questions, but it is like
a self test, I'm able to do this, I'm able to do this, I'm able to do this, okay, it's
a test, then some question that that are great, you know, but the first one is based on some
software and the other one I don't know if it's important to know for an
employer but how many digits the Apple code has. So then I finished my test
they say congratulations and I am an advanced user. Okay so as you can see I
got the highest level and you can generate like a proof that you got that
level. Okay actually they are asking for my name I don't know why because I was
already loving it but it's funny because my label C except band report is also
beyond also to lean on the board. Okay you can type another name and it's okay and
then there is a little bit of roadmap but I don't know why I got this level but I
got the I am a master of remote work really I don't know how they tested that
but I'm and this is my person is he okay you bet I mean this is my opinion this
is an important thing and a cool thing but as you can see the other steps
through the improve. Okay and then the third part is my identity okay my name
is Paulino Khosa. Thanks for the cause mention the cause community mention the
talk before in ESA and we will see the parts that are free to see the issue
must have okay most of them are like a normal CD but the most important thing
is the matrix the I want a CD where you are able to see matrix about the
contributions that to free portal communities that you have done okay
because for equators it's important to know the profile to know how activities
are on how active the the person is on on the frequent or community and I mean
it's in my opinion it shows many information about our identity on how
the way we we work. One of the most important things in in your community in
your CD is your identity okay it's hard to to implement an identity start where
an open identity start and we have two options the first one is key base okay
I suppose that it's well known here it's as a pro it's open source it's privacy
and security focused and it's easy to install okay but as a con it's type of
confirmation and must be developed okay because we will say that
as I said the confirmation it's important to to give trustness to our
CD okay another concept that the server is not open source is not widely used
and it's not focused only on online identity okay so the other one the other
way to create your identity that I prefer that it's key upside that we will
see Aladdin talk later on at 1 p.m. as you can see this is the the Yarmul profile
and this is one of the most important slides because my identity it's my DNA
so my the DNS of my website my github profile my good luck profile and whatever
community you know and I want the most important thing is to generate metrics
about the contributions that using my my community profile let's say you love or
or get help or whatever another thing is the work experience okay we have to have
a list with the companies you have worked out description and the
possibility to add validations that that is to worry and also the recommendations
in terms of education and it's and training is almost the same list of
course description of the content and possibility of the validations for
example I read had certified so that provides a workplace where do you submit
the identity of the certification and work address okay there that person is
certified it's true that what is what are they saying then about the skills I
suppose that it should be mostly free text and we give a multimedia and we
also need validations and this is a list of some of my profile in some communities
you know so we are going to for example this is my profile so I need a way to
get metrics of my contributions to the we can make it we can make a environment
let's say so for example I have a hundred forty image in open street maps
I made a 49 edits as you can see in my profile on open street maps you already
you already have a way to have to get the metrics of the job contributions okay
here you can see some statistics about the internal statistics about my open
street map contributions then you get graphs that the problem is that the
platform that I'm using is not open source you know so the community should
be another way to get that data and to show metrics and to to tell more about
our contributions okay then this is my GitHub profile and I'm already including
metrics inside my GitHub my GitHub profile and there are several ways to
to get those metrics okay the first one is the GitHub really starts project that
it's pretty popular it's more than 51 K half stars and you get the metrics about
your contributions and also that you're the most used language which is this
information is pretty useful for the degree to survey because it tells more
about us that okay I go to the interview and I say I'm an amazing PHP developer
but if then we show your contributions are your contributions are not so good
maybe they they get their recruiters get more information about that another
platform is metrics like up the dial where you can see some statistics and
on the latest version there are pretty cool graphs and things that more or less
are true but as I said we have to to get that information basically from what they
give half API and and provide them in another way another it's web latte that I
got 62 translations you know but and maybe for a for a recruiter of
translator maybe it's important it's how activities on this community that it's
based on its focus it on translations you know and on gird lab I have
contributed mostly in my work 260 project and again we have to find a way
to get this kind of metrics in open foot fat for to survive product and I'm at
code that okay I'm a starter I have started the free quarter city that is
the repository of the the community that I want to build finally a the last part
is the things for inspiration and the first thing is that we already have a
open CV format but it's made by the Spanish recruiters company but it's
based on the Asian of a and this could be the first point for inspiration then
we have to be old we have to create see builders we have here I left for
examples of open source projects that led you to create your CV based on your
guitar profile okay and you got the you enter your information and you get the
your CV in several ways a PDF what page or whatever then one of the most
important things that we have to develop extractors and converters and to we need
the structures to get the information for the the API to to then show them and
we have to create converters to make the life easier for the people that they
have a link in profile and we need a converter for longer your link link it
in CV to the job free quarter CV or maybe a translator to all the pass or I
mean we have to provide ways to avoid just feeling again the information
because I already put in another platform and a list of things that we
should talk about is the ethical things you know that the protection about the
protection for example in Spain many people put the street the street they
read this on the CV I don't know if it's useful or not but for example in the UK
is not possible to add your profile you're a picture of yourself and another
ethical things that do I think we should discuss we have to choose a backend how
they we extract of the information I see it's our past maybe the error passes
that is way to start or maybe we have to sell develop another option then we
have to make a decision if we should have a CV public database if it's always
maybe the project itself it's the best way or the best the place for example
the key oxide is using just your GPD key so maybe that's enough and we have to
provide a way to to allow to share our personal data okay first but maybe we
don't want to add to our CV the the the contact but if a recruiter is asking a
PPA send me your email your phone maybe you we need a way to okay I'm going to I
want to provide this information to this operator then would be important and the
last one is if we should provide virtual compatibility to the old CV okay so we
feel all the information in our amazing a free culture CD but maybe the old
recruiters let's say they need the old CDs I don't know why and maybe to a CV
that could be a printable is a PDF export the best a PDF it's it's important
and obviously we will find another questions on the way and we so let's
start the community and let's discuss that this is the best attempt that I have
seen about the free culture or CV focused on the brokers okay the problem
is that the repo it is already on you have and it's pretty popular but the
webpage is not working so maybe a four but I don't know but there you can show
your developers case so here we see metrics about our
internet our profile let's say the technologies that we use funny facts
and our personal repositories for example I like a lot the idea and it's
more or less the CV that I would like to know to have and finally take home
message okay we have many reasons to improve the way that we are creating
cities as you saw before we need to create a the newest standard and the
newest and that must be community developed because it seems I don't know
I'm not sure but it seems that Microsoft for example took part on the
auto pass the definition which have to show metrics about our collaboration so
if you are interested and you think this is important please join us about
community and less discuss and less to be on something that I think it's
affects to everyone and it's important for us as a community and also as a
person they open sources stuff and the open culture stuff so thank you
I think this thing is on this thing is on thank you so much Pablo