Welcome back. If you thought it was quiet before, it's not anymore. I will now remember
to remove my mask so that anyone who may be following along on the live stream and lip
reading will be able to hear my comments. We're going to go ahead and slide back into
our sessions for the day and I am very pleased to introduce Alex to talk to us about nurturing,
motivating and recognizing non-code contributions, a subject near and dear to my heart as an
open source community member who is not a developer. So if we could get a round of applause
to welcome Alex, that would be great.
Hey. Nice to see you all. So let's start. My name is Alexa Bramova and I work in Percona
for two years in Percona Community Team and I'm really inspired by the idea that open
source can be open to everyone with diversity of experience and not necessarily a technical
one. First couple words about the company. Percona provides best of breed, support, consulting,
managed services, training and free and open source software for MySQL, MariaDB, MongoDB,
Postgres. So we make applications and databases run better. Please check our website for more
information. I'm sure you can find everything for you and for your applications. Also Percona
is a remote first company with 350 employees now in almost 40 countries. I think it's great.
Percona gathered a great experience in working with open source contributions and today we
will talk specifically about non-code contributions in particular and we will look at the different
types of non-code contributions and we will discuss how we can provide value to your project
and team and how to engage and empower contributors. When we talk about open source contributions,
nowadays we still often associate them with coding, with tech gigs, who contribute code
and understand all those strange words like fork, pull request and etc. But the open source
world is very extensive and diverse and I believe that everyone can find their place
there. Even if someone doesn't feel confident with coding, there are still lots of things
to keep them busy. So what are the types of non-code contributions? They include technical
writing, copy editing, translations and everything working with text, testing reporting issues,
designing and advocating, social media coverage and this list is not an extensive one so if
you have any ideas we can add them here too. Just use your imagination. And we will look
into these types a bit more deeper. First is technical writing, copy editing and professionals
who are good working with text can have a lot of work to do. For example, help with
translations and localizations to expand your open source project to different markets.
Maintaining documentation is also a thing that is a source of worries for many open
source projects. A lot of stuff might be needed here from simple hard tools to updates about
new releases and new features. Blogging, which type is my favorite one actually and it includes
help with spreading the word about this project, a project you might love. For example, posting
technical content in your personal blog or different blogging platforms about experience
you gained in styling software in different environments, about basic configurations for
beginners, best practices, tuning and monitoring of a tool, life hacks for experienced users,
how this helps you in your profession, in your business and possible alternatives to
this tool, the ideas of different tools. Next is testing. It includes providing valuable
feedback, looking from the position of the end user or a developer who works with the
tool. For example, reporting issues, describing unexpected strange behavior, reporting bugs,
filling out the surveys and also creating feature requests and sharing your ideas about
future project development. Designing. Well, here, depending on the professional focus
of an individual, there is a wide range of involvement from UI improvements to banner
and format graphics design. Not all open source projects have resources to hire a designer
to involve him into development. And for a contributor, it is also a good way to add
interesting projects to their portfolio. Advocating. So there are lots of things that can be done
here. It includes sharing posts on social media on Twitter, Facebook, LinkedIn, whatever.
Recording YouTube shorts and videos, streaming about software you like. If a person has a
podcast, he can invite project maintainers to discuss different aspects of the project,
its value and perspectives. Active speakers can also include in their presentations mentions
of a project they like. And it all helps to grow open source projects, especially small
ones. And also living reviews on software marketplaces can be also included here. So
let's talk a bit why you need noncode contributions. First, it gives you resources to fill in the
gaps. It's not a secret that developers may struggle, for example, to maintain a communication.
You may not have resources for proper testing. Improving usability or localization. Well,
coding is super important, but it's not always enough. Well, it helps you to become more
visible. For example, this can specifically apply to reviews on software marketplaces where people
come to choose software for their development, for their bad projects, student projects, and
not only bad projects. When it motivates your developer team, when we see how people share
pictures of t shorts with your project time on Twitter, how many reviews they have. When
they see how people use your software and create their own tutorials and explain how
they use this software in their use case. It's very, very valuable for a developer team
to see that. Well, last but not the least, it does make the world a better place for
everyone. Open doors for those who didn't have opportunities to obtain systematic technical
knowledge due to different reasons, maybe economical, personal, whatever. For example,
I myself didn't obtain technical knowledge. I have a humanitarian experience, humanitarian
knowledge, but now I'm giving a talk at the biggest open source event in Europe. Open
source did a big work for me and I believe that everyone who is interested in technologies
can follow my path. Thank you. Okay. So profits for non-coder. What can there be? There are
many. They can share their professional skills and obtain diversified experience with different
projects. In which portfolio connect with community, which is very important, and interact
with passionate people. And I think it also brings lots of fun in your life. So how can
we involve more non-code contributions? And how we work with them in Percona? Offer small
reward for compression of particular task that you need. For example, in Percona, we
launched several campaigns for living a review on software marketplaces, following a technical
review where a user describes his experience, his use case. And we offered t-shirts with
our logo or marks delivered worldwide. People also tend to love $5 Amazon gift cards. And
you can launch campaigns with clear requirements, describe what you want to see, and deadline
to motivate people to participate. And then publish it on your blog post and share social
media. We also reward those who report security issues. In Percona, we have forum. And we
also reward active users of a forum, people who help others and answer questions of the
community. If you don't have a forum but have a Slack channel or Discord channel, you can
also do the same. Be creative and find what's important for you. To send swag, we use Shopify
and Printful and Printify. Printful and Printify are providers of t-shirts and all this swag
stuff. We just add their logo. They have very simple design tools. Even if you do not have
any design skills, you can do something simple there. And when we send them worldwide, when
we participate in different challenges, like Octoberfest in 2022 last year, we did a special
focus on non-code contributors and Percona repositories also persevered in Octoberfest.
We had about 20 contributions and half of them were non-code contributions. For your
swag gifts, personalize them if possible. We also do this in Printful. We add these
nice messages to Alice from Percona with Love, to Matt from Percona with Love. And actually,
it cost us additionally $2.5. And people love to see this way. When they get, they take
pictures, they share them on Twitter, they send these pictures to us. We collect them
and also share. And actually, it makes them not only make one contribution, like someone
fixed a report or reported an issue. And for example, he got his t-shirt and when he started
sharing on Twitter, we didn't even ask him. It makes his contribution even larger. Make
a word visible and document them for the history. Publish blogs on your blog's platform or on
social media. For example, here we posted a blog post who recognized every contributor
and described who did what, how he contributed to Percona repositories during October 1st.
And we love to post such things because people love recognition. We also publish all contributions,
community videos, articles, our repositories, our software on our community website, Percona.community.
We collect them in the list. We share them on Twitter. Here is the example of Twitter.
Percona bytes, it is our community Twitter account. We tag contributors if we can find
them on Twitter. And people love being recognized like this. What's important, of course, is
providing clear instructions for non-experienced users. How to contribute. How to publish a
blog post on your website. How to contribute in different ways. And we also trying to make
sure that we are leaving our email everywhere we can. So people who even read this post
but had issues posting, had questions, have doubts, could easily find our contact information
and then we could guide them through the process. Our website and blog use Hugo Engine and I
believe it's quite easy for everyone to use. Even I coped with it. Okay. So give a list
of ideas. Give a list of things you believe your project needs right now. Just write them
and post openly on your website, on your blog, so people knew they could find and understand
what you need right now. Also, we love to host streams and podcasts and provide a space
for people to come, invite people and talk on different topics. They can include their
career path, open source trends they see. Everything. Not necessarily just coding. And
to host streams we use ReStream, Riverside and PUBbean. If you have a community advocate
program, make sure you include noncode contributions in that and recognize contributors too. We
have cast written dashboards which help us to optimize the process of rewarding people
who made noncode contributions, who posted blogs and videos or mentioned us in their
talks. And we also use Orbit Love for that. And the last thing, but not the least, in
your messaging, emphasize why it matters. Why noncode contributions really matters to
your project. Explain that it is contribution indeed. Recognize it as a contribution. Because
noncoders tend to underestimate what they do. They think like, okay, I just fix the
people. Everyone can do that. No, not everyone. Not everyone will do. Not everyone will stop
by and spend five minutes on your project. So thank you for your attention. Pecona is
hiring. You can check to our website. And also this is nice part of my presentation.
You can participate in a raffle. Scan this QR code and you can win a ticket to Pecona
Live conference in Denver which will take place in May. You need to scan the QR code.
Fill out a simple form and we will choose one winner randomly after that.