Okay, good. Thank you. Well, I'm Gal Blondin. I work for the Eclipse Foundation.
Hello. Can you hear me? Is it working fine? Yeah. Well, I'm the other one.
Alberto, from Open Nebula. And the topic today, so actually that was a proposal from Alberto.
About how about we talk together at first about European Open Source.
So I think you proposed the topic and I proposed the title, which is,
is European Open Source a thing? Because well, over the last, I don't know, two,
three years, maybe more, I have been in lots of events where I see people who want to do
more Open Source because the thing that Open Source is good for Europe. But at some point,
there is always somebody who start with the idea that, well, Open Source is cool,
but what about we would do Open Source and try to limit it to European companies,
to European stakeholders or stuff like that. And so that's what we want to discuss today.
So we prepared it like a list of questions. We expect that some of you maybe want to
change your point of view. I think that we will have different point of views on some
of the topics. And well, let's start. Do you want to define European Open Source?
Okay. Well, I would like to explain a bit how selfish I am because this whole session for me
personally is... Second. Louder, like that. No, but you need to use the microphone because we are
recording. Okay. Yes. Okay. So I just wanted to explain for me personally what this session
means. As Gayle has mentioned, the concept of European Open Source has been around for a while.
It's been in the last three, four years that it's been discussed within this new geopolitical
environment in which we all live now, and also especially at European level. So for me,
I'm one of the people that's actually pushing for this concept to be something different from other
stuff. But I also, I can confess, I have my doubts about how we define European Open Source and where
that is something that might be divisive or counterproductive. Even have my position, let's
say, and that's also part of my job. And I'm happy to say both on my personal level and professional
level, I agree on the things I kind of defend. But I also have as a European some doubts about
this and what these might imply for the Open Source sector. So for me, this session is also
about learning what all of you think about this. And just because we thought that it was about time
to have an open discussion, an open debate within the European Open Source community, the implications
that this concept might have. Yes, maybe just a few words about me. So I work for the Egyptian
Foundation, which moved to its legal incorporation to Brussels two years ago. And that's very
important for us that we are a global organization established in Brussels. Because when it comes
to the answer to what is European Open Source, I think that from my perspective, at least Open
Source and free software, that's everything we do where you can use, study, modify and redistribute
the software. And there is nothing to do with Europe. So that must be done in Europe, outside
Europe. Everything that is written in Europe should be usable everywhere else. We should be
able to use. So that's really sticking to the definitions of the FSF and the open source
definition. So still, I think that we can have a specific approach to Open Source in Europe. That's
how we help European organizations, how we help European companies do more and understand better
in Open Source. And that's also why I wanted to start with this topic, because every time I go in
a conference, I have been in conferences where people were telling, yeah, well, we get money,
we invest in Open Source, and then we have the problem that what we do in Open Source could be
reused by non-European companies. I am thinking, oh, my God. Oh, that's so fucking wrong. Why do
you do that? Why do you do that? So that's really one part of the message I wanted to share today. I
think we agree on that. Still, I think that we should be more diligent in Europe about helping
European organizations, helping European companies, helping universities do Open Source, produce Open
Source, publish Open Source, and also be more ambitious about how to use Open Source as a vector
to project technologies and to project ideas in the rest of the world. We can come back to that.
Yep. So I think, I mean, from my perspective, coming from the European Open Source industry
sector, let's say, as a technology provider, as a company that produces Open Source and makes money
out of the services we provide to customers with this, I mean, I think we share that concern,
that I mean, Open Source cannot be something that in any way limits who's going to use that,
puts any barriers to who can improve the technology or contribute to that technology.
From my perspective, I mean, I've also been involved at several of the European initiatives
for things like data sovereignty and cloud sovereignty, these kinds of discussions,
things like the European Alliance for Industrial Data Edge and Cloud. That's something that the
European Commission launched a couple of years ago. So for me and other people in the sector,
I would say, I think exploring this concept of what European Open Source means is kind of a natural
step after we discuss the problem we have in the market now with cloud providers. So from our
perspective is, okay, we have, we recognize, we identify there's a market failure in Europe in
terms of access to different cloud providers or the dominance of a number of non-European
hyperscalers, you all know the names. Let's fix that because the European players are playing in
this advantage here. So for us, the next step is, okay, so what are the technologies that European
cloud providers are using? Are those led by European organizations? Are those roadmaps
defined in Europe or are those technologies defined and implemented by non-EU companies and
organizations? So for us, it was like the next step, like, okay, what if we apply this sense of this
concept of sovereignty of technological autonomy, let's say, also to the not just the proprietary
software, but the open source software that supports all these cloud infrastructures and
European cloud providers, but other companies as well. Can we do that? I mean, can we get some
understanding of what that will imply for Europe in terms of getting the industry involved in
producing and maintaining the technologies that they consume, not just being mere spectators of
what all the companies and organizations produce outside Europe most of times. So that's the,
that was the kind of the next discussion we had. Any question at some point? Or maybe somebody wants
to shout and I'll say that. What do you think? What do you feel about the concept of European open
source? It's an oxymoron. Why? Yeah, I just don't understand why you put that adjective in front of
this nouns. Right? I mean, it's like, you can do that. It makes dramatic sense, but I don't understand
what the meaning would be. So for me, it's working for the life. Yeah, it's working for the life. I
think, I think we agree. And to be honest, that's definitely not the controversial part in it. I
think that, and to the point is that yes, open source is global and everything that is, that
intends to limit open source scope is certainly not what we want. Still, that's more to not take
it as an adjective, but to take it as a, okay, we have open source, open source is global. And
what we may want as European citizen working for a global organization or as another European citizen
with leading a European company, what we may want is to have a different strategy, like an industry
strategy to sustain and develop open source better differently in Europe. So I completely agree with
that. Yeah. And so that you should have policies and frameworks and a whole bunch of other types of
things. But to do so, let's use that example, right? Water forms the shape of the container that it's
putting. Right? So one, one talks about the, the, what water is, right? One talks about the fact
that it's in a bucket or in a cup or in something because the framework gives the structure to the
water. But you don't talk about whether the water is going to be bucket, bucketed water. Yeah.
We are not, we are not, okay. I'm French in Spanish, so it's possibly grammatically not the right
approach to the topic in English. At least I think that we set the stage for the conversation. Yeah.
So the comment is that it should be European open source industry. Yeah. And that's another aspect
that I like a lot. Yeah. Because for me, I think it's the only concern I've heard, like why this
matters, like is, it's the one about competition. So competition with US and other global companies.
And that is predominantly sort of like an industry concern. I think for example, like there might be
other concerns around sort of like governance of open source projects, like that are based in Europe
or have predominantly sort of a European contributors and things like that. But from my experience,
working with those projects, none of them have sort of, at least intentionally sort of isolationist
sort of like tendencies, they might be isolated just by fact of like, who they know or not to
have diversity of something like that. There's not, yeah, but there's not, it's not, it's less
about lack of outreach rather than we want to be answered. I think most, most of these projects
would rather be not seen as European, but rather as part of more open source movement. You want to
correct? So if we could please just have the seekers call on anyone who wants to speak, we'll
bring the mic to you. And then you have to speak really loudly into the mic. So but please call on
people and let us know. We'll bring the mic to them. Okay. So my take on that is that yes, there
is something that we could define as European open source industry. I think there's also something
we could call the European open source technology. And from my perspective, that is that open source
technology whose roadmap and whose governance is controlled by European organizations. That's
mean external non EU actors cannot or contributors cannot join that community or contribute to that
technology. But the roadmap, the vision of that technology, the values, if you want to talk about
that, the governance bodies that control those technologies are under European hands. Sorry,
before I have, I have slightly different opinion. And my opinion is here on this question seven,
I think that definitely one of the advantages of open source is that we move the needle from having
access to proprietary IP to having the skills to study, to understand, to master, to evolve, to
develop the open source software. And I think that what we need to do, what is what's the next step?
So you represent a relatively small company. And I think that we have a vibrant ecosystem of lots
of small company, small open source companies in Europe. And I think that what we need to do to
go to the next step instead in terms of European power in open source, technology impact in open
source is to involve the larger companies. And in Europe, we have a characteristic which is that
the larger companies are not software companies. With their automotive companies, their aircraft
companies, their utilities, etc. So we have a lot that is being done in terms of policies in engaging
the government. So we have government source pools, etc. But I think that if we really want to get
more leadership from Europe in this topic of global open source, that's really when we manage
to involve the big companies. So we work, for example, with automotive companies, mostly Germans,
but we have Volkswagen, Mercedes, Bosch, Continental, ZF, etc. So that's companies that it's very
interesting. Some of them have been doing software for a very long time, embedded software, etc. And
they are slowly getting to use open source to collaborate together. I think that's very
fundamental because they are likely about to create software that would be game changing for them,
but also for the rest of the industry. So I think that there is a happy battle which is, okay,
what can we do with open source? And on the other side, you have the big, the GAF arm and big
software vendors. We don't have this big software industry in Europe. But open source is really a
tactical and potentially strategic tool that can be used by all our industry. And one of the problems
is that in this industry, all the managers, they have no clue about software. They have no clue
about open source, even less. And so they hear about open source, like, oh, it's open, it's good,
etc. And I think that collectively, we need to propagate the message that, well, doing open
source is, you need to take care about your community, you need to take care, you need to
have a governance, you need to have rules of code of conduct, etc. And so that's really something
that may be counterintuitive for them when you talk to, I don't know, the CEO of an automotive
company that may be counterintuitive for them that open source can be good for them. But I think
that when it will be good for, when they engage with open source, that will also be good for you
because they need you and that will really grow how we collaborate in open source. Because for the
moment, and that's the reaction and what creates the fact that people want to talk about European
open source, that's exactly what you describe in where is the governance. And for the moment,
I can understand the frustration of some European actors, not the system integrators, because system
integrators take the technologies, they create a solution with this technology, and whatever the
technology comes from, they are happy. But for everybody else, to some extent, the fact that
they have these, those open source technologies coming from mostly the US is okay. So what is our
impact on it? Sorry, go ahead. Please, if you want to move away from IP, please do not refer to it as
European open source, but put another word on it, like European open source initiative framework,
community, something that refers to all the aspects aside from the software code. Because when you're
talking about European open source, you think about the code, the IP, and all this stuff, with that,
please use a framework or something that you describe the whole approach. So by the way,
that's leadership. In my mind, more leadership maybe, so we put it somewhere in the screen.
So when you skip away from IP and from non Europeans using open source software, and you can frame it
in a better way. So please refer to it to like an initiative or framework or something that you can
put multiple approaches to it. But please make a big please, please. Okay, just just quickly, I have
one here, then I saw this one next, and there was one up there, then this one, and then here. So I
will try my best. Okay, so this might not only work without the mask. One short question about
the European open source debate. Have you ever considered not to try to frame it as a kind of
license? Because we've seen from the development of the approach of the German carmakers to make
a German car operating system that they paid horribly amounts of pain when they forked off
certain line exports, and spend a triple digit amount of millions and something that they then
had to scroll back. Thus, it might be more useful to go to open source and give them some kind of
label as we are a company and we maintain it, and then eat the liability that comes with using open
source and can be contracted given that the cyber resilience act applies companies in Europe to
actually take the liabilities that come from using open source. So instead of making it a licensed
thing, you basically go to a certain software stack that you maintain that you can still freely
integrate developments from all over the world. And then you basically put a stamp on it like,
if you want to use it, you can contact us and pay us a service level agreement to do the
maintenance for that. And then we will also take the liability with regards to the liability that
will come with the cyber resilience act, where companies have to accept the risks that come from
open source and an IT security aspect. Would that be a different spin to actually fostering a money
flow into European open source companies and actually create a business model? I don't know.
We could try. Just a clarification, I mean, just put something that's going to be a real question
that we'll have to answer in Europe in a few months time, I would say. So let's say we in Europe
decide that we want to develop a specific piece of technology that we think it's crucial for Europe.
We want that piece of technology to be open source. It's going to be funded by with European
fundings and all this. We get, we managed to get the European industry on board, not just as a
consumers of passive consumers of open source, but as active maintainers and developers of open
source around this technology. And we want this technology in the long term to respond to European,
to the priorities of the European Union in terms of the industry and the geostrategic priorities of
the continent. We want that technology to respond to that. But how can we protect that from the
same technology? It's a hyperscaler contributing with a thousand developers to that project and
taking over the governance structures of that project. So how can we from that scenario protect
that open source technology as I define that? Is that a way we can do that without excluding
non-European companies from the government's bodies? I'm asking, because that's going to be a
point to have to respond in a few weeks time enough. Sorry, in a few months time with thinking
all the specific piece of technology that will be developing in Europe by the end of this year.
It's probably going to be the largest open source project in Europe. Yeah, sorry.
So here's next and then there was one over there, another over there, then over here and then over
there. So yeah, a real quick question maybe, hopefully. I find it very difficult to discuss
these topics in abstract terms. So I wonder, do you have concrete examples where kind of important
open source projects, their project management, the governance exercise or, you know, the development
happened against interests of European consumers, contributors. And if you have such concrete cases,
do you know whether this is because the Europeans didn't get involved or because the decision was
really done against them though they were engaged? Do you want to answer? Go ahead. Well, I mean,
in terms of open source projects that are largely controlled, let's say, by non-EU companies or
vendors, I mean, there are a number of examples there. You want me to give you some names?
Not examples for the projects that I can understand, but where the decisions project
management happened against European interests. I know that many open source projects are of course
led by US companies and organizations and so forth, but I'm explicitly asking for, you know,
controversial decisions, project management governance because... Sorry, so he's asking me
for a specific examples in which European companies have been sidelined by in some decisions in open
source projects. I don't know. Doesn't matter. It's about the risk. It's risk management. So how we
prevent things from happening, how we prevent things, vendors from dropping their support to
an open source project overnight and collapsing the sustainability of that project because
in Europe we have relied for so long on non-European companies to develop these technologies and
maintain them that we've lost the skills and the capabilities to take over. That's the problem.
We're talking about thousands of millions of euros invested in technology. I'll give you an example
of that. There's something called the important project of common European interest on next
generation proud infrastructure and services. IPSI this. That's mobilizing thousands of millions
from European funding to create a whole alternative stack of technologies for managing the cloud and
the edge in Europe. That's only for European companies and that is going to produce, I think,
in my opinion, the largest ever open source project in Europe. How we protect that if we open it up to
Google, AWS, Microsoft, the technology... I mean the companies for whom this technology is being
designed to neutralize their dominance in the market and prevent them from taking over the
edge computing market as well. That's a practical problem. That's a topic on which we will likely
disagree but that's fine. That's why we have a conversation. I think because from my perspective,
I think that if you talk about IPSI, if you talk about edge computing projects, I think that there
are effectively millions of euros that are spent on helping European companies and that means
companies with headquarters in Europe because I remember I was in such a project and one of the
comments we had when it was rejected is that you cannot get this specific funding because some
partners are not European. That's not a team. That's not just a company with a subsidiary in
Europe. We have the funding mechanism. That's already in place. Next, the question is not how
do we restrict some of the funding to help European companies. The question is how do we make it
effective? I think that we have a fundamental problem in Europe about that. We spend lots of
money and at some point in research projects, I don't know if you have been involved in those
research projects, but in research or innovation projects, we tell people, A, you need to do open
source. Some of them, and I would say 80% of them maybe, understand that they just need to publish
abandonware on GitHub to check the green box. They think, oh, come on. We published in open source.
I think that we also have to do our part and to understand that, yes, when you do open source,
you need to build a community, you need to build a governance, you need to... I imagine, I dream
maybe that a group of European companies, because they identify that a project that has been created
somewhere else is very important for them, takes over, sends enough developers in a meritocratic
environment to take over the governance of the project and to have more commuters, et cetera.
So I think there is... I know in most countries, in most continents, we can see some protectionist
approach and I don't like it. And my organization doesn't like it either. But I think that it's
really exactly... We should exactly do the opposite. That we have the framework to fund some
developments. We have the incentive or we have the requirement to make the development open source.
The problem is that at some point, it is lost in some of fine-grained open source initiatives
that never reach a critical mass. So of course, when I say that, I have an interest, is that,
okay, at the European Foundation, we can help people group together to reach such a critical
mass. But I mean it. I mean that there are plenty of open source foundations, as the Apache
Foundation. We are here in Europe and we are incorporated in Europe, post-it code in Europe.
And I want to see more critical mass of people and companies who group together and have the
ambition not to be reactive, but to really just create the next technology for edge computing,
for example. And the next technology for edge computing, that will be open source. Whether
it's a started bootstrap in Europe or it's bootstrap in the US or it's bootstrap in China,
everybody at some point will converge to a few of those technologies. So we need to do better
when we do open source. I don't say that for you. No, I agree. I mean, there's no discussion about
that. So I can tell you the next big tool for edge cloud in Europe is going to be open source.
So and that's it. And that involves the main industrial actors in the continent. So that's
a fact. We only have, it has to be approved by Digi competition and all that, but that's
minor details. But if that happens and goes well, we'll have a five-year project, five-year long
project developing some first class open source in Europe. And I agree with you. We have to
mobilize, I mean, the whole community beyond the small technology providers and we have to invest
those fundings better and more strategically as well. So as a company, for instance, I would love
if European projects hadn't been a horizon Europe or research and innovation projects hadn't been
spending this money in small pieces of software to contribute to open a stack, for instance,
which is our competitor and not to open Nebula or some other European providers. So the large,
one of the most striking things of the thing with the work we've been doing a couple of years is
bringing the main European open source providers into the European research and innovation
ecosystem because they weren't there. People like SUSE like MariaDB, limited. I mean, these people
have never ever considered even accessing trying to get this funding or contributing to research
and innovation projects in Europe. On the other hand, we find most of the US open source vendors,
but also cloud providers very well in the decision in that area. So that's something we also have to
work on to mobilize all these resources to actually help European open source companies
being more sustainable in the long term and get these contributions more more fluently.
So we have a question over here. Afterwards, I registered a question here, then one over there,
then I saw one over here and I saw one at the front. One request, if you want to ask a question,
please put your hand up and then try to get eye contact with me, then I can acknowledge that I
saw you. It's also a little bit difficult in this large room. So handing over. So what I think is
that like back to maybe this definition part where we have European open source, I feel like the open
source part of that is very much global. So it shouldn't be localized to any area really.
And then we have in Europe, what we should maybe improve on is the like those two aspects,
the using open source software and the creating open source software. And I can't exactly speak
for those major projects, which are like funded by huge companies either in Europe or mostly in
the US right now. But what I see is just a lot of individual projects from individual people who
just contribute to open source, perhaps even their free time or small company or whatever.
And right, but they still are, they are still the backbone of maybe an entire industry without
that industry even realizing. So I feel like this is where we as maybe the European Union or as Europe
in general could dramatically improve on is just to focus on those essential projects. I mean,
there's this, I forgot the name, a German fund for exactly those projects kind of project that
like the base project kind of small, but still really important. Yeah, exactly. Right. So I would
love to see more of these kinds of initiatives. And I think that's really important. Not, I mean,
I don't know if like those government as governance aspects of open source are even that important.
I see it if we are actually the main consumer of something or we have specific goals we want to
realize in open source as Europe, but just I feel like just empowering those individuals or
companies or anyone who's contributing to important open source projects, regardless of if they are
have a government's role or not is really beneficial. Yeah. Well, I like the topic of empowering people.
I think that when we also when we fund open source, we have a topic is that sometimes maybe we don't
have enough money going down to the developers because, you know, I mean, in some of the places
where I hear a lot about open source, open source, open source, open source, sometimes I hardly find
the developers. And that's so that's we have the problem on the two sides of the spectrum. I mean,
we have under policy aspect, we have policy people who are talking about open source and that's fine.
I think that we need to potentially do better to characterize what we mean by open source and to
make it better consumable by the policy people. And on the other side, we have also, I think the
romantic view of open source being done by individuals, like what you describe, I think that
we have especially here at first day, okay, we have all the individuals coming for the weekend,
etc, all the volunteers, but I think that even in the room, we have also lots of people who are
doing open source for their day job. So that's, I think that I understand the individual aspect.
I think that there are also lots of projects that are not really supported by individuals,
but by some kind of organizations that requires those projects. And I think that after her bleed
and workforce share, etc, things that to some extent, the industry is embracing the topic and
trying to, how do you call it, do better and potentially hire those individuals and contract
your basis, etc, to take care of it. I mean, that's something, you know, any of you attended
the open forum Europe summit yesterday, but it was an interesting, if you can go, recommend if
you look at the talk by the CEO of GitHub, right? It's very interesting. He was arguing
about the AI act and how open source would be left outside the scope of the AI act because of the
nature of open source being run mainly by individuals. But then the contrast is when
you go to argue against the cyber resilience act, then the argument changes and it says,
look, I mean, we are companies, every open source is at some point commercial. So I think we have
to again discuss within, especially in Europe as well, how we explain what we do, how we explain
what the community is and it changes from different parts of the, I mean, if you look at the technology
stack and different projects, I mean, some projects are run by volunteers, some projects are run entirely
by the communities, some of the projects are run by companies alone. I mean, our project, we run it
alone. I mean, we control the roadmap, we control the releases and you can, you're free to contribute
with the site, we accept that or not. And that's it. Other projects, they have a different governance.
It's a community of companies and they somehow benefit from that shirt and that shirt knowledge
and that's perfectly fine. They collaboration among competitors and that's perfectly okay. I mean,
there are different models and I think they are all okay, but each of them have their own particularities.
So this concept of sovereignty in Europe, I think it's especially relevant for those
projects in which they are mainly maintained and controlled by companies, by open source companies
or other companies. So that's just to frame a bit the discussion, I mean, from my perspective.
So those are the kind of projects that for me personally and for others create some concern in
terms of if we develop these projects in Europe and we have this ambition of having the European
industry heavily involved in maintaining these projects, how we protect these technologies in
these communities from the very same companies we are creating this technology, not against,
but you understand me, right? I would like to come back to the European project and I think
it's really important. We want to be democratic. It means freedom and seeing what's happening right
now in the world, it's like, woohoo! So democracy and sustainability, I think it's part of the
European project and so how can we be leaders in and I prefer free software because free is in
freedom not as in free beer. How can we use that for interoperability that leads to right to
repair and that helps sustainability in the long run. So how can we put open source European software
to help build the European way of doing stuff, if I can say it like that. And I think that the
adversary of European open source software is international closed software more than international
open source software. I don't know. When I see that all the better universities are sold to Microsoft,
we have a problem. And how can we change that using European companies that are using open
source software? Yeah, I mean, that's a couple of big questions. I think as we see this debate
taking place, I think at certain parts of the technological world, let's say, part of this
stack, we are happily beyond the debate between open source or proprietary source. I mean, that's
something I understand in some other areas is not that clear. I mean, it's a daily sale. You have to
fight a lot with users and other companies to trust open source. In some parts, in some areas,
that's I think we are we are beyond that. So I'll tell you a very, very small anecdote. We have the
General Assembly of the industrial, what's the name? European Alliance for Industrial Data,
Edge and Cloud in December, for instance. It's only for it's a it's a it's a body of it's an
alliance, industry alliance set by the Commission or supported by the Commission led by the industry
only for European companies. Okay, we we are defining the roadmap, the technological roadmap
for for the cloud and the edge and edge. A bit of such promotion happened out of talk at five in
the sovereign cloud that room about the specifics of this initiative. So we are defining the
technological priorities that we need the Commission to help us co fund in the next year
of around edge cloud and data only for Europeans and when we have this this General Assembly here
in Brussels in December. There are three working groups, the cloud and its working group, the one
for member states, members from different governments. And there's there's an specific
working group for for the fence and aeronautic sector. And for me personally, I'm old enough to
have seen some changes in the sector. For me, watching at this five representatives across Europe
from the main defense companies saying they they understand I mean, they want to use open source,
they do want to use open source, they just need help to use open source, but they want that was
that was surprising for me. Okay, it's it's the defense sector. Okay. But you know, I mean, this
is people with a very specific mindset and very critical projects and very, very hard requirements
on the contracts they get all that stuff. They were saying we want to we want to use open source,
we just need to see how to actually put it under the requirements we have in this in the sector,
because because that's what we want to do. And they want to contribute to these projects,
they we just need to tell them how exactly with their peculiarities and their particularities. But
in some areas, we're happily beyond that discussion. And we are I think mature, I mean, the market in
that area, so the sector is mature enough to get into the nuances of what do we mean by open source,
who's controlling open these open source, who's developing this, what are the risks of taking
assuming or using this technology or that other technology? I mean, obviously, I have to confess
that that's a debate is a small open source European company, this is an environment that benefits the
small company like us and others, because it helps us differentiate from others. But that's what it
is. I mean, we have the European open source sector, you know what it is. I mean, we have a few larger
companies, but most of us are smaller, even if we have been for years, producing very good
technologies, I think. But that's that's what it is. So the question. So we have one last question.
Yeah, I saw many others registered this. But we can't take any further questions after this one.
So I'm very sorry about those who gave their sign to me. And we can't take your question.
Thank you. It's not so much a question anymore, given the time, but I think given what's on the
slide right now, as you've been open source, I think you talk a lot about governance of it. I
think it's about dependence on external actors, which are not a year, but I think we want to be
self sovereign, as it's now the type. But I think we should have expertise in it. It doesn't
necessarily need to be European development. We need European expertise to judge it. And if
somebody decides to stop that, we can take over. It's not so much that we created in the first
place, but we need to build the expertise not only in development, but also in knowledge about using
it, promoting it. I think that's one of the things we just lack education. Exactly. We need more
education on both development and promotion of open source and using it. I think that's the thing.
We need European education on this. I think we agree on that. And in order to see my, when I
put that sentence, and again, I'm French that maybe incorrect English, but my goal was that to
bring us to quickly conclude that the short answer is no. But I think that we must have a European
industry, our industrial strategy for open source. And I think that we at least can agree on that.
And we have lots of talks about open source in the European setup. And it was mentioned in one
of the questions with the CRA. And I think that, okay, on one side, for me, that's really interesting
to see that the cyber residence act mentions open source as an exception. But the way it mentions
open source as an exception is something that is almost not acceptable for lots of people in open
source, because that creates lots of concerns. And so on one side, we have incentives, lots of
incentives to do more open source in Europe. And on the other side, we are creating regulations that
could break the way to redistribute software. So that would really be a problem. And that was
my conclusion. So your conclusion, and we are done. My conclusion is that the time's up.
Thank you, everyone.