I just have to mention that our board has put out a recruitment call, a call for nominations.
We're trying to expand our board.
So if you go to fsf.org, it'll be the top news item.
It's something I just want to plug before I get started.
We also host another conference in a month.
You'll see some information about that too.
So my talk is about SAS, and that stands for Public Speaking.
It takes just a minute.
A service as a software substitute.
And what that means is when you run a service, when you use a service, and you use it to
substitute for your own computing.
And that's a little abstract, so I specify give an example.
And the one I like to give is a photo editing service.
So say you go to a website, you upload a photo, you tell it, you want to turn it black and
white, and you click a button, it does it, and then you click download and you've got
your photo.
Well, that computation done on the back on the server is something that you should control
with a program, with a free photo editing program like GIMP.
And so when you use a service like that, you give away your software freedom in a very
similar way to using a proprietary program on your computer.
But in some ways it's even worse, because the server operator, it's automatically spire,
has all your data, and it automatically has a backdoor to make changes at any time.
So in some ways even worse than a proprietary software.
So I want to talk about, that's sort of the basic case, but I'm going to assume you understand
software freedom a bit.
So I'm going to go into some more other cases.
So let's talk about first some basic examples of when something is not SAS.
So when somebody else is inherently involved in the activity, that's kind of usually a
good giveaway.
So communication service is an example.
Say I want to send you a message across the internet.
We need some intermediary to write that message.
It's just I don't have a direct connection to everybody else.
So somebody has to provide a service to do that.
It's necessary.
Another good example is publication.
So I give you some data.
I send you an email.
I say you can publish it.
Well, there's nothing wrong with you doing that versus me doing that.
It's just publishing information.
Now some websites offer multiple services and well, or one they call it one service,
but it has many different use cases and some are SAS and some aren't.
And let me digress just for a second.
This SAS has nothing to do with the SAS with two S's.
It was kind of meant to be a bad pun and it didn't work out that great.
So just know that when I'm saying SAS, I'm talking about the SAS with the three S's and
you just have to understand by context.
So as I was saying, some services have multiple use cases.
Some are SAS, some aren't.
An example would be the website Flickr.
It's meant to share photos, publication, not SAS, but then it also has photo editing features
that is SAS as I talked about.
So let's move on to another example, a backup service.
So a backup service is something people often like to run themselves.
So you think, well, is it SAS?
Is it not?
Well, if the backup, if the point of the backup service is to give you back your files exactly
as you gave it to them, then it's not SAS because there's no computation there that
you should control if you're only hoping to get back the exact same data that you gave
it.
The result wouldn't be any different.
Now you may want to run that backup service for reasons other than SAS.
Maybe you think it's more reliable.
Maybe you think you have some privacy there.
And that's one of the complications with SAS and services in general is that there are
other concerns besides SAS that are often very important to people.
So it makes it a little difficult to talk about it.
That's part of the reason I'm talking about it today.
Now how about the case of a database as a database service, for example, a SQL database
service?
Well, in this case, SQL queries are actually complex computation.
There's huge manuals for them.
How they work matters to the people using it.
They want specific database programs.
They care about what the version is running.
They care about how that computation is run.
So yes, it would be a SAS if it's a database service.
But then think about contrast, a backup service, and a database service.
So say you use a database service, but you use it like a backup service.
You just dump some data into a single table, and you just retrieve that table.
Well then you're using it like a backup service, and suddenly it's not SAS anymore.
So what we have to think about is the primary purpose of how you're using the service.
And when I say primary purpose, that brings me to a secondary purpose.
And it's not really a secondary purpose that I want to talk about.
But let me bring up another example.
Say you upload some files to your backup service.
And then you say to the backup service, what files do I have?
And the backup service returns you a list of files sorted alphabetically.
So if you have a list of files on your computer and you wanted it sorted, well that would
be something you would want to do on your computer.
You'd want to run the sorting algorithm, something you should control, how it's sorted.
Definitely matters to you.
That's your computation.
But then when the backup service does it, well it has to tell you those files, and it
has to sort them somehow.
It has to give you to them in some sorted order.
So in this case, it's doing computation that is what I call incidental computing.
It's not your primary purpose.
Your purpose is just to find out what files are on the backup service.
Incidentally, there has to be some computing done in that process, which happens to also
be like computing you would do on your own computer if you were running locally.
But it's not the primary purpose of using that service.
So it wouldn't be SAS.
Another way to call it was ancillary computing.
And so when you pick apart a service and its use cases, this is one way to narrow down
the issue to whether something is SAS or is not SAS.
Now for another more complicated example, I've been talking about the computing of an
individual person, but groups can come together for a common purpose, form an organization
or a project, and then they use a server to collaborate with each other.
And an example of this would be like Wikipedia, which runs, well, media wiki, and Wikipedia
and people who, and groups who run media wiki.
Now that service has features like document editing, dipping documents, conflict resolution.
Those are the type of computing, if you were working on your own, something you would want
to control on your computer, but because you're working collaboratively with a group, you
could say the group's computing.
It's the group, and that group should be able to control its own computing by running its
own server and the software on it.
So you could say when you join in with that group, you're a member of that group and you're
collaborating and doing that group's computing.
So you can use those sort of features together.
And this is a little bit hard to think about because sometimes your computing versus a
group's computing can get a little blurry sometimes, but it's important to realize and
think about.
So onto another example.
Think about bug tracking, a bug tracker.
This is a very common piece of software that developers use.
Now one way that a bug tracker could work, or does work for some projects, is they have
a mailing list where they say, bugs go to this mailing list.
So somebody sends an email to the mailing list, say, I have a bug, and somebody responds
and says, yes, I agree, that's a bug.
Or somebody says, no, I don't think so.
And they discuss it.
Well, this is just a form of communication and publication, like a normal mailing list,
and I wouldn't call that SAS.
But consider a software like Bugzilla.
Well, it doesn't work that way.
Especially with a larger project, you customize it so that it has maybe even hundreds of fields.
And the people who are administering it are doing complicated queries on all of the bugs,
running queries that will modify all the bugs, reassign them.
And then it's starting to look like a complicated database with a front end.
And then I would call that SAS.
And this, I think, brings up a little bit of a problem in that it's very difficult.
A lot of software projects want sophisticated software for their project.
But they don't necessarily have the means to run that software, like Bugzilla.
Because complicated software is complicated to run, especially as a service.
Because you have data, you have backups, you have all of the details of running complicated
software.
So in that case, it's like a lot of projects out there actually running SAS, giving up
their freedom.
Well, yes, basically.
But it's an area where we have a long way to go, I think.
And a good way to deal with that situation is for projects to come together in a larger
project that is in their collective interest.
So some of the software I run or I help run, like the GNU project, where many software
packages come together, share the infrastructure that's going to be in all of their interests.
And that way, they're sort of doing a group computation together for a bug tracker.
But now this brings me to an example of GitHub.
So when I think of GitHub, I look around at the GitHub service.
And I think there are a few features that are clearly SAS.
One, some obvious examples would be continuous integration.
That's like they kind of give you a virtual machine and say, run some code on your software.
And well, if the code that you're running, well, is their code, then I guess that brings
up another topic of virtual machines, which are not SAS if you control them.
And but another feature of GitHub would be like they have a feature to tell you which
functions in two repositories are different.
Well, clearly that would be SAS because it's parsing the language of the repositories.
It's doing a complicated diff, function level diff on them.
And then some other features I think would not be SAS, like simply publishing a Git
repository.
That's just a publication of software, a publication of information, not SAS.
And then the bug tracker, for example.
I think in its basic form, it works very much like a simple form, like a mailing list that
one person posts, another person replies.
I would call that just a communication service.
But I'm not too familiar with all of the advanced features of GitHub.
But I get the suspicion that some of the maybe there might be some features of the bug tracker
which go into the SAS area when it gets more complicated, when you're an advanced user
of all of the features there.
So I haven't picked apart every piece of GitHub.
And it takes some time to do that analysis, which I haven't done.
But in general, this brings me to the next topic is that, well, I don't know how many
minutes do I have left?
10 more minutes.
10 minutes?
Great.
OK.
So I think I'm done with some basic examples of analyzing SAS or not.
And I'm happy to talk to people because there sometimes aren't bright lines.
And it's a little blurrier than with determining if a piece of software is free or not.
But it's not like there isn't blurry lines in that either.
So I think it's just something we have to deal with.
It's part of a lot of ethical issues, have their gray areas.
And I just happen to be highlighting them.
That's all.
I don't think it's an inherent problem with SAS at all, with the concept of SAS.
So now I want to bring up one common misconception is that a service which publishes some free
source code that it says it's running means that the users of the service have software
freedom.
They don't.
The users don't control that service.
They can't tell it what program to run.
You can only do that with a program on a server you control or on your own computer.
And there may be important code that it runs besides what's published.
I mean, generally, servers are not publishing the operating system or other things.
The first reason I gave is basically the fundamental one, but some other ones are that.
And of course, you can't ever be sure what somebody else's server is doing.
You haven't installed the program.
You can't be 100% sure.
It's different than running your own code on a server you control.
So for services that are not SAS, now I'm going to talk about this idea of publishing
source code and think about the difference and the interaction between SAS and the publishing
of service source code.
So when we think about publishing service source code, I think about the AGPL, which
says you have to publish the source code if it's a service to the users of it.
And what we say is that the publishing of source code benefits the community so that
they could use that source code.
That benefit is so important to people being able to use that code that it's worth mandating
with AGPL.
And we recommend it for all software that is intended to be run as a service.
And in fact, now not thinking about the SAS issue, but just in general, if I encounter
a service and I say, I think, would there be any reason somebody else besides the server
operator would want to run it?
If there is, if there's a plausible case of that, I think, well, then are they publishing
the source code?
If they aren't, why not?
I mean, why do they not want to benefit the community?
And another benefit that brings, I think the biggest one is if the service is working well,
good, maybe there's some fundamental services we all rely on, like DNS services.
But then if the service stops working, it adds conditions that people don't want to
agree to.
It adds, it changes.
Well, then the publishing of source code is sort of an insurance policy that somebody
else could start up a new service and users could move over there, and that is so important
that I think it's worth considering that in general for any service, which is separate
than the SAS issue.
And I think if we take a service like GitHub, I think that's obvious.
Of course, people would want to run their own GitHub.
So why we shouldn't accept a GitHub that doesn't have the service source code published, it's
just foolish to subject yourself to the whims of that service operator without having some
sort of insurance to go somewhere else, even if you aren't using it in a SAS way.
So I'm going to move on to my next topic, which basically I think the SAS has not gotten
enough attention in free software advocacy.
And why hasn't?
I think there's lots of reasons.
I talked a little bit about the complexity.
I think SAS was far less common in the past.
Nowadays, most services tend to require non-free software as a client, usually in the form
of JavaScript.
And so services in general have caused a lot of problems for software freedom, other problems
besides SAS.
But like I said, I think SAS needs to get more attention because it's becoming more
prevalent.
Database services have, in the past few years, become very popular.
Before that, it was much more common to run your own database.
A lot of people are relying on these services, which are SAS.
And so I think one interesting historical reason for a lack of focus on SAS is that,
well, it's not part of the GPL.
It's not part of any license.
When the GPL was being drafted, the FSF had its lawyers try and think of a way to add
in a provision against SAS, and they couldn't think of a way to do it.
So they just didn't.
And so when we say the GPL protects your freedom, well, there's one little hidden asterisk
there as long as you don't give it away in a SAS.
And I'd be curious to know some of the lawyers, maybe some lawyers here today, if they still
think that's the case.
If there's no way to have a SAS provision in a license, I'd be curious to what that
is.
I mean, it's the one case, I think, of the FSF saying, here's an important issue.
We couldn't write into the license.
I haven't heard many people talk about how that could be done.
Maybe not covering all SAS, but some portion of it.
I don't know.
I'm not a lawyer, but I would love to hear from some.
So how can you give SAS more attention?
I don't have all the answers.
It's just a couple ideas.
I think number one is just to simply call it out more.
When a company has a SAS business model, just say, hey, their business model is SAS.
That's taking away people's freedom.
That's a very simple way.
Another idea I have is that there's this term self-hosting, which basically seems to cover
the idea of SAS plus other things.
It's the idea of services, run yourself.
And sometimes it's even expanded to just non-services, a SAS services that should be run on your
own computer and not as a service at all and running themselves.
And people call that self-hosting.
So it's kind of the idea of self-hosting kind of covers SAS plus other things.
So I think also advocating for self-hosting and saying self-hosting overlaps very well
with software freedom is a way that we can advocate against SAS without having to deal
with the complexity of SAS itself of explaining it fully.
And I'm getting to the end of my talk here.
I think most of the ideas I want to share, I'd be happy to talk to people afterwards.
And one shout out to a specific program, GNU Units, which is a small SAS that many of you
many people use.
They ask Google or a search engine to convert between Celsius or Fahrenheit.
And there's a program you can do that on your own computer called GNU Units.
So look it up.
And that's all I've got.
Thanks,