Hello.
So one quick question for the next speakers.
Can you please identify yourself towards us then?
So Karen, who's the next one?
Sarah Chain.
So if you're around, then please come to Karen.
So our next speaker here is Luca Bonisi and he will talk about one topic when I first
saw what he was accomplishing there as one person.
It was amazing.
So and the rest he will talk about it, but yeah, it's amazing what one person was able
to do there.
Hello.
Welcome to Fosman and welcome to the Sorskum.
This talk is about the right to install any software on your device, on your own device.
And concept is what, in my opinion, is an unlawful behavior to install, to pre-install
software on a PC that you normally bought in your device.
Specifically, this software are a window, a proprietary software that are Windows and
Office.
I briefly introduced myself.
The images, sorry, because the images are missing.
Okay, we need to get the screen.
Sorry.
There we are, display.
How to make a single display.
Okay, I know this one, okay.
Very good.
Okay, I introduce a different introduce myself.
My name is Luca Bonisi.
I come from Italy.
My main job is developing a firmware of electronic devices.
And I also support some school and small office with free software, especially one school
that I defined a free software school where all teachers and students are using free software.
I have some of you that are always related to free software.
I am audio and video technicians where I use Abul, Jack, Jamil, Sinodena, and I play guitar
and piano, and I use Rose Garden as a MIDI player to record from piano.
I like to observe celestial objects like the ISS.
This image is the ISS photographed by me with a normal camera.
I built an Etradiprinter and using them mainly for pairing or also for fun.
I make some free software project or activity.
One is to make a chart on the effects of songs since I play piano and guitar and transpose
it automatically.
Another is I'm the maintainer of an official part of Zlacuo Linux distribution for many
platform and spews.
A project that I just started is to free your Android TV box.
I bought a cheap Android TV box and I installed Linux to be used as a general purpose devices.
And I am a volunteer of the FSC as a translator.
For FSC, I build this project that was built in Peru, a language that maybe not so used,
but I love it.
And I built this program to help translate on FSC, to help translation in the FSC, the
translation process, so the translation has not to care about the HTML formatting and
so on.
I contribute also at this fantastic book.
I maintain the repository of this free software book.
Free software means that this book is distributed with a free license.
And it was translated in five languages actually.
German, Ukrainian, Italian, Arabic and English.
The Italian book is not yet published, but we wish it would soon publish it.
And if you like this book, you can attend the reading of the book, this evening at 6
p.m.
And Matthias will be the reader, I think.
Okay.
Once I'll be, I make ice creams.
Since the book talks also about ice cream, it is very related to my hobby.
And if you are a producer, you go to Ubi 2 this evening.
In this presentation, we found many illustrations, like the one on the right, that comes from
the book.
So I sponsored a little bit the book.
Okay.
We start with the presentation.
We have two different contracts.
One is for the hardware and one is for the software.
This contract cannot be joined together.
You cannot force to join the contract and to force to give back also the hardware if
you ask for the refund.
Because the hardware contract is a sales and purchase agreement.
And you become the ownership of the product, of your PC, of the product.
And nobody can force you to do what you don't want to do.
Instead the software is a license agreement.
You have a right to use the software under some condition that for proprietary software,
like Windows and Office, are limitations.
Instead for free software are freedoms.
I talk about device neutrality.
Because you have the right to choose to install what software you like.
Also by installing free software on your device, you gain the sovereignty of your device.
Preparatory software, you don't know what proprietary software make on your device.
What proprietary software connect to some site that you don't know.
Using running free software can overcome software obsolescence.
Because especially with the newer version of proprietary software, you are forced to
change your hardware because newer version of proprietary software doesn't run on older
hardware.
Instead of free software, you can customize like I do with the two boxes and run also
on lower end devices.
And in this way you extend the hardware lifetime and also you reduce the electronic impact
of the loss.
There is also an open letter that the Free Software Foundation Europe asked you to sign
up to federalize to install any software on your device.
The link is this one.
Maybe it will be available later.
And Free Software Foundation Europe asked to the European Parliament and Commission and
also to the Public Administration to be able that every device should be independent from
the software it runs because using open standards and open interfaces.
This is related to our work because sometimes other manufacturers use this proprietary interface
that limit the possibility to use some feature of your device.
We can first of all technical others.
First say this is real what Microsoft says from a device I put here for the laptop surface
I put here.
Microsoft says that the device would not work properly with other operating system and they
are not supported.
This is said by Microsoft and this is true because my laptop surface that the touch screen
doesn't work.
The webcam doesn't work with new links due to proprietary interface of this device.
So installing the
reference to the links is not straightforward because the keyboard and the touchpad doesn't
work if you don't build the customizes kernel.
So the drivers for keyboard and touchpad are not in the main line but okay you can compile
and then it works.
The manufacturer could also lock the bootloader for example Microsoft with the armed devices
and Windows 8 lock the secure boot in a way that you cannot install software different
than Microsoft Windows.
So the device is not really your because you can only run software certified by another
party.
We come to legal hardware.
Manufacturers often say that you even if the license say that you must contact the manufacturers.
Manufacturers say that you have to ask the reference to the render or to Microsoft but this is
not true because the license agreement say that you have to contact the manufacturer.
Manufacturers say that you must also run the PC.
So you should have all the
you can't have only the software refund.
Manufacturers set a very little time span to ask for the refund usually only 30 days.
Infant says that you must prove you refuse the license but it is impossible to prove
you refuse the license because when you start from the first time Windows you have only
one button asset.
You cannot even power down the PC.
Especially if it is a laptop it could be a problem because the battery is integrated
as usual and you cannot power off the PC if you don't know that you have to press the
power button for that.
Gradually a manufacturer is reaching their policy and say that you must return the PC
to their laboratory because you must remove the product that is information about the
Windows license in the store in the BIOS.
And manufacturers set a price by your own not the market price of the Windows license.
When you first run the PC to see the license agreement because to refuse the license agreement
you have to see the license agreement.
With the latest Windows version it is mandatory to connect your PC to internet before viewing
the license agreement.
I think this could be not compliant to the GDPR because your PC sends information to
manufacturer and to Microsoft sites without your explicit agreement.
There is no refuse button as already said and you cannot install a different license
if you remove the Windows and you download the Microsoft Windows from Microsoft website
and you want to install a few license or also the Gradus license because Windows is Gradus.
This is only limitation that you cannot customize the toolbar.
You cannot do it because when you install the version you downloaded from the internet
it looks for the product key.
So you have in your search circuits.
Very briefly cases of the
Refund in Italy.
There was a case in 2005 against HPE.
The case came to the Supreme Court of Italy and that say the Refund must be give.
It worked about nine years it lasts to all the SQL.
The second case is similar.
It takes also nine years.
It's very similar.
And this case is regarding this PC.
And I repressed the Refund in 2018.
Lenovo refused categorically the Refund of the only software.
They asked that they say that I have to let a known of the PC.
But I filed a court case by myself without an order in Italy
because from my side it was clear that Lenovo has wrong.
But Lenovo introduced artificial complexity so that I cannot continue without an order.
So I asked for an order.
I win the first grade lawsuit.
But Lenovo immediately filed the second grade appeal, the second grade lawsuit.
And they lost the second grade but the judge of Montserrat-Couft
imposed to Lenovo primitive damages of 20,000 euros because they use the legal instruments
with bad faith, without any valid reason.
After these cases, we requested also other rules of the Refund.
The case was simpler but not so easy.
Azure, for example, asked to write on the PC to remove the product K.
In this case, since I had some front end, excessive front end,
I go with the bike to bring the my PC to Azure.
There are also other cases, one with Microsoft, as I already said.
One with HP, I filed a court case against HP.
They lost the court case.
But in this case, the judge does not recognize to me the legal fee.
So the balance was the same.
I lost what I gained from the Refund.
Other cases, I go...
This is interesting, the last year with Azure,
because when I asked to answer, this time I need the PC immediately,
so I cannot wait to send the PC to Azure and to give it back.
And that's to say that it was Microsoft that asked to send the PC
to the manufacturer to remove the product K.
Then I filed a court case, but it was stopped by the officer before
I had reached the first hearing, so they gave me 129 labels.
The latest case against Lenovo that was terminated three days ago.
Lenovo says again that you must write on the PC to the manufacturer
and they say that they are not satisfied by the license.
The license they propose, they are not satisfied by the license,
they themselves propose, so it is not very coherent.
Okay, asking for the phone, I go very quickly.
You have to power on the PC, you have to read the license,
contact the manufacturer, send the mail, and a certified email in Italy.
And you have to be very patient because many, many mails
you have to send before requesting the refund, before having the refund,
but you will have the refund.
Okay, one important thing is that the manufacturer artificially
increases the cost of the PC with a mandatory payment to Microsoft.
I think that if you obtain the refund, you have to give part of the refund
to some free software organization.
I give all 20,000 euros to this association.
And if you want to donate, you can go to the link down
and if you can support the Office of the Foundation for their valuable work.
Thank you.