Okay, thank you. Thank you, Rasaan. Actually, after hearing your talk, I'm kind of
concerned I should join the UniCraft community. Sounds to be fun there.
It's a treasure there, Kim.
Yeah, I see.
You don't have to test.
Okay, so my name is Sihan Kunza, as you now heard. I'm the lead maintainer, also the
original person that started that UniCraft project while being still a researcher at
NEC Labs Europe. In the meantime, we spinned off. We have now a startup also called UniCraft,
so it's the UniCraft GmbH, and I'm their CTO and co-founder. And yeah, we're building
a community and a startup at the same time.
So first question into the room, who has used UniCraft before, I would like to know. Okay.
Who has maybe a more theoretical background, what our key concepts in UniCraft are? Okay.
So then, yeah, I'll have some background slides to bring everybody on the same stage. And
then we jump directly into the binary compatibility topic, but I won't spend too much time here.
Okay. So with this picture, I usually start that. You see on the left side the traditional
setup when you have virtual machines and your applications running on them, so I mean, stuff
that you know since 20 years now. Then you have a setup which is more recent, the more
popular is using containers, where you basically run a hostOS on your hardware and then you
use isolation primitives on your host kernel to separate your containers from each other.
And then there's UniCernels. I don't know, is this interrupted somewhere? Okay.
It seems to be okay. Okay. So we think this could be a different execution environment,
especially for the container setup, bringing kind of maraging what you had before with
virtual machines with strong isolation and really more minimal hypervisors underneath
that are much more secure as well. And you don't need to do a shared host base which
can become an attack surface. And then you want the flexibility of containers, and this
is where we think a UniCernel can come in, so where you build a kernel per application.
So the thing is, since you know the application that you run on, you can also give up a lot
of principles you had in standard operating systems and do simplifications, which is totally
okay because it's not hitting your attack vector actually. So if you say one application,
you can go for a flat and single address space because that kernel that you have underneath
is just for your application for nothing else. We in UniCraft build a single monolithic
binary usually, so it's your application plus the kernel layers, and everything ends up
in function calls into drivers. And you get then further benefits, first by this simple
setup but also since you know your environment, you know where you run on, you know what you
run, so you can specialize the kernel layers that you need underneath. So you put only
drivers that you need to run on your target hypervisor. You build a separate image if you
run that application with a different hypervisor. So floppy drivers, forget it, you don't need
it. Virta.io only for KVM guests. Zen.netfront, for instance, only for Zen guests. And you
know the application, you have knowledge which features of the OS is needed, and that way
you can also from the top down specialize the operating system to just provide that
what you need. So this makes us also slightly different from the other UniCrun projects
maybe that you had heard of, so we are for sure not the first ones. But we claim we are
the ones that follow at least this principle as most strongest because we build it from
the beginning with that in mind, which is specialization. So everything that we implement
should never dictate any design principles. The concept is you know what you need for
your application, you know what you need to run your UniCrunals, so I want to give you
a highly customizable base where you pick and choose and configure of components and
specialize the kernel for you. So that led us to this principle, everything is a microlibrary,
which means for us even OS primitives are microlibraries, meaning a scheduler is a microlibrary,
a specific scheduler implementation is a microlibrary, so like a cooperative scheduler
or some schedulers that do a preemptive scheduling are different libraries, memory allocators,
also things like VFS, network stacks, the architectures, the platform supports and the
drivers are all libraries and because we are also going up the stack, the application interfaces.
So everything that has to do with POSIX, even that is split into multiple POSIX subsystem
libraries, the Linux system called ABI, which you will see in this talk now, and even language
run times, if you let's say run a JavaScript UniCrunal, you can build it with a JS engine.
And the project consists basically of a K config based configuration system and a build
system also make based to not come up with yet another build system, to make actually
entrance easy when people are familiar with Linux before.
And our library pool actually.
And to give you a rough idea of how this library pool is organized, I find this diagram nice,
so let's see if this works at this point.
So we divide roughly, so you don't find it that way in the repos, but we write roughly
the libraries into these different categories, so you have like here on the bottom, the platform
layer which basically includes drivers and platform support where you run on.
Then we have this OS primitives layer, these are then libraries that implement like a TCP
IP stack or file systems or something regarding scheduling, memory allocation, etc., etc.
And then always in mind there's like first the opportunity for you to replace components
in here and also that we provide also alternatives.
So you don't need to stick with light may IP if you don't like it, so you can provide
your own network stack here as well and reuse the rest of the stack too.
Then we have this POSIX compatibility layer, this is basically things here, FDTA, this
is for instance file descriptor handling as you know it, POSIX process has then aspects
about process IDs, process handling, etc., pthread API of course.
And then we have a libc layer where we also have at the moment actually three libcs, muscle
which is becoming our main thing now, a new lib that we had in the past to actually provide
all the libc functionally to the application but also actually for the other layers too.
It provides also things like mem copy which is like all over the place used.
Then Linux application compatibility, that was now a big topic for this release.
Why do we do application compatibility?
It's actually for us for adoption, to drive the adoption because most cloud software is
developed for Linux.
People are used to their software so we don't feel confident to ask them to use something
new or rewrite stuff from scratch.
And if you provide something like Linux compatibility you remove all the obstacles that people start
using UniCraft because they can run their application with UniCraft.
And our vision behind the project is to give seamless application support.
So the users that say they tell you I use that in that web server and it should be like
with the push of a button, so including with some tooling that we provide that we can run
that on UniCraft as they run it before on Linux and they benefit from all these nice
UniColonal properties which are lower boot times, less memory consumption and also improved
performance.
So now speaking about which possibilities you have for supporting Linux compatibility,
we divide actually compatibility into two main tracks.
One track is so-called native which means that we have the application sources and we
compile that together and link that together with the UniCraft build system.
And then we have on the other side the binary compatibility mode where the story is that
the application is built externally and we just get binary artifacts or the final image
event.
And then actually you can subdivide these two tracks.
On the native side we have which we did actually quite a lot until recently this UniCraft driven
compilation which basically meant that when you have your application you had to port
or mimic the application's original build system with the UniCraft build system and
then you compile all the sources with UniCraft.
Has the benefit that you're then staying in one universe and don't have potential conflicts
with compiler flags or things that influence your calling conventions between objects.
And then there is this way that you probably have also seen for instance with RAM kernels.
They did it a lot using an instrumented way where you actually utilize the build system
of an application with the cross compile feature and then you hook in and that's your entry
point into replacing the compile calls and make it fit for your UniCraft.
And then on the binary compatibility side we have so let's start here because that's
easier.
So of course so externally built and this means basically you have elf files so like
a shared library or an elf application.
What you need here is basically just to support loading that and get that into your address
space and then run it.
And then there's also this flavor of let's say build time linking which means that you
take some build artifacts from the original application build system like the intermediate
object files before it does the final link to the application image and you link those
together with the UniCraft system.
And I call it here binary compatible because you interface it on an API and not on the
API level like in the native cases.
So and here this is just a little mark that in the UniCraft project you will mostly find
these three modes in the project that people are working on.
So here that we never tried with UniCraft in fact but I mean some tooling and this should
work too actually.
So as you may have noticed native is about API compatibility so really on the programming
interface and binary compatibility is about the application binary interface so really
the compiled artifacts and how you have calling conventions here etc.
Where are your arguments in which register or how is your stack layout etc.
And this is here on a programming language level.
So the requirements for providing you let's say a native experience is POSIX and POSIX.
Most applications are written for POSIX so we have to do POSIX no excuse right.
So libc's will mostly cover that but yeah it's all about POSIX.
And the second point is that you also need to port the libraries that your application
additionally uses let's say yeah let's take engine access and web so right you have then
tons of library dependencies for instance for cryptographic things like setting up HTTPS
tunnels or doing some other things.
So those libraries you need also port here and add them so that you have the application
sources available during the build right.
On the binary compatibility side the requirements are you need to understand the else format,
shared libraries or binaries depending on which level you are driving it and then since
this stuff got built for Linux you must be aware that it can happen that that binary
will do directly a system call so it's instrumented because it got built together with a libc or
something like that to do an syscall assembly instruction which means on our side we need
to be able to handle those system calls as well.
And if we speak about shared library support we need to support all this library function
or library symbol linking actually right.
And additionally of course each data that is exchanged needs to be in the same representation.
This means because this is ABI right now imagine you have a C struct and here it's fine to
move some fields around because if you use the same definition for your compilation is
all fine you can sort the fields in the struct will all work.
Here you can't because your application they got built externally that layout of that struct
that binary layout that must fit otherwise you will read different fields right obviously.
And then for both modes which is important for us as an operating system we have of course
also some things that we need to provide to the application which are things that the
application just requires because it is that way on Linux meaning providing a procfs or
syscfs entries or files in slash etc or something like that right for because you know they
do they do sometimes silly things just to figure out in which time soon there are so
they go to slash etc and figure out what is configured and also the locales and etc.
So in closing that let's say this high level view up so that we have the full understanding
let's speak a bit about the pros and cons between these two modes.
The native side what is really nice here which is a really interesting pro so if you've
got everything put together you have quite of a natural way to change code in the application
to change code in the kernel to make maybe shortcuts between the application kernel interaction
and can use that for driving your specialization even further right and performance tune your
unique kernel for that application. The disadvantages you always need the source
codes because we are compiling everything here together and which is also let's say
for newcomers a bit difficult is if you require them that the application they have and they
say okay I have the source codes and I just run make and then it compiles but I have the
source code you need to instrument either the build system of the application as we
just saw with the instrument to build that also prompted or you actually we must say
okay sorry you can't use that build system now you need to mimic and write and uni-craft
make file equivalent to build your application. So this is why binary compatibility is actually
interesting really interesting for let's say newcomers because you don't need the source
code they can compile the application that they're interested in so if they need to compile
it let's say right the way as they usually do they don't need to care about uni-craft at all and
normally also no modifications to the application is needed obviously you can still do things here
but it's not a requirement. The risk that we saw by doing the work is at least for the for let's
say on the uni-kernel side is that you get into a risk that you need to implement things the way
how Linux does it and one really stupid example I get a bit nuts on that is providing an
implementation for Netlink sockets because if you have like a web application or you know any
application that does some networking and that application wants to figure out which networking
interfaces are configured and what are the IP addresses there so it will likely lose the libc
function get if address and that is implemented with a Netlink socket so this goes back here
right here I can just provide a get if address which is highly optimized in that sense right
which just returns in that struct all the interfaces but if I go binary compatible and if
I do it really don't an extreme means because that libc which is part of your binary here maybe opens
a socket which is address family Netlink and starts communicating about a socket with the
kernel to figure out the interface addresses which can be really silly right for a uni-kernel
right to do and then also it's maybe it's less opportunities but also a bit harder to specialize
in tune the kernel application interaction right because assuming you don't have access to the
source code of the application there's nothing you can do on the application side right so to give
you a rough idea what that means in performance because it uni-craft let's say the the second
important thing for us is always performance performance performance here we we just show
you nginx here compiled as a as a native version so meaning it uses the uni-craft build system to
build the nginx sources versus we run nginx on we call it elf loader so this is actually our
uni-craft application to load elf binaries and then a comparison here with a standard Linux and here
this is the same binary what that means in performance so it's this quick test we have
just the index page the standard default of any nginx installation served and this is like that the
performance numbers the takeaway here is if you just you know don't go into any special performance
tuning yes and start just you know getting the thing compiled and run you will end up in a similar
performance as if you just take the you know the elf loader to to run that application in binary
compatibility mode that is interesting because you don't need to see necessarily huge performance
drops the only thing that you lose is the potential to further optimize in this mode if you go for
this one but this the nice thing is you can still see benefits right running your application on
uni-craft right and to just give you an impression so this is here a go HTTP application where we go
a bit crazy about we are optimizing and specializing the interaction between the go application and
uni-craft yeah we can get more out of this we can really performance to increase stuff out of it
okay so now in the next slides I go over how we implement these modes with uni-craft because as
I said we we don't want to target just one mode we want to target multiple modes and it has also
some implementation challenges because as an engineer you also want to reuse code as much as
possible so we'll talk about the structure here okay so to give you an overview so this doesn't
mean now this that these applications run at the same time could be also be possible but it's just
to show you how the components get involved in our ecosystem so if you take just the left part the
native port of application we settle now on muscle to provide all the libc functionality that the
application needs and we have we have a library called syscall shim which is actually the heart
of our application compatibility and this is actually you can imagine this is a bit of a
registry where you know it knows where in which sub library a system called handler is implemented
and it can forward then the muscle calls to those places on the binary compatibility side you have
a library called this elf loader which is the the library that loads an elf binary into memory and
then here's the syscall shim taking care of handling binary system calls and now I will go
into the individual items to show a bit bit more zoomed in view what's happening there and we of
course you start with the heart with the core the syscall shim so here we have I mean some macros
when so when you develop like VFS core is our VFS library actually ported from OSB or POSIX
process where you do some some process functionality like get PID or something like that we have some
some macros that help you to define and a system call handler and it's really a system
kind of it's just a function that is defined at that point and you will register this to the
syscall shim then the the shim provides you two options how that system called handler can be
reached one is that compile time this is like macros macros and preprocessor which allows you
when you have a native application that does or they actually it's on the on the muscle side to
call a system call it will replace those calls or will return at compile time the function of
that library that implements that system call then it was also a runtime handler which is provided
here which does you know the typical syscall trap and running that function and behind the scenes
yeah and our aim as I mentioned we want to use we use code as much as possible so the idea is
that we implement that function for that system called just once and the syscall shim is helping
us depending on the modes doing a link or provided as binary compatible so let's go back to the
overview and then you will see it a bit more concrete with muscle but probably I said everything
already so we have muscle natively compiled with a unicraft build system now imagine you have the
application you have a write goes to muscle and muscle does then a UK syscall r write which is
then actually the symbol that is provided by the actual library that's implementing it and the
the rewriting happens as I said with the macros at compile time in libmuscle so what we did for
that is to replace that syscall muscle internal function with our syscall macro which then kicks
in the whole machinery to map a system call request to the direct function call the thing is that in
muscle not all but most of the system call requests have a static argument with the system
call number first so so so this this let's say write is an MC wrapper and internally there they're
setting preparing the arguments just maybe some checks before they go to the kernel and then they
have this syscall function with the number of the system call and then the arguments hand it over
and as soon that number is a const static you know just just written down in your code literally we
can do a direct mapping so that that right will directly do a function call with you kiss is cool
alright if if it's not static which is really happening only on two three places if I remember
correctly then of course we can provide an intermediate function that then does a switch
case and switch and jumps them to the actual system call handler and the thing is since everything
is configurable means I can have a build where be this core is not part of the build or POSIX
process is not part of the build then the syscall symbol automatically also with all this macro
magic that we do replace calls to non-existing system call handles with an inosys stop so that
for the applications look like a functional to implement it yeah and exactly so it's runtime
this is called shim is for that point out out of the game so everything happens at the compartment
so for the binary compatibility side that's unfortunately runtime thing and we have actually
two components here as I was mentioning the elf load itself which loads the the elf application
what we support today is static pies so if you have a static position independent executable
compiled you can run that and what also works is using your let's say with your libc together
provided dynamic linker meaning if you use glibc with the application you can use that dynamic
linkers so LD or SO and also run dynamically linked applications with that what it needs
is POSIX mapp as a library which implements all these mapp and unapp and protect functions
on the on the system call there then system calls are trapped here this is called shim and yeah I
think I said that then the library is not selected it's replaced with inosys so this is called shim
knows which system calls are available which which are not then there's a bit of a specialty
for handling a system call so the the system called trap handler so we provide it with a
system call shim and we don't need to do an domain switch so we have still a single address
space a single what's called not forget the word so it's all kernel privilege yeah so we have done
it's the same privilege domain exactly so we don't have a privilege domain switch as well right now
we have it good good good you learn something but we are sliding a different environment that
will show you later in the slide exactly what this means we have some different assumptions
that you have on the Linux system called API which requires us to do some extra steps unfortunately
so the first thing is Linux does not use extended register or if they use it they they guard it
meaning extended registers are floating point units vector units MMX SSE you know we do
unfortunately so we need to save that state because that's unexpected for an application
that was compiled for Linux before that these units could screw up when coming back from a
system call and the second thing is we don't have a TLS you know in the Linux kernel but
unfortunately on uni craft we have so we use the same even unfortunately the same TLS register so
we also need to save and restore that so that the application keeps its TLS and all the uni craft
functions operate on the uni craft TLS good before I continue and give you some let's say lessons
learned while implementing all these things I would like to give you a short demo and then
I give you speak a bit about what was tricky during the implementation and what our special
considerations that we had to do so then let's hope that this works so this is a super fresh
demo is don't touch it you will burn your fingers my colleagues so thank you mark for getting that
work just you know half an hour before the talk yeah he's amazing yeah okay so in this demo I have
actually engine X as a web server with a standard file system I'll show you with the files around
I have it once compiled natively and once compiled as a Linux application will run it with the
off-loader and you will see that the result is the same right so let's start with the native one
so I'm actually already so probably I need to increase a bit the size right that you can read
it the background is that good yeah that's to any hit you so I hope you can also in the last row
you can read perfect so yeah you have here the the engine X app checked out so we have my new
config so you can oh this the windows somehow wider no wait just one second no it's better
okay so you see the the application is here as an library here the engine X and then you have here
the configuration you know of of you know all this HTTP modules that engine X provides and you can
select and choose like this is really the uni craft way to do things because it builds a while and
for that that my laptop is not the fastest I built it already so you see here the result of the the
build directory you see each individual library that because of dependencies we're coming in and
we're compiled so like for instance POSIX, Feutex, POSIX socket, RAMFS, in memory file system and the
where is it now the application here that's the application image uncompressed so wait I can do
let you see how big it is so it's here 1.1 megabyte so this is like it a full image of engine X
including muscle including all the kernel code and driver to run on a chemo KVM x-rated machine
yeah and then let's let's run it to see what what happens so exactly it's already up and running to
show you these were roughly the arguments so we have in the meantime because I found chemo system
sometimes a bit brutal with command line arguments a wrapper script that shortens a few things but
in the end I mean this is this is running a chemo system and then you know it's attaching to this
virtual bridge take that kernel image load that in ID file system because we we serve a file from
from that RAMFS and here's also some parameters to set the IP address and that mask for that guest
and here down there so we can check actually see here set IPV4 that's the address where the unicorn
is up and yeah you see here with this w get line that yeah I get the page served and to prove that
this is real let kill let us kill this now the guest is gone and this is dead so no response
anymore good so now let's go to the elf loader which is also treated as an application that can
run other applications also here in the build directly let's do the same thing so has also
like similar dependencies of course it's prepared to run nginx so POSIX socket is there etc etc
where's G here so here's the image it's a bit smaller is now 526 kilobytes which provides
your environment to run and Linux elf of course the nginx image is not included here anymore right
so that is part of the rule file system and if I run this now so I so on purpose I enabled now
some debug output so that you see the proof that it does system calls well if you scroll up so the
initialization phase looks a bit different also sets the IP address here it extracting the the
the in it RD and here is starting to load the nginx binary the Linux binary from the in it ID and then
from that point on the elf loader was jumping into the application and you see every system call
that the application was doing and you can even see that you know some stuff probably this is
first GLC initialization here for instance etc local time it's trying to open and find some
configuration of course we don't have it we could provide one but it's still fine it's continuous
booting affinity we don't have so but whatever it continues yeah exactly and there's tons of mmaps
and you know EDC password etc so those files we had provide so you get a file descriptor returned
back otherwise would have stopped etc and then you know configuration and so forth and now you
should see that some system will happen when I access the access the page and you saw it happened
index was opened file descriptor 7 and here is there should be a right to the socket you know
over here this is probably the socket number four yeah I mean you get you get the impression what's
going on so it's working the same way okay how much time I do I have left five minutes five minutes
okay then actually three minutes just to leave some room for questions yeah exactly okay so let's
get quickly back so we had some learned lessons learned lessons for the native mode I mean the
thing is we have we have also this model like you heard the noise V we want to use just one libc in
our build right so meaning all the kernel implementation and all everything that the
application needs is one libc we provide multiple implementations of libc because muscle might be
for some users cases too thick still or too big so we have some and the alternative like no libc
and originally we had new lib and we need also what we want as well in our project is to keep
the libc as vanilla as possible like upstream as possible because we want to keep the maintenance
effort for updating the libc versions low but these causes then I mean let's just list them
I've speak just about one of these items some things that that you stumble on and one was quite
interesting was this get dense 64 issue that cost us some headache was many rust when fixing it
which caused or required actually a patch I've always fixing it yeah I've required a patch to
muscle the thing what happened here is that in this dear end dot H muscle is providing a mark
and alias right to use the non 64 version for get dense and if it finds code with using get that get
dense 64 because of this large file system support thing that was happening it maps it to get dense
right on the other side on the vfs of the first course side so this is the VFS implementation
where we provide the system call we need to provide both obviously we need to provide the
non 64 version and the 64 version and guess what we include dear end because we need a struct
definition here and then you can imagine so if you're familiar with C and preprocessor there's
a little hint with this thunder of course I mean this gets replaced and then you have two times
the same symbol and you're like what the hell is going on here all right yeah so let's keep this
because of time upcoming features Russell was telling a bit already especially for this topic
for application compatibility we will further improve it so this will be now our first release
to officially release out loader and an updated muscle version we want to make that more seamless
which requires a bit more under the hood libraries for that support you should also watch out for
features that are coming up for a seamless integration of unicraft into your Kubernetes
deployment no pressure Alex running unicraft on your infrastructure provider for instance AWS
Google Cloud etc and automatically packaging of your applications right and it would love or
actually all of us everyone with a new culture will off to hear also your feedback and what you
think about you know turning the cloud with unicorns to the next level yeah any feedback to me please
send to Simone right and these are again the project resources if you're interested you can just scan the QR code I think that's it okay Simone right we can take a couple of questions you can also address me to listen to me I mean yeah yeah so any quick yeah please first here and then on the back
yeah thanks a lot both of you for your talks I have a question regarding dynamically linked applications yeah
Linux as far as I can see you only use muscle and how does this work out if my application is linked against GWC and I want to run it with yeah I've loaded what do I have to do because in Linux world when I think against GWC and I only have muscle nothing works right right no so I'm so I'm assuming we
speak you know about the binary compatibility mode in the end what you just need to do is providing the muscle loader if you have compiled with your application with muscle or the G.
Lipsy loaded and then both works the thing is in that setup in memory there is actually two lip sees there's the lip see on the uni craft side and there's the lip see with your application so that's why it works seamless actually okay thank you
so just add to that when you build your unique kernel for binary compatibility you don't use muscle I mean you can if you want I mean because the entire lip see is provided by the application either by the application of course that the binary or the application plus it's lip see inside the root file system and it's loaded from there there's no need to have anything like that yeah please yeah yeah so the question is about the
API you spoke about the POSIX API yeah you also add a diagram showing a direct link to unique kernel so the question is is there some variable next diagram perhaps one of the next day at the other arm okay is it a variable use case yes this one there is a link
directly from the native application to the unique kernel yeah yeah this is what it shows you is like how the calls are going it can happen because some system calls don't have a provided lip see wrapper yeah it's like for that completeness this error is here for instance the few takes call if you do if you use few takes directly from your application there is no wrapper function in lip see you need to do a system call directly and you can do that by also using
the syscall macro then or actually I mean the syscall shim will replace that with the direct function call then to actually POSIX few takes no is it valuable to have kind of application that you develop specially for a unique unique
kernel and native API are you yes yes that's for sure that's for sure so this talk is just about how we get application compatibility in case you have your application already but if you write it anyway from scratch I recommend forget everything about POSIX and speak the native API's you get much more performance and more directly connected to your driver layers and API's that you know POSIX has some implications right there's a lot of things like read write
imply there's a mem copy happening and with these lower level API's you can do way quicker transfers because just because you can do a zero copy one sense yeah sure of course of course yeah have you looked into patching the binary to remove the syscall overhead patching the binary to remove for a couple
of the now with the syscalls do you have to emulate the syscalls have you looked into patching the binary itself yeah instead of running the EL doing it at runtime handling the syscalls at runtime yeah let's say this is at least we thought about that but we didn't do it I mean the
hardware talks that is the other exactly he's sitting in front of it they were doing some experiments with that that works too so you can patch it but yeah I mean this is just we didn't do it okay in regards to memory usage obviously
the unicorn all lowers it but what if I ran multiple unicorn alls multiple VMs how how do you support member loaning or something like that or is it like just over provision and yeah I mean the idea is to have member loaning it's but it's not upstream yet of course there's also some really interesting research project and we should mention that works on memory
deed application so if you run the same unicorn the same like a hundred times you can share VM memory pages right on the hypervisor side but you need hypervisor support for them okay thank you so much Simone let's end it here we're going to ask yeah yeah and get some stickers
Anastasia is for the next talk on VXL so please so please get some stickers yeah stickers they're they're free don't have to pay for now next year 100 euro each