Can you hear me?
Okay, fine.
Stepan, please.
Yes.
Good morning.
Hello and welcome to my talk.
I'm Stepan Karkowski.
I'm a G note developer since 2009.
And today I want to present you how to
transplant Linux kernel drivers into the
G note OS framework much more faster than before
and hopefully precisely.
So let me start with the motivation behind this.
Of course, you might ask why we use monolithic kernel drivers
when we talk in a microkernel devroom.
Of course, there are good reasons to implement
drivers from scratch and we also have several
drivers which are written from scratch,
but the ever-increasing complexity of modern
hardware for single devices but also for the
pure number of devices inside a system on ship
is not easy to handle for a small team.
That's the one reason.
And often it's poorly documented even if at all.
And we also have hardware bugs inside and you
have to find those bugs because they typically
are not documented and then you have to find
workarounds for it.
And all of this is mostly part of the Linux
kernel and you can reuse it because it's free
and open source software.
And so to sum it up, it's simply an economic decision.
So if you want to enable a modern device and
you have limited time, then this is the way to go.
Okay, we have collected a lot of experiences
in the last decades to port drivers from
Linux to the Geno-DOS framework and you have,
in general, two extreme approaches and the
reality is somewhere in between always.
So either you use just the pure driver code,
what I mean by this, I mean code which directly
interacts with the hardware by writing to some
I.O. registers or by setting up a DMA transfer
or something like this.
And in that case, you of course have to implement
each Linux kernel function that is called by
this driver code.
But the good thing is you don't have to implement
the whole semantic which the original function
is implementing.
You only have to match this semantic,
this single driver needs.
This leads to a more low complex function than
the original ones and in sum to a more minimal
Linux kernel driver.
But of course you cannot share this emulated
code in between different code bases.
So if you have not only one driver but several,
they will have slightly different semantic needs
and so reusing the same emulation code might be
a problem and therefore the whole effort,
if you don't only port one driver but several ones,
can increase if you ever and ever again have to
implement the whole emulation code base for the driver.
And of course you need the actual needs of that driver
so you need a deep knowledge of the driver itself.
On the one hand, this is the one approach,
on the other hand you can use as much as possible
from the original code base.
Thereby you might gain more or less the same
runtime behavior than the original one and you can
of course then better share resulting emulation code
because it's already stressed by this whole bunch
of code running on top.
Thereby you get less manual work to do for having
more than one driver.
But of course the code base for the single driver
increases because you have much more of the original
Linux kernel.
And if a problem arises, then you have to know
a lot of the whole Linux kernel itself because it
might be in the timing subsystem and whatever.
You can name it.
So in the recent past we were more on this side
on taking the pure driver approach.
But the high effort for each driver was also leading
to the situation that you keep your old code base,
that you are not that good and maintain the code
and getting a new kernel version in driver updates.
So and at some point there was need for action.
For me this was at the beginning of the pandemic
situation when I was trying to enable the display
engine of this device which is MNT reform 2 from
MNT RE, a small company from Berlin, so a completely
open hardware.
And yeah, I tried to enable the display engine
and it includes an NXP, IMX8, SOC.
And we already had a driver for this because a
colleague of me he enabled in three months on the
early evaluation kit the HDMI connected display.
So this was one part and then another colleague
of me wanted to have a touch screen which is
connected via DSi connector and not VR HDMI.
And again he had to spend three months into this
work because on the one hand there are more devices
involved now.
On the other hand you had all this bureaucracy
for device tree management and it was all hard
to do it for this first use case of using HDMI
for the specific board.
So there was a lot of manual tweaking to do to
enable the touch screen.
And then I wanted to, I thought yeah, I don't have
to do this someone else did it.
I can now use it for the MNT reform for the panel
because it's also connected via DSi.
But actually there's another device in between an
EDP bridge in between the DSi connector and the panel.
So yeah I had to do work again and then I recognized
oh no the code base we used for porting is a different
one than the one of the MNT reform and it's a totally
different kernel version you have to back port stuff
you cannot correlate it.
No I give up.
So that was a turning point for me to start a new
way of porting and of course it was not only me
but we had a lot of discussions formally in the
kitchen, you and coffee breaks, what we want to change
and so number one requirement for the new approach
was to reduce the manual work for tailoring a driver
specific environment.
And we wanted to meet as close as possible the original
semantic of the driver so that whenever you changed
the context like with this display engine it just works.
You don't have to do much more.
And because formally we all at some point we have
the impression you cannot be deterministic in knowing
when you will finish your porting work because when
some problem arises you could not correlate it to the
original runtime often.
So it was somehow hard and we wanted to change this
so it should be an easy way to correlate it to the
original runtime.
And last but not least we wanted to share more of
this resulting emulation code which is more semantic
complete so that we can maintain the code better.
Okay, so this is the story beforehand and now I come
to the actual work.
So I want to introduce you to this approach for those
of you who like to port drivers to G node or like
doing the same approach somewhere else.
So we typically start now by configuring minimal
executable Linux kernel.
We just call it tiny kernel so to say.
So you have to do some manual work here.
You have to use the Linux kernel built system itself
which has tiny config, some small configuration which
is at least compilable for your architecture but it
won't run any device.
And then you just enable certain configuration objects,
config options and of course you have to find them by
looking at the configurations.
And in the end this might take some time but in the
end you will have something which you can correlate
laterally if you run the driver in your ported
environment and you want to look why doesn't it work
then you really have a minimal Linux kernel which just
drives this device and this is the first thing to do.
And another aspect of this is that you gain a minimal
kernel configuration for your code base which just
calls those kernel functions that you really actually
need to drive that device.
So you don't have to emulate that much.
Okay, kernel configuration is only one part.
If you take an ARM device today then you have of
course these device trees which name what kind of
devices you actually have in hardware and which also
contain additional driver information so it's a bit of
configuration is also inside of these device trees.
And this is the device tree for the MNT reform.
You see it's quite complex so you have to identify what
kind of devices are interesting for my tiny kernel
to execute those and this is again some work to do,
some manual work to do but at least you start to know
more about the dependencies of your hardware.
And we have developed some tooling for it.
So you can, this is a small tickle shared script which
passes the device tree sources and then you can name
device nodes that should be extracted and it will take
them and the transitive closure to give you something
like this and then you can take that device tree of
course with your tiny kernel and start it and it will
just drive that device.
And we also take that for our own ported drivers as
input value.
Of course you won't implement everything which is
seen here so powering, reset pins,
IQ stuff like GPIO or something like this would be
part of other drivers in the system like the platform
driver or some dedicated GPIO driver in the
GenoDOS framework.
So those highlighted ones are the ones that we actually
need for porting and this is the starting point for you
to identify the first compilation set that you need.
So each of those device drivers has some
compatibility string and those are used in Linux to
identify the concrete driver of the Linux kernel.
And so you can take those strings and grab in the
Linux kernel sources and then you get something like this.
So you have your first compilation set units and you
can put them into a make file, into a build environment
and then we combine it with the unmodified Linux
kernel headers.
So we take the original include path of the Linux
kernel.
Formerly we always define the whole definitions you
needed by hand so this was a lot of work to do.
I would say initially the most work you had to do.
And now we just take the original Linux headers and
then you can just compile those compilation units you
already have seen.
So it's really a work which is done by this.
But of course there are some exceptions.
So we had to tweak some headers.
We shadow some few headers to prevent the system from
trying to enable, disable interrupts or something like
this.
And especially to define init cores in the Linux
kernel.
So each subsystem in the kernel including any driver
has some init core definition and those are the order
of the init cores is important.
Even if you have one init core priority level there are
dependencies in between the different compilation
units and they are solved by linking order.
So the Linux kernel uses some weird linking magic to
put them all into one order and later when starting
the kernel it takes that order.
So we didn't want it to infect our linking script
with this.
So there by we have built some tooling again which
uses this tiny kernel you built in the very beginning
and just extracts the order of the init cores,
put it into a header and you can just include it in
this built environment and then you run and it will,
yeah, it will, the emulation code environment of us
will just call the init cores by the correct order.
When we all do all of this then you of course get a
lot of undefined references for all the functions
which are not implemented yet.
And this is a lot of error messages from the compiler
so we made a small tool to identify those undefined
symbols, help you to identify the original compilation
unit which implements them and then you can try to
find a correct setup for this.
And I want to show you this shortly.
Oh yeah, yeah.
Okay.
So I've prepared some makefile like here.
So here you see the compilation units we identified.
There's some inclusion of the general emulation
code base and yeah, if you now use this tool,
it will build the target with your name so it will
try to build a driver and it will collect all the
undefined symbols and here it just shows you the
symbols and the overall count of the undefined symbols.
Typically you can also have what I said the compilation
unit which is responsible but I've skipped this here
because on this machine it's a bit slow.
So we can now identify, okay, there are symbols for
DRM mode which we want to solve and we see, okay,
let's try to add the original one.
Sorry.
And yeah, you just run the tool again and it will
show you in a few seconds.
So on the PC this is quite quick but this is just
one gigahertz or whatever, I don't know.
So it's a bit lame and it has to recompile the driver
of course in the background.
Okay, and now you see it's seven symbols less and in
the end I think because of the time we will skip this
in the end you can generate with the tool the missing
symbols and it will give you per function the correct
declaration of the function of course and it calls a
function which gives you the backtrace fill them and
just loops endlessly so you have a no returning
function therefore you don't have to get a valid value
back or something like this.
So if you now take the driver it will link, you can
start to execute it and you will always get the point
where something is not implemented yet.
Okay, so let me just switch back.
So, okay.
So this is the overview of the APIs involved.
I don't want to explain them in detail now but what
you should take from that is we have a very strict
layering.
There is this layer where there is only a C and
assembly code which is actually the Linux kernel code
and the shadow copies of the Linux kernel code.
Those are the only ones which can include Linux kernel
headers and then you have this emulation code base
which is just a C abstraction for the Linux kernel code
above and then you have all this C++ stuff from us
which abstracts the Geno services and the concrete
driver services.
And the good thing is you have those abstractions here
from the device services and you have their pondong
here and then if there is one let's say for an
Ethernet class you can just reuse it.
So if you already have this in our emulation code base
you just need to implement or port the concrete driver
but you have all this glue code which connects with
the actual APIs and services.
It's all always there.
Okay so now let's see this in practice.
Okay I just skip this here and once you shut down
the Fitch Machine Monitor.
So you actually see the whole time Geno in action
and what you see here on this mount reform is actually
everything the device brings with it except audio.
So all other drivers are already in place and this
also is valid for the GPU for instance.
So here you can see the GL mark demo again.
Those of you who have seen Norman's presentation yesterday
already knows it.
So I think I run out of time.
Okay good.
Anyway I think this is enough.
As I said more or less everything runs on this device.
Yeah so what are the results?
So this is the list of drivers we have ported within
one year now besides of course doing other stuff.
So we don't just port drivers all the time
but this is really a significant change.
So we have taken new drivers for our whole X86 code base
for instance and you see a lot of ARM drivers for the
iPhone and for the MNT reform are also added like the
Mali and the Vante GPU for instance.
And this was done by a very small team and we also had
some architecture independent porting of WireGuard
so something which doesn't even use any device at all.
Okay so in numbers the initial driver porting
so nowadays to compare to the initial approach
we have something like 15% of the time that it takes to do this.
Of course it's a bit hard to measure because we don't track
all the times we do in spending porting work
but approximately this is the number.
And this is especially because of this tooling
which reduces the manual work.
Of course you have to find semantic backs
but here this tiny kernel correlation helps a lot.
So you can instrument the original code then just run it on
original Linux and on your ported code and you can see the difference.
Driver updating we also did this within that year
because the first port was done for this display engine
and then there was a new version available, two kernel versions later
and we made an update so it's significantly faster
than the initial driver port of course.
And the drivers meet a better all purpose.
This is what I meant with for instance it took one day
to enable the HDMI connector for the MNT reform once
the panel worked so it's much better matching the different contexts.
And of course there's something bad on the other hand
so the code base for a single driver explodes like two or three times more than before.
Yeah but on the other hand the code to maintain by ourself
decreased to the count of 20% than before.
Okay so I think that's it.
If you want to read more about this I can reference this book,
the second G-note book about how to enable a platform.
There's a lot of this stuff already written by Norman
and we have also much details in different Genolian's blog articles.
So thank you for your attention and I'm open for questions.
Thanks Stefan. Any questions? Yeah please.
Yeah first of all awesome work by the way.
Thank you.
Linux is known for not having a stable driver API.
I think there's a Linux developer from Red Hat who once says
we do not do hardware extraction layers in Linux.
I just did say that the initial port is the hardest
and then there's a lot less work maintaining back ports going forward
but there's still some work involved.
So I was wondering, wouldn't it be less painful to for instance support drivers from BSD
because I'm not mistaken they have a more stable hardware extraction layer.
That might be probably the case but actually we want to have this first argument.
Linux runs on all kind of hardware and all kind of different situations.
You have for instance we have a BSD port driver for audio
but for today's Intel HD audio devices it's somehow, yeah,
that device might work but on that device the microphone doesn't work on that device.
So it's more about we just want to have the functionality
and therefore we need to look at this.
And of course we were not, yeah, we didn't like to get kernel experts,
Linux kernel experts but now we had to do it and yeah,
if you once dived into it then maybe we just take that advantage.
Thank you.
Another question here from other.
Hi, great talk and so I was just wondering,
I wonder if I might be able to use your tooling to introduce NVMe driver into OSV
but I also wonder if maybe similar approach could be used to also port file system drivers
into operating system like OSV is missing an ext2 driver
and I wonder if I could do something like that.
I'm pretty sure you can, I mean we already used this RAM kernel approach
from Ante Kanter who was also in the staff room in the past years
and the support BSD port of the protocol stack
and we also used the Linux IP stack in the past from Linux
and we will of course use this approach again to renew that version
and there's, as I said, we already used Wireguard for this
so something which is not at all connected to any device driver code.
It's possible.
Thank you.
I have a question on licensing, is it okay because GPL, BSD?
It's all under GPL then, only, of course.
Each driver we port has to be under GPL so.
It's no problem with having the link together, I'm not sure about the license of G-node.
No, it's not a problem because this code then is only GPL code
and G-node itself is also under GPL so it's possible.
Thank you very much.
Thank you so much, Stefan. Let's take it again.
Thank you.