Thank you.
So hi, my name is Drew, and I'd like to talk to you today about a new microkernel I've
been working on called Helios.
For context, I work at a place called Sourceset, and I'm the project lead for a new programming
language called Hair.
And I've done many other projects, but that's what's relevant for today.
Helios is a new microkernel.
It's inspired a lot by SEL4, but it differs in many ways.
It's written in this hair programming language that I mentioned, and one of the main motivations
for it is to find out if we can use the hair programming language to write microkernel,
or any kind of kernel, really.
Presently it runs on X8664 and ARM64, and we're thinking about RISC-V in the foreseeable
future.
In terms of the footprint of this kernel, it's pretty small.
The portable code is about 8,500 lines of code.
Each architecture adds about another 3,000 lines of code, all hair code, and then add
on top of that the boot loaders, which are also written in hair, and it's a pretty small
footprint.
We've been working on it for about nine months now, and we use the GPL3 license.
So again, about nine months of progress so far.
Where do we stand in terms of functionality is about here.
We have capability-based security, and the capabilities do work, similar to what SEL4
does, and also similar to SEL4, we have inter-processed communication working using endpoints and
notifications, very similar to SEL4 with some notable differences.
We have scheduler work, we're in user space, and we have multiprocessing, but we don't
have symmetric multiprocessing.
We have only one core at the moment, but we'll do SMP fairly soon.
We also have all of the necessary riggings in place for drivers in user space, so we
have access to ports on x86, and we have memory and map.io support, as well as iRQs are rigged
up.
For booting up the kernel, we currently support EFI on ARM, and Multipoot on x86.
We'll be doing EFI on x86 as well in the future, and our plan is to also do EFI on RISC-V,
so we'll use EFI as the default approach for booting Helios in the future.
Why should we be thinking about writing a new macrokernel, or a new kernel of any sort?
I imagine that for this particular dev room, I don't need to give too many reasons, but
for the sake of anybody who's maybe watching online, the first point is pretty obvious.
It's really fun to write kernels, and that's kind of reason enough, so I'm having a great
time working on it, and that's enough for me.
But also importantly, we've been working on this programming language, Herr, for about
three years now, and it's a systems programming language, and one of our goals is to be able
to write things like kernels, and so in order to prove that we have achieved this goal,
we have to write a kernel with it, and so Helios is that kernel.
I also am a big fan of SCL4's design, but I also have some criticisms of it, and I'm
curious if we do a kernel which is inspired by SCL4, can we make some improvements on
its design?
And if we were to be particularly ambitious, could we perhaps do better than Linux?
We'll see.
I should also point out that this slide deck is going to cover a lot of details which maybe
will seem redundant to people who are already familiar with the design of SCL4, and that
could be a problem with this audience, but please bear with me while I explain things
that you already understand at some point in the future.
So the HAIR programming language, this is the pitch from the website, I won't read it
out to you, but essentially it's a very simple language which is very close to C in terms
of design, but with a lot of benefit of 50 years of hindsight of what could be made better
about C. But compared to other C alternatives that are floating around today like Rust and
Zig and Nim and so on, I would say HAIR is much, much closer to C's original ideas than
any of these other attempts, but it improves in many respects like dealing with modules
and error handling and bounce checked things and some safety features.
So it improves in a number of respects.
It's also very, very simple.
So here we have some more line counts for people who like the line counts.
The HAIR compiler is 18,000 lines of code in C11.
The back end that we use, it's not LLVM, we use CUBE as our back end, is another 12,000
lines of C99.
And then we use binutils for the linker and assembler.
And that's it.
We support three targets, X8664, AR64 and RISC564, which is no coincidence that those are the
targets I'm working on for the macrokernel.
We intend to add more, but this is where the language is at.
I started, you know, again, I started HAIR specifically to work on this kind of project.
And this project exists to validate the language design for this use case.
And also because it's fun and maybe it could be useful.
For those of us who have never seen any HAIR code before, I just have a little snippet
here so you can get a vague idea of what it looks like.
Again, not going to explain this in too much detail, but if you're familiar with C, a lot
of things will seem familiar to you.
And you can probably guess, you know, the double colon does namespaces.
Maybe you can guess what the no return tag does.
It's fairly straightforward programming language.
And this is what it looks like.
The code sample we're looking at here is the portable kernel entry point.
So it starts at the boot letter entry point and then the arch specific entry point.
This is the first line of portable code that runs when you boot the kernel.
So with the context out of the way, let's talk about Helios itself.
We're going to go over a number of things here with respect to the design of Helios
and the implementation of Helios.
So I'm going to talk about our approach to capabilities and on memory management and
some other things specific with how various capabilities actually work like processes
and threads and talk about inter-process communication.
And then also talk a little bit about the implementation as well, not just the design.
So here is the big picture in terms of the implementation.
Again, those who are familiar with SEL4 will find no surprises on this slide.
But essentially, access to all system resources, including kernel objects, is semantically
governed by user space.
And we use the MMU to isolate user space processes from each other and to enforce this capability
model.
On system boot up, the kernel enumerates all of the resources on the system, all of the
memory and all of the IO ports and all the IRQs.
And it prepares capabilities that entitle the bearer to access these resources.
And then it hands all of these off to the first process, the init process, which can
then subject to its own user space policy decisions, choose how to allocate those resources
to various processes in such a way that it can provide a secure system.
So here's a look at our capabilities.
Here's an example here on the left of a fake physical address space.
And on the right shows the kind of state that we'd be storing in this.
So here we have a number of physical pages, one for a capability space, one for a virtual
address space, for a task, a bunch of memory pages, some free memory, and so on.
And in this physical memory, we store the state you see on the right.
So the C space here stores a list of capability slots, very similar to SEL4.
And in those capability slots is a very small amount of state.
They're each, I believe, 64 bytes, so there's not a whole lot to store there.
In this case, a task, which is like a thread or a process, stores a pointer to another
physical memory page where the bulk of its state really lives.
In this case, we have an example of some registers for XDD6.64.
And the access to this state is gated behind the MMU, so only the kernel itself can directly
read from this kind of physical memory.
But then user space, who maybe this process that we're looking at has semantic ownership
over the C space and this V space, they can invoke the kernel to do operations against
those things, but they can't actually directly access the memory.
Instead, the virtual memory can only contain certain kinds of capabilities or certain kinds
of physical memory pages.
So that could be arbitrary general purpose memory, or it could be memory mapped IO, could
end up in their address space.
So while they have semantic ownership over these other capabilities, the actual state
behind them is not accessible to user space.
So in order to work with these capabilities that the user space has semantic ownership
over, it uses, of course, the syscall API.
And Helios has a very, very small syscall API.
It is a microkernel, after all.
We have 14 syscalls, which I have enumerated here.
Twelve of these are for working with capabilities.
And again, if you're familiar with SEL4 here, there's probably no surprises here, except
maybe for syspole, which I'll talk about later.
So here is a little example of how you might invoke a capability on x86 to make use of
the microkernel's API.
Again, you're going to be making a syscall here at the end.
And here we're going to be filling up registers and memory buffers with the information we
want to use.
So this code is going to invoke the vspace map operation, which accepts a page capability,
a virtual address, and a list of mapping flags, like writer or execute.
And its goal is to map a page of physical memory into a slot in a virtual address space.
And in order to invoke this operation, the caller needs to have access to a vspace capability,
which they're going to modify, and a page capability, which they're going to map.
And these capabilities are provided here in two different ways.
The object being invoked is the vspace, and it gets its own register, RDI, which is the
first API register.
The page which is being used, again, similarly to SEL4, is going to be placed into that process's
IPC buffer, which is done here with a fake capability address for the page.
And then we have additional arguments, like the message tag, which contains the operation
name, the number of capabilities, and the number of parameters, and then any additional
arguments to the function.
You run syscall, and the operation happens.
I also want to talk a little bit about the specifics of inter-process communication.
So we have two approaches, and I'll first look at endpoints, which they are kind of
a generalized form of IPC.
And the way you use them is very similar to how you use chronologics.
In fact, the interface is uniform.
But it can send a set of registers or a set of capabilities between tasks.
So one task can transfer a capability to another task.
There is synchronous, so calling send on an endpoint or calling receive on an endpoint
will block until the two tasks run debut.
And if there are many senders or many receivers, then the one who has been blocked the longest
will wake up, so you can have many processes, maybe doing some kind of load balancing operation
against IPC operations.
And also, SEL4 style call and reply is supported.
So if one task does a call rather than a send, then it immediately blocks waiting for the
reply, which is guaranteed to go back to the same thread.
I have here a more detailed example of exactly how that kind of IPC interaction looks on
Helios.
So I have here on the left one task, and on the right two tasks that want to communicate
with each other.
Sometimes the text which is in black is taking place in user space and the text in red is
taking place in kernel space.
So let's say task two is a daemon or a service of some kind which wants to provide a service,
and so it's going to essentially have its main IELP loop call sys receive and then block
until somebody has worked for it to do.
Task one wants to be a consumer of that interface, so it will invoke sys call, and the kernel
will notice that task two is blocked waiting for somebody to call it.
And so the kernel will perform the copy of registers, move any capabilities as necessary,
unblock task two and then block task one while they wait for task two to process the message
and prepare a reply, which is what happens next over here.
The sys call returns from task two.
They process the IPC request according to however they implement their services, and
they call the replies sys call, which copies the reply registers back to task one, very
similar to this fourth step, and then unblocks task one, and then both of them can proceed
onwards with whatever CPU time they're given.
Another interesting feature we have in terms of endpoints, which is one of the things that
distinguishes Helios from SCL4, is support for a pull-like interface.
Similar to Unix's pull-on file descriptors, Helios lets you pull on capabilities.
So this is an example from the serial driver that I implemented for the standard x86 com
ports.
It has two capabilities that mainly cares about.
It has an endpoint capability that it uses to implement its API for consumers of the
serial port.
So if you want to request a read or a write from serial, you'll send a message to this
endpoint.
And then it has an IRQ handler for when the serial port says it's ready to receive or
transmit more data.
And you can prepare a list of capabilities you're interested in and a list of events
you're interested in and block on pull.
And then when one of those is ready to be done, you can call it and it's guaranteed
not to block, very similar to the Unix pull syscall.
And again, I think this is, for me, one of the more notable improvements and derivations
from the SCL4 model.
And I mentioned this earlier, but this interface for doing endpoints and for invoking kernel
objects like virtual address spaces is uniform between user space endpoints and kernel objects.
So it is, for example, possible for a user space process to create a set of endpoints
and then use them to implement an API which is identical to the kernel API.
And if that process is the parent of some other process which thinks it's talking directly
to kernel, it can be sandboxed according to whatever kind of policy you want.
So the kernel is using this API which is uniform with the way that user space communicates
with itself and thus user space can fill the role of the kernel in sometimes.
This can, for example, allow you to very easily run several different Helio systems on the
same computer at once without going to virtualization, which is kind of interesting.
So here I have a little bit more detail on capabilities in particular and the implementation
that some of our capability objects use.
Here we have a capability space on the left which is, again, a little bit distinct from
SCL4.
We don't use guarded page tables.
It's more like a file descriptor table.
It's just zero to however many slots are allocated in that capability space and the process invokes
a capability by its number, not by its address.
Here we have an example of slots where we have a number of things which are preallocated,
but then notably we also have some empty capability slots.
And another derivation from the SCL4 model is that we support capability allocation in
the kernel.
We do this by maintaining inside of empty capabilities a free list.
And so when you invoke an endpoint or you want to allocate a capability, you can set
the capability address to the maximum possible address and the kernel will allocate one for
you using the free list.
You don't have to worry about that state and user space, which is, I think, a very nice
convenience to have and very easy to implement as well.
This is a list of the capabilities that we have implemented.
On the left here is a list of all the capabilities which are available on every architecture.
We have things like memory, device memory, IPC capabilities, threads, and so on.
And then on the right we have a number of additional capabilities which are specific
to each port.
In this case I've listed the capabilities which are used on x86-64.
I'm going to look at just a few of these.
First I want to talk about memory management.
Again, very similar to how we use capability allocation with the C space in the kernel
using a free list.
We also derivate from SEL4 in that general purpose memory uses a free list as well so
you can allocate pages without trying to keep track of a watermark, without trying to reset
your watermark or divide it into smaller objects.
We have a free list of pages so you can just allocate pages which is quite nice.
The only reason this slide is here is to tell you how it differs from SEL4.
We also have address space capabilities, vspaces, which is again similar to SEL4.
In fact, it's so similar that we've cargo-culted this constraint that you can't share page
tables.
I don't really know why SEL4 does that, but once we understand then we will probably either
commit to this or change our mind.
But we have virtual address space capabilities which can be used to manage processes.
And then we have tasks which can be either a thread or a process or something else if
you come up with something creative.
But essentially a task just has a capability space which is optional so that I can do IO
and invoke capabilities as an address space and it receives some CPU time when it is configured
appropriately.
And again, we don't have SMP support yet.
We would like to do that soon.
And for now the scheduler is very simple.
We just have a round robin scheduler, but we would like to expand that in the future.
It should be at least easy enough to add priorities or niceness and we can probably look into
some more sophisticated solutions a little bit later.
Oh, and I missed one on my notes here.
A quick note to add on the topic of address spaces is that I think it's implemented a
little bit more elegantly than SEL4, but I did not write down why in my notes, so you'll
have to take my word for it.
Okay, so that's enough about the design.
I'd like to talk a little bit about the implementation.
The goal is to keep the kernel very straightforward when it comes to booting.
I don't really care for the never ending nightmare which is different ways of booting up computers.
And so the kernel is an ELF executable and the bootloader's job is to do whatever crazy
bullshit is required on whatever platform it's running on to just load a goddamn ELF
executable into memory.
So that's what we've done.
And these bootloaders are also implemented in here, by the way.
We support, again, multi-bit on x86 and EFI on ARH64 and we'll do EFI everywhere soon,
but the bootloader comes up and it's responsible for a few things.
It has to, of course, read the memory map.
It also has to load from the file system any boot modules like similar to an init ramfs
on Linux where it's going to pull out the init binary or the init executable for the
first user space process to run as well as maybe a tarball that init binary wants to
use to read some early drivers from.
It's also going to provide to the kernel that memory map, those boot modules and details
about the loaded kernel like where it was placed in physical memory and so on.
If we're booting with EFI, we're going to pass along some stuff about the EFI runtime
services and if we have a frame buffer at this stage thanks to GOP or multi-boot, we'll
pass that along as well and that will eventually make its way to user space.
Starting boot, we have system initialization.
You saw a little bit of this in the earlier slide which showed the code sample of the
kernel's portable entry point.
That's where the system initialization begins.
Of the three phases of the kernel runtime, we have the boot phase, the system initialization
phase and the runtime phase.
During sys init, the purpose is to do something I hinted at earlier which is to enumerate
all of the system resources, create capabilities for them and then assign them to the init
process which is just again an alpha executable.
We pull that alpha executable in from the boot modules.
The kernel has a simple loader which pulls it into memory.
Enumerate system resources creates enough capabilities to host a task and a v-space
and so on for that initial executable and hand it off.
The basic problem at this stage is not messing up memory.
Everybody who has written a kernel from scratch maybe as opposed to approaching a project
later knows that the hardest thing about memory management is you need memory to manage memory.
There's a lot of stuff in this stage to deal with that.
We also try to enumerate resources on the system at this stage but this is actually
going to change soon.
The kernel at the time of speaking has a PCI driver for x86 or a device tree scanner for
ARM and we try to enumerate the physical address of everything but this is not a good idea
so we're just going to take all physical memory and give it to user space and let it use policy
decisions to figure out who gets what rather than trying to enumerate everything in the
kernel just to keep the kernel smaller.
We definitely don't want to do ACPI so please, please, if anybody here is on the RISC-V board
or something, I'm begging you.
No ACPI.
Device trees.
Then finally we jump to user space and that concludes the sys init.
Speaking of user space, I want to talk a little bit about our future plans.
Here we have the onion of Aries is what is called.
Helios is the kernel at the core of this dream of a larger operating system called the Aries
operating system.
We want to wrap the kernel with various layers to add more functionality.
We have Helios as the kernel.
We've also started working on Mercury which is a framework for writing drivers.
It's basically a user space interface to the kernel API which you can use for drivers plus
some useful functionality like utilities to make it easier to map memory and so on.
Then this Mercury system is applied by Venus which is a collection of drivers, real world
drivers for actual hardware.
At the time of this talk, Helios exists, Mercury mostly exists, and Venus was just started
last week.
Gaia is going to be the next thing that we're going to do on top of this.
Through Mercury and Venus, we'll get this abstract view of the devices on the system
as presented through IPC capabilities.
Then this will be consumed by Gaia and formed into a cohesive user space which is going
to essentially be Unix but everything is not a file, everything is a capability.
You open slash dev slash FB and you get a frame buffer capability rather than an IO
object that you might see on Unix.
Furthermore, the design of Gaia is going to be mostly a combination of inspirations from
Unix and Plan 9.
On top of this, we'll add a POSIX compatibility layer because Gaia is a chance to leave behind
the legacy of POSIX but the legacy of POSIX is strong so we'll have to accommodate it
somehow.
We'll tie all of this up into an operating system called Ares.
Regarding the user space, we're going to build the stuff there.
One other thing I want to show off is something which is part of the Mercury system which
is our DSL for defining IPC interfaces.
We were thinking about not doing a DSL but DSLs are kind of good for this use case so
we made one.
This is an example of a serial device.
It has support for configuring the baud rate and stop bits and parity and so on.
It implements the IO device because it supports read and write as well.
We have a tool called IPC Gen which reads this DSL and generates hair code for it.
This is now mostly working but we're going to start actually writing more real drivers
with it soon so it will be, remains to be seen if we'll like it after we use it for
a while.
Does Helios work?
The answer is self-evidently yes because this slide deck is being presented from this Raspberry
Pi which is running Helios right now.
Thank you.
I have no C code written on this device beyond the point of EDK2.
It has EDK2 to run UA5 but once EDK2 hands over to our EFI bootloader.
From that point forward 100% hair and assembly, just a little bit of assembly.
This port to ARM64 was accomplished over the past eight weeks.
Actually it took exactly 42 days to port the kernel from x86 to AR64.
This system has a simple driver for the Raspberry Pi GPU running in user space to drive the
projector and it has a serial port driver which I'm connected to on my laptop here to
switch between slides because I could not write a USB driver in eight weeks.
The slide deck itself is encoded as quite okay images which are packed into a tarball
and dropped in like an NMRAMFS would be.
There really are very few hacks.
I would say that this is a pretty complete port of the kernel with very little shortcuts
or problems.
The reason why I chose to port the kernel to ARM in 42 days is because I was originally
going to give this talk from a laptop running Helios for x86-64 where I was going to drive
the projector through Intel HD graphics and then I read the Intel HD graphics manuals
and I decided it would be much easier to port the entire kernel to ARM and write an ARM
GPU driver.
So that's what I did.
After about two days of reading the HD graphics manuals I was like I've had enough and then
I pulled down the ARM manual and tried to find a PDF reader which could handle it.
In terms of those hacks and shortcuts, right, there's no SOC specific builds so the same
kernel that I wrote will boot from any ARM device with the standard EFI configuration
and a device tree.
It's not Raspberry Pi specific.
The user space is Raspberry Pi specific.
It's actually Raspberry Pi 4 specific because that's the one I have just because I didn't
feel like doing device tree parsing and user space for the sake of the silly demo.
But all of the silly demo code aside, the stuff that's necessary to make this talk work
is maybe a little bit hacky and Raspberry Pi specific.
The kernel port is a genuine port which is basically feature complete.
I think the only hack that's in place is that I said earlier that the kernel tries to enumerate
the device tree to find physical memory for devices to provide to user space through device
memory capabilities and that was a bad idea.
I was right that it was a bad idea but there is a little bit of a hack in the kernel in
that I just gave all physical memory to the Raspberry Pi, I'm sorry, to user space without
really much critical thought.
That's really the only hack.
The full complete it's done port will correct that oversight by using the EFI memory map
to find memory which is less stupid to just lightly give to user space.
Additionally, I will confess that I don't have support for IRQs in user space so if
I put my finger on the heat sink here, it kind of hurts because it's just busy looping
in user space while I wait for the next slide.
I did get that working before Fostem, I just didn't incorporate it into the loadout for
running the slide deck.
It's a good thing that it's not that hot in here, this would crash.
In total, Helios has been developed in nine months.
The arm port was done in eight weeks and it's sophisticated enough to run this slide deck
which is pretty cool.
What's left to do?
The kernel is mostly done and by done I mean feature complete but not necessarily where
we want it to be.
By feature complete, I mean the kernel API is complete and you can write programs against
it which do everything we want them to do and then other improvements won't maybe not
necessarily affect that API.
Still needs to be polished in a number of places like that device tree issue that I
mentioned is one case.
If you get correct through the code base, you'll find about 100 comments which we need
to address.
One of the more challenging things that we're going to have to do is SMP support but again
the kernel is a total of 15,000 lines of code.
Despite the boogeyman that SMP often appears to be to most kernel hackers, I imagine that
it won't be that difficult for us to do which could be famous last words but we'll see.
I also want to port it to RISC-V.
I have gotten some hair code running on RISC-V at the supervisory level thanks to the efforts
of one of the hair contributors.
We did do some basic OS dev research but we haven't actually ported Helios itself to RISC-V
but we'll do that soon.
I also mentioned that we're going to work on more options for the bootloader so we're
going to try to get EFI going everywhere.
The main blocker for EFI on x86-64 for example is that our programming language which again
is hair which is developed almost alongside this project.
X86 doesn't have support for PIC and so it would kind of be a little bit of a nightmare
to do runtime relocations of the bootloader and assembly or something of that nature so
we're going to do PIC first before we try to do an EFI bootloader for x86 but we do
have PIC for ARM so that's already working.
And then I also want to improve the docs.
I spent the past few weeks in between hacking on the ARM kernel, improving the documentation
on the website Aries-OS.org which there will be a link to in a later slide which is probably
now about 60% complete so if you're curious about the project and maybe you want to try
your hand at a little driver in user space feel free to check that out and wherever you
find a page which is a stub and you need to know what it should say you can come to IRC
and ask about it and we'll fill it in.
After the kernel is polished actually alongside the kernel polish is going to user space where
I explained a lot of the things that we were looking at.
Mercury again mostly exists and Venus is just getting started.
Prior to the introduction of Venus we did have a number of drivers that were built for
the purpose of testing the kernel and testing Mercury and so on.
We obviously have a serial driver for x86, we have a PL011 serial driver for ARM.
We've also done things like E1000 networking.
We did send pings with that.
We did the RDO block devices and a couple of other simple drivers just as we were working
to prove the design of the support code for drivers.
But the support code is mostly done so now we're going to start writing drivers for real.
I need to provide some acknowledgements here to people who helped to make Helios work.
Certainly I mentioned earlier that there's a RISC-V kernel by Alexi Uren.
Ember Savati also did some work on x86 for early kernel attempts.
This was really useful stuff.
None of this code was very little of this code that came from these efforts of A.D.A.
to Helios and these projects never really developed into full systems.
I don't think either of them made it to user space but they were still very useful for
proving out some ideas about how to actually do basic kernel hacking in Heir.
How do we boot up the system?
How do we work from ring zero?
How do we configure the MMU?
How do we do yada yada yada, deal with interrupts and so on?
How do we link it properly?
All questions that had not been answered previously within the context of the Heir programming
language and so this work was definitely instrumental in setting the field upon which Helios could
be built.
Big thanks to these guys.
Also thanks to the Heir community.
There's almost 80 people now.
Obviously I think it's more than 80 now.
There's around 80 people who have been working on the programming language itself.
Again, we've been working on it for about three years now and the project Helios of
course would not be possible without the programming language it's written in.
So a huge shout out to the Heir community for everything they've done.
Very proud of that community.
I also want to thank the OS Dev community on the BarraChat.
Hands up if any of you are in this channel.
So OS Dev on the BarraChat is the single best place to learn about kernel hacking on the
entire internet.
Those guys are so smart and helpful and they're very knowledgeable.
They know everything about kernel hacking and drivers and anything you want to know.
If you want to mess with kernels, go talk to these people.
And also of course to SCL4.
As I'm sure you noticed, we took a whole bunch of ideas from SCL4.
I think SCL4 has got a really cool kernel design and I was really happy to learn about
it and apply a lot of its ideas to my own kernel.
So kernel hacking is fun, Heir is fun, let's all have fun.
That's it.
Thank you so much, Drew.
Any questions from the audience?
Martin.
I'm going to give you guys my talk.
Pass it on to Martin first and then we're going to give you.
Hi.
Thanks for the talk.
Good work.
I was unable to map the standard SCL4 capability derivation tree like starting with untied memory
and then everything that to your slides.
So do you have it as well?
Or?
Yeah, we do.
We just track capability derivations in a manner very similar to SCL4 and it really
would have been smart for me to put in a slide about that.
So thanks for the clarification.
And second, well, I have a hard time formulating it
as a question, so maybe just take it as an unsolicited advice.
Many of the design decisions of SCL4
were strictly motivated by the formal verification target.
So maybe when you have spoken, for example,
about not sharing the pages, et cetera,
just give it a thought that the reason for that
might be that they did not want to make their life harder
regarding the formal verification.
And that might be the only reason.
Yeah, I think I've noticed that for a few other implementation
details from SCL4 when we were studying a kernel to learn
what we could do for ours.
And with examples like sharing page tables,
I had bigger fish to fry, so I left a comment which says,
SCL4 doesn't support copying these,
and I would rather not run into a Heisenberg
because we did it without thinking about it.
And then we can really address it
at some point in the future.
Thanks.
Hi.
Yeah, thanks for the talk.
Very interesting, quite impressive.
Yesterday we were talking about hair,
and thinking about it in retrospect,
it seemed to me, my personal opinion,
that the great mechanisms of language design
are mostly discovered.
Like we have garbage collection and tech unions
and that assuming you agree with that statement
now that you've written that operating system kernel,
would you also say that the great mechanisms how
to write a kernel are established and well-known?
Things like paging, what's the still areas
to experiment in new ways to do memory management?
Things like that.
Interesting question.
I would say that there is a lot of concepts and ideas which
can be applied in the field of OS development, which
are understood, and you can see examples of kernels
and systems which apply these ideas,
and various different designs that you can learn from
and study and maybe apply to your own kernel
if they're the right choice.
And you can make a complete kernel,
which is interesting, basically only using proven ideas, which
is, for the most part, describes Helios.
But at the same time, there's certainly all kinds of research
which is being done into more novel approaches.
There's been talks in this room throughout the day,
which address some of those novel approaches and ideas.
So I would say that there is certainly
room to build a kernel out of understood ideas
and still make it interesting.
But there's also definitely an active frontier of research
ongoing as well.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
Any other questions?
Yeah, please.
Let me.
Oh.
Yeah.
Thank you for the talk.
You mentioned that you need to have
position-independent code, right?
Yeah.
But I don't understand if you use every driver,
and it's just like a user space process.
So can't you just remap that in MMM so that all the processes,
like a normal Linux process, just have the same memory map?
Yeah, actually, the kernel and user space processes
both use a fixed memory map.
The thing where we would maybe want
to look at position-independent code
is specifically for the case of loading our EFI bootloader
as a P32 plus executable.
After that stage, it's all fixed memory addresses.
OK.
Yeah, then I understand.
Cool.
Hello.
Thank you for the talk.
Can I ask a non-technical element?
You've GPL freed it.
How are you making decisions around the kernel?
Is it an everland dictator?
Are you making decisions?
Or are you having massive conversations about things?
How's that looking at the moment?
The vast majority of the work is just
done by me personally at the moment.
The project is still pretty early on,
but we do have a number of other contributors.
I would say that the group of people
who ought to be consulted on changes
is probably in the ballpark of five people in total.
So we just have a fairly informal community
based on trust.
And we try to be transparent, like I am transparent,
in all of my free software.
So we have a public IRC channel where
we have these discussions.
Anybody can jump in at any time.
And there's a patch review process
which just goes through me at the moment.
But in the hair community, for example,
which is a lot bigger at this stage,
we have something more of a governance model
where there's less of a BDFL and more
of multiple maintainers who all can do code reviews
and improve patches and things like this.
And as the Helios project grows, I imagine
it will adopt a model similar to hair.
And perhaps as hair grows, we'll have
to improve upon the model even further.
But we'll see.
Thank you.
Nice share, by the way.
David.
You mentioned that you don't want to deal with ACPI,
but at the same time, you want to make you have i standard.
So what's the plan there?
Is there any way to solve a thought ACPI in your system?
Because I imagine that it will become mandatory, right?
Yeah.
I'm going to wail and gnash my teeth
and hope it doesn't happen in practice.
Because at the moment, you know something like EDK2.
To be clear, by the way, I don't give a fuck
about non-free firmwares.
So I'm thinking about EDK2 and things like that, or U-Boot
and so on, where there's already an EFI standard UUID
for passing a device tree along.
And they can be configured to do that instead of ACPI, which
is what I'm doing on this Raspberry Pi, for example,
and what I hope to continue to do on RISC-V and so on.
Our proof of concept on RISC-V took the same approach.
But there's very little in the kernel
that actually needs to be concerned with ACPI
versus device trees.
And again, it is a microkernel.
So in the long term, we might just pass along the rather
than the previous one.
At least a little bit in x86, because there's
no device trees.
But fingers in my ears not thinking about the fact
that ACPI is upon us, but we'll probably
have to deal with it at some point.
Thank you for the presentation.
Which software is running the presentation itself,
and how is it combined?
This is just a custom piece of software I wrote myself.
It's a single binary, which is loaded by the bootloader
as the init process.
And then the kernel loads it into an address space
and boots it up as PID1.
And there's additionally a tarball
as a second boot module, which is again loaded into memory
and then passed along to PID1, which
is a tarball full of slides.
And then there's just one statically linked executable,
which contains a serial driver and a GPU driver and the code
to glue everything together.
The code, by the way, is available on source
side if you're curious.
As you mentioned, Elios is heavily inspired by STL4.
So is there any plan on formal verification for Elios?
Or is that just not something you're interested in?
No, I'm not particularly interested in that.
In the back, there's someone.
Thanks for the presentation.
I have a question.
Is it on the roadmap that something like Western
or a other GUI server or other service like that
could potentially be ported to Helios?
I'm actually also the original author of W.R. Roots
and have a lot of experience in Wayland.
And so there is a 100% chance that Wayland will be running
on Helios at some point.
OK.
Any other questions?
So you said for Gaia, you are inspired by Plan 9 and Unix.
What's the best?
What do you plan for Gaia?
What's the best of those both worlds?
It's a little bit hard to say.
At this point, there is less plans and more vision
in that respect because we have at least probably a year of work
before it can really start serious work on Gaia.
But I will say that there is a lot of stuff
I admire about Plan 9.
There's per-process namespaces is one great idea.
I'm also going to go further with the idea of there
not being any kind of global file system at all.
We're also going to take a look at things
like using text-based protocols where possible.
And we're going to use different from Plan 9.
We're going to use this IPC generation thing for places
where text protocols maybe don't make sense.
I also have a lot of admiration for things like MBD on Plan 9.
And so I would like to organize networks perhaps
in a similar fashion.
And also, I would say that the bigger vision for the whole ARIES
system is you can almost say it's correcting a mistake
that Plan 9 made, which is that Plan 9 was correct,
that distributed computing is the future.
But it was incorrect that they would
be distributed across a mainframe and a bunch of thin
clients in an office building, which is how Plan 9 was designed.
In fact, the group of devices which
should be running a uniform operating system
is all of your personal devices, my laptop, my workstation
at home, my phones.
They should all present as a single system.
And so it's very vague and lofty and long-term vision.
But I would like to try and achieve that with the design
of Gaia and ARIES.
Thank you.
Any other questions?
OK, then thank you so much, Drew.
Thanks a lot.
Thank you.
10 minutes break until the next talk.