Okay, and so our final in-person talk, the last talk will be recorded playback.
And now we have Ignaz Foster talking about OpenSUSE MicroS and the technical details.
So thanks for coming.
Thanks for the introduction and thanks for joining.
A selfless talk will be about OpenSUSE MicroS.
We have several topics to cover and not much time, so I'll just go over them quickly.
We can't go into too much detail of here, but yeah, we'll see.
Just one slide back.
My name is Ignaz.
I'm working for SUSE and yeah, I'm working as a research engineer.
So what are today's topics?
First of all, I'll give you a short introduction on OpenSUSE MicroS itself.
How is it built up and on which foundations is it built up?
Then we'll have a short look about the update and rollback mechanisms we are using there
and something we haven't talked a lot about today on configuration file management on
our approach to handle these in image-based systems.
We probably won't make it to the full disk encryption and trust it's boot part, but I
can just refer to Len's talk from earlier today.
So when we are talking about OpenSUSE MicroS, we are basically talking about some product
of the whole OpenSUSE universe.
The most known products there are Tumbleweed and Leap.
Tumbleweed is our rolling release distribution and Leap is our stable distribution, stable
not in a sense of Tumbleweed crashes all the time, but stable in a sense of the API doesn't
change all the time.
Leap itself is based on SUSE Linux Enterprise.
SUSE Linux Enterprise in turn is based on a Tumbleweed snapshot which will then merge
into a stable product.
So when we are talking about MicroS, we still have the same products basically.
We have OpenSUSE MicroS which is based on Tumbleweed and we have OpenSUSE Leap Micro
which is based on Leap.
So basically we also have the same ingredients in there.
We still have the RPM packages as a base.
To be exact, exactly the same packages we have in the Tumbleweed or Leap distributions
and we are building up on these.
You may know OpenSUSE as one of the large users of Bt
just the default, but when we are talking about MicroS, then BtFS will be mandatory.
You have to use it because we rely on these features really deeply.
First of all, that's snapshots.
These are the snapshots.
When we are creating an update, we will need those snapshots to have the forward and rollback
handling.
BtFS has a huge advantage.
We have heard that from a previous talk already.
BtFS has copy and write functionality.
When we do an update, it will be the smallest update possible basically.
We don't have AP partitioning where we have to have two partitions the same size but can
have a minimal snapshot for that.
When we are talking about MicroS, if it's based on Tumbleweed and Leap, what's the actual
difference compared to them?
First of all, it's a read-only root file system which is, I guess, common for all the image-based
systems we heard of today.
It contains a minimal package selection.
Minimal doesn't necessarily mean that it's the smallest distribution possible but a minimal
package set for what it's trying to do.
What it's trying to do is being a single-purpose system.
It evolved from a project called OpenSouza Cubic which was a Kubernetes distribution
until we discovered that you can use it for so much more.
Basically, what it's nowadays is a single-purpose system including running containers but you
can use it for any system or any use case you actually want to have.
You also have a MicroS desktop so your single use case would be running a desktop there
with flatpacks as packages for using your applications.
That single-purpose system approach also means you can install packages from the Tumbleweed
and Leap distributions but it's not designed to be used that way.
You should use containers for your actual load or you can say you install one dedicated
package for example if you want to run it as a mail server or whatever.
If you have a look at our commercial site where we have the SousaLix Enterprise Microproduct,
we even have a very limited package set.
You can't even install all the packages you can from Tumbleweed and Leap to make that
clear that it's really meant to be used in a quite a restricted way for example for workloads,
for example for cluster nodes or for embedded systems.
Especially for embedded systems, we also have another very important point namely it's
a self-maintaining system.
You basically install it and then you in theory can't forget about it because it will just
update and maintain itself.
We'll have a short look at that later how that works.
When we are talking about updates, I said it's a read-only system so you still have
to be able to update the system somehow if it's not image-based.
For that we are basically using the B2FS snapshot functionality which the B2FS snapshots are
snapshots of the root file system.
That's the important part.
If you have a workload, for example containers, it's running in VAR.
Of course you also have etc for your configuration files but the root file system basically what's
below user is that part that is actually snapshotted and read-only.
When we have an update, we will just create a new snapshot, the blue square on the second
point and perform the update in there.
The blue snapshot is a B2FS snapshot so it has minimal overhead.
It will just be created in microseconds.
There's no performance penalty for doing that.
Then the update will be performed in that snapshot, for example by just calling the
OpenSouce world superdub for doing a system update.
If anything should go wrong in that step, then that snapshot can just be discarded again
and we are back at square one.
We just have the currently running system and the new snapshot, the active system won't
even have seen the new snapshot.
If the update was successful, then that snapshot will be marked as the new default snapshot.
That means if we reboot the system just like AB partitioning, that snapshot will be used
as the new boot file system.
We have a second step, but that will be later, just a second.
Let me talk about it immediately.
We have a second step at boot called Health Tracker.
If Health Tracker should detect that something is not working as expected, for example a
service you expect it doesn't come up, then an automatic rollback will be performed again.
We will be back at square one again.
It behaves as nothing would have been changed and we can wait for the bug fix for whatever
broke the actual update.
All the metric happens in an application called transactional update and a new library called
TUQL.
Transaction update was originally a shell script.
It called all the open SUSE specific stuff, for example calling super for the package
management or calling MKInnID for rebuilding the InnID.
Something which needed right access, so had to modify the root file system, was just wrapped
with that wrapper script.
Out of that, a new library emerged called libTUQL.
That one is supposed to be platform agnostic.
It includes C, C++ and D
was bindings.
The only implementation currently is for Btriv S and Snapper, but if you want to, you could
also just write another backend.
It's prepared for that for more general snapshot management.
We have, for example, a microDNF plugin to be exact.
You could just use that one library for that.
I just said if you want to activate that snapshot, you would usually reboot and have that snapshot
activated.
That's the atomic part, which is important for making sure that you don't touch the currently
running system, but make sure the update is activated in one atomic step.
With the next transaction update version, there will be also a new option called transaction
update apply.
What that one does is it will just mount basically user into the currently running
system.
That was possible if you heard the talk from Ludwig two talks ago.
That was possible because of the user merge, because practically everything the system requires
is below user.
If it isn't, it should be changed in the future, but for microS, that one's working very reliably
already.
If you just update or if you just installed a new package in the new snapshot, that one
will be totally painless because you just have the new package available immediately.
If you change system services, and I don't know what, then maybe you should still think
about rebooting afterwards because it's basically the same when you're running an update in
a running system, basically an update or superdub in a running system.
I talked about rollback already.
If you reboot the system and something doesn't work as expected, then it will perform an
automatic rollback.
With tracker, you can see the URL at the bottom itself provides an interface basically for
custom plugins.
You have to know yourself which services are running on your system, and you have to know
yourself how to check them.
As said, it's a single purpose system, so I hope you know what you're doing.
You can just extend it with custom plugins where you define what defines a correctly
running system.
Let's have a look at the time.
Excellent.
Let's have a look at the configuration file management.
When we are talking about read-only root file systems, we still have to have some directories
of files writable.
We've just seen that with the Ubuntu core talk in contrast to Ubuntu core for OpenSUSE
micros.
All of WA and all of etc are writable.
WA is a separate subvolume.
For etc, we are using a mechanism called overlays.
It's basically just the kernel overlay of S file system.
That one may need a bit more explanation.
If we have a look at the hcfs tab entry for etc, it looks overly long and overly complicated.
But in the end, it's just the two lines which are colored.
We have the upper-der when we are just performing an update.
That's the overlay of the next snapshot.
The lower-der is the directory of the currently running system.
To avoid having stacks over stacks over stacks, you'll just sync the state of the previous
system as the base of the new snapshot.
That's the three layers we are talking about.
If we have a look at that in detail, what's happening on configuration file changes?
If we have the case of file one, that's a really old file.
That file has always existed, was never changed.
That's no problem at all.
Basically we are just having a look from the top to the bottom.
Nothing is in upper-der.
Nothing is in lower-der one.
Every version of lower-der two will be used.
File two is interesting because that one has an old state.
During the update, that file was actually changed.
It seems either the package refreshed it or some postscript modified it or whatever happened
to it.
In any case, we have a new version of that file.
As soon as you reboot into the new snapshot, you'll see that version of the file, older
snapshots will see that version of the file.
File four, file five and file six are similar.
Those are quite easy.
That one is new in the next snapshot.
That one was new in the previous snapshot and those were modified into the snapshot
before.
The interesting thing is file three because that one exists both in the current snapshot
and in the new snapshot and that may indicate a conflict.
Because as soon as you perform an update or create the new snapshot, the state of the
file will be frozen basically and that one will be used as the base for the new snapshot.
If you change the file before rebooting the system, then the new layer won't see that
new file anymore.
Whether you're operating on an old version of the file or you'd have to check there will
be a warning when you root the system that there may be a conflict if the file in lower
tier one is the file in upper tier.
That's our approach to handling current systems, current packages as we have them from vendors,
from our own distribution and having a pragmatic approach to handling those configuration files.
But in the end, we don't want to have that at all.
In the end, we want to have the files which are packaged to be completely in user.
We don't want to have them in etc at all.
Only changes that were explicitly done by the admin are supposed to be in etc.
That's where we are really approaching our final goal.
For open source micros, we almost achieved that goal.
There are still some problematic files, for example, etcfs type of course, such a singular
file which you can't extend if you have an application and also want to make it possible
to split those files.
We have developed a library called libecon.
You can just embed it and we'll do all the things automatically just in case you're interested
in that.
We have made several pull requests and patches for projects which are used by open source
micros to fix those use cases for us.
In the end, I think we took a quite pragmatic approach using existing technologies to just
be able to use your existing infrastructure, your existing packages, and preserve the compatibility
with all the legacy software which may exist out there.
We are basically doing the opposite of most other distributions by extending the, let's
say, existing distributions to the new use cases.
As I feared, I'll just refer to Len's talk from earlier today.
We do support full disk encryption.
We do support trusty boot and we also have measurement support.
Let's better get to the questions part just in case you have some.
Thank you very much for your talk.
I was pestering your colleagues out here moments before this talk.
Do you have any plans to migrate the old qubit docs to micros?
Because for someone who's new to transactional systems, it isn't immediately obvious how
the classical administration style translates to transactional one.
Yes, we have a new documentation.
The problem is micros doesn't include documentation.
If you're in an embedded use case or using it for containers, the main pages are just
overhead which is not needed.
We have a separate documentation server which will just provide all the documentation, but
I forgot which one it is.
You have to ask me later.
I'll search it for you.
I hope these search engines have picked it up meanwhile.
It's a few weeks old.
There is a question in the chat.
How is micros related to ALP?
Basically, the current state of open-sUSE-ELP which is supposed to be the next generation
of our SUSE-LIMS enterprise, whatever emerged out of that.
Basically, open-sUSE-ALP is based on open-sUSE-micros in its current state.
There will be more use cases than just the container use cases, but that's the base which
it was initially put onto.
A lot of things you can do with open-sUSE-micros.
You can also do with open-sUSE-ALP.
We even share parts of the documentation currently, but open-sUSE-ALP is more than just open-sUSE-micros.
It's just the same foundation currently.
It's just the same foundation.
Going once, going twice.
Thank you very much.
That was wonderful.