Hi, I'm Ludwig from SUSE. I'm a research engineer there working in the so-called future technologies
team and today I'm presenting some crazy idea. Not because we're going to build a product
with that, but just because we can. So first let's take a look what's the difference between
package-based and image-based. I mean I'm from the package-based world so I don't have too
many insights into actual image-based systems like from embedded world so that's just my
view. Anyway packages are known by all of you I guess from your desktop Linux installation.
So you have individual components pre-built, the vendor ships your packages and the client
side decides which one to install so there's some kind of dependency resolver that takes
the components puts them on your local system. Usually you don't need to reboot for that.
This has advantages and disadvantages so the advantages if you need a new VIM version
you just get it and it works right away. The disadvantages if it breaks it's broken. On
image-based systems on the other hand you get a full Linux system pre-built by the operating
system vendor. That means it's a ready-made file system that it typically download and
de-detors some partition for example or it's a tarball that gets extracted somewhere. Installing
that one or activating the install requires a reboot so that's an advantage because it
wouldn't break into intermediate states but it just either works or doesn't. The disadvantage
is that it's typically not extendable at least not the original image so you would have to
have some other mechanism like system de-sysix nowadays that plays some tricks to get extra
layers on top. So let's first take a look at the file-stem
layout of a typical image-based system or one I think our system de-envisioned so we
have the operating system in slash user for Linux systems that have the user merge. Then
the etc partition at etc volume is on slash which is writeable. The boot partition nowadays
should be the ESP no matter where it's mounted actually and your data is in var on a separate
volume again. So how do you do updates? Usually you have separate partitions for user so the
standard case is a B so two versions and then you de-de-de your operating system into one
while the other one runs and on reboot you just switch. That's a quite easy technology
because it's just a regular partition table. It's actually read-only if the file-stem you
use is read-only one. You could use R-Sync or C-A-Sync to download deltas and getting
it from the server and the signing is also pretty easy because it's one image so you
can put some GPG signature on it and that's it and you can even verify it afterwards because
the image is unmodified on your partition. Disadvantages there's no deduplication so you
always consume twice the space basically or however big your user partition is. Even if
your updates are small you still need all that space. The amount is limited so usually
if you have only two partitions you have two versions of the operating system and the space
is pre-allocated. Again that could be an advantage because there's no surprises the space is
just there and if it's there you can put the image period. The disadvantages the image
can't grow and the updates are always of a fixed size basically. So I can be optimized
that we could actually use PutterFest to store our operating system that's how OpenSUSE
MicroS works so more details on that later in Ignat's talk. Anyway we use the sub-volume
for the operating system that means you get the copy and write semantics automatically
so deduplication means your updated system does not automatically need twice the space
but only the changed amount. You can still use Rsync or CAsync to only apply deltas.
The amount of versions you can store is basically infinite only depends on how big your updates
are so if you only have updates on text files it could be a lot of versions. Disadvantages
it's not really read-only it's just a PutterFest flag and that can be changed of course. Also
put a question mark on verification so previously with image we could just run GPG for example
and you can verify whether the image was modified or not. Here we have to take a look how to
solve that later. But how do distributions actually build those images? At least an operating
system vendor like OpenSUSE would use packages to build the image just on server side we
learned that we can even use this technology for building IDRDS and the way the image would
be shipped would be just install packages somewhere on a server system and then throw
away everything that is not in user. That means all the scriptlets that run in packages
just modifying something that's not relevant like in EDC in VAR it doesn't make any sense
to have a scriptlet doing something there. So when for example a package needs to add
a user it can't just call user add it needs to use system desys users. Same if you don't
enable a service it can't just call system control enable you need to ship presets. And
that way packages also can't just put the kernel in slash boot anymore because that's
not in user. That means there needs to be some extra tool that somehow makes your system
bootable when there's a new kernel for example. So back to verification. Actually packages
at least RPM packages have signed headers and the header files and headers have checksums
for each file. So in the end an image is a list of RPMs with signed headers and by verifying
each header you can also verify each file. So in the end you have a tree that could be
verified you can check that there is no file added no file removed and no file modified
just by looking at the RPM headers. These advantages in images that you ship you typically
remove the RPM database because it's this ugly binary blob. Even if it's a SQLite database
it's still an ugly binary blob with more binary blobs in there. So that's why people
really hate having the RPM database there. This is something that nobody wants to see
in an image. So how can we fix that? We could actually store the RPM headers as files. So
we just dump the header part of the package into a directory. That means the directory
is the RPM database that looks much less ugly. Different tool file directory listings to
actually see which packages could update it. That is quite useful if you already use micros
for example and do some snapper compare then it tells you this RPM database and this RPM
database changed but you don't know what. If the database is a listing of files it's
naturally visible what changed. And still we have the RPM header so users fully verifiable
because they are signed. So the question now is what do we actually need an image for?
So you don't need to take those RPMs put them into some file system and then download
the whole file system or this image or tarball. You could actually define an image as a text
file that lists RPMs. And then you download those RPMs which are bits of your image and
just put them into this file system or partition that is user. This advantage of this method
again would be that nowadays RPMs you would lose the ability to do easy deltas because
the payload is actually a CPO that is compressed with some compression. So if you don't want
to use delta RPMs or other fancy things you need to find a solution for the payload of
RPMs. So the payload doesn't actually have to be a CPO that is compressed. It could be
actually completely uncompressed so you just concatenate all the file contents at the end
of the RPM header and because the RPM header contains all the file sizes you know which
file is where. Now if we do another trick and align those file datas to page size you
actually get ref linkable packages. That means you could download this uncompressed RPM for
example by means of CACYNC which would compress it actually on server side. Then you have
the RPM on disk and then instead of copying the payload to some other location you just
use ref link as a file system feature that reuses the blocks. So you have this one big
chunk of data as the RPM and to create your actual files you just link the data into there.
That means user bin bash is not actually a copy it's just sharing the same data that
is in this RPM that is stored there which conveniently is at the same time your RPM
database. So it's not just the headers that are in this directory it is the full package.
So in the end in this example I put userlib sysimage packages. Userlib sysimage packages
would be your image. That means user is just a view and if you would map this into butterfly
like in this example that means you have several versions of the sysimage directory as snapshot
and then you could create other butterfly ffs volumes that just link into those RPM headers.
Or you could even omit this user completely a colleague of mine Fabian even wrote a fuse
plugin that just creates a file system from looking at RPMs in the directory. Quite crazy.
So to summarize we could build a image like system by leveraging butterfly ffs so instead
of using ap partitions we just use snapshots. The behavior would be exactly the same because
you prepare this new snapshot put all your data in there and then you have to reboot
to activate it. But since it's still packages you retain the flexibility to actually change
it on client size. You could ship the image as a list of RPMs and text files but you
could also add RPMs locally in this directory and you have them installed. So best of both
worlds. And this is not just completely crazy in my head. I actually built a prototype that
kind of works so it uses Busybox because it was easy to modify the RPM implementation
in there to work with those reflinkable packages. It uses Rsync for updates and it uses system
D's kernel install to make this system actually bootable. So you can try it out. There's also
a pull request open for RPM I think to have this reflinkable stuff and send a patch to
Busybox but I don't expect it to be accepted. It's just a proof of concept. Of course to
make this work in practice there's a lot of to-do so in existing distros like OpenSUSE
we have to fix all the packages to no longer use scriptlets. We need to talk about the
butterfly sub volumes. The naming should be standardized. There was actually a discussion
like two years ago already on the list. RPM reflink payload would be nice to have upstream.
There's other stakeholders that also would like to have that. I'm already working on
system D's kernel install to make it usable for this use case. In case of micro-as like
systems we want to have rollback also slash and just the operating system. For installing
Deltas I would like to use CAsync. It should be revisited. And last but not least all of
course that should be native in RPM or SIP and in my opinion not just some extra tool.
And that's it already. Any questions for this crazy stuff?
Okay me first. How did you handle the timestamp is C? Because if you're using BTRFS and doing
an RPM minus I you get the A time, M time and C time in the I node. And an image based
system is supposed to hash end to end the same. And if it has different timestamps it
doesn't hash end to end.
Yeah well you can't modify the timestamps you can't modify. You can only look at the
ones that are under your control there.
But then doesn't that mean that effectively we can't use this to reconstruct image based
systems?
Well it's not a bit to bit identical. What is on disk is not bit to bit identical of
course only the actual RPM payload. But you know that the payload that is linked is
actually the same. So I don't think, I mean maybe there's a use case why the timestamps
need to be exact. But in my view it's not important because the user bin bash is user
bin bash no matter what the timestamp is.
Well the use case is just for image based systems the end to end hash tells you that
you've done the right thing. And it's simple to compute. With your system you basically
have to do a tree hash down all the packages to prove that this is what you're supposed
to have installed. Semantically they are equivalent it's just the latter is more difficult to
do than the former which is why people like image based.
I mean you only need to hash the directory with all the RPMs in them right. So if the
RPMs you have a text number of all the RPMs and then you can verify the RPMs.
Yeah I'm not disputing you clearly I'm just saying it's more complicated.
Yeah of course there's always a trade off of course yeah. And depends on how you construct
this user view. I mean if it's really a butterface or really file system tree then you have to
walk it. But if it's only a view like with a views thingy then it doesn't actually exist
on this. It's just you know looking at the RPMs. So it cannot be modified you need to
walk don't need to walk the tree you just hash the RPMs.
Okay.
So how would you integrate that into what we have heard in the previous talks. So during
boot I specify something similar to my DmVerity root hash so that I know that I'm actually
booting from an unmodified root of S.
That's a good question that problem is not solved yet yeah. So far the challenges are
already at the point how do you actually specify which version of the user tree do you want
to boot. Right now all the models assume that if you ship a new image like a new user version
it also comes with a new kernel and a new init ID. So this init ID knows what disk to
boot but in the butterface use case there is a kernel that can have a number of init
IDs and those init IDs match with a number of snapshots that they can actually boot.
So then I'm already struggling with this part so the verification comes later.
So DmVerity gives you authenticity of the blocks at runtime so the device cannot switch
them underneath and I guess that if you verify the kernel headers the RPM headers when loading
the image this wouldn't give you the same runtime properties.
I haven't played with those technologies yet to be honest. So another interesting thing
would be this FA policy daemon. Only with a bit about it it uses the audit subsystem
to actually log access to modified files by comparing them with the information the RPM
header. So would be another area to just explore how to integrate some verification technologies
into this model.
Any more questions? If not then I guess we'll wrap up this talk. Thank you very much.