Good morning and welcome to the very first image-based Linux and secure measured boot
devroom.
A bit of a mouthful, we'll try a shorter one next year.
So let me start by introducing myself.
My name is Luca.
By day I am a software engineer in the Linux systems group at Microsoft where I work on
the Azure infrastructure and by night I contribute to various open source projects.
I am a system demontainer, Debian developer, a bunch of other stuff that I forget and neglect.
So I will give you the introduction to the devroom and an overview of all the topics
that we will touch on to hopefully give you a holistic view of what image-based Linux
is.
So let me start by saying thank you to all the organizers and co-organizers for this
devroom, especially to Thilo, who unfortunately could not make it to Brussels this year, but
he did most of the work on the first website and CFP and so on.
So thank you Thilo if you are watching.
Now some boring logistics.
This devroom has a five minutes break between talks to allow to switch some speed over.
We have a 10 minutes break at 10 past 12 and we finish at 20 past two.
Next devroom starts at half past two.
Now in case this is your first false demo, or it's not, but you never noticed, everything
is live streamed and recorded.
If you are not comfortable with having your back of your head recorded or live streamed,
best against the justice to sit at the sides.
If you ask questions, remember again there will be live streamed and recorded.
If you're not comfortable with that, there's a matrix chat.
You can ask a question there and our devroom organizers will repeat it for you.
We do want people to ask questions.
Please do so.
Please do not just start shouting at the presenter.
Raise your hand and then we will come to you with a microphone.
If you're a speaker and people shout a question at you, please first repeat it and then answer
it.
And I think that's it.
Now let's get into the interesting stuff.
What is image based Linux?
Now if you're an embedded person or addition to that word, you're probably thinking, what
are these guys talking about?
We've been doing image based Linux for 30 years.
It's nothing new.
And you wouldn't be completely wrong.
Now the difference is that our focus within this ecosystem is on the security aspect.
Because let's face it, Linux runs everywhere.
Most of our infrastructure and economy runs through Linux these days, all the public clouds
run on Linux, even Azure.
So we want to get our security story straight.
What does that mean?
What are some of the basic concepts?
First of all, we want to have first class support for at least one, if not both, of
UFIS secure boot and TPM based measurements.
Hopefully both.
Because the goal here is to extend the chain of trust at boot.
Now if you are using a generic Linux distribution like Debian or Ubuntu or Fedora, the story
in your firmware to kernel chain of trust is pretty well buttoned up by now.
Because a lot of people did a lot of work in the past 12 years to get their story straight
and they keep doing that to maintain it.
So in your generic distribution you will have your firmware which verifies the first stage
boot loader which will be shim, signed by Microsoft.
And then shim, the first stage boot loader verifies the second stage boot loader and
verifies the kernel.
And the kernel verifies the kernel modules.
So if you are within rank zero, the chain of trust is pretty solid.
There is this small little thing to the side called user space where things are not so
pitchy and that is what we are trying to improve.
So just a quick summary, we will go into more details but we want either of these to be
signed.
Either of these are completely unprotected right now in most distributions.
They are built locally.
If an attacker or malware can get right access to that, they can embed their malware in there
and you will be known the wiser.
That's a bit of a problem.
Same thing for UFIS.
It probably is encrypted these days but that helps for offline attacks, not online ones.
We want to do better there.
One of the key requirements to use any of the specification infrastructure tools that
we see is you need to have an hermetic ZS user.
What does that mean?
It means your vendor tree must be within ZS user.
If you are in one of those handful of distributions, they still have the top level bins bin or
libdirectories that are not sim links, it's time to move on.
Even there will be a manage finally kicking and screaming but manage to get into merged
users.
That is our core requirement.
The people who work on this stuff kind of got together from various distributions, companies,
projects.
We created this UAPI group.
We have a nice website.
We have a GitHub organization with a discussion tab.
There's already quite some interesting discussions going on there.
I encourage people who are interested in these topics to check that out.
What does actual image-based Linux mean?
This is my personal understanding and analysis.
My point of view, I see at least three different flavors of this.
There's the pure image-based one, it's the one that I do in Azure, where you build images,
your whole images, and you ship to the machines, you have the N-verity to cover the root file
system.
The next talk we go into details.
Then we have AB schemes for upgrade and upgrades.
Nothing groundbreaking.
Android has been doing this for 15 years or whatever.
The second camp is the OSTree one, pure or RPM-based, like Fedora core for example.
What they do there is they build either packages or OSTree snapshots and then they apply them
locally.
If you reboot into the next snapshot or a different one, it's like a GIT tree for your
file system.
The root file system there is either ephemeral or immutable runtime.
I cannot remember.
You cannot change it.
You reboot into the new one.
BattleFS camp, very similar.
Instead of OSTree, you use the BattleFS snapshotting capabilities.
You install a package, it doesn't get installed in your rootFS.
You install it into the new snapshot and then reboot into it.
The core thing I want you to take away from this is that there are different flavors,
ways of stringing things up together.
That's okay.
That's what Linux is great at, this diversity.
The core important concept is that we share goals, we share tools, infrastructure, and
specifications, because we want the same thing in different ways.
Let's look at some of these specifications.
Fair warning.
There's a lot of acronyms coming your way now.
I apologize in advance.
Now, UKI, you will hear a lot about this today.
Unified kernel image.
What is this?
A UKI is a single p binary, a UFI executable.
Why is it good?
Because you mix a UFI stub, a kernel, and an ETRD.
Then you can sign it for secure boot.
Remember I talked about the ETRD being unsecured before?
This is how we fix it.
The ETRD is no longer built locally.
It's built by the vendor and shipped inside the UKI.
It's signed and it's verified as part of the boot process.
I will go into details in this process because one of the next talks will tell you everything
about this.
The UKI is dropped into the boot partition or ESP.
Then it's out of discover by boot loaders implementing the BLS, boot loader specification.
What does that mean is that you don't need to configure your system to pick the UKI up
when you boot.
The boot loader will parse what's available, get information out of it from the UKI itself,
and present you a menu.
It's top and plug and play basically.
This is supported by system in boot.
There are patches for grab as well.
I think Fedora will ship with those patches and hopefully they make it very upstream.
Another good thing about the UKIs is that not just we sign them and verify them as one,
but also we can then predictably measure them into TPM in PCR11.
The hashes will always match.
If that doesn't make any sense to you, that's okay.
Then later we tell you everything about TPM and measurements.
I just mentioned it here so you have overarching view of why this stuff is good.
We want to do some future work here, but the important thing is the specification is at
this URL.
That's for UKIs.
Now, next one.
This is my favorite one, DDI, discoverable disk image.
What is this thing?
It's just a raw image wrapped into a GPT partition table.
The good thing is that it is self-described.
Each partition is tagged with a UID that is fixed and tells you what the purpose of the
partition is.
You don't need to say root equal devs da5 because the partition is tagged with UID that
says I'm the root of this.
Because security is important to us, this natively first class supports the severity
for protection.
Again, the severity will be delved into later.
I won't tell you what it is.
It's for securing the partition against tampering.
All tools that support DDI support the severity natively.
Other important thing is that given they are self-described, you just pass them to the
right tool and they do the right thing that you expect out of the box.
You put it in a few disks where the ESP was, it's at the DDI.
System D will automatically find the root partition by looking at the UID and boot it
from the inter-ly.
If you pass the DDI to N-spawn, it will automatically use it for the root file system or the container
you are booting.
You pass it to portable D or the system service as root image and it will automatically use
for the root file system of that mount namespace.
You pass it to C-Zext and it will be automatically used to extend the root file system.
We've seen an example that means.
One image format, self-described, give it to many tools, they do the right thing automatically.
Security has first class concept.
Now, what is C-Zext?
This is important for the inter-ly talk later.
It's a specific type of DDI.
It can be used to extend a root file system.
It will ship the user hierarchy or the shop if you are a third party vendor.
It's identified by the extension release file which matches the format of the OS release
file that you are probably familiar with.
Specification of this is a dead URL.
You get a root of S-DDI, bunch of C-Zext-DIs and BAM, you get an OVEREFS read-only that
sums the content of all those images.
Again, this is important for the later talk.
Again, security, first class citizen, the D-M-VERE, the support of all of these and all the tools
that use these C-Zext-DIs.
Some ideas before, you pass it to the right tool, it does the right thing by default.
If it's your ESP, we see how it's being used to extend the Intel D. If it's on VAR or
ETC, system D will use it to extend your rootFS.
You pass it to portable D or to a system E service.
It will extend the rootFS of the service or portable service.
Again, with security in mind, so it's all protected and all new and enforced by the
kernel.
You pass it to N-spawn and nothing happens because you don't support it yet.
We should add that probably at some point.
Specification of this URL.
Now, all of this might sound like the increment rumbling of a Raving lunatic, but I swear
it's real.
It exists.
It's used in production.
What you can see here is the stuff that I work on.
It's a PCI Express card that has an ARM64 system on a chip.
It's used in the Azure host.
The machines that run Azure virtual machines have these cards plugged in and the Linux
RnOS provides offloading and acceleration for the Azure nodes.
If you use Azure, you already use this DVI stuff.
You just don't know about it because we use DVI extensively and we are looking into UKIs
as well.
This is all real.
It's all true.
Now, to conclude, come talk to us.
We usually don't bite.
Here's again the URL for the website and for the GitHub organization.
We want you to join us and embrace some of the secure way of doing Linux.
We want you to help us extend the specifications.
Also, we want to finally get the world class of security bugs extinguished.
Any questions?
Yes?
Microphone.
Hi.
How would you compare UKIs to fit images from U-Boot which also supports signing and packaging
all these parts into one single image?
Yes.
It is actually quite similar.
Now, of course, U-Boot is a firmware slash boot order environment used by embedded devices
essentially.
They support this fit format flattened image table and they have very similar concept,
absolutely.
The main difference is done with TPMs in mind.
I'm not sure U-Boot, they don't support that and measure everything.
I'm not very familiar with that.
They are very similar concepts.
I don't know what the main difference would be.
It's just different environments, I guess.
This is mainly for UFI.
U-Boot is a specific boot loader environment.
It can also run on the environment.
All right.
Okay.
They are very similar I guess then.
Thank you for the talk.
From my understanding, we often in usual distribution have shim sign and grub sign but we don't
have system D-Boot sign or a XT Linux sign or U-Boot sign.
What is the plan in the future to have those signs maybe?
Excellent question.
Now, there is a group of people working on this problem of UFI and UFI 2.0 and everything
that happened with the secure core PCs.
Things are moving.
I can't tell you much more than that right now.
We do want to get S-D-Boot sign for some internal use cases so we want to get that
allow listed to be allowed to be used as a payload for a second stage loader for shim.
We have not done that yet.
We would like to have that done at some point in the near future.
Thank you.
Can I make a comment?
So a kind of intermediate option is to have it signed by a certificate that is provided
by the distribution and it's protected by the hardware security measurements and so
on but it's not trusted by shim and then you can self enroll on the first boot and have
like a trust on first boot thing.
We've done a bunch of work on S-D-Boot to allow self-enrollment on first use so you
can always do that.
Of course, it doesn't work by default.
You need to do the self-enrollment but it's a step in your direction.
Yes, thank you.
Anything else?
Any pass please?
Thank you.
If you compile yourself a Linux kernel, what you have to do then?
So we in system 8253, we ship a tool called ukify, you can pronounce it however you want
and that will, this one, will allow you to easily put together a uki.
Of course, in that case, you cannot sign with your off-site key.
You need to do self-key enrollment and whatnot but it is possible to build a uki locally.
Absolutely.
You need to sort out the signature by yourself, of course.
I think that was at the back.
You mentioned, well, I saw in one of your slides the abbreviation DPS.
DPS, yes.
What does that mean?
Sorry, yes, I should have said that.
Discoverable partition specification, yes.
Told you there were a lot of acronyms.
So that is the list of all the GUIDs and what they define, rootfs, a verity, var, tmp, blah,
blah, etc.
Thank you.
I completely forgot about that.
I think we are at three minutes.
Any more questions?
Anything online?
No.
Going once, going twice.
Well, thank you very much then.