Okay, we can start a bit early. So next speaker is Van-Taun David. He will give a technical
overview of Ubuntu Core. So thanks for having me.
Yes, so this will be a very deep technical talk about how we do things in Ubuntu Core.
Ubuntu Core is a distro. It's based on Ubuntu builds, so the Ubuntu packages, but you can't
install or remove packages because we removed APT and DPKG and everything. The system is
split in four atomic snaps, so there are four parts that you can upgrade independently.
If you want to install anything on it, you need to install it as a snap. Ubuntu Core
targets Internet of Things for the month, so it's not a distro for a desktop. You can
have graphical user interface, but it's not ready for desktop. Because it's targeting
IoT, it supports lots of boot loaders, but in this talk I will focus on UEFI because
this is what is really interesting. Ubuntu Core has been doing a secure boot with full
of this description using the TPM for a while, and this was done before. systemd had lots
of nice tools to do that. This is why I thought it was interesting to talk about how things
were done because they might seem peculiar or it was a different approach.
What is a snap? A snap is... You will see that there is a different type of snap, but
what is common for a snap is just that it's a squash.fs image, and there is a specific
file that is metadata that describes what this image is for. Then after they will be
depending on type, there will be more information that you can get on that.
The type of snaps, first is the application. This shipped the application and its runtime,
and it expects to have another snap to run on top, which is the base, which is the root
file system. It doesn't have the root file system, it just has the runtime for the application
itself. Typically, application exports, services, or commands. In the desktop world, we have
also desktop applications, but for Ubuntu Core we don't care about these kinds of things.
Most applications run confined. There is all type of application in snap that we don't
support in Ubuntu Core, which are not confined. We only support confined in Ubuntu Core.
Then after we have the base snaps, and those are the root file system, and they are used
for the applications, but they are also used for the bootable system. It has systemd in
it. An application that runs on Ubuntu Core doesn't need necessarily to have the same
root file system as the host itself. It can just use a different version if it was built
for another version.
Then we have a snapd, because to handle all the snaps, how to unpack it and to install
it. There is a daemon. This is distributed as a snap itself. It's not an application
snap because it has specific things, so it has its own type. Then for Ubuntu Core, we
have the kernel snap, which provides the kernel, which is a UKI. It's a UFI kernel that is
signed and has the integerity in it. The snap also provides modules and firmware files.
Then the final type is gadget. I don't know why gadget, but it provides the bootloader.
In our case, it's shim and grub. It has also lots of configuration for snapd, how to make
the image. Cloud init, some init ced edition. Then we have also, if you want to have extra
command line in your kernel.
The disk starts, the image starts with just one partition, which is the ESP. We call it
the seed. It contains grub and shim, of course. It has the seed snaps. It's like the factory
snaps that you can revert to if you need. It also has a seed kernel that has to be unpacked
from the seed kernel snap because grub cannot read from there. I don't know. It has also
another file that is a modular assertion. It's a signed metadata file. It explains how
to update things. It's some authority file.
Once you have done the installation, I will not explain how the installation happens because
I don't think it's fun. I will explain how we run normally. Once it's installed, we have
three other partitions that will appear in your disk.
The second one is the boot, which also contains a grub. Typically, the grub will change from
the seed one. It will always boot from the seed. If it finds that it doesn't have to
do recovery or anything, it has to do the number one. It will go to the system on one.
The second one will have the current active kernel that you have installed. It will also
have a seal key for the data partition because at that time, I think it was not common to
have this seal key onto the header, looks to header. It was done like that.
After we have two partitions that are all writeable and they are encrypted, there is
a safe partition. Basically, it's to identify the device. It's not much on it. It's a very
small partition. Then we have data which contains most of the writeable data.
To have a runnable system, we have to do things in a TramFS. First of all, we use a system
D on both the TramFS and the main boot. Here are the few things that we do that might be
different for the system. One of the first steps that we have to do is mark all the disks
that we have. The first thing we do is measure the epoch. For now, I think it's always just
measure zero. It's something that has been done probably for revocation. If we need to
revoke the code, we can just increment that. I don't know how useful it is because I don't
think it has been touched.
Then we'll mount the boot and partition. Those are not encrypted. From the seed partition,
we find the model and we will measure it in the PCR. After that, we will find the seal
key from the boot partition and we'll un-seal it and open and mount the data partition.
Then we will do the same with the safe partition. The seal key for the safe partition is on
the data partition. We have to monitor the data partition before we open the safe.
Last we will find the base snap that we need to mount. This will find it from the data
partition. We will find a file that describes what is installed. We mount the base, the
kernel and the gadget. The base will be our sysroot and the kernel is needed because we
need the modules and firmware. The gadget, there's some configuration there that we need.
Optionally, we need snapd to be mounted also, but I will talk about this after. Then there's
some locking of the seal keys so we don't un-seal them again.
Once we have mounted all the disks, we have to prepare the file system. First, we will
by mount the base into the slash sysroot, where we will do the switchroot. Then after,
we have to by mount the userly modules and userly firmware. We do mounting of the seed
and boot partition within boot. There's a specific way to do it. Then after, from the
data, we have to do by mounting of specific paths onto the root file system. Typically,
for example, you want a slash of wire to be mounted, to be writeable. Your base snap is
not writeable because it's a squashfs, so you want to by mount.
We have a script for now that reads a list of paths that we have to do by mount. We also
can configure, saying that if it doesn't exist, we will initialize with the data that is on
the base snap or have it empty. This script will probably be replaced by using TMP files,
the FSTAB, but it was written like that. Wait, what's the time?
We don't by mount slash of wire and slash a TCTiractly as writeable because most of it
is not writeable. This is to ease the update because we can't track everything that needs
to be updated in a TCT. If someone modifies a file in a TCT, it's very hard to track.
We have a specific list of paths that are bindable that you can write.
An example is etc-systemd. This one, we need to install services and mounts for all the
snaps. This path needs to be writeable. There are some things that are really annoying
for us. Doing this is, for example, slash etc hostname because systemd does some atomic
write. That means that it will make a temporary file in the directory slash etc slash hostname
dot some temporary name and do a switch. But it's not possible if slash etc is not writeable.
There's some patches for that. A TCT local time is even worse because it's a symlink
that has to be rewritten. We need to follow the symlinks until we find the symlink that
is writeable. All this thing is a bit confusing and it's a bit annoying.
This was the initialization during the annual time of S&M. Then after, we switched to the
normal boot and most of what happens is just symlink. There are two main things that will
happen. It's done by Snabd. It's mounting the active snaps and starting the snap service
from the applications that are installed. Those are just units in symlink. They are
installed by Snabd slash etc slash symlink. Sysnabd will just start them for us. We just
have S&M installing those things there. But the problem is that in the first boot, Snabd
is not installed. That means that we have something special for the first boot where
we find that Snabd is not installed. We have this process where we have to find a Snabd
that was mounted from the initial MFS, run it to install itself so that we can just continue.
This is what's called the ceiling of Snabd. The disks are encrypted using LUX2. We use
a TPM. The PCR that we use for the policy are 4, 7 and 12. If you don't know what 4
and 7 is, it's from the system. You don't have to worry about that. 12 is something
that we deal with. We do our measurements. We might have several expected values because
we have a current parameter that changes if we want to do a recovery or some other things
that need to still mount the 5 systems that are encrypted. I think there's several values
for the PCR. Then we have another thing. We have a counter that we use for evocation.
This is because we need to reseal our keys every time we change what the values of the
PCR can be. To not allow all the values to be able to boot again, there is also a non-volatile
counter that is used that we increment each time we have to change. What we measure in
PCR 12 is one is done by system D stub because we use a system D stub to make the UQI. This
is a current command line. It's important for us because... Then we have, as I said
before in the
trauma phase, we have the APOC and the model. There are some interesting things that we
have. What happens when you have a failure that happens and you have a failure that happens
and you want to have the emergency shell to open? There is two things. First Ubuntu core
doesn't have... We try to not have password. You can have password, but by default you
don't have password. But even if we add... We have the inter-mafest that is built for
all that has to be signed in the UQI, it can be only built for every... One built for everybody.
That means that there is no... In the inter-mafest there is no password, but we still need to
have an emergency shell if we want to be able to debug things. To allow that, we only have
this emergency shell if we have a specific kernel command line parameter, which is dangerous.
You have to remember that since we measure the kernel command line in PCR 12, that means
that you will not be able to unlock with the TPM your disk if you are in that shell. You
will need to use a recovery key to be able to unlock if you want. We can do some debugging
and figure out things, but you have to change things and to disallow you to unlock, to use
the TPM. But maybe there is other things, the other ways we could have done things.
Maybe we could have done some specific measurement for when there is a need for emergency. I
don't know. Oh, yeah. Let's see quickly. When we update
the gadget, the interesting thing to know is that the gadget provides the... The gadget
not provide the shim and grub, and we might want to update it in different partitions.
So the seed or the boot, usually we want to only the boot, but if we might want to do
the seed which does the recovery, there is some versioning that we use to do that. That's
very important. Then when we upgrade the kernel snap, we copy the new kernel in a specific
way in the boot partition. We update a grub environment file. The grub will boot and see
that there is something to try to boot, and if it found that it did try to boot and it
didn't work, it will roll back. Then if snapd found that it managed to boot with the new
kernel, that it knows that it has finished the update and will update everything. This
we can skip. This is not that important. If you have any questions.
So, I'm from the Ubutu Touch team and the Ubutu Touch team still use the writable pad
system, the same thing that is still using Ubutu-Hore today. My question is that does
Mbutu-Hore have any plan to move on from this system or are you still planning to be using
this system in the foreseeable future or any update on that?
Are you thinking about the writable pad? Yes, the writable pad.
My plan is to move to TMP files and fstab, so use just tools that come from systemd because
we can do those things. It means there is a bit of duplication in how you write the
things, but that means that we have one less shell script do my thing that is not maybe
the nicest thing. I don't think there is any data when it will happen. It's just that we
know it works and we have to decide when we move to that.
Thank you. Any other questions?
You mentioned resigning or resealing on updates. Could you do away with that and use the trick
with binding to a hash of a certificate and then using the certificate to sign whatever
needs to be signed?
That would be better. What I showed you is how the state is now and it would be better
not to have a reseal. There was not that much experience I think in the community about
that at that moment that we could just do that which was better. When it's been designed
I think people didn't realize that could do something better. At some point we will get
there. I don't think we have any proof of concept on Boonjukor using this yet. We have
talked about it, that's it.
We still have time for questions.
It feels to me like using snaps in this way is a bit complicated. My question would be
what benefits do you get from this approach compared to something like system D Sys extensions
that were talked about earlier today?
You mean those? The point is that the application snap is the important thing for the user experience
because they want to have their own application and they can do quite a lot of things. This
is very interesting. Having everything to update in the same way makes things simpler
for them. I showed you what was the complex thing behind the curtain but I think the point
of having snaps there is just for the simplicity of the users. People who make image for their
applications they have to deal just with snaps and not many different technologies.
I don't know how to use all the things and make it look like it's a snap. I'm not sure.
Maybe there is a way. Which would be nice because if we have less code to maintain and
we just have a wrapper to something else it's much better. For the user I believe that it
has to look like a snap.
Round of applause.