I'm going to talk to you today about machine OS.
US, we've been working on for a couple of years and its design points are focused on appliances for data centers, lights out, hands off environments.
Over a year or so ago, we presented at the Clinic Security Summit with some details about securing secrets into PIMS for data center devices with some of the information about how we are going to keep those secrets fit in these environments.
Key pieces that we've incorporated from that design discussion on machine OS focus on use of security platform and the TPM2 device that we need to guard a unique identity and key piece that would be placed into a TPM that we use for identity and device authenticity.
And further, the operating system may be able to extract the TPM secrets if we have security booted all the way up to kernel user heads and that the change for us is still verified.
It ensures that we are the device, all the device we expect and the one software we expect as well before we can access these secrets. We also include support for unencrypted storage for access to data protection and incorporating continuous updates.
Your trust for machine OS is a certificate that an associated key pair, which we protected in TPM hardware. The certificate holds a product, ID and serial number that binds it to the physical system that we are using it.
And then, the certificate key pair in TPM, those are inserted at manufacturing time and then the certificate will give us a new identity to verify that the device is authentic and that we will be running the software that we accept the product expects and that it hasn't been tampered with.
At the run time of the box frame, for the last, we start with our device for TPM.
Thank you.
That protects us from the unusual expectant
of the current checks.
We've loaded and we're executing sort of a normal view of how the kernel comes up.
We'll transition into the loaded end of our MFSes startup
and then we get into where the machine OS creates the line.
We're going to unlock the storage to pull out our EA policies
that's loaded into the TPM and we need to access the registers to make sure that the values
in these registers are what we expect.
If they're not for them, we help the system run off on the board for something that's been modified
and we don't have access to any of the secrets in the TPM that we've locked away.
On success though, we can load our little trust keys and certs
which pass phrases that are protected in the TPM, loaded into the key
and used for only by the root.
And then once we have attracted that information, we extend the HCR7 with a rolling measurement
which will protect further access to the TPM from any of the runtime services.
Before we start the containers of the runtime service, we brought along that we have to go through steps
to ensure that the images that were included on the system match the product
and the product's expectations.
And these will have been signed by the product certificates to verify certificates, signatures
and that all winds up going so we'll go ahead and activate those.
So for each of the OCI images in the manifest, those will be mounted up and then the services can be started.
We also option to give this into a particular OCI that we call the Obstacles
and it's also across the environment.
That's what we're perfectly fine running just out of the area.
So for the OCI, we want to ensure that the image is stored, haven't been modeled
and the way we do that is the standard builds as a squash effect for all the layers in the OCI
which is a read-only file system that is mounted.
In addition to the squash-effect layer, those setting images have very much issues that were calculated and built up
and with that we can build a game-threatening block device in Linux which on access as we read
the first time we accessed that block device, the kernel will do the work of patching and then communicating
evaluating whether that block is valid or it's been tampered with.
In the case of tampered with, then the IO for reading will fail, it can't just stop the system to be rebooted,
we won't move further on the system.
For more details, later today one of my colleagues Scott Moser will be in the containment's dev room at 1405
talking more about this in depth.
Please go see him later.
For our updates, we have continuous updates as we can sync from our image repository
and an update is much like what we do when we reboot up.
We have to go through the same sort of verification of signatures such that we know that this is the software
that's expected for the device that we're running on and that all of the layers that we pulled out have been signed correctly.
Once we've applied that, we can update our configuration database,
that point to those versions for currently executing containers, we can simply restart them,
but if we have changes to reboot RFS or UKI, we'll need to reboot the system so that we can execute those versions.
Lastly, for offline protection or other prevention of maybe that is sort of an excellent town or a zero day turnover kernel,
we need to talk about verification and wait until the rest of the verification...