So, welcome again. The next speaker is Bernard Puttering, known for system D, post-alveo
and other fundamental projects. And, yeah, he will talk about his journey and learnings
of fusing TPMs and how that is working with four image-based Linux operating systems,
rendering boots and so on. Hi. Yeah, what he said. So, I'm going to
talk about image-based Linux and TPMs. We don't have much time. I think it's just 20
minutes and it's a complex topic. I already know right now that I'm not going to be able
to finish, but, yeah, that's not too bad. I hope the slides should be online sooner or
later. So, if we don't finish, it's not too bad. So, let's jump right in. What's an image-based
Linux? I don't think I have to say too much about that because Luca already gave an introduction
about this. But, yeah, it's really about having a core file system images instead of fine-grained
images. Many benefits. I'm not going to go into detail. Here we'll focus simply on the
relevance for building trusted systems. These images we now call DDIs. Luca had that on
the slides as well, which is like discover a little disk image. It just means that there's
a DPT partition table which describes what's on it and usually has a variety and things
like that. The other thing in the title of my talk was a TPM. Yeah, I hope some of you
have a rough idea what a TPM is. It's a security chip. Traditionally, it's a discrete one,
but nowadays it can also be in firmware or even in software. It's a cryptographic scope
process in a way that usually people then think, oh, it must be something fast, but
it's usually not. It's actually terribly slow usually. But it's not what it's supposed to
be. It's standardized, widely available, all your laptops in particular. The business laptops
usually have it as a discrete chip. The cheaper ones nowadays have it in firmware. It's pretty
universal. Conceptually similar to smart cards and fighter keys, right? It's a storage for
keys, but it's also very different. Supposedly, TampaProve can store at least one key securely.
Actually more than this, but yes, the primary purpose is there's a seed key stored on it
and then everything else can be derived from this. That key cannot be extracted. That's
the fun part about it. So ideally you have to have that specific chip or if you don't
have that chip, then yeah, you can't retrieve the keys. You can do lots of things with these
things. Most interesting, I think, is one that you can ask the TPM to encrypt and decrypt
data ultimately with that seed key that's stored on it. So that basically means while
you don't have that much storage on the TPM, you can see me store as many keys as you want
with the TPM simply by wrapping that key as they say, by taking any secret key you have,
passing it to the TPM so that it encrypts it with its own built-in seed key or some
key derived of that. And then you get it back and you store it on disk. And so you basically
have infinite ways how to bind keys to the TPM. What's fun about this part is that this
encryption can involve policy. Policy basically means that you can make restrictions about
how the key can be decrypted. For example, you can require that also pin is provided,
right? Like a human typed in pin. Pin just means password by the way. It doesn't mean
it has to be a number. It can also imply that system has to be in a specific state for the
key to be decrypted. State means, for example, that specific software firmware bootloader
runs, that the system is in a specific boot phase, that the specific disk encryption volume
key has been used and things like that. It's via a concept called PCR. It's more about
that. It's probably mostly we're going to actually talk about that point. It can also
mean you can bind policy to time, right? Like so that it can specify time window when a
key can be decrypted and prohibited otherwise. It's actually a useful feature. Sounds crazy,
but it's actually pretty useful. Hopefully we can quickly talk about that later. The
prior slide, that's just the TBM stuff that I find interesting that we're going to touch
in this talk, but there's a lot more about it. Like it has an RNG. You can actually do
store stuff there. Dictionary, tech protection, like millions of things you cannot just encrypt.
You can sign. I don't know. I'm not going to go into detail with that. Only 20 minutes.
These PCR policies, I want to go into detail. It's the most interesting type of access policy
and most people who deal with TPMs have encrypted their hard disk and linked it to the TPM usually
just played around with the PCR policies. That's something PCR is short for platform
configuration registers. They're basically just registers like little data variables
on the chip. Usually you have 24 of those. Initially they boot up at zero. You cannot
set them to anything you like. The only thing you can do is you can pass some data to the
PCR and then it's going to execute this. It will update the PCR with the number n. You
have 24. That's 0 to 23. It will calculate a hash value of the old value plus concatenate
with the new data. I said that it's SHA-256 because it's effectively what people use these
days, but it actually can be anything. That's the only operation it does. That basically
means if you pass data and later data and later data, it's going to come up with a value
and this value is derived from all the data you pass to it. This is a way of how we can
implement a chain of trust. This operation where you send the data to the PCR is called
extension of the PCR or you can also say the measurement of the data depending which way
you look. How are these PCR used on most of the laptops that you have? The firmware already
starts writing data to it. What data does it actually write to it? Usually all the code
it executes right before it executes it and also all the configuration for that code right
before it makes use of this. Afterwards, the PCR has a specific value and this value you
can then use to prove that the system went through certain stages because every part
of the system always measures the next thing so that if every element in the chain originally
was trusted, then it will pass on the trust and so on and so on. Nobody can change the
past but only the future and that's how you implement a chain of trust for the formatted
boot. The other good thing is that if you know the elements of that chain that you're
going to measure in advance, you can pre-calculate PCR values. You can basically say offline,
okay I'm using this firmware, this boot loader and this kernel. I can tell you what the PCR
is going to look like ahead of time because I can actually calculate this hash operation
myself in a very, very trivial way. You can pre-calculate PCR values. This is awesome
because if you can pre-calculate the PCR values and these PCR values can be used in policy
and secrets on keys that encrypt with the TPM, then you basically can say with that
that keys can only be decrypted if the system booted up with software that I actually trust.
That's what is kind of useful about PCR. You can do even other stuff with that but this
is like the key takeaway. If we can bind the decryption of secrets by the TPM to the state
of these PCR values, we can protect the secrets so that only on very specific systems running
specific software, running specific configuration, these secrets can be recovered. For disk encryption
that's the primary use case. Image-based OSes have this benefit that they can be measured
as a whole. If you have the entire OS in an image, it's very easy to calculate the hash
value of it and then it's very easy if you take that hash value and pass it to the TPM
to know in advance what the PCR is going to be at the end when the system is fully booted
up. This is systematically different if you have a package-based OS. In package-based
OS, locally you create a file system. Locally you unpack all these packages and sometimes
you update them at this time and sometimes you update them in another time. In package-based
OSes, you would end up as a file system that is going to be widely different from everybody
else who installed the same OS. Image-based OSes have this vulnerability because they
are cores, they update as a whole, you can do these pre-calculations and they're going
to have the same hash values in every single system and hence the same PCR values in every
single system. What's also great is it's not just about hash values in the PCRs that
eventually will show up because that sucks a little bit because it basically means that
if you have a secret that you bind to a specific hash value and then you update the image that
you ultimately calculated this from, then all these hash values will change. That sucks
because it basically means that you can't update your software anymore because if you
do, you lose access to all your secrets. Nonetheless, this is what Windows actually does. But we
can do better and actually assign these things because if we can pre-calculate them, we know
that this OS version is going to end up with these PCR values, then we can actually sign
them on like the vendor can do this and provide the user both with the OS itself plus information
about what the expected PCR is plus the signature for it, then you can actually use the TPM
and link secrets instead to the hash values, can link them to the public key that belongs
to the signature that you will get. This is awesome because it basically means that you
can update as many as you want, you will not lose access to your secrets. Now I'm going
to talk about SysTomy because I'm the SysTomy guy. Quick overview about all the TPM stuff
we now have in the most current system dewort and it actually covers the unreleased version
that's coming up, two, five, three. But yeah, SysTomy stub, it's a stub that like a UFI
stub that you can glue in front of a kernel and it does measurements of the kernel that's
about the boot. It does lots of other things but this is, yeah, for this context about
TPMs, this is what I find interesting about it. It still runs in UFI mode before Linux
is invoked and then passes control to Linux. There's a service system to call SysTomy PCR
phase. What that does, it measures certain strings at specific times of the boot into
a specific PCR. What's the purpose of this? Sometimes or I guess always it's kind of useful
that for example the encryption key for the root volume can only be unlocked in the inner
ID but not after. And that's an awesome property because it basically means that when somebody
exploits your system after the root file system is actually activated, then they can't talk
to the TPM to get the password back because basically these phaser stuff can destroy the
PCRs and because the PCRs are now used for the policy, yeah, the key is inaccessible
until a reboot is done and we end up in the inner ID again. There's SysTomy PCRFS. What
that measures is like FS identity, like file system identity. That's UUIDs of the file
system. The thinking about that is that there should be PCR where you can basically say,
okay, that identifies a specific installation that I have. Do we use PCR15 for this? So
basically that you can guarantee, yeah, my laptop is going to have that value there.
My laptop is definitely going to have a different one. So it's about being able to bind policy
to specific installations. There's SysTomy PCR machine that measures Etsy machinities.
Etsy machinities is just an explicit system ID that we introduced a while back. SysTomy
Crypt Setup is now something that can consume all this stuff that I was talking about there.
These things measure. This one then actually is able to unlock disk secrets based on these
PCR policies. There's something, yeah, it's, Crypt Setup is actually not just about making
use of the PCR policies. It also measures a hash derived from the volume key of the
root file system, for example, or actually can measure any volume key with that. So the
identity, the idea is basically that the secret is also measured to DPM and that this gives
a much stronger protection of the PCR15 stuff that I was talking about. In future, we probably
also add something similar to SysTomy variety so that basically, yeah, you can very protect
file systems and have the top level hash measured. Yeah, Crypt Setup can consume this. Then there's
also SysTomy CREDS in the service manager. That's the concept we recently added SysTomy
is basically how we can pass secrets into services and they can be encrypted via TPM
stuff and things like that. So it's kind of useful that you basically can say, I want
my X509 secret key encrypted in a way that it can only be unlocked on my specific server
running my specific OS during the InnoDartie brute phase but not later or something like
this. SysTomy measure is a tool that can pre-calculate expected PCR values for UKIs. UKI is the unified
kernel images. We had talked about that before so I'm not going to explain that. You can also
sign them so that you can basically have a UKI that carries both like the signature along
with it so that then later people can just make use of this to unlock their volumes.
There's a recently added tool, UKifi, I don't know how we supposed to pronounce that yet.
But anyway, it builds on SysTomy matter and a couple of other tools and you give it just
the components, it builds the UKI stuff, signs it with security, it signs it with the SysTomy
measure and then you have this one blob that you can ultimately deploy. The net result
of this is three relevant PCRs. In 11 we're going to America the kernel and the root file
system into. In PCR 12 there's going to be basically the configuration you pass to the
kernel that's primarily kernel and parameters and things like that but it's also more like
we have this credentials concept that I mentioned is going to measure it into that if they are
passed into the system and we'll have soon something called sys cfg which is like a secure
way how you can manage Etsy stuff. It's also going to be measured into that. Then PCR 15
I mentioned it's kind of the identity of the local system. Then you can consume this and
I mentioned this already with system decrypt and roll. There where you can basically say
now this disk can only be unlocked on a system that has physical access to this very TPM,
so to hardware, that can only be locked if it's booted with properly signed OS, UKIs and
OS, DDIs by a specific render. I can say I install Fedora here and this secret key shell
only be unlocked ever if it's actually Fedora that is booted but not if hacker OS or something
is booted. I can say, if linked to the configuration, I can say that secrets can only be available
during a specific boot phase. For example, in the NERD but not later. So that you know
that if you leave your booted up laptop somewhere in your hotel room or something like that
and you're not supervising it, that at least they'll not be able to get your root volume
encryption key via directly talking to TPM. You can also add a pin, you can do rate limiting
and things like that so that there's a dictionary attack protection so that people cannot just
go and hammer the TPM trying a couple of things, trying a couple of pins or something like
that because the TPM eventually says no, you have to wait or something or you have to provide
an unlock pin. I'm good at time actually. So far so good. PCRs are really useful stuff
and you're probably going to extend users them all across the system before other things.
They have other users like remote attestation, like you can use them to basically remotely
say like verify that a system in a specific state. People usually use that for servers
and stuff so that if you have a cloud and you have lots of nodes that before you give
a workload to a specific server, you can verify that still running exactly the software that
it should be and nobody hacked with it and booted something else and things like that.
It's also useful actually, back to the hotel situation, I leave my laptop in the hotel,
I come back and I can use the remote attestation so that this device can prove to me that it's
actually my device running my software as I intended and not something else. So yeah,
configuration and images I already mentioned, credentials I already mentioned briefly. Yeah,
last thing, Sakeboot and MagicBoot, people shouldn't confuse. MagicBoot is whatever
I was just talking about with all the measurements like this chain of PCRs and things like that.
There's also Sakeboot and UFI. Usually you do both, but they have different purposes,
right? Like one is ahead of time stuff where it doesn't even allow software to boot that
isn't signed properly. The MagicBoot is two differently, like the software can all run
but it will not get access to secrets if it's the wrong software. Anyway, we don't have
much time anymore. I would like to take at least some questions, so let's do that.
Hello, so all these measurements, are they going to be an TPM event log for systemd2
where I can debug that stuff?
That's a good question. So yeah, we currently mentioned this to the login framework, like
the regular Lexus log and the journal. We do not write a TPM event log. I know that
there's a specification for actually writing a TPM event log. We totally should, but I
didn't want to implement this Tcg spec for that yet. I didn't find a good library doing
this that I wanted to use. But ultimately, for the remote attestation case, we absolutely
need this. Eventually I want to get to this world where we can, before we run any service,
any container or any VM or something, we can measure ahead of time what we do and we write
that result to that event log and then people can consume the event log. So I think systemd
should write that.
I'm not a dihad fan of the format 2 work, but if you implement that stuff, we have now
three event logs. We have the UFO one, we have the IMA one, and then now we have the
systemd one. So it's kind of a kernel thing that actually the kernel should provide, I
think.
Well, I mean, it can grow indefinitely. I'm not sure you want the kernel to write stuff
indefinitely. I don't know.
Where is that?
If you care about these things, I don't think we should come up with our own standard for
this. If we write anything, it probably should be the Tcg one. But I don't know. I didn't
look into details like rotation or whatever else.
Okay, thanks.
So right at the moment, systemd-crypton-role has a least privileged problem in that whenever
you're handling cryptographic materials, you should always expose them to the least number
of subsystems. And the problem is that systemd-crypton-role is unwrapping the TPM key and then passing
the unwrapped key down into the kernel. But the kernel itself has a system for handling
the unwrapping of TPM keys. So what we should be doing is passing the TPM key straight into
the kernel and allowing the kernel to unwrap it. Are there any plans to actually implement
that?
I didn't know this existed. So I don't know. Is it documented anywhere?
Yeah, it's called the trusted key subsystem.
Yeah, I mean, yeah. So far, we don't really make much use of the curing thing because
of complex beasts. But if it exists, I see no reason why we wouldn't use it.
Okay, thanks.
I have a talk on that tomorrow on trusted keys if you are interested. My question is
about something else. You know about systems where the TPM2 communication is encrypted
and authenticated to avoid someone disordering the TPM and missing with it.
We do parameter encryption. And originally, it was just bound to the pin and then the
recent version, there's some solving going on. But I think we are like, you know, the
good thing is that nowadays, even the TPM2 SS maintainers themselves send us all the
patches to fix these things. So I think we're pretty like, at least we're way better than
what Windows currently does. And we keep on improving.
Hi. How to integrate this into a GRUB boot process? So you always need so as far as I
see, you always need an initial run file system to set up or to process all these TPM functionality
and then initializing a looks key store and then switch route into the root file system.
So is there a better way? You're asking me if GRUB is a better way
for anything? You're right. We're asking the wrong guy. I think GRUB, yeah, I'm not going
to say bad things. But you know, we have this other bootloader, like S-Sysdb. I mean, it's
not a bootloader, it's just a boot menu, but Sdboot. And I am not a fan of GRUB and these
things. And I systematically think it's really, really stupid to do disk encryption in GRUB
because it's not what you want there. You want authentication, not encryption. And so
I don't know. It's like to build a trusted boot, I'm not convinced that GRUB should be
part of the solution. It should just like, you know, an EFI system at least if you use
S
another way of protecting things. I know that many distributions, if they want to, like
because they use unencrypted, like they want to use encrypted slash boot, which I think
is stupid, but if they do this, then yeah, of course you need to add a disk encryption
support to GRUB. But I think the problem is you shouldn't have an encrypted boot. You
should use UKI's and things like that. And then have your secrets come in once the internet
already initializes and tells the system what to do. So if you ask me, is there a better
way? No, what you're proposing is the worst way. This is the better way. So yeah.
Thank you for your talk. Quick question. You didn't talk a lot about recovery. And I'm
more interested in through your test, have your encounter TPM2 wearing and TPM2 dying?
And what can happen in those situation regarding field recovery, disaster recovery and so on?
So you know, in all the stuff we're doing, like the TPM stuff is just one option among
many, right? Like we have multiple key slots and luck stuff. And so we added actually to
system decrypter enroll, high level support for its concept, like recovery keys, which
are just regular passwords. The only difference is they're generated by the system instead
of selected by users. So they have high entropy and should be good quality. But I would say,
yeah, if like, it's what everybody else does too, right? Like on MacOS, you can have a
recovery key and on Windows, you can have a recovery key. And this is what we should
do here as well, right? Like use TPMs, absolutely. And then hide entropy recovery keys, things
are fucked up, things are fucked up. But yeah, it's a matter ultimately for the distributions
to have a nice UI for this, right? With all of this, I kind of want to push into that
direction that the TPM stuff is the default. And then if you want something else, like
FIDO or whatever else you enrolled in addition to that, and that's, yeah, anyway. Thank you
very much.