Okay. So today I'm not going to talk about image based or anything that I'm going to
talk about.
Containers.
So not just containers.
Sorry.
There will be different ones there.
Okay.
So we have a demonstration and CPMs and such. And we have a demonstration if you act up
making sure that what you run on some device is the code that you expect. Checking it from
another device that you trust.
So everybody in this room I guess you're coming here with what we changed in the next slide
when you brought your computer.
Then you just look at the UI.
We will then change the computer controller.
Oh yes, I was on mute. Sorry.
So again maybe for the remote audience, when you get a boot chain, you put up your computer,
you have UFI goes to bootloader, goes to the kernel, goes to initramfs.
And then because we are talking about a lot today, security things, you want to crypt
your disk partition and so enter a passphrase to unlock it.
Then if you want to make sure that what you've loaded is what you expect, you can store measurements,
so signatures, hashes of every step inside the TPM.
A TPM is a passive component.
It is just there to store information, perform some cryptographic computation on it if you
ask it, but it doesn't block anything in the boot chain, right?
It is just there to store and execute commands that you pass to it.
And so later on, after the boot is done, you can go back, for instance, in init in your kernel,
to read back what you had in the TPM and check that what you have is what you expect.
The problem is there is an issue if it's not what you expect, you end up here, you enter your passphrase,
but your system was already compromised into the passphrase that you just entered, maybe
got extra created, and now your disk is compromised as well.
That's typically the case when you have offline attacks on a laptop you may have forgotten
or left unattended for the conference room.
So what we can do and what people in large organizations typically do is use remote attestation.
So you have an app started, for instance, in the init RAMFS, which will talk to the TPM,
get the measurements, and then ask a remote attestation server somewhere trusted to check
that the measurements are what's expected.
And that's where what you got in the previous talk, that you want to have images that are
reproducible, that are signed, comes very key because a remote attestation server would
typically be your organization server, it knows about the signature, so you can check
that the image is the one that it signed, that it is the one that is blessed by your security team.
And then if everything is fine, typically the remote attestation server would hand back
a secret to your dedicated attestation client, and the client could use that secret to decrypt
your disk.
And in that case you don't even need to enter a passphrase anymore.
I mean, you could also add a passphrase if you want to be more sure, but if you had some
kind of control on the attestation server, then you may not even need the passphrase.
The issue is that everybody in this room, maybe some of you work at big companies, but
not everybody, obviously.
And so how do you set up the server?
Do you need to run something in the cloud?
It's super inconvenient.
As a matter of fact, all of you, I think, have a server in their pocket.
It's called a mobile phone, and so you just need to run the remote attestation server.
OK, that's the security part because I work for a government agency.
And so you have the server run on your phone, and then you can communicate with your laptop
over Bluetooth.
And that's what we implemented.
A user-friendly, lightweight, TPM remote attestation running over Bluetooth with a server, well,
client, it depends who will change names, but one of them running on your phone and
the other on your laptop.
It's an idea that was prototype by Matthew Garrett a couple of years ago at Linux Connect
Australia, but it was just a rough prototype, and basically you're trying to make a production
grade, at least hacker grade.
So we have the server running on the laptop.
You can know I'm switching names between client and server because we can't decide.
So on your laptop, you have the server, it's written in Go, it talks to Bluetooth stack,
and then we have clients for Android and iOS written, well, for the TPM part in Go, and
then for the UI in Kotlin or Swift.
So the way it works is when you start the server on the laptop, it shows a QR code with
a key so that we can encrypt the communication between the laptop and the phone and pair
them in a secure way.
You scan the QR code on your phone, it gives you the key, and then on first use, you have
a trust and first use step where you need to kind of trust the measurements the very
first time.
We do not support right now downloading trusted measurements from an external server the way
you would do if you are in a large organization.
Remember, this is for individual users, but we could extend it to support that use case
if needed.
And then every time you want to test and let things haven't changed, then you just render
the other here again on the laptop.
You don't need to scan the QR code anymore.
You just start the attestation and the client, it tells of our Bluetooth automatically using
the key that it remembered, it exchange cryptographically the results of the measurements.
Thanks to the TPM remote attestation protocol, you can check that it is the same physical
machine, or at least the same physical TPM.
So if you left your laptop and attend in the first demo room, unless the attacker put it
up and swap TPM stuff like that, it doesn't happen.
So it can really make sure it is the same hardware it is talking to, or it is the same
TPM.
And then it checks that the measurements of the boot chain haven't changed since last
time.
And it can send back a secret optionally to the laptop if you want to use it for this
encryption.
Of course, it doesn't send a secret back if things have failed.
So we have a demo, and because we know how a demo works, it is a recorded video.
I mean, I can also try the demo for real afterwards.
So this is running in a virtual machine created with MayKozie that was mentioned in previous
talks.
So now I'll first show the enrollment.
So the virtual machine is booting for the first time.
So on the left, you have the virtual machine.
On the right, you have the phone.
In that case, the iOS client, because it is much more beautiful, because my intern spent
a lot more time working on it.
But I don't have Xcode.
So the client I reviewed is the Android one.
And so the one you get on GitHub has fewer features.
I'm sorry.
Eventually, we'll merge everything back.
So here, the first time we boot, we need to enter a passphrase, because we haven't enrolled
yet.
So it's the bottom of the screen, but we run the old trial server to perform the initial
trust and first use enrollment, now that we are fully booted to align Xcode.
So here, you have to trust your system.
It's the first time you boot if it's already compromised your host.
It's going to display the QR code that we are going to scan with the phone.
And then it starts at station, showing the steps on both sides, get the measurements.
And now we have the device registered on the right.
So we can change its name.
We know when we created it when we last ran an attestation.
And as you'll see, you can edit the security policy.
So the way it works, when you boot is, you choose what kind of measurements you want
to check.
Again, this is only in the iOS application, but coming soon on Android.
Then the next step is to run system decrypt enroll, so that because when we enroll the
phone, we send back a secret to the laptop, which was stored in the TPM in a special register,
in PCR9.
And so here we run system decrypt enroll, so that we add another factor, another slot
to unlock the disk based not on the passphrase, but on the content on TPM register 9.
So here basically, yeah, that's what we did.
And now we regenerate the initramfs using drag cut modules.
We would like to get rid of them because they are very buggy, but maybe see previous talk
one day we can, so that we can enable Ultra Blue and startup.
And here we start again, but now startup stops at some point, starting the Ultra Blue server.
And we go on the phone and just press this button, the play button, starting an attestation,
fetching the measurements.
It works.
So we send back the secret.
And we don't need to enter a passphrase anymore, because we send back the secret, so it unlocked
based on the secret.
Now what happens if something has changed in the boot?
So again, we start an attestation.
And here we do not send back the secret.
We say, oh, something is different this time.
It's in PCR8.
It has changed.
And PCR8, we provide some info to the user, is expected to contain the hash of the kernel
command line.
Then you can even look at the diff.
And if you look at the diff, you can see that you have a new command line option, super
AVLopt, that has been added.
So this data, you cannot really trust it, but you can trust that this data, its digest,
is the same as the one stored in the TPM.
And then you can choose what you want to do.
You can say, OK, this is a legitimate update.
For instance, I updated my firmware.
It's an expected change, so I save the new one.
You can say, OK, trust, but only once, as you would do in a browser.
Or you can say, oh, no, it's definitely an attack.
I want to reject it, maybe call some security team.
We haven't implemented that yet.
But do not send back the secret in any case.
That's what we do here.
We reject it.
And so it falls back to asking you a passphrase to end up your disk.
And that's about it for today.
So you can, it's versatile.
You can embed it in any tramFS.
You can use it as a second factor.
We provide in the release sample makers a script to build the VM that I just demonstrated.
We also just today published a release just for you, first-time attendees, so that you
do not need to rebuild everything.
You can just test.
Then if you're interested about the protocol, you have five minutes of questions.
But trust us, we asked the security team, I mean the cryptography team in our lab to
review it.
It's fairly standard.
It's fairly standard for a mutatestation protocol.
And so, yeah, we want to integrate more.
That's why we are here today to talk to you.
So go on ancfr slash ultra blue, add slash release if you want some binaries for Android
and x86 Linux.
And yeah, I'm here for questions.
I'll start with a question.
How practical would it be to run this on your laptop?
Well, I just basically mentored Loic, but I commented Loic with Nicolas Bouchinais,
who should be in this room somewhere hiding.
Yes, here.
And Nicolas mentioned just yesterday that he's now quite ready to use it on his laptop.
So I guess ask him.
I don't even have secure boot enabled on this laptop.
So I guess the French NSA doesn't allow you to use that.
So it's like, I mean, this is the public source.
So it's endorsed by our agency.
It's been endorsed in the sense that it's okay to release the code publicly.
We have reviewed it as carefully as we can.
We do not consider it production grade right now.
Hi, have you thought about using it to assess the IMA log at runtime as well?
So for files that are accessed against some network accessible database, not only for
boot, but also for checks at runtime.
So I think for checks that there are two things here.
For checks at runtime of your file system, I think you want to use more like the variety
and other mechanisms that we have.
But the TPM doesn't only have uses at boot time.
So the fact that you run remote attestation, this could be done later.
The advantage to make it early is that you can detect if you're compromised in putting
your class well, basically.
Yes, I see some questions here in the back.
Let's say that nobody swaps your TPM.
Like yes, put that case aside.
Could you get the same level of attestation just with signatures with the TPM?
Like let's say you don't think that somebody was going to swap your TPM.
So could you just like check some all the parts of the boot chain and just like sign
the hashes and just add boot, verify the signature with TPM?
Yes, but the problem is how do you trust what you see on the screen of your laptop?
The idea that the phone remains in your pocket.
So the phone is trusted or it's not trusted to have two devices than one because it's
harder to compromise two devices.
So if something in your bootloader is compromised, it could show you on your computer that, okay,
the TPM measures checkout, et cetera.
And this is even more true for something that's called dynamic root trust measurement, root
of trust measurements.
So not only trusting your bios to make the measurements, but like some special instructions
in CPUs, whether you restart the root of trust later in the boot process.
But for this to work, the check has to be external.
You said it's not production ready.
Do you see it being production ready anytime soon?
Is that the goal?
It's not a stated goal of the agency.
I'd be very happy for it to be used more widely.
And I think for this to happen, we need people outside of the agency interested.
Yeah, looks great.
I have a question regarding the app on the mobile phone.
So how does the app know that it's speaking to a trusted server or the server that it
can trust?
So does it exchange keys with the server on first use or how does it work?
So there is a trust on first use, so there are two levels of security.
First, the Bluetooth communication is encrypted and the key for that communication is embedded
in the QR code that you scan first.
And then the identity of the TPM.
The TPM has a secret key inside and uses it to answer the public key stored in the app
on the mobile phone.
And so the app can check that it talks to the expected TPM.
So basically, the encryption key is used to attest that it's the same operating system
or in each RAMFS.
And the TPM key is used to check that it's the same TPM.
Yeah, but that's still, as far as I understand, does not prevent a malicious server to send
the app the wrong values or to just imagine the values and send them.
Boom.
So that is something that we haven't implemented right now because we wanted it to be easy
to test with virtual machines and software TPMs.
But one thing is that the TPMs certificates, basically, you have a list.
The TPM keys are signed by vendor.
And so you have a list of the keys of the vendor that are used to sign the certificates.
So when you get the quote from the TPM, you can check that it's a hardware TPM by some
well-known manufacturers and not some accumulated TPM.
So you can be sure that you're actually talking to a physical TPM device.
And so the server cannot mess with that.
But you're right.
We haven't implemented this right now, otherwise the demo on purpose, so to say, because otherwise
the demo wouldn't work.
That's an option I want to add.
Very good question.
This is using Bluetooth.
Bluetooth specification is very complicated.
How much does it rely on Bluetooth working fine as expected?
So it's using Bluetooth low energy.
It's relying on the Go Bluetooth library to work fine.
So we don't use any of the Bluetooth stack encryption for the encryption part.
We roll out our stuff.
And we layered the code so that it's mostly agnostic to the underlying transport.
So if you want it to run on your infrared, it should be relatively easy to port.
It is not allowed to code that.
And we are extremely conservative in that we just abort as soon as we receive packets
out of orders or unexpected packets.
OK.
Last question from online.
Someone asked if any distribution expressed any interest in making it in the Ultra Blue.
Yes, in fact.
But not officially.
Twitter message is we presented this at Open Source PMR conference last September as well.
And after that, there was some interest online and people saying that that were federal.
They may be interested.
But it was not official federal position.
Some federal contributors.
I can say that this is interesting to that.
Thank you.
Thanks for the speaker.
And we have one.