Please sit down if you can.
So the next speaker is speaking of Yandere Smek and he will talk about MK OSI INIT ADI,
a new project to build INIT ADIs from system packages.
Yeah, so my talk builds on previous talks.
So my name is Bishak, I work in Red Hat in the Plumbers group and I work on System B and
Fedora, Rust2RPM, RPM, Autospec, build tools and stuff like that.
And so we heard today about a new approach to delivering the kernel and the user space,
the root file system to computers.
And I mean all the stuff that was mentioned today, so secure boot to trust your code,
PCR measurements, boot phases, locking secrets to the PCR state.
This creates a situation where we should think how we put, how we build INIT ADIs and I think
it's a good opportunity to kind of throw away a lot of old approaches and use a new approach.
And doing the things the way that I'm talking about today would have been very hard a few
years ago because we didn't have those mechanisms that we have right now, like credentials and
system extensions.
So right, Luca talked about system extensions, so the compact disk images that carry a file
system and one partition, the inverted data in another partition and a signature for the
root hash of the de-inverted data in a third partition and this is squished into an image
with minimal padding, so actually it sounds kind of awful but it's basically just a file
system image with some metadata that can be trusted.
And those tools allow us to do things in a completely different fashion than we used
to do them in the past.
So what do we do now?
I mean, there's various different distributions but the approach is generally that on a general
purpose distribution like Fedora, the user wants to have an INIT AD so they scrape some
files of the file system, whatever is installed, sometimes with some local modifications, sometimes
not, you use LDD to figure out what libraries should be loaded and whenever there are extra
files that need to be put in the INIT ID, somebody has to remember to do that.
So essentially we duplicate the packaging layer.
And we do it on every user machine so this costs time during upgrades, it's actually
quite noticeable because of compression.
And so this was before we booted and after we have booted into the INIT ID, generally,
for example, the Fedora INIT ID, they have system D but they also have lots of extra
functionality added that came before system D was there.
And over time, this functionality has been moving into system D. And now we are at the
point where it's completely useless.
I mean, the part that is apart from system D is not useful because we could just get
rid of it and because it is implemented by system D in a better way in general.
And people here, okay, now we should do something, access a file system in the INIT ID, let's
like some patch to do it.
And why?
I mean, we should just do the same thing we do in the host file system and use proper
tools.
And if those tools are not good enough, then we should fix them so that it's nice to use
them in the host file system and they're also nicer to use in the INIT ID.
And it's like a legacy that this INIT ID environment used to be much different.
But we use system D and system D does the setup where it sets up slash proc and slash
dev and mounts everything that needs to be mounted.
And the INIT ID doesn't have to be.
The fact that it's different from a real system is just something that we should get rid of.
And so we have this duplication where we have the system D way to do things and the non-system
D way to do things in parallel.
It just adds complexity and it's not beneficial.
And everybody does the INIT ID in a very, very different way, every distribution.
And even some distributions have multiple ways.
I know that one of the goals of Trapwood was to unify the approach between distributions
that didn't really work.
So this is another approach we'll see in 10 years.
So we sign stuff.
If we sign the kernel but not the INIT ID, then we are just pretending.
It's a waste of time.
We need to sign both.
But in general, users want to have the thing, users don't want to play with local key management.
It should be signed by the distro.
If it's signed by the distro, then the INIT ID must be also built by the distro.
So all this functionality that we have to inject things into the ID based on local configuration,
well we cannot use it.
So essentially the idea is that, OK, if we are going to move the whole build of the INIT
ID into the distro infrastructure and build it like a package, then let's do it in a clean
way.
And for me, this means taking a declarative set of distribution package names, letting
the distribution package manager figure out all the dependencies, and then using the distribution
package manager to put the files in a directory, and then just zipping it up into any INIT
ID.
So before I talk about the specifics of how to do this, let's talk about some problems
that immediately appear.
If we try to build one INIT ID for, let's say, whole Fedora, then we will end up with
this gigantic blob that will take 60 seconds to load whenever the kernel boots.
This is not nice.
So we need different INIT IDs for different people.
And one option is to just build multiple variants, and we definitely plan to do this.
For example, a simplified INIT ID that works for VMs that only has some basic stuff that
you need in the VM and no other drivers and no other tools, and I know one for laptops
and so on.
But this only scales so far.
We can have maybe five variants, but anything more than that would be annoying.
And the other approach is to use systemd extensions.
So the idea would be that you have the basic INIT ID, and let's say you want, I don't know,
it's in your INIT ID, and you install this additional extension.
And I should mention what happens with trust here.
So the bootloader verifies the kernel and the INIT ID before loading it.
And then after the INIT ID has been loaded, and we want to use the INIT ID code loads
the extension, so it checks the signature of the extension before loading it.
So systemd extensions are a mechanism to add code in a way that it is trusted before, I
mean the trust is checked before it is used.
And if we use UKIs, we need some way to inject configuration into the...
Well, I mean we build an image that's supposed to work everywhere, so it cannot have local
configuration, and we need to deal with this issue somehow.
And one approach is to use the just auto discovery of partitions and not have any local configuration,
which is nice if we can make it work.
But a more general approach is to use credentials and to inject a configuration that has been
signed and bound somehow to the local system using systemd credentials.
And I would say that this is an area of active research, because I don't think that anybody
really knows how this is supposed to work in details.
And I wanted to mention that if we build INIT IDs from packages, we have builder reproducibility,
because we have an exact list of packages that was used, and we can download them again
and unpack them again in the same way, and we should have bit for bit identical result,
which is good for checking that the EID was put together correctly, but it's also very
useful if you want to build some system extension afterwards, because you build the extension
by adding additional stuff and then taking the difference between the old image and the
new image.
And the tool that we are using for this is...
Well, the project is called mqsi-interd, because it takes mqsi, which is a very simple tool
that takes a list of packages and calls the package manager to download the packages and
put them into an image.
And it does all the things that we happen to need, so it supports GPT tables and the
mvarity and signatures, so we can do system extensions, and it can also do archives, and
this is what you need for INIT RAMFS format.
And mqsi itself is just a set of configuration scripts for configuration files for mqsi,
right now only for Fedora, but the concept carries very cleanly into other distributions,
so I think that if it works in Fedora, maybe other people will pick it up too.
So just a list of packages and some local...
Some tweaks to turn the installed packages into an INITRD, and the same for system extensions.
And well, in general, the plan is to do it on the distro side, but right now this hasn't
happened yet, so we have a kernel install plugin, and you update the kernel and you
very slowly build the INITRD from packages on the local system.
It's not very efficient, but it works surprisingly stably.
And for Fedora 39, we want to propose changes to the build system to allow INITRD to be
built in this way in the build system and deliver those packages for people who want
to try it out.
I think it's years from being the default, if ever.
So, this works.
It works without too much issue.
The INITRDs are bigger, but they're not infinitely bigger, they're maybe just twice as big.
And the biggest difference surprisingly comes from kernel modules, because what Drakut and
other INITRD builders do, they select a specific list of kernel modules that are needed for
the local system.
I wanted to avoid this, I wanted to take all the modules from a kernel package and just
put them in without knowledge about specific modules.
I think that this is not feasible, we'll have to do some kind of filtering too.
But the code itself, there's very little difference in the size of executables and libraries
installed into the INITRD.
And this is because the code that we use in the INITRD is the same code from the host
file system, so it has the same library dependencies and you need to put the same set of libraries,
and actually most of the space is taken by libraries, because the functionality has been
moving more and more into shared libraries because we build more complicated stacks.
So this means that in principle the size overhead is not too big and can be reduced.
And this works in some cases, but for simple cases, for laptops and for some types of storage,
not certainly not for everything.
And what do we get?
We have less things, we use the package dependency resolution mechanism so we don't duplicate
packaging, we don't need to care about installation because we have RPM to do it for us or whatever.
We have replaceable builds because we don't take files from the host and everybody has
the same image which is important for people trying to debug errors reported by users.
And if we build things centrally, we can assign them, and we use system D and just get rid
of the extra stuff so our life is simpler.
And there's a common set of things that people complain about, like arrays when this is discussed.
So I wanted to underline that system D is already used in the INITRD so we're just removing
things, not adding new things.
And system D sets up the environment so things are already like they should be.
So all the extra work that people have put into having scripts that work without slash
prop mounted, it's not useful.
And we remove stuff and we would be moving from scripts to demands anyway, right?
And shared libraries because if somebody tells you to provide to authentication, for the
root disk, you're not going to script it, you're going to use some compiled code to
do it anyway.
And I don't know, netling, timeout, retries, localization, D bus, all this stuff is just
semi incompatible with scripting.
And we would be moving in the direction of normal compiled code anyway.
And so in case the ID itself is kind of, it's implemented and mostly works.
The stuff that is happening is in the surrounding areas.
So in particular, this development in system D related to credentials is very important
because we want to make use of this.
And support for unified kernel images is growing.
There are patches, there's a link here, patches for grab two to load unified kernel images.
And I mentioned that we want to build MKSI interior images in Fedora, so this will require
changes in the code you build system.
And that's what I have.
I have to have time for questions.
One minute, three minutes.
Okay.
When I was thinking about systems that boot from network and for instance, where the root
system is on ISKASE or NVM over fiber, you need some information that is really device
specific.
How can we separate that from the init ID?
Because you want a single init ID for all the systems.
Yes.
So one option is to put it on the kernel command line if this is an option.
And the second option is to provide a credential that is unpacked and becomes part of the configuration
in the init ID.
So essentially, yes, you just inject this configuration, but it wouldn't be part of
the init ID itself.
It would be delivered in a different way.
Same questions.
What would you do if you want to have files from the local file system?
For example, you need a custom mount command that does more than a feature mount.
Well, I would say ask why do you need that?
But if you need that, then just do the build locally.
And the difference is, I think it was kind of the same question as before about unified
kernel images.
You can do the build locally.
You just don't have the distro signatures.
Thank you.
It might be a bit similar to the previous question, but thinking from a distribution
standpoint, there is a lot of hardware out there which is incompatible with default configurations
or default init urges.
And you need to add patches to kernels.
You need to add special kernel modules which are not enabled by default.
What is going to be the flow to support this hardware to use it on distribution by default?
So I think that this is much less common than people think, right?
Because I mean, how many people build their kernels nowadays?
Small minority.
And from the distro point of view, this is already outside of scope, right?
If you report a bug that your custom compiled kernel does not work, then nobody is going
to help you because people have too much bugs reported for the standard distribution.
The existing ways of building things locally, they will always be there, right?
I mean, they are not going away.
So basically the answer is, well, I mean, if you are doing something specific, then
you keep doing this specific thing.
And this is the way to make the life for the distro easier, but it's not going to cover
all cases, maybe like 90%.
Any more questions?
You mentioned kernel model making the entire bigger.
Could this be shipped in a standard extension somehow?
Can you repeat?
Could you ship the kernel models which are in the internet in system extension instead?
So the kernel and the initial internet, the kernel must have enough stuff built into to
understand the int rd and the int rd must have enough modules to be able to load system
extensions.
But once you do that, like you can have an extension with kernel modules and whatever.
Yes.
So last question.
Is there a path to getting your int ramfs core from somewhere and running a different
distro?
Like essentially to your project or some project providing the core int ramfs with the system
D inside it and everything inside of it.
Get the modules from elsewhere.
And then when you pivot, is that a hard line that you can live?
I think that technically it's doable because system D is kind of used everywhere and there's
really no reason why it wouldn't work.
I assume that distro would want their own code in the int rd, but technically it's not
required.
Okay, thank you.
I mean, if there's this general requirement that because there's a switch route where
the state is passed from the int rd to the host and you don't want to pass the state
from a newer system D to an older system D. So the int rd would have to be just older,
old enough.
Thank you very much.