So, hello. Oh, it vanished. Okay. Oh, it reappeared. So, hello. My name is Armin Le Grant. I'm
working on the graphics stack for a long time, as many of you know. And this is actually
also a kind of update from the LibreOffice conference where I already talked about system-dependent
primitive renders and why they are important. I'm talking about them for years, as you know.
And at the last conference, I was so... I wished to promise to implement a prototype, and I did,
and it's finished. And I did it on Direct2D, and it renders what you expected to render. So,
with Direct2D, of course, it's on Windows. But there was no special reason for Direct2D. I just
wanted to try out if it fits well to a standard graphic library, and if I could figure out how
to do it myself, because I didn't know Direct2D too good myself. So, it was some safe training,
too. So, it's finished. It's working. And everyone can have an example now how to do some system-dependent
primitive render, if he wants to. So, what happens when painting? I don't want to go in detail about
that. I have tried to formulate what's all happening, so you can just check it when you
download the presentation. That's the history, why it happened, what happened. Also, some history.
So, what did I do? Just started with a simple primitive processor, and it's feature-complete,
because it supports all necessary primitives. There are four primitives you have to support,
and some grouping primitives you have to support, and there are quite some extra primitives
supported to get some more speed into it, which is not necessary to be feature-complete, because,
as I hope you know all now, you can decompose a primitive, and it just dismantles the simpler
primitives, which can then be rendered. So, it's in a single source file, so no hacking required.
Inside this single source file, you can do whatever you want. It's just 2,000 lines,
so not too much if you compare it with some backend implementations, which are spreaded
over the whole office. It translates primitive data directly to direct2D, uses already available
system-dependent buffering, which was not used in other implementations. I don't know
why, because it's working and available. It does not need any adaption of bitmap bitmapX,
which of course would be even better to do, so to directly use the data without converting
it. But now, it's just converted once and held in this standard system-dependent buffer.
So it's quite fast, and you can try yourself, because it's in the master, so if you have
a Windows Pro version and you started with the environment variable mentioned here, you
will get the new renderer, and you will see the added view of the impulse and the parts
of Witer and Kalk, as far as, say, support primitive rendering, rendered directly by
direct2D without using output device at all. So that's proof of concept, and I delivered.
So now, I hope we find some guys who can help. These are the ones I added to make it faster,
and it's not even optimized, but already pretty fast, because just think about the layers
which are used. We have the model. It creates primitives. The primitives are thrown at a
renderer currently to the VCL Pixel renderer. That renderer packs it to output device, still
to output device, and that output device sends it to a backend. So you have a five-level
stack and output device alone does a lot of work in between, old, un-maintainable, incredible
stuff in between. So what a system-dependent primitive renderer does, it removes the three
last steps and packs it into one. You go directly to the renderer you want, in this case direct2D.
So what does it look like when you let it run? It looks the same, and that was exactly
the target. It looks the same, but it's fast, and it does not use output device. So what
else can be done? Currently it has no support for text, so text is decomposed and rendered
as anti-aliased poly polygons, not too bad, but of course for production state we would
need something more. And direct support for gradients, so for direct2D I already looked
a little bit into it. It might just be done as a custom effect, which is some kind of
texturing. So with some more work this could easily be extended to product quality. Let's
see if we find resources to do with this system.
So what also happened? Krallen started a system-dependent primitive renderer on Kyrol. Thanks Krallen,
you're my man. So he just tested out by copy-pasting the structure and filling it out with Kyrol
stuff and it does render some things. There are some KFETs and it would need some more
love. But it's easy maintainable and can be extended. So another proof of concept that
this really works well. So in the process I also did some upstream cleanup stuff in
the master, which was in the race. It was another reason to do this proof of concept
and prototype. I can no promise that you can do exactly the same in drawing layer and do
your own system-dependent primitive renderer for any target system without having to fear
that you get hung on something in the master, which would be in the way because I had to
clean that up anyways. The other point is, this is good for edit view visualizations,
but what about the rest which is still painting using output device? So I did two more experiments.
One is forward calls in the backends. So the backends has a lean API. I just made a proof
of concept prototype. You can find it in Garrett with the link I gave. You can edit as a patch
to the current office, compile it and see it running. And you will see that it currently
forwards a single method, draw a rectangle for test. And to make it visible in the office,
it's just a little bit color coded so we can see it. So that works perfectly. And the good
thing is the backends are libraries themselves. You can just link them against a drawing layer
and all functionality can be in drawing layer and you're storing layer stuff. The other
way I tried was a kind of draw for water in the output device itself. So for every paint
command, call something in a virtual structure, which is then overloaded in output device.
Also works flawlessly. And I also use the draw rect again. And this is proof of concept
too. There's also a Garrett link. You can just use that link, patch it into your office,
compile and see it running. You get the same color styling to see how it's running. Yeah.
So which way to continue? Best convert all to LibreOffice primitives. I always wanted
to have that done, but I know it's not possible. Combination of one of this solutions with
system dependent primitives or worst, just keep it like this. Like always. So I'm still
very interested to do this, but I did this prototype now mostly in private with some
support from Torsten. Thanks. But I cannot continue doing it in the needed intensity
just privately. So without getting resources, this will fail again. And we will stay at
VCL output device forever. That's it.