Hello, so my name is Sisko Foley.
I work for the Document Foundation as a keyway engineer, and today I'm going to explain how
in the last month I cleaned up the unit as the code that we used.
So it all started.
So basically this is a report from Jenkins, and there was one test, this one CPP unit
test SCVBA macro test failing on Windows.
We didn't know it was failing for quite some time, and we didn't really know what was the
problem.
It was failing every now and then.
And in the end it turned out that it was a problem that the teardown method disposing
this MX component was missing, and well, eventually it was fixed thanks to Noelle.
So I started to look at other places where these kinds of problems might happen in the
unit test.
So basically when we want to create a unit test class, these are the four main classes
that we can use.
So this one is the one inheriting directly from the library CPP unit test.
So this is the basic one you use to create a basic test, and basically it handles the
setup and teardown of the test.
Then if you want to, let's say, work with documents to load them and so on, you can
use also this library, this class, sorry, macro test.
And then when you want to work with XML, let's say you want to parse those XMLs, you can
use that class XML test tools.
And finally, we have a special class that we use to load and save documents, but we
only care if they fail or if they pass.
So the idea, because most of the classes that we have in unit tests, they normally inherit
from these two here, or in some special cases, they inherit from these three.
So basically the idea was to create kind of a wrapper for these two and then another one
for the other three.
So when I started to do it, well, a lot of duplicates were found, especially with the
setup and teardown methods.
So this could be removed in all the classes.
Then same for the X component, each class defined their own X component.
So now we only define it in the, you know, AP test class.
So this removed a lot of duplicate definitions.
And I also found that we had an special, you know, AP test class for CAG for no real reason.
So this was merged into the, you know, AP test class.
And actually we also, well, I also factor out other methods like for parsing PDF export
or execute a macro or create a temp copy.
So in, we have the impress and CAG modules.
You have their own methods to load and save files.
They were actually copy paste from this, from the filter test class.
And they were actually very, yeah, complicated to set up.
Basically you have to define all the formats that you wanted to use.
Then create this array with all the formats.
And then finally the load of the document looks something like this, where you have
to define the clipboard, the version.
And yeah, it was in the end really complicated and we already had a method for that.
And yeah, so basically now instead of returning a reference, a doccell reference, we just basically
load the local document and save and reload and makes it easier.
The problem before it was that after we were done with the test, we need to close the reference
and in some tests it was missing.
So that's not a problem anymore.
And also there were many places where this kind of chunk of code was used to save and
reload the document.
So they are gone.
There were many of them.
So now it's just one line to do that.
And the good thing is that now we always validate the files on a sport.
And in case there is a problem with the validator, we can also use the skip validation.
And there is also support for password, sporting and importing.
That's something that in the past was only available in writer module.
And yeah, the same for pass export.
SD, SW and SC, they use their own ways of handling this.
And we already have it in macro test.
So there was also a duplicate for that.
And right now we just do it like that.
And yeah, there were also operators that were duplicates.
Like for instance, this one for comparing colors.
There was also for comparing rectangles.
So they were already duplicates in prayers and call and writers.
So all of them are gone now.
And there was also a problem with this unit test.
The problem is that the way it works, it compares the calculations using openCL, enable and
disable.
And the problem is that before I found out, the comparison was always when it's enabled.
So the test didn't actually test anything.
And now that's fixed.
And also we also had some custom assets like this one as a formula equal, which can be
done as a string comparison and just using the get formula.
So yeah, in the end, a lot of duplicated code was dropped.
And yeah, that's it.
Thank you.
I think we still have time for maybe a quick question, if anyone.
Two minutes of questions.
Yes, sorry, yeah, how you brought it with the first slide.