Great. Okay, my name is Noel Grandin. I'm talking about the work that I've been doing
making Leber Office faster. We all know that Leber Office is a bit of an elephant. It's
a cute elephant, but it's still a bit of an elephant. We've got 10 million odd lines
of code, some of which is 20 years old. Practices that were perfectly acceptable 20 years ago
are a little bit trickier these days. Optimizations that made perfect sense back in the day are
not great anymore, and things have just changed around. For example, CPU memory bandwidth has
dramatically changed. When we ran about the error of the 486DX2, we suddenly saw a dramatic
shift in the speeds of main RAM versus the speeds of your main CPU. Up until that point,
you were looking at CPUs that could touch location and memory at about the same speed
as they could touch local cached memory. You wrote your algorithms around those sorts of
things, the DX2 changed things, and it only got dramatically worse after that. To the
point now where touching something in an L1 cache versus touching main memory can be anywhere
up to 50 times slower. Cache-friendly algorithms are now the new game in town. We now have
multiple cores. Everybody has multiple cores. It used to be that only people with vast sums
of money had machines with multiple cores or L1 CPU. Now, everybody has one. Locking
algorithms that made perfect sense because they only got touched by a handful of people
suddenly get exercised by everybody, and all sorts of interesting flaws come up. An interesting
note, the locking algorithms that were written back then, nobody actually knew if they were
truly solid or not because Intel's own engineers refused to commit to a cache-coherency protocol
until somewhere around the Pentium era. Up until then, they ruthlessly refused to say
anything about it, and if queried, they would just say that it wasn't something they had
locked down yet. You were kind of in the dark, so we end up where we end up. The good news,
I've been at this for a little while, and the worst and ugliest of the stuff is largely
gone. I mean, there's lots of performance issues left in LibreOffice, but the stuff
that used to hang LibreOffice up for minutes at a time, I've managed to nail most of that
down. There's still lots of places where it's slow, but it's not like heinously slow like
it used to be. The bad news is that the remaining stuff is really, really ugly. It's typically
the stuff that I just couldn't get my head around the first time, and some of it I've
looked at again, and I still can't get my head around it. Some of it I've been beating
on for a while, and I'm not making a lot of progress. But anyhow, the point of this exercise
is that you keep beating on things, and eventually either you break or it breaks. Hopefully,
get the right thing. So what worked out nicely? I'm going to talk today about what worked
out well and what worked out worse, because I think it's important that we share both
the successes and the failures, because I think you learn equally from both. So what
worked out nicely is reducing allocations, primarily with things like using standard
optional. So for example, if we were allocating a temporary data structure inside a subroutine,
I would switch that to declare that thing using standard optional, which does have the
downside that it takes up space on the stack even if you're not using it. But on the upside,
using the stack is about 100 times faster than allocating from main memory. The reasons
for that are because any time you touch main, any time you have to allocate out of the heap,
you have to take a lock. That leads to locking contention, et cetera, et cetera. You have
to talk to main memory because you're doing all sorts of stuff there, whereas the stack
is pretty much guaranteed to be in L1 cache. And so allocating out of there and deallocating
out of there is just ridiculously fast. So you can allocate quite large amounts of memory
before you start falling out of L1 cache from talking up to a couple of kilobytes here.
So throwing this sort of stuff at it worked well. The other thing I did was I've been
converting the usages of our internal OSL, colon, colon, mutex class to the standard
mutex class. Now, despite the naming here, we're talking about two different kinds of
mutexes. Our internal mutex is what's normally called standard recursive mutex, whereas
standard mutex is a non-recursive mutex, and it is considerably faster. In the uncontended
case, standard mutex is about 20 to 50 times faster than standard recursive mutex. In the
contended case, they tend to fall back to roughly being about the same cost. So given
that we run most of the time with very, very little concurrency, except for an occasional
use case here and there, standard mutex is a major win. The downside of standard mutex
is that if you use it and you try and lock that mutex a second time, you get a dead lock.
So you have to write your code quite carefully. Most of our usages converted very easily.
I did make a couple of mistakes, so there were a couple of regressions I had to fix,
and in a couple of cases, the regressions were simply unfixable, and so we backed it
back out again. But in general, it's a win. And as a side effect, standard mutex is allocation
free. It's literally just a single word in memory, and the common unattended case of
taking a standard mutex is what's called a CAS operation, compare and swap. So it's
really fast, and it doesn't use even less memory than OSL mutex, so a win all round.
What didn't work out? So we've got this SVL shared string pool. It's a really nice thing.
We use it in spreadsheets primarily, because spreadsheets often have many tens of thousands
of strings which are all identical across all the cells, so we store references to those
strings in the shared pool. Now, this shared pool gets hit very hard at load time, because
other people just implemented concurrent loading of spreadsheets. So we have this nice stuff
where we fire up multiple threads and load a bunch of different chunks of the spreadsheet
at the same time. This is great, speeds things up. But it was bottlenecking very hard in
SVL shared string pool. So I thought, oh, it's great. This is a hash map. Best case
scenario, we can stick a concurrent lock free hash map in there. I found this great
cuckoo hash map written by some very bright people, much smarter than myself. I stuck
it in there. Oh, it was great. It worked out brilliantly. It completely destroyed the bottleneck.
Spreadsheet loading went up by a factor of two or three, and I thought I had a great
win. And then the first bug came in where there was an edge case where it wasn't quite
the locking, because we were doing concurrent locking now. It was getting some weird edge
cases. We had two different maps. They were both talking in the same thing. So I then
had to fix those edge cases. I reworked it. We fixed those bugs. We reworked it again.
I fixed the bugs, and eventually got it working. And then another bright guy came in, Lubwash
came in and said, but wait. String pool is indeed a hotspot, but the hotspot is not actually
the hash map inside string pool, the hotspot is the upper case conversion. He improved
the upper case conversion. And by the time he was done improving the upper case conversion,
my concurrent hash map was making no difference whatsoever. So I had identified a hotspot,
but I hadn't identified the hotspot. So we backed it out, because there's no point in
keeping a highly complicated piece of equipment like that around. So I was very sad to see
it go. But I learned some stuff in the process. So no harm, no foul. And we backed it out
again, and we were back to being faster than we were before. Red line processing in writer,
which is our document editor section, is often very, very slow, especially if there's a ton
of red lines in a big document. And it's slow both loading and slow at runtime, because
when we're doing red lines, we often are doing massive amounts of adding and deleting to
data structures as we internally render and stuff. And so I thought I'd try and speed that
up. However, this is writer. Writer is the most cache-unfriendly program known to mankind.
It just wants to chase pointers all over RAM. It's data set once you have more than a sort
of 10-page document. You are completely falling out of L1 cache. So you have no chance of
getting cached algorithms. The data structures are inherently very, very complicated. Human
languages and documents just are. Consequences are we do pointer chasing. So we're constantly
loading a pointer and then following it to some other location in memory, which is guaranteed
to not to be an L1 cache. And then we're following that again to something else, which is also
not an L1 cache. And in the process, we've now blown apart our cache. So if we need the
first pointer again, that's also not an L1 cache. So we just take our tails around, enable
very slow processing. I did my best to fix this. And that involves trying to speed up
something called a node index and a content index. And I failed. I am now three levels
deep, fixing different things related to that. No end in sight. And I'm currently bottlenecked
on a piece of processing that I just don't understand. So that didn't work out. But in
the process, I now know a lot more about writer. And so I consider that a word. Thank you.
Thank you.