Hello everyone, I'm Saar Perakhtimish and I work for Collateral Productivity.
This talk will be about any interoperability improvements in LibreOffice Impress Tables.
So this is a screenshot from the bug report and let's talk about what was the problem
on the surface level.
On the right you can see how it appears in PowerPoint and on the left you can see how
it appears when it was opened by Impress, the pptx file exported by PowerPoint.
What we need to focus here is the rows pointed by the arrow are somehow shrunk when it was
opened in Impress and it wasn't immediately obvious.
If we look at how PowerPoint exports the table layout into pptx files, what we will realize
is it defines row heights.
So let's just focus on that part but it doesn't really define a total table height to fit
inside and while we are importing this row heights what we do is we first calculate what
does all of the rows, row heights add up to because we use the total table height to layout
the table.
So we calculate that by adding up each of the row heights and also we assign each row
with their own heights.
But turns out when this specific file is exported and if you look at row heights for the empty
rows they are correct, there is nothing wrong there but if you look at for instance the
one row that says cola it appears to have a row height of zero which doesn't really
make sense.
So now let's also something to mention here is if we start typing anything in one of the
empty rows there are no text properties actually imported from the pptx file they are somehow
lost in the process like the text when we start typing in the empty rows in the PowerPoint
one starts as a blue it has a blue color etc it has a different size but if we write it
in the impressed one it has just defaulted so it's black and 18 points.
So before understanding the problem we need to know a little bit about how impressed layouts
the table is basically fitted into a given total height but while doing so we also care
for what were the each row heights were so basically we need to know the total height
correctly because if it is smaller than some of the rows we basically happen to be shrinking
trying to shrink the table when that happens what the impressed tries to do is adjust the
row heights proportionally to what were they before and if there is text inside there is
a minimum height it can go to and when that happens it like in this case when that happens
since it can't shrink the line that says color further it shrinks the empty line because
it can to try to fit in that to the wrong table height also if you explore the pptx
output we will realize that the empty cell properties are exported in and paragraph run
properties we need to import that there is an already an implementation for that but
I'll discuss this a little bit later if you look at the problem in detail let's say what
we need to fix here is we need to somehow care for this problematic row heights that
during import which they don't have a height of zero but they are defined as so such and
empty cell we need to know the text sizes for empty cells too we need to do this from
n paragraph run properties also there was some previous range of pixels here that's
kind of altered the layout in code instead of the import code and there are some regressions that
messed up some table resizing functionality there we need to revert those changes and
so basically it turns out to be parboin tries to export desired row heights for instance if you
try to just pull arrow to zero while it has text in it it doesn't let you but it actually
saves it as such so in the end that creates a problem for us so to fix this what we can do
and what what I did was during the import before layouting the table into an area which how
impress usually does it we do a pre-layouting which is we just take the row sizes and we don't
give the layout in code any area to layout into and we let it layout itself so it basically
just looks at the row sizes and tries to expand them if they are smaller than possible and
then that gives us a final height that we can use to in successive layouting attempts so
we kind of correct the total lay table heights doing that and
then we also don't have the text properties for the empty rows so the problem there was
and turns out these text properties are actually imported into text nodes but
when there's new text is being typed they they actually inherit their properties from the
cells owns properties instead of the text nodes text nodes are just being dumped and any ones
are being created so to fix that we need to push the text properties from the n-paragraph
run properties into the SAS properties that themselves to make it work correctly
well to finish up with these fixes we were able to get rid of the problematic regression
causing code in the layout thing and we moved the conceptual fixes from there into the import code
making it possible to work correctly and additionally some unit tests were added to
make sure the n-paragraph run properties stayed correctly that covered those areas
thank you that's all from me