Cool. Hi everyone. My name is Balazs Wargo and I'm working at Olu
Tropia, GMB, and this presentation I would like to talk about WebAssembly, M-scripted
technology running the Collabra online in WebAssembly and the headless conversion stuff
in WebAssembly as well. So let's get started with the Collabra online in WebAssembly stuff.
So it was a common project with the Collabra. We were together with Tor and Mihai Shtan.
The goal was to approach offline document editing. On this slide there is a initial
script design for this. The goal was that when the connection breaks in a browser,
the application is activated and that contains the Collabra online server functionality.
And when the connection is restored, the document will be edited in the Collabra online server
again. I think Tor will talk about a little bit more. But to make it work, first we had
to build it in WebAssembly. For that, we are using the M-scripton compiler 2 chain. So
let's talk about that. The M-scripton is a complete open source compiler 2 chain to WebAssembly.
Using M-scripton you can compile C and C++ code or any other languages that uses LLVM
into WebAssembly and you can run it on the web or Node.js or other runtimes. The M-scripton
generates small and fast code and the default output format is WebAssembly and highly optimizable
executable format that runs almost as fast as the native code.
Little bit about M-scripton 2 chain. The main tool is the M-scripton compiler frontend.
This is a drop-in replacement for a standard compiler like ECC or C-lang. The E-MCC uses
K-lang and LLVM to compile to WebAssembly. E-MCC also emits JavaScript that provides
API support to the compiled code. The JavaScript can be executed by Node.js or from within
HTML in a browser. There are more information there, but you can read that. About porting
code to use M-scripton. Support for portable C and C++ code is fairly comprehensive and
supported for the C standard library, C++ standard library, and the exception, etc.
It's very good and also the OpenGL supports. Okay, the multithreading is supported but
depends on the shared array buffer which is still being standardized and implemented by
browsers. Now let's see the porting, how it works in case of columbra online. The building
for wasm, the M-scripton is a bit immature and some projects needed to patch in to make
it work. First we need to build the bro-office core. With M-scripton, earlier the best was
to use the feature wasn't in branch but nowadays it's working with upstream. Mustard with
the Qt 5 framework and then it needed to build the columbra online. Dependence is the ZFTD
libraries, the poco library requires two patches to make it work. Then it's necessary to build
the columbra online code and then linking all the binaries and executables together.
Linked-in-wasm executable uses a lot of memory and without optimizations or with the O1 flags
it should work anywhere but there are different kind of flags like the O2, earlier flags which
is the default and some link time optimization happens that uses very much RAM and because
of that it causes segmentation error so we are using the O1 flag in case of online and
also in case of the LibreOffice core. A little bit about running but Tor will talk about
it more. Structure is quite similar to the columbra office iOS and Android applications.
There are one differences that in case of mobile the C++ code is what transfers and
then that then loads the HTML page into WebKit in which the JavaScript runs in the WebAssembly
application the other way around the web page is naturally the one that is loaded and then
the JavaScript code then starts running the C++ code as a WebAssembly. You can see an
image about it, it's a document tile in the browser, it's running in WebAssembly, there
are some Dactu's where you can debug. It's working but still needs some optimization
work which is in progress. If you have an image in the document it's quite slow but
we are working on that as well. Let's talk about a little bit some another WebAssembly
work at Allotropia. We have also worked on a headless conversion product. Last time in
LibroCon there was a little demo about it but it wasn't completely a headless conversion
but now I make a video about it and let's see how it works now. We are not using the
Qt 5 framework anymore and we are also using the unique HTML which is created in the Libro
V score by Emscripton. Let's hope the video works. It's working. This is the very basic
HTML page but it can make any kind of HTML work. There is just a button. You can select
multiple files and using the convert tool arguments, convert it the document and you
can convert it any kind of format that the Libro V score can do. Documented and downloaded
and you can see it in the browser as well. There is a common line in the browser where
you can see the results. But the HTML page can be edited and that's a future plan to
make it much more nicer. Also some future plans at Allotropia we would like to call in
a function called from JavaScript and creating for that UI. Emscripton provides various options
for connecting normal JavaScript and compact code which range from functions to call compiles,
C++ from JavaScript and the versa. So to accessing environment variables from compiled codes.
These options are the web IDL, binder and the mbind. It's binding between C++ and JavaScript
and all in C++ code and it is to be used in a natural manner from JavaScript. That's also
our future plan. I think that's all. Thank you for that.
One minute for questions, maybe one question and an answer if there's any.