I am a software engineer at Colabora.
I just recently joined them.
This is my first conference and I am not very good in English, so forgive me if I say something
wrong.
I will speak about the footnotes in multi column sections.
I worked on this last year, a year ago.
I thought it can be an interesting problem.
Oh, I had to go back.
So I got a back ticket to a fix and it was a very simple ticket at first sight.
It was only just one line text and some way the writer displayed it as two pages and why
the word was displayed just one page.
Beside the one line text there was a footnote and its section has two columns and there
was a continuous section break.
First I thought it was a problem about the section break, some way it changed to a page
break or something like that.
But that was an instinct.
It was a strange thing why the footnote and the column were needed.
If I deleted any of them, then the writer changed to one page and it was okay.
It was changed why it is needed.
So I started to debug to find where it's become two page and I found the problem in the layout
in calculation and there was even a comment about it stating that the footnote container
causes to maximize size in this case.
This function to maximize function will calculate if we have to maximize the column frame, the
whole section frame to the whole page.
And it has several conditions like is footnote at end and is end note at end.
They are check boxes on the GUI named collect at end of text and call at end of section
for end notes.
They are diverse falls in this case.
Oh, the hasfollow isn't matter now.
It was falls in this case too.
But there was another function that contains footnote container.
I checked this function and this function just blindly check if the section have column
frame tried that has a footnote container frame tried and if it has one, then it returned
the first one it found.
So it seems the function was directly righted like this way.
So the question was why do we want to break a page in this case?
I even checked the git who changed it or something like that.
But it was in the very first commit I could reach in the initial import at 2000 years.
And nobody changed it.
And I was even wonder why this many condition is needed.
Not just the first one I found, but the note collect at end is still needed for it.
For this I had to analyze the frames how they work.
So I listed the frames related to footnote some case.
The footnote frame is for one footnote entity.
It can contain a text frame.
And this can be in a footnote container frame.
And that frame contains a list of footnotes.
It's important it's not two-dimensional list.
It's just a simple list that it can display.
And this footnote container frame can be in a page frame or a column frame.
So what is important in it that the footnote container frame does not really support columns.
It just a I could say just one column of footnotes and that's all.
But we can put this container frame in any of the column frame event.
So if we put this container frames in every column frame then it will seems like if we
support oh sorry it's like we support multi columns.
So in one case we want footnote like multi columns as like it in the word.
In the other case we want if we don't check the collected and text we want the footnote
to be at the page end.
In the other case we want the footnote to be in the columns end in physical as we say
in the display.
And it can be true only if the column end is equal to the page end.
So that's why they maximize the size of the column to the page size.
In our case it's not a good idea because in my test case there was only one footnote
and it doesn't need to be multi columns.
But if we wouldn't do this what I showed in the previous slide there could be a contradiction
like I made a test document.
There is two section.
I checked the collected end of text which means I want the footnote be after the section
end.
There is two column at the first section and three column at the second section.
It's very good in this way but if we would change the collected end of text we would
uncheck this.
I mean we want all of this footnote at the end of the page then how many columns we want?
It's a contradiction.
We can't say that two or three because any of them could be wrong.
So what we should need we should be able to have column children for the container frame
because it's not should be, it must be, it just should be like words able to have indifferent
number of columns at page as many as in the text.
So we should have the ability for the users to choose how many columns we want in the
footnote but we should keep the ability to, that's all, okay, sorry, it's almost end.