So this talk will be a follow-up to the one I did at the LibreOffice conference last year
in September.
That was about content controls in a writer in general.
And some of the follow-up work was expected, some of that was more like a surprise.
So a couple of incremental improvements appeared in the past half year.
So it seemed like a good idea to overview where we are compared to where we were in
September.
So for those who don't know me, I'm Miklos Weina, I'm from Hungary.
I used to be very much involved in the writer RTF import-export.
So much these days about, I'm still focused on writer, I work for Collabra.
And for content controls, for the scope of this talk, we talk about this rich text content
controls.
It's like it's for fulfilling.
We used to have these input fields in writer already where you can provide some placeholder
text and you can mark that this is the place of the document where you can type when you
fill in some form.
But one big limitation of that was that it was beyond its own fields and fields can't
have formatting, so it was really just for plain text.
And where writer really shines is more like there can be a rich text.
So we want something that provides rich text, so that's where you can have rich text content
controls.
The Oaxima specification calls these structured documents tags, but it's really the same thing.
They are user interface calls these content controls, so we also call them content controls.
And the way it's structured is that you can, once you have paragraph text, then you can
have multiple text portions inside that.
So let's say you have some text, normal text, and then some bold text, and then again normal
text, then we split up the paragraph text to three portions, the normal one, the bold
one, and again the normal one.
And for fields, the restriction was that you can't have multiple of these text portions
inside that's two if you are there.
And content control support this, so you can have multiple portions.
Although they are limited to a single paragraph, at least this inline content controls that
I'm talking about.
So you can't have a content control starting at some random point in the document and ending
at some random point.
Perhaps you know that you can do that with bookmarks.
It might start inside the table and outside the table, and field marks can provide the
same thing.
Content controls are intentionally limited to be inside a single paragraph.
So we enforce that when you create them, we enforce this when you edit them, we enforce
this during exporting to Docx and ODT.
So this is an invariant that we want to maintain.
Another complexity is that it's possible to do nothing for this.
So when you look at how we write this in ExoMod, then ExoMod elements naturally support nesting.
And we call this well-formed nesting.
So the outer content control starts, and then the inner one starts, and then it's a requirement
that the inner one will finish, and then the outer one will finish.
So you can do nesting, but you can do the start one, start two, finish the first, and
finish the last, similar to what you know from HTML, for example.
So we want to support this setup, that you can do nesting, but not in a random order.
And you can include multiple text portions, but not random positions with start and then
what constrain that they are in a single paragraph.
And if you have fields, then fields typically have some kind of instruction text, like
commands, and there is the field result.
Content controls are more like annotations and a piece of text.
So you have some start and end, and you can have a bunch of properties on top of that.
You will see you can give it a title, you can give it an alias, you can define the type
and so on.
So the rich text is the simplest type, where you just say that you can fill in something
here and if the task is like provide your one-liner command from this presentation,
then you say it was really bad, like really, really.
So you select the really and mark it bad, because it was really bad.
But you can do multiple paragraphs, you can write a novel on how bad that was.
So that was rich text.
And so somehow the picture is missing the top pixels,
so you missed the whole point.
But I will explain what you should see there.
It's called, I think, the Veruse and the Interface cause this title, but in the markup we call
this alias, but it's the same sign.
The point is that you have some complex form and you are supposed to fill in the date,
the date and the date and finally the date.
And of course they mean that that means you are registering your company and there was
a date when you created the company, there was a date when you filed the papers for it
and there was a date when the first employee was hired and sent in.
But it's just the date, so it's very confusing to fill that in.
And what content controls can provide is that when you enter that content control, then
there is a small pop-up similar to when you added headers and you get the name of the
paste style and so on.
So you get some tool tape explaining what exactly you are filling in.
That might be half, so let's say the text would normally just say that you need to enter
information about the, let's say, the birth data.
But that means that they want the birth location and the birth date and then when you enter
the content control, they can give you this hand so that it's a bit easier.
So the output, the field inform might conform to what was expected, how some regulation
is expected.
But when you try to enter it as a mere mortal, you are actually able to fill it in because
you don't need to look up some time pages of documentation, how to fill in that form.
You go to the form and you get enough helpful context information so that you can just do
that.
So these aliases and tags were initially missing on the right-hand side and now we stop on
it.
Then one other problem was that I mentioned you can have multiple text portions inside
the single content control.
So what you see on the above screenshot is that we have an X character, then a new line
break, so we kind of hack it around.
Technically, it's still a single program, but you see it's multiple lines.
And then we even define some tab stop and then tab portion.
So technically, it's still a single program, but you see that this is at least three different
text portions.
And we used to take each and every text portion and then it's PDF widgets for that.
So in this case, when you export this to PDF and you wanted to fill in the PDF form, then
you got three different pages, which is a nonsense, which was not the intention.
So in case originally the placeholder text would be multiple portions there in the right
turn, then we still take the bounding rectangle of the content control and just omit a single
widget as probably the user would expect.
Then another thing is the primary use case we had in mind was that you create some editable
writer document and at the very end, you export that to PDF and the actual form filling will
probably happen in some PDF reader.
But you might also have some slightly different workflow where you mark most of the document
as read only and then you can have the editable document handed out to users and they actually
fill in the form in the writer.
Now the trouble is that in case we made the document read only, then you can't fill in
the form because you change these content controls and they are part of the document
and the whole document is read only.
So that content control is also read only.
Now this was working with input fields before.
They had various problems, but this bit was working.
They knew that they are an exception from this general read only.
It was possible to fill in input fields.
Now we do the same.
And we can have this setup that the whole document is read only, but the content control
can be still added here.
Another thing was that if you look at what Word provides for VBA, if you want to manipulate
these content controls, then they have an understanding of what is the list of content
controls in the document.
This can be very handy in case you want to have some macro that automatically processes
the already filled in document.
There are other ways to do that, but one way is that you write some macro that will extract
all the filled in results from the document.
For that, they can just go to the first content control, the second one query, how many content
controls you have in the document, and so on.
But on the writer side, this is really just a formatting on a program.
So you would have to scan the entire document to find out if you have any content controls
at all.
So we don't have this random access to content controls.
Initially we ignore this VBA problem, but when Justin was trying to build a VBA compact
layer on top of content controls, then he found that there is no random access to content
controls.
So you can't do this without scanning the whole document, which can be very slow, so
this is not great.
And we discovered that actually footnotes already provide this.
That's also kind of formatting on some piece of paragraph tags.
And that has this manager that will track as footnotes are created and deleted, and
then you can quickly get a list of all the footnotes in the document.
So why can't we do the same for content controls?
And yeah, you can do that.
So now there is some Star Basic access, or actually Uno API access, that's visible in
basic.
And also there is a VBA compact layer on top of that where you can query how many content
controls you have.
If you fill in these alias things, then you can even say that I want to jump to the birth
date content control without saying that is the third one.
So if you insert something in between, then it won't break.
So this manager provides that what's necessary here.
Another thing was that initially when I was adding dropdowns, I wanted to incrementally
extend what's available in rich text content controls.
So the idea was that in case there are list items for this content control, you know that's
then probably a dropdown.
But there is complexity there.
You can have dropdowns, okay?
You can have dropdowns, and you can have combo boxes.
And it's possible that you can't say which one it is.
If it has list items, it might be any of that.
And also it turns out it's valid to have a dropdown with no items.
So that's what you see there.
Notice that's working.
We explicitly track if that's a combo box or a dropdown.
And then you can have both types.
We enforce that if it's possible to just choose one item from a complete list, or you can
also have free form text there.
And also in case some existing document for whatever reason has no list items, then we
don't break that.
And we don't implicitly turn that to rich text content control just because it has no
list items.
I think this is the last one.
So, Hossein was doing lots of testing on content control.
And of course the first thing he was trying is some Persian text.
And of course it was breaking.
I think it has three pieces.
So one was the positioning.
If you have the dropdown arrow on the left-hand side now for RTO text, that means that if
you take the position of the whole bounding rectangle, then you need to shift that to
the left to have the correct position.
So fixing up the position based on the direction of the text frame.
So the paragraph was one thing.
Then also what you render inside the bounding rectangle for the arrow button and for that
frame that needed fixing.
And the last thing is that if you see a button, then you might have the silly idea to click
on the button.
And you expect that something happens.
But we need to do this heat testing to decide if you clicked on the button or not.
And if you do that, then we need to handle this correctly for RTO versions, RTO.
So that's no more working.
So this is it.
There was some polish.
Since the LibreOffice conference is still what the feature set it provides is still
something that meant to be one-to-one possible to map to the word feature set.
We tried to fully save this to ODF without any loss.
You can export that to a PDF.
There are these various types.
You can see a few types there.
And basically more properties are now added, some small editing improvements.
And it's a little bit easier to script that now.
So that's what we have.
Thanks for listening.
I hope you enjoyed propagate test testing times.
Thank you.