A very quick update on how we use C++, C++ standards in LibreOffice to finish off this
afternoon.
So yeah, we're still using C++17.
Almost there's one thing that keeps cropping up.
I think Noah tried to sneak it in twice and Mike once.
This is this unsuspecting standard from cars thing where you have a string view of characters
and you want to get an integer or floating point value out of that and there's a standard
function for that.
Unfortunately, it's not in the standard C++8 or only in 8 and only in 11 for floating point
values which we don't have, we're still stuck at 7.
So people keep trying to add that to the UNO libraries and I as the gatekeeper of these
UNO libraries which we never want to change because then we have these maintenance problems.
I keep banging them back.
We don't need that.
We don't need to add anything there because we'll have C++17 functionality for it anyway
and I keep saying that for years now.
At one point we'll get there, I'm pretty sure.
Just C++17 for now still.
But of course we're making use of whatever gets available, becomes available in the latest
standard so that C++20 is out for two, three years now and C++23 is almost finished.
It's the standardizing stuff takes its time but it's quite frozen by now.
And then there's always these small things mostly in the standard library that are easy
to approximate and then we usually make use of those ideas in our own code and have one
header file, one include file where we either use the original alias to our O3TL namespace
or implement our own approximation which we then throw out once we have that available.
So this is the span thing similar to the string view where you just have a range of values,
start and length.
Then these comparison functions, they are very interesting if you don't know them, then
check them out.
So you always have a hard time comparing two integers in C and C++ if they are of different
types signed and unsigned and you get surprising results.
And finally in C++20 they decided to come up with ugly syntax functions but they will
do the right thing whatever types you throw at them and we have at least one place where
we use them by now for good measure.
And another example is these standard unreachable magic function that they introduced.
We still have a macro for that to approximate it.
So if there is a place in your code where you can't reach so a default in a switch and
you don't want to return any nonsense from that and the compiler would warn you that
you don't have a return statement there then just add an unreachable there to tell the
compiler this is impossible to reach anyway.
Then there is bigger features or beyond library features that we try to make use of one way
or another.
For example the C++20 const eval similar to const expression where you have something
that should be computed at compile time and constexpr is do it at compile time if possible
otherwise do it at runtime and const eval is forcing you to do it at compile time.
The trick there is if you have a function that has some research and you make that function
and const eval function then if the assert would not hold then you get a compilation
error instead of just a runtime error later on or not even an error if you build with
the assert disabled and we make use of that in some places like this.
We have this color class and I think Noel again at one point tried to get rid of the
ambiguity whether it has alpha channel or not so we now have a constructor that wants
to make sure you pass in some value that doesn't have an alpha channel in there so we have
an assert in there and if we have const eval in the latest compilers then we use it and
then we would get a compiler at compilation time error already if you pass in some value
that does have an alpha channel after all so that helped the improvement of the change
in the code from the old semantics to the new semantics.
So we have a if around that if have Cpp const eval then use const eval otherwise we use
constexpr and in our config script we have lots of checks whether we can use const eval
and unfortunately only Clang by now even the latest compiler versions we have five checks
in there for bugs that we discovered with all these const eval implementations and Clang
the latest one has all its bugs sorted out but GCC and the Microsoft compiler still can't
use it so that shows how if you have a feature sheet of what the compilers support and there
are ticks for that don't trust that too much if you then actually try to use it you run
into all kinds of issues and then of course coming up is issues there even bigger way
you can't use some ifdef trickery or some include file value approximate things because
two things that come to my mind are the concepts in C++20 which would make code really more
readable but which is hard to do in some macro way.
We have one place I think by now where we have again around this requires thing we have
an ifdef or if we have a C++20 implementation that supports it there is one place where
we have some function that internally does some dangerous dynamic casting and you know
proxies didn't support dynamic casting so I wanted to make sure that we never use that
function on a template type that is you know could be a proxy so I came up with this wonderful
requires cloth there too if you have a new enough compiler to get that sorted out at
run time and otherwise we ignore it an even bigger thing is modules and I guess we will
have to wait for others to come up with real implementations of that or real world usage
to see how we would make use of them.
But even if these features are out in the distant future in some cases still what we
already can do is try to force the compilers hard to run our code and demonstrate to them
that they what bugs they have worry what bugs are in the standard library implementations
if they introduce new things so what I do is opt into this thing to use whatever compiler
you use with the latest C++ version that compiler implements which is typically C++23 by now
and then have a big matrix of platforms and compilers and libraries run time standard
run time libraries to build on and find all kinds of interesting bugs whenever I update
one of those things and then mail the people mail Jonathan that he introduced something
new in the standard C++ that doesn't make clang happy and so forth and these people
are happy that we are the guinea pigs for them and that's it.
Time for beer.
I guess we have time for questions if there are any questions.
Who do you contact if you find a bug in the microsauce compiler?
They do have a web form now that you can fill in and I think I even got a response one.
Mike Agansky brought that up.
One more question since we're at the end of the track.
What's the status of modules in compilers because as far as I know only Visual Studio
does it and does it kind of sort of?
No, I think they're all three by now in their hedge trunk versions.
They support them, I think they claim it works but I didn't ever try it.
A module is a new way of organizing so that you don't have this issue of having all these
includes that you need to include.
This is like precompiled, a newer version of precompiled headers actually.
Yeah, that sums it up.
Thanks again.