Let me start. This talk is partly about the same thing as the previous talk, so repetition
is the mother of invention or mother of what's it called, mother's to the orumest. And here,
so as Balash mentioned, the problem that this is supposed to solve is that if you are editing
some document in Collabara Online, and for instance, on your laptop and then the connection
breaks because you are going into a tunnel or something else happens, and then you can
just seamlessly, eventually, it will start using the local bus instead in the browser
and the same document that has been downloaded without you knowing into the browser's memory,
not to your file system. Yeah, so the solution is that. And of course, implementing this
actually will be quite a problem or quite hard, but we are already working on it and
I assume it will be successful. And then when the connection comes up again, you can, or
the document will be uploaded to the Collabara Online server and everything will continue
and then using the online server. And I'm using the name Cobosm for this or actually
was Thorsten who invented that name, I think. And what we don't think is a solution at least
for some customers is to install Collabara Office locally because there are situations
where you are not allowed to install third party software very easily. And if you did
that and wanted to be prepared for this connection in Collabara Online, you would have to keep
downloading the document yourself anyway all the time and then start Collabara Office locally
separately. And what is WebAssembly? Well, this is what Balazs already told you. One
thing that I guess could be mentioned is that this WebAssembly runs in the same sandbox
as a web page and it has access to the same things that JavaScript has access to or more
importantly doesn't have access to anything that JavaScript doesn't have access to. So
it's quite safe. It can't read any random files on your disk and so on. And WebAssembly
doesn't even have access to the, direct access to the DOM, to the HTML page, but it can easily
run on JavaScript in a way that has access. So that's not that important. There are also
awesome environments that are not in the browser. I don't remember what it's called. There's
something, well, at least one such exists. And WebAssembly is supported in most current
servers. Firefox, Chrome, Safari, Edge. Are there any others? Mscripten, toolchain, is
this Clang-based toolchain. I'm not sure if the C and C++ library are like, are they considered
part of Mscripten or not? Probably yes. And this C library contains much of normal Linux
or POSIX functionality. Also, threading using pthreads. And there's even a in-memory file
system that you can use to pass files from building the most application into the application
at runtime. Some of these very traditional Unix functionalities are a bit oddly implemented,
which can be surprising. For instance, pipes, which are like 50 years old and have always
worked the same way in Unix in most days, suddenly are non-blocking, which was a surprise
to us. And they use a very specific version of Mscripten currently. We could try to update
on new one. I think it will work also. But this selecting what version of Mscripten to
use and what toolchain options to use has been quite complicated. There are so many
different versions to choose from, and they all have slightly different issues or functionality
differences. So once you have something that works, you tend to stick to it. And the code
version application, it contains all the relevant C++ code of LibreOffice Core itself and also
all the external libraries that LibreOffice uses, plus then the C++ code of LibreOffice,
I mean, Collabara Online. And then the same JavaScript code as in Collabara Online is also
used of course. And that is what provides the UI. And compared to the typical Mscripten
examples, you see if you start reading about Mscripten, in this case the Wasm code doesn't
do any UI itself, but all UI is handled by this JavaScript layer. And the application
structure is quite similar to the iOS and Android apps. They are built in quite a similar
way, constructed in a similar way. And just like in these apps, instead of having several
processes, there is just one process and multiple threads. And here you can see how the Collabara
Online is constructed and then they communicate using WebSockets. And in COBASM, instead of
several processes, we have multiple threads and as such the message passing between them
is more or less the same as in the web-based Collabara Online server. And this is actually
something that should be eventually improved. As you see, instead of all this message passing,
we could just simply call the function directory that will handle the message eventually. So
that should be faster and easier or let's say simpler on the system.
Here are some pointers how to build this thing. You first compile LibreOffice Core and then
the online dependencies and then online. And if you need to run this through a web server
because you can't use these shared array buffers if you load a page from a file URL. And here
is a sample screenshot where I actually then disconnected the internet and it still continued
working. And that's it. Thanks to Allotropia for doing this initial work and making LibreOffice
work as a WebSockets application. I'm not sure why I put this thing on this page but...
Well, yeah, it was Allotropia who figured out what versions work and so on. So that's all.