I will start, hopefully. 30 slides and 10 minutes. Excellent. So, there's a next button
here. Eventually we'll get there. Good. So, a good number of things changed over lockdown
and perhaps you're interested in that. So, Collabra Online is an amazing piece of software
and built on LibreOffice technology. And one of the things that we really, really you'd
have noticed changed, I guess, in lockdown was that we binned this dialogue saying, this
is an unsupported version of whatever. Yeah, we thought this was a good way to encourage
people to consider supporting the project and getting something supported and contributing
back but it turned out everyone hated it. Even I hated it. So, there you go. Even though
it did a good thing. So, we got rid of that and after a large discussion which doesn't
bear repeating, yeah, we then decided to use the Collabra brand to make people aware that
you could get something. So, one of the biggest and most significant changes, I guess, is
removing that and providing then a free version that anyone could deploy at scale without
asking anyone which is kind of cool if you like that sort of thing. And, yes, there's
a bit of a catch-22 there and we unrounded. So, the things that changed, I guess, is now
public unlimited online binaries and we also published all of our SDK documentation, Docker
image build instructions and just got a lot more open. And Italo, wherever he has came
up with this inspired umbrella brand for LibreOffice technology, I guess, that's, yeah, this platform
for personal productivity. So, quite a lot of sort of end user facing change there and
obviously making those two things work together nicely and be friendly is important. So, we
spent lots of time putting, you know, LibreOffice technology logos into the here and there.
Those are such and next cloud office as well. I guess I got these two the wrong way around.
But anyway, and everything was beautiful except no one could see it at TDF. Oh, I need to
move this way, right, out of the frame. Sorry. Because Gillem is a genius and the cleverly
locked down the CSP rule. So, you couldn't actually fetch the logo from your client because
it was forbidden. So, we then had to implement a whole load of work to get the server to
download and then reserve the image. So, there's some kind of funky HTML proxy built into
Cloudbron line for this image. So, anyway, it gets out there now. And so, when you click
on it, you get these nice credits that tell about all the good work that everybody has
done. So, hopefully, there's even pictures you might feature if you're careful. And there's
some more branding there planned. So, we have a welcome stream that comes up now and shows
you the differences and we'd love to get this accelerated. Sadly, we're a bit busy at the
moment, which is good, all good for LibreOffice. So, I just wanted to talk quickly about some
of the things that we've done because that's quite fun in the technology underneath. So,
there you go. Look at this lovely logo. So, one of the things then is to make the blockchain
useful and which means providing money to us to do LibreOffice hacking, obviously. And
so, we got rid of this really deeply annoying dialogue and which was triggered by all these
clever people that accidentally had typed in the far right corner of their spreadsheet
once and made the size apparently larger, which was really good. Hopefully, lots of
people enjoy that. Content controls. So, this is just Microsoft has many strata of content
controls. Every idea has been tried many times. And these are, I guess, the latest one and
say, McClosh has done a fantastic job. I think he had a talk for realness to implement those
so that we can do all sorts of forms and things and then starting to add things on top. There's
color theming, lots of beautiful interoperability work, chart data tables. Everyone likes pictures
or some people like pictures, others like numbers. So, well, you can have both on the
same screen and hopefully see it in your slides, which is kind of cool. Yeah, DeepAll. Yes,
built-in language translation. Just sort of unique to get your German into English or
vice versa. And yeah, that's all good fun and hopefully then with formatting of some
degree as well. You can imagine perhaps the problems of turning this into HTML, translating
it and then trying to get your styles back at the other end. And anyone that wants to
help improve that, I'm sure will be thrilled to have some help making it better. So, that's
all good fun. What else? I missed the button. No? Good. And then there's whole loads of
things we've done in Collabor Online. So, one of the things I'm excited about is the
language tool. So, people ask me, what about your artificial intelligence story? And of
course, we need some intelligence around. That's for sure. If only we had some. And a robot
seems like a good way of providing it, reproducible, repeatable. Anyway, the wonderful people at
LanguageTool have managed to build an open source business sort of off the back of Grammarly's
market positioning and price setting skills. And so, they're making money selling open
source things here, built around the open source language tool and contributing loads
of good code. And there will be some pots down. So, it's thrilling to be able to integrate
with them and to get much better grammar checking. And of course, you can run LanguageTool on
your premise. So, you're not sending it all to some random other server. You're sending
it to your own random other server, which is good. So, that's all fun. And then of course,
the Duden corrector has been integrated with people like this. Actually, these are both
German companies, I believe. So, your genitives are safe with us. But anyway, so, a similar
web service there and that can be integrated. Have reflowing your text, positioning beautiful
boats for core, you know, in just the right place, you know. It's very, very important
to get your images nice. Yeah, it is. You can see the anchor. Yeah, it's one of these
metaphors that's probably not used. It's like the floppy disk anchor, you know. I don't
know how many people sail. But anyway, sailors get their images in good places. And putting
that into the web UI. And there's some chunk of accessibility work and just ease of use
stuff around the formula entry building on Qua-Lons work to make formula entries JS dialogable,
which is all good. That came for our mobile thing. The accessibility checker, I guess
we brought that to the online suite so you can see all of the many failings that you
have in your accessibility. And then maybe fix them, which would be good. And then lots
of work from, I guess, Shimon primarily, but Pedro and others on bringing JS dialogues,
more JS dialogues. So having the dialogues, again, using Qua-Lons WX widgets like welding
framework, we can move these and run them on the client which brings a whole load of
prettiness and performance and accessibility improvements. What else? Deltas. So we also
the way Clabber Online works is it has tiles. It splits your documents into 256 pixel square
tiles, which at least in the past I was told is optimal for some GPUs on mobile phones.
And it seems like a good size. So, yeah, so we do that. But we now use Deltas for that
as well. So as you type your hello or H something, it will find just the H and then it will compress
that. And previously we did this with PNGs. And PNGs, well, they use deflate. Well, as
you can see, really bad. Not only is it slow, it also produces big compressed data. So there
you go. So Z standard is much better and we do that now. And yeah, thanks to Facebook
for their contribution to digital sovereignty and control of your data. That's fantastic.
So what else? Various new exciting dialogues, property things, innumerable PDF options built
in. So new export stuff. Some great things there from the team. What else? Online embedded
video playback. If you have embedded videos, you can drop them in and get them. Of course,
Kadex are the hidden nightmare of any kind of video. It's a disaster area. But we just
use what your browser has. So let's hope your browser is doing well. And luckily, browsers
seem to have reasonably good Kadex supports. Somehow, what else can I say? Come heck with
us. It's cool. Talk to us. Get involved. And the cool kids are all using LibreOffice technology.
So you should be too, if you're not. There's a LibreOffice hack fest this Monday and Tuesday.
So that's not tomorrow, but the day is after at the business and technology incubator.
So if you want to be incubating technology, you can get B2K working. It's a great place.
And you can take a photograph and then you'll have all the details you need. And in March,
we're having something in Clare College, Cambridge. Again, you're welcome. There will be a LibreOffice
hack fest there. Come make us open source rock with us. And that's about it. Thank you.
Any questions? OK. 47 seconds for questions. I lie. 42. Never mind. Well, thank you very
much. Grab me a beer afterwards. Thank you.