Okay, the next one is me. So somebody else has to watch the time and drag me off the
stage. Welcome to a bit of an update on LibreOffice accessibility, in this particular case, PDF
accessibility. My name is Thorsten. We're running our own company here, Consultancy,
and some products around LibreOffice. This work here has been funded by a customer, so
it's always great to have people paying for improvements in LibreOffice. I'm very grateful
for that. That's why we can present this today.
Quickly, there is a difference between document and application accessibility. So accessibility
can be many, many things from the Wikipedia, makes products, devices, services usable by
people with disabilities. And of course, the main thing that needs to be accessible with
LibreOffice is the software itself. And there's been a lot of work ongoing over many years
there, but also what LibreOffice produces, the documents, also need to be accessible.
So that's more on the services side of the products, the outcome there.
Application accessibility, as I said, lots of work has been ongoing. There's been two
tenders from the foundation. Both of them went to Hypera. And I think one of them, I
think there's still a bit of work ongoing there. The first one definitely is finished.
That resulted in some cleanups and some checks and also some build time checking that all
the dialogues have all the prerequisites set so that the GUI remains is and remains accessible.
And the second tender is for actually being able to, like, enabling to run and also not
breaking it going forward with the platform accessibility APIs so that the screen readers
and other tools actually work with LibreOffice and make that testable and lock that down.
So that was some LibreOffice. And Jock's Corner advertising. So LibreOffice is looking
for some accessibility engineer. There's a drop posting there. And if you're interested,
apply about now. I think the deadline is sometime next week, I believe. Closing that. Or tell
your friends and family. So document accessibility, that's what I'm focusing on. Relevant standards.
And we're talking about PDF here. Some web content. Accessibility guidelines. That's
about HTML mostly. But much of that also applies to other document types. And then there's
the PDF UA, the PDF universal accessibility standard that mandates lots of things. Mostly
meter data that is out of the document so that suitable tools like screen readers can
extract that and say, okay, I need to read this, but I don't need to read that. Or for
images that there's a description, like a textural description of what this image contains.
There's a nice overview and an actionable list of checks that you can go through in
the so-called Matterhorn protocol. Yes. And if you pass that checklist, then you can be
pretty sure that your document is accessible. And there's validators for that. The pack
one and the veri-pdf pack is closed source or source available or something if you ask.
And veri-pdf is a proper open source. Okay. So what did we do? We fixed a lot of bugs.
There are still some bugs left here. About 14 when I checked last. So anybody who's interested
in having accessibility bugs fixed, give them a call. And that's what we did. So quite a
chunk of things that still had to be fixed after so very many years at the, let's say,
core level. Like actually getting metadata that was already there in the document down
into the PDF in the correct way. So like getting the information down. That was the first thing.
So that the PDF export could write it to disk and then also getting it in the proper way.
So like at the right position in the metadata structure. Not forgetting something. Not mistyping
some tags, et cetera. Yeah. And it's quite across the board what we did there. And I
can say that for reasonably complex documents actually were passing now the accessibility
checks like those validators. So that was actual bug fixing. And we also had to add
a few features. The most important one is adding the stack-related flag for flies. So
if you check the latest, I think we missed 7.4. I'm not sure. But in any case, a recent
master. If you insert in writer, if you insert a text frame on the options page, you get
a new check box that says decorate. So you can now say this content here is not important
for the document. This is just some whatever coat of arms for your family. Or it's just
a background picture or something that is not really important for the content. It's
just decoration. And that was not saved. Also not saved in ODF. So that actually was a feature
we had to be able to so users could say, okay, this is not important. That is not important.
But this is. And then being able to save and reload that. And some UX improvements on the
accessibility checker dialogue. Which was the work from Colabra. Good stuff there. Also
the third one, the online accessibility checker. If you enable experimental features, then
you get the extras menu. You get some automatic checking thing. Which is this one. Automatic
accessibility checking. And if you do that, you get this kind of counter there. Like how
many more accessibility bugs you still need to check or fix. So that part of the toolbar.
And so we made the actual dialogue a little bit nicer to use. So in this case, not making
it modal. Because if it's modal, you can't interact with the document. So you get a warning.
Like in this case, no alt text for the image. So you want to kind of select the image and
set the alt text. But for that, you need to close the dialogue. So if you have more than
let's say ten things there, then you'll forget where you were. So it's much nicer if it's
not modal. And yeah, and also have some rescan buttons. So it's kind of orthogonal to this
automatic online check. Right. So that was that. As I said, in a decent shape now. Far
from done. But it starts to be usable. Future plans is some user experience. So the goal
should be to be in power with Word. So really not having users click four times every single
image that they need to put an alt text in. Which is really annoying. And do something
that is kind of smooth. That is like one click. Or even perhaps optionally something like
AI supported auto image generation or something like that. Presumably. Or other great ideas.
But I think what's really, so I think the basics, the let's say technology, the engine
start, it's pretty okay. And the focus now should be on the usability. So making what's
implemented actually usable. And I guess that's it. Thank you.