Okay, hello, I'm Gabo Telleman from Allotopia, Bienvillea, and I would like to talk about
how we do crash testing in the backyard.
So let's start.
What is even this crash testing?
Crash testing is a QA sub-project of TDF and it runs on the master branch around every
second week.
So what is this testing?
It's testing continuously opening files, saving them in different formats, and reopening of
those saved files.
And make sure that crashes during this workflow don't happen because that's kind of bad for
user perspective.
And usually this process sends a resulting mail to the developers list and interested
parties like Mosley Kowlan fix those crashes.
And that's good on master branch, but what if the long-term support branches, which we
maintain for customers, introduce such errors?
That would be kind of bad for customers.
So we wanted to avoid that in the longer run.
Okay.
So what are the prerequisites for this work?
You need first some hardware, a beefy system with many CPU threads because there is a lot
of files to test.
And of course, a bunch of files, tens of thousands.
And this can be downloaded using scripts in the core repository.
Then you need the crash testing scripts themselves.
You need to download them and on the beefy system, configure them to build LibreOffice,
run them on the set of files you have first downloaded and also interpret the results.
So this is how the beefy system looks in real life.
It's nothing entirely in the backyard, but on the couch, let's say.
It was only some 40 CPUs or so and a lot of disk space as well.
Next second step is downloading files.
First script is called like this in the core repository.
And this makes, is downloads user made file attachments from public backtrack cars such
as TDF and Apache OpenOffice, backzilla, Linux distribution, backtrack cars and other software
backtrack cars such as KOffice, GNumeric and Abi word.
And it has some lovely or less lovely on user friendly properties such as you need to install
some extra Python modules and set an environment variable to tailor for your hardware so that
the download happens quite quickly.
And you need to run it from the target directory.
That's all that gave it at this script.
Next second script is our website scraper code like this.
It needs also some Python modules.
You can add the target directory as parameter and some Microsoft Office themed forums will
need registration before this can work on them and login data needs to be stored in
a format file.
Next getting the crash testing scripts themselves.
It's not in the core repository but this other country dev tools repository and in the test
backzilla files directory.
So how to make sense of that?
In the environment is also very important and this is the most difficult part of this
talk.
So before you start running the scripts you need to confirm the environment with this
config file.
It needs to be placed on that path.
There are some defaults in the dev tools repository but you should override those.
The most important settings are this compiler.
The compiler version GCC or Clang works the same in this regard but you just need to take
care that the old version of LibreOffice you want to compile actually compiles with your
compiler.
You need to set the parallelism how many CPU threads you have.
It's with workers environment variable and the most important thing is the path for this
script.
So we need the location of the files to test which were downloaded by the two scripts two
slides ago and after that you need to hardcode the dev tools repository path with this TT
pass and next is source therefore the LibreOffice core repository clone which you also need to
compile and you need a build directory where the output of the compilation will go.
So in the build directory you need also place the autogen input file.
It's also in the dev tools repository.
Of course you don't want to send the casual email and upload the results to the DDF site
because it's internal for the company so you need to set these two other two last variables.
Okay next it's easy there is a crash test data variable for the downloaded files.
You need to copy your files there and execute the command share script which will do all
the heavy lifting and basically that's all.
These are the crash test data directory under logs and the mere TXT file will be the summary
of the run.
Next step is finding what went wrong and fix the actual crashes which is just casual back
porting back fixing.
So what were what are gains of upstream from this work?
There are some.
I made these scripts a lot more configurable so you can set them up more easily for other
companies.
Before that it was it was only fixed only able to run on the DDF server and it was a
kind of a pain to transplant it to another machine.
There was a little bit of performance gain there was a bottleneck and upstream also can
run this and this work more quickly.
And that's all.
Thanks for the attention.