I guess I start already because otherwise it gets boring.
Hi everyone, I'm Zvante Schubert.
I started in 1999 with StarOffice in Hamburg and never worked on LibreOffice, Core, StarOffice
earlier.
But always from the beginning, I although applied at C++, are the Java-based Webtop,
we called it, a WebOffice, right?
And we had two in some.
The second one was where the Golden Master came in 2011.
It was canceled, everything.
And this library I'm talking about, the ODF Toolkit, was the core of this WebOffice and
later on a fork from OpenExchange for another WebOffice.
So I worked once at the ODF standard, which is the FIFR mod, the shock-frozen runtime
that you dump and send to others.
And the reason of the standard is to be interoperable with other things like Microsoft Office.
Microsoft is also participating in the OASIS ODFTC.
Okay.
So far, not bringing your own laptop because everything goes faster this way.
Anyway, it doesn't matter.
So by the way, we are three from seven members in the OASIS TC.
We are three from the Buckman Foundation, Rigina Henschel, who is very active, and Michael
Stauff from Atropia, many thanks for Atropia joining that.
And Michael is also the co-maintainer of this ODF Toolkit.
And yes, sorry.
Dennis, bring my back, please.
Okay.
So yes, yes, yes.
So, the ODF Toolkit is basically Java-based and it has two main core deliverables.
This is the ODF DOM.
And the other thing is the validator.
And yes, I know, but gosh, here we go.
Sorry for the inconvenience.
It's over there.
Gosh.
Oh.
Hey, here's something.
Okay.
Sorry.
The one thing is the core of the ODF DOM.
And the online validator is the wrapper around it.
And you know it's host of ODF and it's used for validating this ODF file format.
And ODF DOM, you hear it by the name, it's not only an ODF implementation, but also
in DOM.
And you might know this from the browsers.
And that's the browser standard, the HTML standard, the demand that at the runtime,
the browser is accessible by the DOM API.
And that is the way that JavaScript not only runs in Firefox, but that is this macros are
inter-bubble in all browsers.
And ODF doesn't have such runtime API.
You have either a libroface macro or a Microsoft often macro and they do not work to each other.
This is a real downtime.
I don't say that we need a DOM, but there's no DOM access at libroface.
But it would be nice to have a feature API, a high-level API.
And the reason is that we have a standard, a blueprint, the OSTC-given standard, and
then we have this implementation where ODF has one of them and it's hosted by ODF.
And just in a nutshell, what is the standard defining?
The standard blueprint is defining the zip.
If you have an ODT document, you can exchange the suffix and then you suddenly have a zip.
And there's parts in the specification parts, number one introduction, number four formula
that's not implemented here.
But the zip itself is defined in the package like the encryption signature and also this
meta-inf manifest which is a content table and you find the signature XML as well.
And the whole XML part is one of them.
And the reason now, the high-level goal is to have to close the gap between the standard,
the blueprint and the implementation.
Like want to get away from paper because you don't want to get, oh, here, developer, here's
another 500 pages of specification, I'll start.
But the idea is to generate as much as possible like documentation and most of the core by
this.
And yes, ease by this development.
And how it's been done because we are generating from the XML, look, there are a lot of elements
of XML, but the manifest is like a set of content table signatures, also the manifest
XML and all of these is taken away abstracted from the developers.
So we generate the DOM tree and type DOM tree like for each element and attribute.
We have a class and element gives you methods to what's inserted.
And the default values are extracted from the spec.
So soonish is like you should have a constructor from all the mandatory words of the sub tree
or something like this.
But there's also some gap in the digital gap in the spec, like there's some formulas in
the floating text saying, oh, when attribute A is active, then the attribute B, sorry,
if it's B is present, then A become active or there's a certain value for B. And these
conditions I would love to read out and generate from it the source code because I don't want
to type it myself with thousands of attributes.
Another thing that's not there because it's a lot of things, the puzzle pieces, I would
call them feature.
And this should be the feature API.
Everybody expects there's an image and there's a table.
And this is like even if you don't know anything about ODF, you will find another platform
that's HTML markdown and you have a certain assumption that if there's a table, you can
insert a column.
So this insert column function, yes, this change API request that has a certain pattern
of XML change.
And this might and should be defined and spec generate even this API from it.
So in the end, it's something like this.
We have a semantic layer, this is currently not generatable, an XML layer and a package
layer and the idea is that you might exchange the semantic layer with even other platform
elements like there's also a table where you can do a table insert column and markdown
this way.
So let me run through it a bit.
Of course, there's just a model and not a view.
This is for Libre of us only and because as well that the spec is not very strict on the
view.
And the highlights is we've done recently a release for ODF1 or O2 still.
We refactored a lot this code generation and also did a release after 20 years and took
over the multi-schema value data which is for loading and understanding the grammar because
we have something called real XMG which is simpler like XSD, grammar and from this we
traverse and are able to generate as much.
There's one three upcoming release.
Now I thought I could do a reset with Michael for Fosten but it was some bugs.
And one at four later.
Why one at four later?
Let's do the ODFTC update.
You see this was the last release one or two with Sun that was stopping Starfish this year
and it took a while until we made the next release for OASIS.
And now we are closing on ODF.
There's a link.
You can click on it and see the query of the 66 issues which are already in and then I'll
turn it to the candidates where people can validate from, take something from it.
So there's another thing I did project on a search engine where the text of the data
being extracted from ODF.
I realized there's something missing in ODF.
Just for discussion after something.
It's like we don't have this ODF model in the middle like this feature model and then
we say okay now I tell you how do I do the export.
How should a table look like in Markdown and you can do cherry picking of features.
You like to have in your own format like Markdown or HTML.
I realized that the whole design like we came from XML and later we realized we need this
feature level to abstract from this distinct XML details that this is missing.
So here's some sources left and I really, really love to discuss on some kind of this
later by TB or something.
Thanks a lot.
See you next year.
Thank you.