So, I'm Pedro, Pedro Silva, and today we are going to look at how we can make Collabora
Online yours and how those customizations can actually lead into new features while
going through some cool new features.
Why not?
So we start over with these different themes and different aspects that Collabora Online
can have.
But not only we can have these different faces, but we can also have different buttons.
If you have a different button that you'd like to have, or maybe you are hacking on
something and you want to have it in front of a button that triggers something, you can
do that.
And we'll show later how, but spoiler alert, we have an XML file that you can customize
it, we have a post message API that you can actually use that to hack directly onto the
interface and beyond.
And third of all, we also have some kind of cool variables that go through some invisible
input field that then customize it.
So there is a lot of stuff that you can just hack around.
And by the way, LanguageTool, as described by Michael Meeks, thanks to Athvinis, and
we got this cool integration, file properties, another improved and now native functionality.
You see here on this tab, there's plenty of space.
You might want to add a button here.
Why not?
It's a good candidate to do that.
Our clients, accessibility check.
We go through these new features, how we can create diagrams, and you will soon start to
feel that, okay, this is fitting my workflow, but maybe I want to go a step further.
By the way, we can even do this crazy stuff.
Isn't it crazy?
On the browser?
I don't know.
I think it's crazy.
Oh, and while doing this, we got a lot of performance wins left and right, which is
it's cool and all, but what about new features?
What about upcoming features?
We work with LibreOffice technology around in a group with friends, and this means not
only the people that are here, but even other people.
For instance, in this case, next cloud, and we are just doing something that can start
with online, then forces us to go to the core to LibreOffice kit, and in the process we
are improving both sides.
That's interesting.
For instance, this is an example with form controls, as Miklos described, content controls,
right?
Repair documents, some other improvements.
How do we make it, how we customize it?
That's the question.
So, as I hinted before, we can do that via XML, and there is a lot of variables that
you can just turn off.
We even saw it earlier with Pranam's talk, one of those examples, but you can set what's
going to be the default UI mode.
If you want to go a little bit further, you can hack what will be those key colors that
we can see, and you see here the input values that we can pass.
Or why not hack it directly into it?
Maybe you have a different, your native language is not English, and you might want to test
it on that.
Maybe you don't know, but you can add, at the end of your URL, you can add this end
length and for instance, some different language directional layout, and you can test that
and maybe even help us translate.
Why not?
You can just go to the web later and just start to contribute.
You see, all those things, you are making that yours, because it's answering your problem,
but at the same time, you are helping everyone else, so I think that's the key here.
Or inserting a new custom button, for instance, insert button is just one of the options that
you can use and abuse with PostMessage API.
So if you go to stk.collaboronline.com, slash docs, slash PostMessage API, you will see all
these listed in a table with examples, so you can just hack it.
Have fun with it.
Even if it doesn't work out of the box, even if you are trying to hack something and it
breaks, it's okay.
You can always keep in touch.
You can go to cola slash io, and there is our IRC, our matrix telegram, all these things.
You can report bugs and maybe push a PR, and you will find out that maybe your PR will
leave to learn more about LibreOffice technology, LibreOffice kit, and suddenly you already
have two PRs, both on cola.collaboronline and on Garrett on LibreOffice.
So hopefully it's what will happen.
And while doing that, you have three minutes questions, yes?
And while you are doing that, you will be able to experiment to crazy new features,
the bleeding edge, that still no one knows about it, because you build it.
So maybe you can already see what is happening there, what's the new features, new integration
that's coming, hit on citations, but many more things.
So I hope you take that at heart and give it a go, and join the team.
Thanks.
Any questions?
We've got some two and a half minutes.
Thank you.
I use cola on my next cloud.
Can I do all this on my next cloud?
Yes.
Is it?
Yes, if you have your built environment, you can hack all these things and have it.
Now if you have a production environment, that's probably what you are hitting at,
okay, then you can still do some of these customizations just by simply hacking on the
coolwst.xml, that it should be under ATC directory, and you should find there, coolwst.xml.
You can, for instance, set up the default UI, what will be the default UI that will
appear if you want to use the integrator's theme or not, for instance, if you are using
next cloud, next cloud has its own theme, so you can hack all these things.
What's the default language?
Maybe you have three or four languages there as a list, and maybe you don't need.
Maybe you just use maybe two, Portuguese or English, and both, two, and you can remove
the others and it will maybe use less resources.
So there is a lot of things you can hack.
Will do, thank you.
30 seconds, one very quick question and answer.
If not, go for the matrix chat.
Thank you.