Okay, let's go. It's me again. Somebody just throw some, I don't know, vegetables at me
if the 10 minutes are over. If you came for WebAssembly here, I have to disappoint you.
So we'll have to wait another one or two talks when we will talk about that. I repurposed
the slot here to talk a little bit about something equally cool, wonderful, spiffy with a rocket
engine for LibreOffice templates. Well, small disappointment, it's about warmocks. But I
think it's a kind of serious there, perhaps the name we could think about a different
one. So quick intro, what is that? If you haven't heard about it. It's a Java extension
to LibreOffice. And it's there for template and forms management and also like extending
mail merge. So those are two views on it. The left one is the sidebar extension. You
see three sidebar panels been added there. This is just a selection of sample templates
there. And the right side is the kind of constructed generated document out of that thing. So all
of that has been developed by the city of Munich, starting around 2005ish to 2006ish
under the Linux project umbrella. Why? Because they wanted to migrate to OpenOffice. They
wanted some template management and there was nothing that was powerful enough. So they
did what you do when it's not there. And you do open sourcey stuff. You started doing something
yourself. And then open source it. So that's what Munich did. And there was some well,
it was in production I think since 2008 and there was some major upgrade to LibreOffice
from OpenOffice which had some we had to change some UNO stuff there. And another major rework
migrating from Java swing dialogues and UI to native LibreOffice UI and mostly sidebar
which really nicely integrates as you've seen before. And this year or end of last year
since the Linux project is kind of sun setting, the extension itself which is extremely powerful,
incredibly great, also cool for QA because it triggers really literally every little
corner of the writer UNO API there. Moving house to TDF. Again, what is it in the first
place? It's predominantly for let's say very complex document generation workflows. That
you will find in larger companies, perhaps also in law firms or something but predominantly
in the public sector. The idea behind there is kind of assemble your letter on the fly
and employ the dry principle and only ever have one stylistic element or part of the
template defined once and then you kind of include that like PHP or other template programming
languages so you kind of piece that together. There's also like loops and control flow statements
that you can use to kind of very dynamically generate forms. There's a forms generator
so you can kind of have some user guidance like where to fill in what and pre-fill things
and also dynamically kind of say oh when this is on then do that or not to do that or disable
here. As I said mail merge stuff and text programming and quotes content based directors
for doing something very dynamic. That thing has now moved to TDF. End of last year and
we have been quite busy first of all doing the move and also doing some adaptations and
adjustments and getting it kind of fit for let's say an international open source project
like LibreOffice. What happened? Git repos moved to under the LibreOffice project on
GitHub which was an easy like click so the old URL still work. You got a redirect that's
pretty nice feature on GitHub so everybody can still who had this clone can still work
with it but the official location is now there. We added some translation workflow stuff.
We made the Java like everything that was a user visible string and the Java sources
is now on PO files. We put this on TDF's web plate so the UI can be translated. We moved
the documentation from a markdown Git based workflow into MediaWiki which is also much
nicer than to translate for the community. For this markdown stuff we essentially needed
some kind of developer set up to do that and MediaWiki has really nice excellent translation
support meanwhile. Fixed a number of bugs. Made sure that it actually works not just
with all the LibreOffice versions but with the most recent ones. We did some build fixes
on the bits of the internal build system kind of leaking through that still so we made it
actually build out of the box. You clone that, you build that with Maven and it actually
works. Some tweaks with namespaces so we can then upload artifacts to the LibreOffice Maven
repository and it doesn't have the old names anymore that were kind of sometimes internal
to city of Munich. We set up Jenkins jobs so we can actually not only run tests on pull
requests, we can also run releases there on the CI and tons of smaller things like started
to do comment translation in the code, renamed variable names, got the built-out and other
auxiliary documentation translated to English. It's not done in particular the code stuff.
That's not done. Part of that was already English but there's quite a bit left. Which
gets us to next steps and the possible future. So, handbook is not fully line of super clean.
The original handbook was German so we translated it to English and then we wanted to reuse
the old German translation because why do that work again? With the big key markup so
that's kind of busy work there and we're kind of still mostly gone, we're still busy with
that. I guess help appreciate it but no, not okay. So, we get it done in the very near
future. Some renaming for the Java packages that kind of blocks each other with possibly
renaming the project. We don't want to rename it twice. Have some new landing page done.
Some more bug fixing. There's still some sidebar, not so nice things and some thing that was
one crash somewhere and then we want to reasonably soonish have some release there so that people
actually can use that. If anybody's interested we can have some snapshots possibly published.
Then again it should be relatively easy to build and if it's not let's fix it. So, actually
maybe not publishing snapshots far and wide is a feature, not a bug. So, we can fix the
build system. Yeah, renaming. So, we kind of brainstormed a little bit in the background.
Those are three suggestions that we will probably mull over and think about. So, this LibreOffice
template tool or template engine is probably what it actually is. So, people would understand
what it does when they see that somewhere. This forms and templates is a bit more ambitious
because it does much more than just templates. But hey, naming is hard. So, yeah. And if
you're curious, come and help. So, there's some easy hack there for common translation.
It's the easiest thing to get your feedback. There's certainly more like UI and document
translation. That would be great. And of course, if you have cool feature ideas, go get it
implemented. So, there's one thing. That is there's an old branch about QR code support.
So, you can kind of generate QR code and insert it like in this process of programmed software
controlled template generation. That would be nice to get in or other things that people
want to templates these days. Okay. And that's it. Thanks so much.