Okay, good. Hi, everyone. Welcome to this one. Hopefully it's not going to keep doing
that. So today my talk is called putting the R in librofist's shiny dashboard for QA. My
name is Stefan Guilloux. I joined the TDF team, the document foundation, just recently in November
as a QA analyst. And this is about a little project recently started to create something
that everyone can come to and to learn a bit more about QA numbers around the project,
around librofist, but also everything else that's hosted by the document foundation.
So just a little bit about where I come from because it matters in some way. Quickly, I studied
plants, ecology, sustainability, that's my background, then moved on to working in agricultural
research, and then finished the last four years working in the library as a research
software trainer and in research support. But throughout the last 15 years, I've been a free
libro and open source software user and advocate, trying to push for the solutions, especially in
teaching, learning, research environment. And because of that, I've been a user of a few
different tools, including the programming language R. This is what I use for this project.
There's quite a few things already around QA and librofist. So quality assurance numbers and graphs
can be found in lots of different places. Here I've listed a few. There's a wiki that has an
absolute wealth of different pages and tables and links you can use and also stats about us,
QA project, our QA team and community. There's a blog also that's a specific QA blog. It's not
just one blog at the document foundation, around librofist. It's also the QA blog, there's a
dev blog, there's a few different blogs. And I really recommend having a look at this one,
whereas there's excellent monthly reports that are done with a few different graphs to explore
and also updates on who has been working on what, so what new features and bug fixes are coming up.
So it's a great read. I really think you should subscribe to that one if you're interested.
Obviously, Bugzilla, this is where we report bugs and where we trash them and mark them as fixed
eventually if someone's keen to take those ones. We've got QA scripts and our QA repository. Those
are Python scripts to process the Bugzilla data. We've got a crash reports website that has some,
for example, timeline graphs where you can see how numbers of crashes evolve throughout
in different versions. And there's an interesting website as well called Dev Central which gives you
quick links to different important tools for development around librofist. Just to give you
a quick idea, this is the wiki page where you can also find ways to keep in touch with us.
And there's going to be options for chat rooms but also the mailing list. So if you want to keep
hearing about those things, do join that. This is the December 2022 blog post and you'll find a few
graphs in there to see how things are evolving. But at the top, there's a lot about new features
and new fixes by different developers and this is the crash report website. This is what I mentioned
just before, Dev Central where you can find links directly to, for example, the wiki. Bugzilla to
report a bug on the crash report website. But also other ones like Weblight for translation,
Gerid for submitting your patches. Now, the idea of the QA dashboard, an extra tool that's not
supposed to necessarily replace other things but complement them. I think I've used R and Shiny with
it. So R, the R programming language. Very useful for data analysis, statistics. Shiny is the
framework for creating web apps that goes on top. So interactive visualizations and tables using two
packages called Plotly and DT. There's ggplot2 in the background too. Quite a few other packages
are coming in in play there. And also very importantly, I don't want it to be just pictures,
just nice pictures to look at, but it needs to also link to activities, to things that we can do.
And it doesn't need to be this bottleneck or this dead end. So I'll show you what it looks like
currently. This work in progress. We've got a few different files here that we will eventually
share once we're happier with what we've got and we want everyone to use it. There's a few helper
functions. A script to pre-process the data because it is currently based on a dump from
Bugzilla. That's quite large. And finally, the app that has both the UI and the server
functions on there. So I'll open this in the browser. Maybe a bit better.
I'll quickly show you what we've got. So it starts with this page where it looks at the snapshot,
the most recent data we've got, depending on what export we've used. And we can see, for example,
the first graph here are the most important components of the project. And other projects,
not just LibreOffice. But you can see that most reports will be related to writer,
calc, LibreOffice in general. And then you've got impress. You'll see that base and draw
probably attract a bit less attention. Looking at the importance of reports or how it's been
classified, we've got a graph on severity. Thank you. And priority, which work together. You can
learn a bit more about those ones with the links underneath if they don't necessarily mean that
much. And you can see that obviously it's going to be bigger in the middle where there's the
default fields that are used, normal severity and medium priority. Now, looking at how bugs have
been classified, depending on what happens with them, you can see in general, green is what has
been resolved for different reasons, what has been actually fixed by a commit, and what has been
resolved with other resolutions. You can see that there's a few different categories where it might
fall. And you can see the numbers by using your mouse going over them. It's looking also more
precisely at just that green part that's up there, looking at how bugs were resolved. So you might be
interested in knowing that most of them have been fixed, but then a lot of them have been closed
because they've already been reported before duplicates. Quite a few are closed as works for
me because it's been resolved without necessarily knowing how it has been resolved. We've got a
graph on which is the first version that's been affected as far as we know. You've got all the
major versions of LibreOffice here and the creation time as well as the last time of modification.
But for example, here there's a link to action. A list of bugs that haven't changed for more than
five years. This is where there's potentially bugs that we can very quickly close. You can use this
date range picker to focus on one patch kill period. You can remove enhancement requests
and automatically invalid reports are removed as well. But I also want to work with timelines.
This is a fun, the graphs that we've got in the QA report, the monthly one. And here we can see how
unconfirmed bugs have evolved over the last 13 years. If you're interested in just the last year,
you can toggle those ones. And if you want to look good, you can remove the zero and it looks
like it's really dropping. And then, thank you, I've got a table here that looks at that specific
snapshot. So that stops on the second of Feb, I think. First of Feb maybe. There it is. There's
the date. It tells you. And you can look for different bugs here. Bugzilla might be a bit
daunting sometimes to do a search. This table is a condensed table. It doesn't have all the
information. But if you're interested in, for example, dark mode bugs that have been, that are
unconfirmed, you can use those filters at the top. It might take a bit of time because there's
thousands of thousands of them. But it should come up with a short list of those unconfirmed
bugs for dark mode. There we go. We've got four of them. You can click on that link and it takes you
straight to Bugzilla. You can sort them by whatever you want or look at only a specific version of
the brotheus. The next steps would be those ones. Thank you.
And if you want to contact me or contact the QA team, there's options here.
Yeah. Thanks. Have a great afternoon, everyone.