Okay, let's start. It's quite 3 p.m. Hello, my name is Sverda Becker. Welcome to my talk
to migrating to LibreOffice technology, old and new motivations and challenges. Well,
migrating to LibreOffice technology is a very complex task in technical issues and non-technical
issues. So, both worlds where we come from, from a proper attire office suite to a free
office suite like LibreOffice and LibreOffice technology once, develop further. These tasks
are done now, for example, by me for over 20 years. And so, in the meantime, the technologies,
both worlds are evolving further and it makes sense to think about old things which are
deprecated, old motivations and new one which is coming up with new versions of both worlds.
So, with respect to the time of 10 minutes, it's very, very short for such an item. I
have chosen five items. I think the most important one and there are some new ones in it which
I want to bring to discussion if you have time to discuss or ask me later if you want
to have more here in this. So, the first one is, is it working? The first one is an old
one and a new one and it means desktop client is still and will still be there. Everybody
is going to cloud, to online and so on. But, as you could imagine, in a professional environment,
you are sometimes in regional or in areas where no internet or bad internet connection
is and you have to work there as well for your job or something like this. So, the most
deployments are going with the solution that you have and the possibility to work online
and have an additional office suite installation on your client. This will be, especially in
Germany where such regions where you have no or bad internet connections, a long time
last. So, I mentioned these new developments in both worlds and both office worlds. So,
there are some new, over the time, there are some new functional and UI developments which
are, some of them are positive for our world, for our technology world and some are negative,
have negative motivations for a migration. So, let me start with a positive one. One
is in the client, in the office client, positive for us, if you have a look in the new Microsoft
Office client that there is working with format templates which is very important in professional
document processing is becoming more and more obscure for the user. So, it is hidden for
the user that it would be nice to work with templates and we are in favor of working with
such templates. The negative side is, if you have a look in these new versions of Microsoft
Office, you can experience that there are a lot of new assistance and automatisms which
are partially laid upon artificial intelligence and this is a kind of functionality we totally
miss in LibreOffice. That is one example for it where we did it. It is the integration
of the deeper translation, the possible integration into your text processing to translate, but
this is just one. Yes, it is a two-sided coin. Some users are totally fine with these automatisms,
but the negative side is that functionality is hidden behind such assistance and they
do not know what is happening in the document and could not work with it. The second one
I want to highlight is also node one. It is the task for a migration to have the right
strategy for the document format in-house and for interoperability aspects. I think
this is a well-known item, but with new versions of the document format as well in the proper
attire world as well as in our world, it is becoming more and more complex. For example,
Microsoft is nowadays supporting also open document format, but if you try to define
which version of the document format they support, you are a little bit lost in space,
so there are some interoperability issues for ODF in the other world and it is intransplorent.
What is very interesting in a few last migrations we did for professional deployments, we have
some aspects in the interoperability from LibreOffice to OpenOffice and back. OpenOffice
is still on Open Document Format version 1.2. We in LibreOffice technology on 1.3 and extended,
if you choose the standard one, and there are some issues sending ODF documents to
other people who use OpenOffice. Next one is indeed a new one. You all know this big issue or
item of digital sovereignty. It's a huge wave of expectations coming to us, especially to the Office
Suite, to do all the expectations around it for free and open software. So they are becoming more
and more aware about dependencies in the proprietary world and they want like a big bang, get everything,
something like in one-stop shopping, we say, just click install and you have all ours integrated,
even with other tools we have not in the LibreOffice technology like chat, like collaboration and so on.
And this is, as I said, a man out of the box, so doing it in a big bang and all who are doing
migrations know that this expectation of one big bang is not very realistic. So the next one is
online compilation and smart devices. Also a good side and a bad side. Good side is if you have a
look in the Microsoft Office online apps, it's a total disaster. It's a total disaster and this
is a point where we with solutions in LibreOffice technology are on the positive side,
definitely are on the positive side. Upcoming more and more, it's very, very interesting. We have a
long time where synchronous collaboration was out of no value, but this is coming up more and more
and more with this pandemic home office work. More people are working synchronously on the same
document. Other stuff like file sharing you have to do with tasks for file sharing, integration
with chats and so on. And the differentiation between online and smart devices is not known
by the user. It's the same for them that they are doing their work online or on a smartphone. We all
know that this is definitely not the same with the apps on the smart devices and the online office.
I have to hurry up. I'm sorry. Last one is also a new one. It's an interesting development. We
have long worked to have this notebook bar UI and more and more is the notebook bar seen as the
standard UI. What we get is that we have more efforts, have to make more efforts and migrations
for training and support in different user interfaces. There's an additional aspect we
have to have be careful what we are doing on this different devices, client UI, online UI and mobile
UI, which can confuse the user a lot with it. So what is TDF doing for such
challenges in migrations? What we are doing is we are certifying people in three different areas,
professional developer, which are doing supporting stuff. If you have integration
tasks and so on, we have professional migrators and professional trainers. If you want to know
more about that, please visit the document.com. You can see what we are doing there. It's a very
special certification and it covers exactly the aspect of these challenges to have the best
quality in migrations. If there are questions, I'm around and come to me and pass.