Thank you.
Hi.
Can I start it?
Okay.
My name is Laszlo Nemec.
And the presentation, title of the presentation, Farm Project by Design, the short, the summary
of my presentation, I don't, whole LibreOffice development can be full of flow, but I can
show the best moment of my recent developments.
So my motto from Goethe, Merlichte, more light.
And in the end, I hope I can give more light about LibreOffice development or fun around
LibreOffice development.
First one, I work it on improving the spelling dictionaries or spellcheckers too in the last
few weeks and months.
And here, there is a Wikipedia one-liner I use to extend the spelling dictionaries, pushing
the word text of the Wikipedia, for example, the Hungarian in my case, to a Unix pipeline
and ranking their entries of the dictionary in the case of the Hungarian.
There was 400,000 entries with a very huge variant of the different localization of the
Wikipedia.
And counting their backlinks.
And after that, we have a data about the frequency of the entries and we can filter the unknown
words for the spelling dictionary.
Here is the one-liner.
I was so excited to show, to see the Wikipedia XML from downloads from the dump Wikipedia.org
that is five billion characters in a single PC as 50,000 books, the text content of this
single file.
And it was able to create a frequency database immediately.
I called my son that, check this, this is the prototype of the $1 billion algorithm
of Google, the page rank.
Wow, why so wonderful.
He said that it's a little bit late, but no problem because it's not late for me.
When I, I know the Unix pipeline, the history of the Unix line, why so it started with the
moon landing.
I know the history of the graph, so it's related to the language analysis, to the federalist
papers, the founders of the United States.
I was a guy, a man, a linguist, working in the Bell laboratory.
So it's a history, but it's a present.
So that is why interesting that in the liberal office development, like the open office.org
was the first big office suite built on the Solaris system, Sun Microsystem developed
this with joy.
And I use the VI editor and modification by a Dutch face of the developer, the VI version.
So it's a history, but the present too.
And this is the result related to the Hungarian dictionary.
And it seems that humans just want to have more fun because check the most frequent
new unknown words, McLaren or music or soccer, football and car racing, et cetera.
But there was a, in the first, the most frequent dozen words, there was a exception as misfit,
nochny, a small ochrein on village with 1000 people, only 1000 people.
Why?
So I checked the Wikipedia and this was the place of the Crimean astrophysical observatory.
That is a huge number, near 3000 links in the Wikipedia for this, the village, show
me that it means thousands of asteroids, stars, galaxies discovered in this observatory in
the last 100 years.
So it was a nice experience.
I do some other words, not this one to the Hungarian dictionary, for example, Higgs,
the physics related to the gravitational waves or Tice-Tetraops because this extinct animal
is the most popular in the young age people as toddlers.
So sometimes it's useful.
The other development, this is a sort of language, is a mini language to handle a problem, handle
the problem that converting the digits to a written form, the words of a number, for
example, Euro to French.
I'm sorry for my French, but I don't want to pronounce the French version, but I'm sure
there are people here who can help me later.
And this is the history of the source language.
It's related to the software patients because that was in Microsoft, XMS standardization
has very special function, the bat text, using converting numbers to Thai language.
That was maybe Chinese suggestion in the open formal list to create a more generalized version,
number text.
But the answer from the open office dot developer studies and developer at that time, that was
defining a general purpose number that would be a nightmare.
He had the experience.
It's really a nightmare.
And a few years later, I made a one-liner in Ofk, the Unix tool, a prototype to create
something useful, a mini language to describe the different grammar rules of the languages.
And the first version within a week or I don't know, supported the English, Thai, German,
Hungarian, Italian language, and it's a very special numbering system.
Shuzo numbers, which in the night is still used by the Chinese market, two lines of the
numbers with a magnitude of the number, for example, this number is 2023.
And the next line contains the thousand year sign.
The best, the worst problem, so it's not so well the development that this was a spin-off
of my grammar checker development supported by the FSF.H2 foundation.
But that time with three small children without too much money, it was a crazy idea for me
to create a new development.
So that is why I asked the NNet foundation, help of the NNet foundation.
And later, one development, 11 new language support in the software.
And the interesting thing here that when I made a C++ version from this project, also
was funded by an FSF foundation,.H2 foundation, I got help from Ekharathka, at that time a
LibreOffice developer, and later with the Russian developer, Michael Gonski, from Kola
Bora, and now if you check the new features of LibreOffice, you will try to, you will
check the, it's possible to select this format, you will number formats in the dialogue windows,
so useful.
And this was the two characters fixed, but it wasn't able to fix five years ago, because
my, related to my complexity of my development.
LibreLogo, a special language, but not only for children, I will check the next example.
This line fixed the SVG export with the special font features, open type of graphite, so you
can use, for example, the special generated graphics.
About books, I improved the type setting, the paragraph line breaking algorithm, adding
the hyphenation zone of the OXM standard, and this standard helped create more DTP-like
text in LibreOffice, my plan to create something better, picture books, thank you very much.
This is the mascot of the LibreLogo development I made last night, the idea is quite new,
and solving a thousand years problem that, what is this?
Log or a crocodile, both of them, log the LibreLogo crocodile.
So 400 bucks fixed in the last four and a half years, for buying me, using special methods,
Unix programming language, or the approach, creating, funding the freedom in these developments.
So you like bug fixing, you can see new features.
A language, for example, 200 years, end of the famous Hungarian poet, Sandor Pätterty,
made a very short poems you can read later, and these poems are from Goethe and related
to other Tesla who made the biggest innovation in Budapest, thanks to Goethe.
This is the end of my development, and you can check the numbers and the downloader.
Thank you very much.