At our final talk for this session, we have Pierre here.
He's going to discuss about Loop, a tool that, well, he and we have been using to measure
compatibility for different OSes.
Pierre, you have the floor.
Thank you, Rizvan, and thanks everyone for attending my talk.
This is joint work with a bunch of colleagues and students, including Hugo, my PhD student.
He's a key player behind his work.
I'm just getting all the media suggestion, but he has built all this stuff, so all the
credits go to him.
In this brief talk, I want to speak a bit about application compatibility for custom
operating systems.
I guess most of you don't need to be convinced that we still need custom operating systems
today.
We still need both research operating systems and prototype operating systems from the industry.
The thinking that Linux has solved everything is not true, in my opinion.
We still need things like UniCraft if we want to go fast or if we want to specialize like
crazy.
We still need things like Resty-R-Met if we want security or SCL4.
We still need custom operating systems.
The thing is, with this operating system, they're only as good as the applications that
they can run.
Compatibility is key.
Compatibility with existing applications is extremely important.
If you want to build a community, you want your user to go to your website, compile your
custom OS and then try some of their favorite applications or try some of the highly popular
applications in a given application domain like engineering or Redis for cloud.
If you want to attract sponsors or investors, or even if you, like me, are a scientist,
you want to gather some early numbers to make a publication, well, you need to do that on
standard applications.
Compatibility is important.
Another argument would be like how many times did you hear the one POSIX spoken today?
There were some slides, there was POSIX like three or four times written in the single
slide.
Compatibility is important and it can be achieved in a few different ways as we have seen with
Simon.
But one important thing to note is, in my opinion, porting is not sustainable.
Porting is what many of us do.
We build a custom operating system and then we take Redis and obviously it doesn't work
as this with our operating system.
We modify Redis a bit, we disable some features because we know that they make our OS crash.
And then we have Redis like a version customized for our operating system.
This is not sustainable because you can't maintain a branch of Redis for every operating
system out there.
In the long term, it doesn't work so well.
So porting also basically means that you as the OS developer, you ask the users of your
application to make some effort to the application developers, they need to make some effort
to be compatible with your operating system.
This doesn't work, nobody is ready to make that kind of effort.
Maybe if you give them 10x performance speed up, but this is unrealistic.
What you want to do is, once again in my opinion, as an OS developer, you want to provide compatibility
as transparently as possible.
And this means you emulate a popular operating system, for example Linux or a popular abstraction
like POSIX or the standard C library.
And then you can be compatible at three different levels.
The first level is source level or API level compatibility.
So you ask the user to compile the application code against the sources of your kernel in
the case of a unique kernel.
So you're still asking some effort from the users.
In many scenarios, you don't have access to sources.
If you have proprietary binary or pre-compiled binary, you can't have source level compatibility.
So it's not perfect and binary compatibility is a pure version of compatibility.
And there are many ways to achieve it.
You can do that at the level of the standard C library like OSV.
So you will dynamically link your kernel plus a standard C library against your application
compiled as a position independent executable or as a shared library itself.
This is great, but if the application is making directly system calls to the kernel without
going through the C standard library, well, once again, it doesn't work.
And as a matter of fact, I have counted more than 500 executables in the Debian repository
that contains the C score instruction.
So they make C scores directly to the kernel.
They don't go through the C library.
Go, for example, is making most of its C score put directly to the kernel and not through
the C library.
So what you want to do is to be compatible at the level of the system call.
So your kernel needs to emulate the C score API that Linux is providing.
This is the most transparent way of achieving compatibility.
Now this is scary, right?
Linux has more than 350 system calls we need to implement them all.
Will we be and aren't we going to re-implement Linux by doing so?
And some of them are extremely scary by themselves, right?
You have like hundreds of IO controls and each of them require its own implementation.
The Linux API even goes beyond system calls.
You have things like slash proc slash dev that are used by many applications.
The first thing a muscle binary does when it runs is to look in, I believe it's slash
proc or slash sys to get to the size of the terminal, right?
So you need to have emulation for this part of the API too.
And this, because it seems like a big engineering effort, this creates, it hinders the development
of custom operating systems.
So this is inspired by the keynote by Eti Mati Roscoe at ATC and OSDI 2021.
We looked at all the papers.
So these are top tier operating systems conferences.
And we look over the past 10 years over a total of more than 1,000 papers, how many were
about proposing a new operating system as opposed to things like security or machine
learning?
And among them, how many were just hacking Linux versus proposing an actual operating
system implemented from scratch?
And the numbers are similar to what we saw earlier, right?
You have just a very, very, very few papers proposing a new operating system because it's
a significant engineering effort.
And part of the effort is providing compatibility to run applications like Apache or Redis to
get a few numbers at the end of the paper, right?
So this is a problem.
Now the particular problem that I want to talk about is how I'm sure several people
in this room have attempted to build some form of compatibility layer for an operating
systems.
And we are all kind of working on the same thing in parallel with some form of ad hoc
processes that may benefit from some optimization.
So I've just listed here a few projects that have a Cisco level binary compatibility layers,
but actually there are many more.
And from what I understand, it is a very organic process.
So first of all, it is application driven, right?
People have a few sets of application in mind that they want to support.
If you are doing cloud, you want to support the user and suspect, Redis, Apache, whatever.
And the process basically looks like that.
You take an app, you try to run it on top of your operating system.
Obviously it fails.
You investigate, you're like, oh, I'm missing the implementation from this system code.
So you implement whatever operating system features are required to fix that particular
issue, rinse and repeat until the app is working.
And then you go to the next app.
So it's a very intuitive and organic process.
So when I built the Almetix, this is exactly what I was doing.
So something that comes to mind is, can't we have some form of generic compatibility
layer that we could plug?
Something a bit like Newlib that would provide generic interface.
And I believe it's not really possible because most of this implementation to support the
system code is very specific to whatever operating system you are using.
And it's not clear if a generic compatibility layer can be achieved.
But can we still somehow optimize that process?
Some have tried static analysis.
So they take the binaries of the applications they want to support and they look, okay,
so what are the system codes that are made by these applications?
So this has been done in the best paper in Erosys 2016, analyzed all the binaries from
Ubuntu.
I believe it was 1404 repositories.
And they concluded that every Ubuntu installation, including the smallest one, require more than
200 system codes, and 200 IO controls, five controls, and PRCTL codes, and hundreds of
pseudo-fives.
So this doesn't help.
It is still quite scary.
It's still represent like a gigantic engineering effort.
But do we want full compatibility with Ubuntu installation?
In the end, especially in the early stage of the development of an operating system,
you just want to get a few applications up and running.
And do you even want 100% compatibility?
When I write a paper, I don't really care if everything is stable.
I just want to get some numbers.
So isn't there a better way?
And obviously, maybe you think about, yeah, let's do dynamic analysis, right?
Let's run the applications that we want to support.
We send them some input that we want to support, like I'm running an engineering and I'm submitting
some HTTP or something like that.
And then we trace the system codes that are done, right?
So this is going to give us a subset of the system codes that can be identified through
static analysis that has a tendency to overestimate.
So with this trace, the engineering effort to support an application and a set of input
is a bit lower.
But it's still not a panacea because it's not taking into account two things that we
do when we implement compatibility layers.
So this is my code.
Don't judge me.
One thing that I did from Hermitax was at some point, it was a map that was calling
MNCORE to check if some page of memory wasn't swapped or not.
It's as actually, there is no swap in most unique channels, so it really didn't matter
to implement this.
So inosis means operation not supported, right?
So stubbing a system code is just saying, yeah, we don't support it.
And you cross your finger that the application has some kind of fallback pass to do something
else if the syscall fails.
And it works in some cases.
Then we can do something even more nasty.
Don't judge me again.
You can fake the success of a system code, right?
Surprisingly, in some situation, returning a success code, even if the system code doesn't
have any implementation in your operating system, it's going to work in some cases.
I'll tell a bit more about why this works sometimes.
So stubbing and faking lets you implement even less system codes than what you would
trace with a trace.
So in the end, if you want to support an app or a set of applications in your custom operating
system, the amount of system codes that you actually need to implement, so obviously it's
more than the entire Linux syscall API.
Static binary analysis will, on the binaries of the applications you want to support, will
identify a subset of that, still pretty big.
It's another estimate.
Glass analysis gets you more precise results, but it is pretty hard to achieve, and it is
still overestimating.
S trace will give you, once again, a subset.
Things start to look better.
And among these trace by S trace, you actually don't need to implement everything.
You can stub and fake some of the syscalls.
So can we measure that?
Yes, with loop.
So loop means magnifying glass in French.
It's a tool that was built by Hugo, my student, and it's some kind of super S trace that is
measuring the syscalls that are required to support an application, and that can also
tell you which one you can stub and which one you can fake.
So we used it to build a database of measurement for a relatively large set of applications.
And with loop, if you give me a description of your operating system, basically the list
of syscalls that you already support, and you give me the list of applications that
you would like to support, we run them through loop, and loop can derive a support plan,
which basically will tell you, okay, for this set of target applications, and given the
set of syscalls that you already support, what is the optimized order of syscalls to
implement to support as many applications as soon as possible?
Okay, so I will give you an example of support plan by the end of the presentation.
So from the user point of view, loop needs two things to perform its measurement on a
given application.
You give it a Docker file that is describing how you want to build and run the application
for which you want to measure the syscalls needed.
And optionally, you may need an input workload, think about a web server, it's not going to
call many system calls until you actually start to send requests to it.
Loop will instantiate the application, launch it on a standard Linux kernel, and analyze
the syscalls that have done, and with a few tricks, we'll be able to know which ones can
be faked or stubbed.
The results are, it's basically just a CSV file.
For a syscall that is made by the application, can it be faked?
Can it be stubbed?
Or does it require a full implementation?
We start that in a database, and later, so we populate the database with as many measurements
as possible, and this database can, given the list of syscalls that is already supported
by your operating systems, give you some form of optimized super plan given which of the
applications you want to support.
So how does it work?
When Loop runs the application, first it does a quick pass of a trace to measure all the
system calls that are done by the application, and then for each system call that we identify,
we use seccomp to hook into the execution of each of the system calls, and rather than
actually executing them through the Linux kernel, we emulate the fact that the syscall
is stubbed.
So we just return in assist without executing the syscall.
We can also emulate the fact that the syscall is faked, return zero, and then we check
if the application works or not, following the stubbing or the faking of this particular
syscall.
We use that for each system call that we have identified with this trace.
How do we actually check for the success of the execution of the application?
So we identify two types of apps.
Some we call them run to completion.
There will be something like fio, when you start fio, it runs for one minute and then
it exits outputting some stuff on the external output.
So with run to completion apps, we run the app instrumented with loop, we check its exit
code.
If it's different from zero, we consider that the run was a failure, could have been killed
by a signal or things like that.
And we can also run a script optionally in addition to that, after each run of the application
to check its standard output, we can grab error values, we can grab for success printing,
something like 50 requests per second have been achieved.
The files that may have been created by the application and so on.
And then another type of application is client servers.
So with client servers, we run the app instrumented by loop and in parallel, we run a workload,
could be WRC, HTTP, the Redis benchmark for Redis and so on.
And we check the success of both.
We check that the app doesn't crash, we generally say others are not supposed to exit.
So we check that it doesn't crash and we check the success of the workload.
Like if Redis benchmark returns something different than zero for a reason, something
went wrong.
And then we are able to see, okay, so I'm currently trying to stop the Redis system
call, is the application succeeded or not?
So we'll use the database, let me check the time, okay.
And we analyze the results.
So these results are made in a relatively small database of about 12 highly popular,
sorry, 15 highly popular cloud applications.
So this is just a subset.
So what you have on the Y axis is a number of system calls that are identified by static
analysis in purple on the binary, on the sources in yellow and then dynamic analysis.
And we run for each of these application both the standard benchmarks that we Redis benchmark
for Redis, WRC for engineings and so on.
And we also run the entire test suite.
So the key idea with the test suite is if you support, I mean, if you measure what's
going on during the entire test suite, you get a very good idea of what are all the possible
system calls that could be done by the application.
Obviously, you need to assume that the test suite has a good coverage, but it is the case
with these very popular applications.
And what we see is, first of all, you know, static analysis overestimates.
This is not very surprising.
The amount of syscalls that is identified by static analysis is relatively high compared
to what we get with dynamic analysis.
And if something interesting too is that the amount of syscalls that can be stubbed or
faked, so the green bits on the dynamic analysis path, it is actually quite, it's non-legligible,
right?
So what this means is that if you want to support Redis with a Redis benchmark where
binary level static analysis tells you that you should implement 100 system calls, if
you just want to run the Redis benchmark to get performance numbers for your paper, you
actually need to implement just 20, right?
So that's what, like, divided by 5, right?
And if you want to pass the entire test suite of Redis, you need to implement about 40.
It's still like half what static analysis is telling you.
So it's kind of a message of hope, right, for building compatibility layers and for
developing custom operating systems in general.
So yes, static analysis overestimates a lot the engineering effort to support a NAP.
And even naive dynamic analysis does measure much more syscalls than what is actually required
if you know that you can stub and fake syscalls.
Another view of these results can be seen here.
So for each of the system calls, you know, 0 is red, 1 is right, 2 is open, I guess,
and so on, among a dataset of about 15 apps, how many of these apps require the implementation
of the system calling question, right?
And then so you have here the result for static analysis at the binary level.
At the source level, this is estray, so without counting which system calls you can stub or
fake, and this is what is actually required.
So if you consider that you will not implement what you stub or fake, this is what you actually
need to implement.
And as you can see, it's much, much, much, much less engineering effort versus what static
analysis is telling you.
Why does stubbing and faking work?
So here you get some code snippet from Redis.
So if you stub, get our limit, the C library wrapper will return minus 1.
And as you can see, Redis will actually fall back on some kind of safe value.
You know, so I'm not able to understand the maximum of files that I can open, so I'm going
to fall back on 100, sorry, 1000.
And the fact that faking works is actually that you have quite a bunch of system calls.
So this is for each system call and each app in our data set, what is the percentage of
apps that are actually checking the return value of the system calls?
And some system calls are almost never checked their return value.
It kind of makes sense, right?
When you see this, why check the return value of close?
And this is why faking work in many cases.
Another question that we asked is, okay, so when you speak about providing binary compatibility
and you don't do porting anymore, basically all the effort of supporting apps is on you,
the operating system developer.
And this is how it should be, in my opinion.
But how much effort does that mean in the long term?
So we had a look at versions of Redis, and Genix, and Apache over the last 10 years,
and what are these calls that actually needs to be implemented in purple.
And we saw that this number does not change very much, right?
So once you make an app and you make it work, it actually means that you need to keep up
to date with the most recent version of this app that are coming up.
But it doesn't necessarily mean a very big engineering effort either.
And these are the support plans.
So we had a look at UniCraft, Fuchsia, which are some operating systems that have already
a relatively good support for a good number of system calls.
And we look at Kerala, so Kerala is another UniCare mail written in Rust.
And it's very, I wouldn't say immature, but it doesn't have support for a lot of system
calls.
And for our set of 15 apps that we had in the database, we derived a support plan.
So for UniCraft, for example, in its current state, it's already supporting most of the
apps of our dataset.
If you want to support an additional app, what you need to do is to implement system
call number 290 and stub these, and then you'll get memcached.
And next, if you implement this C-score, you get H2O.
And then you need to implement these two C-scores, and then you stub that, and you get MongoDB.
So same thing for Fuchsia and Kerala.
Obviously, it's a bit more interesting because this one doesn't support many applications
out of the box.
And I believe I have time to do a quick demo.
Okay, I'm going to do it real quick.
So I'm going to do a test with LS, which is like the simplest test because we don't have
a lot of time.
In the Dockerfile, I just copy a test that I'm going to show you, and then I call, this
is kind of the top level script of loop with a few options that don't matter that much.
And I say, okay, the binary that we are going to instrument is slash bin slash ls, and this
is the parameter.
So I'm going to do ls slash, and we are going to check if it works or not with every possible
C-score that can be invoked by ls.
And the test, which should be there, the test that we are going to run after each execution
of ls to see if things have worked.
So this shell script will take the standard output of ls as parameters, and to make things
simple, I'm just checking that ls actually output something.
I'm doing ls slash, so something should be outputted.
If nothing is output, there is a problem.
And keep in mind that loop is also checking the return value of ls itself.
So okay, so I'm launching loop like this, so it should work.
So what happens under the hood is that we build a container that we've seen the Dockerfile
for.
We are starting two containers in parallel.
Each one is running a full set of tests trying to stub and fake all the system calls, and
we use this to check for differences between the replicas in case there is a problem.
Most of the time, there is no differences.
So it takes a bit of time.
And then, okay, it's done.
So if we go to the database, so we have now much more than 12 apps.
And if we go to ls, the most interesting result is this CSV file, which contains four hc
calls, zero being read, one being write.
Is it called by ls or not?
Can we fake it?
Can we stub it?
Or can we both fake and stub it?
Or it's more like, does the application work when it's faked?
Does it work when it's stub?
And does it work when it's both faked and stub?
And as you can see, some syscalls, like 11, I don't know which one it is, can be both
stub and fake, something for 12, something for 16.
Some syscalls, like this is read, for example, it is called, but you can't stub or fake it,
which kind of makes sense.
And this wouldn't work if you can read.
And yeah, that's pretty much it.
So briefly, what we are currently working on is some more fine-grained measurement.
Some syscalls have kind of sub features, like a lot of programs will require at least a
map anonymous for a map to allocate memory, but not really to map a file.
So we are looking at checking which flags can be stubbed or fake and things like that.
And we are also looking at the virtual file system API.
That's it.
So building compatibility layers is important for custom operating system.
It seems a bit scary, but actually it's not that much engineering effort.