All righty.
So hi, everyone.
I'm Razvan.
We are now part of the microkernel component as a component-based OS dev room.
It's a pleasure to have you all here.
We're going to start right away.
So we have, I think, 10 talks.
We're going to delve into microkernel, UNICOL, and component-based OS topics.
We're going to start with Martin, with his talk on the state of the microkernel environment.
So Martin, please go ahead.
Thank you.
Good morning.
Thanks for coming.
Welcome.
It's my pleasure and honor to open this dev room today.
And it's also a great pleasure that we can continue this tradition of this dev room since
2012.
I would like to thank Razvan for organizing the dev room this year.
And let's go to it.
So my talk will be about the currently developed micro kernels that I'm aware of.
Maybe I'm missing some.
But this should be like an overview.
If you might be interested in seriously using a microkernel or just trying it out, what
you can expect.
This first slide is about me.
I won't go into it.
Let me just say that I have been working with micro kernels and contributing to micro kernels
for almost 20 years now, half of my lifetime.
I assume that most people here do know what a microkernel is, or at least most people
have some kind of idea.
But I will still try to very briefly introduce the micro kernels to you.
Maybe I will save a few minutes for the follow up speakers.
So a microkernel based operating system is a fundamental way how to achieve operating
system reliability and dependability.
By the means of having purpose of the architecture, especially driven by specific design principles.
Now every microkernel has their own design principles.
This is where the different implementations differ, obviously.
But I think there are three common universal design principles, the separation of concerns,
the split of mechanism and policy, and the principle of least privilege.
So this generally results in a system that is modular, customizable, and verifiable,
potentially formally verifiable.
By the way, some micro kernels do have a minimality as an explicit design principle,
but many micro kernels actually don't.
So the micro part in the microkernel and the whole microkernel term is a little bit of
a misnomer, at least as I see it.
Because having the microkernel as small as possible is not necessary.
The a priori goal is just the result of the other design principles.
And I really think that there is no point in comparing whether one microkernel might
have 20,000 lines of code and the other one, 30,000, it's really comparing the post to
oranges.
These design principles also don't affect just the kernel design, but potentially also
the user space design.
So therefore you might see descriptions like microkernel multi-server operating system
with fine-grained components.
This means that not only the kernel is non-monolithic, maybe that would be a better term, but we
are stuck with the microkernel term, but also this might suggest that in many of these systems
also there are no monoliths in the user space.
I have some slides about the history, but I will skip them.
You can go to the slides if you are interested.
Just one note, the idea of micro kernels has been around almost as long as the idea of
operating systems.
So if some people say that micro kernels are strange, are they strange over engineered
idea that proper operating systems should be monolithic because this was the way how
they started and et cetera, I don't think those are very valid arguments.
So let's go to the core of my talk.
There is a website, microkernel.info, which is basically a condensed version of this.
So this is a very simple site that lists the current state of the art open source micro
kernels.
So if you are interested or if you are looking around, going to this site is probably a good
idea.
By the way, this site was started by Yakub Mirmash, my colleague, and I'm maintaining it right
now.
Of course, if you are a microkernel developer and you don't see your project on this site,
just send us a pull request.
It's so simple.
Okay, let's start with the overview.
I should say that there are surprisingly many projects, active projects that are microkernel
based.
And for a microkernel developer, this is really exciting times, I would say.
So Gnode by Gnode Labs is perhaps the most versatile example of a microkernel based operating
system, but I mind you, it's actually not an operating system in the common sense, like
you would consider Windows or a GNU Linux distribution.
It's actually an operating system construction kit.
So it's a way how to pick and match different operating system components, including different
micro kernels or kernels in general, with some user space components and how to build
a bespoke operating system for your specific needs.
So what is really interesting about Gnode that you can really use all these different
micro kernels like SCL4, Fiasco OC, micro hypervisors like Nova, and you can even use their own
custom microkernel, which is called base-HW, or you can even run this infrastructure onto
both Linux for development purposes maybe.
There is strong focus on resource accounting and management in Gnode.
You can read the Gnode book for the details.
Gnode is driven by a commercial company, so they have customers, somebody is paying them
to do that.
They don't state their references publicly, as far as I know.
I might know some, but I'm not in the liberty to name them.
And there is also this thing called Scalp OS, which is like a pre-built distribution of
Gnode.
So if you would like to try something that you don't have to pre-configure in advance
for your specific needs, you can go for that.
This is a picture from Norman Feske, one of the co-authors of Gnode from, I think, FOSDAM
2017.
So maybe the image is a little bit outdated, but I still think it gives you the big picture.
So you have all these components like different kernels, different user space, runtime environments,
if I can say.
So this one is, for example, Unix-like runtime environment, drivers and UI components and
stuff like that.
And you mix and match them.
And then this is a screenshot of the Scalp OS, so like this one instantiation of Gnode.
And you see that it's actually a nice desktop-oriented operating system.
Some final closing remarks to Gnode.
I really like Base-HW, as the bespoke microkernel for Gnode, because it's really nicely integrated
with the rest of the system.
For some reason that I don't know, I don't understand, but there are Gnode guys here,
you can ask them.
I don't see complete feature parity of Base-HW with the other microkernel's support.
So as far as I know, there is no support for hardware virtualization.
And this is not a criticism, this is just a comment.
If you start playing with Gnode, you need to read some documentation.
There is very nice documentation available, no doubt about it.
But really it's not so simple by just downloading an image and running it and expecting a fully
blown desktop environment.
At least not from just by booting it.
You have to do something.
But I think it's definitely worth it.
So there are some links you can follow.
It's an open source project, by the way.
Now let me talk about L4E, which is something slightly similar, some aspects different,
by my current employer, current concept.
So this is also a production grade microkernel-based environment.
A little bit more integrated, I would say, because we basically support just the one
kernel, which we called the L4E microkernel, but you all know it by the name Fiasco.
We use this name currently because Fiasco is a very poor name, trust me.
So we strongly focus on virtualization, we strongly focus on safety and security certification
currently.
And we also have customers, because we are a company that pays us, et cetera.
I'm again not in the liberty to name them, but I can say that if you're going to buy
a new car from a German car manufacturer, there is a high chance you will be running
L4E.
There will be L4E code running in the software stack of that car.
To be honest, the code base is not the most verbosely commented that I have seen, especially
the kernel itself.
So again, the learning curve is a little bit steep, but at least there are some scenarios
you can just build or download and pre-built image, and this will show you the potential
to a certain degree.
And here are some links.
Again, it's an open source project.
Now let's talk about Helen OS, which is to compare with the previous two.
It's a slightly different breed.
So this is like an integrated operating system.
So the purpose is to build it or download an image, boot it, and be presented with a
subenvironment with a shell and some mostly familiar commands which you can use to explore
the system.
So it's not about compile time or deployment time configuration.
It's really about configuring the system at runtime as you go.
What do you expect from a desktop-oriented OS?
And of course, I'm a little bit biased because this is my project, but I would argue that
if you want to understand how a microkernel-based system works inside, this is the one to understand
and to pick because of the lower entry barrier.
The code base is portable, self-contained, well-structured.
So for example, we know how to use directories and not only a single level of them.
So this is how we structure the system to be more understandable.
The code is well-commented, and this is not just my observation.
If you run a tool that will analyze the sources, you will get a number around 30, 35% of commands,
which is not bad.
And believe me, I have seen many microkernel code bases.
I have seen the code of many operating systems in general, and I can tell the difference.
So I would compare Hellen-OS to something like the Solaris kernel in terms of the structure
and commands and stuff like that.
And we also prefer to use our native components, so no ported components or components that
might use some unicernal layers to really make the system feel coherent.
Let's put it that way.
So this is how it looks like when you boot the image, which you can compile or download.
So you have a user interface, a shell, et cetera.
And we have some interesting features that are not present in the other microkernels.
So we are portable not only in theory, but also in real life.
So we support eight different architectures, including strange beasts like Itanium.
And yes, the RISC-V port is still not finished.
And that goes to me.
We are using asynchronous IPC, which transplantry uses shared memory for performance.
We have interrupt controller drivers in user space compared to some other microkernels.
We have a fully decomponentized TCP IP stack.
We support USB 3.0, and we have a sound stack, so just a few highlights.
I will go quickly through these slides.
We don't have the time to go to the details, but the microkernel, while being quite small,
still has a structure.
So we have a well-defined hardware abstraction layer in the kernel.
This is how the user space or how the entire architecture of the system looks like.
So you might see some similarities with the G-node image, but the difference is that all
of this is potentially running in the system for all the time, depending on the actual
configuration of your machine.
And there are some device drivers, which are somehow structured in a tree, starting with
some platform drivers, et cetera.
If you want the details, please come to me.
It's a community-driven effort currently.
So yeah, we are not so fast regarding the development, but we still do some regular
releases.
And sadly, we don't support some of the new hardware features.
If you'd like to contribute, you are more than welcome.
Vuxia by Google is a relatively new kit on the blog.
It's a microkernel-based system that is strongly focusing on the Internet of Things, specifically
their target is to support maintenance, remote management, and remote upgrading of a fleet
of devices.
So imagine, for example, the Google Nest Hub, which is the device where Vuxia is being shipped
currently with, and they even managed to do a remote update of all those Nest Hubs from
the previous Linux-based OS to Vuxia over the air without the users even noticing.
So I think this is quite impressive.
The microkernel is called Zercon, and it's capability-based message-passing microkernel.
And I have spoken to the developers why they don't actually stress that it's a microkernel.
And it's their deliberate choice to somehow underplay, understate that it's a microkernel,
because of some bad press of the term.
So they don't call it a microkernel explicitly, unless you ask them, but it is a microkernel
for sure.
This is how it looks like on the Nest Hub, or this is the way how you can tell whether
your device is still running Linux or is running Vuxia.
And yeah, the learning curve, again, somewhat steep, because this is not a desktop-oriented
system or a server-oriented system that would be Unix-like.
You have to install a non-trivial toolchain and a custom emulator, sort of like when you
do Android development and other things.
But again, what I believe is very nice about Vuxia, that they are only using their own
native core components, not ported components.
And it's an open source project.
Managarb, again, relatively younger operating system, which is microkernel-based, at least
compared to the first three.
One of the key features, a fully asynchronous kernel design, which tries to somehow mitigate
some performance problems by implementing some features in the kernel, which might not
be considered pure by microkernel purists, like the page cache.
And Managarb tries to be compatible with Linux, so they already support the Wayline Protocol
in Western and some other applications.
They even have some accelerated GPU drivers, or at least one.
And it's an open source project, and this is how it looks like.
Of course, you can run more than just the clock there, but yeah, you get the idea.
Redux, another interesting microkernel-based operating system that tries to be Unix-like.
But this one has this primary feature of being implemented almost completely in Rust.
Also the core user-based components are written in Rust, like the libc.
So they have actually a C library written in Rust.
Interesting.
What to say?
Again, POSIX compatibility layer, they already support some interesting end-user applications
and libraries, and it's an open source project again.
And this is how it looks like when you boot it.
So again, you can run a terminal with Bash, in this case, and just explore the system.
A little bit aside, there are also other, let's say, currently non-open source microkernels
being around.
I just tried to mention them here very quickly.
I know it was them, but just to complete the picture.
So Huawei is working on something which they call HomeMonk.
It's actually quite buried under this Harmony OS brand, and it's a little bit confusing
because you might have heard rumors, the original ones, that Harmony OS will be a microkernel
based system, then Huawei released something that was clearly Linux-based.
So yeah, this did not resonate well with our technical folks.
But the point is that this is just a marketing confusion.
So Harmony OS is a common brand for different operating systems.
One of them is Linux-based.
One of them is LiteOS-based, which is a real-time kernel by Huawei.
And the most progressive one unreleased so far is the microkernel-based.
The microkernel was originally inspired by best practices and state-of-the-art in other
micro kernels, but it's a clean slate implementation and design.
For example, they have the capability-based physical memory management in user space,
so the kernel does not manage the physical memory.
It's sort of similar, the design is sort of similar to a CL4, but it's slightly more practical,
in my personal opinion.
Sorry that I can't go into the details.
And they also target safety and security certification.
And actually, this is also running in the wild as trusted execution environment in several
Huawei smartphones.
Then there is this R&D project called DAQ, which is primarily being driven by my former
colleagues at the Dresden Research Center, which tries to be, again, a completely clean
slate design and implementation.
The primary goal was really to use state-of-the-art best practices and software engineering to
achieve really the highest code quality and maintainability.
For example, one of the goals was to be fully MSRAC compliant.
Another goals were high-level safety and security certification and other interesting features.
It's an R&D project.
And honestly, I don't know what's the current state, maybe you can informally ask some of
the Huawei guys here, but it's good to know that this is there.
Very quickly, some other systems.
BlueHort, for 30 years, the intended replacement of Linux in the GNU Linux equation, still alive,
still kicking, still with semi-regular releases.
And yeah, you can actually run 70% of the VM packages on top of it, which is not bad.
Honestly, yes, it's limited to 32-bit x86.
But I always say if they would get one-third, one-fourth of the Linux contributors, they
would finish it in a few months.
ARS, which is a microkernel-based operating system based on the Helios microkernel, which
is supposedly inspired by a CL4.
There will be a talk later today from the author, so I'll skip the details for now.
Composite, another microkernel-based project that is focusing on predictability and component
composition.
The kernel itself is designed as lockless, and it has user space scheduling, and it uses
thread migration IPC.
So if you remember vaguely the idea from Mac 3.0 from Fort Tor, this is the continuation
of that.
And there is UXRT, which is like a user space part built on top of a CL4.
This is still an ongoing project in early stages of the development.
Let's see how it goes.
And finally, let's mention a few standard micro kernels.
So these are not entire operating systems.
These are just the kernel building blocks.
Nova, micro-hypervisor by Udo, is again alive and kicking.
It has been used by bedrock systems as their primary product, as I believe.
So this is one of the projects that sort of went into limbo for many years, and now they
are alive again.
By the way, G-node, I believe, is maintaining their fork of Nova, or maybe Nova with their
own patches.
But there is also HEDRON, which is an official fork of Nova from Cybers, and they are also
using it as their commercial product.
Again, I think there might be Yulian somewhere here who might tell you more.
As CL4, of course, the microkernel with the most, I would say, the most visible formal
verification story.
We need to mention it.
We also need to say that Google has adopted a CL4 recently as their foundation for secure
firmware sort of something like that.
I'm not really sure what are the targets of this cantrip OS, also as Kata OS, but it's
a static configuration mostly.
So it's not a dynamic system, it's a static configuration system.
And in that same area, I would mention also the MOOAN separation kernel, which again is
a separation kernel, so its primary goal is to do static partitioning, but I think it
belongs to the family.
And yeah, sadly there are some microkernels that are interesting, worth looking into for
inspiration, but are currently in limbo, like Escape and three, Linux 3, Herbigalia and Redleaf.
I hope they will be resurrected.
And of course, I might continue with a list of other microkernels that are certifiably
dead.
And of course, those could be resurrected as well, and it's always good to know the
history, right?
Yeah, but I will stop here.
Thank you.
If you have any questions, I would be happy to answer them.
Right, thank you so much, Marty.
If there are, yeah, please.
We have time, yeah, two questions, two questions.
Hello, congratulations for your excellent talk.
Thank you.
Among all those that you studied, which one you think would be more compatible to the
Linux end user base, like for a person to use Linux?
I mean, that is a good question.
Thank you.
So the question is which of those systems would be most Linux compatible?
Most of them actually, most of the systems that I have presented do have some POSIX compatibility
layer.
So I would not make this as the only criterion.
I understand it might be important for you, but I would look also into other aspects of
that, because most of the systems do provide some kind of Linux compatibility.
But if you would be looking for something that is really Linux compatible by design,
or that makes it as one of its primary goals, then I would probably go for Managar.
But again, this is just a first idea, first suggestion.
I would not rule out the others.
Thank you.
Any other questions?
Alex.
Hi.
Thank you for the talk.
So what trends do you think you'll see in the next few years with the microcovid?
That's a tricky question, but thanks for that.
So the question was about the trends.
So I think there will be this kind of retargeting of the systems to very specific use cases,
like Fuxia is doing.
So really implementing custom microcovid-based operating systems that really do fulfill the
specific needs of those areas.
That's one thing.
The other thing that I would like to see, I'm not sure if it's going to happen soon,
but I would like to see more hardware-software co-design.
So basically, the actual appeal of microc terminals is the fact that most current CPUs don't
really provide hardware features that would help the microc terminals, especially in the
terms of performance.
And we see this vicious cycle.
The microc terminals are not performing greatly on the current hardware, so nobody is using
them.
So the hardware vendors don't see a need for changing the CPUs to provide features that
would help the microc terminals.
But I think with RISC-V and the democratization of the hardware design, I think this might
change, hopefully, quite soon.
The third trend that I definitely see, which was probably also seen on the slides, is really
the certifications in terms of safety, security, and hopefully more for more verification,
because this is where microc terminals really excel.
So why not go for it?
Okay.
Thank you so much, Martin.
Thank you.