All right. So, we move on to our next talk. We have Udo here with the Nova Micro-Hypervisor
update. Udo, please.
Thank you, Arsan. Good morning, everybody. Welcome to my talk at Fostem. It's good to
be back here after three years. The last time I presented at Fostem, I gave a talk about
the Nova Micro-Hypervisor on ARMv8, and this talk will cover the things that happened in
an over ecosystem since then. So, just a brief overview of the agenda. For all of those who
might not be familiar with Nova, I'll give a very brief architecture overview and explain
the Nova building blocks. Then we look at all the recent innovations that happened in
Nova in the last three years. I'll talk a bit about the code unification between ARM
and x86, the two architectures that we support at this point. Then I'll spend the majority
of the talk going into details, into all the advanced security features, particularly in
x86, that we added to Nova recently. Towards the end, I'll talk a little bit about performance,
and hopefully we'll have some time for questions.
The architecture in Nova is similar to the micro-carbon-based systems that you've seen
before. At the bottom, we have a kernel which is not just a micro-kernel, it's actually
a micro-hypervisor called the Nova Micro-Hypervisor. On top of it, we have this component-based
multi-server user mode environment. G-node would be one instantiation of it, and Martin
has explained that most micro-kernel-based systems have this structure. In our case,
the hostOS consists of all these colorful boxes. We have a master controller which is
sort of the init process, which manages all the resources that the micro-hypervisor does
not need for itself. We have a bunch of drivers. All the device drivers run in user mode, deprivileged.
We have a platform manager which primarily deals with resource enumeration and power
management. You can run arbitrary host applications, many of them, and there's a bunch of multiplexers.
You want multiplexer that everybody can get a serial console and you have a single interface
to it, or a network multiplexer which acts as some sort of virtual switch. Virtualization
is provided by virtual machine monitors, which are also user mode applications. We have this
special configuration or this special design principle that every virtual machine uses
its own instance of a virtual machine monitor. They don't all have to be the same. For example,
if you run a unique kernel in VM as shown to the far right, the virtual machine monitor
could be much smaller because it doesn't need to deal with all the complexity that you would
find in an OS like Linux or Windows. The entire hostOS consisting of the Nova micro-hypervisor
and the hostOS, the user mode portion of it is what bedrock calls the ultra-visor, which
is a product that we ship. Once you have virtualization there that is very small, very secure, and
basically sits outside the guest operating system, you can build interesting features
like virtual machine introspection or virtualization assisted security which uses features like
nested paging, breakpoints, and patch-tivver overrides to harden the security of the guest
operating systems like protecting critical data structures, introspecting memory, and
also features in the virtual switch for doing access control between the different virtual
machines and the outside world as to who can send what types of packets. All of that is
another product which is called ultra-security. The whole stack, not just the kernel, the
whole stack is undergoing rigorous formal verification and one of the properties that
this formal verification effort is proving is what we call the bare metal property. The
bare metal property basically says that combining all these virtual machines on a single hypervisor
has the same behavior as if you were running these as separate physical machines connected
by a real ethernet switch so that whatever happens in a virtual machine could have happened
on a real physical machine that was not virtualized. That's what the bare metal property says.
So the building blocks of NOVA are those that you would find in an ordinary microkernel.
It's basically address spaces, threads, and IPC. In NOVA address spaces are called protection
domains or PD, and threads or virtual CPUs are called execution contacts, short EC. For
those of you who don't know NOVA very well, I've just given a very brief introductory
slide for how all these mechanisms interact. So let's say you have two protection domains,
PD, A, and B. Each of them have one or more threads inside, and obviously at some point
you want to intentionally cross these protection domain boundaries because these components
somehow need to communicate, and that's what IPC is for. So assume that this client thread
wants to send a message to the server thread. It has a thread control block, which is like
a message box, puts the message in there, invokes a call, an IPC call to the hypervisor,
it vectors through a portal which routes that IPC to the server protection domain, and then
the server receives the message in its UTCB. As part of this control and data transfer,
the scheduling context, which is a time slice coupled with a priority, is donated to the
other side, and as you can see on the right, that's the situation after the IPC call has
gone through. So now the server is executing on the scheduling context of the client. The
server computes a reply, puts it in its UTCB, issues a hypercall called IPC reply, and the
data goes back, the reply goes back to the client, the scheduling context donation is
reverted, and the client gets its time slice back. So what you get with that is very fast
synchronous IPC with time donation and priority inheritance, and it's very fast because there's
no scheduling decision on that path. Also, NOVA is a capability-based microkernel or
hypervisor, which means all operations that user components do with the kernel have capabilities
as parameters, and capabilities have the nice property that they both name a resource and
at the same time have to convey what access you have on that resource. So it's a very
powerful access control primitive. So that said, let's look at all the things that happened
in NOVA over the last two and a half or so years, and we are now on a release cadence
where we put out a new release of NOVA approximately every two months. So it's always the year
and the week of the year where we do releases, and this shows what we added in NOVA in 21,
22, and what we'll add to the first release of this year at the end of this month. So
we started out at the beginning of 21 by unifying the code base between x86 and ARM, making
the load address flexible, adding power management like suspend resume, then extended that support
to ARM. And later in 22, when that unification was complete, we started adding a lot of,
let's say advanced security features in x86 like control flow enforcement, code patching,
cache allocation technology, multiple spaces, multi-key total memory encryption, and recently
we've added some APIC virtualization. So the difference between the things that are listed
in bold here and those that are not listed in bold, everything in bold I'll try to cover
in this talk, which is a lot, so hopefully we'll have enough time to go through all this.
First of all, the design goals that we have in NOVA, and Martine already mentioned that
not all micro-chronas have the same design goals. Our design goal is that we want to
provide the same or at least similar functionality across all architectures, which means the
API is designed in such a way that it abstracts from architectural differences as much as
possible, that you get a uniform experience, whether you're on x86 and ARM, you can create
a thread and you don't have to worry about details of instructions that registers that
page table format. NOVA tries to abstract all of that away. We want to have really simple
build infrastructure, and you'll see in a moment what the directory layout looks like,
but suffice it to say that you can build NOVA with a very simple make command, where you
say make architecture equals x86 or ARM, and in some cases board equals, I don't know,
raspberry pi or NXP, I'm x8, whatever, and it runs for maybe five seconds and then you
get a binary. We use standardized processes, like the standardized boot process and standardized
resource enumeration as much as possible, because that allows for a great reuse of code.
So we use multi-boot version two or one, and UEFI for booting, we use ACPI for resource
enumeration, we can also use the FDT, but that's more of a fallback, and for ARM there's
this interface called PSCI for power state coordination that's also abstracting this
functionality across many different ARM boards. So we try to use these interfaces as much
as possible. The code is designed in such a way that it is formally verifiable, and
in our particular case that means formally verifying highly concurrent C++ code, not
C code, not assembler code, but C++ code, and even weakly ordered memory, because ARM
V8 is weak memory. And obviously we want to be, we want Nova to be modern, small, and
fast, best in class security and performance. And we'll see how we did on that. So first,
let me talk about the code structure, and Martin mentioned in this talk this morning
that using directories to your advantage can really help. So on the right you see the directory
structure that we have in the unified Nova code base. We have generic Inc directory and
the generic source directory, those are the ones listed in green, and then we have architecture
specific subdirectories for ARX64 and X8664, and we have architecture specific build directories.
There's also a doc directory in which you will find the Nova interface specification
and there's a single makefile unified. And when we looked at the source code and we discussed
them with our formal message engineers, we recognized that basically all the functions
can be categorized into three different buckets. The first one is what we call the same API
and same implementation. This is totally generic code. All the system calls are totally generic
code. All the memory allocators are totally generic code. Surprisingly, even page tables
can be totally generic code. So these can all share the source files, the header files,
and the spec files, which basically describe the interface pre and post conditions. The
second bucket is functions that have the same API, but maybe a different implementation.
And an example of that would be a timer where the API could be set a deadline for when a
timer interrupt should fire. So the API for all callers is the same. So you can potentially
share the header or the spec file, but the implementation might be different on each
architecture or it's very likely different. And the final bucket is those functions that
have a different API and implementation and you can't share anything. So the code structure
is such that architecture specific code lives in the architecture specific sub directories
and generic code lives in the sort of parent directories of that. And whenever you have
an architecture specific file with the same name as a generic file, the architecture specific
file takes precedence and basically overrides or shadows the generic file. And that makes
it very easy to move files from architecture specific to generic and back. So the unified
code base that we ended up with, and these are the numbers from the very recent upcoming
release 23.08, which will come out at the end of this month, shows sort of what we ended
up with in terms of architecture specific versus generic code. So in the middle of the
green part is the generic code that's shared between all architectures and it's 4,300 lines
today. X86 adds 7,000 and some lines specific code and ARM to the right adds some 5,600
lines. So if you sum that up for X86, it's roughly 11,500 lines and for ARM it's less
than 10,000 lines of code. So it's very small. And if you look at it, ballpark 40% of the
code for each architecture is generic and shareable. And that's really great not just
from a maintainability perspective, but also from a verifiability perspective because you
have to specify and verify those generic portions only once. If you compile that into binaries,
then the resulting binaries are also very small, like a little less than 70K in code
size. And obviously if you use a different compiler version or a different Nova version,
these numbers will slightly differ, but it gives you an idea of how small the code base
and how small the binaries will be. So let's look at some interesting aspects of the architecture
because assume you've downloaded Nova, you've built such a small binary from source code
and now you want to boot it. And typical boot procedure, both on X86 and ARM, which are
converging towards using UFI as firmware, will basically have this structure where UFI
firmware runs first and then invokes some bootloader passing some information like an
image handle and the system table. And then the bootloader runs and invokes a Nova micro
hypervisor passing also the image handle and the system table maybe adding multi-boot information.
And at some point there will have to be a platform handover of all the hardware from
firmware to the operating system, in our case Nova. And this handover point is called exit
boot services. It's basically the very last function that you call as either a bootloader
or a kernel in firmware and that's the point where firmware stops accessing all the hardware
and the ownership of the hardware basically transitions over to the kernel. And the unfortunate
situation is that as you call exit boot services, firmware, which may have enabled the IOMU
or SMU at boot time to protect against DMA attacks, drops it at this point, which sounds
kind of silly, but that's what happens. And the reason if you ask those who are familiar
with UFI is for legacy OS support because UFI assumes that maybe the next stage is a
legacy OS which can't deal with DMA protections so it gets turned off, which is really unfortunate
because between the point where you call exit boot services to take over the platform hardware
and the point where Nova can actually enable the IOMU, there is this window of opportunity
shown in red here where there's no DMA protections and that's the point. It's very small, maybe
a few nanoseconds or microseconds where an attacker could perform a DMA attack. And for
that reason Nova takes complete control of the exit boot services flow so it's not the
bootloader who calls exit boot services. Nova actually drives the UFI infrastructure and
it disables all bus master activity before calling exit boot services so that we eliminate
this window of opportunity. That was a very aggressive change in Nova because it means
Nova has to comprehend UFI. The next thing that we added was a flexible
load address. So when the bootloader wants to put a binary into physical memory it invokes
it with paging being disabled, which means you have to load it at some physical address.
And you can define an arbitrary physical address but it would be good if whatever physical
address you define worked on all the boards. And that is simply impossible, especially
in the ARM ecosystem. So on ARM some platforms have the DRAM starting at physical address
zero, some have MMIO starting at address zero so you will not find a single physical address
range that works across all ARM platforms where you can say always load Nova at two
megabytes, one gigabyte, whatever. So we made the load address flexible. Also the bootloader
might want to move Nova to a dedicated point in memory like at the very top so that the
bottom portion can be given one to one to a VM. So the load address is now flexible
for Nova. Not fully flexible but you can move Nova up down by arbitrary multiples of two
megabytes so at super page boundaries. And the interesting insight into this is for pulling
this off there is no L3 location complexity required. Nova consists of two sections, a
very small init section which is mapped, which is identity map, which means virtual addresses
equal physical addresses and that's the code that initializes the platform up to the point
where you can enable paging. And then there's a runtime section which runs paged so it has
virtual to physical memory mappings. And for those virtual to physical memory mappings,
if you run this paging enabled, the physical addresses that back these virtual memory ranges
simply don't matter. So paging is basically some form of relocation. You only need to
deal with relocation for the init section and you can solve that by making the init
section be position independent code. And it's assembler anyway so making that position
independent is not hard. We actually didn't make the code just position independent, it
is also mode independent which means no matter if you EFI starts you in 32 bit mode or 64
bit mode, that code is dealing with all these situations. There's a limit, an artificial
limit of you still have to load Nova below four gigabytes because multi-boot has been
defined in such a way that you can't express addresses above four gigabytes because some
of these structures are still 32 bit and that little emoticon expresses what we think of
that. So then after we had figured this out, we wanted to do some power management and
this is an overview of all the power management that ACPI defines. So ACPI defines a few global
states like working, sleeping and off. Those aren't all that interesting. The really interesting
states are the sleep states and the things that have this black bold border around it
is the state in which the system is when it's fully up and running, no idling, no sleeping,
no nothing. It's called the S0 working state and then there's some sleep state. You might
know suspend to run, suspend to disk and soft off. And when you're in the S0 working state
you can have a bunch of idle states and in the C0 idle state you can have a bunch of
performance state which roughly correspond to voltage and frequency scaling so ramping
up the clock speed up and down. So unfortunately we don't have a lot of time to go into all
the details of these sleep states but I want to still say a few words about this. We implemented
suspend resume on both x86 and ARM and there's two ways you can go about it. One which is
I would say a brute force approach and the other which is the smart approach. And the
brute force approach basically goes like you look at all the devices that lose their state
during a suspend resume transition and you save the entire register state. And that's
a significant amount of state that you have to manage and it may even be impossible to
manage it because if you have devices with hidden internal state you may not be able
to get at it or if the device has a hidden internal state machine you may not know what
the internal state of that device is at that point. So it may be suitable for some generic
devices like if you wanted to save the configuration space of every PCI device that's generic enough
that you could do that. But for some interrupt controllers or SMUs with internal state that's
not smart. So for that you can actually use the second approach which Nova uses which
is to save a high level configuration and you initialize the device based on that. So
as an example say you had an interrupt routed to core zero in edge triggered mode. You would
save that as a high level information and that's sufficient to re-initialize all the
interrupt controllers all the redirection entries all the trigger modes based on just
this bit of information. So there's lots less information to maintain. Saving becomes basically
a no-op. Restoring can actually use the same code pass that you used to initially bring
up that particular device. And that's the approach for all the interrupt controllers
all the SMUs all the devices managed by Nova. The next thing I want to briefly talk about
is P-states performance states which are these gears for ramping up the clock speed on x86
and Nova can now deal with all these P-states. The interesting aspect is that most modern
x86 processors have something called turbo mode and turbo mode allows one or more processors
to exceed the nominal clock speed to actually turbo up higher if other cores are idle. So
if other cores are not using their thermal or power headroom a selected set of cores
maybe just one core maybe a few other cores can actually turbo up many bins and this is
shown here on active core zero which basically gets the thermal headroom of core one core
two and core three to clock up higher. So Nova will exploit that feature when it's available
but there are situations where you want predictable performance where you want every core to run
at its guaranteed high frequency mode and there's a command line parameter that you
can set that basically clamps the maximum speed to the guaranteed frequency. You could
also lower the frequency to something less than the guaranteed frequency. There's a point
an operating point it's called maximum efficiency and there's even points below that where you
can clock really high but then it's actually less efficient than this point. So all of
that is also supported. So as an overview from a feature comparison perspective ARM
versus x86 we support P-states on x86 not on ARM because there is no generic interface
on ARM yet. We support all the S-states on x86 like stop clock, suspend resume, hibernation
power off, platform reset. On ARM there's no such concept as S1 but we also support
suspend resume and suspend to disk if it's supported and what does it mean if it's supported
it means if platform firmware like PSCI implements it and there are some features that are mandatory
and some features that are optional. Suspend resume for example works great on the NXP
IMAX8M that Stefan had for his demo. It doesn't work so great on Raspberry Pi because the
firmware simply has no support for jumping back to the operating system after a suspend.
So it's not a Nova limitation. There's a new suspend feature called low power idle which
we don't support yet because it requires way more support than just Nova. It basically
requires powering down the GPU, powering down all the devices, powering down all the links
so this is a concerted platform effort. But from a hypercore perspective the hypercore
that you would invoke to transition the platform to a sleep set is called control hardware
and whenever you try to invoke it with something that's not supported it returns bad feature
and for the hypercalls that assign devices or interrupts the state that the system had
when you assigned devices or interrupts to particular domains will completely be preserved
across the suspend resume calls using this safety high-level state approach.
So next I'll talk about some radical API change that we made and being a microkernel and not
being Linux we don't have to remain backward compatible so that's one of these major API
changes that took quite a lot of time to implement. What we had in the past was basically an interface
with five kernel objects, protection domains, execution context, scheduling context, portals
and summer force and every protection domain looked as shown on this slide. It actually
had six resource spaces built into it. An object space which hosts capabilities to all
the kernel objects that you have access to, a host space which represents the stage one
page table, a guest space which represents the stage two guest page table, the M.A. space
for memory transactions that are remapped by the IOMU, port I.O. space and an MSR space.
So all of these existed in one single instance in every protection domain and when you created
a host EC, a guest EC like a virtual CPU or device they were automatically bound to the
PD and picking up the spaces that they needed. And that is, that worked great for us for
more than ten years but it turned out to be suboptimal for some more advanced use cases
like nested virtualization. If you run a hypervisor inside a virtual machine and that hypervisor
creates multiple guests itself then you suddenly need more than one guest space. You need one
guest space per sub-guest. So you need multiple of these yellow guest spaces. Or when you
virtualize the SMMU and the SMMU has multiple contexts and every context has its own page
table then you suddenly need more than one DMA space. So you need more of these blue
boxes and the same can be said for port I.O. and MSR spaces. So how do we get more than
one if the protection domain has all these singleton? So what we did and it was quite
a major API in internal reshuffling is we separated these spaces from the protection
domain. There are now new first class objects. So Nova just got six new kernel objects that
you get when you create them you get individual capabilities for them and you can manage them
independently from the protection domain. So the way that this works is first you create
a protection domain with create PD then you create one or more of these spaces again with
create PD so that's a sub-function of create PD and then you create an EC like a host EC
and it binds to those spaces that are relevant for host EC. So host EC like a hyper spread
needs capabilities so it needs an object space it binds to that it needs a stage one page
table so it binds to that and it needs access to ports so it binds to that on x86 only because
on ARM there's no such thing. So for host thread all these assignments are static. We
could make them flexible but we have not found a need. It gets more interesting for a guest
EC which is a virtual CPU that runs in a guest. So again the sequence is the same you first
create a protection domain then you create one or more of these spaces and when you create
the virtual CPU it binds to those spaces that it urgently needs which is the object space
and the host space. It does not yet bind to any of the flexible spaces shown to the right
and that binding is established on the startup IPC during IPC reply you pass selectors capability
selectors to these spaces that you want to attach to and then you flexibly bind to those
spaces as denoted by these dashed lines and that assignment can be changed on every event
so every time you take a VM exit Nova synthesizes an exception IPC or architectural IPC sends
it to the VM for handling and when the VM replies it can set a bit in the message transfer
descriptor to say I want to change the space assignment it passes new selectors and then
you can flexibly switch between those spaces and that allows us to implement for example
nested virtualization. The same for a device which in x86 is represented by a bus device
function or an arm is represented by a stream ID the assigned depth hypercall can flexibly
rebind the device to a DMA space at any time. So that took quite a while to implement but
it gives us so much more flexibility and I heard that some of the Nova forks have come
across the same problem so maybe that's something that could work for you too.
So let's talk about page tables and I mentioned earlier that page tables are actually generic
code which is somewhat surprising. Nova manages three page tables per architecture the stage
one which is a host page table the stage two which is the guest page table and a DMA page
table which is used by the IOMU and these correspond to the three memory spaces that
I showed in the previous slide. And the way we made this page table code architecture
independent is by using a template base class which is completely logless so it's very scalable
and the reason why it can be logless is because the IOMU doesn't honor any software logs anyway
so if you put a log around your page table infrastructure the IOMU wouldn't know anything
about those logs. So it has to be written in a way that it does atomic transformations
anyway so that the IOMU never sees an inconsistent state. And once you have this there's also
no need to put the log around it for any software updates so that's completely log free. And
that architecture independent base class deals with all the complexities of allocating and
deallocating page tables splitting super pages into page tables or over mapping page tables
with super pages and you can derive architecture specific subclasses from it and the subclasses
themselves inject themselves as a parameter to the base class that's called the Curiously
Recurring Template Pattern. And the subclasses then do the transformation between the high
level attributes like this page is readable, writable, user accessible, whatever into the
individual bits encoding of the page table entries as that architecture needs it. And
also there are some coherency requirements on ARM and some coherency requirements between
SMUs that don't snoop the caches so these architecture specific subclasses deal with
all that complexity but it allows us to share the page table class and to specify and verify
it only once. So let's look at page tables in a little bit more detail because there
are some interesting stuff you need to do on ARM. So most of you who've been in an OS
or who've written a microkernel will have come across this page table format where an
input address like a host virtual or guest physical address is split up into an offset
portion into the final page 12 bits and then you have 9 bits indexing into the individual
levels of the page table. So when an address is transformed by the MMU into a virtual address
into a physical address the MMU first uses bits 30 to 38 to index into the level 2 page
table to find the level 1 and then to find the level 0 and the walk can terminate early
you can have a leaf page at any level so it gives you 1 gigabyte, 2 megabyte or 4k super
patches. And with that page table structure like this, 3 levels you can create an address
space of 512 gigabytes of size and that should be good enough but it turns out we came across
several ARM platforms which have an address space size of 1 terabyte. So twice that they
need one extra bit which you can't represent with 39 bits so you have a 40 bit address
space. So what would you do if you were designing a chip? You would expect that it would just
open a new level here and that you get a 4 level page table. But ARM decided differently
because they said if I just add one bit the level 3 page table would have just two entries
and that's not worse building basically another level into it. So what they did is they came
up with a concept called the concatenated page table and it makes the level 2 page table
twice as large by adding another bit at the top. So now suddenly the level 2 page table
has 10 bits of indexing and the backing page table has 1024 entries and it's 8k in size.
And this concept was extended so if you go to 41 address space again you get one additional
bit and the page table gets larger and this keeps going on. It can extend to up to 4 bits
that the level 2 page table is 64k in size. And there's no way around it. The only time
at which you can actually open the level 3 is when you exceed 44 bits and then when you
get 44 bits you can go to a 4 level and it looks like this. So the functionality that
we also had to add to Nova is to comprehend this concatenated page table format so that
we can deal with arbitrary address space sizes on ARM. And we actually had a device, I think
it was a Xilinx DCU102 which had something mapped above 512 gigabytes and just below
1 terabyte and you can't pass that through to a guest if you don't have concatenated
page chips. So the generic page table cluster we have right now is so flexible that it can
basically do what's shown on this slide. And the simple case is x86. You have 3 level,
4 level of high level page tables with a uniform structure of 9 bits per level and 12 offset
bits. 39 isn't used by the MMU but might be used by the SMMU and the MMU typically uses
4 levels and in high end boxes like servers for 57. On ARM, depending on what type of
SOC you have, it either has something between 32 or up to 52 physical address bits and the
table shows the page table level split, the indexing split that Nova has to do and all
these colored boxes are basically instances of concatenated page tables. So 42 would require
3 bits to be concatenated. Here we have 4, here we have 1, here we have 2. So we really
have to exercise all of those and we support all of those. And unlike the past where Nova
said page tables is so many levels per so many bits, we now have turned this around
by saying the page table covers so many bits and we can compute the number of bits per
level and the concatenation at the top level automatically in the code. So that was another
fairly invasive change. While we were at re-architecting all the page tables, we took advantage of
a new feature that Intel added to Ice Lake servers and to all the Lake desktop platforms
which is called total memory encryption with multiple keys. And what Intel did there is
they repurposed certain bits of the physical address in the page table entry, the top bits
shown here as key ID bits. And so it's stealing some bits from the physical address and the
key ID bits indexed into a key programming table shown here that basically select a slot
and let's say you have 4 key bits that gives you 16 keys, 2 to the power 4. So your key
indexing or your key programming table would have the opportunity to program 16 different
keys. We've also come across platforms that have 6 bits. It's basically flexible how many
bits are stolen from the physical address can vary per platform depending on how many
keys are supported. And those keys are used by a component called the memory encryption
engine. The memory encryption engine sits at the perimeter of the package or the socket,
basically at the boundary where data leaves the chip that you plug in the socket and enters
the interconnect and enters RAM. So inside this green area which is inside the SOC, everything
is unencrypted in the cores, in the caches, in the internal data structure. But as it
leaves the die and moves out to the interconnect, it gets encrypted automatically by the memory
encryption engine with the key. And this example shows a separate key being used for each virtual
machine which is a typical use case but it's actually way more flexible than that. You
can select the key on a per page basis. So you could even say if there was a need for
these two VMs to share some memory that some blue pages would appear here and some yellow
pages would appear here. That's possible. So we added support in the page tables for
encoding these key ID bits. We added support for using the P-config instruction for programming
keys into the memory encryption engine. And the keys can come in two forms. You can either
randomly generate them, in which case Nova will also drive the digital random number
generator to generate entropy, or you can program tenant keys. So you can say I want
to use this particular AS key for encrypting the memory. And that's useful for things like
VM migration where you want to take an encrypted VM and move it from one machine to another.
And the reason why Intel introduced this feature is for confidential computing but also because
DRAM is slowly moving towards non-volatile RAM. And an offline either made a tag or so
where somebody unplugs your RAM or takes your non-volatile RAM and then looks at it in another
computer is a big problem. And they can still unplug your RAM but they would only see ciphertext.
So next thing we looked at was, so this was more of a confidentiality improvement. Next
thing we looked at is improving the availability. And we added some support for dealing with
noisy neighbor domains. So what are noisy neighbor domains? Let's say you have a quad
core system as shown on this slide. And you have a bunch of virtual machines as shown
at the top. On some cores you may over provision the cores, run more than one VM, like on core
0 and core 1. For some use cases you might want to run a single VM on a core only like
a real-time VM which is exclusively assigned to core 2. But then on some cores like shown
on the far right you may have a VM that's somewhat misbehaving. And somewhat misbehaving
means it uses excessive amounts of memory and basically evicts everybody else out of
the cache. So if you look at the last level cache portion here, the amount of cache that
is assigned to the noisy VM is very disproportionate to the amount of cache given to the other
VM simply because this is trampling all over memory. And this is very undesirable from
a predictability perspective, especially if you have a VM like the green one that's real-time
which may want to have most of its working set in the cache. So is there something we
can do about it? And yes, there is. It's called CAT. CAT is Intel's acronym for Cache Allocation
Technology and what they added in the hardware is a concept called Class of Service. And
you can think of Class of Service as a number and again like the key ID there's a limited
number of classes of service available like 4 or 16 and you can assign this Class of Service
number to each entity that shares the cache. So you could make it a property of a protection
domain or a property of a thread. And for each of the classes of service you can program
a capacity bitmask which says what proportion of the cache can this Class of Service use?
Can it use 20%, 50% and even which portion? There are some limitations like the bitmask
must be contiguous but they can overlap for sharing and there's a model specific register
which is not cheap to program where you can say this is the active class of service on
this core right now. So this is something you would have to contact switch to say I'm
now using something else. And when you use this it improves the predictability like the
worst case execution time quite nicely and that's what it was originally designed for
but it turns out it also helps tremendously with dealing with cache side channel attacks
because if you can partition your cache in such a way that your attacker doesn't allocate
into the same ways as the VM you're trying to protect then all the flush and reload attacks
simply don't work. So here's an example for how this works and to the right I've shown
an example number of six classes of service and a cache which has 20 ways. And you can
program and this is again just an example you can program the capacity bitmask for each
class of service for example to create full isolation. So you could say class of service
gets 40% of the cache, ways 0 through 7 and class of service 1 gets 20% and everybody
else gets 10% and these capacity bitmas don't overlap at all which means you get zero interference
through the level 3 cache. You could also program them to overlap. There's another mode
which is called CDP, code and data prioritization, which splits the number of classes of service
in half and basically redefines the meaning of these bitmas to say those with an even
number are for data and those with an odd number are for code. So you can even discriminate
how the cache is being used between code and data. It gives you more fine-grained control
and the Nova API forces users to declare upfront whether they want to use cat or CDP to partition
their cache and only after you've made that decision can you actually configure the capacity
bitmas. So with CDP it would look like this. You get three classes of service instead of
six distinguished between D and C, data and code and you could for example say class of
service 1 as shown on the right gets 20% of the cache for data, 30% of cache for the code
so 50% of the capacity in total exclusively assigned to anybody who is class of service
1 and the rest shares capacity bitmas and here you see an example of how the bitmas
can overlap and wherever they overlap the cache capacity is being competitively shared.
So that's also a new feature that we support right now. Now the question is class of service
is something you need to assign to cache sharing entities to what type of object do you assign
that and you could assign it to a protection domain. You could say every box on the architecture
slide gets assigned a certain class of service and the question is then what do you assign
to a server that has multiple clients. It's really unfortunate and what it also means
is if you have a protection domain that spends multiple cores and you say I want this protection
domain to use 40% of the cache you have to program the class of service settings on all
cores the same way. So it's really a loss of flexibility. So that wasn't our favorite
choice and you said maybe we should assign class of service to execution contexts instead
and again the question is what class of service do you assign to a server execution context
that does work on behalf of clients and the actual killer argument was that you would
need to set the class of service in this model specific register again during each context
switch which is really bad for performance. So even option two is not what we went for.
Instead we made the class of service a property of the scheduling context and it has very
nice properties. We only need to conduct switches during scheduling decisions so the cost of
reprogramming that MSR is really not relevant anymore and it extends the already existing
model of time and priority donation with class of service donation. So a server does not
need to have a class of service assigned to it at all. It uses the class of service of
its clients. So if let's say your server implements some file system then the amount of cache
that it can use depends on whether your client can use a lot of cache or whether your client
cannot use a lot of cache. So it's a nice extension of an existing feature and the additional
benefit is that the class of service can be programmed differently per core. So eight
cores times six classes of service gives you 48 classes of service in total instead of
six. So that was a feature for availability. We also added some features for integrity.
And if you look at the history there's a long history of features being added to paging
that improve the integrity of code against injection attacks. And it all started out
many years ago with these 64 bit architecture where you could mark pagers non-executable
and you could basically enforce that pagers are either writable or executable but never
both. So there's no confusion between data and code. And then over the years more features
were added like supervisor mode execution prevention where if you use that feature kernel
code can never jump into a user page and be confused as executing some user code. And
then there's another feature called supervisor mode access prevention which even says kernel
code can never without explicitly declaring that it wants to do that read some user data
page. So all of these tighten the security and naturally Nova supports them. There's
a new one called mode based execution control which is only relevant for guest page tables
or stage two which gives you two separate execution bits. So there's not a single X
bit there's no executable for user and executable for super user. And that is a feature that
ultra security can for example use where we can say even if the guest screws up its page
tables its stage one page tables the stage two page tables can still say Linux user applications
or Linux kernel code can never execute Linux user application code if it's marked as XS
in the stage two page tables. So it's again a feature that can tighten the security of
guest operating systems from the host. But even if you have all that there's still opportunities
for code injection and these classes of attacks basically reuse existing code snippets and
chain them together in interesting ways using control flow hijacking like ROP attacks and
I'm not sure who's familiar with ROP attacks it's basically you create a call stack with
lots of return addresses that chain together simple code snippets like at this register
return multiply this register return jump to this function return and by chaining them
all together you can build programs out of existing code snippets that do what the attacker
wants you don't have to inject any code you simply find snippets in existing code that
do what you want. And this doesn't work so well on ARM it still works on ARM but on ARM
the instruction length is fixed to four bytes so you can't jump into the middle of instructions
but on x86 with the flexible instruction size you can even jump into the middle of instructions
and completely reinterpret what existing code looks like and that's quite unfortunate so
there's a feature that tightens the security around that and it's called control flow enforcement
technology or CET and that feature adds integrity to the control flow graph both to the forward
edge and to the backward edge and forward edge basically means you protect jumps or
calls that jump from one location forward to somewhere else and the way that this works
is that the legitimate jump destination where you want the jump to land this landing pad
must have a specific end branch instruction placed there and if you try to jump to a place
which doesn't have an end branch landing pad then you get the control flow violation exception
so you need the help of the compiler to put that landing pad at the beginning of every
legitimate function and luckily GCC and other compilers have had that support for quite
a while so GCC since 8 and we are now at 12 so that works for forward edges. For backward
edges there's another feature called shadow stack and that protects the return addresses
on your stack and we'll have an example later and it basically has a shadow call stack which
you can't write to. It's protected by paging and if it's writable then it won't be usable
as a shadow stack and you can independently compile Nova with branch protection, with
return address protection or both. So let's look at indirect branch tracking and I try
to come up with a good example and I actually found a function in Nova which is suitable
to explaining how this works. Nova has a body allocator that can allocate contiguous chunks
of memory and that body allocator has a free function where you basically return an address
and say free this block and the function is really as simple as shown there. It just consists
of these few instructions because it's a tail call that jumps to some coalescing function
here later and you don't have to understand all the complicated assembler but suffice
it to say that there's a little test here of these two instructions which performs some
meaningful check and you know that you can't free a null pointer. So this test checks if
the address passed as the first parameter is a null pointer and if so it jumps out right
here so basically the function does nothing, does no harm, it's basically a knob. Let's
say an attacker actually wanted to compromise memory and instead of jumping to the beginning
of this function it wanted to jump past that check to this red instruction to bypass the
check and then corrupt memory. Without control flow enforcement that would be possible if
the attacker could gain execution but with control flow it wouldn't work because when
you do a call or jump you have to land on an end branch instruction and the compiler
has put that instruction there. So if an attacker managed to get control and try to jump to
a vtable or some indirect pointer to this address you would immediately crash. So this
is how indirect branch tracking works. Shadow stacks work like this. With a normal data
stack you have your local variables on your stack, you have the parameters for the next
function on the stack so the green function wants to call the blue function and then when
you do the call instruction the return address gets put on your stack. Then the blue function
puts its local variables on the stack, wants to call the yellow function, puts the parameters
for the yellow function on the stack, calls the yellow function so the return address
for the blue function gets put on a stack. And you see in the stack goes downward and
you see that the return address always lives above the local variables. So if you're local
variables if you allocate an array on a stack and you don't have proper bounce checking
it's possible to overwrite the return address by writing pass the array and this is a popular
attack technique buffer overflow exploits that you find in the wild. So if you have
code that is potentially susceptible to these kind of return address overwrites then you
could benefit from shadow stacks. And the way that this works is there's a separate
stack this shadow stack which is protected by paging so you can't write to it with any
ordinary memory instructions it's basically invisible and the only instructions that can
write to it are call and read instructions and some shadow management instructions. And
when the green function calls the blue function the return address will not just be put on
the ordinary data stack but will additionally be put on a shadow stack and likewise with
the blue and the yellow return address. And whenever you execute a return instruction
the hardware will compare the two return addresses that it pops off the two stacks and if they
don't match you again get a control flow violation. So that way you can protect the backward edge
of the control flow graph also using shadow stacks and that's a feature that Nova uses
on Tiger Lake and all the lake and platforms beyond that that have this feature. But there's
a problem and the problem is that using shadow stack instructions is possible on newer CPUs
that have these instructions that basically have this ISA extension but if you have a
binary containing those instructions it would crash on all the CPUs that don't comprehend
that. And luckily it will define the end branch instruction to be a knob but some shadow stack
instructions are not knobs. So if you try to execute a CET enabled Nova binary on something
older without other effort it might crash. So obviously we don't want that. So what Nova
does instead it detects at runtime whether CET is supported and if CET is not supported
it patches out all these CET instructions in the existing binary to turn them into knobs.
And obviously being a microkernel we try to generalize the mechanism. So we generalize
that mechanism to be able to rewrite arbitrary assembler snippets from one version to another
version. And there's other examples for newer instructions that do better work than older
instructions like the X-Save feature set which can save supervisor state or save floating
point state in a compact format. And the binary as you build it originally always uses the
most sophisticated version. So it uses the most advanced instruction that you can find.
And if you run that on some CPU which doesn't support the instruction or which supports
some older instruction then we use code patching to rewrite the newer instruction into the
older one. So the binary automatically adjusts to the feature set of the underlying hardware.
The newer your CPU the less patching occurs but it works quite well. And the reason we
chose this approach because the alternatives aren't actually great. So the alternatives
would have been that you put some if devs in your code and you say if dev CET use the
CET instructions and otherwise don't. And then you force your customers or your community
to always compile the binary the right way and that doesn't scale. The other option
could have been that you put some if then else. You say if CET is supported do this
otherwise do that. And that would be a runtime check every time and that runtime check is
prohibitive in certain code paths like NT paths where you simply don't have any register
free for doing this check because you have to save them all. But in order to save them
you already need to know whether shadow stacks are supported or not. So doing this feature
check at boot time and rewriting the binary to the suitable instruction is what we do
and that works great. So the way it works is you declare some assembler snippets like
XSaf S is the preferred version. If XSaf S is not supported the snippet gets rewritten
to XSaf or a shadow stack instruction gets rewritten to a knob. We don't need to patch
any high level C++ functions because they never compile to those complicated instructions
and we basically have a binary that automatically adjusts. So finally let's take a look at performance
because IPC performance is still a relevant metric if you want to be not just small but
also fast. And the blue bars here in the slide show Nova's baseline performance on modern
Intel platforms like NUC12 with Alder Lake and NUC11 with Tiger Lake. And you can see
that if you do an IPC between two threads in the same address space it's really in the
low nanosecond range like 200 and some cycles. If you cross address spaces you have to switch
page tables, you have to maybe switch class of service, then it takes 536 cycles and it's
comparable on other microarchitectures. But the interesting thing that I want to show
with this slide is that there's overhead for control flow protection. So if you just enable
indirect branch tracking the performance overhead is some 13 to 15 percent. If you enable shadow
stacks the performance overhead is increased some more and if you enable the full control
flow protection the performance overhead is in the relevant case which is the cross address
space case it's up to 30 percent. So users can freely choose through these compile time
options what level of control flow protection they are willing to trade for what in decrease
in performance. So the numbers are basically just ballpark figures to give people feeling
for if I use this feature how much IPC performance do I lose. So with that I'm at the end of
my talk. There are some links here where you can download releases where you can find more
information and now I'll open it up for questions. Thank you so much. We have time for some questions.
Yeah. And then you'll part in it. Thank you. It was really nice to see how many new things
are in Nova. One thing I would like to ask is you mentioned that page table code is formally
verified and that it's also lock free. What tools did you use for formally verification
especially in regards of memory model for verification. Thank you. So I must say that
I'm not a formal verification expert but I obviously have regular meetings and discussions
of people and the tools that we are using is the Coq theorem for basically doing the
proofs but for concurrent verification there's a tool called Iris that implements separation
logic. Well the form of the memory model that we verify depends on whether you're talking
about x86 or ARM. For ARM they're using multi copy atomic memory model. Also thanks for
the talk and it's great to see such a nice progress. Just a quick question. In the beginning
of the talk you said that you have this command line option to clamp the CPU frequency to
disable the turbo boosting. Why can't you do that at runtime? Why can't you configure
it at runtime? We could configure it at runtime too but we haven't added an API yet because
the code that would have to do that simply doesn't exist yet but there's no technical
reason for why userland couldn't control the CPU frequency at arbitrary points in time.
Okay wonderful thanks. Any other questions? Yeah just say, sorry Jonathan it's going to
be a lot. Yeah just very quickly I am on the point of the DMA attack. Were you talking
about the guest or the host? The question was for the DMA attack that I showed in the
slide here and you'll find the slides online after the talk. This is not a DMA attack of
guest versus host. This is a boot time DMA attack. You can really think of this as a
timeline. Firmware starts, bootloader starts, Nova starts and at the time that Nova turns
on the IOMU both guest and host will be DMA protected but Nova itself could be susceptible
to a DMA attack if we didn't disable Busmaster simply because the firmware does this legacy
backward compatible shenanigans that we don't like. And I bet a lot of other micro kernels
are susceptible to problems like this too and the fix would work for them as well. Thanks
Udo for the talk. I would like to know can you approximate how much percentage of the
architecture specific code is now added because of the security measures? So most of the security
measures that I talked about are x86 specific and ARM has similar features like they have
a guarded control stack specified in ARMv9 but I don't think you can buy any hardware
yet. You can take the difference between x86 and ARX64 as a rough ballpark figure but it's
really not all that much. For example, the multi key total memory encryption that's just
a few lines of code added to the x86 specific pitch level class because it was already built
into the generic class to begin with. Control flow enforcement is probably 400 lines of
assembler code in entry, pass and the switching. I did a quick test as to how many end branch
instructions a compiler would actually inject into the code. It's like 500 or so because
you get one for every interrupt entry and then one for every function and it also inflates
the size of the binary a bit but not much. And the performance decrease for indirect
branch checking among other things comes from the fact that the code gets inflated and is
not as dense anymore.
Okay. Yeah, final question please because Red is one of them. Yeah.
You were saying that you were able to achieve an L binary without rotations. Can you elaborate
a little bit on how did you do that? Which link are you using?
So it's the normal new LD but you could also use gold or mold or any of the normal linkers.
So the reason for why no relocation is needed is for the page code as long as you put the
right physical address in your page table, the virtual address is always the same. So
virtual memory is some form of relocation where you say no matter where I've run in
physical memory, the virtual memory is always the same. But for the un-paged code which
doesn't know at which physical address it was actually launched, you have to use position
independent code. Basically say I don't care at which physical address I run. I can run
it in arbitrary address because all my data structures are addressed relative or something
like that. And at some point you need to know what the offset is between where you want
it to run and where you do actually run. But that's simple. It's like you call your next
instruction, you pop the return address of the stack, you compute the difference and
then you know.
Thank you so much, Judo.
Thank you.
The slides are online. The little recording as well.