So, once again, hello, everybody.
Welcome to my talk.
This talk is going to be about OSV, evolution of OSV towards greater modularity and possibility.
Thanks to Aslan for introducing me.
So, I've been contributing to OSV since 2016.
Like a year ago, in 2015, I heard about OSV in one of the conferences.
And then, a couple of years later, I was nominated to be one of its committers.
And my greatest contributions to OSV include making OSV run on Firecracker and significantly
improving ARG64 port, among other things.
So I'm not sure if you can tell it, but OSV is actually my hobby.
So I'm not like a real current developer like many of previous speakers are.
So it's actually, you know, I work on it in my night when I feel it.
And I have a day job, so I don't represent my company that I work for.
So this is all my personal contribution to the project.
So in today's presentation, I will talk about enhancements introduced by the latest release
of OSV, 057, with a focus on greater modularity and composability.
But I will also discuss other interesting enhancements, like lazy stock, novel ways
to build ZFS images, and improvements to the ARM port.
Finally, I will also cover an interesting use case of OSV, C-WIDFS, running on OSV,
which is a distributed file system.
So as you can see in this talk, besides the title, modularity, I will actually try to
give you state of the art, where OSV is, how it has changed recently, and a little bit
of where it's going, hopefully.
So I know there are probably many definitions of unicurns, and each of them is a little
bit different, and I'm sure most of you understand what unicurnls are, but just a quick recap,
with emphasis on how OSV is a little bit different.
So OSV is a unicurnl that was designed to run single and modified Linux application
on top of Hypervisor, whereas traditional operating systems were originally designed
to run on a vast range of physical machines.
But simply speaking, OSV is an OS designed to run single application without isolation
between application and kernel, or it can be thought as a way to run highly isolated
process without ability to make system calls to the host OS.
Finally, OSV can run on both 64-bit x86 and ARMv8 architectures.
Now a little bit of history.
So OSV, for those that don't know, OSV was started in late 2012 by the company called
Cloud Use Systems, and they built pretty strong team of 10, 20 developers, I think.
I wasn't one of them, but they pretty much wrote most of OSV, but at some point they
basically realized they have to make money, I'm guessing.
So they basically moved on and started working on this product you may have known, CillaDB,
which is this high performance database, but I think they took some learning.
And after that, basically, I think OSV did receive some grant from European Union, so
there was some project on that, and I think there may have been some companies also using
OSV, but honestly, since then, it's been really maintained by volunteers.
So like me, there's still some people from CillaDB, Nadav Harrell, and others that contribute
to the project.
I would just single out 46 and Aqis, which actually was the one that implemented Virtay
OFS as a very interesting contribution to OSV.
And obviously, I would like to take this opportunity to invite more people to become part of our
community, because honestly, you may not realize it, but our community is very small, so it's
just really me, Nadav, and a couple of other people that contribute to the project.
So I hope we're going to grow as a community after this talk.
So a quick recap of a little bit of how OSV looks like, what the design is.
So in this slide, you can see major components of OSV across layers, starting with G-LIPC,
the top, which is greatly based actually on Mosul, then core layer in the middle, comprised
of ELF, dynamic linker, of VFS, virtual file system, and then networking stack, thread scheduler,
page cache, RCU, read, copy, update, page table management, and L1, L2, pools to manage
memory.
And then you have a layer of device drivers, where OSV implements Virtay O layer based
virtual devices on both over PCI transport and MMIL transport, and then Zen and VMware,
among others.
And obviously, and one more thing, so OSV can run on KVM based hypervisors like QEMUIAC,
like Firecracker.
I did test also OSV on cloud hypervisor, which is I think Intel's hypervisor written in Rust.
And then I personally didn't really run OSV on Zen, so I know that the Zen support is
a little bit dated probably, and I'm not sure how much it has been tested.
I did test on VMware vbox, virtual box, and I think on Hyperkit at some point.
So I will just, I won't go into more detail about this diagram, but I will leave it with
use just as a reference later.
So in the first part of this presentation, I will, about modularity and composability,
I will focus on new experimental modes to hide the non-G-LIP-C symbols and standard
C++ library.
I will also discuss how ZFS code was extracted out of the kernel in form of a dynamically
linked library.
And finally, I will also explain another new build option to tailor the kernel to a set
of specific drivers.
I call them driver profiles.
And another new mechanism to allow building a version of kernel with a subset of G-LIP-C
symbols needed to support a specific application, which I think is quite interesting.
So by design, OSV has always been a fat unicernel, which has been some sort of, some other criticism.
And by default provided a large subset of G-LIP-C functionality has included full standard
C++ library and ZFS implementation drivers for many devices and has supported many hypervisors.
So on one hand, it makes running arbitrary application on any hypervisor very easy using
a single universal kernel.
But on another hand, such universality comes with the price of bloated kernel with many
symbols and drivers and possibly ZFS that is unused.
That's causing inefficient memory usage, longer boot time, and potential security vulnerabilities.
In addition, C++ application linked against one version of LIP-SDC++ different than the
version the kernel was linked against may simply not work.
For example, that happened to me when I was testing OSV with.NET.
And yeah, the only way to make it work was to hide basically the C++ standard library
and use the one that was part of the.NET app.
So one way to lower memory utilization of the guest is to minimize the kernel size.
By default, OSV comes with a universal kernel that provides quite large spectrum of G-LIP-C
library and full standard C++ library and exposes over a total of 17,000 symbols.
And most of those are very long, as you know, C++ symbols that make up the symbol table.
So the question may be posed, why not have a mechanism where we can build a kernel with
all known G-LIP-C symbols hidden and all unneeded code that is unused garbage collected.
So the extra benefit of fewer exported symbols is increased security that stems from the
fact that there's simply less potential code that is left, that is harmful, that could
be harmful.
And also, that way we can achieve better compatibility as any potential symbol collisions, for example,
and mismatch standard C++ library, which I mentioned can be avoided.
So the release 57, 057 added a new build option called conf-hide-symbols to hide those known
G-LIP-C symbols and the standard C++ library symbols.
These are enabled, if enabled, in essence most files in a source tree of OSV, except
the ones under LIP-C and MOSL directories, would be compiled with the flags of visibility
hidden and only if that build flag is enabled.
On the other hand, the symbols to be exposed as public, like the G-LIP-C one, would be
annotated with OSV asterisk API macros that translate basically to attribute visibility
default and the standard C++ library is linked with the flag, no whole archive.
Those S-V asterisk API macros basically would be like OSV LIP-C API or OSV P-threads API,
OSV LIP-M API and so on.
Basically that match all then I think around 10 libraries that OSV dynamic linker exposes.
Finally, the list of public symbols exported by the kernel is enforced during the build
process based on the symbol list files for each advertised library.
Like for example LIP-C SO6 and is maintained under the directory exported symbols.
These files are basically a list of symbols that are concatenated using the script called
generate version script, which goes into version script file and then is fed to the linker
as an argument to the version script flag.
In order to now remove all unneeded code, basically garbage, all files will be compiled
with the flag function sections and data sections and then they would be linked with the flag
GC section.
Now any code that needs to stay, like for example the bootstrap start points or dynamically
enabled code like the optimal MAMCPY implementation or trace point patch size is retained by putting
relevant kept directives and relevant sections in the linker script.
The kernel L file built with most symbols hidden is roughly 4.3 megabytes in size compared
to 6.7, which is reduction of around 40%.
This great reduction stems from the fact that the standard C++ library is no longer linked
with whole archive.
The symbol table is way smaller and unused code is garbage collected.
Please note that the resulting kernel is still universal as it exports all julipsy symbols
and includes all the device drivers.
As the result of this size reduction, kernel boots also a little bit faster.
These all sound great.
One may ask why not hide most symbols and standard C++ library by default.
The problem is that there are around 35 unit tests and some also application that were
written in the past that rely on C++ symbols and they basically would not run if we hide
all of those symbols.
Those are basically used to, they were implemented in the past and it was done sometimes out
of convenience, sometimes basically out of necessity.
To address this specific problem, we will need to expose some of those OSVC++ symbols
as C basically, as API expressed in C.
We will basically define very simple C wrapper functions that will call those C++ code.
I can use this one.
A good example of modularity improvements made in the release 0.57 is extracting ZFS
code out of kernel as a dynamically linked library, libsolarisso, which effectively is
a new module.
To accomplish that, we changed the main OSV makefile to build new artifact, libsolarisso
out of ZFS and solaris file sets in the makefile, which basically used to be linked into kernel.
The new library has to be linked with a bind now flag and OSV specific OSV MLock node to
force OSV dynamic linker to resolve symbols eagerly and populate the mappings eagerly
as well.
This basically is done to prevent page faults that would lead to potential deadlocks as
the libraries load it and initialize.
The init function ZFS initialize called upon the library is loaded creates necessary thread
pulls and registers various callbacks so that the page cache arc, which is adaptive replacement
cache from ZFS, and ZFS dev driver can interact with relevant code in the ZFS library.
On another hand, the OSV kernel needs to expose some around 100 symbols that provide some
internal FreeBSD originating functionality that libsolarisso depends on.
Actually, OSV borrowed some code from FreeBSD and actually a good chunk of this code was
actually implementation of ZFS, which right now is outside of the kernel.
Finally, the virtual file system bootstrap code needs to dynamically load libsolarisso
from bootfs or read-onlyfs using dlopen before mounting ZFS file system.
There are at least three advantages of moving ZFS to a separate library.
Most of ZFS can be optionally loaded from another file system like bootfs or read-onlyfs, partition
on the same disk or another disk.
I will actually discuss that in more detail in one of the upcoming slides later.
Then also kernel gets smaller by around 800 kilobytes and effectively becomes 3.6 megabytes
in size.
Finally, there are at least 10 fewer threads that are needed to run non-ZFS image.
For example, when you run read-onlyfs image on OSV, with one CPU, it only requires 25
threads.
The regular Linux GLLipsi apps should run fine on kernel with most symbols and standard
C++ library hidden.
Unfortunately, many unit tests, which I mentioned, and various internal OSV apps, which are written
mostly in C++, so-called modules, do not, as they had been coded in the past to use
those internal C++ symbols from the kernel.
We have to do something to deal with that problem.
In the release 0.57, we introduced some of the CRAPR API, which are basically in C-style
convention.
We changed those modules to use those CRAPR function instead of C++ code.
The benefit is that down the road, we might have some newer apps or some newer modules
that would use those CRAPR functions.
It also may make OSV more modular.
As you can see, one of those examples is, for example, OSV gets all threads, which is
basically a function that gives a thread-safe way to color to basically iterate over threads,
which for example is used in an HTTP monitoring module to list all the threads.
A good example of OSV-specific modules that uses some internal C++ symbols is HTTP server
monitoring.
We modify the HTTP monitoring module to stop using internal kernel C++ API.
We do it by replacing some of the calls to internal C++ symbols with this new module
C-style API, symbols from the slide which you saw on the slide before, for example,
SCAD with all threads with this new OSV getAllThreads function.
In other scenarios, we fall back to standard G-LipC API.
For example, the monitoring app used to call OSV current mount.
Right now, it uses basically getNT and function and related ones.
The release 0.57 introduced another build mechanism that allows creating a custom kernel
with a specific list of drivers intended to target given hypervisor.
Obviously such kernel benefits from even smaller size and better security as all unneeded code,
all unneeded drivers are basically excluded during the build process.
In essence, we introduce a new build script and make file parameter, driver's profile.
This new parameter is intended to specify a driver profile which is simply a list of
device drivers to be linked into the kernel and some extra functionality like PCI or ACPI
these drivers depend on.
Each profile is specified in a tiny include files with the MK extension under conf profiles
arch directory and included by the main make file as requested by the driver profile parameter.
The main make file has a number of basically if expressions and adds a conditionally given
driver object to the linked object list depending on the value of 0 or 1 of the given conf driver's
parameter specified in that include file.
The benefit of using drivers are most profound when they are used with when you build kernel
and hide most of the symbols as I talked about in one of the previous slides.
It's also possible to enable or disable individual drivers on top of profiles.
Files are basically list of the drivers but there are number of configuration parameters
that where you can specifically for example include which I'm going to be actually showing
here.
You can include specific driver.
One may ask a question why not use something more standard like menu config like for example
what Unicraft does.
Actually OSV has this specific build system and I didn't want to basically now introduce
another way of doing things.
That's where we basically script the build uses the various effectively parameters to
for example take to hide symbols or specify specific driver profile or list of other parameters.
As you can see in the first example we built default kernel with all symbols hidden and
the resulting kernel is around 36 3.6 megabytes.
In the next example we actually use we built kernel with the VITIO over PCI profiles which
is like 300 kilobytes smaller and then we in the third one we built kernel which is
intended to for example for Firecracker when we include only VITIO block device and networking
driver over MMIO transport.
And then just to see basically in a fourth one just to see how large the drivers code
in OSV is when you basically use driver profiles base which is basically nothing no drivers
you can see that roughly 600 kilobytes of the drivers code is roughly 600 kilobytes
in size.
And then in the last one actually option is where you can specify you use basically drivers
profile and then you explicitly say which specific drivers or driver like the capability
like in this case ACPI, VITIOFS and VITIO net and PV panic devices you want to use.
Actually with the new version with new release of OSV 0.57 we started publishing new versions
of new variations effectively of OSV kernel that correspond to this I thought you know
interesting build configuration that I just mentioned and in this example the OSV loader
hidden artifacts are effectively the versions of OSV kernel built with most symbols hidden
and then for example which will be at the top for both ARM and x86 and then for example
right here in the second and the third and fourth artifacts basically version of the
kernel built for micro VM profile which is effectively something that you would use to
run OSV on firecracker which only has VITIO over MMIO transport.
Now the release 0.57 introduced yet another built mechanism and that allows creation of
a custom kernel by exporting only symbols required by a specific application.
The extra such kernel benefits from the fact that again it's a little bit smaller and thus
offers better security as in essence all unneeded code by that specific application is removed.
This new mechanism relies on two scripts that analyze the built manifest, detect application
L files, identify symbols required from OSV kernel and finally produce the application-specific
version script under app version script.
The generate app version script iterates over the manifest files produced by list manifest
files pi, identifies undefined symbols in the L files using object dump that are also
exported by OSV kernel and finally generates basically the app version script.
So please note that this functionality only works when you build kernel with most symbols
hidden.
So I think what is kind of interesting, well interesting, worth noting in that approach
is that you basically run a built script against given application twice.
Basically first time to identify all symbols that application needs from OSV kernel and
then actually second time we do is to build the kernel for that specific app.
In this example we actually generate kernel specific to run a simple going app on OSV
and when you actually build kernel with symbols around I think 30 symbols in by going pi example,
the kernel is effectively by around half a megabyte smaller and it's around 3.2 megabytes.
So this approach has obviously some limitations.
Some applications obviously use for example DLS then to dynamically resolve symbols and
those would be missed by this technique.
So in this scenario basically for now you have to manually find those symbols and add
them to the app version script file.
Conversely a lot of jilipsy functionality is still in OSV in the Linux CC where all
the system calls are actually implemented is still basically references all the code
in some of the parts of the lips implementation.
So this obviously also would not be removed.
So obviously we could think of ways of finding some kind of built mechanism that could for
example find all the usages of Cisco instruction or SVC on ARM and analyze and find all these
only code that is needed.
In the future we may componentize other functional elements of the kernel for example the DHCP
lookup code could be either loaded from a separate library or compiled out depending
on some build option to improve compatibility while also planning to add support of statically
linked executables which would require implementing at least clone, BRK and arch PRCTL syscalls.
We may also introduce ability to swap built in version of jilipsy libraries with third
party ones for example the subset of libm so that is provided by OSV kernel could be
possibly hidden with the mechanism that is discussed and we could use different implementation
of that library.
Finally we are considering to expand standard procfs and syscfs and OSV specific parts of
syscfs that would better support statically linked executables but also allow regular
apps to interact with OSV.
A good example of it could be implementation of netstat like type of capability application
that could expose the networking internals of OSV better during runtime.
In the next part of the presentation I will discuss the other interesting enhancements
introduced as part of the latest 0.57 release.
More specifically I will talk about lazy stack and new ways to build ZFS images and finally
the improvements to the AR-64 port.
The lazy stack which by the way is actually the idea that was felt off by Nadav Harrell
which maybe is listening to this presentation effectively allows to save substantial amount
of memory if an application spawns many p threads with large stack by letting stack
grow dynamically as needed instead of getting pre-populated ahead of time which is normally
the case right now with OSV.
So on OSV right now all kernel threads and all application threads have stacks that are
automatically pre-populated which is obviously not very memory efficient.
Now the crux of the solution is based on observation that OSV page fault handler requires that
both interrupts and preemption must be enabled when fault is triggered and therefore if stack
is dynamically mapped we need to make sure that the stack page fault never happens in
these relatively few places where the kernel code that executes with either interrupts
or preemption disabled.
And we basically satisfied this requirement by pre-faulting the stack by reading one byte,
one page down per stack pointer just before preemption or interrupts are disabled.
So a good example of that code would be in a scheduler right when OSV scheduler is trying
to figure out what the next threads to switch to and obviously that code has preemption
and interrupts disabled and we wouldn't obviously want to have page fault happen at that moment.
So there are relatively few places when that happens and this idea is to basically pre-fault
this code.
So to achieve that we basically analyze OSV code to find all the places where the IRQ
disabled and pre-empt disabled is called directly or indirectly sometimes and pre-fault the
stack there if necessary.
As we analyze all call sites we need to follow basically five rules.
The first one do nothing if the call in question executes always on the kernel thread because
it has pre-populated stack.
There's no chance that page fault is going to happen.
Second one is do nothing if the call site executes on other type of pre-populated stack.
The good example of that would be the interrupt and exception stack or syscall stack which
are all pre-populated.
And the number three rule is do nothing if the call site executes when we know that either
interrupts or pre-emptions are disabled because we don't need to somebody already probably
pre-faulted that.
And then pre-fault unconditionally if we know that both pre-emptions and interrupts are
about to be enabled.
And otherwise pre-fault stack by determining dynamically basically by calling the pre-emptable
is pre-emptable and IRQ enabled functions.
Now the idea basically if we only always if we did if we followed only rule number five
which actually this is what I tried to do in the very beginning the first attempt to
implement like syscall it would be actually pretty inefficient.
I mean I saw pretty significant degradation of for example you know context switch and
other parts of the OSV when I dynamically checked if preemption and interrupts were
disabled.
So this access was pretty painful to basically analyze the code but I think it was worth
it.
As you remember from the modularity slides the ZFS file system has been extracted from
the kernel as a separate shared library called libsolyzeso which can be loaded from the different
file system before ZFS file system can be mounted.
This allows for three ways ZFS can be mounted by OSV.
The first and original way assumes that ZFS is mounted at the root from the first partition
of the first disk.
The second one involves mounting ZFS from the second partition of the first disk and
at an arbitrary non-root point for example slash data.
Similarly the third way involves mounting ZFS from the first partition of the second
or higher disk at an arbitrary non-root point as well.
Please note that the second and third options assume that the root file system is non-ZFS
obviously and which could be like read-onlyFS or bootFS.
This slide shows you the build command and how OSV runs when we follow the original and
default method of building and mounting ZFS.
For those that have done it, there's nothing really interesting here.
This is a new method, actually the first of the two new ones where we actually allow ZFS
to be mounted at a non-root mount point like beta for example and mixed with another file
system on the same disk.
Please note that libsolaris as always plays on the root file system, typically read-onlyFS
under usr.libfs and load it from it automatically.
The build script will automatically add the relevant mount point time to its ZFS style.
The last method is basically similar to the one before but this time we allow ZFS to be
mounted from the partition from the second disk or another one.
Actually what happens with this option, I noticed that OSV would actually mount ZFS
file system by around 30 to 40 milliseconds faster.
Now there's another new feature we used to run in order to build ZFS images and file
system we would use OSV itself to do it.
With this new release there's a specialized version of the kernel called ZFS loader which
basically delegates to this utility like ZPUL, ZFS and so on to mount OSV.
But there's also now a new script called ZFS image on host that can be used to mount OSV
ZFS images provided you have open ZFS functionality on your host system.
Which is actually quite nice because you can mount basically OSV disk and introspect it.
You can also modify it using standard Linux tools and unmount it and use it on OSV again.
Here's some help on how this new script can be used.
Now I think I don't have much time left but I will try.
Also I will focus a little bit on the AR64 improvements.
I will focus on three things that I think are worth mentioning.
The changes to dynamically map the kernel during the boot from the second basically
gigabyte of visual memory to the 63rd gigabyte of memory.
Additional enhancements to handle system calls and then also handle exceptions on a dedicated
stock.
As far as the moving memory, visual memory to the 63rd gigabyte, so I'm not sure if you
realize OSV kernel is actually position dependent.
But obviously the kernel itself may be loaded in different parts of physical memory.
It used to be before that release that you would have to build different versions for
Firecracker or for the QEMU.
Basically in this release we changed the logic in the assembly in a boot loader where we
basically OSV detects itself where it is in a physical memory and in essence builds dynamically
the early mapping tables to then eventually bootstrap to the right place in the positional
code.
So now basically you don't need to... You can use the same version of the kernel to
on any hypervisor.
Now to add system calls on ARM we have to handle the SVC instruction.
There's not really much interesting if you know how that works.
What is maybe a little bit more interesting was the change that I made to make all exceptions,
including system calls to work on a dedicated stock.
So before that change all exceptions would be handled on the same stock as the application
which costs all kinds of problems.
For example, that would effectively prevent implementation of the lazy stock.
So to support basically that, in OSV which runs in EL1 in a kernel mode we would basically
take advantage of the stack selector register and we would basically use both stack pointer
register SPL0 and SPL1.
So normally OSV uses SPL1 register to point to the stock for each spread.
With the new implementation what basically we would do before the exception was taken
basically we would switch the stack pointer selector to SPL0.
Once basically the exception was handled it would basically go back to normal which was
SPL1.
I think I'm going to skip with the fast because we're running a little bit of time left but
you can read it on that.
We've also added Netlink support and we've made quite many improvements to VFS layer.
So both actually of those Netlink and VFS improvements were done to support C-WitFS.
So there are basically more gaps that have been filled by trying to run this new use
case.
So just briefly as we are pretty much at the end of the presentation I think in the next
releases of OSV whenever they're going to happen I would like us to focus on supporting
statically linked executables, adding proper support of spin locks because OSV for example
Mutex right now is lock less but under high contention it would actually make sense to
use spin locks and we have actually a prototype on that on the mailing list.
And then supporting ASLR, refreshing Capstan which is a build tool which hasn't been really
out because we don't have enough volunteers, improved for a long time and then even the
website and there are many other interesting ones.
So as a last slide I would like to basically use this as occasion to thank basically organizer
Rasvan for inviting me and everybody else from the community of UNI kernels and I would
also want to thank SillaDB for supporting me and Dorlauer and Nadav Harrell for reviewing
all the patches and his other improvements and I also want to thank all other contributors
to OSV and I also would like to invite you to join us because there are not many of us
and if you want to have OSV alive we definitely need you.
So there are some resources about OSV, there's my P99 presentation here as well and if you
guys have any questions I'm happy to answer them.
Thank you.
Thank you Voldemort.
So any questions for Voldemort?
Yeah please, just ask it's going to be a bit too.
I have two questions.
First when you have spoken about symbols, about the GLC symbols and the CLC symbols,
do I understand it correctly that the problem is that a kernel might be using some GLC functions
and some applications might be linked to its own GLC and some symbols clash with it?
Well not really, they would use the same version and there's no problem with for example malloc,
like malloc we don't want to expose malloc but there is a good chunk of OSVs implemented
in C++ and all of those symbols don't need to be exposed because they inflate the symbols
stable a lot and they are not, they shouldn't be really available to visible to others.
And now I think OSV exposes if you build with that option around I think 16 hundreds of
symbols instead of 17,000.
So it's really about the binary size there?
Yeah, yeah basically binary size and with in case of C++ library avoiding a collision
where you build OSV with different version of C++ library versus the application that.
Yeah okay so this is the case I am interested in.
So have you thought about maybe renaming the symbols in the kernel image during the link
time, maybe adding some prefixes to all the symbols so that you can have them visible
but they would not clash?
That's interesting idea, I haven't thought about it yet.
And Marti the second question?
Yeah, yeah just a quick second question.
So when you have spoken about the lazy stack you said that you pre-fold the stack to avoid
the problematic case when it drops and preemptions disabled.
So basically when I am thinking about it you still need to have some kind of upper bound
of the size of the stack so that you know that you pre-folded large enough to not get
into the inter-dependence of the stack.
So what I am thinking about is that you have to have a kind of a
upper bound for the whole kernel.
Well I mean this is a technique for applications, threads only.
So for application stacks where the kernel threads would still have the pre-populated
fixed size stack.
Because I mean there are many applications like good example is Java that would start
like 200 threads and all of them right now are pre-folded like 1 megabyte and you would
all of a sudden need like 200.
So this is just for application.
Okay so basically my understanding is wrong so you have obviously yeah so you have the
user stack and the kernel stack is the same stack.
Well no it is in the same you know virtual memory but yeah there are I mean when I say
kernel stack I mean in OSV basically there are two types of threads.
There are kernel threads and there are application threads.
So basically application threads use their own stack but.
But when they enter the kernels so to speak they are still using the original.
I mean application threads use application stack and kernel use a kernel and when I say
like some kernel code obviously as a, well obviously because uni-kernel as the code executes
in an application it runs on application stack but it may execute some kernel code as well.
Which yeah.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Any other question?
Okay thank you so much.
Let's move on.