Okay, now that Pierre is here, we can get started.
So it's my pleasure to invite Martin to talk about Rust-based unicernel.
So combining the two cool words here, unicernels and Rust and security.
Go ahead, Martin.
Yeah, there were two words.
Okay, hi, everyone.
Thanks for coming to our talk.
I'm going to be talking about Rust-y-Hermid, which is our Rust-based modular unicernel
for micro-VMs.
Who are we?
This is us.
So there's Stefan, who initiated the project a few years ago.
There's Jonathan, and there's Martin.
That's me.
We are from the Institute for Automation of Complex Power Systems at RWTH Aachen University.
Stefan is the academic director.
Jonathan is a PhD student.
And I'm a master student.
I'm currently writing my master's thesis with both Stefan and Jonathan as my supervisors.
And yeah, I'm happy to be able to present our project to you now.
Just a remark, this project has been funded through EU projects.
Okay, Rust-y-Hermid.
Rust-y-Hermid is a library operating system for creating unicernel images, similar to what
you've seen before with unicraft, if you were here.
It started as a Hermit core research project around eight years ago, started by Stefan.
That project was written in C and had a focus on HPC, high performance computing.
And in 2018, it was completely rewritten in Rust.
Every component of it.
Well, and assembly, but that doesn't count.
Quick recap, unicernels.
Very similar to a slide you've seen before presented by Simon.
On the left, we have the classical Linux VM running on a hypervisor type two here.
And we have a fully fledged operating system inside of the VM image, which is quite large
and has its own distinction between kernel and user space inside the virtual machine.
Docker containers run on a container runtime, which have their own user space, but share
the kernel with the host system, which makes it faster and more flexible.
Unicernels on the right are very small.
They are created by linking your application against a library operating system to create
a tightly integrated unicernel image, which can then run on machines, real or virtual
machines.
It has the same isolation from the host or other guests as classical Linux VMs.
And since it's just one application and one process, we have a single address-based operating
system and no distinction between user space and kernel space.
This is really good for performance because we don't need to do any privileged context
switches, which are costly otherwise.
And we don't have preemptions and don't do interruptions in that case either.
Also it's very small in this case because we can just throw away everything we don't
need from the binary and have a runnable Hello World image at around half a megabyte.
We also focus on microVMs.
MicroVMs are a special type of virtual machine platform, which are more bare-bones because
we don't need to emulate things like PCI or ACPI.
This of course requires para virtualization.
So the guest image needs to be specialized and know that we don't want to talk about
PCI in this case.
That can make the unicernel image even smaller in some cases.
And let's talk about Rust.
Our unicernel is written in Rust for a number of reasons.
It's productive, it's fun, and it's safe.
Rust has many modern language features that are really nice to work with compared to C
or other older languages.
It has a strong type system, helpful compiler errors, which are really a bliss if you're
coming from C++ template errors.
It's a growing ecosystem.
It's being adopted by several big projects.
I'm sure you've heard of Linux adopting Rust, at least in some parts, already upstream.
Rust has also great tooling.
There's a very nice package manager that virtually everyone uses to put their projects into so-called
crates in Rust.
And there's great tooling for formatting and linting, for example.
For our case in OS programming, it's also very cool that you can use very much of the
Rust standard library without an operating system.
Like for example a vector for a growable dynamically allocated array, for example.
The biggest point which really put Rust on the landscape is the last point, which is
that Rust is a safe language.
It's the first major systems programming language that guarantees memory safety.
That's pretty cool because memory safety is hard if you do it manually.
I think if you've programmed C or C++ before, you might have dereferenced a null pointer
and resulted in some segford or something.
And it's very cool if you don't do that.
Just don't.
In big projects like Chromium or other cases, it's been shown that around more than 60%
of vulnerabilities are caused by memory unsafety.
And moving those projects to Rust is in the spirit of hoping that that alleviates this
problem.
I have an example, proof of coolness of the Rust language.
Just one example that I picked to demonstrate the modernity and elegance.
It's sometimes a.k.a. tagged unions.
You can see on the bottom here that there is a generic enum type option, which is either
none or sum and then has some data in it.
And in Rust, these types are coupled.
So the sum variant of the enumeration contains the data.
And it's really nice working with that.
If we have an option as shown at the bottom, we can match this option and then either unpack
the none or the sum variant and then reuse it directly.
Okay.
I've kind of lied to you before because Rust is really two languages.
First there's safe Rust and unsafe Rust.
Okay.
What does that mean?
Safe Rust is awesome because safe Rust gives us all the guarantees that we want.
Things like accessing invalid pointers, which would result in use after three, double, three
or out of bounds problems as well as data races are classified as undefined behavior
in Rust.
And using only safe Rust, these problems can't happen to you.
These problems don't guarantee correctness though.
So things like race conditions, which are different from data races or logic errors
can occur, which is natural, I think.
When doing OS development and other low level stuff, we have a few additional requirements
though.
We might want to do raw memory access for MMIO or we have to sometimes write assembly
code for invoking special CPU instructions.
This unfortunately cannot be checked by the compiler for safety invariants.
That means this is not possible to do in safe Rust.
This is why unsafe Rust exists.
Unsafe Rust is a strict superset of safe Rust.
So it means you can do everything that you can do in safe Rust, but a few things more.
But you have to tell the compiler that you promise to be extra careful and don't do
any bad stuff.
You have special superpowers then.
You can access raw pointers and call unsafe functions, which is required for inline assembly,
for example.
At the bottom you can see how we can access raw pointers or write inline assembly, which
if we are not careful might really do bad stuff.
This is why we have to put this in unsafe blocks.
That means if something goes wrong, we can just grab for any unsafe things and rethink
if we did everything correctly there.
When writing this unsafe code, we have to be sure not to violate Rust's fundamental
soundness property, which says that no matter what, safe Rust cannot cause undefined behavior.
If we encapsulate some unsafe code in some safe function, we have to make sure that this
API cannot be misused in any way.
Enough about Rust.
Let's talk about Rusty Hermit again.
Rusty Hermit is tightly integrated with the Rust language.
It's our first language of choice for applications and very specialized.
Now I'm going to show you how you would port a Rust application that runs on Linux to Rusty
Hermit, which is really easy, I think.
But let's see.
We have a few requirements.
Rust up the first one is the Rust toolchain manager that virtually every Rust developer
has already installed.
We then need, of course, a hypervisor for our choice.
We can either use the ubiquitous Kuemu or UHIVE.
UHIVE is a specialized hypervisor created by us in Rust, of course, that is specialized
for the Rusty Hermit operating system to have really fast API between those two.
If we are compiling with simultaneous multiprocessing for interprocessors, we also need nothing,
but that's not important if you don't need that.
This is a bare bones Rust project.
We have a cargo tome, which is a manifest file for the cargo package manager, which
describes the package metadata.
It just says, hello world, version, edition, something.
Not very important.
We have then our main source file, the main RS, which is just a main function and prints
hello world.
Everything that we need to do to get Rusty Hermit support is first add a Rusty Hermit
dependency.
It's written a bit complicated to just include this dependency if we actually compile for
the Hermit operating system.
And then we just need to add two more lines to the main RS to import this dependency.
And what this does then is that Hermit sys in the background transparently builds the
Hermit kernel, the library operating system, and then by importing it like this, we make
sure we actually link against this.
And what we then get is a runnable, a unicorn image that can be run in Qemu or UHive.
To then build this, we have to pin a Rust compiler version because we have some internal
things that require that, but we're working on getting rid of that and then just build
it.
We say cargo build, then specify the Hermit target, which is our target, and then we tell
it to build the standard library on the fly because we are small yet and only tier three
target which is why Rust does not support us natively yet, but we support Rust.
And yeah, that was easy.
And to make sure that all of you can believe me, I have prepared a small demo.
I have to get on this screen, okay?
Right here you can see exactly the project I talked about.
It's just a hello world with the Hermit sys dependency.
It's a main RS which does hello world.
And then we can go ahead and open a terminal, then do cargo build, which is really fast
right now because I pre-built it, normally takes around one minute on this machine I'm
logged into.
And then we can run it on UHive.
Hello world.
And to make sure that we didn't cheat, I can also show you the verbose messages which tells
UHive to please print the kernel messages along with it.
And we can see that there's Rust, the Hermit booting and initializing all the hardware
and preparing the memory and everything and then in the end jumping into our application
and printing hello world.
After that, that's just shut down.
Okay, back to the presentation.
Yes.
Okay, now a bit about our modularity story in Rust.
The Hermit.
There are several modularity stories.
The first one is user facing.
This is the same similar dependency declaration in our cargo manifest as before, but a little
bit expanded.
We added features.
Features are a thing in the cargo package manager that allows us to select and configure
conditional compilation in our dependency.
In this case, Hermit Sys.
And we use this to be able to specify in this manner which features we want to be present
in the unicorn image.
In this case, I enabled SMP, TCP and DHCP4 and disabled PCI and ACPI.
This means that this should be runnable in a micro VM, for example, with no PCI support
present.
Internally, we are also quite modular.
And we're working on further modularizing our kernel.
So at the top, you can see the libhermit kernel which has a few dependencies.
The first one is a internal hermit entry dependency which is shared between the kernel and anything
that loads and jumps into the kernel.
We then have hermit sync for internal collection of synchronization primitives like mutexes.
And the other crates are really provided by the rust ecosystem which is really rich.
So the linked list allocator is our allocation algorithm that we just import and then use.
We can also just import and use some device drivers or architecture specific abstractions
so that we don't even have to write assembly code ourselves.
Also small TCPs, our TCP stack, just import it and configure it.
And yeah, we also contribute back upstream which is cool.
But this shows the strength of the rust ecosystem and community for rust OS development, I think.
In the end, this is a broad overview of the hermit ecosystem as it is today.
On the left, you can see a unicurner image that has been built.
At the top, we have the application.
It's either a rust application or a C application, although rust application is our primary focus,
which then either uses the rust standard library or a new C library.
Those are then customized by us to invoke the special syscalls into the kernel to do
the required functionality.
And this all together then makes up the unicurner image.
This can then be run on either our specialized virtual machine monitor UHive or a generic
VM like KEMO.
For KEMO, we have a rusty loader which then chain loads our unicurner image and rusty
loader supports some boot protocols as you can see here.
That's been the main part.
So what are we working on right now?
I'm working on the first three things, further code-based oxidization, which means making
it more rusty.
That means applying more rust idioms more throughoutly because there have been a few
C-isms that we've been stuck with from the original part.
I'm personally also working on Miri's part, also as part of my master thesis.
Miri is an interpreter for rust, which initially sounds strange, but using Miri, we can spot
a few cases of undefined behavior if we do something wrong in unsafe code.
If something runs in Miri though, that doesn't mean that this is guaranteed to be correct,
but it can help us in some cases.
Third point is more modularization, and I already talked about that.
It's about spinning out internal drivers, for example, in separate projects and crates.
Then TCPI stack overhaul is something that Stefan is currently working on, and UHive
network overhaul is something that Jonathan oversees.
We are also generally working on firecracker support and arm support, both of which have
working prototypes but have not really been mainlined that much.
Please find us at GitHub.
We are always happy to have conversations and contributions.
That's been it.
Thanks for listening.
Thank you so much Martin.
Okay, any questions for Martin?
UniCernels, Rust Security.
Alrighty.
There's one.
I just want to know what is the primary focus of this project.
Do you have some industry which is already picking up on Hermit, or is it pure science
so far?
What are the plans?
As far as I understand, it started as a research project, and it's much there now, I think,
Stefan?
Yeah, it's still a research project.
But we use it in two new projects, and they are mostly partners from the cloud area and
edge computing, and we want to use it.
Thanks.
Thank you for your talk.
I have a question.
As far as I know, the original C implementation supported quite a few more targets than only
Rust and C. As far as I remember, you could run Go code as well, and Fortran, and some
other stuff that linked against Glib C, if I'm remembering correctly.
Newlib, I think.
Is there any plan to open up your targets as well for the new Rust implementation to
support some more stuff, not only Rust and C?
As far as I've been there, it's been only Rust.
I'm not that old into the project.
I'm not sure what the plans are on further supporting that.
We currently have bare-bound support for C, and I don't think the Go implementation
is currently working.
It's possible to get it working, but we are not really working on that actively, I think.
Any plans for RISC-V support?
RISC-V support.
This is also done by two students.
It didn't need time to just manifest this, so it's there, but the lack of time.
Proof of concept is working, but not upstream yet.
Okay.
Anything?
Yep.
This question obviously has to be asked, is there async support?
Is there what?
Async support.
Async.
Rust async.
We have a runtime, or async runtime.
I think not mainline yet, right?
In the kernel, it says async support, but there's coming up your support or something
to start with.
I know the kernel uses it internally for networking, and I think the exposure to user space via
MIO or something is not merged upstream, but it's something that we are actively interested
in, yes.
Right.
Anything else?
Okay.
If not, thank you again, Martin.
Thank you all for coming.
Thanks.
Thank you.