Okay, hello everybody.
So, my name is Doji.
I work in the tools group at Red Hat.
And so we're here today to, okay, first of all,
thank you for staying.
So, yeah, I wanted to talk about
application binary interface analysis today.
And okay, first of all,
who doesn't know about the Babigail and ABI stuff?
So, okay, so I think we'll have something for you guys.
So, what are we going to talk about?
So, first of all, I'll introduce what
Abigail is and we'll look at how it works,
what the projects brought recently,
and what we're looking for as far as the future goes.
So, Abigail is about
doing analysis of application binary interfaces.
So, it's a set of tools that can do things like compare
the ABI of two binaries or store the ABI of
a binary onto a disk format.
Can do a comparison of binaries that are in packages,
like Debian packages, RPMs, star files, etc.
And it is also a shared library that you can
use to write more tools if you want.
So, that's all well and nice as far as marketing goes,
but then let's look at what we mean by ABI.
So, suppose you have a simple binary which has,
okay, simple, no, very complicated, let's say,
which has three functions that are here.
The types of the functions are defined here in a simple hierarchy.
Here you have the first type that inherit,
S0 which inherits base type,
and let's say another type here that inherits S0.
Okay. So, that's the first version of it.
Let's see if, I don't know if it compiles.
Yes, it does.
Then I have a second version of it which looks quite the same.
But okay, what does it do?
Okay. What's the difference between the two?
Very simple. I just inserted
a data member in the base class,
and we want to know what the impact of this is on the ABI as far as the binary goes.
So, where am I here?
I'm in the source code of the project,
and so I've built a version of it.
So, here we have one of the tools which name is ABI diff,
which does what you think it does.
So, if I run it, what does it say?
Basically, there are two changes as far as ABI goes in that battery due to the change of scene.
So, the first change is about the first function,
which is here.
So, it is telling us basically that that function has a parameter type that changed,
and the change is about this structure.
Remember, something is interesting.
The size hasn't changed,
even though I've added a data member in there.
So, you know the drill, right?
If you don't, I can explain it more.
But size hasn't changed,
the base class has changed,
and the change here is a data member insertion at a certain offset, blah, blah, blah.
So, this is the impact of the change of the first type on the first interface.
So, there is another interface that got impacted.
And the parameter of that function, which was struct S1, changed as well.
It base class changed.
The base class was struct S0, right?
And the details of S0 change were reported earlier.
So, we don't have to repeat it again, right?
So, here you see that we compute the changes, right?
And we also analyze those changes so that we can detect
if things have been reported earlier or not.
And also, we mess up with more stuff because here we say,
for instance, that there were two changes, for instance,
but one got filtered out.
What does that mean? So, let's see, for instance,
if I recall the...
Okay, I'll add a special...
So, I've asked ABI-DIF to show me redundant changes
because by default it removes redundant changes.
And we see that we have the third function that was impacted as well
by the change we created.
And so, well, all the changes that impact function three
were already reported.
So, this is why it was suppressed.
That change was suppressed by default because it was redundant.
So, it's not just...
We're not just diffing things.
We're analyzing the diffs and we're trying to massage those diffs
so that they can be consumed by human beings.
So, this is what we mean by analyzing ABIs, basically.
So, how it works.
Libaby-Gal has...
So, the library used to implement the tools has a front-end
which is kind of backward.
The front-end reads the binary.
Usually it is backends that write binaries,
okay, here, backward.
So, we read the binary which has to be in the ELF format right now
and we build an internal representation of it.
We look at the publicly defined and exported symbols of,
you know, declarations, basically functions and variables.
We build a representation of them and their types.
And then we construct the graph of the types like that
and their subtypes and we pull all that together
and we call that an ABI corpus.
A corpus is an artifact for us that represent the ABI
of the binary we're looking at.
And so, there is a middle-end that acts
on that internal representation.
Said otherwise, it acts on ABI corpora.
Corpora being the plural of corpus in Latin, right?
Let's be pedantic.
So, we can, as you've seen,
compare two instances of ABI corpus.
Then we build an internal representation
of the results of the comparison.
We call that a DIF IR.
So, it's a different IR.
And then we perform transformations on that DIF IR.
Like categorization, so we will walk the graph and say, okay,
this DIF node, we've seen it before,
so we'll mark it as being redundant to this other one.
And then there can be transformations
that are suppression as well.
Well, suppression.
We will mark the nodes as being suppressed.
For instance, because the user wrote something
that we call a suppression specification file requiring
that some type's changes might not be reported.
So, once we have that well-massaged DIF IR,
we have backends that work that DIF IR, obviously,
or the initial IR, and do useful stuff.
Like writing, you know, emitting reports, for instance,
or emitting the representation of the ABI corpus
in a disk saved format that we called ABI XML.
So, what we've done recently, so I'm going a bit fast
because to let time for questions and stuff,
and we can go on and let's say not very structured discussion
afterwards, if you like.
So, yeah, in the recent times, what we've done is, well,
you know DWARF.
You know that it changes all the time
with new versions of DWARF producers.
So, with GCC 11 and LLVM 14, the default DWARF version
was bumped to the version 5, which is quite ancient,
actually.
I think it was released in 2017 or something.
So, yeah, we support most of that right now.
And another major thing that happened recently
was that, thanks to folks in this room that I won't,
don't worry, I won't give your name,
new debug info format were added because, yeah, we
started with DWARF only.
And so the CTF debug info format was, support
was added to libabigail.
So basically now, if you have a binary having CTF N or DWARF,
you can choose whatever you want to use as a source of type
information.
So things being how they are, the code
got changed a bit to be turned into a multi-frontend
architecture.
We also have a multi-backend architecture,
basically, because we have different types of reports.
The one I've shown you is the default one,
which is quite verbose.
So some people like it more terse.
So, yeah, and who knows whatever weird request users might
come with in the future.
So, yeah, different report backends.
And well, it doesn't stop there.
We are still working on new stuff
while coming from user request.
So, yeah, apparently the new kids on the block,
well, new kids in town now, cool stuff is BPF, right?
And with BPF comes BTF, which is the type description
format of BPF.
And so there were some requests to support that.
So it is now in mainline, even though it's not
in the labial mainline, but it's not released yet.
It should be released in the next version.
So what do we do with that?
What's that thing?
Basically, because BPF describes the C types,
basically, we are using that to compare the interface exposed
by the kernel to its modules.
So we're doing that with CTF already, with BPF now,
and also with Dwarf.
With Dwarf, it is much less fast, shall we say,
than with the CTF support and BPF.
So people are using that feature to analyze the KABI,
basically, kernel ABI, that thing that doesn't exist.
And then we've had weird project-specific requests
over the year.
And the last one that came in last month, I say,
or last month in January, was to have a,
I call that the library-set ABI analysis.
So basically, it's a project that has a huge library,
shared library, and they're planning
to split it in different libraries.
But then they keep ABI compatibility,
they're supposed to.
And so they would like to ensure that the set of broken-down
libraries has an ABI that is equivalent or compatible
with the first initial one.
This is what I call library-set ABI analysis.
So we're going to add support for that.
I don't know if it's going to be in the next version or not.
So yeah, these are the kinds of things we are working on.
So yeah, and now I'll let you ask questions if you have any.
Yeah?
Does the library have any support
for language-specific API?
So languages are used on top of C, for example,
where they have main means cubes?
Yeah, exactly.
So yes, of course, dwarf is multi-language.
So if the compiler of that language emits dwarf,
then we're good to go.
There is a small layer of language-specific stuff
we add for reporting so that we can report stuff
in the native language of the programmer who
wrote the thing.
So to give you a concrete example,
right now we support C++, C, Fortran.
Someone asked me for Rust support.
So we had that, basically.
We have some crashes on OCaml.
So I thought we were supporting it too,
but I need to do some stuff.
So yeah, basically, yeah, it needs work.
But the new language, I just have
to define a small layer for the mangling logic.
The mangling logic, so OK, I can show you.
Let me show you an example.
So yeah, I was writing.
So yeah, let's see.
So you see, for instance, in C++, we'll compare.
So here, you see this function, the function 3.
I'll change it in the second version here, function 3,
and I'll add an integer here, right?
Yes, let's, whoops, we compile that.
And whoops, weird stuff happened.
So look at what it is saying here.
So you see here, because we are in C++,
I changed function 3 in the source code.
Let me just, yeah, see?
I changed function 3 here, and I added a parameter.
That's what the programmer would say.
But then, from the binary standpoint, what we're seeing
is that the first function was removed,
and then another one got added.
This is because in C++, the name of the symbols
of the two functions, the two versions of functions,
are different.
They have a different mangling.
So we go from the name of the symbol
to the name of the declaration.
But if I do the same in C, then, like, yeah,
I knew you would ask that question.
I don't know you, but.
So and I have a second version here.
Boom, boom, boom.
And so here, some, oh, sorry.
I changed the parameter of the function there,
but this is in C, OK?
And so if I go in the shell, and I look at the two.
The first one was hello, and this one is bye, of course,
because I think this is going to be the last C here.
Because in C, the name of the two symbols are the same.
Now we say that the function has changed.
So these are the kind of things that we'll
have to adapt, basically.
But there is not much to do.
In some cases, you have mangling,
and in the other cases, you don't.
So you don't have anything to do with them for the mangling.
Does that answer your question?
Roughly.
You have this part of the code which decodes the mangled name
to a non-readable name?
No, because the matching is done by dwarf.
So we know that this symbol is for this declaration.
So we don't have to do the mangling or demangling.
We look at the addresses, and we know
that this symbol is for that one.
So yeah, we don't really care about that.
Yeah, please go ahead.
Do you think it's more about performance
to keep when you analyze your results?
Like, are they the one?
Well, there is none.
No, no, no, no.
It's so yeah, just to repeat the question for them.
What are the performance issues when
we analyze big libraries like he said LLVM,
but there is WebKit, Geko, et cetera, et cetera.
So when we're looking at dwarf, we
have a fundamental problem, which
is the duplication of types.
Here we are in the business of comparing things.
And so when we compare types, basically we
are in the land of quadratic algorithms.
So things are inherently slow if we do them naively.
And so the thing is in dwarf, every single type unit
is represented.
But then when you have the final binary, the final shell
library, for instance, and you have, I don't know,
1,000 translation units, and in every single translation unit
you had the string type, for instance, that was used,
then you will have the string type represented 1,000 times,
at least in the dwarf.
And so we must be sure that those 100 occurrences of string
are the one and the same.
We can't just look at the name and say they're the same
because they could be otherwise.
And so we have to compare them and make sure they're the same.
And then we'll say, OK, I'll just keep one
and throw away the others.
This is the duplication of type, it is called.
And so this process takes a huge amount of time, which is, well,
for huge libraries, it can take forever.
So we have heuristics to make this thing be faster.
But then it takes time.
So we have some of the heuristics
that we're using now is in the land of partitioning.
We will do things piecewise so that we
can do things in parallel.
It is not main line yet, but this
is the future we're thinking about.
Another approach is to have the types be deduplicated
before we intervene.
This is what, for instance, the CTF guys do with C.
So they will do the deduplication at debug info
production time.
And then in that case, we're golden.
There is another case where we're doing that
is when we are building distribution packages,
like, for instance, I don't know,
RPM or Debian package or whatever,
there is a tool which is called DWZ, which
does the deduplication to one extent.
Well, when it works, it works.
It does the deduplication.
But the problem is DWZ has the same issue as us.
And sometimes when the binary is too big, DWZ will just give up.
And in that case, well, we have to use our little hands
and do the deduplication in line.
And then, well, we'll spend time.
But this because someone should get
the DWZ turned into a library and put it in the linker.
Yes.
And yes.
Do it in link time.
Yeah, we can.
Yeah, that's something that one of the things
that we need to do to improve the entire ecosystem
of these things.
And yeah, that's definitely.
So someone comes for free time and.
Yeah.
So yeah.
So as I'm, do we have other questions?
Or?
Yeah.
So are there any other formats that are on your roadmap?
Right now, no.
But three months ago, BTF was not on my roadmap.
So the future is not what it used to be.
So I don't know.
Yeah.
Anyway, so yeah, we are hosted on Sourceware.
We still use mailing lists.
You send us patches.
And yeah, you can find us on IRC on the OfTeeC network.
And well, thank you very much.