All right. So it's two minutes early, but I have
a tendency to speak and not stop,
so we better get started here.
So I am so tired of doing introductory talks to poke.
So I have decided that this is the last one I'm going to do.
So, but let's see.
Is anyone here familiar with this program somehow?
Yes? Okay. So yeah,
we need to do an introductory talk.
So, GNU poke is
an extensible editor for a structure binary data.
So it is a program that you can actually expand.
We will see how, and you can expand it
actually quite to a very high degree.
And we will see that it's a program that is used to poke,
or to mess, to edit data which is encoded in binary.
We will see what this thing about binary.
Everything is binary at the end of the day.
So first, I'm going to do a very small introduction,
an abstract one.
I mean, why would you use such a program?
Then we will see how we are actually integrating poke in
other programs via a shared object, a library.
Then I will basically talk a little bit about
the project itself, the current status.
We just made a major release that we are very happy about it.
And we are very busy because the project is getting a lot of,
we have a lot of things to do.
It's getting very fun actually.
And then finally, an invitation to you to actually join us
in hacking this program.
So let's start with a very small introduction.
I mean, when it comes to edit binary data,
well, what do you use?
You use a binary editor, right?
If you go around and then you look around in internet about
binary editors, you have the simplest kind, what I call
simple binary editors, which is your garden variety programs
which show you a byte dump.
And then a lot of them also show you the ASCII
representation of the same bytes.
What do you see in the screen?
How many of those programs are around?
Quite a lot of them.
And they are nice.
I mean, they are nice.
They are useful.
They are small.
They are very easy to use.
There is nothing mysterious about them.
They are interactive usually.
The ones that allow you to actually change the value of
those bytes in the files, you just go to the byte you want
to change, you put in the new value for the bytes, ta-da.
If you want to change based on some string, you go to the
ASCII column there.
You go to the position you want to edit.
You change it.
But the file gets updated.
Very nice.
They are interactive.
They support immediate editing.
You go, you change here, and it immediately gets reflected
in the file that you are editing, for example.
What do they let you edit?
In terms of what?
Well, it depends.
But those simple binary editors, they let you operate
in terms of bytes, in terms of strings, like we just
mentioned, and sometimes this is not often, but sometimes
in terms of bits as well.
Some of those basic binary editors, they support down to
the bit level too.
And that's it.
That's the thing.
You can edit in terms of those entities, of those
concepts, bytes, bits, strings sometimes, sometimes numbers.
Then the editor is not so simple anymore.
But it's always a fixed list of abstractions that you can
edit, you manipulate your data using those abstractions.
Then they give you, generally, byte dumps, the ASCII views.
And they have fixed capabilities, depending on
how nice the particular editor is.
Some of them allow you to search for patterns.
Some others to search and replace, to make byte divs.
That kind of thing.
Measure entropy, to search for frame buffers.
Simple binary editors.
They are useful.
But then sometimes you have to edit, or you want to edit,
your data in terms not just of bytes or bits, but in terms
of more abstract entities, like MP3 headers, or else
relocations, or lists of numbers, or whatever.
And then for that, you have traditionally specialized
binary editors, which are editors, like the two that you
can see here, that know about some particular format.
Like some of them, the one on the left
knows about the L format.
So you can see a tree view, which is quite nice, you know,
with the different sections in the Ls.
And the one on the right, which is small, but it's nice,
is a very small MP3 editor to edit MP3 files.
Actually, the metadata associated with the MP3,
like the title of the song, the name of the singer,
or whatever, right?
Those specialized binary editors, they are nice too.
They are useful.
But they are not extensible usually.
I mean, you cannot go and say, oh, well, you know.
I mean, in the Ls program here, you know I want to,
you know that Ls sections can contain arbitrary data, right?
So you say, well, I want to use the same editor
to edit the contents of one of the Ls sections.
Usually they don't let you do that.
So they are not extensible.
They also, they are not quite good at dealing
with incorrect data.
So if you get a corrupted L file or some MP3 file
that has problems in it, those editors probably
they are going to refuse to actually open them,
open those files.
And if they do, they are probably going to show you garbage,
right?
So they are not good at that.
And you know it's the typical situation.
Exactly what you need is what they don't implement, right?
It's always like that.
So those are the specialized binary editors.
And then we have Katai's tract and friends,
which is they implement this paradigm of,
as you know, we got a nice presentation before.
The first you decode the data, like with one of the parsers
of Katai's tract, for example.
Then you do your computation with the data.
And then maybe you use an encoder, right,
to write back the modified data.
This is what they call the code compute and code.
Programs like these are also useful.
Those are extensible, like we have seen with Katai's tract.
You can define your own structures.
They use, usually, some sort of declarative way
of describing the layout of those data structures.
They generate code in several target languages.
I don't know why Katai's tract does not generate C. I mean,
to me, I'm so puzzled about that.
But OK.
Usually, those are non-interactive.
They are not interactive.
Like you generate a parser that generates that parser
in some programming language that then you incorporate
your program and then you run, right?
Usually, they are not that good to dealing with incorrect data
either, right?
Because the parser that they generate expects correct data.
And they are either bit-oriented,
which is not common.
I don't know if Katai's tract can deal at a bit level.
Good.
Also, not aligned stuff.
And orbit-oriented.
And often, there are no encoders.
I know that Katai's tract now, they
are starting to add the support for actually writing data back
to the file.
This is nice, too.
And then you have the poke approach, which is circular.
What we wanted with this was the following.
We wanted the immediate aspect of the simple binary editors.
Like, OK, I go to this byte and then I change it.
Now, I mean, now change it immediately.
But also, we wanted the extensibility
and the ability of working with higher abstractions
like you have with the parser generates,
like Katai's tract, for example.
We wanted everything together.
And that is what poke is in few words.
Basically, you describe your data structures,
like in a struct type, for example,
and you can immediately poke at it.
You can immediately update it, edit it, write to it.
And if you are not satisfied with that,
you can on the fly using the same program in the prompt,
you can redefine your data structure and do it again.
This is good for also discovering the format
of what you are editing, like in reverse engineering
and whatnot.
And when you are developing a new format,
you know that kind of use cases.
So it is interactive with the poke application.
It allows immediate editing.
It allows data integrity.
You can define your own complex structure, quite complex ones.
And then it supports a very powerful and to the point
domain specific language.
I'm a big fan of domain specific languages
because we have the ability and the brains
to actually talk in several languages
and write in several programming languages.
And it is so great when a tool actually
gives you the way of expressing things
that are most suitable for the task at hand.
The DSL is called poke as well, like the program,
but with a big P to distinguish the programming language
from the program itself.
It is interactive, aesthetically typed in purpose.
It is garbage collected.
It has some very interesting features,
this programming language, because it's designed to,
you know, to the point, to the task at hand.
So for example, it's not bit oriented,
and it's not byte oriented.
It is unit oriented.
So in poke, when you start talking about offset sizes
in memory and so on, you don't talk in bytes or in bits.
You talk in terms of arbitrary units that you can define.
I'm sorry I cannot get in detail because this is, you know,
like a fast pitch, but you have all the information,
you know, in the internet and so on.
And also it works in bit addressable IOS spaces.
It can work with incorrect data because you
can do non-strict mapping, saying, OK,
I want to disable the constraints,
do that integrate the constraints.
So you can actually discover what you have in front of you
and adapt your own definitions to it and so on.
You can define several versions of the same structure
very easily to be more strict, less strict.
And it is extensible.
We will see that notebook is not just a binary editor.
It is a full infrastructure to write binary utilities as well.
And then similarly to what KITA is trying to do,
for example, when it comes to document formats,
you can use poke also to document formats
and protocols in a functional way
because your same documentation, you can use it, you know,
to actually operate with the data.
To do prototyping, to write binary utilities,
to implement filters, and so on.
And then to integrate in other programs, which is very cool.
I will show you in five minutes one example with the debugger,
with GDB.
Now, poke operates in, it can operate on files, memory
buffers, you know the memory of running processes.
There is a collection of IOD devices, right,
which are what you are editing.
But what a poke program or what you have access
from the command line is to a bit addressable IOS space.
We call those IOS spaces in which you can actually map
or you know manipulate different kind of entities, which
are integers and same integers are things, right,
from the poke language.
OK, we all know what bytes are, right?
You will be surprised many people don't.
They are just little numbers in a certain range, right,
from 0 to 255.
So this is the way you know in poke
you have to refer to bytes.
But what I wanted to show you, because I think
it's the interesting part, is that it's the way that you go,
that in poke you have from bytes to actually encode
in integers, right?
So you see here, I don't know if you can see,
you see here the IOD device there,
which is the underlying device that you are editing,
like the file, right?
And then it has bytes, which are little numbers, right,
from 0 to 255 in the range.
And then the IOS space, which is on top of each byte,
of the bytes, is the bit addressable IOS space
that your poke programs actually see.
But we all know that bits, it's actually
a very interesting thing.
Bits exist usually at the hardware level.
Then they disappear until you will recreate them.
You know virtually, you know on top of those byte numbers,
right?
It's very interesting.
So from poke what you see is the bits
that are conceptually on top of the bytes.
And that's the poke type, for example.
This is an unsigned 16 bits integer
mapped in the IOD device at the first byte.
But this is a boring example.
It gets even more interesting.
What we call wired integers, weird integers, right?
So for example, in poke you can operate with 12 bits
unsigned integers, as naturally as you
will do with a 32 bits unsigned integer.
This is quite cool actually, and useful, believe it or not.
Then we have some conventions, you
know, to refer to the bits and everything.
But this integer actually occupies one full byte,
and then half of the next one.
But also you can go to less than one byte, right?
Like in this case.
So you can actually operate with an unsigned integer of five
bits.
And then it doesn't feel like a complete byte.
Obviously, since everything that there is in a computer
is actually bytes, the drivers level, hardware level,
you know, and everywhere, this is an artifact.
But it's a useful one.
And poke also has full support for an aligned stuff too.
So you can work with actually a 16 unsigned integer,
shift to bits in the IOS space.
Can Kaita Yestrak do that?
Yes, we will have to see.
So yeah, so you could obfuscate your file just by shifting
that three bits to the right, for example.
Why not?
Maybe fun.
I included this here not to impress the cat,
but to give you an impression, you
know, the impression that actually poke,
it's a serious problem.
I mean, it's not just, you know, a stupid problem,
you know, that poking at bytes here and there.
We actually take it very seriously.
And you can do this kind of stuff.
And believe it or not, people need this kind of stuff.
The other day in the IRC, we met the politicians,
which is a community of people who are, you know,
dealing with multics.
And you will not believe what they need.
Really, right?
I mean, like nine bits bytes, you know how it's unbelievable.
And we are struggling to actually give the people
what they need because they have rights too.
The multics people have rights too.
Anyway, so the poke sphere, poke is growing and growing.
This started with one simple.
It was always a little bit special, but you know,
a little program.
But it's getting out of hands at the moment.
And in the sense that we have LeapFolk, which
is a shared object.
Obviously, first I made it in a problem,
but the dodgy in one column, I got an asshole.
Put it in a library.
So I did.
So and then LeapFolk is a shared object
that has the poke incremental compiler, the IOS space
support, and everything.
We will see now with GDB as an example how you can actually
make use of it in your own programs.
Then poke is the command line application, right?
Which uses LeapFolk.
But it's just a program, a very small program,
you know, with a prompt, you know, like,
bin LS, load, you can dump bytes, right?
Sorry, here.
And bar elf, elf, 64, file at 0 bytes, you know.
You know, stuff like this.
The command line application.
But all of the logic is actually in the shared object.
Then you have other applications like GDB, which have,
this is not upstream yet.
It's in a branch upstream, but not in master.
But they can actually use LeapFolk
to give you poke capabilities.
I will show you now in a two minute little demo.
There is a poke daemon too that Muhammad will talk about.
Yeah?
Take a half a minute.
Utilities, the pickles, which are the poke programs that
give you the support for some particular format
or some particular domain.
Then there is an MX interface, of course.
Then there is an MX mode for the poke program, VIM for unholy
people for everything.
You know, the poke code in VIM, in VI.
Something called pokelets, and so on, and so on, and so on.
So it's getting fun.
And then the integration.
I'm very, I like this.
You know, there is one problem when people write a program,
they want it to do everything very well.
And that does not work.
So for example, in poke we have some support
for editing the memory of running processes.
We do.
Well, I could show you, but I don't have time for that.
Because we have an IOD, which is you can specify the process
ID of a process, and then you can edit the running memory,
you know, of the memory of the running process.
But poke is not a debugger.
It's not.
I mean, it doesn't, there is a dwarf pickle,
but you know not to the same extent that a debugger.
You cannot set breakpoints.
You cannot use ptrace to command a process.
But gdb is a debugger.
So gdb is good at debugging, at running processes, and so on.
And poke is good at poking at data, right?
So let's put them together.
So then the combination is good at both.
And this can be achieved by using libpoke.
So I can show you very fast.
So I have the C file.
You see the C file?
I have a C extract frob with an int tag.
Can you see it properly there?
Yes?
Which one?
No, I'm not going to address this.
Trust me.
OK.
So there is this extract type.
Then there is this buffer.
There is this db global variable here, and so on, and so on.
Right?
And an int main.
So then I compile that into an aout.
And then I do home.
This is the poke-capable gdb, a.out, break main, run.
Now I am in main, right?
Here.
And then I can use gdb to look at the database here.
You know this db global variable, and so on.
Now this gdb is extended with poke.
So you have a poke command where you can execute any poke code.
Like this, like 2 plus 2 equals 4.
Brilliant.
But here you can do anything that you can do with poke.
So for example, you could say, and poke in this case
is it has access to the memory of the inferior
that you are debugging with udb.
So even if it's multiprocess or multithread, you switch in gdb
and then poke has access to the memory of the inferior.
So what kind of things you can do?
Well, anything.
I mean, what is the address in gdb of this global variable
here?
Sorry.
That is the address.
So with poke, you could access to that address.
But you have a command which is poke at types, which
is you are telling gdb to make poke aware of all the types
known to gdb at this point in time.
So the type char, the char type int,
destruct prop that we saw before.
And then this translated into poke type definitions
for the key-valent gdb types.
This means that you can go from btf, from ctf, from door,
from any debugging format that gdb understands to poke types
while you are using gdb in this way.
Now, poke now has access to the memory of the inferior.
So we could do, for example, and those are poke expressions,
right?
extract prop at where?
And you can use something we call alien tokens,
which is the address of the gdb symbol db, which
is the variable, right?
And this is the poke extract.
This is not a gdb value.
This is a poke extract, which is poking at inferior memory.
And you, of course, can write.
You can do whatever you want.
You can load pickles.
Why is this useful for?
Well, imagine you are debugging a program that
is some sort of router for TCP.
So the program itself, you have TCP packets
and some buffers in the program.
But the program itself doesn't need
to understand the payload of what it is transporting.
But imagine that you want to take a look at what
is going on there, right?
So then you don't have the Dorf definitions
of the structures that are in the buffer in the payload.
But with poke, you just load your pickle
or you are right your own, and you can poke at it
from gdb in the buffer of the running process, for example.
So this is one example of application.
This is 400 lines of C, the integration using lead poke.
It's very nice.
You know it's easy.
Another example, which is work in progress,
and I can't wait to get this finished,
is basically to add to the assembler a dot poke directive.
Because you know those dot war, dot byte, and so on directives
in the assembler?
They are not portable.
And this is a pain in the ass.
Because when you have to actually, for example,
test Dorf or test, you know, that kind of things,
then they are not portable.
I know it's amazing, but they are not portable.
So see, for example, that.
This is a real example of something I found.
I will not tell where.
Of some people who are actually embedding
some sort of executables inside other sections of some
of the stuff.
This is a video games, you know, kids.
They do these kind of things.
And that is a struct, in theory, of what?
Of some heater, right?
For the PlayStation or whatever.
Well, compare.
You see?
So once we have the integration in the assembler,
then you will be able to load the PSXX pickle.
It will be a small one where you define, you know,
that structure of this executable.
And then you could poke at assembly time,
you know, like that too.
And accessing gas assembler symbols,
you know, using alien tokens, like we saw you
could do with GDB as well.
So this is another example of integration.
Yeah.
So we are on these kind of things now.
We are looking into parasiting other programs, you know,
and incorporating lip poking them.
So they do all the boring work, and we do the fun one.
OK.
So what's the current status of the program?
We just released the POC 3.0 a few days ago.
Up to now, we were doing one major release every year,
and we had a maintenance branch.
But people are not happy.
Why?
Because it was too long, and the difference between POC 2
and POC 3, it was too big.
It was too much.
And actually, we released the POC 2.0, for example.
And in two weeks, we have forgotten about it already,
because we are so happy, you know,
and so excited with the main branch.
So now we are committing to release two big major releases
every year.
Let's see if we can actually do that.
The development, we are old GNU P spots, right?
So we don't use GitHub or anything like that.
So we use a mailing list, and you
send your patch to the mailing list in Unity format,
and so on and so on, right?
And well, that is the website of the project.
We have a Git repository, obviously.
We have a mailing list, a development mailing list.
We have a very nice build box at sourceware.
Thank you very much to the sourceware overseers.
They are doing a great job maintaining
the infrastructure of many GNU programs, including
Polk and also the toolchain, GCC and the Ellipse and so on,
for many years.
And also, we have a pipeline hosted at GitLab
that Bruno Heibel maintains.
And I have no idea how it works.
It's not clear to me what even a pipeline is in that context,
but it's green.
So I guess it's good.
We have a community website.
It's called Polkology.
And we try to get practical information there,
like how can you write your pickles and so on.
And also, I have a blog in my website, where sometimes I
publish small articles, like also with practical stuff.
So how can you do, for example, implementing sparse tables
using Polk or accessing them stuff?
We want to be friendly to users.
And now, starting now, in Polk, we
had in the Polk source distribution, GNU Hacks Polk,
we had a pickles directory with a lot of pickles, right?
Like for P, for L, for DOR, for BTF, for this, for that.
Some instructions said RISC-V, BTF.
But this is getting crowded.
And actually, some pickles are big and complex enough
to actually need their own releases,
so you can have several versions that
work with the same version of Polk.
So we are basically putting some of the pickles
in separated packages.
And that's the case of the ELF pickle and the DORF pickle.
So for example, the ELF pickles, now
they are distributed separately.
Have not made the first release yet,
but they are in the git repository.
They have their own manual and so on, and the DORF pickles
as well.
Those are the first ones.
We want to get the P-Cov support because it's
a huge fat monster, that one.
We want to put it also in its own package.
And also, with nice manuals, I have
to show you this because it is such a pain to do it
that you have to brag about it.
So this is the Polk manual, the GNU Polk manual.
And then when you install the pickles packages,
like Polk DORF and Polk ELF, and here you
have a nicely documented pickles and everything.
And the source distribution.
Sorry?
You use man pages, not the menu.
Well, well.
Oh, well.
We are generating man pages from the tech info.
Yeah.
Then actually, the idea is to use the ELF pickle
because we are new, writing pickles,
because Polk is sort of new, right?
So we are trying to discover our way forward.
But the Polk ELF pickles is sort of the canonical example.
We are using it that way.
We are writing it very carefully.
So if you want to write a complex pickle,
you can look at it.
This is it.
I am so sorry that they could not give you
an actual taste of how this program is.
But there is no time for that.
And there are other videos in the internet
that they have done already.
And then if you want to join the development,
read, please read the hacking file,
because we took the effort of writing it.
It's huge.
It has a lot of good information.
And absolutely no one reads it.
So thank you very much.
Thanks.