I'm Matthias Waldmann, I'm the author of this FQ tool.
I'm not going to be able to show all slides, I think.
I want to do a lot of demo because I think it's a good tool to demo.
Can you talk a bit louder?
I can try.
There is FQ, it's a tool and the language and a group of set of decoders to work with
data more or less.
It used to be binary data, but now it's also text data.
Well, I guess it's binary also in a sense.
So it's heavily inspired by JQ, both as an easy JQ, the language, but it's also the CLI
tool.
It's inspired by how the arguments work and everything.
And it's a tool for querying and displaying data exactly like JQ.
But it also has an interactive weapon so you can work with it in a more interactive way.
It has auto completion and a lot of other bells and whistles to make it very nice to
work with.
And it's available for a lot of operating systems.
So I like to call it like a debugger for files.
That's how I use it.
So while JQ, it's a very CLI friendly language.
You don't need any new lines.
It's like the syntax is very, very tears.
You can do a lot with a little syntax.
And it's very composable.
You have this pipe, it's more or less like shell pipes.
But it has these generators.
You can even do loops and iterate and recurse using these pipes.
So you see these square brackets like that to iterate and dot dot is to recurse it through
three of values, you can say.
And it's also kind of like DSL for selecting and transforming JSON.
You can call it JSON.
It just happens to have JSON as an input output.
Internally, you can call it JQ values.
It has arrays and objects and numbers and strings and boots.
So it's kind of like a super set of JSON.
And I have an example here that you build a new object that has a key A that is an array
that is one plus two plus three and empty.
And you see that it becomes the object with just A and array one five.
And empty was just a function that does nothing.
It outputs no value at all.
And you can also select values from the input.
So here we have the object with A and B and then you create a new object that has the
sum key and then that's the sum of A plus B. So that's point three.
And it's purely function language based on generators and backtracking.
But it has conditioners, it has function, it has bindings, it has all things you need.
And the default is that you had one JQ filter or program that you run individually on each
input file.
But then it has functions to tell it to not behave like that.
So you can run one filter on a group of files, for example.
And FQ has support currently for 113 formats.
And it has most of, I guess, half of them are media related because I work with media.
So just like MP3, MP4, or Flack.
And they also have support for like the de-muxing some of these forms.
Some of these containers they have support for segmenting, I think.
So you can kind of recombine it and then decode the de-muxed sample and things.
But there have been other people added other things.
So executable formats, archiving, networking.
So you can do PP cap nowadays.
You can do TCP reassembly even.
And even decode the TCP stream.
So it has support for RTMP, for example.
And it also has support for some serialization forms like message pack and ASN1BR and C-BOR.
And it also has support for some text format.
Some of them you can even decode ending code.
So you can decode it into a JQ or JSON value, transform it with JQ and then encode it back
to some other text format.
You can't do it with the binary formats.
I will see if I get to that to explain why that is not easy.
So what does it mean when you decode?
What does it mean that the FQ support the format?
It means that it can, there is some code, it's written in Go.
So there's like a kind of a DSL for writing decoders.
And that produces a structure that is JSON compatible.
But each value in this structure also have a know which bit range they come from.
And they also have an option that it can have symbolic mappings.
You can map the number to a string or string to a string or a Boolean.
In binary formats we usually encode some number that means something.
Like this is the app level, you will get that.
And for media this usually means that it's, you decode everything except the pixels or
the audio because it's like, ah, then you can use it as a fanpape or whatever you want.
There are some format that actually decodes to the samples.
Flack, for example, we have support for actually decoding.
So there is a full Flack decoder in Flack Cube, but you can't listen to the sound.
And some format can use other formats.
That's how they are.
They are like hierarchy that they use.
So you can use like a PPA uses Ethernet decoder using IPV.
And then you can even end up with the loops here that they like zip files in the zip file
and yeah.
And there's also support for formats to pass.
You can even return value, you can return like values from a decoder into another decoder.
You don't see this from the outside, but then for example MP4 has some boxes that have like
information about how the samples should be decoded, like how long or some fields or things.
So then MP4 and MP4 decoder can pass that information down to another sample decoder.
So how do I use?
I use it because of this, because I work in media, so all more or less the whole MP4 file
is metadata about how to play this.
How to see, how to sing, how to yeah, everything.
And I guess Derek had a good talk about why this multimedia is basically endless pain.
And I guess FQ can't really fix the pain, but it can locate the pain, I guess.
So this is what I use it for.
I debug query assist when I work in media files and it's used for someone that is usually
at work, there's a media file that has broken, it doesn't transcode or it's not in sync or
and they say what is wrong with this file?
And we have to figure out like what is it?
Is it a decoder problem, the moxer problem, is it an encoder?
Is it corrupt?
Is it whatever?
So FQ is very useful to quickly triage a lot of broken media files.
Let's see.
And I can just short, what is the time?
Short like, well, what can it not do?
Or what is not good?
It's not good for encoding, like to change things.
You can change things, but it's more about slicing binaries into and then concatenate
them together and then write them out to a new file.
So there's no like you can't just change the value in some JSON structure and just
serialize it back because it's like a quick sample.
I gave an example here with the MP4 moxer.
But what would it mean to add or remove a sample in MP4 file?
Then you would have to change all the boxes that describe how big the samples are and
it just cascades away into.
Yeah.
And you can see that MP4, FFmpeg's MP4 implementation is 17,000 lines of C code, very dense C code.
So it's used FFmpeg if you want to do those kind of things.
And I think you see and Pietter will talk about more about encoding, I guess, and why
this is complicated.
And you can repair media files with FQ, but you probably have to be more or less an expert
in the format that you're fixing.
I usually do like I have, you can fix things by kind of testing the code, the configurations,
or you use some kind of, you encode something and borrow from another media file and somehow
stitch together to see what it is.
So there is, I have some FQ code to build like ADTS headers and whatever, if you want.
If you find an AC frame somewhere, you don't even know what, because an AC frame has to
have metadata about like what, how many channels it has and what profile it is and things.
And it doesn't do any decoders in runtime at the moment.
You can't write the decoder, you have to write it in Go now and then compile it.
So we'll see.
Maybe in the future it will have characterised support.
I have to have a prototype for K-Type, but it is complicated.
It has an expression language.
I have to write a parser for that.
Maybe I will talk to you about this and see.
There is more slides here, but I will, you can read them.
I want to do a demo instead.
So is it big enough?
So FQ is just a CLI tool, works like this and you can do, if you want to list all the
format that it supports.
So if you run FQ, let's see, it has a pickup if you do.
So the first argument is the filter that you want to run and dot in the AQ is just an identity
function that is just, it gives you what you put in to get the root, kind of.
So here we see that it's a pickup.
It has a header, it has packets and some TCP or some TCP connections and things.
So you can do dash I, actually I want to do a cache course in the JQ.
I don't know how many people know how the JQ works.
So I can do a short version how, just to show the particularities of JQ.
So now I started JQ with dash I, which gives you just a null input.
You get one input that is just null.
So it's just a way of, you can at least just execute JQ values because it needs to have
input somehow, out all ways.
So now you can just write, yeah, strings or whatever you want to do.
And if you do dot there, you just get null.
And I guess the most special thing about JQ is the comma operator and that outputs a value.
So you can do one comma one, two, three.
It gives you one, two, three.
But then in JQ you can, there are some special forms like this collect, which sounds, this
looks very familiar to us as an array that then collects those values into something.
But then in JQ you could, you could just write the expressions here or whatever you want.
So let's say we can define a function, for example.
So and then you can just collect that function or you can call it two times or you can map
those values.
But you see how, maybe it was too fast to, but you see how you can define function, you
can have bindings.
So it's a full function language that's, it's very, I like it a lot how it works.
So let's back to that pcap file.
So let's see, you can do, for example, if you want to see, look at the first packet,
you can do this.
You can pipe it to D which is, shows more recursively all the, like if you, if you just
give it, when you do this, you actually run D also, but it also show, it only shows one
level.
So if you do D it, it will show you all of it.
So here you can see, like you can write on the AQU expression here that is like, show
me the first and the last packet and it will do this.
And then you can say both of them.
Yeah.
So you can do things like that.
So let's see, we can go into the GCP connection and we take the first one.
We can do D and we see that this is a, so it seems to be HTTP request.
Someone has downloaded the file.
So let's see, we can go to the server stream.
Let's see.
And there's one thing about the AQ is that the AQ doesn't have binary support.
It only has strings.
So FQ has, to support binary, you can, there is some special functions in FQ to tell it
up.
So that this string is actually binary or I want it as binary if it's possible.
So then you can say like this string, for example, if I would just do type just a string,
but if I do two bytes, you will actually get the row bytes.
And then I can say like, I want to maybe 400 first and DD is something that shows the whole,
it doesn't truncate out.
So here we see that this is some kind of HTTP request.
Let's see.
It's torch.
Class 10.
Class 7.
So let's say we want to get the bytes for this.
Okay.
Plus.
So here I think I have the body of the whole request.
So in YAQ you can more than do, for example, this, all the coders in FQ are YAQ functions.
You can do this now and it will decode this MP4 file.
So now you can start with a sub-repl, for example, and now you're inside the MP4 inside
the PCAP.
And now you can do, and here you have the whole box tree for MP4 file.
And you can, for example, go into the samples.
I think this is some kind of subtitles MP4 file that I found somewhere.
And here you have the tracks.
It has samples.
So this is like the raw bytes for that sample.
And you see it's some kind of weird XML subtitle.
And FQ has support for XML, so you can do this.
And then you get a JSON version of the XML.
I see we can see that most, there is some, let's see, I can write something that takes
out all the, this is probably not how you write the TTML subtitle parser, but we can
do a quick, quick version of it.
And there is some functions like grep by that recurs with look for some condition.
So here, for example, you can look for, I did not work.
Why?
I see.
Ah, this should be XML dot.
So, so now it recurs to define all those texts, the objects that had the text field and then
just took that text field.
So now you can, for example, take this expression, go out to the, where did you have the rectum?
Here.
And then you can go out to the prompt again and then remove the interactive and then do
this instead.
Or you can do this if you only want to have text.
And we can even, let's say we want all samples.
So here is all the, that's the thing you can do with all these decoders, the codes and
blah, blah.
And then you can iteratively do all this.
It's like, yeah, it's nice.
So let's see.
And I also want to show that you can, you can actually, you don't have to write this,
all this.
When after a while you maybe with your expression starts to get very long.
So you want to have more structures.
I can show you, I have some helpers for MP4 files, for example.
Maybe you know, so I spent a lot of times in MP4 files.
Of course that's like what is used everywhere nowadays.
So here is some helpers, for example, that can be written in a more structured way with
the indentation and things.
So you, you don't go crazy.
And I can show here, for example, this, this is a bit long, but for example, here is an
expression that loads this MP4.yq and it finds the video track and then it uses some yaky
code to produce a GNU plot output.
And it uses GNU plot and then I have my weird tool I have for producing images in the terminal.
So here's the bit rate for the video, bit rate per, bits per second in this video.
And you see that it's probably the, this top there up over the iframes in the MP4 file.
So that was, maybe we can take questions.
I think.
Yes.
Yeah, you can use that as a hexa tool also.
Maybe it's not very convenient as a hexa tool, but you can, for example, you can do dash
D bytes or bits.
Then you get like a, it's just a dummy decoder kind of.
So you can do, for example, bytes, file.bcap.
So, so now you just get bits, so now you can do.
So and then you can concatenate this into, you can, you can build this like a binary
array cycle.
They are like IELTS in Erlan, if you have used that.
That you can, it's just an array with things that can become binary and then it can, and
you can kind of pipe this to two bytes and then you get back.
So you can kind of do this.
You can, yeah, I'll bet you don't see it now.
Yeah, so you see that you can, you can build this.
That's how you can, how you can repair things with FQ that you take the samples and then
add on some header and then you concatenate the bytes.
And you can even decode it with the AQ again.
You can, I mean, you could, you could try the code this as an MP3 file for example,
but it won't work.
Yes.
I would like to have some more timey version.
I can show how there's one slide show actually how the DSL, how the, how the Golang DSL looks
like.
Yeah, here, here is how kind of how the go DSL works.
That you, there's like a D function of this kind of like the context for the keep structure
where you are and then you create like new structs and fields and then, and you have
these mappers that say like, this is a binary for made up binary format for like binary
open source licenses that I was going to the moment there.
So that's how, how most of the code looks like.
So you can do, you can write any go code.
I mean, I prefer to write them to make them look very declarative, like don't use too
many.
Yeah.
Too much weird coding.
Keep them simple.
Any other questions?
Yes.
I'm going to say that it's probably hard to write the code.
I think it creates a lot of options.
How about what, what does the user mean when they change something?
Like do they want, yeah, it's also like, do you, do you want the check sums to be recalculated
or not?
Do you want, what happens if you change something in a, if you have the max something and then
you change the size.
So now the segmenting becomes different.
So then it cascades to change the whole file.
So it's like, do you want that to happen?
It's also like, there are encodings that are, there are like many ways to encode the same
integer, for example.
VAR ints can be encoded in many, many ways.
So you would encode it and normalize all that, or should it be, should it remember, try to
remember how, how the original thing was decoded.
Yeah.
So it's, it's complicated.
Any other questions?
Well, thank you.
Yes, thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.