Hi, everybody.
Welcome to my presentation about KITAI's tract.
I am Peter Puccio,
and I have a question.
How many of you have any experience with KITAI?
Okay, so there are a few of you.
What is KITAI's tract?
It's a tool for dealing with binary formats,
especially parsing.
It is based on a declarative language,
KITAI's tract YAML,
that can be used to specify arbitrary binary formats.
It works as a parser generator,
and it currently supports 11 target programming languages.
Parsing means to convert the binary data you see above,
to the structured data and object tree,
so that you can work with it later.
Today, I will also introduce a new functionality,
which is serialization,
and I've been working on it for the last six months,
and it currently works in Java.
Serialization means, I didn't mention that,
that basically the inverse process.
So you want to create a binary file from an object tree.
Something about this story.
So the author of KITAI's tract is Michael Action,
and the project started in 2014.
In 2016, Michael decided to
release the project as open source,
and at that time,
the only supported languages were Java and True
and at that time, the only supported languages were Java and True.
In 2017, Michael presented KITAI's tract at FOSDEM,
and by then it already supported eight languages
and had over 400 stars on GitHub.
And Michael also wanted to come today,
but unfortunately he couldn't,
but if there is some chat or something,
I think he should be there so you can ask him some questions or whatever.
And how is it today?
So we have 11 target languages and over 3,000 stars on GitHub,
and KITAI is used in more than 500 GitHub projects.
So let me share how I discovered KITAI's tract.
This was in 2019,
and I was playing electronic keyboard with a band,
and I wanted to create a MIDI editor so that I
could record the songs on the keyboard and edit them on the computer.
And I wanted the user to be able to upload
a sound bank in the Soundfont2 binary format so that
they could control how the song could sound.
And I wanted a web-based MIDI editor,
so I searched for a JavaScript parsing library of the.sf2 format,
but I couldn't find one that would work for me.
So I started writing my own parser,
but it was really hard and a lot of debugging had to be done,
and it was just not fun.
And when I finished,
I came across KITAI's tract and I found that my two months of work I spent on this
could be done in just one day with KITAI.
So KITAI impressed me with its concept,
simplicity, and versatility,
and I started contributing a lot.
And KITAI also helped me in my personal development because until then,
I'd only programmed in JavaScript,
PHP, and a little bit of Python.
And within a few months,
I was able to work in
14 programming languages that were used in KITAI.
And in 2020, I accepted an offer from Michael to become an administrator of the project.
So in my story, I showed what options there are to get a parser.
So the most convenient way that you are probably familiar with is to
use a dedicated format library in the given language.
So it will probably have a user-friendly API and can be optimized for a format.
But sometimes it may be of poor quality and incomplete,
and it may be difficult to debug and fix it.
And also for the most common formats like JPEG,
L4ZIP, you can find even several libraries and you can choose.
But for less common formats,
some obscure ones, there will simply be no library in your language.
So we need to look into other options.
And another option is to simply write your own parser.
But in my experience,
this is the worst option because it takes a lot of time
and you need to do a lot of debugging using some debug prints and dumps,
and it's just not fun.
But it's what most people do,
often because they just don't know any better.
So that's why I'm here today.
And well, the problem is that if you have already written a parser for your format in Python,
for example, and then after some time you are asked to create a Java parser for the same format,
you basically need to start again.
So a bit better way is to parse a combinator,
which means that you are essentially still writing your own parser,
but you are using some building blocks from a library.
And a parser combinator typically allows you to declaratively define some substructures,
but still in the code.
And like in C, you can define structs for the fixed size pieces of the format,
and then you can directly interpret some block of bytes with that struct.
And there are many parser combinators,
perhaps dozens in popular languages,
but as with the two previous options,
you have still the disadvantage that the parser will get this way,
is still bound to a particular language.
And it may be even bound to an application, for example,
if it was developed for a graphical editor.
So it may be difficult to separate just the parser from that application to use it somewhere else.
And the fourth option is to use a parser generator,
which means that you are not writing the parsing code directly in the programming language,
but instead you describe it in a domain, describe the format structure in a domain-specific language.
And this description can be then automatically translated into a parser.
Yeah, so Katai struct falls into this category, and the Kata struct language is designed
so that it's independent of both the application and the programming language.
Here I will show you how to work with Katai.
The first stage is compilation.
So you take this Katai struct specification of the format,
and in this case this is a format that has one byte,
because this u1 type means unsigned integer of one byte.
And you take this Katai struct specification and you compile it using the Katai struct compiler,
which is a command-line tool, and as output you get the source code of the parser,
in this case in Python.
The main stage is parsing.
You give the input binary file to the generated parser,
you get in the first step, and you give the input binary file to the parser as input,
and you get parse data as output, so an object tree.
And in case of Katai struct, the generated parser works with the runtime library,
so you need to include it also into your application.
Why use Katai? What are the advantages?
So as I already mentioned, the advantage is that you write the KSI specification once,
and you can use it everywhere.
It standardizes the way we describe binary formats, and there are already many formats described in the Katai format gallery,
and any described format can be visualized automatically in a graphics diagram,
and the Katai struct language is simple, you will see.
There are also several visualization and dumping tools available in Katai struct.
So the Write Once, Use Everywhere feature means that you get parses in 11 programming languages for free
from a single KSI specification, so in this case I've had the compiler generate Java, Python and Ruby parsers
from a simple KSI specification you see on the left.
When you look for specifications of binary formats, you will find that each one looks different,
and there is no single standard to how to document formats.
Katai is intended primarily for creating parses, but some people write KSI specification
just to document a format in an easy to understand way,
because you don't even have to be a programmer to understand a KSI specification, and it's often easier than
to read these long PDF documents.
The Katai project includes an extensive gallery of described formats.
At the moment there are 181 formats described by 76 contributors, and
there are also several hundreds more format specifications in various Katai projects.
The Katai format gallery contains formats of various kinds, for example,
as you see archive files, for example, executables, file systems, game data files,
multimedia files and network protocols. You can go to this page, and I took it from there,
and this suggests the wide applicability of Katai.
It offers an idea to create an international database of formats, where various
obscure and historical formats would be documented in a uniform way for future preservation.
This would guarantee that we could read the binary files we write now in 100 or 200 years from now.
The fact that the Katai struct language is declarative makes it possible to automatically
visualize the described format in a Gravis diagram.
The Katai struct language is simple but powerful. You can describe pretty much any binary format with it.
A KSA specification starts with the meta section,
and this sets the little and then byte order as default.
The SEQ section is a sequence of attributes. The attribute name is in the ID key.
The type u4 means that, in this case, num underscore files will be an unsigned 4-byte integer.
You can define your own types in the type section.
A field can also be repeated. So in this case, the files attribute will be a list or an array
of base type file.
In the instances section, you can define attributes that start at an arbitrary byte position.
You can also use a powerful expression language in many places.
Another built-in type is a character string in a certain encoding.
If you omit the type and only specify the size, the result is a byte array.
There are several visualization and dumping tools available for inspecting files.
This can be useful for finding errors, forensic analysis, or debugging.
The visualizers allow us to view the structured data, parts from the input file,
based on a Kitex track specification. You can use the console visualizer
or also the command line to ksdump is available, which can give you the same structured data
as you can see in JSON format. This can be useful for automation.
The most popular visualization tool is the Web IDE. You can check it out on this URL.
At the top right is an example of the input binary file. In this case,
I selected this.png file in the file tree on the left.
At the top left is the Kitex track specification editor, a ksya spec editor.
According to the Kitex track specification, the input file is parsed.
The result is the structured data that you see in the object tree at the bottom left.
When you edit the Kitex track specification, the input file is automatically parsed again.
The object tree is updated.
Serialization is a new feature in Kitex track.
It's being developed thanks to the financial support of the Analet Foundation.
While parsing allows you to read binary data to an object,
serialization is all about the inverse process. We want to write an object to binary data.
Currently, in Kitex track, the serialization for Java is fully working
and C-sharp and Python are in development.
There are basically two use cases of serialization.
You can edit an existing file or you can create a new file from scratch.
The support for serialization greatly extends the use of all written format specifications
because now you can use them not only for parsing but also for serialization.
This has many uses. For example, you can convert one format into another
or it can be used for fuzzing or video games modding and so on.
The serialization process in Kitex track can be divided into four phases.
First, you need to create a ks object and then you fill it with data.
So you set its individual fields or attributes using setters.
Then you should call the underscore check method
to check the consistency of the data with the format constraints.
Finally, we can call underscore write and pass the stream where to write.
You can actually check out more details of how to use serialization in Java on this page.
Currently, the serialization support in Kitex track is designed for the general case
so that it works for every conceivable format specification.
While a simple solution would work for perhaps most specifications,
well, the solution that works for all of them was chosen.
Even at the cost of delegating some task to the user.
In the future, I would like to automate these tasks that need to be done manually at the moment
so that it's more convenient for the user.
The basic idea is that the user sets everything,
including lengths of sets, magic signatures and Kitex track checks for consistency.
Also, only fixed length streams are considered.
So once you create a stream, you cannot resize it.
Finally, I would like to talk about the plans for the future.
Serialization for C sharp and Python is in development and they should be ready in two months.
There is also interest in adding Rust, C and Julia as target languages.
I would also like to see Warshak de-sectors as a target.
Because the concept of Kite is not limited to programming languages,
a target can be anything.
For example, we already have a target for construct,
which is Python library for parsing and serialization of binary data.
Thanks for listening.
Now it's time for our questions.
In the English KSI language, how much room do you have for explanations if you want to use it as a for-proof file format description?
You also need a lot of those texts.
Yes, yes you can.
There are, I don't know if I, yeah, there is a doc key for which you can use on attributes and types and in many places.
And you can use it, you can write some documentation of the specific element.
And in some languages, it doesn't work like 100% of the time, but the idea is that it should,
these documentation should translate to the generated parser as the blocks.
And then you can, then the IDs and tools like tools for development should auto-complete usually this documentation.
Do you support in the English when generating source code, depending on the part of the machine?
Yes, there is a feature for calculated NDNS.
It is called and it will, you can switch the NDNS or the default NDNS based on the value of an arbitrary expression basically.
So this can, yeah.
But do you support like host NDNS and target NDNS?
Well, not really, but it's not that of a limitation because you can, for example,
you can use parameters, for example, to pass it from your application basically.
Because I don't know if I can, I don't know if it's a good idea, but another feature of Kiteastrack is
that you can define that types can have parameters and even the top level, yeah, I should probably at least,
well, never mind, yeah, and you can define parameters and you can easily pass a parameter from your application
that will somehow change the behavior of the specification.
Yeah, so it's possible.
With KSI you seem to aim to define specification for certain languages or formats,
but for languages and formats that already have a specification, how can you ensure that these two specs are actually the same
and that you're not passing differently than other passwords?
Either, well, you mean that there is already an implementation of some, or...
For example, someone's passing zip files out there, how do you guarantee that Kiteastrack will pass zip files the same way?
Well, you don't basically, but, well, it's from this point of view, it's just another implementation,
well, if you compare it to other parsers, for example, so there is, for example, a zip parser
in every language, so zip parser library and this Kiteastrack specification is just another implementation, so...
Well, it needs to be developed carefully so that it works well or...
I guess you would need a way to translate from a written specification to the Kiteastrack structure
or the other way around to validate that what you wrote as the script actually corresponds to the actual specification.
For example, if a specification is already match machine readable, I mean, it's not clear,
we should have a tool to convert from one to the other, so that would ensure that the parsing is correct.
But it doesn't have, because the implementation is done by humans.
It's impossible, it's just an interop.
You have to run all those tests.
One of the performance...
If the process is generated from a specific data, this is not impossible, this is not impossible.
Right, but only if the other part is automated by the same...
By the same science.
Yes.
One of the questions is, I am wondering if it would be possible to have
some functionality to do that.
Not only parsing, but some very common functional.
Can you add that in the higher...
Common functionalities, so...
Like, for example, there is a binary format and there is a very common functional that everybody uses on that.
Let's say, like, I don't know, cutting a part of it or getting, calculating some, I don't know, value,
magic value or hash value, something.
Could you add some extra functionality other than parsing in there?
Well, so the question was that if you can, if we can add some common functionality in addition to the format specification,
and the answer is that, well, you can do this to a certain extent because there are...
I didn't mention them, or talk about them, but there are value instances and you can prepare some...
You can...
This is like a calculated attribute.
So you can write an arbitrary expression to it and this can calculate, for example, some...
Like, I wrote a BMP specification or I extended it and I used this, for example, to...
Well, in the BMP format, there are, like, color masks in different places depending on the header version.
And I used a value instance to get it from...
So depending on the version, so either get it from here or here, or if it's a fixed...
Fixed...
I don't know if it's a fixed color palette or what is it called?
So, yeah, we can do this to a certain extent.
But some common functionality, like, I don't know some...
Well, if it would require, like, a programming language or something like that...
So this would be infeasible, basically, because then we would have to some...
Programming language that translates to all targets, which is basically impossible, I think.
Yeah.
There is a tool that is called Diffoscopes that explains the differences between the two binaries.
And it's very inconvenient so that you can prove that a specific build system generates the same results.
And you can explain the differences. How would it be possible with these tools or these tools set to write a comprehensive...
Diff tools that explain the differences between two binaries and that can leverage the existing descriptions to explain what the difference became to find?
Yeah, so I think you can compute some diff.
Basically, I would do it. I showed the ksdump tool here.
So I think you could generate the JSON dumps of the two files and compare them.
But when I did this, it was usually very, very massive. You can probably improve that somehow.
I don't know.
But it's...
Thanks and...