So, in this presentation, I will try to show you the project, what's the current state,
the features, most used plugins, and which are the main features.
Okay, so first of all, a quick presentation.
I'm Sergio Alvarez.
Everybody knows me by my nickname, which is Pancake.
I'm the author of her tool.
I live in Barcelona and I work at NowSecure, which is a company from US, which we basically
use different static and dynamic instrumentation tools for analyzing applications and find
out privacy issues like identifying if the application is leaking data, stuff like that,
and then generate some reports for the customers and developers to improve the quality of the
applications.
So, I work as a senior mobile security analyst.
I like command line tools.
I like command text interfaces.
I brought many open source software, so my first goal is basically publishing all the
stuff that I'm doing, so I like free software.
I'm maintaining the whole R2 ecosystem nowadays, so I'm basically focusing on R2, but I also
maintain R2Kedra, R2FREEDA, and many other plugins that work with R2.
We have to reduce the font size here.
This slide is a little bit...
So it's a 17-year-old project, so I started this tool basically as a forensic tool.
I wanted to recover some files that are lost in the hard drive.
The thing is that I was working as forensic analyst, but I was not going to use the private
software that was in the company, so I wrote a simple external editor that was able to
find some patterns in the disk and then dump a one megabyte from there.
After this, I was interested in participating in some CTF and different competitions for
recent engineering, and I found out that there were so many tools that didn't really solve
my problem.
So starting by, for example, GDB, it was not possible to script it at the time and typing
comments all the time was tedious, and I just wanted to automate many things.
Also, there was extremely similar details, but it was not possible to extend them with
plugins or anything like this.
There was disassemblers, but object dump is cool, but it's not interactive, and the only
interactive tool was private, which is IDA.
Anyway, there was no real ecosystem for open source to solve any of these problems at once.
There were so many little tools that were solving one problem, but not really being
able to integrate with the rest of the ecosystem or other tools.
So I decided to start picking ideas, picking tools, developing everything from scratch.
That's why I did R2, because R2 is not depending on anything, so you can only depend on the
plastics like Slipsy, and all the rest of the dependencies are written from scratch,
like console handling, red line interface, all the socket interface, parsing libraries,
disassembling things, etc.
It's less sensitive than the LGPL3.
The focus of the project is basically to read other tools and be useful for hackers.
It's not going to be a general purpose solution for all the problems, because, for example,
I don't plan to write disassemblers from scratch.
I think that there are better projects for this, so I'm integrating them into R2.
Same goes for Lipoke.
It's one of the tools that is able to use R2.
It's fully written in C. I mainly focus on portability, because I like the things that
I write to run everywhere.
So the only option nowadays is C. I mean, there are some rasp haters around that.
The thing is that R2 can be compiled into WebAssembly, so you can run R2 inside your
browser.
You can also build it in a static-linked single binary, so you can drop it in a router.
This year I plan to port it to UFE, so you can run R2 inside your bootloader, and then
you can use it in the panoparenting system to use R2, non-file systems, and things like
that.
There are some really high constraints on all the code that R should be in R2.
So there is a CI that is basically verifying everything.
There is a 24-7 fuzzer that is running and finding bugs and fixing them.
So my policy is I don't let bugs stay for more than one day.
So the code cannot contain set jump or aborts or hazards or anything like this, because
if you are doing something in hot, you don't want things to crash or to break.
So the idea is that all the code that is running in R2 must be used from a library, so I don't
want to use, like, double variables.
I don't want to depend on something that if it's not parsing properly, I don't want to
crash.
If the malloc is failing, I want the program to still run.
Things like this.
So there are some concerns that I have when I write code for R2.
It's developing a single repo, but it's separated in different models.
So it's like a big project in one repository, but there is a bunch of libraries.
Each library has a bunch of plugins, and many of these plugins are integrated or exposed
interfaces for extending it with scripting languages.
So at the end, it's basically like a different line of capabilities that can be extended
pretty easily at different layers.
So there is a command line interface.
You have a prompt.
You can type things.
There is a visual mode, which is basically a list of commands that you execute every
time that you press a key.
And then you have the panels mode, which is like you can make splits.
You can have different tabs.
You can have different frames and so on.
And then there is web interface.
There is some people writing graphical interfaces for it, like Yaito, which is the Qt interface
for it.
For scripting, the easiest way for scripting R2 is R2Pipe, which is basically the simplest
interface for interfacing with anything, which is basically you run something.
You pass a string with a command, and then you get the output of the command as a string.
But there is also bindings for the CAPI.
There's automated bindings for Python, for Rust, et cetera.
And there is also support for using these bindings from different scripting languages.
So, what are the libraries implementing or exposing?
So you have the IO library, which is basically abstracting the access to the IO.
This basically defines how you access a file.
Everything is abstract.
This means that a file doesn't need to be anything physical.
There is support.
I mean, you cannot map a full file in memory and then work on it, because this is abstracted
by the IO.
So you can map a remote file running in a remote instance of R2, so you can run R2 as
an instance.
And then you can map, for example, like a ptrace backend, which is basically reading
and writing memory from another process.
And this is another IO interface.
And all that stuff is just the file descriptor.
So when you have one IO open, then you can map this file descriptor into separate maps.
A map is basically a portion of the memory taken from the file descriptor.
So you say that from this offset to this offset from this file descriptor, we'll be mapping
this virtual address in the IO space of R2.
And then there are IO banks.
And the IO banks are basically a bunch of maps.
So you can have separate memory spaces, like, for example, you want to manipulate a thread
local stretch.
You can have one IO space that only contains the contents of the thread local stretch.
But then there is another bank that contains all the memory layout of the processing memory.
And you can do that just by typing comments.
You can do this also by using the API.
But anyway, it's also possible to create, like, secret memory maps, memory layouts.
For example, B850 is like an architecture that is used for auto mobile and things like
that.
And this architecture basically relies on having, like, some solid infrastructure.
So you see there are some models that have, like, two CPUs executing the same code at
the same time.
And there is, like, a verification that two CPUs are doing exactly the same at runtime.
And the memory of this CPU is basically circular.
So there is some references that are going backward.
So you have, like, one instruction at the zero address that is referencing something
up.
And this something up is basically going to the negative of other space.
And this negative other space is not 52-bit in size.
It's 26, for example.
So you can basically configure these kind of things inside the root.
And you can basically get emulation, all the flags, which are basically naming offsets,
in all these things.
And everything will be shaped properly.
You can also define bit size at memory spaces, like, seven bit bytes and things like this.
It's also able to parse binary formats.
This works on any of the memory layouts that I said before.
So you can parse from memory.
You can parse from disk.
There is support for the most known formats, from console binary, from headers, like, etc.
But there is also for LP, Markov, etc.
It's also parsing, DWARF, PDB, and other debug information.
This is only for getting, like, others of memory, taking, like, a file name and so on.
It's not really exporting all the structures and so on.
But it's also possible to do that in the future or using external libraries.
It's also parsing, like, class information from Swift, Objective-C, or C++ binaries.
And all that stuff is integrated inside of those.
So you can, it's subtracting all the information from all these final formats into single naming.
So for example, imports in a P is not the same as, like, an import in ELF.
But for, or two is the same.
So when you're, when it leaves what the, a binary is importing from other libraries,
you can just use give me the imports.
You don't have to use, like, different APIs or different comments depending on the, on
the file format.
So it's unifying all the formats into a single naming.
It's also for disassembling and assembling.
It's using, like, one API.
So there is, like, a library that exposes an interface for doing this.
And this library exposes plugins.
So there's, like, plugins that are used by this API.
And then you can basically implement, like, new architectures, like, writing plugins for,
for this library.
But it's not, not only used for assembling and disassembling, which is basically text
bytes.
There is more low level detailed information.
Like you can, for some architectures you can get, like, a structure metadata, like, which
is the first operand, which is the size of the second argument, things like this.
But it's also exposing a seal.
A seal is, like, a very simple text interface for explaining what an instruction is doing
at low level.
So it's kind of, it's very similar to fourth.
Like a stack-based machine.
And it's basically one statement separated by comma.
So you have, like, o, comma, a x, comma, equals means that it will be pushing the number,
then pushing the resistor name, and then pushing the operation, which is the equal, and then
popping up from the operation to execute the statement.
The reason for that is because there are so many ways to extend or to define an architecture,
and there are some really fucked up things that can be done in so many architectures.
So I was not going to define, like, extensible structures or doing some really complex things
because at the end I was always finding, like, something that was not compatible with another
architecture.
And I end up, like, saying, okay, I just can't define, like, a comma-separated string that
it's just allocated in a single memory chunk, and I can just split it by comma and then
emulate that.
So there is a bunch of tools or libraries that are using a seal to extract this information
and then use that for emulation, use that for extracting information from a specific
instruction, or even for the compiling.
It's very portable, so it works on, supports debugging also.
So you can do local and remote debugging.
This means that you can run R2 as a local debugger in your Linux Mac or iOS device,
but you can also attach to a remote GDB or one DBG, etc.
It's a functionality for searching for different patterns.
So you can search for strings, access the minimal values.
You can also find, like, find me something that is repeated multiple times, and then
it will be finding, like, if there is any pattern that is repeated many times and give
you the offset of these things.
It's also able to generate function signatures, so by taking all the whole analysis for the
program, it will identify all the functions, basic blocks, etc.
And then you can generate, like, metadata for each of these functions.
And this metadata can be imported again to search for this information in another binary.
So you have, like, one binary with dwarf information or debug symbols, then you can re-import this
into a binary that is a strip it, and then you can basically identify these data structures
or functions in another binary that is not containing this data.
It's also possible to give code level, but you can also give data.
You can find, like, using delta diffing, so you have, like, two binaries that contain
the same data, but in different offsets, it will identify which offset is the ship at
the end of the binary and which is the main difference from that.
It's not byte per byte level instruction checking.
You can also give basic blocks, like, you can take the two control flow graphs and then
identifying which basic block is added, which is removed, or if there is, like, a percentage
of difference, so you can use that for bind diffing.
And you can also find differences, like, A, B, D, for getting, like, there is new symbols
removed or things like that.
And I also took code from GRAP group, which is basically the bootloader, and I used that
for parsing file systems.
Things at GRAP is doing a lot of things for, like, assuming that the file system is correct,
and R2 will never assume that anything is correct.
So if there is, like, a corrupted file system, I want to be able to mount it.
So R2 is using this code basically for mounting file systems.
You can have, like, a fake or, like, a virtual file system interface in Sartre 2, and you
can use that for mounting local or remote file systems.
You can use R2 free.
I will show that later, but I don't have time for showing it, but anyway, I will...
You can use Free.
Which is, like, a tool for injecting code in remote applications, and you can use TCP
or USB for communicating with that.
And then Free.
That can expose, like, an interface for accessing files remotely.
So you can mount zips in a remote file system, extract the zip contents from one binary,
parse the binary in local, mount that memory layout in local, and then whatever you would
like to do with these things.
Okay, obviously there is, like, a huge amount of things that can be done with that, so there
is a need for a package manager.
So I wrote R2-PM.
It was like a 200-line shell script, so it's not really a big thing.
But one year ago, they started to write it in C, so this way you can basically run the
package manager anywhere, even in Windows.
So it doesn't depend on anything that is not the same R2.
So this package manager is basically pulling a zip repository, and this repository can
contain, like, scripts.
And this script is basically defining a very simple way for installing and uninstalling.
So it defines instructions for compiling and installing the plugin.
And, yeah, there is, like, basically a amount of tools that are installed in your home,
and also plugins that are loaded by R2.
So the most common or most used plugins for R2 are, for example, about the compilers.
You have, like, R2-DEG.
You have R2-GIDRA, R2-RED-DEG.
So if you know GIDRA, for example, they provide, like, a compiler.
There is, like, a part of the compiler which is written in C++, not in Java.
And this code can be reused for writing at a compiler, so depending on the whole Java
thing.
Then there is RED-DEG, which is the compiler based on LLVM and a bunch of parallel scripts
that mess the thing.
And they basically use the compiler toolchain to do the backwards steps to get from the
binary disassembly to get, like, C-like code for the compiling.
Then you can also use the afra.
There is support for signatures for IDA.
There is, like, native signatures.
There is, like, some repository for people writing this.
And then there is support for to Frida.
If you know Frida, who knows Frida?
Raise your hand.
Okay, half of the room.
It's not the compiler, right?
No.
Frida is a tool that basically injects code in a remote process.
And then there is an agent that is running in a separate thread inside the process.
So you can basically instrument the process at runtime.
And you can basically inject JavaScript code or C or assembly inside the remote process
and instrument that.
You can use that for profiling.
You can use that for modifying behavior.
You can use that for tracing APIs, identifying when the specific function is called with
some arguments and then execute some code inside the remote process.
Most people use JavaScript for doing this.
But you can also use C or with libgam or whatever.
We basically use that for documentation on iOS and Android applications.
So you can use R2 Frida to have, like, an R2 interface for interfacing with Frida, which
means that you don't need to type long JavaScript one-liners.
You can also use R2 comments, like, which are pretty mnemonic and easy to type if you
know them.
And there is also support for external assemblers, like NuGAS or the unicorn library, which is
kind of like a stripping code from LLVM.
And there is also problem solvers, like Radios, as you saw for anger, that are plugins that
basically you define some constraints.
You have a function and you define, OK, I want to know which are the arguments that
I need to pass to this function to reach these specific others.
Like you want to know, for example, if it's possible to create a buffer overflow in a
specific variable in a local stack.
Or you want to define which, or you want to know which is the password that matches a
specific crypto algorithm.
So you can use that to define, OK, I want to know which is the block of bytes of one
specific length that generate this hash, for example.
Things like that.
And these won't be brute forcing.
It's like using problem solvers like Z3 and so on.
So there is like different plugins that are integrated in R2 to use from R2 comments.
And then you can define the preconditions, post-conditions and the boundaries of the
function to emulate.
Then there is also support for parsing data structure.
There is support for Kaitai, there is support for Polk.
This was integrated last week because I didn't know it was possible to have like a library
of Polk.
I was seeing it as a program, not a library.
So it's integrated, but it's not fully integrated.
So I plan to continue integrating it to use like for disassembling, for parsing, headers,
etc.
So what can you do with R2Frieda?
R2Frieda is basically, as I said before, is front-end for R2Frieda.
You can run scripts in your host, in your agent site.
So you can write a JavaScript program that runs in R2, but it can be also loaded in the
remote site.
And you can load and unload plugins.
So you can basically extend the R2Frieda comment set with JavaScript plugins that are loaded
and unloaded at runtime.
It's also scriptable with R2Pipe.
So you can write a program in Python, JavaScript or the language you like that interacts and
automates comments and actions in the host site or the remote site of the R2Frieda site.
So you can spawn applications, you can attach to local remote processes, you can use different
protocol or communication channels like USB, TCP, etc.
And you can promote the file systems.
You can use that for interfacing with tracing, APIs, profiling, and also supports extracting
metadata from Java, Dalvik, Objective-C, and Swift support will be ready by the end of
this year because right now it's supported but it's kind of unstable and the API is changing.
So yeah, certainly it will get better.
Okay, so let's talk about R2Pipe.
Since the first release that I did this year was the 580, I plan to keep ABI stable.
Actually I use ABI in the CI.
So every commit or port records that people send to the project, they verify that it's
ABI stable.
This means that I'm not breaking the ABI.
You can rebuild or update R2 without recompiling all the plugins or the tools that are using
R2Libraries.
This is pretty cool.
And the thing is that I was having some kind of like a contract with myself that I don't
break ABI but this is something that you end up like doing in Ruby when code by hand.
I'm having like a tool that can automate this is great.
But I wanted to have like a runtime, something that can you run from R2 like interpreter
that is not a custom language or like an external library that needs to be integrated and it's
really big.
So I was experimenting for some time with different languages and I ended up like realizing
that QuickJS is the only option.
So I mean Lua is using SetJump.
So you cannot compile with Lua as a WebAssembly plugin.
Also if you want to use SetJump with threads is kind of a mess.
So I end up like picking QuickJS which is the same JavaScript runtime that Frida is
using.
I pick the code from there and as long as every commit in R2 is verifying with fuzzers,
other sanitizers and so on, I end up like finding a lot of issues there.
I send like 12 patches to the project.
So it's basically the fork that is used by Frida.
So all these patches are upstream now.
And the idea is basically that you can use TypeScript and JavaScript from R2 and you can
write code like this.
So you basically have like an R2 pipe interface but it's running inside R2.
You can use this from WebAssembly.
So you can basically open RadaR2.online and then you have like a terminal that you can
run R2.
You can drop a binary inside the browser and use JavaScript to automate a bunch of actions
for analyzing the binary.
Basically as I said before, you have like a command that you run and then you get the
output of the command in exchange.
As long as most of the commands in R2 spit out JSON, you can basically use the CMDJ which
basically get the output of the command and pass the output as JSON.
And then you get like a structured data that you can use for extracting it or processing
it with the tools you like.
I think that JavaScript and JSON are quite standard and useful nowadays.
So you don't need to learn new things.
But there is support for so many other languages.
Like I said here, there is Python support, Rust, Node.js, Rabi, Guile, Nivlisp, Haskell,
Delang, Swift, etc.
So it's very easy to write this simple interface and you can use basically different interfaces
to communicate with R2.
So you can use like a fork and a pipe or you can also use like a TCP socket or an HTTP
interface, WebSockets, whatever you like.
And for the TypeScript thing, it's pretty cool because I'm writing like a types description
that basically defines the APIs of R2 and also the structures that the commands are
returning in JSON format.
This means that you can get the JSON of a command and then you can generate a schema
out of that.
And this schema can be used like a types.
So if you use TypeScript, Lisp server, like the language service that autocompletes the
code, you can basically use that for using tap to autocomplete all the code.
So for example, you can analyze function, you press p.i and then you'll get all the
function name.
You can get all the basic blocks.
For each basic block, you can use tap to get all the fields of this basic block like the
address, the amount of instructions, et cetera.
And for each instruction, you can get the mnemonics, et cetera.
And everything runs.
I mean, you can just like Visual Studio Code or Nailbeam or whatever you like, or MX, I
guess that's also SuperSellows P. And use that for automating and scripting using these
languages.
So R2 is able to visualize that and code in so many different ways.
So all this, I mean, I can press e so you can get the source code of the slides.
So you can see here, this is the content of the slide.
So it's running a bunch of comments in R2 and the output is generated inside the visual
mode that you saw before.
So you can generate graph.
You can, from the control flow graph, you can also generate like a vertical or horizontal
line graph like frame things.
You can disassemble, you can render pictures in bit formats, in RGB format.
You can also generate like a different, like comparing data and identifying which bytes
are changing by changing colors.
You can define like a color for a specific bunch of addresses.
So when you are disassembling, you can mark some regions like hot code or this is like
a portion of code that you're interested in.
And then you get highlights for one specific register.
So you want to highlight SP and then you get SP highlighted in the whole disassembly, things
like that.
But also there is also UIs, but I'm like common line guy, so I prefer to use the shell.
But there is like a Qt interface, but also I started to write like a new graphic interface
using WX widgets because I mean, Qt is great because it's big and it's also so many things.
But I don't like the license, it's so huge.
It's getting like a really huge and it's not handy for the kind of things that I like to
do.
So when I'm developing, I like to have fun and I don't want to be suffering because of
license or companies that are developing things in the background.
So I wrote so many UIs for it too, like in GTK, in using Imble, also other HTML, CSS for
the web UI because I have like a web server inside.
So at the end I want to have fun and I don't want to spend time like learning new APIs
and so on.
So I'm writing like a WG widgets API, a user interface and the idea for this is to not
follow the same flow of interaction flows that people use.
So I want to have like a common line interface but integrated in the UI.
So I want to be able to have multiple windows using multiple sessions or drag and drop things
from one window to another one instead of having like a big thing with panels and the
common interaction ways.
So what's the future?
So there is short and long term plans.
It all depends on my time because most of the things I maintain it or done by me.
There is a lot of contributors but they come and leave so there is like not really a core
developer team or there is no really big plans for having like big organizations and so on.
But the things that I want to be able to keep pushing like stable releases, I want to have
like a stability mainly because there is some people or companies or users that are writing
tools on top of this and I don't want them to write things every time that I make a release
or break without updating this.
I want to have like a create, so which is a rushed API that you can basically specify
the version of Erto that you want to ship and then this create will build Erto inside
with a specific version and then you can use your Erto esthetic link inside your program.
So you don't need to depend on system installations or depend on other things like that.
I want to basically reduce the tech depth because as long as I'm alone doing most of
the things I don't want to depend on humans so I want to reduce the amount of things that
are done manually.
So for example a friend of me wrote the Flatpak integration so there is like a bot that basically
detects when there is like a new release in Erto or in Yaito and when this happens it's
basically pulling the code from all the projects, generating a change log generating a new build
and publishing that automatically.
And you basically get like a graphical interface for Linux and Windows for free.
I want to improve the code coverage and all the testing for fuzzing and yeah, there is
like a lot of things that you can see and if you have questions please let me know after
the talk with some viewers.
I guess that everybody is hungry so.
All right, thank you guys Cam from phased