you
somewhere here
and yes what is group poke?
so the project has
you can say that it has many components
on the way you counted but in a simple way you can say okay it's a leap poke
which has the incremental compiler for the
poke programming language by incremental
you can add stuff you know redefine thing redefine types redefine variables
over the time and it also had the other part is the pvm poke virtual machine
which is powered by GNUjitter
a project by Luca Sayou
and yeah it's a
virtual machine generator which is fun but no time for talking about that
sorry Luca and the other part is the IOSpace
which is the abstraction to make things you know you can address
bits from the IODevices so these are the main components of the leap poke
the other component we have in the GNU poke project is the poke the CLI
application
which is based on
user leap poke and you can using read line
you can write to the std in and then it gives you error on std error and
output on stdout
but the third thing is we have is the poke d
poke daemon
you know daemon in the term of server or in the background
it's a program that exists we don't see it but it's doing something
so it's a daemon for me but some people believe that okay daemon is only
system things but I don't think so so
I like to call it poke d
so a very brief
looking at the components inside the leap poke
so if you go to the leap poke.h
file you will see three op-h types
the pk compiler which presents the interaction with the compiler
the pvm pkval
it is the values from the
poke virtual machine and you have the pikios
which is the abstraction over different devices like we have
network block device we have zero device we have sub device file
stream like std in stdout and
process which is you can poke other processes
you attach using the PID or memory which is a you know
in process memory for doing
temporary things and we have also a foreign dev which you can introduce a new
device like you have like as an example I have
I can show that but like reading from packets
and writing to memory and then in poke you can
poke the packets no network packets given from like
network or for example at my
job I have to work with Bluetooth things so we verify the data formats we read them
and then we verify with the poke that we are
we get what we expect to so
and the language the language is procedural of course
statically type of course interpreted because of
you know pvm stuff and it's interactive
DSL for binary data you know it is designed to specifically
be expressed be enough powerful to express
binary formats and yeah
so we can have variables var a equals something
we can have a weird integers
like I have here and int 32
literal which I'm casting to you int 13
we have strings which are null terminated there is no
non-null terminated string in poke if you want to use you can use arrays
this is the offset so in size and
offsets in the poke are magnitude which is
an integer and a unit which you can define
the the basic unit is bit but you can define your own unit like
let me know let me not yeah here we have
a a REPL which is poke REPL
so I can say okay I have unit
foo equals three and then I can define
one foo which is here in the this is the output you know the
output of the result so which is one three
an offset one magnet one thing of this
foo things which is three bits white
13 here it's the bits of this integer it's an
integer of size 13 yeah I'm casting to that from 32
and yeah this is syntax for arrays so for literals
for unsigned byte things you have to specify the ub
so this is an array of I can copy actually
var e equals 0 1 ub and then e which we can see here that 0 1 so
it's an array so units like you can define if you go
to the is that pk in the our repo it's it's there you know
b uppercase b is eight kb and kilobyte the stuff we have in
managing so you can also define types like
you have an structure which is consists of a three bits width integer
followed by an offset and int signed int 40 bit number
which represents offsets in unit byte of and we call it j
and then we have three strings you know null terminated strings
and functions you can use the syntax fun my function equals
this is the signature input signature output column and then
you can do the this thing here is for attributes of of this value like
the lengths you the is it mapped or not or stuff like
that so the application the poke it's a ripple
you can you know declare stuff like what you see here but it's not deep
poke application it is something else so and it provides a bunch of
utilities so here i switch the i'm opening a new terminal here i open
the poke the program the cli so you we have here
something like dot dot commands start with dots so dot help
you see here that we have a bunch of you know things here
or look for example dot set if you said okay you can
do printing or here you can very define variables
like you can change the set output base to 10
okay this kind of things also possible here so
uh you can do anything and you can redefine a again to be
hello and it will be hello and yeah so uh the next thing is
also okay i can run these things which i ran so i
don't go over there so uh if we want to know how
poke the the cli works a very simply oversimplified view is that it uses
these two um uh p uh leap poke functions pk
compile buffer and compile statement uh
the trick in poke application is if the input
starts with these keywords like where you need type find immutable
if you compile and run the thing using this disfunction
which expects you know arbitrary poke code
but otherwise it uses a statement which assumes that you are passing in a
statement in the refold and and despite the name both of
them compile and run the poke program so yeah and this is an example of
uh because this thing started with var so you can
add more than one statement to it here is a
statement because there is nowhere immutable form and but and this is also
a syntax error in the poke ripple i can show you yeah there is error
because it expects a statement not uh uh arbitrary code uh so
you see that there are some limitations so uh what is this uh thing called
let me yeah yeah so we read from terminal it gives a
structure called input somehow the first where we
compare it with these things if it's that compile buffer uh this check macro
uh this is also pseudo code it's not real code so
uh checks for first the output of this compile buffer function
which is compile time error and also the exception during the execution of
this program and if it's not okay check things and then you know in
the compile statement you get the value back
and besides this exception so but what is poke d so
here in the poke application we have this
layer of std in std out and std error over the lib poke
so what about uh you know generalizing this abstraction to Unix sockets
instead of getting information from the input
uh we can get information from Unix socket
it's a daemon acts like a broker so uh it listens on uh on this socket
and it has a concept of channels like you have input channels and output
channels and or completely independent and
then a client we call them pokelets connects to this
poke d it should it should tell the uh uh the poke d that what is its
uh role so the role is an eight bit thing which is integral
struct you know the syntax is this is different from
normal structs but um yeah should i explain that no i don't
know no so it's a the the the most significant
bit is a direction followed by seven bit of channel
which is limited we reserved them for future
upgrades so when you connect to this again you have to
write this byte to the poke d then he knows that okay your input so expect
something from you or it's an output channel
then when some user code write to this channel
you will get the data and it's distributed to all
and there is no addressing thing it's a broadcasting
so uh for the you know if you want to know
how these things work there is a pickel i can show
why not if we go to the gnu poke poke program okay here in the
oh i have to sorry i have to enable the syntax highlighter which i have so yeah
vim pickels pdap so all this communication
poke the application protocol and i see here you can see the description here
okay this this rolls what is the outcome stage what is the
all of them are there so if you are curious you can go there and study
so but we will now go to the more detail so
here is the poke d oversimplified view so here we have reading from input
channels and we have a concept of iteration
you know when you start sending something because
you know you can have different print of statements so it should you know
it's you know partially send data in chunks so
we have to somehow notify our user that okay
here you're starting a new iteration of compiling or something
and so if it's from input channel which is channel number one
it's simpler i think it gives to the pk compile buffer
and if it's from command input which is input channel number two it will give it
to the statement and here we have this check
publish instead of print it it publishes to all this subscriber
all the clients are said that okay we are interested in getting data from this
output channel so any question regarding the things
poke the poke poke the cli pickles nothing great
nobody is following so that's great so let's talk about pacme so question
where no if you i'll open the questions
what okay i'm trying to my best to answer questions
okay so now let's talk about pacme
which is the title of this talk so it's an acme inspired you know poke
interface it's not acme acme let me explain it
the reason is because text rocks and anything else like graphical interstices
sucks really seriously i'm not this is in the
line of code of conduct of postum or not i don't know
anything else sucks yeah good thank you for the support
so examples of good interfaces in my opinion are list machines
small talk environments oborone which is a desktop computer system
written scratch from nikolas birt the creator of the pasco
for the students but it's a very interesting text oriented interface
and the acme which is the editor of a great operating system called
plan 9 from bell labs written by rutpike the co-inventor of co-program language
which is also inspired by oborone the good thing is text is the
is the main thing there so you can select text and execute text so it is
very it is very interactive but also you have
the text so you can compose things and then okay put them to in a function and
this kind of things you know it's much powerful than you know
this dumb button you have to click on that and oh you don't you cannot even
change it you know if it's not useful for you
so the reason is okay easy to compose automation friendly you can have
explore it's very useful for binary data you you are exploring you know different
things and then over the time you have it
scraped so copy paste it in a function and then call it later
why not and it's extensible you know you need something more
which we don't know you develop your own program
which is you know a very simple thing you can do that
and for your information i'm not against graphics graphics is awesome
the way that we currently use you know graphical interfaces is bad like
i have a button i cannot change the function attached to it i cannot
you know remove this button put two buttons which is more useful to my
case so yeah i love graphics like formulas
visualization because the best pattern matcher
we already have on plan there's our brain so
why not visualization is cool so but this
yeah never mind yeah it's it's getting out of conduct so
kind of so okay pack me is pokelets plus tbox
so the idea is okay um okay this terminal thing is not the
best thing we have it's from 60s but yes it's it's by far the
best thing we have today so let's leave there so the option is
one option is to to implement everything from scratch which is
i'm too lazy to do that so we have already programs like tmux
and screen which you can do you do interesting stuff with them
like let me um if you don't know about it let me
okay this is a normal x term thing and i say like um let me use one
a specific configuration for that thing so here i'm opening
this thing so i can like this i have um there is a prefix so you want to
say that okay please uh you know do this thing or
like resizing things you know running commands you can
do many cool things here i'm not you know this is good you know we have
this kind of thing so we can use this infrastructure and
with the power of little programs the pokelets which talk with the
poke the over uh the the socket we can create a user
interface which is dynamic you know not the best but yeah we can
improve it it's it's more interactive and also because of
this the there is no limit here pack me i'm talking about terminals
but you can run on emacs which is we have
these things can coexist together you have pick me here emacs here and even i
have an implementation in web socket but it's still in python so like i'm not
allowed to publish it unless i have some C implementation for it
yeah i'm not looking at you yeah and in future we will have uh
support for screen i chose tmux because i use it all
all on a daily basis also why not and okay so i showed the the tmux for
you so let me show you the pack me if you
like type pack me it's here so home user bin pack me
but uh this is it so it's uh called the tmux on a specific
unique circuit which is a tmux thing not important for us
with this specifically so pack me is uh this tmux configuration file so
let's look at what is it so here share pack me yeah here
so here like we are uh you know the default key because you
when you want to do something to the instruct the tmux you have to
send the key combination that okay now i'm talking to you tmux
so by default ctrl b here we are unbinding it and here i chose
ctrl g you can choose whatever you want in my
favorite one is ctrl o because it doesn't conflict with anything anything
else b a g are conflicting with the gnu
uh read line which i hate but this is for you people so you can change it
and so we are like we can have uh ctrl o so if i press ctrl g
and uppercase o i now automatically split the window
send uh these literal things like p let out
enter this is you know what you see here and then select
you know go back to my cursor to my current pane which is this one
uh the the upper one so you can now if i go to the
okay i can uh new one p let echo print
it's better to be coated hello fustum
and i guess with this one i have a very little program
which reads from stit in and writes to the poketie
so you see here this uh 73 is the iteration number and that's the
execute the results of execution it's there so i if i rerun it again uh a new
thing so here in this pack plet out i decided to use this but you can use
anything you are interested in and uh just for the record this
uh slide thing it's a pokelet 2 and i can show the code to you like
user bin p let slides it's like p let out channel number 60
uh don't put the length so it's not important and this is the terminal
uh code escape code for clearing the this thing so it just instead of writing
this slash slash the number it just clears
this so i have this slides here uh so
the other thing i'm and i can show you so uh let me finish this thing
so now key bindings normal key bindings like
i have this power here to like let me this is also cool let's out
okay here in in my think i think uh let's define a variable echo
var a equals hundred and send it to the
poke okay so we know that it it has so but with the power of uh
t mux i can go and select this a and i i'm i'm telling that this is a key
binding okay execute it the e upper e this this key
binding so pipe and cancel put a semicolon at the end and get give it to
the pokelet in channel two which is for the
command so if i press shift e hundred you have
c so it executes this a it's like that you you've written the
a on the command in the ripple so uh
very simple thing so i have also for because i love users so i provided
predefined layouts for you so you can here control g f1 like it's opened your
editor here which is hell yeah this is using
this editor thing so you can just use your favorite
editor you have here the pickel which i write
a you see the logic is in the poke d so when you can
connect disconnect everything is there and
another layout is uh f2 yeah it worked so let's show let me show
you something maybe a little bit more interesting
yeah yeah yeah where let's open the file
which i have somewhere no this is error i
okay home
oh drone i don't remember that
called runia test zero one elf okay it's an elf file
uh you see here the number zero this is the
handle to this i think this file so i can load
elf module and uh okay and i know that it's a risk five
elf so let's load this risk v module we call module pickles
if you wonder why i came and uh so var file equals elf it's a elf
sixty i know that it's a elf third oh i can
like do the view here you get a dump and you can the fun thing is you can
add as many as viewer you want so it's the same thing you can have a viewer in
web so here you instruct your thing and you in
the web you get your things you highlighting stuff anything you want
uh yeah and uh so let's do elf 64 file
at this iospace at offset zero so i'm telling that okay
uh consider look go to this iospace number zero go to that
offset and give me the elf file there there's an elf file there
and it's okay oh and if i here not very oh yeah
in the i can zoom in so here you see that you get
all the elf insta stuff here like e-edence and all type machine
section header and others so let's
let's get the text section of this thing elf32
um no we have the file get sections by name
dot tags i know that this elf file only has one so
it's gets all the sections so i have one so sub zero
if i write text so he at the end you you see you you get this this section
header with the offset in and and size right
so this is the address where the code the actual execution code
resides in the binary so oh but you know you can say okay give me
the bytes give me how much bytes text sh
size bytes is uh is an here this is an offset i'm telling that
okay i need bytes of this size at this iospace and at this offset you
know go to this offset sh offset so you get all the bytes here
i can vm set output base to 16 and do it again so in
more interesting thing so but it is bytes what else can we do you can say
okay i know that these are risks we risk 532
uh i instructions you know this is a subset you know this basic
base component of this risk machine so i'm
give me that amount of uh element of instructions at this
offset so here if we go to the end so you get
all these instructions risk five instructions which be
written in poke the description of the this instruction that's the extensible
thing so for example here we have an
instruction of format i which immediate of this value rs1
functionality zero rd this one and opcode stuff like
i can show you the uh i think i'm done you know i don't have
any time so let me just show this one and then to
radare so poke uh what what was yeah
pickles what
yeah yeah yeah yeah he i didn't pay for them you can it's
free from my point of view
you have to handle him you know so this is a risk five you see
we define the opcodes uh different instructions like
this is the instruction type b it's a it's a integral strike so you can read
about this so we can have very complex things we have pretty printers
nice thing is we have also i want to show this this is from
uh okay i can put it into incense variable incense
uh incense
zero which is let me close this view dumb view yeah yeah here i have the
thing so you can give the this is the actual
number which is there in the memory it is stored
in the little indian so 13 80 something like that
and one what what yeah as as so we have a method
uh you you call this method you you don't need to
parent put the parenthesis if there is no argument so it gives you
uh real valid instruction for the assembler so this is part of the
whole story so you can add more pokelets next year i will come back with more
interesting things no gui but the right way and uh yeah
thank you thank you if there's any question