Welcome, everyone. Today we are going to talk about walking native stacks in BPF without
frame pointers. So my name is Roshali. I work at Polar Signals as a software engineer. I
mostly work on profilers and eBPF related stuff. And before that, I have worked in different
kernel subsystems as part of my job. My name is Javier. And I've been working at Polar
Signals for a year, mostly working on native stack and windings. So the work that we're
going to introduce today. And before that, I was working on web reliability, tooling
for developers, and performance at Facebook. Yeah, so before we dive into the topic, I
wanted to go through the agenda. So first, we actually want to talk about why there is
a need for a
dwarf-based stack walker in eBPF, because that's like the most asked question. Then
we will go into the design of our stack walker and then we'll talk about how we went from
the prototype to making it production ready and then a bunch of learnings so far and some
future plans. So as we said, we work on the production profilers, which means that generally
sampling profilers collect the stack, traces at particular intervals and attaches values
to it. Note that the profilers generally need the user and application level stacks as well
as corner stacks. And it sort of involves iterating over all the stack frames and then
collecting the return addresses. Historically, there have been a dedicated register for that
called frame pointer in both x86 and x64. But in recent times, because of some of the
compiler optimizations, it has been mostly disabled in most of the run times as well
as in distros. Also, it becomes really hard when you don't have frame pointers. And instead
of involving a couple of memory accesses per frame, which is quite fast, we will need to
really do more work in the stack walkers. Note that the stack walking is also a common
practice in the debuggers, as you all know. So what's the current state of the world?
Well, it's not a problem for the hyperscalers because hyperscalers actually have all the
applications which are already enabling frame pointers in production. And this is important
because when the things break and you want to really go through the inspection, it's
really helpful to have all the stack when it's needed. There's also a recent discussion
in the federal mailing list. So just feel free to go through it. The LDR of that discussion
is that it's being so FPS are going to be enabled. Since I think Fedora 38, so that's
about to be released in late April. Mac or software always have binaries which has frame
pointers enabled. There's also an amazing work going on by Oracle engineers to have
like a simple format instead of dwarf. And we hope that that work also goes through and
helps the ecosystem. So that's sort of the current status. But what we want is we want
that right now. And we want the support for all the distros as well as all the run times
which is scattered over here and there. For example, only go run time. Anibus FP is like
since go 1.7 and since 1.12 in 64. So now some of you might be wondering if not frame
pointers, what do we have? For example, say in Rust where it has been disabled by its
own by default. But when you have the panic, you still get the all back dress. So how is
it happening? So well, compilers always have this information. And we generally need to
know the value of the stack pointer in the previous frame and it can be like from any
offset if there is no frame pointer. So that way we can always find the value of the return
addresses and the continuing unwinding the stack. This information is generally encoded
as part of.eh frame section or debug frame section in the dwarf. And there is also another
way which is like unwind tables can be also synthesized from the object file which is
something being done by Ork format that has been used in kernel for a while now. We will
talk in detail about.eh frame in a minute. But first of all, let's see if anybody else
is using eh frame already, of course. So the profiler we have developed is not the first
thing who is going to use eh frame. Perf, the profiler from Linux kernel added the dwarf
support since when the perf event open syscall was added which was in 3.4 and it can collect
the registers for the profiled processors as well as the copy of the stack for every
sample. While this approach has been proven to work, there are a bunch of drawbacks to
it. One of the things which perf does is it actually collects all the stacks and copies
it into the user space. The second thing is that the implications of one process having
another process is data in the user space can be quite complicated and also be it's
like a lot of data especially for the CPU intensive applications. So why BPF? Stack
working in BPF for our profilers actually makes a lot of sense to us because in that
case we don't really have to copy the whole stack. The information, a lot of it still
stays in the kernel which provides like higher safety guarantees especially in the case of
like stack working mechanism once it's been implemented we can like sort of leverage the
perf subsystem to get the sample CPU cycles and then instructions, altricache misses,
et cetera and it can then also help us to develop other tools like allocation tracers,
runtime specific profilers for example for JVM or Ruby, et cetera. So some of you who
are probably also familiar with BPF may know that there is already BPF get stack ID so
why there is a need for implementing something different. Well, as it turns out the problem
with that helper is that it also requires frame pointers so it also uses frame pointers
to walk through the stacks and for the historical reasons fully featured dwarf and winder is
like unlikely to be part of the Linux kernel. So before we dive into how we are using EH
frame with BPF let's look at what EH frame actually has to offer. So the EH frame section
contains one or more call frame informations. The main goal of the call frame information
is to provide answers on like how to restore every register for the previous frame at any
part of our code execution. Directly storing the table that sort of contain each program
counter and all the registered and then locations such as like whether they have been pushed
with the stack or not, et cetera, would generate huge unwind tables. And for that reason dwarf
is actually quite compact and very space efficient in that sense. So the unwind tables are encoded
in the CFI format or in the form of opcodes and those opcodes needs to be evaluated so
in the case of stack walking once it has been evaluated we generate the table that contains
for each instruction boundary like how to store the value of the register. There are
two main layers to it. One is that it helps with repetitive patterns that compress well
and allows for like more compact representation of some data. In some cases there is also
specialized opcode that consumes say one, two, four bytes rather than just four bytes
at all time. And the second layer which we call the second layer is the spatial opcode
contains another set of opcodes containing the arbitrary expressions. That needs to be
evaluated and that's a lot of op. The main difference between these two is that in the
first one we just need like these two values. But in the second part of it we will actually
need to evaluate the arbitrary Turing complete expressions. So for that reason we would need
to have the full blown VM to be implemented in the BPF itself which is not quite practical.
So those who don't know how generally the BPF applications flow box, this is how it
would look like, you know, very high level point of view. So like in the user space you
would have like the driver program written in Go, like that's our stack and we are using
like BPF Go over there. We are doing like creating the maps, attaching the BPF program
to a CPU cycle, perf event, it reads, passes and evaluates the EH frame section of the
process and all the dynamic libraries. And in the BPF program we have using the PID we
are fetching the table and then we have like an unwind algorithm which processes the dwarf
information. We will go in depth for each component but let's see how the algorithm
looks like. So basically for this one it's like a really simple one but basically we
just read like three important registers. First one is instruction pointer, RIP, next
one is the stack pointer and the third one is of course like frame pointer, RBP. And
then when the frame count is less or equal to the maximum stack depth we have defined,
we find the unwind table for the program counter, we add the instruction pointer to the stack,
calculate the previous frame stack pointer, then update the registers with the calculated
values for the previous frame and then continue with the next frame. So this is like just
a nutshell that's what the algorithm is in the BPF. But now the important part is how
we store that unwind information and what we have done to make it scalable. So now Javier
will talk about that. Cool. So now we have some unwind information that we're going to
describe the format later but we need to put it somewhere, right? So one possibility will
be to store this unwind info in the memory space of the applications that we are trying
to profile and we could do this using a combination of P trace, M-up and M-lock and we could use
P trace to hijack the process execution and make it allocate a new memory segment and
then we will have to lock it because in BPF we need to make sure that the pages that we
are accessing are never going to be swapped out. But this has a big problem that is altering
the execution flow of the program and it's something that we never want to do. One of
the reasons for this is because first this memory will live in the process which means
that accounting for it will be odd and developers will find a new memory segment there that
appear out of the blue so in their metrics there will be something that changes behind
their backs which is not great. But also because the life cycle of managing this memory chunk
is very complicated. For example, what do you do if our application, if our profiler
dies before the processes that we are introspecting, how do we clean this up? It involves a lot
of problems and adding solutions to these problems will require crazy engineering which
we were not planning to tackle because it will overcomplicate the project a lot. The
other problem is that sharing memory is way harder and accounting for our overhead is
also very hard. If you think about it, for example, LibSee is probably linked in most
of the applications in your machine so why having the same information for every single
process, right? So how do we actually store this information? We use BPF maps which are
data structures that as Vashali said they can be written and read both from kernel and
user space. We use in particular hash maps which in the case of BPF they are basically
a mapping of bytes to bytes where you can put arbitrary information. So this is always
locked in memory. BPF allows you not to lock memory but in the type of BPF program we use
it is mandatory to lock it. Otherwise, as we said before, these pages could be swapped
out and from the type of BPF program that we have page faults are forbidden. And, yeah,
in the end we could reuse these mappings because they are in this kind of global BPF map that
we have control over. We can store, for example, LibSee in one particular area and then we
will have to add metadata for where it is for every single process that has this mapping.
So yeah, this is a logical representation of one information for different executable
segments. So imagine this is LibSee, MySQL, Zlib, systemd and then some chunk that is
unused. So this assumes that we have like this logical view has like a chunk of memory
that is contiguous. But in reality we cannot allocate any arbitrary chunk of memory on
BPF. We cannot say we want 200 megabytes and it needs to be like contiguous. We cannot
do like a malloc, right? So we've been doing some experiments and in the systems that we
have tested and the kernels that we want to support we can add up to 250,000 and one entries
to each value of a BPF map. So because we want to be able to fit larger unwind tables,
we basically use the same solution that you would use in any other data intensive application
which is partitioning or sharding. So we are splitting the unwind table into different
shards and depending on the memory that your machine has we will allocate more or less
shards ahead of time. That will result in a CPU to memory tradeoff because when they
get full we'll regenerate them. But we'll talk about this later. So for example let's
see systemd's unwind table and let's suppose that it's a bit bigger than 250,000 elements
so it doesn't fit in a single shard. So because it doesn't we have to chunk it up. So we store
the first chunk in the first shard and then there's a little bit that is stored in the
second shard. Because we have added all these layers of indirection we need some bookkeeping
to do and this metadata is also stored in BPF maps. So we have a process that can have
many mappings. Each mapping can have one or more chunks and then each chunk maps to a
particular shard because you might have one unwind entry or up to 250,000 in a shard and
we have some other metadata to exactly tell you where that information leaves. So yeah
thanks to this way of organizing data we're able to as we said before share these executable
mappings and thanks to that we skip table generation for most of the executables in
your box. And thanks to this we only use 0.9% of the CPU cycles during the process that
Vashala was talking about before which is not the most complex process in the universe
but it consumes some CPU cycles because we need to read some information from your L
file, find the section, then we need to read the section and we need to parse it and interpret
the dwarf information. So now we need to do way fewer times. So in your machine we're
only going to do it once per unique executable section. So what happens if we run out of
space? So basically what we have implemented is basically a bump allocator. We keep on
appending information to the shards and logically you can see it as a big chunk of memory. Once
it's full at some point we'll decide to wipe the whole thing and start again but we do
it in such a way that we give every single process a fair chance of being profiled. So
yeah let's take a look at how are we doing this. So we start with a PID of any process
that you find in your machine that at that point happens to be running on CPU and the
first thing we do is to check if it has unwind information. If it does we need to find the
mapping with the current instruction pointer that we have for that frame. Then we need
to find the chunk. We can find it doing linear search because we have the information of
every single like minimum and maximum program counter that is covered by that chunk. Once
we get the chunk we can have the shard information and once we have the shard information we
have the unwind information. But the problem is the unwind information as we said before
it's basically an array. And this array we need to find it but it can be up to 250,000
items and if you have done anything on BPF you know that you don't have like you have
to basically build whatever you need yourself and you don't have for example some sort of
binary search that is executed on kernel space for you so you need to implement it yourself
which is not a big deal in general. Implementing binary search is not rocket science but the
problem most of the times it's difficult to get all the off-fi ones right but the problem
here is that in kernel space we have a lot of limitations we're going to talk about later
and we're going to talk about how we overcame them because this produces quite a bit of
code that has to be split logically. So not only the data structures are sharded but the
code is sharded too. So anyways we binary search this with up to seven iterations but
let's say eight if you're feeling pessimistic. And then we're going to get the unwind action
so what is the operation we need to do to the current registers to recover the previous
registers and add the frame to the stack trace and continue with the next frame as I shall
explain before. If the stack is correct and we have the luxury to know that because when
we have no unwind information and RBP is zero that is specified by the x64 API to be the
end of the stack the bottom of the stack. So if it is correct we hash the addresses
add the hash to a map and bump a counter. So it is reasonably cheap and I will show you
some data later on this and then every couple seconds I think it's every ten seconds or
so we collect all this information from user space and we generate the actual profiles
that we send to some server. As I said before BPF has some interesting challenges for us
and I think it's the closest that I've been to coding in the 90s or 80s because we have
very little stack space we have 512 bytes if I am not mistaken. So in order to overcome
that we used BPF maps as some sort of heap. Then there's a problem that I mentioned before
about memory locking and that memory can never be swapped out and it is in kernel space.
So we want to make sure that we allocate the minimal space you need and we need to do it
properly because each single environment has a different C group configuration and as some
talks explained yesterday it's quite tricky to know the actual memory that your machine
has available. For the program size there is two main issues. One of them is that there's
a limitation on the number of instructions that you can store in the kernel but also
the BPF verifier which is this machinery that makes sure that your program is safe and for
example your program is going to finish you're not the reference in any null pointers. Sorry.
And that in general you're not going to crash the kernel has a limit on the amount of iterations
that it does internally. This is a problem for us because doing a full binary search
already fills these limits. So we need to use some techniques like this thing called
BPF tail calls that is similar to Lisp tail calls and if you're lucky, we are not, you
can use, well, we use bounded loops but we can use this new helper called BPF loop that
basically is a function that you can call multiple times creating some sort of loop
in BPF but we cannot use that because we want to support other kernels. That's a pretty
new feature. So let's switch to something else. We have written our application in user
space in Go and we are a profiler so we want to make sure that the overhead we have on
your machine is as little as possible. But unfortunately many of the Go APIs aren't
designed with performance in mind. I'm new to Go. I didn't know this was like this and
every single time I profiled our profiler and I found these things I was like how is this
possible? But it has the dwarf and elf library which is great but they are not designed for
performance sensitive environments, let's say. And also there's two functions that are
binary read and binary write that we use all the time because we need to deal with bytes
back and forth that allocate in the fast path. But anyways, we profile our profiler all the
time. We have found lots of opportunities that we keep on fixing but of course there's more
work to do. And one of the areas where we try to be pretty comprehensive is with testing.
So we have thorough testing for, well, unit testing for most of the core functions to
ensure that we don't regress but I think that in my opinion has helped us the most is snapshot
testing. If you're not familiar with this technique it's very simple. You basically
generate some textual representation of your data structures, write them to disk or somewhere
in memory, doesn't matter. And then you generate them again after you make some changes to
your code and then you compare them. So this is how it looks in our case. We have some
GitHub repository called test data and then we have this textual representation of the
unwind tables. You don't have to understand it all but the idea here is that this covers
a full function which program counter starts in the one over there and ends in the one
over there. And then we have the information for every single program counter and then
it tells you, for example, what to do here. The first one says CFA type 2 that I know
is for RBP. So you need to get the current RBP at 8 and that will give you the previous
frame stack pointer. But anyways, the interesting thing here is that this is very easy to implement.
As you can see by our very advanced setup in our makefile, we just build our binary.
We dump these tables to disk and then we ask it to give us the changes. And if there's
anything that has changed, we fail. So thanks to this, we have found a lot of bugs and it
has allowed us to iterate with confidence. One of the important things in this project
has been derisking it. It's been quite complex. When I started working on this, I had no idea
about dwarf unwinding. I had no idea about unwinding without frame pointers at all. So
we had to make sure that all these avenues were properly covered. We had, for example,
the dwarf parser properly implemented, that we had all the interactions with BPF cover
and the BPF unwind that worked well as well. So for this, we always try to have a plan
B at every stage of the project and we try to go in depth as well as in breadth. But
anyways, I have five minutes left apparently. So we had a lot of automated testing and one
of the things that we did was adding kernel tests, which is super important, especially
for BPF programs because the BPF subsystem changes a lot over time and there's a lot
of features that we want to make sure we don't use because otherwise it wouldn't work in
other kernels. So we have a kernel testing system where basically it runs our application
in multiple kernels and reports the state. And one of the things that I want to talk
about is that production, as usual, brings a lot of interesting challenges. So by deploying
a profiler to production, we found a lot of things that we didn't know about and we were
able to find some of these things thanks to using continuous profiling, our own profiler
on our profiler. As you know, different hardware and different configurations are the biggest
sources of performance differences as well as incidents in production. So I want to show
you two things that we have found recently. One of them is basically we were using almost
30% CPU time opening files in our production environments that never showed up on my NVMe.
And the reason is because turns out cloud disks are very slow. So we are since now we
have fixed this. Another very interesting thing that we fixed the other day, it's something
that happened when we rolled out our profiler to production and then it started crashing.
If you are interested, we will upload the slides. Feel free to check the pull request
because everything is open source. But basically what happened here was that for reasons, Go
has a signal-based profiler and we have it enabled for even more reasons. And this only
was enabled in production. So SIGPROF was interrupting our program execution while we
were trying to load the BPF program. The BPF program takes a little while to load because
the verifier has to run a bunch of algorithms to ensure that everything is safe. And it
was getting interrupted all the time. The BPF library we used to load the BPF program
was retried up to five times until it basically said I tried. This didn't work. Sorry. And
obviously we need the BPF program to be loaded to work. So there's many other considerations
in this project like short-lived processes which we haven't optimized for. But we are
still pretty decent at. If your program runs for one second, we're probably going to catch
it. But if this is something that you care about, feel free to message us. It will be
something that we optimized. And then, yeah, this is our current format. I probably have
one minute left or something like that. So you don't have to understand it all. But the
point is we represent every single row with two 64-bit words. But since we are making
it a bit smaller, and this is basically how our size compares to dwarf. We are bigger
because dwarf is optimized for disk while we are optimized for disk space while we are
optimized for just raw speed. So, for example, our whole table for one shard pretty much
fits in L2 cache. I guess do I have any more time? Probably not. Two minutes. Sorry. Maybe
I sped up too much. So we need to support parsing every single dwarf CFI up code. And
the reason for this is because otherwise we won't be able to progress. But we cannot unwind
from every single program counter, which sucks. But this is not a problem in practice. The
reason for this is because the most typical way to recover the previous frame stack pointer
is which is called CFA in dwarf. It doesn't matter. You will get given which register
you need to apply some offset to and that will give you the previous frame stack pointer.
We support that. But the problem is it could be any arbitrary register. Right now we only
support either RBP or RSP offset which happens 99% of the time. This is nothing we are going
to work on soon. The other problem, as Vashali said before, is that dwarf has a VM that you
need to implement which has to be Turing-complete and can implement any expression. The second
level, yeah. Okay. But you need to implement a VM that basically has a set of virtual registers.
But the second one, we will talk about those later. The first level, yeah, it's the stack
machine 100%, but the second level, I can show you our code, it's messed up. It's messed
up. But anyways, the thing is that we are very lucky here and you can check more about this
in this PR. There are two dwarf expressions that account for 50% of all the expressions
that we have seen in most distributions. They are the expressions used by the dynamic linker
needs them. And the other expressions for linkage tables or PLTs. The other good news
is that RBP and RSP offsets rarely occur and all the other possibilities I haven't talked
about they almost never occur. We have seen them very, very, very few times. Oh, good
question. So... That's what I was talking about. Yeah, yeah, yeah. But right now we only support
X64 but I'm also going to talk about this later. Sorry. But anyways...
Okay, done? Okay, well...
But we have the minutes buffer for the next one, right?
Five minutes.
Okay. I have two more slides. Well, anyways, our BBM program, we tried to make it as fast
as possible. So this was running on my machine with a bunch of applications that have 90
frames or more. So even the maximum time that it takes is 0.5 milliseconds, which is not
terrible on my CPU, which is from late 2017. And this is in a big part because we have
optimized everything for memory. So everything's aligned properly and we try to fit as many
things as possible in the CPU cache. What about high-level languages? So there's a project
that I happen to work on, which is called RBPerf. So this is something that we're going
to be adding in the future. Basically, for dynamic languages, you need to have knowledge
of the ABI of every interpreter version. And then the stack walkers are implemented in
BPF. But instead of getting the return addresses, because you have no return addresses there
that are meaningful to you, you have to directly extract the function names and other information
of the process heap. Our project is called Parca. So there's a couple of things that
we're going to be doing, like mix and wipe mode, that as far as we know, no one else
does this in profiling, in debuggers for sure, but not in profiling, which is the idea of
that different sections will be unwound using different techniques. So for example, if you
have a JIT that will be used like Node.js that has frame pointers, so you will unwind
it with frame pointers. But once you reach the actual code from your interpreter, which
is compiled and has unwind information, we will use dwarf unwind information. ARM64 support
is coming late this year. And this feature is now disabled by default, but it is stable
enough that we're going to be enabling it in a month. And then we're going to add other
on times such as the JVM or Ruby. And then just to say that we are open source user space
and the Apache 2, BPF and the GPL. And yeah, all the links are here. And yeah, thank you
so much.