Okay. So hello everyone.
This presentation is about OpenCSD,
which is a computational storage emulation platform.
The reason we're emulating that,
I'll get into shortly.
But first, I think I owe you an explanation of
computational storage and what it's actually is.
Because I don't think many people are familiar with that.
Even in this dev room,
but I'm pretty sure most people are familiar with camera and eBPF.
You can email me, there's a link to the repo.
This has been a long time collaboration with my master's thesis at the food.
So let's get started.
I'm going to briefly explain who am I.
I'm Kone Luka. My handle online is mostly Dentalian.
I'm also a licensed ham radio operator,
Papa Delta 3CR uniform that is.
My expertise is in parallel and distributed system.
I've been in academia for some while,
associate degree, bachelor degree, master's degree.
I've had some experiences throughout that time.
So I've worked on health technology for officially impaired people.
Worked on OpenStack with Cloud optimizations.
I've done computational storage for my master thesis.
That's what this talk is about.
Currently, we're on SCADA systems for the lower two radio telescope at Ostrone.
So why do we actually need computational storage?
That's because we live in a data-driven society nowadays.
So the world is practically exploding with data.
So much so that we're expected to store 200 setabytes of data by 2050.
These high data and throughput requirements
pose significant challenges on
storage interfaces and technologies that we are using today.
So if you look at your traditional computer architecture,
the one that's being used on x86,
it's based on the Von Neumann architecture.
Here, we basically need to move all data into
main system memory before we can begin processing.
So this poses memory bottlenecks and
Internet interconnect bottlenecks on networks or PCI Express.
It also drastically it hinders energy efficiency to an extent.
So how much of a bandwidth gap are we talking here?
Well, if you look at the server from 2021,
say using Epic Milan with 64 SSDs,
we're losing about four and a half times the amount of bandwidth that could be
offered by all the SSDs in tandem but can't be
utilized because we can't move it into memory that fast.
So that's quite significant.
What is this computational sort?
How does this solve this actually?
Well, we fit a computational storage device,
so a flash storage device with its own CPU in memory.
Now the user, the host processor,
can submit small programs to this computational device,
let it execute, and only the result data from
this computation can then be returned over the interconnect into system memory,
thereby reducing data movement and potentially improving energy efficiency.
Because these lower power cores using more specialized hardware are
typically more energy efficient than your general purpose x86 processor.
If we then look at the state of current prototypes as of September 2022,
we see three main impediments.
Firstly is the API between the host and device interface.
There's no standardization here.
People aren't building hardware prototypes,
but not so much looking at the software interfaces.
We also have the problem of a file system because these flash devices,
they have file systems and we want to keep
that synchronized between the host and device.
So how do we achieve that?
We can't use cache-coherent interconnect or shared virtual memory because by the time
we back round trip between the PCI Express interface,
we'll have lost all the performance that we decide to gain.
How do we stick to existing interfaces?
People that access file systems, they read,
they write, they use system calls.
They are very used to this.
If you would suddenly need to link a shared library to access your file system,
people wouldn't be up for that.
So we need some solutions here.
That's what OpenCSD and FluffleFS introduce.
We have a simple and intuitive system.
All the dependencies and the software itself can run in user space.
You don't need any kernel modules or things like this.
We manage to entirely reuse a system,
system calls that are available in all operating systems,
most typical operating systems,
freeBSD, Windows, Mac,
iOS, and Linux.
So I'd say that's pretty good.
We do something that's never been done before in computational storage.
We allow our regular user on the host to access a file concurrently
while a kernel that is executing on
the computational storage device is also accessing that file.
This has never been done before.
We managed to do this using existing open source libraries.
So we've Boost, Cine infuse,
UBPF, and SPDK.
Some of you will be familiar with some of these.
This allows any user like you to after this talk,
try and experience this yourself in
Canvas without buying any additional hardware.
I'll get into that hardware in a second because there's
some specialized hardware that if we want to have this physically in our hands,
we have to do some things.
If you look at the design,
then we see four key components and
a fifth one that I'll explain on the next slide.
We're using a lock structured file system,
which supports no in-place updates.
So everything is appended and appended.
We have a module interface where we have backends and frontends.
So this allows us to experiment and try out new things.
We can basically swap the backends and keep the frontend the same.
We're using this new technology in Flash SSDs that's called zone namespaces.
They are commercially available now,
but they're pretty hard to get still,
but that's going to improve in the future.
The system calls that we managed to reuse,
those are extended attributes.
So extended attributes on any file and directory on most file systems,
on the file system you are using likely now,
you can set arbitrary key value pairs on these files.
We can use this as a hint from the user to
the file system to instruct the file system that something special needs to happen.
Basically, we just reserve some keys there and assign special behavior to them.
Now, let's get back to the topic of
zone namespaces because I own you some explanation here.
Back when we had hard drives,
we could perform arbitrary reads and writes to arbitrary sectors.
Sectors could be rewritten all the time without requiring any erasure beforehand.
This is what is known as the traditional block interface.
But there's a problem and that is that
NAND flash doesn't actually support this behavior.
So when you have NAND flash,
your sectors are concentrated in blocks and this block needs to be linearly written.
Before you can rewrite the information in a block,
the block needs to be erased as a whole.
So in order to accommodate Flash SSDs have to
incorporate what is known as a Flash translation layer,
where basically all these requests that go to
the same sectors are somehow translated and put somewhere else physically,
just so that the user can still use
the same block interface that they have been used to from the time of hard drives.
So there's this physical translation between these logical and physical blocks.
When we try to synchronize the file system from the host with
the device while a kernel is running,
this introduces a whole lot of problems.
So how do we solve this?
Now, you know the answer, it's the sound namespaces.
We basically present an interface that's not a block interface,
and it's an interface that fits to NAND flash behavior.
So when you use the sound namespaces SSD,
you need as a developer of a file system or the kernel,
need to linearly write each sector in the block,
and you need to erase the block as a whole.
So effectively, you become the manager of this SSD,
the flash translation layer and the garbage collection lives on the host,
and we call this whole system host managed.
If we now combine this with a lock-structured file system,
which also didn't have any in-place updates,
and then you naturally see that this becomes a very good fit.
Now, together with these two technologies,
we can finally synchronize the host and the file system,
and we can do that by making the file temporarily immutable while the kernel is running.
And we do that using a snapshot consistency model by creating in-memory snapshots.
So we were able to create a representation of the file as it was on the host,
with metadata, put that to the computational storage device memory,
and we can assure that all the data that is there will remain immutable
during the execution of the kernel.
Meanwhile, the user can actually still write to the file,
and the metadata of the file on the host will differ,
but that's not a problem.
So this is very powerful,
and it allows us to also understand kernel behavior in a way,
because we can now have metadata and send it to the computational storage device that says,
well, actually, if the kernel tries to do this,
remember it's a user-submitted program,
it might be malicious,
then we want to block those actions.
So we have a security interface as well.
The final kick in the bucket for this design is that we want to be
architecture independent and we do that through eBPF,
the system that you're also using for network hooks
and event hooks in the Linux kernel nowadays.
With eBPF, you can define system calls and expose those in a header,
and this is actually the format of how you would do that,
that's a real example,
and then the fender would implement that code,
and you would define in a specification some behavior,
but the fender doesn't have to open source their code,
which in the case of Flash,
SSDs and fenders is pretty important because they don't seem to be that keen on that.
This way, we can still have an interface,
the users can write programs once and reuse them across all fenders without any problem.
The nice thing about eBPF is that this instruction set architecture,
what eBPF essentially is,
is easily implementable in a VM.
So there's even pre-existing open source implementations of this,
and that's what we're using, eBPF.
Now that I've explained all the key components to OpenCSD and FluffleFS,
I want to start with a little demo and show you what are
some of the actual practical use cases for this.
So how can we use such a computational storage system in a way that it
makes sense in terms of data reduction and energy efficiency?
For that, we're going to go to the example of Shannon entropy.
This is heavily used by file systems who can perform
background compression or by just compression programs that compress in the background.
What you basically do is you try to quantify the randomness you have in a file.
Typically, it's between 0 and 1,
but for computers that doesn't really make sense.
So we use this lock B that's over here to normalize this for bytes.
Then we can say what's the distribution of bytes.
So we create, because a byte has 265 different possible values,
we create 265 bins and we submit a program to calculate this,
it runs in the background and only the result is returned to the host operating system.
Then the host operating system is free to
decide whether or not this file should be compressed or not.
So how does such a kernel look like?
The kernel that you actually submit to the computational storage device,
or you can just write them in C and compile them with Clang.
So you write them in C and we have
two individual interfaces here that we are exposing.
The yellow commands, those are introduced by the system calls,
the EBPF ABI that we are defining,
and the purple ones,
those are introduced by a file system.
What that means is that using this system as is now,
that it's not agnostic to the file system.
So it is agnostic to the vendor and the architecture of the vendor.
If it's ARM or x86, that doesn't matter.
But now it's specific to the FluffleFS file system that we have written.
I will address some possible solutions for this at the end.
Other things we need to realize is that
the EBPF stack size is typically very small.
We're talking bytes here instead of kilobytes.
So we need a way to address this.
So what you can do is in UBPF,
you can allocate a heap just as your stack,
and then we have this BPF get mem info
that we have defined as part of the ABI
that allows you to get your heap pointer.
Now, currently, you have to manually offset this,
which is a bit tedious, if you will.
You see that that is actually done here.
To store the bins, we offset the buffer by the sector size,
and then the data from the sector reads is actually stored at the top of the buffer,
and the bins are stored at the offset for precisely one sector size.
Now, when we go to look at the file system interface,
and all the helpers and data structures
and additional function calls that we introduced,
we can later see that we can also make
a basic implementation of malloc and free here,
and then just resolve this.
But for now, for this example, it's a bit tedious.
Now, how do you actually trigger this?
So we had the extended attributes,
we had all these systems in place,
but now you just have this kernel,
you have compiled it,
you have stored it to a file,
and now you want to actually offload your computation,
well, in an emulated fashion,
but you want to see how you do that.
So the first thing you do is you call start on the kernel object.
So this is your compiled die code,
and then you get the inode number.
This inode number you have tend to remember,
and you then open the file that you want to read upon,
or write upon, but for the examples we're using read mostly.
Then you use set extended attributes,
you use our reserved key,
and you set it to the inode number of the kernel file,
and then when you actually issue read commands,
the read commands will actually go to
the computational storage device and they'll run on there.
But when do you actually take these snapshots?
The trick is as soon as you set extended attributes.
This is just by design, right?
Could also be once you call the first read,
or once you execute the first write.
But we have decided to do it at
the moment that you set extended attribute.
That means that if you make any changes to your kernel,
once you've actually set extended attributes,
then nothing changes anymore,
and the same goes to the file.
Now, I want to briefly explain
some different types of kernel that you can have,
and what the example here is mainly
showing is what we call a stream kernel.
So a stream kernel happens in
place of the regular read or write request.
So the regular read or write request doesn't happen,
only the computational storage request
happens on the computational storage device.
With an event kernel,
it's like the opposite way around.
First, the regular event happens normally,
and then the kernel is presented with
the metadata from that request and can do additional things.
This is for databases interesting.
For example, say you're writing a big table,
and you want to know the average or the minimum or the maximum,
and you want to emit that as metadata at the end of your table write.
Well, you could use an event kernel to let it write as is,
then you get presented with the data,
the kernel runs on the computational storage device,
and you emit the metadata after,
and you can store it as like an index.
We have also decided to isolate
the context of this computational storage offloading.
So what is considered once you set
that set its attributes by PID,
but we also could make this by file handle,
or you could even set it for the whole I-node.
More so, we could use specific keys for file handle PID or I-node offloading.
So it's just a matter of semantics here.
Now, I have some source code in Python of
this execution steps that I've just shown here,
because there's a little bit of details that are left out in the brief overview.
The first is that you have to stride your requests,
and those have to be strided by 500 to 12K.
Why is this so?
Well, infuse the amount of kernel pages that are
allocated to move data between the kernel and the user space is statically fixed.
So if you go over this,
then your request will seem fine from the user perspective,
but what the kernel will do is it will chop up your requests.
Why is that problematic?
Well, then multiple kernels spawn,
because from the context of the file system,
every time it sees a read or write request,
it's going to spawn this kernel and move it to the computational storage device.
Then here, you can see how I set the extended attribute and get the kernel,
the I-node number.
What I want to show here at the bottom is that I'm getting
265 integers and that's for each of the buckets of the entropy read,
but I'm having a request of 512K.
So that shows you the amount of data reduction that you can achieve using systems like this.
Do you want to 65 integers?
512K? Pretty good.
Could be better though.
The reason it's not better is floating point support in
EBPF is limited to the fact where you need to implement fixed point match yourself.
So we could do this as part of the file system helpers,
but that's not done for this prototype at the moment.
Now, some limitations.
This was Amostites' work.
This was my first time defining a file system ever.
It's solely a proof of concept.
There's no garbage collection,
no deletion, no space reclaiming.
Please don't use it.
Please don't use it to store your files.
Yeah. EBPF has an endianness just like any ISA would have,
and there's currently no conversions.
So if you happen to use something that uses different endianness,
all your data will be upside down.
So you have to deal with that yourself for now.
But once again, we can make it part of the file system helpers to
help with these data structure layout conversions and the endianess conversions.
As I mentioned briefly earlier,
floating point support in EBPF is practically non-existent,
but we can implement fixed point match.
Currently, I haven't shown any performance examples
because I don't think they are that interesting.
Because what's currently happening when you emulate offloading,
is that it just runs on the host processor as is in EBPF.
So it isn't representative of
the microcontrollers that you would find on SSDs.
So the runtime that it would take to execute these kernels would be much too fast.
So that's something that we need to deal on,
I think, because then we can more easily reason
about what would be the actual performance if we would offload these applications to SSDs.
Frankly, these SSDs do have very capable microcontrollers,
typically even multiple processors.
The reason they do that is because they need to manage the flash sensorias layer.
So they are already fairly capable devices actually.
Only read stream kernels have been fully implemented for this prototype as well.
That's mainly because event kernel performance is problematic.
Because the data from the event kernel,
remember the IO request happens regularly.
So all the data is moved back into the host processor,
and only then is the event kernel started.
But what you really need is a two-stage system where
you prevent the data being moved back from the host.
This requires some more tinkering.
The final thing, we need to make this agnostic to the file system.
We can very easily achieve this using this file system runtime,
where tune ICD, an installable client driver,
much the same way that Vulkan and OpenCL and OpenGL are working,
you can dynamically load a shared library that
implements all the functions you have defined in a header.
This can also dynamically compile your programs and then
store cache versions of this program.
Using statifers, we can easily identify on what file system it is running.
That allows users to write their programs one,
run on any architecture,
and for any computational file system,
which I think is pretty powerful and flexible.
So that's it.
I encourage you to try this.
I've also written a thesis on this that does have some performance metrics.
It also shows you some interesting data structures that we had to
design for the file system to be able to support these in-memory snapshots.
There's a previous work called SetCSD.
It also has some early performance information.
I've written quite an extensive survey on the last decade history or so
of computational flash storage devices,
which also quite interesting. So thank you.
Seven minutes for questions.
It's quite good.
I imagine this is quite difficult, right?
Computational storage, what the fuck's that?
So please don't hesitate to ask questions if anything is unclear.
What's the availability of hardware that can do this?
The computational storage?
Yes, the computational storage.
There's one vendor that is selling a computational storage device
that's not based on zoned namespaces storage.
So it's using conventional SSDs.
It supports computational storage to a network interface.
So you have the normal PCIe interface,
and then there's this transport over needs to do TCP IP,
and then you basically just connect over it to SSH,
and then you can do things on the SSD.
That one's commercially available.
I don't know what they would ask for that product.
What does the CSD have to do with zoned namespaces?
Nothing in principle,
but you need a way to synchronize the file system between the host and device,
and zoned namespaces make that trivial.
Whereas conventional SSDs,
the logical and physical block translation,
severely hinders this,
makes it extremely difficult to perform.
So why didn't you include the performance metrics from your thesis?
Because the performance.
Oh, sorry.
Yeah. Very good.
I forgot that actually all the time.
Yeah. So why didn't I include any performance metrics if I have them?
The answer is because I don't think I would have time,
and I don't think they're interesting enough to include.
This is a very complicated subject.
It's very new for most people, computational storage.
Most people have never heard of it.
So I'd much rather spend the time to explain this properly,
and try to show you that this is a very interesting concept to solve this bandwidth gap,
rather than show you some metrics that are not representative anyway,
because the kernel is running on the host CPU,
and you're not going to have an additional CPU on the Flash SSD.
Can you talk about what kind of test setup you have for your metric?
So I don't have the metrics themselves.
Yeah. So the framework.
Okay. Yeah. Yeah. Very good.
What kind of test setup I had to do all these analysis and to try these things out.
So I run Camu on my own host machine,
just a normal laptop, basically this one.
And Camu then creates a virtual sound namespaces device.
That's actually quite recently introduced to Camu.
So you can now try sound namespaces without owning sound namespaces.
That's the whole reason Camu comes into play,
because otherwise people wouldn't need to buy a sound namespace SSD,
which is quite badly available.
And then you just run the prototype as is.
So that's all you need,
and you really don't need any special hardware.
Yeah. It could be even on an ARM laptop. It doesn't matter.
Did you test them?
No, I did not test it.
But whether or not I tested it,
if it works on ARM, the answer is no, I did not test it.
But I'm pretty sure Camu compiles from ARM.
So I'm pretty sure we're good there.
Because you have to remember that's
maybe not intrinsically clear from this presentation,
but we didn't extend Camu in any way.
It's just a normal Camu accumulation.
You don't even need to custom install it.
You can just get it from the package manager and use this.
I have a lot of questions over here.
Regarding the computational part,
what are the limitations of what kind of CPU or kernel
that it may run on these devices?
I think the main limitations, yeah, yeah.
What are the limitations of the kernels that you run on these devices?
Well, first of all, you need to have data reduction, right?
If you're going to read one gigabyte from the flash storage,
and you're going to return one gigabyte of data to the host,
then there's no real point in offloading this,
because the data is going to be moved anyway.
So the first thing that the limitation is that you have to
find an application that is reductive in nature.
Once you do the computation, you return less data.
The nice thing is that's 99 percent of all workloads, right?
So that's pretty good.
The second thing is that if it's time in critical,
and the computation takes a long time,
then it's probably not that interesting,
because the latency will then be too bad,
because the performance of these cores
is much less than your host processor.
But you can implement specialized instructions that could be
very efficient in doing database filtering or things like this,
and that is where the whole ASIC and FPGA part would come into play.
But if it's not time in critical and it's in the background,
like the Shannon-Manser pre-compassion,
those are ideal cases,
reduction in data and not time in critical.
So what you mean is we can have software kernels with
a back-end in hardware so we can also program the hardware?
So like maybe a core CPU board or GPU board?
To repeat the question,
whether or not it's just software or whether we also program the hardware.
Of course, FPGAs can be reprogrammed on the fly,
and we have seen prototypes in the past for
computational storage devices where they do just that.
From the host device, the user sends a bitstream that dynamically reprograms
the FPGA and then the kernel starts running.
That's not what we're trying to achieve here.
What I envision in this study,
FPGA has specialized logic to do certain computations,
and then from the EBPF ABI,
once the Fender code triggers those instructions,
we'll utilize the FPGA to do those computations.
But it would be defined in the specification beforehand.
Because typically, re-flashing
FPGA with a new bitstream takes quite some time.
So in the interest of performance,
it might not be that interesting.
So I'm going to ask a question.
So you might have mentioned it,
but are there like close source competitors?
If there are close source competitors in the space of computational storage.
Well, actually, that's one of the things that's been growing really well.
In the scene, I'd say the vast majority of everything is open source.
At least if you look at the recent things.
If you look at the past decade,
then it's a bit worse because there's a lot of research
published that doesn't actually publish the source codes,
or rather the source codes is published,
but everything is a hardware prototype and they didn't publish
the bitstreams or the VHDL or the Fairlock.
So you then stuck as well,
but it didn't have any PCB designs,
or you can't reproduce the work, if you will.
I say this is a much bigger problem than just
computational storage in the field of academia,
but it's also present here.
Yes.
Can we go back to the Python code?
Which one? The Python code.
Yeah, this one. We were talking about the moments and questions.
I was just wondering about the complexity of the
complexity in terms of?
I have a nested loop there.
The reason this is a nested loop,
in the phase of performance,
I have a nested loop here.
So why that?
In the terms of performance, how?
The Python.
Python. Yeah. The trick is,
this is just for demonstration purposes.
There's one you can easily make this example in C or C++,
and you shit if you care about performance.
The trick is that this program is already spending
99 percent of its time in IO weight,
because it's waiting for the kernel to complete.
So in the face of that, it's not that interesting.
The reason we have a nested loop is because
the floating points in eBPF is not
existent or at least I didn't implement the fixed point mod.
So what I have to do after this,
at the bottom what you don't see here is that from all these buckets of these bins,
I'm actually computing the distribution using
fixed point using floating point mat in Python,
which is why I don't get a single number from this kernel.
Because if I would have floating point implementation in eBPF,
I could already do that computation in eBPF and only return
a single 32-bit float as a result instead of these 265 integers.
But the reason this is a loop is because I still have to
try for the read request because I can't go above 512K,
even if my file is bigger than 512K.
Well, the trick is,
couldn't I implement multi-threading here?
Currently, the eBPF VM runs as a single process.
So even if you submit multiple kernels,
only one will execute at a time.
Why? It's a thesis prototype, right?
Time and things like this. Okay.
Thank you very much.
No worries.