All right, I think we can begin.
So good afternoon.
Thank you all for being here at the on-campus part of the Energy Dev Room.
And as you might have seen, we kicked off the Energy Dev Room this morning with an online
section and there was quite a bit of interaction.
We had nine great presentations, over 70 people in the chat and, yeah, of course, many, multiple
of that of people actually watching the live stream.
So I was glad that the hybrid forum was working out.
And yeah, we are here with the team that made this Energy Dev Room possible.
Nicholas Hurning, Dan Brown, Anna-Linda Helsen and Kyua Herman.
Some of them will be presenting or have presented already.
My name is Nico Hicke and I've been active in the energy sector and the free and open
source software community for quite a while now.
I will repeat some of the talks I did this morning.
I assume most of you here have not yet seen that talk, that speech.
So in the last couple of years, I've seen free and open source software take over the
energy sector.
And being active in that energy sector, I thought it would be cool to have an Energy
Dev Room here at FOSDAM like this.
And FOSDAM gave us the opportunity after we submitted a proposal and then you responded
with proposals and we were overwhelmed by the amount of proposals we got.
We got submissions that range from home automation to green software and energy system modeling.
And by adding the online section in the morning and shortening the talks, we were able to
accommodate most of them.
But still we have to say no to a couple.
So maybe next year, right?
Energy of course is a timely subject.
Our society runs on cheap and reliable energy and that is something we can no longer take
for granted.
Scientists warn us that we are acting too slowly and need to ramp up the adoption of
renewable energy.
The Russian invasion of Ukraine made matters worse by disrupting supplies and causing a
price hike.
And so it is clear that our energy system is under pressure.
Humans are protesting, businesses are shutting down and so society needs solutions and they
also demand them.
Unfortunately it is not just a matter of installing wind turbines and solar panels because these
new sources of energy are decentralized and they are weather bound by nature and thus
they require changes in energy management and distribution.
While energy generation, consumption and distribution differs per country, we can really speed up
the worldwide energy transition by a tremendous amount if we avoid the usual reinvention of
the digital wheels.
And we think that this is a mission that unites us here today at FOSTAM in this energy dev
room.
Today's presentations you will see or have seen will cover projects that model, manage
and optimize energy and unfortunately these solutions will not be sufficient to solve
the energy crisis or limit climate change by themselves.
More impactful and direct changes will be necessary to achieve those goals but these
projects can be the building blocks of the future energy system.
So the projects presented here today besides being great projects are available under a
free and open source license and this is important because it enables collaboration, mass adoption
and customization to fit specific use cases.
And this really fits the energy system in which everything is in a state of change and
integration is needed to fulfill the purpose.
So I hope you all will take this opportunity today to learn, get inspired and strengthen
the free and open source software energy software community.
So please raise your questions after the presentations in the Q&A or join the online conversation
in the matrix chat room and Alina will keep an eye on that.
And so all of us would like to thank everybody that made this all possible.
So we'd like to thank the FOSTAM organizers and volunteers, the people that put in the
effort to submit proposals, all selected speakers and all of you for participating.
Thank you and have a great conference.