Okay, shall I start folks?
I'm afraid I have quite a few slides to go through folks.
So if you, I guess I'll start now then.
Hello folks, welcome to my talk, Getting to a Fossil Free Internet by 2030, before I start.
Can you folks hear me alright?
Excellent.
Okay, alright.
As you can see, there's the title, a tour of the tech and policy changes to get us there.
Hello, if you can't see my face here, because you're not in this room, that's what I look
like I suppose.
My name is Chris, I work at an organisation called the Green Web Foundation.
I've spent the last 10 to 15 years working in a series of wacky climate and data themed
start-ups as you can see here.
Loco2 is about locomotion like trains, but also low CO2 and going loco, because you don't
go on holiday, so stuff like that.
And it's just a panzeric thing that I have been working with.
So these days I do most of my time working with the Green Web Foundation.
So we track the transition of the internet away from fossil fuels.
I also run a podcast where I talk all about green software with other people.
And I also work with a larger organisation called the Green Software Foundation, where
we do work on policy specifically.
During the time I have with you today, we're going to cover these three things here.
I'm going to tell you about why I care about a fossil free internet by 2030.
I'm going to share a framework for helping you think about sustainability in the digital
realm.
And then I'm going to use this framework to look ahead at some policy and tech changes.
So let's start.
Why a fossil free internet by 2030?
So the main one, it's like, let's be real clear about this.
We're in a climate crisis because we keep burning fossil fuels.
Every single time over the last 30 years, we've had a chance to get off them.
We haven't.
If you want to actually speak to your friends or your boss about why a fossil free internet
is important, these are the ways I think you might explain it to someone.
So first of all, it's achievable.
There are big firms already doing this, but we'll see that small firms can do this, like
climate emergency, carbon savings.
That's another one.
It saves lives because all the kind of stuff that gets put into the sky that it doesn't
heat the world up ends up poisoning lots and lots of people.
That saves money because, as we know, fossil fuels are not cheap if you try heating your
house recently.
And yeah, people like being in green firms.
And yeah, there's a whole geopolitics thing that I think people in Ukraine will be very
aware of.
And as Germans, we also, or as people, Europeans, we're aware of too.
So that's why I'd stay there.
Now a framework to think about this is what we use where I work.
We have a model that we call CID, consumption, intensity and direction, where consumption
is about can I change how much we need.
Intensity is can I change how much harm is done by the things that we have to do.
And direction is about changing where do we want to go, what kind of future do we want
to build.
So the first of these is the lenses is consumption, because our society is largely still based
on fossil fuels, using pretty much resources in any way, or create some form of carbon
pollution and waste.
And to start off with, if there are things that we want to do, it's a good idea to try
to minimize the amount of resources we need to do that, no matter what.
So with that in mind, we know that we should be really reducing this, reducing emissions.
What do the trends look like for the last year, right?
This is a chart of historical CO2 emissions created by Dr. Robert Rode at Berkeley Earth,
a kind of environmental data science nonprofit.
You can see your direction we're heading in.
And the good news is that in 2015, almost every single country on Earth agreed at COP
21, a climate conference, that we really should aim to reduce emissions.
And we should go for well below two degrees of warming for this century.
Since then, we've actually found out that we need to be aiming for not just well below
two degrees, but more like well below 1.5 degrees, which is a much more aggressive target.
And that's what you can see.
These are the potential pathways we should be on.
And what does that mean for our sector, the tech sector?
Well, the Paris Agreement will require for the information and communication technology
industry to reduce greenhouse gases by 45% by 2030.
So that's about 7% year on year if we started in 2020.
And I'm not sure it went down the last three years.
So this was actually something that was put together by the Science-Based Targets Institute.
The ITU, which is the International Telecoms Union, I think, and a number of other kind
of official organizations who spent a decent amount of time looking at this.
And this is just for two degrees.
So we need to be doing more than 45%, really.
So how are we doing so far?
Well, there's good news and there's bad news, I suppose.
So the good news is that like two billion people have been connected to the internet
in the last, say, five or six years.
And we've been able to use the internet a lot more, which during the pandemic was very,
very useful.
I really appreciated having access to the internet during the pandemic.
And what I want to draw your attention to here is that while we've increased usage of
digital services, we haven't necessarily increased the usage of energy at the same kind of proportion,
except for cryptocurrencies, which, to be honest, the less said about that, the better.
So I'm not going to really be talking about that too much if that's OK with you folks.
However, and I should ask, why have the figures not been higher?
Well, the simplest answer is that Moore's law has been helping us.
And Moore's law is basically where computer chips have been getting steadily faster and
more power efficient over time.
And as the sector has grown so fast, the average efficiency has increased.
So the thing is, Moore's law is not infinite.
So going forward, improvements in efficiency will likely have to come from new places,
not just the chips themselves.
And this is what this diagram from a paper in Science magazine illustrates.
This paper is called There's Plenty of Room at the Top, What Will Drive Computer Performance
After Moore's Law.
It's a fun read.
And the general argument is that for efficiency gains to keep up with, or keep pace with growth
and really need to be going faster than growth so we don't just stay flat, but actually go
down, we'll need to start applying all these ideas at the top.
All right.
So that directly means it's going to land on us as developers and designers of digital
services a lot more than it otherwise would have.
We can't just rely on Moore's law doing the work for us.
So that's consumption.
And as Phil Griffiths, the author of Electrify, says, you can't efficiency your way to zero.
If we don't want to be cold and wet and without Wi-Fi, at some point there will be a minimal
amount of resource usage that takes place.
Based with that, we need to think about the harm that occurs as a byproduct for every
unit of usage that we have to make.
So in our framework, we talk about this in terms of intensity because there are multiple
dimensions of intensity from water usage to resource depletion to soil toxicity, air quality.
But for the purpose of this talk, I'm going to focus primarily on carbon pollution.
Now in Germany, where I live, the carbon intensity of electricity is influenced by two main things.
There's a lot of wind and solar for sure.
But there's also the majority of our power comes from burning coal.
And these machines, that's what's powering our data centers.
These machines you can see, they destroy forests, they destroy people's homes just to dig up
coal, which we then burn to heat up water to create steam.
The steam turns a turbine, which generates electricity, which is what we end up using.
Along the way, we lose about two thirds of all the energy through cooling towers, and
we emit a lot of carbon.
So a kilowatt of hour of power is around like a kilogram of CO2.
This isn't the only way.
An alternative approach would be to directly harness the energy around us using either
solar or wind turbines, geothermal and so on.
Now we're not burning fuels in this case.
So we're no longer wasting lots of energy in the form of waste heat that we need to
put into the sky.
And it means that there's no need for the kinds of cooling towers that you frequently
see.
So it looks somewhat different as well.
Also the carbon emissions are much, much, much lower.
Even when you factor in the actual making of the solar panels and disposing of them,
for example, you can see the figure here, it's something like 17 times lower.
So this is why it makes sense to not be running on fossil fuels.
Now globally speaking, about 60% of the electricity we use right now comes from burning fossil
fuels.
So it's a global average in certain parts of the world.
Energy is much cleaner.
In other parts it's much dirtier.
The numbers look tiny on this part.
What you can see is that wind and solar in the top right are growing and they've really
been plummeting in cost over the last 10 years.
Solar energy is nearly 10 times cheaper than it was 10 years ago.
And something like 90% of all the new energy capacity that comes on stream these days is
coming from renewables.
So there is some hope.
It's not just going to be that awful black line forever.
So because the carbon intensive compute is not uniform, like I said, all around the world,
if you want to reduce the harm done by carbon pollution from the energy usage that powers
your servers or powers any digital services, you have two main options.
You can move work geographically to run things where the energy is cleaner.
So this is like geographic migration.
That's like the Iceland, the Nordics and so on.
But because the energy, the carbon intensity of energy changes based on how much, where
the generation is coming from, you can basically move things through time.
So you can wait to run things at a different time of day, for example.
So you can wait till it's windy or sunny or send it to where it's windy or sunny.
So that's consumption, intensity and direction.
Finally we have direction.
If you care about open source technology and free software, you know, they're very important
ideas that are kind of re-embed into free software.
And this is like you choosing to work on one project over another, you're making one version
of the future more likely to actually happen than another.
And this is the quote that I find really useful.
It's from a guy called Cade DM.
He says, technology is a social, political and environmental accelerant.
I think it's useful because it really kind of gets across the idea that we're making
a deliberate decision about what we're supporting.
And to give you some idea, this is a graph showing the direct emissions from a number
of companies you've heard of in 2019 plus a single contract from Microsoft with Exxon
Mobile, one of the oil companies that recently, like in the last month, announced $150 billion
in profit last year.
All right.
Basically the consequence of using AI to help Exxon Mobile basically drill for more oil and
gas is basically around 6 million tons.
So that's about a Facebook.
And this is the same figure and this is actually something why I talk about actually thinking
about what you use it for, not just can I make myself efficient, basically.
It's not all bad again.
So Microsoft, they do this, but they've recently been doing more work about actually finding
ways to actually get coal fired power plants off the grid and replacing with other forms
of power like geothermal or nuclear sometimes.
All right.
And every single time, that's like more than a Facebook, more than a Facebook, more than
a Google is worth every single year coming down.
So this is why it's important to actually be thinking about what you use it for.
So let's use this framework to talk about some of the policy and tech changes ahead
of us.
So remember that chart that I showed you before about emissions going up when they need to
be going down, right?
Okay.
For better or worse, this idea of reducing emissions to within safe limits has started
to be referred to as net zero.
And we're finally starting to see some consensus about what it actually means.
Now this is the ISO, the people who set standards.
They've created some guidance about what net zero should really mean.
And the actual guidance is pretty strident.
They basically say net zero claims are no longer considered credible if they are not
halving emissions by 2030 for an organization.
So if your organization doesn't have a net zero target and it's not doing that, not really
credible.
But also say it needs to include the entire supply chain, not just like your own stuff,
basically.
And also you need to have interim targets.
So targets for 2025 or 2026.
And this is because seven years is roughly the typical kind of tenure of a CEO that you
can say, well, we know it's all about 2030.
Leave and then leave it for someone else's job to actually fix.
And this is why it's actually quite important to actually do this because you need to have
something which actually brings action early.
So in Europe, the it's a bit of a mouthful, the European Corporate Sustainability Reporting
Directive in 2024.
That's what organizations above 250 employees now need to be reporting, which means you
need to have started reporting two months ago for 2023 if you haven't already started
reporting.
So this is a thing that's important.
And then finally, the IFRS, they're a bit like the kind of pope of accounting standards.
They basically set a decree that everyone ends up following.
And they've said that, no, if you're going to talk about the carbon footprint of your
organization, you need to talk about not just your organization, but you need to talk about
your supply chain as well.
And that's actually really important because around 90 percent plus is makes up most people's
emissions in the supply chain, not really your own emissions.
So let's use our framework we spoke about consumption and all that.
OK, can I change how much we need?
Joseph did a really good job talking about things like the Blau angle and things like
that.
And he's now emerging standards to actually try to label sustainability of digital services.
And as he mentioned, yeah, there is Ocular was the first ever product that got some decent
got actually certified for this.
This is important because people who spend money on digital software, like, say, public
sector or large, large companies, they can they can write these into contract and say
you need to have a blue angle certificate in order to actually for us to spend tens
of millions of euros with you, for example.
If you want to like work with this stuff yourself or work out the environmental footprint of
this, we mentioned before the guy called Arna Tarrara.
He actually demonstrated a really, really cool piece of technology that does this stuff.
If you have a digital service, it will show you it will basically create a system so you
can see this and then it will come up with all these cool charts.
So you can see this is like a chart.
This is the output showing me doing various things and seeing how it creates spikes in
usage.
So that's testing something from the outside.
You can also look at something from the inside.
So the Firefox profiler, that will actually self-report its own information.
So it will tell you I'm using I'm using this much power and this part of my browser is
using this much.
That's really, really, really cool.
And there's a whole talk about that later.
We did some work with them to actually turn some of these into carbon metrics.
So you get an idea of what these figures are from.
And this is the kind of stuff that my organization tends to do.
If you know this, then you can actually figure out, OK, now that I understand there are hotspots
and what I'm doing, what do I do?
And this chart has been shared or this table has been shared quite a few places.
Basically different languages have different kind of memory footprints.
And this might give you the impression that you should just rewrite everything in C or
something like that.
That's not the end of the message you should take away.
But in many cases, it may be that there are certain parts that are already being rewritten
for you.
Or it's worth remembering that you might be using a language for other reasons than just
efficiency.
And if you are building something super efficient that help people dig for more oil and gas,
probably not that useful.
So intensity.
Can I change how much harm is being done?
So as you might be aware, renewable energy from wind turbines and solar panels depends
on the sun and the wind.
And they don't always blow.
Data centers are normally on 24-7, though.
So how do you power something that's on with 24-7 with energy like that?
The truth is that most of the time we rely on averages.
So when Google says and said that they already run on green energy, they're basically saying
they've used the same amount of energy as they've generated the same amount of energy
from green sources as they've used over the year.
That sounds fair.
It's not quite that simple.
Because you know how, say, people say you should get eight hours of sleep a day, more
or less.
So over a year, which is maybe 9,000 hours, that means you should probably get 3,000 hours
of sleep.
Now, if I got 3,000 hours of sleep by sleeping from January 1 to April 1, then survived on
Red Bull and chocolate bars for the rest of the year, I mean, it's better than no sleep.
But I'm not sure it's 100% sustainable.
And this is actually one of the things that we'll be talking about later.
So this is the difference between annual and hourly and why it matters.
And as I mentioned before, if you don't have massive solar farms and you can't invest on
all this stuff yourself, some things you might need to do is think about how and when you
run computing jobs or how you do stuff like this.
Now, there was a talk all about this.
And if you've heard of Kubernetes, right, there's basically, you can basically say,
please run this computing job where it's green, where it's sunny, or please run it when it's
when there's lots of energy on the grid.
All right.
There's a really good talk about it.
So I'm not going to talk too much about it.
Okay.
So what I will talk about, though, is just going a bit more detail about what our computers
run on, really, I suppose.
So when we think of computers just using energy right now, what we're really using is a mixture
of electricity from different sources, each with slightly different properties.
So if you have some onsite renewables connected to, say, a building, that's one source, it
will be very low carbon.
But you won't have much control over when the power comes on, because it's basically
the wind and the sun that's deciding this.
And you're dependent on the outside environment.
If you've ever used a laptop, you'd use battery storage here.
And like, that means it comes on when you want it to be.
I mean, a laptop that only turns on when it's sunny would not be that useful.
So this is like what you could refer to as dispatchability or things like whether they're
dispatchable or not.
All right.
But they have limited amounts of power.
Or sometimes, but it's getting a lot better.
Finally, there's the grid energy.
Sometimes it's clean.
Sometimes it's dirty.
And you can normally rely on it.
But when, like, awful geopolitical events happen, they kind of change how much it costs,
both in human terms and in actual financial terms.
Now, I apologize for going super nerdy on some of this stuff.
But if you've ever used a virtual machine, you'll understand that what we do with virtual
machines is we take a big server, and then we use virtualization to turn it into a kind
of abstract set of resources like compute, like computing power, network, RAM, and storage.
And once we've got this kind of broken down way of thinking about it, we can then turn
it into a series of smaller machines.
So there might be one virtual machine that has lots of RAM, but only a little bit of
storage.
And by doing that, I can basically make much, much more efficient use if I have a set of
computers.
And this idea of breaking things down and breaking them up again, I think is one thing
that you can use when you think about energy as well.
And there's a really cool paper that was published last year about this idea of eco visors.
And the general idea is that you can do the same with power as what we've been doing with
like computing resources.
So if you virtualize the power as a kind of grid made of three different things, then
you can allocate maybe a significant amount of battery for one program that needs to be
on all the time, and maybe less to another, which doesn't need to be on all the time.
So you can basically allocate it in these different ways.
And this allows you to then do something like this.
You could basically create virtual machines with certain amounts of virtualized power
that you can actually work with.
And this is actually something that you can then share visibility of to the machines because
computers generally just aware of them having power.
They don't really know about what the kind of power is like, whether it's green power,
whether it's battery or so on.
But you can make some of this available to people to see.
And there are ways that you can implement like an API.
So a program can be aware of its own power that it's using.
And that allows you to then actually basically design a system so it's aware of this and
can make much, much better use of this or turn things off when it doesn't need or actually
use more when there's an abundance of green energy, for example.
So that's kind of one of the ideas, which I think is super exciting to haven't seen
anywhere else.
You can also do some cool stuff with networking, carbon away networking.
And I've got a few more slides, so I'm going to have to run through this quickly.
But the short version is if I want to visit a website in England, sorry, and the website
and the servers in Poland, that's all the way through here.
Now, every single time there's going to be different kinds of energy that I use.
But if the Internet was aware of the network, I could go I could take different routes,
which are cleaner and greener and some kind of like low carbon trick shot thing.
So this was actually was a this exists right now.
There's a network program called Sion that does something like this already.
There's also a way to extend IPv6 like this.
We shared a paper specifically to this IETF Internet Architecture Board workshop all
about this stuff.
There's 26 papers, 26 papers all about this.
And it's super exciting and interesting in my book.
And funny direction, can I change where we're headed?
So we work on this idea, a fossil free incident by 2030, because we think the Internet should
be a global public good.
And it's healthy for the planet.
And you should be healthy, healthy for people who use it.
And remember, I spoke about the idea of hourly figures like annual versus hourly.
It's Google as one company, they've actually put a lot of time and money behind the idea
of saying, well, we're going to run 24 seven carbon free energy, none of that Red Bull
and chocolate stuff, we're going to do it properly, which is good.
And this is something that we didn't realize was possible.
Microsoft is now doing the same thing as again, but they're coming up with their own words,
because they can't possibly have the same words for some reason.
Right.
And I thought, wow, this is really, really cool.
And then I found out literally like a month ago that this company, this company here,
Peninsula Clean Energy, they're a small nonprofit organization.
They've said, oh, yeah, we we're already at 99 percent 24 seven matched.
And we reckon we'll do it by 2025.
So this is a small company, 100, maybe that is reaching, say, 100,000 people in California.
They've basically built this into their governance to say, no, this is a priority over share
buybacks, dividends to shareholders, everything like that.
It's about intention.
And they've basically got there.
But what's super cool and for the FOSDEM group is that they've open sourced how they're doing
it.
They've actually shared the model they use to actually figure out where they buy the
power from and the ideas behind this.
And like, I think this is pretty freaking cool.
And it's like, basically why I'm excited about open source and everything like that.
Finally, I've only used American examples so far.
But now I can't say that this was entirely Europe's plan because Nord Stream was kind
of switched off by like Putin and everything like that.
So they've spanned it this way.
They've basically said, well, we've completely got rid of our dependence on Russian fossil
fuels now.
It went much faster than we expected.
So we now have the possibility to redirect the money we would have spent on gas to repower
EU, 250 billion euros to net zero industries.
So this is basically a quarter of a trillion euros to basically talk to deploy the kind
of cool green stuff rather than the bad brown stuff that I think we should be getting away
from.
So that's my recap.
I wanted to share a model with you that I call CID, consumption, intensity and direction.
Can I change how much we need?
Can I change how much harm is done?
Can I change where we're headed?
And I want to tell you about a fossil free internet by 2030.
It's achievable.
We've seen that big firms do this, but small firms do it and faster and better.
We've seen how it basically saves carbon.
We know that doing this saves lives.
It saves money because we know that fossil fuels are actually really, really expensive.
And I've already done this slide once.
I'm just going to skip it because I'm running out of time.
But folks, I think that's the time I've used.
So if you want to know more, my organisation, the Green Web Foundation, we publish open
source code, we publish open data, and we work with other organisations who are trying
to do the same.
We also offer training and consulting.
If I've been speaking too quickly, there is a transcript of this entire talk at that website.
And I'm also online as Mr Chris Adams on Twitter, but less so these days.
And on Macedon social as there.
And also if you use email, I use email too.
Yeah.
Thanks.