I think we're good to go, Robbie.
Okay, my name is Robbie Morrison and I'm here to talk about energy system modelling.
I want to take you right up to the stratosphere.
A couple of things on my background, I won't go through all this, but I started climate
campaigning 33 years ago.
I started High Resolution National Energy System Modelling 23 years ago and I started
open source energy system modelling 20 years ago.
So I was right at the beginning of those trends pretty much.
I want to talk briefly about the Open Energy Modelling Initiative, which started about
eight years ago and it's an informal collection of modellers.
We now have about 1,000 people involved.
The bulk of them are early stage full-time researchers.
That gives you an idea of how much interest there is in this open side.
There is an entire parallel universe doing closed modelling that we don't have much
contact with in the power companies, in the World Bank, in the multilateral organisations.
So I'm only going to talk about the open source side.
The final point up here is that this whole field has flipped in the last year, radically.
I get contacted by corporations and economists and so forth now, which would never have happened
two years ago.
So this is a complete game change.
I'm not going to talk very much about energy system modelling, but if you want an introduction
I recommend this YouTube, which is made with my partner in a car park and it's descriptive
and it's quite good.
This is a quick schematic showing what these models can capture.
This just happens to be one that I pulled up that's hybrid with agent-based modelling
in it.
But you see a lot of the entities, if you like, that were being discussed in the previous
talks, but brought together in a collective...
So we have households and we have market operators and we have lines companies and we have markets
and we have AC power flow and we have a lot of kit in the system, hydro system, storage,
gas turbine sets and so forth, and a whole lot of external characteristics coming in
through weather conditions, interest rates and so forth.
So that sort of gives you the broad picture.
If you want to look at the models that exist, this Wikipedia page is worthwhile.
It's about half complete and it covers the various models.
Some are directed specifically to the energy sector, but increasingly they're sector coupled
and they come into the whole energy system.
The basic paradigm is operations research.
So the underlying model produces a set of constraints in a sparse matrix, has a goal
function which is normally minimum aggregate cost and feeds that all into a solver and
returns a result.
The way that the analysis proceeds is by so-called comparative analysis of scenarios.
So you pick a base scenario, a reference scenario and then you propose different scenarios that
you want to explore with nuclear, without nuclear and so on and so on.
These are the high resolution.
They have a lot of detail in them.
So they have the plant and the network and so forth in them.
A lot of external circumstances, weather, demand for energy services and so forth.
They are contiguous time which is really important nowadays because with renewables and storage
you can't kind of do typical periods.
You actually have to work your way through the entire system as it evolves.
That evolution might be out for 30 years, out to 2050.
There's a degree of different types of foresight.
Sometimes it's perfect foresight so we know everything about the future.
Other times it's stepwise so we do recursive dynamics.
Not up here.
Technological progress is included.
One factor, multi-factor, for example, the uptake of a particular technology like solar,
PV, the model will internally reduce the costs for that particular technology as it's taken
up and it evolves through time.
The optimisation is usually mixed integer linear programming.
Anything else more exotic runs into performance issues.
Conceptual extensions include embedded decision taking using agency, multi-criteria optimisation,
some assessment of co-benefits such as urban air quality, sensitivity to the framing of
the problem, the role of uncertainty and the exploration of near optimal solutions.
So this is system modelling.
All systems have kind of natural systems and problems if you like together have natural
boundaries.
If you want to model Europe or you want to model an energy system in Germany you probably
want to go to the boundaries of Europe, for example, because that's kind of a natural
point.
The methods naturally seek technical synergies.
That's one of the advantages of using these systems.
The least cost approach will pick up the synergies and get them working.
Future climate change is normally included, projected future climate change.
These models may exhibit undue sensitivity to both data quality and to system resolution
so they're not without issues that have to be explored by modellers.
They started off with energy systems, electricity systems coupled into district heating, into
gas and so forth.
But they're increasingly branching out into land usage, water use, the industrial sector.
When you're looking at things like hydrogen ammonia, thermal integration and steel production.
Carbon capture is included now outside of the energy system.
So residual emissions from cement and from agriculture are now being included in these
models.
E-mobility also, and we've had some talks about vehicle charging, but this is to look
at the whole picture and not just the perspective of the householder or even the lines company.
Co-benefits beyond climate change mitigation I mentioned.
What isn't in the models is there is no embedded economy.
If you want to do that, then you have to go to process-based integrated assessment models
which are widely used by the IPCC, in which case you have a lot more economic take on
the system.
The model started off being open source, but there are good reasons why we want to look
beyond open source.
The first reason is to go to open science.
So we want genuinely open data and we want under communal curation.
We want full transparency.
As modelers, we want an engaged overarching community so that we can compare and contribute
and support each other.
The goal in my take is that we should be looking at public policy analysis which is based on
peer production, on commons-based peer production.
The reason I say that, and I think there was a talk earlier this morning from the European
Commission, people like the European Commission do not have the capacity to explore the solution
space and I will add, nor do they have the creativity required.
That's not a criticism, that's just an observation.
So we really want a massive effort in exploring what our future could be out to 2050, the
kinds of trajectories and pathways and requirements that are needed.
Some potential for public engagement, but very few examples to date when these models
are used for more specific projects.
Our biggest Achilles heel is complete and coherent data for public interest analysis.
We are not data scientists.
We are desperate to have data which is complete and coherent.
If it's dirty, it's a problem, if the semantics behind the data collection is somewhat inconsistent,
it's a problem.
If the information is missing, it's a problem.
This may not be an issue for our data scientists using statistical techniques or machine learning,
but it is for us.
One issue that doesn't get much airplay are data standards and quite a lot of the data
standards in this area, especially in the electricity sector, are proprietary.
They come under so-called FRAND.
We heard about that, fair, reasonable and non-discriminatory conditions.
The problem is, is if the data standards are legally incumbent, then the code bases that
reflect that and the data sets that comply with it could become derivative works under
intellectual property law and we are in trouble.
We want basically CC by 4.0 or something similar on the data standards.
I'll skip the last bit on data sets actually.
I'll skip this slide, but I just want to point out that the situation in Europe is pretty
awful on a number of levels.
Go to the US and you'll find a much friendlier environment for this kind of public interest
information.
Okay, the second part of my talk is about the Global South.
The question is, why is someone who's white, male and old standing here talking about the
Global South?
My short answer is I'm from Aotearoa, New Zealand, and New Zealand became bicultural
over my lifetime and I saw that process and contributed to it.
I had radio programs in the early 90s on sustainability and conservation on tribal radio, on E.B.
radio and so forth.
I went to land occupations.
I organized joint meetings with tribes, Hui they're called, and they take place on Marai.
That's kind of my back story about why I can talk about this I think.
This is a map of Africa with the high voltage network present and you'll see that there
is very little structure there.
South Africa a little more.
David is going to talk a little more about this so I won't.
This is another example of a model called Osmosis.
This is in Africa and these are the cumulative trades out for the next 30 years.
This is the kind of thing that the models are starting to look at.
There are two overarching projects in this area, the Osmosis Global Project.
Osmosis is written in a high level mathematical programming language called MathProg.
The second one is Pipes to Meet Earth which is written in Python and you'll hear a little
bit more about.
One of the interesting things I looked at, Software Heritage collects the forks for a
particular code base and lists 135 fork repositories for Osmosis and 308 fork repositories for
pipes.
That gives you an idea of how the open source world works when people will fork the project.
These aren't hostile forks I presume and use them for their own work and hopefully contribute
their contributions back upstream.
This clear activity now in Central America, Costa Rica, South America, countries like
Brazil, India and surrounding regions, South Africa, Sub-Saharan Africa.
Most of this is in the context of academic work.
We have no connection or very little connection crossing over with the multilateral development
organisations and so forth.
This is the parallel universe I mentioned.
How are we doing for time?
One of the issues that we face I think is interacting with official agencies because
we are relatively informal and relatively self-directed.
We also are a competition against the agencies like the International Atomic Energy Agency
or IRINO, whoever are doing their own analysis.
I quite like this quote from Oliver Geddon, everyday politics is therefore dominated not
by evidence-based policymaking but by attempts at policy-based evidencemaking and that's
exactly what we want to avoid.
I talked to the incumbent NGOs about using our kind of analysis and they weren't very
interested but I feel quite encouraged now because there are a new set of foundation
backed think tanks who are actually very keen on this kind of stuff.
I'm sorry I can't mention too many names because I was ill for the two weeks prior to this
talk and I didn't get consent to talk about them but a couple of climate analytics and
transition zero.
Some official agencies are starting to talk about open sourcing their stuff but they're
not doing it in a particularly robust way in my opinion and this is a problem.
They will either open, wash or they will do what's called throw their code over the wall
which is put it on GitHub but there's no attempt to develop it.
There are no issues listed and whether it even runs is open to question.
In regards working with the Global South and I had about ten interviews with researchers
in the Global South to try and find out what scopes and issues, their unstructured interviews
but that was kind of interesting.
The clear benefits of open source projects, of course few cost barriers with a caveat
that the commercial solvers can be expensive.
Open license for Garobi might equal three full time researchers in India for example.
There's a soft technology transfer, it's bidirectional, it's lightweight.
All the software projects bundle associated communities and this is I think really a useful
part and the work is transparent.
It can be studied and challenged which I think is really important.
There are some cost cultural considerations I think that are necessary to explore and
I talk about this in Aotearoa and New Zealand becoming bi-cultural but indigenous languages
bundle different concepts and they're quite noticeably different.
Sovereignty is an issue, it's really easy to transgress sovereignty without realising
it.
There's a question of representation, the projects are all pretty much white and male
and the Global North at the moment.
The next question really is also a matter to be traversed is that the framing of the
models and the problems from a Global North perspective may not be very appropriate to
the circumstances in the Global South.
Final slide, challenges, just overarching challenges.
So these won't be very surprising, code maintenance is always a challenge, support for maintainers.
Building a suitable knowledge commons is going to be a real challenge.
For instance the International Energy Agency only sells its data under non-disclosure,
we don't get hold of that although it's collected from our national governments.
The European Union is focused on data commodification through its single digital market.
The scientific institutions are unnecessarily protective.
I talked about cross-cultural issues.
We need to find new ways of interacting with official agencies to get any of this information
into the policy process and I'll just conclude with a quotation from an East German playwright
Heine Muller, optimism is just a lack of information.
Okay, that's it, thank you.
Any questions?
Can you speak up a little too if you ask questions?
Maybe you said the European Union has some issues with open data.
I know that the European Space Agency has a really strong footprint on doing all this
as a Sentinel data stuff, maximum open to drive a new economy.
So has this not spread to the other agencies yet?
The ones I want to mention, and I will mention some names, the Merideth for Future Climate
is under a bespoke licence.
The YASA data on scenarios going forward also under a bespoke licence and so on.
So a lot of the Horizon 2020 projects are also problematic.
The stuff under statutory reporting is also legally encumbered so I can't for the life
of me understand why, but some of it is technically encumbered.
So for example the transparency platform run by NSE is legally encumbered.
The EEX data from the European Energy Exchange also and also technically encumbered.
You can't cut and paste it off the website.
It's not very deep protection.
And we've complained, my friends, to the regulator and they say it's compliant.
Sorry, yeah.
So now I've just got a comment though, which is, I've had a few minutes, you've been
experiencing, for example, in London all the authorities were publishing air quality data
under random crappy licences where they could do stupid things retrospectively.
We've persuaded it to punishment under a UK Open Government licence.
Another case I've...
Open Government licence, UK 3.0.
I don't know which one they're using, this was a few years ago.
Yeah.
And the other decent experience was with Elexon UK balancing where I...
Well, I think I'm their only official agency, but other than that they can tell me to retract
everything.
I can use it completely openly, which is quite nice.
So it can sometimes be worse.
I just want to comment on licensing.
The one that, really the only licence that works is CC by 4.0.
If you go to the Open Government licence, UK 3.0, you'll find it's not interoperable
with Creative Commons.
And so you end up with legal data silos.
But still better than 15 random licences written by people who aren't lawyers, right?
It's still in the improvement.
I know all the licences are written by lawyers.
I can assure you that the lawyers all know what they're doing.
I don't think you saw some of the things they published.
Okay, okay, okay.
Was there a question up there or no?
Yeah.
Has anyone done any of the IAM
IAMs?
I have a clause in the – remember when Java was proprietary?
And you have to have an open language for a GPL licence.
They use GAMS, which is not an open language.
And I filed a bug report.
And I know personally the lawyer who responded who said it was okay.
Now, look, I'm not an open source lawyer.
I don't know about the textbook.
But that was where that discussion went.
Have you seen any new funding come into this particular field to open things up more?
Because all I know is that in December, I know that the Creative Commons group,
they've started to hire new roles in this specific role
because they landed like a small millions of euros grant for this.
But beyond that, I don't know if there's any other groups starting to do stuff in this field.
Thanks for answering.
Okay, okay.
Yeah, finished.
No, good question.
Oh, sorry.
The question was funding specifically for open source.
And the sort of short answer is – hang on.
The short answer is that the funding – I'm talking about Germany, let's say –
has been quite good for modelling in general.
And it hasn't been specifically directed to open source.
The high-level organisation, the Open Energy Modelling Initiative,
hasn't needed resources as yet.
But what will happen going forward, I don't know.
But the funders are interested in the kind of open science component of what we do.
That's quite clear.
And I presume that the next round of funding will start looking for real open source projects to be for support.
Yeah?
Yeah, so what would you say in all the years of experience has to change?
And how can we push for the change so that we get these open data?
So what are the levers we have to pull with the open source?
In a particular – well, the question was what levers are needed to come to genuinely open data.
It depends on the jurisdiction. In the US it's quite good.
Federal – work by federal employees is public domain.
And there's been enough copyright – litigation around copyright that most of the stuff isn't actually covered – protected by copyright.
They don't have a database directive.
Tracking back to Europe, the only solution I can see is CC by 4.0 as a policy,
which is lightweight, doesn't require legislative change and so forth.
But it does require the European Union to get out of the data commodification.
And I didn't mention it, but there's a thing called the Data Producers Act, which is still live,
which might come back into the Data Act, the proposed Data Act.
And that would be a complete travesty for us, because that would mean all this machine-generated data
would now have its own intellectual property.
And I couldn't think of anything worse.
Okay, yep, thank you everyone.