Shortly about us, so I'm there on the left.
So we are Saita Energy Flexibility Software Startup who decided to go the open source
way two years ago.
In this project we're working together with positive design, a small company in the Netherlands
as well.
They are more working on the UX part of this.
So something where I really know a lot about are these two projects because we are building
Flex Measures, a project we donated to the Linux Energy Foundation.
Before you leave the room, get some swag over there.
And together we built this V2G Liberty project which actually works as an umbrella for the
rest.
It's a vehicle to grid.
Some of you might know roughly what it is.
It has been a buzzword going around.
It basically means other than most of the car charging that's going on today, just power
into the car, you could actually get power out of the car, for instance, back onto the
grid.
Here I listed some use cases why that is supposedly a good idea.
And specifically the third one, that might be pretty interesting because in a scenario
where you have a varying energy price, now your car could be a trader.
And actually the spreads in the energy markets are increasing by a lot these days.
So that makes it suddenly interesting.
And when I look at industry coming up with vehicle to grid by themselves, people observe
a lot of delays.
From my perspective it seems that the actual industrial players, closed source players
are looking to actually deliver an ecosystem.
These are pictures you are getting from the big names Hyundai, Volkswagen, Tesla.
They are always thinking about putting multiple things in your home, basically taking it over.
And that takes longer and it's also something I'm not looking forward to.
That's why we decided to do this project.
It's more than a year ago now, so we have more than a year of data from one location.
And recently we've attracted some other enthusiasts and there's five more locations where this
is being employed in reality.
Quickly about the motivation, so why should we do that?
Is this something that I want to sell with Site Energy Flexibility and focus on that
completely?
Actually, probably not.
Site Energy Flexibility and our Flex Measures project is about making the best use of energy
flexibility in general.
But this is very cool to show that we can do something today.
We don't have to wait.
There's open source projects.
If you put them together, they are super powerful.
And that was a great way to bootstrap ourselves to challenge our technology.
So I'll talk about the stack, the design of what V2G Liberty looks like if you use it,
and some outlooks.
First, what do you need in this context to actually get going?
You won't find a lot of cars you can use for this.
The Nissan Leaf is one of the only ones, specifically in 2021, that could do vehicle to grid.
Same goes for the Charger.
So this is the Charger from a Spanish company, Wallbox.
Of course, they promised that open standards like OCPP will be very soon working.
And that hasn't happened yet.
So what was it?
You need some kind of computer in your house.
This has been mentioned in talks this morning already.
And then we work with an energy contract with Dynamic Terrace.
So in the Netherlands, you already have, I think, six or seven to choose from.
That's going very hard.
But the Tiber, for instance, is launching in a couple European countries and offers
you that.
And so this is actually the software architecture in a nutshell.
I don't want to make it too difficult.
If you imagine you put this in your house, what you need is to install Home Assistant.
So that's this logo here.
Home Assistant is a very stable home automation software.
And we've basically built V2G Liberty as a Home Assistant plugin.
That's also actually fun to do.
It's nice when you get a lot of presence like UI widgets and things like that.
And then Flex Measures is actually not running in the house.
It could.
It's dockerized.
You could put it in the house next to your home automation software.
And I think a couple of these enthusiasts who now are using this are doing that.
But for such a software, it's sometimes nicer to run in the cloud because it's more difficult
to maintain.
Flex Measures itself is then responsible to get the relevant real-time data that is important
to schedule the cars charging, discharging.
So in this case, the prices that the consumer contract is on.
We could also get, I think we actually do in a new version.
It's not listed here.
We also get some public data that helps us to look at the CO2 levels of your car cost
consumption.
So that would be another box right there.
I talked about this connection.
We have to somehow talk to the wallbox.
And we found out for now, this has to be Modbus.
And we found out how this responds.
And we talked to the wallbox company if we're allowed to put our code in a public repository
if you could see in the code which registers their hardware reacts to.
But I think we've sorted it out.
That was a bit difficult.
And basically what we have to do is simply say start or stop the charging or discharging.
And we are able to read the state of charge of the battery.
And on the left side are some more nicer UX features.
So you want to put along for a longer ride.
You want to tell our system that the car needs to be full.
And maybe you want some overrides.
I'll come to those later.
So first about the components.
I mentioned Home Assistant.
It has been around for a while now.
I think it has also some origins in the Netherlands.
But it's also developed in California now.
Actually we had a couple of Home Assistant people over in a demo.
I think it's these people here.
So that was nice to actually have that also in real life.
And as I said you can write plugins to really do your own logic on top of Home Assistant.
Now Flexmeasures is the project that I spent the most time with.
Our company develops that.
Basically it's a data driven platform to get the best timing for your flexible energy assets.
When should they be on or off.
And what I'm talking to you today about is an e-mobility project.
But we've also had some commercial projects in industry.
The built environment.
And actually our goal, our dream is that this all comes together.
So for instance we're working on heating now.
The energy flexibility of heating.
And heating and e-mobility somehow happen right next to each other.
So that's where we want to go.
And Flexmeasures itself has a UI.
And I'm just showcasing that here.
But in our project right now, in this V2G Liberty project that wasn't really being used.
So what we want is for Flexmeasures to be a back end that you talk to through APIs.
And you usually build your own user interfacing flexible service.
Or you integrate what Flexmeasures helps you with into your existing service.
That's actually what we did with V2G Liberty.
So that's actually a kind of typical home assistant look for your dashboard.
I think we have the goal to bring our own style into that when we have the help.
But that's what you get.
And you can see what your car is doing, what's the charging power right now, what's the state
of charge.
And then we come into the more interesting or self-built features.
I will talk about this in another slide.
But this basically shows you the state of charge that happened in blue.
And what Flexmeasures has advised to happen with that in the upcoming hours.
And the energy price.
Here you have the ability as a user to simply say, I don't want this.
Stop the automation.
Or just charge the car right now.
I don't care about the optimal result.
You see if you've reserved the car.
And that's where our partner, Positive Design, came in to rethink with us, well, if we get
to design a V2G application, what do we want to experience when we use it?
And these are the goals.
It should basically, you want to be happy that it's there for a few weeks.
But then you want to stop thinking about it every day.
It should just happen.
And you might look at your end result and be happy.
And of course, it needs to be ready for you to do trips.
At least trips, let's say, groceries, hospital, go to a nearby town, which in the Netherlands,
of course, is quite easy.
So Utrecht, Amsterdam, for instance, works with 20% of charge.
Yeah.
And CO2 saving and cost saving, of course, are the goals.
You can really put numbers on.
Yeah.
Let's go one level deeper in the detail here.
I'm not sure it was all clear.
I already said the state of charge history will be shown to you in blue.
And then it's shown to you what the planning would be.
So here you can see a bit, if you look at the price in gray, that in the future, you
will charge your battery because the price is low.
You will discharge because there's a higher price later.
And you do that twice, actually, in that day.
And the new feature, as I said earlier, is that we're also plotting the CO2 intensity
on the grid.
That's going to happen in those hours.
That's something we are basing on the scheduled coal and gas power for the upcoming days.
Of course, there's also professional services for that.
Somebody in the earlier talk mentioned electricity map.
I think that's in the capital tool.
That's a third-party integration.
For cost reasons, we basically developed our own version of that.
And what's interesting, of course, is you see there's a slight correlation.
And we actually have a plot somewhere where we looked at the whole year from our data
and checked.
So is low carbon intensity, does that kind of correlate to lower prices?
Because in that moment, you have a lot of sun and wind on the grid, which have zero
marginal costs.
So that can happen.
And in the day ahead prices, of course, there's an economics that makes that complex.
But it does actually happen during the day.
During the day, you see a correlation in the night, not yet.
So here's one or two features of this application in V2G Liberty.
For instance, you come home from some trip.
You connect the car.
V2G Liberty talks to the charger and asks, so what's the deal with the car right now?
What is the state of charge?
It comes back as below 20%.
And then there's only one course of action.
We have to get up back to those 20%.
So that's just a simple fallback that gets you to 60 to 80 kilometers.
And when you've outlived your range anxiety, that should be OK.
And another feature I've shown in the UI before as well, you can go to your calendar on your
phone.
And that's where Next Cloud comes in here.
I'm a personal company where I'm next cloud users.
And that's why I was so happy to bring Next Cloud in this as well.
But it's basically just used for the agenda integration.
You can use Google Calendar if you need to.
That's no problem.
So you make your own agenda for your car.
And you create an entry in the agenda for your car that you're going on a road trip,
let's say, tomorrow at 8 o'clock.
And that will be picked up by V2G Liberty.
What's nice, you see here the mobile view.
I showed the desktop view before.
But Home Assistant even gives you something that looks really well on your mobile app.
Which is basically the same widgets just rearranged.
So then this will show up.
V2G Liberty will know about that reservation.
Will contact Flexmeasures automatically.
Flexmeasures will realize, oh, there's a new constraint coming in.
I need to recompute everything.
And that will change.
So here you see State of Charge will go up to 100.
Trying to avoid that price peak there in the middle.
Do it cost efficiently.
All right, so where are we now?
This project.
So it's working nice.
First thing that comes to mind now that the other enthusiasts being on board it, the installation
effort is still a bit high.
We have written it all out on that V2G Liberty.
It's not up to me, but as a couple steps you need to install your Home Assistant and make
that plugin work.
So there we can have some low hanging fruits in Home Assistant.
You can basically have an actual plugin that is downloadable and updates itself and all
that.
You do have configurations to make in a file.
That could be a wizard.
There's some stuff there.
It really helps us also with Flexmeasures to see if it runs in the background.
What kind of monitoring do we need?
It's really helpful.
Some people are installing Flexmeasures themselves as well.
So that's really, when you're really a techy enthusiast.
I will briefly go into some earnings or economical results.
So here's some hints that sometimes you have a day where there was huge price spreads and
your car basically sat at home the whole day.
And then you can really have a great day with earnings above the 10 euros in the Netherlands.
Good to keep in mind, energy flexibility is only usable if your asset is there and you're
not using it.
So if you take your car for long rides every day, well, there's less time to do something
with it and then you have less earnings.
So actually this user is making a lot of kilometers actually.
So here's a report from, I think this is 10 months of data.
And this is an overview where you really see how much has been charged and discharged.
So this is actually large parts of these kilowatt hours have actually been charged just to save
them and give them back to the grid at a better time.
This is where a lot of policymakers put high hopes on, of course, that cars will work as
batteries so that the grid can use and carry energy at the best times.
Well, there's a big Excel spreadsheet behind this, but if you just look at the bottom line,
that you would see they have driven their car for 3,000 kilowatt hours and paid 200
euros for that.
It's a pretty good price.
And you could compare with scenarios, so what if I had just a fixed cost contract from a
year ago?
You wouldn't get that today.
You arrive at some price.
As you all know, these numbers, they change so fast these days.
And you got before the Ukraine crisis already lots of movement in the markets after that
more.
So this is difficult, I think, to make these look at these as hard facts, like how many
euros will I save if I install this in 2023 or 2024?
I will not subscribe on the number there.
But there are savings.
And there are some other people making these calculations also on a more higher level.
But it's nice to have an actual project.
This has really happened.
We can dive deeper into the data.
So if anybody's interested, let us know.
And of course, another one, a part of the cost is that the V2G capable chargers are
currently much more expensive.
But I think the difference is coming down soon.
Right.
So what we will do, the installation I already mentioned, updating V2G Liberty if you have
it running and we have a new version, that can be easier.
We want to actually show you KPIs.
What did I save in money or CO2, let's say, last month?
I think per day can also work.
Now we have more users, enthusiasts who installed it at home and rerun it.
So the learning curve is going up right now in the sense of how much information we get.
It's great.
And it's going to be an interesting year with more things to support.
I'm not sure what kind of things this project should support, the V2G Liberty project.
It potentially has to do with demand from the community.
And of course, if chargers actually support OCPP, then that's just a great idea.
And on the FlexMeter side, that's something I also know the near future a bit.
I already mentioned that we are tackling immobility in projects like this, but also heat in other
projects and we don't look at the built environment.
This has to come together.
So our big next challenge is to really model the energy flexibility from these two usages
of energy combined and make one computation about a building or a site that uses heat
and uses immobility as two big, flexible power demands and come up with one optimization
and then actually automate that.
So that's our next big milestone.
And the other thing that's really important, of course, to mention is network congestion.
That's the network operators are coming up with ideas how a project like this, flexible
consumers can do their part.
So for instance, can stop their demands in a specific moment and in a specific region,
which would help on the lower and medium parts of the grid.
And that's also for us really on the map.
This is almost at the end.
Of course, we need to hear questions, but of course, for people to get in contact.
And I'm just listening to the best contact points for each of the projects.
For V2G Liberty, that's just come to the GitHub project and interact there.
Flexmeasures itself has more channels that you can contact us on.
We listed them here in the read the docs, for instance, through LF energy, there are
ways.
I do have, I think I have two minutes.
So one thing I have on the very last slide before I close is something we built in Flexmeasures
recently because if you talk about projects like these, basically after they happen and
you just summarizing what happened, they don't really come alive.
Because what actually happens and what we do is that throughout the day, new situations
arise all the time.
New circumstances like the car comes back, it has a completely new state of charge.
It could be lower, maybe they charged on the way, it's higher.
You don't know.
This is a new situation, so we need to recompute.
And in each of these situations, you also need to have a different set of forecasts.
So you ask yourself, it's this point in time, I was asked to recompute.
And I look at the set of forecasts, what do I know now about the state of things?
So maybe not all the devices have sent me everything yet.
There's always delays, there's always lags in IoT applications.
In the future, which forecasts do I have now available?
And that's what I mean with it doesn't come alive, right?
And let's see if it works.
Yeah.
We made a UI that uses JavaScript so you can travel through time basically.
So imagine that that bar is now, you hit that button, and we have kept the old schedules,
we have kept everything that's old, and we know when we knew it.
That's how we can travel through time.
And when we stop it anywhere, we know what we knew at the time.
So let's say we knew the day ahead prices.
You can see the day ahead prices on top coming in in batches, for instance.
And then the new schedules, that's a red dotted line also.
All right.
Let me stop in time and if there's any questions.
All right, there's a few, but who decides on the order?
Well, let's just start on my left.
I think that V2D Liberty.
Can you repeat the question?
Oh yeah, sure.
The question was if this has been built for one car or if there's the opportunity to have
multiple cars at the same location on a charging station supported.
And V2G Liberty has right now been built for one household with one car, which is expandable
in principle through some work.
And Flexmeasures itself has a solver that could also schedule multiple cars.
So that's not a technical problem on that side.
I have a question about the price spread that you talked about.
You optimize on day ahead prices and as you know, day ahead prices are a result of what
the energy suppliers predicting that customers will do the day ahead.
Yet by what you're doing, you're changing that behavior.
So inherently you're not doing what the supplier has bought for you on the day ahead market.
So then you can imagine if thousands of people are doing this, then of course the suppliers
need to change the way they are forecasting and get this at this loop.
Have you thought about how to solve that issue?
Yes.
So the question is that for the day ahead prices, the energy suppliers make a forecast
usually or traditionally what all the consumers will consume.
Aggregated over thousands of consumers, they get a nice curve and they try to buy that.
Now if the consumers react to that price, you have a loop, somehow a more dynamic system.
The question was if I have thought about it.
Yes, of course.
It's super interesting.
There's two thoughts.
One is that there's now a couple of providers like that in the Netherlands and I think they
basically adjust for that.
They would assume that a bunch of their customers do act flexible.
They might have to add a model for that, a behavioral model, economics behavioral and
try to get it right.
On the other hand, I think that some, there's going to be more energy suppliers because
I know of a company in the Netherlands that is basically helping larger companies become
an energy supplier.
So they don't have, it's basically energy supply as a service so you can brand your
own energy supply contract.
And some of the organizations I've talked to think about adjusting their price signal
themselves.
So they buy something on the day ahead market, but that's not the price they give to you.
They give you a different profile to try to sort that out.
Yeah, it could be that you're not doing as much money on the market, but now you add
services.
Let's go on.
I was talking about hardware.
So can you repeat the question?
Do you mean the Everest project?
Well, we are both in Linux energy foundation so we know about each other.
So that would be a way out.
The question.
I haven't found it yet when you did that project that was before our time.
Everything's super new.
And the question was for the audience online that there's the Everest project and they
also have open source hardware, although that's not the core of the company, but they offer
that and they had a great talk this morning.
So that could help, of course.
So that's a great opportunity for the community, for anybody, maybe for us to combine these
two.
I don't know.
Especially young companies have to sprint.
It's difficult.
I want to also get some part of the...
I think we're out of time.
We are out of time?
I'll be answering questions in the chat if there's something burning or right now in
person afterwards in the break.
Thank you.