Okay, awesome to see there are so many people here.
Really cool that there's big interest in the energy topic.
My name is Frederik Stuhl and I'm from Aljondur which is a grid operator and I will be talking
about Open Staff today.
First of all, I put here in the graph, this is a load profile.
So the energy load somewhere in the grid and you can see how it fluctuates over time.
Sometimes it's positive, sometimes it's negative.
This means whether there's netto production or netto consumption.
And now the question is, or you could ask, if we are at the red line right now, what
will be the load in the future?
And that's what we want to predict and if you're interested in that then you can use
Open Staff because Open Staff means short-term energy forecasting.
Okay, let's zoom out a bit first and before I go into a bit more detail about what Open
Staff does, first I want to talk about, I gave a short introduction about why this is relevant.
I don't have hours so I have to keep it short but there's a lot to talk about here.
But I want to start out with this picture and it's actually quite cool because I think
the last presentation talked about flexible energy that consumers can use and this is
one of the many things that are changing in the energy sector.
So consumers have flexible products that also start producing.
Consumers also have solar panels.
Your local farmer might have a wind turbine somewhere.
We have big wind parks on the sea.
So there's all kinds of developments going on right now that make it harder for grid
operators to forecast what's going to happen tomorrow or even the day after tomorrow.
And I'll put this picture here because all the things that I mentioned you can see right
there and probably in the future it's only going to get harder and harder.
We're now going to focus on the renewable energy part because it's also quite impactful.
As you can see on this graph here, this is for the Netherlands, the percentage of renewable
energy production.
And you can see that in just a couple of years, like five years, it has more than doubled
the electricity percentage that has been produced by renewable sources.
And renewable sources don't produce at a constant load, of course, they change all the time
depending on weather.
And this means it's harder to forecast.
And to put that into perspective, I have another slide here.
And this is a typical consumption profile.
If you have your local neighborhood, then this is what the energy load will often look
like.
So you have the five peaks, which means it's a peak for every day and then in the weekend
it's a bit lower.
You can see the dips, these dips in the middle of the day, that's because there's a couple
of solar panels on some roofs.
It still looks easy to predict.
If you go to other places where there's way more renewable energy, you can see these energy
profiles change dramatically.
So here you can see a profile for a big solar park.
You can see these huge negative peaks, which on some days are there and some days they
are not.
Probably that's a cloudy day, so there's no or less energy generated.
And this is an energy profile for a big wind farm, which you can see is, well, seems hard
to predict because there seems no real...
Why are you always negative?
Yeah, so a negative energy means that the consumer or the customer is giving back to
the grid.
So then it's negative for us.
If it's positive, it means...
It means the negative number.
Sorry?
Our sunny day is the negative number.
Yeah, exactly.
So if it means a big negative peak, it means the customer is producing a lot of energy.
So it's just a convention.
You could also switch the sign, but you have to choose one convention.
It's power, not energy.
Megawatts?
Yeah, power.
Yeah.
So is this a site which uses electricity and also has solar?
Because otherwise, how can it be using power?
Yeah, so it's not just one site.
It's more like a general profile for...
Like a substation for the grid operator, but connected to it is a lot of solar.
Okay, so there's load and there's also production.
Yeah, exactly.
So on all of these, there's load and production.
But yeah, I just wanted to share this feeling.
So this can be difficult.
And this also leads to problems.
And this is two maps of the Netherlands and the colored areas are the areas where Aleander
is currently active.
And on the left is energy consumption and on the right is energy production.
And this map shows if you're a new customer and you want to be connected to the grid,
if it's red, it's probably difficult because there's no more room.
According to the Dirge law, the energy grid is full over there.
And you can see that this is for huge areas in the Netherlands and also large areas on
the consumption side.
And of course, Aleander is doing everything they can to solve this by building new cables
and new substations, but this takes time, a lot of time.
And we don't have the time, as you can see in the graph before.
So I don't have that one.
But I assume it's very similar because we're not the only one who are having these issues.
So how can we solve this?
Well, one important thing is that we need grid insight.
And therefore, this also includes forecasts.
So transmission forecasts.
And these are important for all three parts in electrical grid.
So all three parties.
So for customers, for DSOs, such as Aleander, and for TSOs, such as Tenet, which control
the high voltage grid.
Using these forecasts, operators can try to maintain grid safety and grid balance and
can give customers as much electricity as they want and as they need because the need
is high.
With these forecasts, we can also enable smart solutions.
And I put here two brochure pictures of those solutions.
One of them is a pilot flex power, which was in Amsterdam, which was about charging electrical
vehicles and charging them faster if it's possible and not charging them as fast if
it's not possible.
We at Aleander supplied forecasts for this project.
And another platform is the GOPAX platform, which is like a trading platform for electricity
where customers can trade with operators to either consume or to produce energy flexibly.
And this is also being used right now at Aleander and we also provide a forecast for that.
So it's no longer working.
So let's use.
So now let's talk about OpenStuff again, because that's why I'm here.
I'm going to give a short introduction to OpenStuff and then I'm just going to give
a short demo about OpenStuff, how you can make a forecast.
And also want to talk a bit about using OpenStuff in operational settings.
So first of all, the primary thing OpenStuff can help you with is that it's just a complete
machine learning pipeline.
So I'm just going to give a short list of what it can do.
It handles input validation, such as like checking whether your data is complete.
It has feature engineering.
So it automatically calculates for you lag features or other features that are based
on input features.
So for example, if you input it with wind speed, it can calculate wind turbine power
output for you, or the same for direct normal irradiance.
Next it is some kind of intelligent train validation split of the time series.
It has support for multiple types of regressors.
So right now we have, for example, XGBoost, which is at Alejandro, the most commonly used
one.
But we also had a collaboration with Sonyo, which added Proloft to OpenStuff.
And we also have support for probabilistic forecasts.
So that means not just one line, but quantiles.
And unless it has integrated the model and artifact storage using MLflow.
So what does this all mean then?
Let's go to an actual demo.
So on this up here.
That's a low resolution.
Let's zoom out.
It's a bit too much.
Okay.
So I'm just going to walk you through an example or how you could make a forecast.
So first we need to make some kind of compare object that's just what you have to feed OpenStuff.
Let's close this.
So let's run this line.
Next I put some example input in this project so we can load it.
And we can visualize it.
So as you can see here, well, this is upon a state of frame.
And here we have the load and we have a lot of predictors.
Well, some of these, well, the names should make sense.
So for example, the amount of variation predicted by the K nearby or the temperature of these
predictors are already in this example data.
So if we have this, I can also plot it for you.
You can see, well, this is another power profile.
Okay.
So now imagine you have this and you want to know, well, what's next?
Then first we need to train a model.
So OpenStuff has a train model pipeline which basically this, all those things I just mentioned.
So we can just call the pipeline and let's hope the live demo does not fill me.
It will take about 15 seconds, I think, to train the model and store it.
So you can see some info about what it's doing.
And it's stored.
So let's have a look.
Digital flow comes with an interface so we can directly see that we train a model.
So right here, this was the run.
Let's hope this works.
I see that my internet is no longer working.
So apparently this, then this figure doesn't work.
All right, I'm not showing it.
This is the MLflow interface and you can see that we just trained a model.
You can also click on the model on the train run.
This is just MLflow and you can see a bit more information about what happened during
the training.
Next, of course, we want to make a prediction.
So again, OpenStuff has a pipeline for that so we can just say, okay, I want a prediction.
So it's loading the model and using data to create a prediction and then we can visualize
that as well.
And then we have a graph right here.
So this is the forecast that it made for the next.
Well, this was in some example data in 2021, but about 48 hours of forecast.
That's OpenStuff in practice.
Let's go back to the presentation.
To this slide.
Yeah, so well, this flow has been a manual flow, but of course in reality, at least for
if you're a grid operator, you want to do this in an operational setting.
So this means that you want to do daily forecasts for a lot of different locations with all
kinds of configurations.
And OpenStuff also comes with a so-called reference implementation about how you could
do this.
So this is a picture of what you would have to do.
So we have OpenStuff right here, which is basically I just showed you the training and
forecasting pipeline.
Then we have another package, which is called OpenStuff DBC database connector, which can
connect to a database.
And we use MySQL and InfluxDB to store all the data required to run it operationally.
And we also have a Hafana dashboard built upon this database stack, so we can also see
what's going on.
And again, as I already have shown, you can use MLflow to keep track of all the models
and all the runs that are being done to see what's going on.
So I want to show this dashboard as well.
So let's put it up here.
Maybe some other ones.
So this dashboard is just example data, so it's not our real dashboard.
But here you can, for example, see some load that was there on the system.
And you can also see that, for example, this is not just one area, but it has a sum of
two systems, which is quite common in electrical grid that you have a lot of measurement points
that you have to add together with different signs.
And you can see, for example, here's then a live forecast of this location as well.
You can also see plots of the feature importance that are obtained during training of the model.
You can see which data the model has been trained over here.
These plots are really small.
Here you can see them.
So it's a dashboard where you can see everything that Oberstaff does for every location that
you could be interested in.
When you talk about forecasts, are you, within the forecast, also taking other forecasts,
like the weather forecast into account, or are you forecasting that yourself?
No, so we use all kinds of data, and the weather forecast is...
The question is whether we are using other forecasted data or whether we forecast those
forecasts as well, like whether we forecast the weather ourselves.
And the answer is that it depends a bit.
So in general, we use the weather forecasts for multiple sources.
And also, for example, price, like the day ahead pricing.
So we use those data.
But sometimes we also feed the prediction itself, or we feed one prediction into another
prediction.
So I mean, you can play around with that.
Yeah, you have to feed Oberstaff with all the predictors that you wanted to know.
Okay, let's move on.
I've got one last slide, and that's basically the key information.
Yeah, because that was my presentation.
So I put all the info you might be interested in on this slide.
And if there's any questions, then feel free to ask.
Yes.
So the information is really useful, but what is the purpose for the grid operator?
What is the use of the grid operator to make of this information?
Is it for congestion management?
Is it for some kind of load shedding?
What is the role of this exercise?
So I think the question is, why would the grid operator be interested in forecasts,
I guess is what you're asking.
So there's many reasons, but I think you already mentioned congestion management is indeed
an important reason, but also, well, grid insight.
So yeah, the more congestion management is going to be used for the grid, the more important
it is also to maintain grid safety.
And grid safety is not just one operator.
We're all connected to multiple grid operators.
So everyone has to communicate what they are going to do and what they expect the energy
flow to be the next day.
So every operator can decide to do what's necessary to maintain grid safety.
So that's what I mentioned before, the transmission forecasts.
Every operator has to communicate to everyone who is connected to what they expect the load
to be on the next day.
I see that my time is up.
So I'm afraid I have to answer the questions in the chat.
Yeah.
Or in the hallway.
I think for time management, we have to learn from these talks, see if we can manage to
keep a couple of more minutes for questions.
Sorry.
Thank you very much for listening.