So, our museum is located in Namur, so it's not far from here, so if you have some time
to come, you're welcome.
So, we have different mission, of course.
One of it is to preserve all machines, to show them to the public, and also to study
those machines, to keep understanding them.
So, I might talk more precisely about that.
And actually, why this machine?
Actually we have a big collection, part of our museum is actually a big mechano-graphic
collection, you can see it's here.
So, we have a whole bunch of machine, electro-mechanical machines that are still being maintained.
Unfortunately we don't have the bull, Gemma Trois, it's very rare, but it was connected
with those machines.
So, we have many documentation about those machines, and we were interested to study
that machine more specifically.
So, I will go through the historical context, make you discover the machine, and then go
into it to try to emulate it, looking at some existing emulators, and then detailing our
own emulator and what we learned with it.
So, let's go back in time, so you know we are here now, in 2023.
So, if we go back, how long is it, 70 years ago, in the 50s, just after World War I, the
first generation of computer was developed.
So, at that time the technology was very different than today, because there were no integrated
circuits, there were no CPU, microprocessor, they were developed in the 1980s.
In the 70s, there were no TTL circuit, there were no transistors, there were no magnetic
core.
Actually, when you really want to build a computer, you had technology like vacuum tubes
and delay lines to try to store some memory and drums.
So, it was really a very different technology, and of course you can imagine the memory was
very small.
And so, another point is that at that time, well, most of the processing was made because
of course there was automation before the computer, so most of the automation was done
through electromechanical machines.
So, tabulating machine, you know it was developed in the end of the 19th century with the, oh,
with the tabulating machine and then it became the IBM company.
And you can see here that there was some kind of transition between that area and those
machines, those computers that were starting to be developed.
And actually, the interesting point is that one that I will show you actually, at the
beginning it was not really a computer, it was still some kind of auxiliary calculator
for tabulating machine, that one that you can see in our museum.
And after, actually, it began to improve and the dependency between the machine were reversed.
So, the gamma 3 became the computer and the tabulating became the peripheral.
So, you can see other machine after, of course, you can see that will develop also a gamma
60, gamma 30 machine, but in the second generation, so I will not focus on that.
So, maybe in the next for them.
And so, how did we study the machine?
Of course, we have documentation at the museum.
There is also a number of existing examples of that machine, one in Orgé where it was
built by Beaul, in Grenoble.
They acquired one and they preserved it and one in Frankfurt.
So, of course, we don't have one, but we have those documentation and we have also many
documentation that was also provided by Acornis, which is another museum located in Grenoble.
And there are a few emulators, so we'll come back to that later.
Have a look at the hardware.
So, as I told you, it's a first generation computer.
It's based on vacuum tube delay lines.
Actually, the code was stored in a connection panel.
So, you can see it on the top there.
So, in order to program it, actually, you had to plug the instruction to say, well,
the first instruction, it has four characters, but the first character, it's that exact
decimal code.
The second one is that code and so on.
So, it's really like the spaghetti coding.
And for that reason, actually, the spaghetti coding was also used in a tabulating machine.
So, it was the way to code at that time.
And that's also the reason why we cannot really call it a computer in that form because it
does not follow the von Neumann architecture because in that architecture, you have to
have the code inside the main memory.
Although some old that panel was memory mapped, so you could consider it like some kind of
read-only memory.
What about the memory?
Memory itself, actually, it was only seven registers.
And in order to keep the information, actually, the information, it was the equivalent of
six bytes, so it's 12 characters of four bits.
It was just circulating in a line with a regeneration system, so it's a LC circuit.
And for just one word, so for six bytes, you can see the device here, it's more than eight
kilograms.
So, you imagine the start of the...
It was really very big.
About the computation, it was also based more on the data, so we'll not go into all the
details.
It was mostly addition and subtraction, as I will see.
The multiplication and division were implemented through iterative addition and subtraction.
And what about the frequency?
The frequency was 2.5 hertz.
Why that?
Actually, it could go...
The inner could go faster, but it was just because it was synchronized with the mechanical
machine that we've bunched car, so it was limited by that part.
And you can see also there is a nice drawer.
It's really easy to open, of course, for the maintenance because when a vacuum cube had
a problem, you had to replace it and it was designed for that.
So is it a computer or a calculator?
Well, in French, we have different tapes, but as I told you, we cannot really consider
it as a computer first time because of that.
It was not following the von Neumann architecture, and it was really designed as auxiliary machine
for the tabulating.
So as you can see there, a quote from a guy who designed the machine in 1953.
So it's really an extension.
And the good point is that that computation was so fast that there was no delay by the
calculation, so it was really transparent for the tabulating.
And actually at that time, well, the programs inside the machine were more like auxiliary
computation that were augmenting the capability of the tabulating machine.
And there there were evolutions.
That's the interesting point.
There was a version, of course, that first version is only adding a substring integer,
so there was a version that was able to do floating points.
And then in 1957, there was a dynamic extension.
That's the interesting point.
It's about 100 kilobytes, and it could store the program.
So from that time, we can say then that it's really the first French computer, and it's
also the transition between the electromechanical device, the electromechanical area, and the
computer area.
Also, another interesting point is that those first computers were not using binary or hexadecimal
representation.
They were still computing in decimal.
So it's interesting because I found it's in front of this transition there.
And there is a whole discussion about should we use decimal or should we use binary or
hexadecimal for computation.
So there was some advantage, benefit, and some disadvantage.
So you can see the advantage.
Two figures, zero and one.
It's really powerful for the relay.
It's ideal to map.
And for the disadvantage where binary, it's become very long, very long word, and we need
to translate back and forth with the decimal.
So the conclusion, it's quite funny.
We will use semi decimal, which actually is the name for binary coded decimal, and then
introduce those coding on a four bit for the binary coded decimal.
So that was for the first version.
Also they came back on that decision and actually an update for the drum extension was able
to support the binary mode.
So what do we have as memory?
As I told you, we have those registers.
Actually, we have seven main registers.
You can see here a bit more because there were extensions.
So a register is one word of 12 digits, 12 characters.
So those four bit.
So it's actually six bytes.
So the main memory was only 42 bytes.
So you see it's very, very limited.
And if you look at the full architecture here, the full, the gamma 3 with all the extensions,
you can see on the top left, the panel.
The main register are on the left.
The top one, the M1 actually is the only one where you can read and write.
So all the computation will be performing that one.
And the other one, M2 to M7 will be used as a register to read operands.
And the instruction you can see, the decoding of the instruction, the structure of the instruction
is composed of four parts.
I will detail them after.
It's called TO, AD, OD, and OF.
And the rest are extensions.
So this is more memory.
So you can switch those registers with those ones.
And the drum extension can also map on those octets.
So you can load a part of program from the drum to those parts and then execute them
into the computer.
So about the instruction set, you can see that there are four parts.
So the first is quite natural.
It's just the type of operation.
So you can have addition, subtraction.
I will detail after.
The second part is also quite natural.
It's just the address.
It means which operand we will use.
So for the addition, for AOE, we can see it means M4, the register number four.
And what's a bit different and word is that then we have two other pieces of information
in the instruction that will tell you which range in the register you will manipulate.
Because the reason is that the memory was scarce.
And so if you wanted to store two different information in the same register, you can
then address one part of it.
And you could really select if it was two bits and then 10 bits and things like that.
So we can see here a very simple addition.
So I can record it with you.
So this means a transfer from one register to the accumulator, so the M0 register.
So it's from M4.
So you can see in M4 we have two parts, A and B. So A is from six to nine and B is from
one to five.
So the first thing is that we will load the part six to nine into the accumulator.
Then we will ask to perform an addition with what we can find in the same register four
in part one, five.
You can see one, five here.
And you can see that as an internal flag, it also remembers the part that is used for
the shift part that it should use for the addition.
And then you can perform the addition and we'll have A plus B inside the register.
And then you will put back the result.
So it's a reverse instead of B or it's OB to store back the result in M4.
And of course, here you have to think, oh, I've done an addition.
So maybe there is one category overflow.
So you can see here that we have provisioned one byte more to be able to store the result
back.
So you can see all the, in mental gymnastics you have to do to be able to program with
that kind of range in the registers.
So it means that when you are coding, you have to use that kind of sheet.
You can see, of course, the mnemonic.
You see here the translation where you have to think about those range and you have then
to facilitate that for the range, you have to allocate your range and reason about your
range also on this sheet.
So you can see here the problem is computing that formula.
And then you will just perform the different calculation, multiplication, shift to one
to have the right power and then divide by the square root of three.
Okay, quickly, this is the full instruction set.
As you can see, it's not very regular.
Well, a natural thing is that no operation is still zero.
It was already zero.
You have operations to different kinds of jumps, there was an inner flag to remember
how to jump.
You have different memory transfers.
I will not go into details.
Of course, to set memory to zero or to load a value to make the transfer between different
kinds of registers.
There is a logical and.
I didn't find any logical or.
I don't know if there was one.
It's a bit weird, but okay.
Different comparison and then of course the most important one from ABCDEF, the addition
and the arithmetic operation.
And you can see there are two flavor for the multiplication and division because there
was one what's called reduced multiplication and reduced division that was faster but that
we will not operate on a double register because of course if you have a big tool, the result
of multiplication can of course take twice as much as space.
Okay, so this is the code.
So it summarizes the whole instruction set and it reflects the complexity of its organization.
You can point just three things.
First, it's called ordenator.
So in French, the name was ordenator but the name ordenator was coined one year after for
a IBM machine.
So it was not, it didn't exist yet.
So you have to think about all that.
You can see here the different arithmetic operation for 12 to, well A2F, so 12, 13,
14, 15.
And you can see the order is not always in the order.
The seven is presented higher because just the shift and operation and the two is not
represented because it was an extension for the drum.
Okay, let me go quickly.
So about existing emulator.
So this one was written in 1995 by Vincent Gauguin, sorry, in x86 assembly code.
And it still runs but, well, thanks for the emulators because you need those bugs to run
it.
We don't have the source code.
You can just see there but it's just emulating everything.
So it's quite good, complete.
And you can see there that it's just loading some information.
So it's just loading 0, 9, 4, 2, 7 in the memory tree register.
And then you can, well, there is a drum emulated and then you have a number of programs on
the drum you can try.
A more recent one, it's a variable online.
So this one is very interesting because it's very well documented.
And you can even play with the panel.
There is a full console where you can step in.
And actually it was one of the sources of inspiration of our work because that one was
in Java 6 and our is in Java so we kind of transposed and first studied that code.
There is also an extension, a visualization, 3D visualization, which is funny because
you can explore inside the machine.
You can see here the connection and there are big cables to connect the machine with
the tabulating.
Okay about the emulation structure, of course, what we have modeled is all the components.
So you have the machine, you have the different kind of memories, banal memories, it's just
the registers, different series, groups, and then a special one which is the panel which
is actually, as you can see, memory mapped to one of the series.
And of course you can also have connected machines and the drum.
Then of course the whole instruction set, you can see there the modeling, the way the
instructions are structured depending on the kind.
If it's for drum transfers, all the arithmetic operations have some common parts so we have
some here.
And of course there is some execution management and tests and you can see the code there on
GitHub.
And what's interesting from also the emulation point of view, of course, all operations will
have to specify the different information.
So for the addition, this is an inner operation just to show you how it's implemented.
So of course you have to specify the range where you are performing the addition.
And this is quite standard implementation where you just loop over the different bit
and then you propagate the query.
What is interesting is just that you have the base so that code would work both for
the binary and for the decimal implementation actually, variant of the machine.
So this is trying to mimic the whole operations.
Another one very simple is just to use the Java operations.
For example, for the subtraction, we just translate everything in decimal, perform the
subtraction and then store the result.
There is only one thing that must be careful is that we have to use long in Java because
those 12 numbers are more than 32 bits in Java.
We skip the division.
So the current implementation, while we have our prototype just in Java, so we are just
using the Eclipse as an environment and running the test.
So this is just test.
We have a small interface, not yet finished.
And you can see here a quick code that just showed Fibonacci suite.
And while you can see the result here, I will not go into detail, but you can see there
is actually a loop, so there is a jump for 10 iterations and then you have the different
number.
You can see the number after a few iterations.
You have 13 and things like that which are being computed.
So it's working.
And now I will finish.
So what did we learn?
So it was quite funny and strange to look at that machine.
It's not so complex to code, but there are many, many implementation details you see
about those range manipulation.
And we still have a lot to explore.
For example, all the floating points, improving the user interface.
And of course, we have the start, so we would like to really to study what was used as code
at that time.
So in summary, it was very neat, it's still very rewarding from the technical, but also
from the historical and cultural point of view.
Thank you.
And if you have questions, you're welcome.
Some reference there about all the guys who have worked on that machine.
We have maybe five minutes for questions.
Yeah.
Simulate the core memory and the reading that was required to rewrite it again once you
read it.
So the question is about the read.
The core memory.
Simulating the reading of the memory.
So it's a good question because I don't know how to call this a simulator or an emulator,
but the component, well, the machine is quite, quite also at what we are emulating.
It's kind of an abstraction of the machine, I would say.
So one limitation is that we don't really know the physics of the reading.
So we are assuming that we can read reliably the information and that we don't have any
timing issue with the things that are bothering you.
But of course, we don't have a working machine to compare with.
So we can only compare with expected result or with what other, the older emulator is
delivering.
Actually, the older emulator had a problem.
We discovered there was a mistake discovered.
So it was corrected by the guy who's still maintaining it somehow.
But yeah.
So the point would be really to be able to study the electronic circuitry if we would
like to go to that level.
But we don't have one, sorry.
Yeah.
There's a question from the stream.
Is there a compiler for gamma 3?
A compiler?
Well, is there a compiler for the gamma 3?
So you could see, well, assembly code was, assembly language was invented two years before,
I think by Booth.
And the assembly was done manually at that time.
So at that time, the answer is no, there were no compiler.
But no, today, actually, the guys from McConit have developed a compiler from a language
that looks like Java, I think.
So you can, actually, yes, you can compile from that pseudo code language into the gamma
3.
Yeah, it was done.
I didn't try it, but I did.
Yeah.
Was the program done in the case with the wires spaghetti code?
Or could you load instructions from the drums?
The question is, was the program, the program that I showed was in code date, was executed
from the panel.
So the panel is just a way to specify the content of the memory.
It's the same, but just with wire.
But the emulator supports the drum.
The original machine, could it load in front?
Yeah, it could load instructions.
So the drum could contain instructions, or it could contain data.
Yeah.
Last question.
Do you have any detailed information about the cycle count of the initial instructions?
Yeah.
So the question is about the cycle count of the different instructions.
So we have time, timing about the addition, subtraction, and different kinds of multiplication.
So that's available.
And that's a good point because the emulator is not taking that into account.
So it would probably be a good point to try to reproduce that behavior.
Thank you very much.
So maybe a last time go.
Thank you.