All right, so yeah, our last speaker for today, for this year actually, is Cerman Gomez.
And this is his first time doing a talk in general, so he's very nervous.
He has a very low voice, so if you could stop breathing.
Okay, do you want to start now?
Okay, hello?
So this is a title of my talk.
It's a bit long, but the short version is at the bottom.
I'm just going to talk to you.
I spent some time a couple of years ago making a gimbal emulator, and I'm going to talk to you about it.
So wanting some introductions, but that's my name, and if you want to reach out to me after the conference,
those are some of the ways.
I work as a software engineer.
I don't work on emulators.
I use them sometimes, but it's not part of my work.
This is mostly just a hobby.
So I've done all of these on my own time, and I can emulate the gimbal camera as well.
So this is what I'm going to talk about today.
So points one, two, three are going to be...
I'm going to talk to you about my particular emulator, how you can run it if you want to do so.
And afterwards, I'm going to talk more generally about gimbal emulation and how you can build your own emulator.
I'll give some tips that I found that are useful for debugging.
And at the end, some lessons learned, and hopefully if there is time, some demo.
So this is what my target audience here is mostly...
for this talk is mostly going to be emulator beginners, emulator development beginners.
I find the gimbal to be quite beginner-friendly.
One of the reasons is because it's very heavily documented,
and there are other reasons as well that I'll get to later.
If you're interested in Rust and WebAssembly, you're going to see a use case.
And if you're just generally a fan of this device, then you might enjoy that also.
So why make this in the first place?
The main reason I'm sure many people here will relate, or people making emulators, is the nostalgia.
I used to own one of these, so I want to know how it works.
Another reason, more generally speaking, this system is very attractive to emulate
because there's a huge amount of software out there, so you can spend many hours
just trying games and seeing if they work.
And if they don't work, then you can spend many more hours trying to fix them.
And it's just something I do for fun.
I did it mostly... I don't work on it much these days, but every time I do, it's a lot of fun.
So it's made in Rust.
The selling points for Rust are performance and memory safe.
My main selling point is that it has a very useful package manager and build tool.
It's very quick to prototype things, and I was able to put this together very quickly, actually.
And one of the other main reasons I want to use it is because of WebAssembly.
The support in Rust is great, so you almost get WebAssembly for free if you use Rust.
The tools are very nice.
And it runs on the website because it's WebAssembly, it can run on the browser, so it's very portable.
That's my phone. That's my PC.
It also runs natively. It's not just WebAssembly.
So if you want to run it, these are the commands you need to run.
There's a native build, single command.
You give it the ROM and it will emulate it.
The web build is just a few more commands because you have to deploy a web application.
So it's just very straightforward. It just works.
And that's the link if you want to try it.
So I'm going to talk about the architecture and emulation.
So these are the two devices that I emulate.
The original game board came out in 1989.
It was extremely popular. It was designed to be as cheap as possible.
So lots of games were made for it, and it lasted close to 10 years.
There were a few revisions in between, but it was mostly the same system.
And then almost 10 years later, the Nintendo released the color version,
which has still a very similar shape.
And also internally, the system is also very similar.
So the game board color is like a superset of the original game board.
So these are the two devices that I target.
And I have to mention the game board advance.
It's a completely different system. It's ARM-based.
It was still backwards compatible, but it's very different under the hood.
So I don't support it for the time being.
So I'm going to talk about the architecture.
So if you open the original game board, you'll see a bunch of stuff.
But for emulation purposes, we only care about those three chips.
One of them has the CPU and the pixel processing unit,
and the other chips are memory.
So I'm going to limit this section to just talking about the CPU,
the pixel processing unit, which does graphics.
And at the end, to wrap it all up, I'll talk about the memory map.
Which is what allows the CPU and the pixel processing unit
to talk to each other, basically.
So some basic stats about the CPU.
It has 8-bit registers and 16-bit registers.
It can do 500 things, has 500 instructions,
a 16-bit address bus and an 8-bit data bus,
and it can run at two different speeds.
The original game board could only run at 4 MHz,
but the game board caller could choose between either of those two speeds.
So about the registers, some general information.
It has general purpose registers.
These are here for intermediate calculations.
There's also a flag register, which has information about
the last arithmetic instruction that they run.
So if you add two numbers together, or subtract numbers together,
and the result is zero, this register will tell you and other things.
The 16-bit registers are basically just the 8-bit ones,
but used in combinations of two.
Mostly just for pointers.
The general purpose ones, it has the normal program counter
with the address of in-memory of the next instruction.
A stack pointer for implemented subroutines,
and there's a global switch for interrupts.
It's boolean, so when you set it to zero,
the CPU will stop listening to interrupts,
such as problem presses, until you set it back to one.
So how can you model this in Rust?
It's very simple.
This is exactly what it looks like on mine.
The state is very simple.
It's just a few fields for the registers.
So I'm going to talk about instructions.
This CPU has 500 instructions.
It has your typical instructions that you would expect,
so memory reads and writes, arithmetic, and branch instructions,
so jumps and calling to subroutines.
Some of the instructions can be conditional using the F register.
On this website, you can see them color coded in a very nice table.
This is at the core of the CPU.
This is how you implement instructions.
You have to do three things.
First, you have to fetch the instruction from memory using the PC register.
Afterwards, you have to decode the instruction,
so that means figuring out what instruction to run
based on that byte that you just read.
You can do this with a, in C++,
you would use a switch statement.
In Rust, you can use a match statement.
After you decode the instructions, you have to run it,
so those are the three things you do.
You fetch the code and you run,
and you run it in a loop, and that's what the CPU does.
This is one example of an instruction.
The code is very simple.
This is a memory instruction.
I'm only going to comment on the return statement.
This particular instruction on the real CPU would take eight cycles of the clock,
and we need to keep track of this because afterwards,
we need this information to synchronize all of the emulator.
Otherwise, it will need to box,
so that's why I returned the number.
Another example of instruction,
an arithmetic instruction and XOR operation.
This one takes four cycles and it's arithmetic,
so it modify the contents of the F register.
You can look at how to implement every instruction on this PDF.
You do this for 500 times.
You might make mistakes,
but there are ways to fix those.
I'll get to those later.
So you do it 500 times and you will end up with
a massive match statement or a switch statement.
But the code inside of each of the branches is very simple,
but it's still error-prone.
This is an optional thing you can do,
because this is going to run very frequently.
It doesn't hard to turn that into binary search,
so you can optimize the code a bit using in Rust.
This is very straightforward using the match statements.
So that's pretty much the CPU.
I'm going to switch to the Pixel Processing Unit.
This is the chip responsible for graphics.
So the Game Boy had an LCD panel.
The size is 160 pixels by 144.
Total of four colors,
more on Game Boy color, of course.
It runs at roughly 60 Hertz.
The way graphics works on this particular system
is by a composition of three layers.
You have the window layer,
the sprite layer, and the background layer.
Then there are like the CPU has registers,
this device also has registers to program
the how you composite these layers together.
So I'm going to go layer by layer.
So the first layer is the window layer.
This is usually reserved for things like game stats.
It's fixed on the LCD,
you can move it around,
but the graphics within the layer are not movable,
they are constrained to a grid.
Can anybody guess this game?
Yes, Link's Awakening.
So that's Link. Link is a sprite on the sprite layer.
So sprites are basically freely movable objects on the LCD.
You can have 40 in total,
and they come in two different sizes,
programmable by registers again,
along with other things like color,
imposition, and orientation, and things like that.
Finally, the background layer,
what I think is the most interesting one.
It's basically a grid of 32 by 32 tiles.
The total size, each star is eight by eight,
so the total size is 256 by 256.
So it doesn't fit on the LCD screen,
but you can scroll it using registers.
Also furthermore, the scrolling wraps around,
so you can be clever and implement infinite scrolling that way.
So it cannot this.
So there are more registers.
I don't have time to talk about all of them,
but there's a link.
So by today's standards,
this graphic-wise, this system cannot do much,
but there are games that are quite clever using these limitations.
So this is one example.
It's not really a game,
it's more of a technical demo, but still.
So this particular example is using the background layer only,
and it's modifying the scrolling register.
So it's actually moving it around the screen.
However, it's changing the value of the register on every single line.
This accomplishes is like a vertical stretching effect.
At the same time, they are stretching the internal logo horizontally in memory.
You can see it right there.
In combination, these two things looks like they are assuming in the internal logo,
which is something that the Game Boy cannot do in hardware,
but they work around this by combining hardware and software.
So I think it's quite interesting.
There are many more examples of games being clever to this one.
So implementation-wise,
this pixel processing unit is a bit more tricky to implement than the CPU.
Because of that, it is a source of most of my bugs.
This game is easy to recognize.
It's tiny hot.
So the reason it's tricky to implement correctly is because we need to keep
the CPU and the pixel processing unit in constant sync.
That's the reason I was returning the number of cycles on each instruction before.
If you don't do it accurately enough,
it would lead to stuff like this happening.
However, I found that most games don't really care.
Most games are quite forgiving of inaccuracies.
Every now and then, you will encounter a situation like this.
In this particular example,
the rest of the game looks fine.
It's only the inter-screen that is glitchy.
I think this is one of the reasons why the Game Boy is
a good beginner-friendly emulation project
because you don't need to be super accurate to emulate most games.
This is how you would implement the synchronization.
This is how I do it.
So first, on each iteration step,
you implement, you run the CPU for an instruction.
It will give you the number of cycles that it will take.
Then you use that to synchronize the rest of the components.
So you feed it to the rest of the components so that they catch up to the CPU.
So you do this forever.
Basically, this loop right here is the core of this emulator.
It's where the emulator looks like.
There are a few things like getting the image from the screen and so on.
But conceptually, this is an emulator. It's very simple.
So I've talked about the CPU and the big processing unit.
Both have registers,
but they are separate things on the circuit board.
So the CPU needs to be able to modify the registers of the pixel processing unit.
The way this is done is through memory because
every register that is not a CPU register is exposed in memory.
So by reading and writing
particular values to a particular address in memory,
you can modify the registers of these devices.
In this, you can map the memory map a bit like this.
You have the cartridge right there.
The video RAM and work RAM are the same size because they
are those two chips on the circuit board, those two other chips.
They are the exact same chip.
There are other things.
The buttons themselves are inside of these registers IO.
So yeah, there are some regions that are a bit special.
You are not allowed to write to this region for some reason.
There are other details.
This link has a technical recommendation of the rest of the map in detail.
So implementing the memory is quite easy.
You just list every single component and every single register a bit like this.
So you get the cartridge, the video RAM,
pixel processing unit's registers,
the buttons, sound registers,
interrupt controller, and then you need to be able to read from them.
So based on the address range,
you route it to the appropriate device,
and you need a similar method for writing values.
Some of the values will be read only, so keep that in mind.
So at this point, maybe you'll have a working emulator,
but if it's your first emulators,
as it was my case,
then you'll run into bugs.
They can be a bit tricky compared to other types of software I found.
So there are a few strategies that I- Sorry.
So there are a few strategies you can follow in order to track them bugs.
The first one I could give is just because there's so much documentation about the Game Boy,
you can turn it into unit tests,
to unit tests, particular sections of the hardware.
The other reason why the Game Boy is so beginner-friendly,
is you can actually run the diagnostics.
There are available ROMs you can run,
and it will tell you where you have issues.
So if you make a mistake on the CPU, which is likely,
then this particular ROM will tell you what the mistake was.
You can also integrate this into your testing framework to run in
CIO for extra credit.
So the next one, the next step is debugging.
I'm going to show debugging using an example.
After you have an emulator,
the logical step is to build a debugger for it,
because it will allow you to see how it will teach you things about the games running,
but it will also teach you where you might be making mistakes.
So in this particular example,
when I run this game at the moment, it doesn't work.
So basically, this is what it looks like.
It just gives you a black screen,
so there's nothing going on.
But if you spend time making a debugger,
then you can start finding clues.
In this case, I spent some time just getting the instructions,
the registers, the disassembly, very useful.
In this particular example, thanks to that,
I know what the issue with this game is.
So it's reading a value from this address and expecting a value that is never there.
So this address corresponds to something called a DMA transfer.
What this tells me is that I have made a mistake in this emulation.
So I can go to that particular section of my project and fix it.
But I haven't fixed it yet because I found it quite recently.
Also, I found that it's already more fun to add
debugging features than it is fixing the issues themselves.
I think I'll be busy recently.
So that's the end of my technical talk,
and I'm going to finish with some conclusions.
This is my favorite glitch by the way.
Only happens when you set the name to a particular name.
This is very weird. So writing an emulator,
at least on a Game Boy emulator,
is the easy part of emulating Game Boy.
Like I said, there's tons of documentation,
and the hard part of the work has been done by
other people who have been kindly enough to write down their findings.
So I just have to read the information,
interpret it, and turn it into a program.
So I'll keep that in mind when I move to the next system to emulate,
because it might not be as easy.
So most games, as I said, are forgiving of inaccuracies.
This is more of an issue with my emulator.
Most games are forgiving of inaccuracies in the graphic,
so this is yet one other reason why it's friendly for beginners.
Finally, WebAssembly and Rust are great.
If you use Rust, using WebAssembly is very natural,
and the support is great.
I have a small demo. It runs on the browser.
So that's the LCD.
I'm also drawing the video memory and the color parts.
One of the things you can emulate on the Game Boy is,
it came with a camera.
So if you load the camera on this application,
it will request permission for the camera.
But I've shown the picture at the beginning.
So if you cancel the permission, it will still boot.
So it has a fallback. That's the Game Boy camera.
So it cannot get the webcam because I haven't given you permissions,
but you can still put the first demo in there.
So yeah. I don't know how to use this.
I think you can play games with it,
but I don't know how it works.
But that's the demo.
So that's it from me.
We got permission for like five minutes extra for questions.
So people, please leave quiet.
Can I just break in? I'm leaving immediately.
But if you go out or please continue your questions and your discussion,
please look around you and take any garbage that you see from the room here
and put it in the back.
If a lot of people help, it's not much work.
Otherwise, we will be here forever. Thank you.
I have a question. With the emulator,
is it easy to add like a three or more like the actual replay?
Like you can do unlimited drives and you can add other levels?
So the question was if I can
just to make sure that I understood the question correctly.
Can I modify it in such a way that I can mess with the logic of the game?
Was that?
Yes. Like actually playing garbage,
I can recognize when you have like three drives and you get built,
you get two drives and it is probably the memory location.
Okay.
That's the functionality that you can use.
Yeah. So the question was,
can I identify particular things happening on the different games?
Sorry?
Use that in trainers.
Do you know about trainers?
No, I don't.
To cheat basically.
Oh, so can I point?
You can change the value of a register,
actually play what the user had actually played.
You also had action.
I know GameShark again.
You can leave this right.
Yeah. So the emulator is,
so the question is,
can I implement something like a GameShark to cheat on games?
Yes, I could. The emulator is built as a library.
So you can use it as a library and read
arbitrary bytes to arbitrary addresses.
So you could potentially build something like that. Yes.
Was your first talk right?
Yeah.
Yeah. Well done.
Thank you.
Very good actually.
This is the last presentation I ate today.
You're welcome.
Thank you.
I also had a co-op
Yeah, you have a single loop where every hardware like
this is a single loop.
What?
I know, but this is a real part of the system.
No, my question was that you have a single loop
that has processes on the CPU.
Yes, it's, yeah.
What if you are emulating with Rust system
where you want to have different threads for different peripherals,
but they are all accessing the memory.
Will the Rust memory save you the fuel with that?
So can I use Rust to, can I run things in different threads
and would the first problems?
And probably yes, but that was a kind of worms I didn't want to open.
And also if the system was simple enough like this one,
you don't really need to optimize like that.
You can all run in a single thread.
But for a more complex device, sure,
I would have to investigate more on that.
But I didn't have to do that on this one.
Question, why did you pick Rust?
Was there any reason that you did not select C++?
I mean C++ also does well for some.
Yeah, why did I pick Rust over something like C++?
It's what I use Rust for my personal projects.
It's what I like using it.
It's what I like using.
And you know Rust better than C++?
I think I do, yeah.
And the processor is 6502 for a ZD?
So the question was what the processor is.
It's not a 6502.
I think it's a mix of a Psylog Z80 and an Intel 8080.
So it's like a combination of the two.
Something specific custom?
I think it is specific. I'm not really sure.
The audio is good today.
How is this thing recorded?
You split your match up into a binary set.
Did you actually benchmark that?
Because I thought the compiler would have just translated it into a job table.
On mic, you know.
And we're going to get kicked out.
I'll be honest, I didn't benchmark that.
That is why they're very loose in change.