Hello.
Hello, yeah, sorry.
As the slide says, so my name's Neil Coffey.
I'm a Java developer.
Of course I'm a Java developer with that surname.
And so this is a talk about a little side project that I started a couple of years ago.
It was kind of, I was just keen to see in Java how far I would get with developing an
emulator.
This is the first emulator that I've developed from scratch.
And it kind of started, you know, had a bit of time, you know, we had a lockdown and I
kind of thought, well, what do I need to write an emulator?
Well, one of the things I might try and do to start with is get a ROM reader to kind
of start from scratch.
And then I found, I don't know if you've heard, but my country left the EU a couple of years
ago.
And so I actually found it hard to source the ROM reader from Germany.
So the first thing I did for this new work is I built my own.
Obviously, that's the first thing.
And then so by the time I'd done this, I was kind of committed at that point.
So what I'm going to go through then is my experiences of writing an emulator and kind
of, as I say, first one I've written, the decisions, challenges.
It's going to be a little bit mature through some of the APIs that there are now in the
Java platform, this kind of thing.
And in all honesty, some kind of, there are some pros and cons that I'll talk about.
And above all, some kind of little, little tricks in the APIs that aren't always very
well documented that can kind of help us.
So why Java?
So I'll be completely honest.
The main reason for me was it's the language I'm most familiar with.
So I've been using Java now for about 20 years.
The first JRE that I used came on floppy disk.
That's how long.
These days, it's obviously cross-platform.
And these days, it's got quite a rich set of APIs, hopefully everything we need to develop
an emulator.
It's got good longevity, so you tend not to have this thing in Java that you sometimes
get in Swift, for example, where you kind of come in one morning, try and recompile
your code and find it won't compile anymore because Apple's changed something.
Java tends not to have that.
It's maintained good backwards compatibility over the years.
And so hopefully, anything I write moving forward will also run.
I don't have to have an emulation a few years' time to emulate the emulator.
There are, as well from a person's point of view, there's some APIs coming up that I was
kind of keen to have a benchmark to see, well, in a couple of years' time, things like the
foreign function and memory API that's kind of just about to kind of hit stability.
I was kind of interested to see, well, what will I be able to do with that when it comes
out?
So I set myself some goals that I wanted my emulator to be accurate enough to allow
most software to run on.
In all honesty, for kind of version one of my first emulator, there were some things
that I decided not to emulate, things like memory contention issues.
There are some weird things that you can get that I'll maybe have time to talk about on
the spectrum with kind of glitches in the video display.
So essentially, my kind of overall goal was anything that software uses that isn't a kind
of bug in the hardware that people might accidentally get around or use.
I'll try and emulate that.
So I already mentioned one thing I was trying to do is get a baseline from the basic Java
APIs and try not to bring in additional libraries as a kind of starting point.
I wanted to be a cooperative application, not necessarily just full screen, performant
enough.
Yeah, as I say, I'm not trying to write a one gigahertz Z80 for my kind of first project.
These machines I tried to emulate.
So I went for the trusty old ZX Spectrum.
So apologies to Steve.
I'm adding to the pile of emulators now available for ZX Spectrum.
And I also thought that the Sega Master System.
So why these two together?
A, these are the machines I had as a kid.
But B, if we look at the technical specs, there are actually some similarities that are going
to help us.
So the video resolution is similar, although the video chips and formats that they use
are very different.
The CPU essentially is Z80 around 3.5.
So around 3.5 actually, there are different models of the Spectrum with different speeds
and the Master System.
I think it was 3.58 for the Master System.
You can see then here, probably everybody in this room is fairly familiar with machines,
but for those who aren't.
So you can see that the ZX Spectrum in comparison was all about saving money.
So you had one custom ULA here that was handling the video and the sound and was also the memory
controller compared to the Master System that had a bit more on board hardware that we're
going to have to try and emulate.
So just a little bit more detail of some of the difficulties again for people.
It made it familiar, so the ZX Spectrum, it renders its video all from RAM, essentially
with kind of no acceleration as such.
And it's got this format that really kind of gives the ZX Spectrum its look and feel.
Yes, you have essentially a one bit per pixel bitmap and then over the top of that, you're
allowed two colors essentially per 8x8 cell.
This kind of gave the Spectrum a bit of a unique look and feel.
It was bright and flash as well per cell.
Compare that to the Master System where you've got an actual dedicated graphics chip, but
this was all tile based.
So you have a 34x24 tile display, each tile can be 8x8 pixels.
So the eagle-eyed amongst you will notice that you can't actually define enough unique
tiles to give each pixel in that display a unique pixel.
So anything that looks like it does, you'll see you get these kind of almost like little
manga cards for some games.
But here where we tried to fill the screen but obviously secretly around the edges, we've
actually got blank space.
There wasn't actually enough memory to have unique tiles for every space on the screen.
But despite that, it did have features that were actively kind of advocated by Sega to
its developers to make the most possible use of the video chip.
So the way it worked, you have a series of registers to control things like the scrolling,
the colors.
And there was a mechanism via an interrupt to actually on each scan line or on every
nth scan line, depending on how you programmed it, you could actually change those registers.
Yes, you could change the scroll position at different parts of the screen, you could
switch off the screen, you could potentially change the color palette.
And so that's something when we're doing our video rendering, we're going to have to have
a little think about how we can kind of optimize that a little bit.
I'll just give a very quick example.
So we're going to see here we've got some parallax scrolling where you see how on different
scan lines we're setting a different x position.
And then that's quite a nice fact, that's a game called Chop Lifter.
On the next example, we're actually going to have a case where here we're actually,
it's not literally turning off the screen, but it's changing the base address of the
screen memory to effectively turn it off at that bottom part.
And this is kind of probably the most, well an extreme example here, where literally on
kind of every other scan line, we're changing the scroll position to kind of give that effect
there.
So very briefly, I'll just give a little bit of the overall organization of the emulator,
it's kind of the first thing you really need to think about.
So it's how we kind of turn this, this is very high level obviously, but this is essentially
what the hardware looks like.
We've got an address bus at the top with the ROM and the RAM connector, we've got a data
bus at the bottom with any peripherals, which on the spectrum were fairly minimal, there
was a one to eight version with the sound chip.
And then on the master system, you can see again, similar idea, but notice that the ROM
essentially is the cartridge that you plug in.
Yes, when you plug a cartridge in, you're kind of directly communicating with the Z80
and any logic for things like memory paging, you can have that on the cartridge.
And then a few more peripherals going on the data bus, we've got the video processor there,
the programmable sound generator, there's also an FM unit, which I'll touch on briefly, and
the controllers.
So then what I tried to do, I'm sorry, there was the emulator clock there as well.
And what I tried to do is to abstract that down so that I'm going to organize a program
this way, we've obviously got the Z80 implementation, is obviously a kind of fairly fundamental part.
But then what I've actually done is, in my implementation, I've separated out the Z80
decoder from the actual instruction loop.
This is quite nice and we want to add a debugger as well, then you can go through the same
code to decode the instructions for the debugger.
And we've got an abstract IOBUS, from which again, then on the master system, we'll have
our master system IOBUS on the spectrum IOB, etc.
A memory similar idea, so we have subclasses of these overall base classes.
And the clock, which is actually working the other way round to the way the hardware is
working, the clock is effectively going to be a kind of break on the CPU thread and is
going to tell it when to pause to keep things at the right rate of instructions.
And there'll be a little bit of feedback as well between the video thread so that it can
interact with the CPU to do the things I've just mentioned about accurately timing the
scroll register and things.
So just an example, I end up with interfaces like this.
And then to the Z80, it's effectively, it doesn't care whether it's a master system
or a spectrum it's communicating with, it just goes through these abstract interfaces.
A little bit of detail just on, I've just mentioned about the CPU.
The implantation that I went for, which isn't necessarily the most kind of popular of the
traditional emulators, I tried to really break down the instruction set into more of an object
oriented form.
So you've got instruction types you'll see there and then for each type the individual
instruction is kind of returned as an object that says well it's this type and it's from
this source, this destination.
So I've tried to kind of not have to write 900 different routines for all the various
combinations that the Z80 have.
And that gives quite nice code.
There's a little bit of a performance trade-off obviously but it turns out not to be too
bad.
Okay.
And then the other decision I made was well we're now writing in Java in 2023 now.
So I decide well I want to make the most of multithreading.
So the various of the components I've just mentioned will actually sit in their own thread.
That's kind of nice organizationally and also in terms of monitoring the performance of
the app it means we can break down a little bit more easily what resources are being used
for each component.
So just to give a little bit of an overview of this.
So we'll have at the top kind of got our, is that good?
So we've got our CPU thread at the top there which is going to be interacting with the
clock and it's periodic on the site and I've done this many instruction cycles.
How am I doing?
Do I need to pause to kind of maintain the correct instruction rate?
Then we've got the video controller which is going to be sending periodically sending
V blank instructions every frame to the CPU to notify it.
We've got then also a separate rendering thread which is going to do any of the kind of heavy
lifting rendering that we need to do.
So anything like scaling, calculating what the actual pixels are and then the idea is
that here in the event dispatch thread which is a single threaded at that point we have
to kind of have our ducks in a row and know what we're actually going to render.
And then additional complication is, it's going to be an audio service in its own thread
as well.
So a bit of choreography going here.
So different APIs that we're going to use.
There's a standard Java swing API so there's no additional OpenGL plugins here.
A couple of the Java sounds I mentioned, monitoring, kind of a little hidden one but when we're
emulating data, when we're emulating kind of cartridge saves and we want to write data,
actually open a mapped file for that to save the data and threading is often important.
I'm not going to really mention too much but there are also desktop and taskbar integration
APIs that help with integrating into desktop with system menus and things.
So we'll start with the graphics.
The standard swing Java 2D APIs we're maybe familiar with, the idea is that you override
the JComponent class and you implement a paint component method and in here in principle
we can set various options to hint with what we want, quality, speed, etc.
And then finally we can render an image and it will be rendered with these different settings.
But some caveats for that.
Unfortunately it turns out that some of those options effectively end up turning off GPU
acceleration and they can be quite CPU hungry and efficient.
It's not clearly documented which ones actually run on the CPU and the GPU but effectively
ends up that the fast options without any quality interpolation are the ones that run
that just go straight to the GPU.
So we're going to have to be a little bit careful not to use too much CPU time for each
frame render.
And then there's also an additional problem that the standard API to set and get pixels
from buffered images actually is quite inefficient for setting individual pixels.
But we have a workaround.
So this will be the standard API that we'd use.
We create our image like this, lovely, and we set different types, about 15 different
types that we could use and then we can set RGB and whether that backing store is an int
per pixel or bytes per pixel or whatever, it will work out how to set the RGB, lovely.
But in practice we're probably never going to have anything other than an int per pixel.
So this is the least efficient way we could possibly imagine to set the pixel data.
Luckily we can actually, with a little bit of jiggery-pokery, we can ask Java2D for the
underlying int array and then we can just directly write to that.
The advantage being then things like array, fill, array copy, array.fill, sorry, they
then become available.
There's a caveat that normally you wouldn't do this because if you've got static images
that you're rendering lots of times, what would normally happen is that Java2D sends
that to the GPU you want and then subsequent renders are effectively free.
But we don't really need that for our purposes.
We're going to be rendering a different image on each frame effectively.
So that's not such a problem for us.
So then just to come back to what I was showing you earlier with the different scroll per
on different raster lines, we kind of want to get the best of both worlds with how we
then end up structuring things.
So what I do is I basically I kind of break down the image and say, well, for this frame,
where are the points where the things like the scroll registers actually change?
On some games that will they will just have one setting per frame and I can then just
efficiently render the entire frame without having to worry about clips per section, et
cetera.
So I don't kind of literally go through pixel by pixel kind of chasing the beam.
Just yes, just a kind of brief example here.
So I'll split into sections and then I can say for that section, get me the relevant
settings and then go through and fetch from the tile map data and render it kind of almost
as you expect.
So by doing that and by using this trick of getting the raw kind of inter-ray, this does
allow us to get quite a good speed up on the rendering.
So if there's kind of one thing you're doing in Java, the one kind of speed up to think
about is probably this.
Mention so having known about that trick, there's some little tricks that we can do.
Obviously people familiar with CRTs where they were actually the way these systems work,
they kind of render every other scan line.
And if you've got a really good quality monitor like that, most people's monitor is a bit
more that, you kind of have bleed in between the scan lines and you also kind of get ghosting
effects this kind of thing.
So we can try and give a little bit of that look and feel.
So I'm literally going to do here in the Java is I'm going to render every other kind of
scan line, I'm going to render the kind of darkened version of that scan line so I can
kind of produce something like this.
And just have to be a little bit careful with the scaling because you can get more effects
if you've got kind of odd scale factor.
So I do a little bit of extra interpolation to try and get around that.
Then another effect that we can do in Java is to make these kind of ghosting effects.
If we can define our effect in terms of a convolution matrix, which you may have seen,
then we get native library built in that will allow us to render that efficiently and that
will also access the integer data under the hood.
It won't go through that set RGB every time.
So we can get effects like this.
Again we're kind of at low rendering time.
And then this is for my favorite Spectrum games from a child.
Something like this, combining the kind of CRT effects on there.
Another issue we just have is there are multiple ways to scale images in Java.
And depending on which one we pick, we kind of get different performance characteristics.
So the thing I'm actually looking at, which is kind of most stable, is to actually just
hard code the scaling myself because then I can go through this, you know, access the
inter-a directly.
Some of these other built-in APIs, unfortunately, you know, they go through that get RGB, set
RGB to support different formats.
But we don't really need that.
Okay.
Let's talk about sound.
So the mass system and the Spectrum had quite different ways of producing sound.
The Spectrum obviously was this kind of very simple speaker.
It could effectively be a one or a zero and you kind of control a square wave literally
from the CPU to produce your sound.
But then something like the Master System that had an actual sound chip, you would control
the sound by setting register to say I want tone one to be this frequency, etc.
So we want to abstract those two ways of producing sound so that we can just have one generate
sample data method and then our audio service is going to call into that.
And so it's just a brief step here of what I do.
So I've got the subclass, for example, for the Spectrum type sound there.
And then here, a bit more complicated, but we effectively do a similar thing.
We're going to be, whenever we're asked for some sample data, we're going to calculate
that sample data and split it back.
And then the question becomes, well, given that sample data production, how do we actually
pipe it down to the audio output?
Java has this slightly quirky model where you have a notional mixer that's got inputs
and outputs.
And the slightly perverse thing is that everything is seen in terms of this notional mixer.
So when you want to output sound, you're actually sending it to an input of the mixer.
So we call it a source line.
Whereas to us, it's not really a source.
It's a target.
But that's the reason for that.
So if I, you see here, they're also tied to particular drivers.
I can enumerate the different drivers on my machine.
I found out, for example, that my Mac can listen through my iPhone microphone.
That was the first time I found that out.
So yeah, so we created available mixers, and then we query them for their available source
lines.
And then we can write the data to the source line.
We open it with a format that we want.
We write the data.
And so this is now where I can call my generate sample data method when there's some frames
to send.
I send them.
People might have spotted a slight flaw with that.
I've got a nice infinite loop there.
Because on something like the spectrum, I need to be able to tell the difference between
there's no audio and there's no audio yet, but there's some on the way.
And I don't want to sit in an infinite loop in the meantime.
So this is where, so yeah, this was just code examples of how I get, we output those ones
and zeros, and then we translate them.
So I'll just skip quickly.
So we get those ones and zeros, and then what we're actually going to do is we're going
to use a condition object, which is part of the Java concurrency API, so that we can basically,
in our audio service thread, we can wait for a notification that there's actually some
audio that we want to send.
There we go.
Okay.
There's also a little bit that we can do with hybrid buffering is basically where we want
to ideally have a small buffer to fill to send.
But that then induces a problem of we run the risk that if we can't fill our buffer
in time, we end up with choppy audio.
And so in practice, what we can actually do is have a larger buffer and detect when it's
half full and kind of keep topping it up.
So that's basically how I do it.
The FM synth, which I'll mention briefly, I never had one of these.
I think they're quite rare, you can only get them in Japan.
But the master system, this was an option for the master system.
And what I actually do for this, I cheat slightly.
I use Java's built-in MIDI software synthesizer.
So I translate the instructions to that FM synth into MIDI commands.
And I send these to the soft synth.
And I don't know if this is going to play on the projector, but I'll turn up the audio
here and just see.
So you'll hear the normal PSG sound chip.
And then you will hear the FM kind of synth.
Oh, don't even hear that.
It's probably too quiet.
And you see there, we can then start playing about with things like the voices that we
assign to those.
OK, so I'll just touch on very briefly, because time is getting to the end.
So I'll just touch very briefly on the timing and concurrency.
So the CP, obviously, we need to maintain it at our desired instruction rate.
So the way I do this is I introduce pauses.
But then we want to be able to accurately measure those pauses.
We also need to accurately measure the timings between the frames that we're sending.
And there's obviously standard APIs in Java to do this.
A little issue that I did come across, the standard executor framework that we'd normally
use for doing this.
So here we say, OK, I want a frame every 60th of a second.
Depending on your platform, you can actually, in practice, get quite erratic intervals between
the events.
So you can see, in particular, on Mac OS, you could get this kind of 20% error.
So this is just one experiment, for example.
What I luckily found was that if we request low sleep interval, the accuracy is actually
better for low sleep intervals than the higher sleep intervals.
And it seems to max out a particular amount.
I'm not exactly sure of the underlying reason for that.
I must admit, in Darwin.
But then what this leads to is we can kind of come with, depending on the platform, we
can come up with a different strategy for maintaining accurate timing.
And a challenge, a perpetual challenge with Java really is that the best strategy will
depend on the platform.
Very briefly, data manipulation, which sometimes something a bit scared of.
In Java, all of the types, well, they're generally signed.
Chari is unsigned.
But they're generally fixed width and signed.
We can't do what we can in C and other languages defining our own types.
So one way to work around this when we want to do things like register access, send the
audio data, is the byte buffer is generally the easiest way to do that.
You'll notice when we want bytes, because byte, the byte type is signed.
So if on an unsigned byte, then we would normally promote it to an int.
And then we can basically undo the FF and lop off the lowest byte.
And then, so there's just a, I'll just skip forward.
Then there's just a question with that about, well, how do we check that the JIT compiler
is doing what we need to do?
So I'll just step forward slightly.
And what we can actually do, we can ask it.
So we can ask it to dump out the JIT compiled assembler.
And then we can check if some of those optimizations are actually going in.
So this was a very simple test I set up.
It's basically, it's iterating through repeatedly, effectively, writing a word and then reading
it from a byte buffer.
This obviously is slightly contrived.
This is really the kind of the contrived corner case example.
But it kind of illustrates the kind of thing that's possible, yeah?
So I'm effectively, that BTF, effectively writing a two byte unsigned value into there
via a byte buffer.
So it looks like I'm creating a byte buffer, setting values on it, calling a method on
it.
But by the time we get down to the actual JIT compiled assembly code, in the best case
we're actually not.
That just compiles down into we are storing a half word in there.
So that's the kind of thing that we can do to kind of check for those things.
Okay?
I think we're skipped to the end.
There we go.
So mentions, yeah.
Those method calls are completely optimized out.
Okay.
So there you go.
So in conclusion, using those various APIs together, we can write an emulation in Java.
A few pros and cons, caveats around the different platform behavior.
Few things that still to add in here.
This is very much kind of version one.
However, it was at the point where it will actually run quite a lot of the spectrum master
system software.
If anyone's curious, I've got an initial release there on GitHub.
There's going to be source codes and further improvements on the way.
So watch that repo as they say.
A few references there that people may or may not have come across.
This book here by Chris Smith is I think kind of a remarkable piece of work about the kind
of the very kind of low level details of how the spectrum works and the usual kind of reference
guides that over the years have surfaced on the web.
So with that, I think I'll hand back.
Thank you.