So hello everyone. We start with the next project, the next routing project. I'm really
pleased that Janik Vassal came all the way here from Montreal, Canada and is going to
present us transit network planning for everyone. It's a great project to show how a research
project is going into real life and he just, or the project just went open source last autumn.
So we're really excited to see what your project is about. Thank you.
Bonjour, hi everyone. I'm really happy to, I always find a good excuse to come to FASDEM.
So as Melja said, I'm from Montreal. I live in a borough called Verdun, which is still in the
island of Montreal. I'm a little bit far from the subway so I have to rely on buses to get
everywhere on the network. Luckily Montreal is a well grid, it's a grid-based city so it's really
easy to pass bus line about everywhere. But the problem I have every time I try to get the bus,
they all seem to be in sync. Even if I have like three or four lines, I look at the schedule and
there's like no bus available right now. And I ask myself, can I find a way to prove that and ask
the city council or the transit agency, there's a problem there. Luckily a couple of years back,
I started about paying a couple of friends at the Polytechnic University on a software project called
Transition, which is a transit planning tool which is aimed for transit planner at first. But
as much as you want to make a really good tool for transit planner people working in transit
agency, our ultimate goal is to make the tool as easy to use for every citizen, everybody,
to actually solve and understand what are the transit problem and come up with solutions
that everybody can bring. We are really far from that goal but we want to make it as easy as like
your favorite city simulation game. So as I said, we are a research group based in Polytechnic,
Montreal called Share Mobility. It's a mix of transit engineers who studied transit problem,
mobility problem, but we have also other people like we have an economist and we have a few
software folks to help with the software development. Being an engineering school,
we tend to work with applied solutions. So we develop a few tools over the year. We have
evolution, which is a travel survey platform. I'll talk a bit more later. We have a tool for
congestion dashboarding, taxi dashboarding, and the one I'm talking about today, the tool about
transit planning. So if you're a transit professional, your main day job is to actually
draw new lines for your city. There's more analysis to that, but this is the main thing that the tool
will provide you. Give you, you have the map of the city and you can just add new stops, you can
add lines, draw where they go, or you can just import a GTS file for your network or export them
as you go. This is a Brazil. I just imported the old city and can just go and try to work on that
and see where are the problems or what we can improve. We have the concept of a variant or
scenario. So basically you want to do some studies and like maybe exclude some part of the line or
exclude some mode of transportation, like some people only like buses. They just want to take
bus or you will study maybe your network that way. We have a schedule editor
or viewer. Basically you can just sell a schedule, you can edit it. We have a simple addition like
you can tell. I have five bus for this line. It'll just like generate you a schedule,
considering the time to go over the route, the dwell time at every stop and there.
We are not aiming to make a tool to operate the network. Like OSRDB4, it's more tailored to
like actual scheduling of your train in real life. We want to keep it more eye level. Like
what's the idea of the planning? If you are a small city, small transit agency, you can use
that to do your operation. It's simple enough. It will give you some information. If you enter
the schedule, it will tell you how many buses you need so we can give quick estimate. But we will
not consider things like scheduling of staff, maintenance, another issue in there. So we want
to keep it more eye level, at least at this point in time. So the first kind of analysis we do
and like the MODIS project presented before is routing. So basically the same simple problem.
You have a source of destination. We allow you to specify a bunch of parameters to represent
what Felix was talking about. Different kind of needs for different kind of people. Do you want
to do multiple connection or not? Are they older people? Do you want to walk less? Do you want
slower? That kind of things. We can calculate like the best route or we can show you all the
different alternatives. So if you want to go from the ground plus to here at 9am this morning to get
in time, the best option you will give you is the 95 bus. But there was 17 other alternatives that
was like in range to get here in time. We show you transit. We show you walking. We are working
on other modes like cycling or parking ride. There's a lot of complicated problems to combine
network like cycling and ride. There's a lot of difficulty in there. And I'm looking at what do
you do if you can save us some time to do that there. I was talking about variant. I'm sometimes
a bus nub. I take the bus a lot at home. So when I go, especially on this side of the Atlantic,
I try to stick to rails. So I excluded all the buses. And this is like the route, the best route
if I want to keep on metal road. The second kind of allows this really used in transit planning
is the accessibility map. The idea there is to specify a point in the region. And it will show
you the area you can reach in a specific amount of time. In this example, I'll show you from this
place what you can reach in like 15, 30 and 45 minutes. You can specify this area. And the main
interests of the tool, you can do one point at a time. If you want to do a real analysis, you'll
know what to do a lot of them. And that's what the tool provides. Also for the routing part,
you can just upload a file of origin for the accessibility map or origin destination for
the routing. And then you can do real life analysis of all your movement in a day and see
what's best in your network. Every time you will get a bunch of statistics for the accessibility
map, the interesting part is like, on many square kilometers you can reach at a specific time.
If we use the same variant, excluding the bus network, you see you reach a little bit less if
you stick to L. And you have about like 10 square kilometer less. So that's an interesting
thing to analyze. Like if you have some new lines, you do the analysis with the new line
without the line, you compare the result in there. We are currently working on new views,
like to especially do this diff. Instead of having to look at the map yourself, we're going
to show you like, okay, this is the difference between the two analysis that you did and
the statistic difference between those two solutions that you are exploring for your network.
A third analysis that we do, we have a simulation and optimization algorithm. It's based on a
genetic algorithm. So basically the idea, you can provide like your existing network,
add a bunch of new lines or create some random lines in your network. And using some simulated
trips or actual trips, if you have the data there, we'll try to find the best route, the best line
to put in your network to reduce the overall transit time for your population. You can keep,
I have other parameters like I want to keep the cost constant to what I have right now. So I will
not add new trains, new buses, or you can give it like, okay, I have some extra budget. I can do
like 10% more in there. For some of the statistics we studied, we showed that we can, by using that
kind of algorithm, reduce the overall transit time of user by about 15%. Some user will get worse,
but most of the user will have better time. And we did it for real for some cities. This is
Romanville. It's a town about 80,000 people sitting mostly between Montreal and Quebec City.
And they came to us with their actual network. They were like, yeah, it doesn't serve our user
well. We want to have something better. So we just ran the algorithm and give them that. So if you
compare quickly, you see like the same overall idea with the lines. We started with some what
they have, but we explored some space around that. For this case, we draw the line ourselves. We have
a couple of students working on algorithm to just generate new line automatically instead of having
you try to add the new idea there. So this is actually being implemented right now as a new
network for that city. Another real study that we did, there's an idea to add a new subway line
that would go diagonal in Montreal, a project that we called the Pink Line. It might not go,
but there's a lot of ideas floating around. But the city and the government came to us like, okay,
can you show us what would be the impact of adding that line to the city? So basically,
using the batch routing capability of the tool and using actual travel survey data from a previous
study, we were able to simulate all the movement of people with the line and without the line.
And we've seen some interesting result that overall adding that line will reduce transit time
by about 5% for the whole population. Interestingly, we've shown that the people would get the most
benefits from that line would be people who actually use car right now. So hopefully adding
that would shift some mode of transportation from car to some other better transit solution.
This is the overall map of the city with that project and all the currently
projects being constructed in Montreal. And in blue, we show where most people would get at least
a two-minute improvement in their transit in average with a new city.
So how does the tool build? Basically, it's a web application. It's run on Node.js. We mostly
write, we conduct all the code to TypeScript to have at least something that is not too awful to
maintain. A couple of components in surplus plus in Rust. In the backend, we try to move more and
more of the component in Rust just to make improved the maintainability. And it's all running on top
of PostGIS and PostGestQL. For the basic routing, as most people use OpenStreetNet data, we use OSRM
to do the basic route on the road, on pedestrian path. We did modify the basic profile to have
more accurate results, especially for buses in cities. You want to be more accurate because
a bus is not a car. A bus cannot go on every street necessarily or cannot turn as easily as
of the car. So we have some specific mode for that. Same with the motors. We actually are also
looking at Valhalla. Maybe it could give us some improvement in our operation. For the transit part,
we develop a tool car. TR routing. It's a standalone component, also available. We implemented the
connection scale algorithm. Reference the paper there from some people at the
really efficient algorithm. We added a trip base algorithm before, but we used to that. Mostly in
surplus plus at this point. Wanted to convert to Rust, but maybe I can just use motors in there,
that part, and don't have to worry about it. But if we want to do planning, we have to do some data.
Like if you're a transit agency, if you're a city government, you have that already probably. But
if you're a citizen, you need to find that data somewhere. Luckily, most of what we need to do
the planning is available in OpenStreetMap. The basic part of the road network, all the pedestrian
path, rail line, it's mostly all in there. So you can go around, use the SRM, do some quick planning
there. You have everything that you need. If you want to do population simulation and trip base
analysis, you will need to simulate the population. Even there, OpenStreetMap can help us.
If you have all the building drawn on the map, you can extrapolate a little bit your population.
If it's residential building, you know some people will probably live there. You can see where the
population is distributed in the city. And on the other side, if you have the POI, the point of
interest, all the other building, all the shops, all the school, all the industry. So you know
where people usually go in the day. So we can just simulate what is that in our general algorithm.
You actually use that kind of information and just create trips to do the analysis in there.
OpenStreetMap is pretty good, but it's not always good enough for what we need.
We estimate we have to spend a little bit of time validating the data to make sure we have the
accurate result. You can use as is, but you might get error in there. For like a dense urban environment
like Montreal, like Brazil, we spend about 25 hours per square kilometer doing the validation.
For suburban environment, 10, maybe 10 hours per square kilometer in the rural side, maybe a couple
of hours. The good thing is when it's done, then it's done, you just have to make sure new exit
don't break everything, but the information will be there. What we look at when we do the validation,
what are the important things we need? The first part is make sure we have all the link between the
pedestrian network, the cycling network, with the rest of the road network. If you have things like
if you like the tram stop near the ULB, there's a lot of pedestrian path going in and out. If we
didn't have connection well between all those times, the routing algorithm will not be able to just
get you from the tram network to the campus or we'll find a route that goes around. It's really
important to make sure you have all the correct access tag so we have to go look at everything
in that and even add maybe some connection between street to go around in there. We usually
split the sidewalk and the cycling path. I know it's a little bit a debate in the Open Street
Network community, like should you split the sidewalk and just use the sidewalk tag?
But at least for us, we get a really more accurate result if we split the sidewalk.
For Big Street, having a few meters difference between the middle of the road and the sidewalk,
that can be more easy to go around. We also know the quality of the road there. We don't use that
information yet now routing. We want to get there and be able to tell people, yeah, this route,
if you walk on that street, there's a large, large, hard wall. There's streets more fun to walk there
versus some other road. Whenever I plan from my place to the subway, I always take one. Never take
the road that the tool proposed me because it's more fun to go in that other road because there's
shops, there's more life. It's more interesting. The other thing, we will add doors to big buildings.
A big building like a university like that. If we use the center, the center of the building,
we might route you on the other side of the building. If it's a big one, maybe that will
end up being a different bus completely. We need to make sure to know where are the main entrance.
We're going to go and add that big shopping center, things like that, industry, big warehouses.
We're going to spend time just making the street are well aligned. That's the one way out there.
Useful to ride cars and buses. Make sure we have the speed limit. We can consider that in the
transit time of a vehicle. Since we have open street map open, we'll just try to add all the
point of entry that we can find. At least the name and the type that will help the algorithm in there.
We can go further when we have time. We can have reserve line for buses.
We would like to automate a little bit more of that with using MapRulate or the task manager
from the open street community. We are not there yet, but it's going there. For the population,
I've talked a little bit about the OSM building. What we tend to use a lot is the land use register.
A lot of government will provide that for free or at least you can request information to that.
Basically, the information about all the building in a specific area. You would know the building
type. You can find out the population on there or the interest where people want to go in there.
You might want to use the census information that most government will provide. The difficulty
there is the general area is really big. It will often cover multiple blocks in the city.
So, it will cover multiple bus lines or stops. It's going to be hard to find exactly where some
people would come from. We are trying to work on some ideas, some algorithms to spread the
population in some sensible way to be able to simulate based on that. But it's still a work in progress.
Lastly, if you have travel surveys and if you're not familiar with that idea,
most of the agencies will spend time once in a while to just go and ask
most users where they are coming from, where they are going, why they are traveling.
They're going to do that by phone, sending mail, or just stop people on the network and ask them
where they are going. That's really useful information. You can take that and do an exact
simulation of your specific day. But that data is not generally available. If you're a researcher,
you can have access to it. But a general citizen will not have that. That's why we try to get the
population and just simulate that kind of movement there. It will be interesting to know, to get at
some point, if you can, anonymize the information, use the same idea, spread the population somehow,
and make that private free in there. But, yeah, I talked about the evolution tool earlier.
It's a web-based kind of survey platform that can be used for that, which is all the plug-ins to
actually ask people about where they're going, where they're coming from, more specifically from
a date or SurveyMonkey kind of thing. As folks were talking, we also research groups.
So there's a couple of challenges to bring stuff to the real world. How do we make sure
the things we do are actually useful? The first thing would be the code is open source.
As most research, I really strongly believe everything should be open source. And having
trying to get the student to work in the open first would be a good first step. It's not there
yet. A lot of people want to go as fast as they can and just finish their thesis and
give us the code at the end that we have to, as a research professional, do a lot of cleanup
and make sure it works for everybody, but would be a good way. The other thing we do is we make
sure we partner with actual transit agency. Like in Quebec, we work with almost all the
main transit agency for a major city. And we actually have them use the tool, give us feedback,
we sit with them, and ask them what kind of data, what kind of studio you do. And sometimes,
like, we do a batch routing thing and then we take the CSV file and then we do some Excel and then
we do some Python and we're like, okay, what if we just give you a button that would just give you
that and have a quick plug-in to open in QGIS. So we try with those ideas in there. So as I said,
we are far from done. We have currently like 450 open issues. Like, not all bug reports, yeah,
there's some. But stuff like improving the UI, implementing new algorithm, trying to
get integrate some of the tools in there. But yeah, it's a work in progress and we always open to
review pull requests. As for my original problem, so I ran a batch accessibility map, so basically
from my place every five minutes, how far could I reach in the city for like 60 minutes. And I got
this really big association. Like, that kind of showed me there's some kind of a problem with the
schedule. Especially around this 1030 mark where I dip about by almost 15 square kilometers. So I
think, and yeah, I remember every time I tried to go out of the house at that time, which is a good
time to start working, 1030. And there's no bus available. So I think there's a problem there.
It's not highly scientific so far. I'm just like a computer engineer trying to fight myself into
transit engineering. But I think there's a problem there. So that's it. Thank you. If you have any
question.
You've shown us the use of the transition at the state of the city to design and grow new
bus lines, for example. Do you think it would make sense to use that same tool to work at a bigger
scale, for example, drawing train lines at the scale of a country? Would it make sense
to wait transitions? Yeah, so the question is like, doesn't make sense to work at the higher
scale, like country level. I think so. I think right now the performance of the tool might not
be there yet. Like we can think when I do work on Montreal as a world that's starting to like
things getting slow, we are at the limit. So at this point, we are trying to increase the scalability
of that. And we definitely want to go at that level, especially like maybe what depends on the
size of the country, like Canada wide might be a bit too big, but at least province level,
we definitely want to be able to do that.
Okay.
Thank you.
Yeah, it's an interesting comment. And yeah, that's where we want to make the tool for people. But
I know a lot of politicians and I want to make the tool as good for them to actually be able to
try it by themselves and understand the problem. We often have people come to
Catherine, which is the head of the research lab and like they ask them for studies and
but they are not always implemented. But if people can just see for themselves what would
be the improvement that could be interesting in there.
Maybe one last question.
Yeah, very short. You mentioned point of interest people go to and this is the input for the system
to build the route. It doesn't make sense to use the system to solve the dark problem. Okay,
we have existing routes and we want to place the new and special area somewhere. What's the
blank one? What are the best places for that? It doesn't make sense. That's the comment is like,
doesn't make sense to actually sort of like adapting the network to the city. How can we
adapt the city to the network and where can we build new development, a new residential plan,
new residential area. That's a really interesting idea. We never thought of that. But maybe it's
something we can find a way to to implement see where there's potential to develop the city,
maybe an increased density in some places. Thank you for your time.