So, we are ready for the second talk.
And yeah, I'm happy to have Joel here from SPP talking about Rayc audition monitoring
and how to do that with open source software.
Hello everybody.
I'm happy to see that it's this crowded.
I wasn't expecting that, but I'm pleasantly surprised.
So I'm going to talk to you today from a very niche department of SBB, which is measurement
and diagnostics.
We're basically part of the infrastructure like Eloy before.
We're trying to maintain and run the infrastructure in Switzerland.
It's not such a big country, but a very dense train network.
So the problems we face is basically that we have shallow train passing times and a
lot of maintenance to do.
And to be able to do this maintenance at the right moment, we have the measurement and
diagnostics department, which I am part of.
And we basically have two major goals.
One is to maintain the safety of the system and the other one is to gather data of the
infrastructure assets in order to be able to do predictive maintenance or maintenance
at the right moment and just to make sure that the money spent is well spent in order
that assets can live the most long without breaking down.
Here you can see two of our measurement trains, they're typically sensor-based measurements,
typically optically made measurements, and we'll go a little bit deeper into that afterwards.
Normally I was planning to be here with one of my colleagues, Jean Frederick.
Unfortunately he got sick, catch the cold, so I'm here alone, but I thought I will still
have his picture on a slide in case somebody is interested in what we're doing later on.
You will know him by faith at least.
He is the guy who is doing a lot of the technical implementation, solving a lot of the technical
problems and I'm more on the strategic part of the project.
And yeah, we'll leave it by that.
Such a measurement from sensor to information is quite a long way, so it's a very complex
thing, such a measurement system.
I've drawn here a couple of steps from beginning to end for track geometry measurement.
As I said before, most of them are optical by now, so what you actually do is you have
a laser plane that shines on your track and then you have a camera that makes a photo,
and the first picture is basically a digital photo of the rail.
And then you extract this contrast change and you do a lot of software and you get the
second photo, which is a half profile of your rail.
Then you do the same thing for the second half of your rail and you get a full profile
and you start measuring on it.
And you do, for instance, it may be a bit difficult to see, but there's a lot of little
crosses on the profile and those are the points that you're interested in, the top of your
rail or there's 1.14 millimeters below the top of your rail.
And from this, if you have both rails, you can deduce your track geometry.
An instance, the gauge and the...
Louder.
Okay.
I will talk louder.
You will have the possibility to deduce the gauge or the elevation or the longitudinal
levels of your tracks.
And you can then print them in form of the fourth picture, like as 1D plots.
Afterwards, you've gathered this information, you have to deduce what to do with it.
So in SBB and I think in a lot of other countries in Europe now too, you try to do analysis
over time to see how the track geometry or other parameters in your railway system change
over time and find critical passes to where you know in some time in the future that asset
will break.
And then you can do maintenance in the right moment and assure that it won't break or that
it stays safe a little bit longer or you can deduce, oh, I'm too late, I have to change
that.
And RCM, our software suite that we built ourselves is basically an acronym for rail
condition monitoring saying this whole first part of the value chain here up to the fourth
picture.
And we try to automate that and to make it a bit more generic.
And we're currently trying to do that with the now shown architecture.
So we have the measurement platform on the left side.
It gets from the administrative tools, for instance, topology, like to know what kind
of tracks exist in Switzerland.
We've talked yesterday with Infra-Bell.
It's quite similar.
And I've also talked to people from SNCF, I've also talked to people from Network Rail.
At the end, you need a topology to put your measurement data to an asset, to a certain
location in the physical world.
And while before I was not sure, before we started with this project, I was not sure
if this will be a big problem, if the topologies will be vastly different from country to country.
But at the end, since the requirements are very similar from country to country, I came
to observe that the solutions that came up are also very similar.
And I do believe that it's possible to have a generic topology description between countries.
And this will be, we'll see later on, a bit crucial for this project to work in different
countries.
Once we gathered the measurement on the measurement platform, we have this automated data cleansing
and quality control processing platform.
And the first, basically the first thing is the positioning.
As I said before, that would be to tie the measurements to a physical location on your
topology.
And the second thing that we do is a conversion.
So whatever comes into one of those measurement, whatever comes from one of those measurement
platforms, one of those measurement trains, we convert it into our open data format.
And this is the first thing I would like to talk to you about.
How do you say that?
We'll talk about a bit more detail afterwards.
Once we have it in an open format, we do a standardization like the different measurement
systems provide the same measurement in different flavors.
Let's say the gauge ones come in an absolute number, 1.35 meters.
The second system shows it as a deviation from zero.
One shows it in meters.
One shows it in millimeters.
You have to standardize that a little bit in order to be able to compare it afterwards.
We do a consistency check, and then we do a persistence.
And once we persist that data, we have, at least in Switzerland, regulations to follow,
especially on the duration and on the capacity to be able to read the data again in the future.
In Switzerland, this is about 15 years.
So if we do a measurement, we have to guarantee that for the next 15 years, we are able not
only to show the measurement, but also to open it and to read the data.
And this, again, something that is much easier to do if you have an open data format, which
is not proprietary, which is not tied to a specific software or a specific software version
that you have to maintain to.
Then it goes to the presentation layer, and the presentation layer typically can be various
different programs.
In our case in Switzerland, we use E-Rises from Eertman in Germany.
I think there's a couple of other countries in Europe that do that too.
But we also use our own viewing software, which we call RCM Viewer, which will be the
second part of the open source project I would like to talk about, and which can show, obviously,
the open data format that we use.
So once this data is gathered, typically now if you buy a system on the market, there are
different enterprises that sell such systems.
For instance, Mermeck in southern Italy or Placer & Toiler from Austria, which are two
of the biggest players.
Also there's Ensco in the United States.
You get a proprietary format from them.
You may or may not be able to read it, depending on how your contract is.
So I know as NCF had in the past some problems with that, that the contract did not state
that you are allowed to actually know the data format your data comes to you.
Once you've figured that out and that you are able to read it, you will free yourself
from the use of the software that they impose on you if they sell you the measurement system.
We've done that in Switzerland over the last years.
We've had the same issues, don't worry.
Are now at the point where all our measurement systems are either directly delivering an
open data format or at least that we have a full specification of the data format that
is delivered to us in binary.
We're now trying to transpose that into our open format.
For that, with the last measurement train that we acquired, we specified such a format
based on an open standard, which is HDF5, Hierarchical Data Format 5.
You can find it online.
It exists since, I think, 20 years.
It's widely used in the academic world.
It's also the base of MATLAB's.m files, for instance.
It has the advantage that most programming languages and most measurement data programs
like R or the ADM or all others that are out there already have stops or libraries to read
it.
They themselves, HDF5 themselves, says their key features and advantages are metadata with
data, fast IO, big data, and the other stuff that you can read here.
What we try to do is to write a specification upon the HDF5 that is specific for railway
data, but generic enough that it can handle all type of measurement systems.
Basically you have the advantages of HDF5 and on the same time the possibility if you
follow this specification that we wrote that you can find on GitHub that a software like
the one that we built can read it whatever your measurement systems are.
If you buy it from Mermic, if you buy it from Placer Interior, if it's Track Geometry, or
if it's, I don't know, from Sperry, ultrasonic measurements, or whatever else is out there,
as long as you follow the specification, you can use the software to display it.
You can use the software to overlay it, and so on.
We named it RCMDX, Rail Condition Monitoring Data Exchange.
Our key features for it is that it includes the metadata like configuration, but also
the topology, and it makes it completely self-contained.
In 15 years you take one file.
You do not need anything else than the file itself and the specification of the data to
be able to reproduce a view of the data.
On the track, in the system as it was in the moment that the data was gathered, and this
I think helps a lot.
As I said before, it's accessible through the standard HDF5 tools, so you can download
an HDF5 library from their website and directly access the data.
You can also build your own using the programming language.
Python has a stop, and Java, and C++ and C Sharp also.
On the other side, you still have the generosity in order to use whatever measurement system
you want.
Let's see one of the benefits that you would get if you decide to use such a thing.
For us, one of the main benefits is that if it gets adopted by more than one country,
let's say, you get the advantage that in Open Tender where you have to specify what you
want to buy, you can handle the whole data part with just one single phrase.
Please deliver the data in this specification.
You can find it on GitHub.
As soon as more than one tender writes it inside, I think it's basically close to standard
because this market is very small.
The companies that I told you before are basically covering over 80% of the whole market.
As soon as they start to see that it is necessary to deliver their data in this format, you
can get it for free.
I think it's quite a big advantage that could be resulting out of using that.
Of course, then as a result, you have a complete open data.
We will see now I'm switching from the data format to the viewing software.
This also is available already as freeware and will be in future as open source.
Once you have your data in the RCMDX format, as soon as you follow the specification, you
can basically use the software to display it.
It's highly generic in the case that everything that you see now here is a workspace that
can be easily configured by the user.
You can drag and drop every little window inside that workspace, put it somewhere else.
You can configure it to show whatever data you want.
You can change the parameters that are shown.
You can change the boundaries that are shown.
You can change the limits that you want to display.
You can show in parallel and synchronous in time, in space, and also on your topology
different measurement systems.
You can show data from the track geometry system together with video data, together
with optical data, together with ultrasonic data, whatever you think might benefit you
the most.
You can easily do it very complicated or you can try to build new views that are less generic
for an end user.
For instance, for a maintenance manager, if he has to do a specific job, like in our case,
the lower right part, like this part with optical data, he has to find surface defects.
You can put on a specific mask on the viewing software in order to help him to do that more
efficiently.
You've seen it play.
It's like a video that I made before.
This viewing software is currently done in C-sharp and we're trying to put it open source
since I don't know, a bit more than a year.
The main problems that we are facing is we have begun building it like seven years ago
together with a new measurement coach and it has some proprietary libraries in it.
The main ones are Sidechart and Telerik for C-sharp and we're now trying to find a way
to use open source while having those libraries inside because it's very difficult to throw
them out and especially Sidechart.
There's no good alternative for the moment in order to be a performant viewing software.
That's basically where we are right now.
You can already download it on GitHub.
Here's the link.
There's also an overview later on.
We also have a couple of measurement files from Switzerland that you can download to
a couple of workspaces and like that you can see how the data format works, how the viewing
software works, how they interact together and in case of implement your own version
of it.
Of course, the benefit of the viewing software would then be that you are able to do massively
complex views with Synchron, I don't know how you say that in English, display data
at the same time and at the same position or at the same point in the physical world.
Basically the viewing software allows you to include the topology also if it's not exactly
the same.
We have in Switzerland twice a year an update on the topology and obviously some things
changed due to maintenance work, due to new building of the tracks and so on.
The viewing software can handle that in order if you have different states in different
files.
As I said before, every file includes your topology too so then you can display the data
where it is taken on tracks that did not have changes and it will show you where it had
changes and do not display the data in the same way if the track changes were applied.
You can in the viewing software change from one topology view to another one.
You have an easy and powerful presentation layer I think if you do so.
Of course, we talked yesterday about the detail.
If you take a measurement run and you run from 8 o'clock in the morning till noon and
you do a 100 kilometer and you do a circle, then if you show it in time you will have
a straight 1D chart of your measurement data.
If you show it in distance you will have the same thing, a straight chart with a distance
based on the x-axis instead of time.
If you show it in topology then you have a much shorter bit showing an overlay of how
many circles you have run through in the morning.
This is quite an interesting thing to do and it is basically what most easily accessible
viewing software lack.
So this possibility to tie it to your physical location like that.
Then we have the licensing.
We worked a lot together with Cornelius, together with Mahalia and also with Christian which
is sitting back there on the licensing that we will be using.
We decided to use an Eclipse public license after some discussions on what would make
sense mainly because it is a weak copyleft license.
I can imagine a future where a measurement system company uses this software directly.
Say you are a startup company, you built your own measurement system, you need a presentation
layer.
You can take the RCMDx data format and the viewing software and create your own possibly
commercial version of it by adding your own flavor to it and still be able to sell it
as long as the core functionality, if you improve it, you send it back upstream.
That would be like the ideal version that we could attend in the future.
That is basically one of the reasons why I am here too.
Hope that all of you will go home and use it and spread it and bring your own companies
to use it too.
Let's see an overview.
Right now the most important link is the first one.
SBB has since one week now a project website for this.
If you click on it, maybe something happens.
You will directly get to a website where you can find the...
It does not show.
Thank you.
Why is it so big?
At least you can read it.
You can see the website and there is a couple of links somewhere.
You have sample data that you can download directly.
I think it is more or less one kilometer of data but gives a good impression how the whole
system can work.
If you are really interested in having more data, you can still contact me or Jean Frederick
and we can give you access to it.
There is more on topic.
Normally if it would not be so zoomed out, it would be a bit nicer and on the top right
of the site.
You can directly download the installer for the viewing software and you can directly
go to the GitHub page with the format description.
You also have the workspaces that you have to load into the viewing software.
You can also create your own ones.
That is just a help if you want to play around with it.
That is basically what I wanted to say.
Thank you very much for listening.
I think we have a couple of minutes for questions too.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Please.
That is the neat point.
It needs to have the corresponding software if you don't want to.
As soon as your data is described properly, it is self-contained so you can build at any
moment a new software to access it.
You can of course keep your software too but you don't need to.
You have the specification.
You can build the tool to read it within a couple of days.
Time is up.
Okay.
Thank you very much.