Hello, everyone, and welcome to this presentation where we talk about automated short-term trend
planning, what it means, and how we handle it in OSRD.
So what is the problem?
Let's say a train wants to go from station 4 to station 4.
We could easily just find a path, but the problem is there's many trains that have already
been scheduled, and we need to find a path that doesn't just work havoc on a timetable.
We can be completely realistic in our simulation.
We assume everything is on time.
We know where every train is going to be located at any time.
So there's a few rules we have to follow to make our blue train go to station bar.
We can't add the trains that would be delayed by other trains.
So in those examples, I use a signal system pretty simple where signal is red if there's
a train behind it and the signal is yellow, meaning slow down, if the next signal is red.
What I mean here is that our train cannot ever see a yellow signal, meaning slow down.
We can add delay before it reaches a signal, but once the blue train sees a yellow signal,
it's game over.
The solution is invalid.
The opposite is, of course, true.
We cannot cause delay on other scheduled trains, meaning by being here, our blue train cannot
cause another train to see a yellow signal, or red, of course.
This means that we need to handle all the weird behaviors of the signal systems, which
can become pretty chaotic quite quickly.
So in these examples, there's one truck with signals going both ways.
What happens here actually is that the signals change around the train, but what really matters
is on the white.
The other train cannot actually enter the main track at all, even if it's really far
away, because otherwise it goes face to face.
So the last signal would be red.
The signal behind that would be yellow, and as soon as we see it, it's over.
There's some other weird behavior.
Sometimes we even have to know in advance where we will go next to know if we would
be delayed.
So in this example, if the train continues straightforward, it would see a green signal.
But if it would turn to the white to the other train, it would see a yellow signal.
Before we even reach the point where we need to take a decision.
This may seem pretty minor here, but in some signals systems, we need to know like kilometers
in advance.
But there are some things we can do.
The train can take detours to avoid busy areas, and we can also sometimes not go at maximum
speed.
Like if we need to fit between two trains that would go slower than our train, we can
just slow down.
What this means is that this is actually not a good thing for us, because we can't just
find the shortest path and then find the departure time.
We need to actually consider all the possibilities that we have.
So that's the problem.
And in OSRD, we are currently working on a solution to this problem.
So OSRD, meaning open source railway designer, is an open source tool that can be used to
edit railway infrastructure and run all kinds of simulations on them.
Keep in mind that on these specific features, we've come a long way, but it's still very
much a work in progress.
So not everything is properly handled for now, and we're still currently working on
it.
So how do we deal with this?
The main problem is that the solution space has a lot of dimensions.
There's, of course, position, because we do need to find paths that go from origin to
destination.
There's also time, because the constraints caused by other trains depends on a certain
time interval when the other train is here.
The tricky one is speed, because unlike cars and bikes and most means of transportation,
a train cannot just speed up really fast.
It can take dozens of kilometers to just speed up or slow down.
So if we find, for example, a solution that does reach our destination, avoiding all other
trains, but where we reach the destination that, say, is 300 kilometers per hour, this
is not a good solution.
It's not even a good approximation of a solution.
So we do need to keep track of the speed that can be reached by the train.
So the way we do that is that we represent the search space as a graph that considers
all those dimensions as well as all the constraints, because once we do have a graph like that,
we can just find a path.
And at this step, it becomes pretty simple.
The main challenge is defining the problem itself as a graph.
So in this case, a node would have a position, a time, and a speed to consider those three
dimensions and must not be defined implicitly.
To get the speed and times, we want train simulations, which we already know how to
do in other parts of the project.
So we consider everything we need to, like slope, curves, the rolling stock data, and
everything we need to.
So I have a small question.
Is there a speed derivable from the position and time?
Yes, but we actually compute the speed to get the position and the time.
So I have a small graphical representation to explain really what I mean by that when
we add time to our solution.
So we start from a simple graph that represents the physical infrastructure.
In this case, that would be, for example, track sections.
And what we do is, in a way, we duplicate all nodes of the graph at different times,
meaning that the point A always represents a specific point in space.
But there's a different node for A at t equals 0 and another node for A at t equals 1 and
so on.
And then we link them in a way that actually reflects the travel time.
So meaning that we start at A at t equals 0 and we can reach C at a certain time after.
And yeah, we can, for example, go from A to F at the same time because we can't just teleport
there.
So this graph is constructed.
As we explore it, it would be too expensive to just build a whole graph on the whole country
at first.
So it's all implicitly defined at first, but then we actually run simulations when we move
forward in the graph.
It's also discretized in time, but only when we evaluate visited location.
What I mean by that is that when we run simulations, we actually keep full track of the time at
full accuracy.
But once we reach a point that has already been visited, if we've visited it at too close
in time, we consider that it's already visited.
Once we have that graph, we just run an A star on the result, a resulting on the graph.
So A star means we have two functions to define.
We have a cost function and an optimization heuristic.
In this case, a cost function would be the travel time of the train from start to the
current point.
And the optimization heuristic is based on geographical data.
And because our heuristic doesn't overestimate the remaining cost, we are going to find the
optimal solution.
So we will find the path that takes the least amount of time.
But I've talked about how we add time to the graph, but I haven't really talked about speed
yet.
So the default behavior is that we always go at full speed unless we need to.
By full speed, I mean not just the maximum allowed speed, like the train speed up as
much as it can and always stays at maximum speed.
But so in this slide, we have a space-time chart.
So we have time on the horizontal axis and distance on a given path on the vertical axis.
And there's an area that is unavailable, meaning there's another train, for example, in this
specific area at a given time.
And I've shown the edges, the arrows represent edges of the graph.
So in this case, we can just, if we speed up as much as we can, we can go before that
other train, but we also could go after that train, which would lead to different solutions.
So in this case, we actually create several edges that are all considered as valid paths.
In a way, you can see it as a decision tree, except we can actually reach the same point
through different paths.
Okay, so, oops, good matter.
So I've talked about the general principle of the solution.
Now I'll talk about a few problems we faced on how we handle them, this problem, what
are them, concern, speed, because it's actually a pain to manage.
So as I said, we want simulation to get the speed of the train, but we do that only one
edge at a time when we explore the graph.
What that means is that we don't know what comes after.
So when we reach our destination, we only know that when we explore the graph, the edge
that contains that destination.
That doesn't always leave enough distance to properly break.
So in this example, we have speed plotted with a distance, and we start in the first
stage by going at full speed, and then we see that we need to stop there.
We start breaking, and there's a discontinuity.
This is not a valid solution.
So in the next slide, it's mostly the same situation, but represented differently.
Here we have edges of the graph, where in red, we have edges where we speed up, and
in blue where we try to slow down, and we have the same discontinuity here.
To stop at the end of section four, we need to enter that section at 10 kilometer per
hour, but because we've been speeding up, we are at 50 kilometer per hour.
So the way we do this, we handle this case, is that we go back in the graph, we backtrack
to back propagate the constraints.
So we see that there's a discontinuity there, and what we actually do is that we go over
the previous section, and we create a new graph edge, but this time slowing down, and
we know that we need to enter the last section at 10 kilometer per hour, so we create an
edge where we end at 10 kilometer per hour.
We notice that to do that, we need to enter that section at 20 kilometer per hour, which
is still not the same as the previous edge, so we keep going, and we continue creating
new edges going over the previous section until we have something that look like that.
We have a valid path that actually stops there.
The two different paths still exist in the graph, because if we go another direction
or something like that, we can still find paths that would take the top path.
Then there's another problem.
I've talked about adding delay previously to go after another train, but I haven't explained
how we do that.
So when we can, as soon as we can, we shift the departure time, meaning that the train,
for example, needs to leave not just at 10 AM, but between 10 and 12 or something like
that.
So if we notice that the train reached the final station 15 minutes too early, and the
other train is already still there, we just make the new train leave 15 minutes later,
and this fixes the problem.
But it is not always possible, like in this example.
If we try to shift the departure time to avoid the problems on the section three, we would
cause new problem on section one.
So we actually need to add delay between two specific points of the path without affecting
the rest.
The way we handle this is actually the same way as the other problem, meaning that we
go back, we backtrack on the graph to propagate the, to add the delay.
So we actually have the old edges that go at maximum speed, but we have a new edges
going from section one to three that has what we call an engineering allowance.
I can't go too much into details in how it's computed, but basically the idea is that we
can do, precisely what we need to do, we add delay between two points of the path by slowing
the train down without affecting the rest of the path.
So this edges here isn't changed.
This one is actually the same, but this one is slowed down.
So we're in the end of the presentation.
So to conclude what we can do, we can find paths that avoid delay on any train, the one
we add and any other.
We can take detours, we can slow down, we can have all kinds of way to avoid any scheduled
train.
There are some features I haven't really talked about because I didn't have the time, but
for example, the user can input allowance parameter, what it means is that the train
generally go a bit slower than they can at fastest.
So as they can catch up, their delay is being delayed.
And as far as performances go, it takes up to about five seconds.
So it's not instant, but not really a problem for now.
This is good enough.
And some features that we still need to work on.
For example, the signaling systems, for now we only support the simplest signaling systems.
The reason for that is because we are currently refactoring the signaling engine in our system.
We are already, which is actually really amazing and we would have loved to talk about it today.
But it's almost finished and when it is done, we need to plug the two systems together.
There's some features a bit more minor, like for now, the user can set the departure time
and leave the overall time unspecified.
We also need to do the opposite, meaning we need to arrive at a given time and we don't
know when we leave.
And we also need the user to be able to say we want to stop there, there, and there on
the path.
Okay, so I've been faster than I thought.
So what I'm going to do is that I'll show a small video demonstration of the project.
This is a few months old, but it shows generally what we do, what we can do with this tool.
So we are on the Brittany region of France and we have the trains that go from Lorient
to Breist.
We just set the schedule.
We have several trains going there, which we can see here.
I won't go too much into details in what the boxes are, but generally it's like, is this
box overlap?
A train is slowed down.
So now we ask for a last minute train that starts from Rennes to Breist.
And we do find the path.
So I'll explain it a bit.
I do have time.
What we see here, horizontal axis is a time, vertical axis is distance.
And previous trains we already had it at the end of the path.
So we see them at the top and the new train goes over the whole path.
Now we add some other trains.
No, we don't add other trains.
We move one of the trains so that it blocks one, actually, the path we took at first.
So if we ask for another train, what we'll see is that it will be shifted to avoid the
previous one.
And we notice that it leaves around 720, something like that.
So what we'll do is that we'll add another train, this time going to Qibron, called
the Qibron, and we'll make it leave around that time.
We add a few of them.
And what we see here is that the train started before, before all those trains that have
been added on the first, actually, I'll explain a bit more.
The trains we have added diverge here.
From here they move away from the path we used to Qibron.
But so we only see them up to here.
And the train we add starts before, then it slows down to enter in this section here.
And we can see the speed of the trains.
So it, anyway, I'll just move on to the questions.
I have also a kind of links, website for the project, GitHub link, an email.
Yes?
Does this kind of solution is used to create schedules in the advance?
It's not used to create the schedules, actually.
It's used once the schedule is set.
Like in the last minute?
Yeah.
You need to add a train on the train?
Yeah, that's it.
There's a given date where the, it's something I wanted to talk about, but I didn't really
have time in this position.
So there's a train railway manager offers some pass for trains.
And at a given time, those pass are assigned to trains, like train operators who want their
trains on those paths.
And once this is set, all the, there's still room for more trains.
And this is what we do here, we find the room for new trains.
Yes?
Five seconds response time.
Yes.
For how many nodes and trains?
Not a lot of trains.
We don't have the tools yet to import the whole, what we call SR.
I'm not sure what the English, like the whole set of trains on the line.
And there's generally we test with a few trains here on the, like the kind of things I showed
and the pass of a few hundred kilometers.
And we do know that it doesn't scale that well with a number of trains.
And we'll work on that kind of questions once we have something actually working and finished.
Yep.
My question about sharing that because we live in France for me, I'm quite concerned
with the security, from cost, et cetera.
When you go from France after Paris to me, you are coming from several countries.
In the France you don't have a go in the railway in between Paris and Lyon.
You can have some stuff that can block the train, et cetera.
Why is the problem you have in local countries?
And especially in Canada, you share that that train for the stuff you see?
I actually didn't really hear your question that well.
Sorry.
If I got it right, like you asked about the troubles we can find along the way.
Mostly, we assume at this step that everything is on time and works as expected.
When people work on the trucks or something like that, we know in advance that it's unavailable.
Yeah.
It's not real time.
Not real time.
Yeah.
It's not real time.
It's actually not exactly last minute, it's generally a few days before the train's actually
won.
So, yeah, it's a fair assumption to just...
Theoretical timetable.
Yeah.
There was one question on the chat that this problem might be a good candidate for an artificial
intelligent plan to solve.
I have to consider that.
Please repeat the question.
Oh, yeah.
Someone has got a chat if artificial intelligence have been considered for this problem.
We do have considered them in the project in general, but not specifically in this context.
I personally don't think it would tell that much.
I mean, it would be a good heuristic to know which path to evaluate before another, but
if we want to still find a good path towards the end, we do need to explore all the kinds
of solutions.
The place where we thought about using artificial intelligence is a decision like which train
goes before one another.
So the context where we really thought about this is not in this case, but when train are
actually running late, which one do we favor over one over the other?
I think it could be a good heuristic in this case, but not really that important.
There was another question.
What are the biggest remaining challenges to be solved?
There is a signaling interface plugging the things together because as I showed in this
slide, this problem, this is a pain.
We do have some leads, like some intuitions that we could do things in some way, but I
won't go too much into details because we don't know if that's true, if the solution
we are thinking about are valid or not.
But we'll work on that in the next few months anyway.
I'm working in an international organization, but an end link aviation, so same kind of
problems, but we have a different dimension.
I'm asking how have you managed or your organization has managed to say we will do that open source
in a region if this type of solution available for others.
So I guess you are working for SNCF, so you had to get some money from SNCF and make open
source.
How have you got agreement on that?
So the question is how we manage to make the project open source in SNCF.
So I'm not actually the one taking those decisions or even negotiating them.
But the general idea, I think, that's my vision of it, is that we don't have any competition
or something like that.
We want the infrastructure for France and I think no one else will.
So maybe the other countries nearby have the same kind of problem and maybe they could
use our solution and maybe contribute to that solution, to these tools.
And generally it makes more sense to contribute than to compete in this context.
Thank you.
Yeah, cool.
Thank you for the spread.
Thank you.
So the presentation has arrived on time.
We are starting in a few minutes with the next panel.
Thank you.