So, we start with three presentations. It's like a routing topic now from three different
countries. We present you three different routing topics, and I think all of us can
relate to this topic, at least as a customer. And it's a pleasure to me to introduce Felix
Gintling from Germany. He's introducing MODIS as a door-to-door platform, what is going
open source in 2020, and is already used by some companies for internal use cases. And
we are really pleased to hear what is MODIS about.
Thank you very much for introducing me. Today I will talk about MODIS project.
This is a very rough overview of MODIS. I think I could talk hours about all the details,
but I tried to make it short, so to give an overview, MODIS is a mobility platform and
is modular, so it has different modules for different purposes, and you can mix and match
all those modules for your use case. But I think the main functionality of MODIS is
the door-to-door routing that involves all kinds of means of transportation. So, this
includes walking, trains, buses, flights, or we have also experiments for ride-sharing
or on-demand integration, basically you name it. Everything that brings you from A to B,
we can use it in MODIS. And to display the data, like the connections, we have also our
own tile server, so this is a very easy way to get your own tile server. Also, if you're
only interested in displaying connections or anything on the map. And of course, for
the user to be able to enter their wish from where to where they want to go, we can also
autocomplete places and it's open source. So, a short history of MODIS or a long history,
basically it started in 1996 when I was still in primary school. So, I cannot tell you much
about it, but there were first experiments about timetable data models and also the first
routing algorithms. And in 2003, it became a multi-criteria optimization algorithm and
I will go into some details later. In 2007, MODIS was the first platform that already
had real-time information and could find connections on this real-time information. So, basically
if you had delays or cancellations or reroutings, this was the first time that you could actually
find alternatives that would work in real-time. Then, 2013, we had a very, very, very, very
important topic. Then, 2013, we started to work on the door-to-door routing and this
is actually my main topic. And there we have all kinds of special topics. For example,
we had one guy working on reliability. So, to find especially reliable connections where
you also consider the reliability of all the alternatives. So, if something breaks, you
find still an alternative that brings you to your destination before your deadline with
a high percentage of reliability considering the data from the past regarding the delays.
Currently, one of our main topics is accessibility. So, we are aiming at finding connections not
just for everybody who has no problems, but for all people who have some disability. And
there are different profiles. So, this is a profile-based approach where you can give
us the information, what profile you have and motors will find those connections regarding
your profile. Additionally, we are working on park and ride. So, if you don't want to
just go from A to B, but you want to go back and you have your car parked somewhere, then
you have dependencies between the outward trip and the return trip. And you cannot plan
those journeys easily with the algorithms that are available on the market because your
outward trip and return trip would not necessarily contain the same parking place. And motors
has an integrated optimization algorithm that optimizes the park and ride problem. Additionally,
we are working on integrating ride hailing and ride sharing. So, different kinds of mobility
and we are mixing everything together and find optimal journeys from door to door using
all of them. Basically, in 2020, then came the time that we made it open source. And
the open source version doesn't contain all of our experiments because those experiments
were like branched from the master branch and it's a lot of work to combine everything
into one version. And so, currently we are working on making all those experiments also
open source and to maintain them all in one consistent version where you can also mix
all the features together. Since we made it open source, we gained some interest also
by other companies. So, our primary partner for all the time since 1996 was Deutsche Bahn,
German Railway. And since then, since we made it open source, also other companies became
interested in using our software and some of them are already using motors in production.
So, and yeah, that's the path and we will be like, I'm happy to see even more usage
of motors in production. Yeah, so you might also be interested who is developing motors.
This is mainly the Technical University of Darmstadt. And we have at currently we have
three researchers that are working on motors. That's me and to others and all the time we
have a lot of students doing their thesis projects or lab topics. And so, we have a
lot of like churn in developers. It's not always the same team. But yeah, that's the
research topic. And as mentioned before, I want to talk a little bit about multi-criteria
optimization because that's one, the main difference between rooting on the street and
rooting with all kinds of transportation means is that, you know, we have a lot of
rooting with all kinds of transportation means is that usually it's not sufficient to only
optimize the travel time or the distance traveled, but you have also other criteria like the
number of transfers or some people are like want to travel cheap or some want to travel
sustainable so they don't want to have a lot of CO2 produced. And yeah, so there are
different criteria and we actually don't know exactly what mix of criteria the user currently
using our software has. So, this is a difficult problem to solve and since we don't know this,
we give them all the optimal solutions regarding the criteria. So, basically we do multi-criteria
optimization and find the Pareto set of all optimal solutions that form an optimal trade-off.
And currently, the main version of MOTIS has the three criteria, departure time, arrival
time, and number of transfers. So, it's better to depart later, arrive earlier, and we want
also to have the number of transfers. So, in this example, we have three connections and
basically, for example, the nine o'clock connection that goes to 10-15 has two transfers, but
it takes longer. And then nine to ten connection has three transfers, but it's faster. And since
we don't know exactly who wants which connection, we just show all of the connections. So, if
we look at those criteria, we would show the optimal connection for the fastest connection
for all number of transfers. And, yeah, basically the approach can be adapted to optimize a
set of all criteria that you can basically measure in math that you can count in a way.
So, how does it work? How do we make the door-to-door routing? Basically, we have two steps.
One step is to compute the connections from the actual address where you start to all the
stations that could connect you to public transport or in general, time-table-based means
of transportation. And we do the same on the destination side. So, we look at all the stations
in proximity to the destination, and we route basically from all those to the destination.
So, we convert these options to go from the start to the station or from the destination
to the destination to a set of edges. And all these edges are then inserted temporarily
in the data model of our main routing algorithm. And for those main routing algorithms, we
support a variety of routing algorithms that optimize the connection, the overall door-to-door
connection. So, here we have, for example, the Raptor routing algorithm, the trip-based
routing algorithm, or just a graph-based solution that is Dijkstra based. And, yeah, so this
is the optimization approach. And it's a nice approach because it guarantees optimality,
and all those algorithms that are named are producing exactly the same results. So, this
is basically our quality assurance that we want to make sure that all the algorithms
that we have in our system produce exactly the same results because they have the same
definition. We are, like, the department at Technical University of Darmstadt that is
producing or working on motors is the algorithm department. So, our focus is basically on
the algorithms. But to be able to show the platform, we have some front-ends, and we
have an Android app. We can show the timetable data on a live map, and we have also an interface
to search the connections and actually use the routing. But those front-ends are currently
not capable to display all the functionality that the backend has. So, our focus is more
on the backend and algorithms. And I want to talk a little bit also about our roadmaps.
So, we are currently working on making those accessible door-to-door routings possible.
That's our main focus. And therefore, we are working on a new data model that is also
capable of displaying or saving the timetable data in a compressed way. So, we don't have
one object per connection. But if a connection takes place on several days of the year and
at the same time, then we store the connection with a bit field that has a one if the connection
takes place at that day and the zero if not. So, this is a very efficient way of encoding
the timetable. So, additionally, we use for the street routing currently OSRM, which is
very intense in memory usage. But there are alternatives, and we are trying to integrate
those two. And of course, as I said before, we are working on bringing more and more of
the research functionality that we have in different branches into the mainline motors
so you can use them together and bring the research into production. That's it about
motors. If there are questions, I'm happy to answer, or I could also make a short demo
because, yeah. So, maybe questions first. Yeah.
Currently, we ask the user to give us the maximum time he would like to use for the
first and last part of the journey for each means of transport. So, he would say,
I would like to travel maximum 20 minutes by car, and that's basically our limit. But
of course, this is only one way to do it, and this is the back end functionality. So,
if you would use this as a user in an app or on a website, this doesn't need to be the
way that the user interacts with the system.
Compared to, for instance, or maybe you were heard of that algorithm, use apparently more
sophisticated for special needs, et cetera, but fundamentally, are there differences in
the approach? I didn't look, like I think their algorithm is not open source, so I couldn't
look into the very details. But from what I've seen, I think they are not doing their
computations in one data model. Like we have basically then one data model where we do
the overall optimization so we can guarantee the optimality on this data model because
it's all included. And from what I've seen, what they do is that they have different
routings and they try to combine the routing results in a post-processing step. And I think
this doesn't guarantee optimality but produces probably reasonable results for the end user.
Thank you. Are you able to take into account like a traffic jam or all the end? What kind
of data do you have inside your app? We have the option to use GTFS RT real-time data for
the timetable-based means of transportation. And currently we are using for the street
and also our arm or like we are planning to support Valhalla. And those can or cannot
depending on how you configure them. So this is not our main focus but this basically depends
on which algorithm you use to compute those first and last edges.
I'm interested in the connection with the APIs so obviously you have to collect a lot
of data for these three-time points, real-time data and so on. And how do you deal with that
within these sizes of data? Do you connect to each and every API of different transport
points that you download all the data, put it all in one folder on your server and give
that folder to Motus. So it has all the timetables in the GTFS format or Hafwah's Hordaten format
and you give it the open street map data and you can give it for the real-time data API
endpoints where Motus will pull regularly like in a one minute or 30 second interval
the real-time data. And so this is basically how all the data comes together in one data
model. So Motus loads all the static timetable data at boot time and possibly does some
pre-processing on it and then in the real-time it pulls real-time data from the sources that
you have configured it to pull. And a proper data model, is trans model of any relevance
in your works? Trans model? Sorry I didn't, I haven't heard about it. Okay, it's the
CN standard concerning data modeling for multimodal transport, this is why I thought that might
be an association, but it's independent. Okay, it's independent. Thank you.
We have more time for questions, but I think Felix is here and you can ask more questions
if you have it. Thank you Felix.