So to have enough time for our last routing specialist now from Finland, we would start
on time.
Yes.
Please, no, it's not working because it's for the camera.
I'm screaming because we don't have an audience here.
Yeah, it's not a microphone.
But let's welcome our last speaker from Finland.
It's Gerald Lapallain.
I hope I speak your name well.
And yeah, we are really glad to have you with us.
Introducing Diki Transits to us from Finland, we expect a lot because you are already known
for great mobility solutions.
And yeah, let's give him the chance to explain Diki Transits to us and highlight the really
interesting components.
Thank you, Gerald.
Okay.
Hello.
Hopefully you can hear me well.
My name is Gerald Lapallain.
I'm from Finland, a set, and I work as a developer on the open trip planner and the Diki Transit
projects.
And today I'm here to talk about the Diki Transit project.
So what is Diki Transit?
It's an open source project that does multi-modal public transportation journey planning.
It was founded in Finland around 2014 or 15.
I have personally been working on the project since 2017.
The goal of the project was to replace existing legacy propriety journey planners.
And the project is funded by three transportation authorities or sort of authorities in Finland.
The project has, or the components of the projects have since been used elsewhere, for
example, in Germany.
The project consists of user interfaces, which I'm going to talk more about in this presentation,
Open Packend Services and Open APIs.
So first, a bit about the pack and services.
So for routing and much more, we are using open trip planner.
Hans will have a presentation next about open trip planners.
I'm not going to go too much into it now.
For geocoding, we are using Pelya's that we have further improved.
So it deals with GTFS data and so on.
And for maps, we are using this project called HSL map server, which uses dialogue GL and
OpenStreetMap.
And we also use OpenStreetMap for the geocoding as well.
So now for the user interfaces.
So first, this is the digit transit user interface.
It's written in JavaScript and uses React.
It's responsive.
Most of our users are on mobile devices.
It's browser based and it's also meant to be so you can use it with screen readers and
so on.
It's configurable.
You can have different themes.
My screenshots will be from different sites, so they will have different configurations
and themes.
So this is the front page on desktop.
Here you can start the it in a research.
You can enter origin and destination, which can be like addresses or stops or whatever.
And you can add some favorites or use favorites for locations.
And then you can enter these stops near you pages.
I will display later on what this means.
And then you have this search box for stops and routes and bike rental station and bike
and car parks and so on.
I won't show those views now because the time is a bit limited.
And on the map, if I would have tuned in a bit more, there would have been more.
So now it's just showing some stations.
So these are the itineraries on mobile.
The view on the left, it's showing the summary of the found results.
It's showing multiple itineraries in this view and just like a summary of those.
The length of the legs is based on the duration of the leg.
And that's like we support real time data.
So those three numbers are real time estimates.
And this is more the model.
So in this such instance, there's buses, trains, metros, walking.
There could be bike rental.
And then we have like this model also speed into separate such as this on the top.
There's like cycling.
There could be just walking, combining cycling with public transportation or combining cars
with public transportation.
And on the right, the view is shown when you click open some such as then.
It shows more details about the such as then.
And it shows the map.
If the trip was happening right now, we could display the relevant vehicle on map for the
such as thens.
And yeah, there's more details here.
This view is the stop near you page that I mentioned earlier.
So we did some design and discussed with real users.
And they found this view to be useful.
So we have split this into like different modes.
It shows the next departures for buses in this view.
But there's another view that shows for trains or metro or whatever is available in the city.
And there's also one view that shows the departures for your ferret stops.
And these stops are the stops that are near you or select a location.
And on the map, it will show the vehicles that travel through the stops and also the
bus lines.
So here's an example how this digit transit UI can be integrated into different website.
This is the front page for the Helsinki Regional Transportation Authority.
On the left side, we have the same components we had in the front page from the digit transit
UI.
This is done through shared components.
So this only acts like an entry point.
So once user does select locations here, he or she will be redirected into the digit transit
user interface.
And here's another example how digit transit UI can be integrated.
This is done through an iframe widget.
There's a view which can be used to generate this iframe snippets.
And this is for like general routing, but it's also possible to have only like this
for like walking or cycling.
So the user will be redirected to the correct view.
This is another project, another user interface.
Previously, we called it virtual monitor, but it's now, now there's more called stop
monitor, which kind of describes it better.
So this stop monitor is meant for like businesses or private persons or public transportation
authorities.
So they can have the screen somewhere which displays the departures for the stops near
that location.
So this view is for, I should also mention that this is written with TypeScript and also
used Vect.
This view is for generating this view, the stop monitor view.
In this you can have multiple stops on the same view, and you can have multiple views
that can rotate based on some time frames.
So for every five seconds it will change which view is shown.
And there's many options for layouts here.
Here is just an example entry result.
You can have like this speed view where there's departures on the left and on the right.
This is for airport.
And on the bottom there's relevant alerts for that stop.
And this stop can be modified later on.
So once you have created this, it's not really final.
You can still do modifications.
So what's next in the Digi-Trent project?
We started the project so early on that OpenTree Planner only had version one out.
So we are currently working on improve the support for using OpenTree Planner version
two.
It's already working, but there's some optimizations that can be done.
So the Digi-Trent UI that I showed, it's like version two, and we have version three that
is better optimized for using OpenTree Planner two.
And then we will have a possibility to have a map view on the stop monitor so you can
have display the vehicles that are going to the stop so the user can see, okay, this vehicle
is going here.
Maybe I should start going to the stop.
And then we will improve the support for first and last one services.
So we have already been supporting like bike rental stations and in Germany they have added
support for like scooter rentals, like floating vehicles.
And we will also focus more on like flexible public transportation.
So there's many types of services like that.
And this can include like taxis or stuff like that.
So for more information, you're going to visit digi-trent.fi, which contains some documentation
relevant to the project and the repositories are hosted under this HSL development community
GitHub account.
There's many projects there, some are not Digi-Trent projects, but if you search for
Digi-Trent projects, you will find the relevant ones.
And we have this email address, digi-trent.fi, which if you send message there, I will get
the message.
So thank you, that was the presentation.
Now it's time for questions if you have any.
Yes.
For me, it's interesting for your country that I would like to have this kind of information
for Europe, European community first.
And it would be interesting to have the best range to reach a place everywhere in Europe.
And it's not easy for the moment.
You have only national lines.
And so I remember it was 20 years ago when it was SIPRA with regional trains in Germany,
but there was low and high problem with that.
Also I know also to go from Brussels to Firebook in Bridesville in Germany, it was SIPRA by
the train in Germany and so on.
So all this kind of information and you plan to have to extend your project to the European
planet?
So we might expand it to include Estonia for this Finnish project.
There's still some issues with scaling this because if you're using multi-criteria search,
it doesn't scale to this continental scale yet on the machines we are running on.
So there's some optimizations needed to get it work.
Yep.
Are you working on integrating ticketing so you can also buy in your app, the ticket and
APIs on discovering the ticket price?
This might be included in the first and last mile services.
I'm not quite sure on the details yet.
We are still on the design phase on what we will support, but that is an idea that we
have discussed previously.
Yeah.
Okay.
Thank you, Jay.
Thank you.