Yep, okay, then we'll start. Well, everyone's now seen all the slides, so we can just go
down the pub. So, as this part of the slide says, my name is Steve, and as that part of
the slide says, I'm a bit of a geek. Now, if we've all turned up to the right room,
this is a talk about old computers and emulation and things that I've learned about old computers
through emulation. Over the course of the next 20 minutes or so, I'm going to look at
why emulation is really quite fun. I want to mention these seven things that I've learned
over the last year or so, and then the honoree mentions just some other stuff that I found
that was too good to go to waste. So, before all of that, who am I? What have I done to
earn a place on this stage? Or is this slide should really be called? It's the ego slide,
where the speaker brags about themselves for 10 minutes while everyone else gets bored.
My slide has that on it. That's not a computer, that's Lego. Yeah. So, who am I? Well, I'm
a game developer. I've been a developer for quite a few years. I've written console games,
I've written mobile games. I've written a book,
which was crowdfunded last year. And it's a very good book on old computers, because
that's essentially all I do. I've spoken at this conference a few times before, and I
still haven't got it right. So, everything that's on that slide is not really that useful.
It's about what's not on that slide. I'm not a professional retro developer. I haven't
built the Vega. I've not built the new Commodore 64 machine. Everything that I have done with
retro has been just me having a fiddle around with electronics. Essentially, that's a long-winded
way of saying, if I can do this, anyone can. So, why is emulation useful? Well, it just
is. And it isn't necessarily about games. It's about being able to see the machine.
How does it boot up? How does it start? What goes on behind the hood? And you can do it
safely. You can't break anything when you're running this stuff through an emulator. So,
where should we start? The Jupiter race. Each of these, I'm going to mention a couple of
emulators that I've used and experimented with. Obviously, MAME has probably got all
of these anyway, but MAME is just too big for me to compile. I like the smaller emulators
because I can compile them easier and I can actually see. That way, I've got the development
environment of the emulator and I can then run it through GCC as well. So, what did I
know about the Jupiter race before all of this? Well, it uses fourth. The first thing
anyone will say about the Jupiter race, well, it programs in fourth. And it's just like
the ZX81 because the guys, Vickers and Alvasa, worked on the ZX81. They also worked on the
beginning of the spectrum. And they said, why is Clive Sinclair making all this money
on our computer? We could build a computer ourselves and we could make all the money.
And they did. Unfortunately, they didn't sell any machines. So, they made all the money
of about 4,000 quid. But it's a very nice machine and the prices on the old eBay are
just stupid. It is why I don't have one. And when I said it's like the ZX81, it's very
like the ZX81. This is the code from two different emulators that reads the keyboard. Can you
spot the difference? No. There is one difference. Jupiter 8 added an extra shift button in the
bottom right. And that's the only change between the two machines' keyboard code. One thing.
What else do we know? Oh, it's got a font which is stored in memory. And this was really
interesting. Because the font is stored in memory. But this is the font. But it's not
stored like that. Well, if you have a look, look at some of the, it's stored here. That's
not a very big memory location for the code. So, what's it actually doing? Well, if you
look at letters, you know, some of these, they could go below the line. But most don't.
So and you've got some things which go to the top and some that don't. So, if you've
got a capital letter that doesn't go above a line and go below the line, why do you need
all eight bytes to store that letter? You don't. You just chop the top off. And then
you write a piece of code that puts that byte back in before you render it. So they managed
to save a whole chunk of code, the graphics symbols you see at the top. They're not stored
in memory. They're generated by code. Again, you've saved another 200 something bytes by
doing that. In fact, the only symbol in the whole font which is copied in its entirety
is the copyright symbol. It's the only one that uses all eight bytes. And everything
else is just modified some way. And it took only 64 bytes of code to do all this munging.
So that's quite a big saving over every single top and every single bottom of each letter.
This machine. Oh, there's a couple of murmurs for that one. Good. It's one of my favorites.
Obviously, when anyone mentions the Welsh computer industry, they have to mention the
dragon because it's pretty much the only one that existed. But it's a great machine. The
6.9 processor is a phenomenal piece of work. Wonderful machine. It's also told it's a bit
of a rip off for the Tandy Coco. It isn't. Both the dragon and the Tandy Coco were based
on the same reference design that Motorola put out to basically sell their chips. So
they both both used exactly the same setup. The other thing that people know about the
dragon other than the fact it uses Microsoft basic is green. The video chip defaults to
green. Which color green? That's color green. Seriously, dudes. Why who thought that was
a good thing to boot up to in the morning? It means your games look like this. Now, luckily,
someone had the bright idea that you could actually just not use the color. Build all
your games in black and white because then they look a bit better. And they look like
this, which is fairly respectable for a machine from 1982. This one is Jet Set Willy. Very
well known that the 48K spectrum had Jet Set Willy, but the much smaller Dragon 32 had
Jet Set Willy with more rooms in it. Because they did all the graphics in black and white,
so there was less color needed, so they got more data space. And of course, the processor
was a lot better than the Z80. What else do we know about the dragon? Yeah, that's its
font. It's not very pretty, I'm afraid. But this is the bit that I found interesting.
This sets up the graphics mode. At no point are you actually sending data across the bus.
If you write to a memory address, FFC6, for example, it will set a bit. Doesn't matter
what data is on the data bus, it's just not read. If you write to C6, it writes a zero
bit. If you write to C7, it writes a one bit. You can send data by just writing anything
to an address. That, I thought, was a really interesting approach. Turns out it's not the
only machine to do it. Turns out Arm did it as well. The Archimedes, they just said, right,
we're not going to connect the data bus to this chip, it'll be cheaper. And then we'll
write data to it just by toggling addresses. Nice, clever way. So what computer's coming
next, everybody? It's the Game Boy. Pretty sure most people have had one of these. They're
a bit like the Nokia phones of their era. You drop it on the pavement and the pavement
cracks. That sort of thing. So what did I know about the Game Boy? Well, there are so
many emulators out there that emulate this and some variation of it. Four Shades of Green
and had a version of DRM. Now, I know where we are, so I'm pretty safe in saying DRM is
a bad thing. But this is what they did. Now, that code is obviously too small for you to
be able to see, but that's not important. What's important is that it's all on the screen.
That's the first 256 bytes of the Nintendo Game Boy ROM. And in this lot, it has to set
up the graphics system, the sound system, it has to do its copy protection on the cartridge
you put in to make sure it's an official cartridge. And it does that in that 256 bytes of code.
And then this is the bit that does the check. You put two pointers into memory, one into
the cartridge that's been inserted, and one into the 256 bytes of ROM. And it says, okay,
if all of these bytes in the cartridge match all of these bytes in the ROM, then it's a
legitimate cartridge. You're allowed to play and the game then continues. But what bytes
are these? Well, there's not many of them. You can see it goes around the loop. And if
it doesn't match, the machine just locks up. That's fine. Well, these are the bytes that
it checks. Can anyone spot the pattern in those bytes? Let me show you in a graphical
form. Anyone spot the pattern in those bytes? The logo that comes up when you switch on
the Game Boy is that it's in code. So it checks for the Game Boy Nintendo logo at the start.
This means if you're doing a dodgy cartridge, you have to copy the Nintendo logo into your
cartridge. This means you are committing a copyright law infringement. And because it's
a logo, it's a trademark law as well. Yeah, as much as I hit the down thing, whoever came
up with that idea, that was a smart idea. I just disagree with it. Pac-Man. Originally
called Puckman, I can't think why they would change the name. It's a lovely little machine
and it's incredible when you consider how much memory it has. 3K of memory for a full
screen of color graphics. Now the way that does this is through tiling and through a
lot of clever hardware. But the bit that's interesting is how it's laid out. Again, you
don't really need to look at this, but if you come up close, the memory goes in this
direction, then in that direction, then in that direction, then down the other side.
It's a weird way of mapping. But it means that when you get to level 256, this happens.
I don't expect anyone to have got there, but thanks to emulation, I can write one byte
and I can actually play level 256. Now it looks like the screen is all corrupt because
some kind of, it's not. You know when you're playing the game and you get oranges and strawberry
and fruit in the middle a bit here, that's what it's trying to draw. They never thought
anyone would get to level 256, so they never had a piece of code that checked the number
of pieces of fruit that it should draw. And this is just running over all memory, drawing
all the fruit that it can find and then the rest of memory that it can find. That bit
there, that's brilliant. So, Pac-Man done. ZX81. Any fans of the ZX81? I was expecting
a bigger cheer to be honest. We've got two fans over there. First machine I ever had.
Don't worry, that's not one of my security questions. 1K of memory. One kilobyte. No
colour, no sound. It's a complete moot. But we had a chess program that ran in 1K. There
was a 3D monster mice, not 1K, but still 3D games on a piece of plastic, basically a black
plastic cheese wedge. You can go 16K RAM pack. Wow, think of all that extra memory. What
can you do with that? And a very interesting fact that I found out completely by accident.
I was taking a photograph of this for the book and there's a big story about the ZX81
RAM pack wobble. And because this RAM pack is set on the back of the machine, it does
this and then it crashes. Well, people solve this problem by blue tack and with glue. Some
people solve the problem by just buying a better machine. I solve the problem by actually
sticking the two together with screws and really folding it in nice and tight. I thought
I'm going to get a picture of this and this famous RAM pack wobble thing. So I measured
the angle between the ZX81 case and the 16K RAM pack. It's 16 degrees. So what did I find
about ZX81? Well, how does it know there's a 16K RAM pack in there or not? Well, it just
tries everything. It just writes to every memory address it can find. And when it slowly
says, oh, well, I've got no memory addresses over here. It says, well, that's where your
memory stops. Just writes data into it and then reads it back again. Very simple, but
effective. The grown up version of ZX81 was the spectrum. This one did have color of sorts.
It had sound of sorts. It went beep. But what a machine. There are so many emulators for
this machine, it's not even funny. Even I've written one. But what can we say about the
machine or the keyboard other than being rubbery dead flesh thing is how the keyboard's red.
It's kind of interesting. And it works this way. A Z80 machine has an input output system
using memory and an input output system using ports. So you can communicate with systems
that aren't based on a memory bus. So what does it do to read the keyboard? It does an
out request onto a port. And if there was a zero in any one of these bit positions, it
means the key is down. What a traditional thing at a lot of these machines are the early
keys. It would always be negative logic. So if you have zero, zero, zero, zero, for example
in that, it means all of those keys are down. Which funnily enough means it's quicker to
check for five keys being down than it is to check for one key. Because if you want
to check for a very specific key, you've got to check the individual bit. Whereas if you
just don't care about it, you just say, right, well, if it's not, if it isn't one, one, one,
if it's, you know, it will just trigger as one of these keys is down. That's all it needs
to worry about. And finally, of our seven, the Commodore 64, which I'm kind of contractually
obliged to sort of put in since I put in Sinclair as well before. Commodore 64, what can we
say? Well, it's a bread bin. And there are far too many emulators as well to mention.
It was originally called the Vic 40, because the one before this was the Vic 20. And by
a nice coincidence, 40 and hex is also 64. A lot of memory, 64 kilobytes of memory, 64K
of memory. Hang on. Wait a minute. How does that work? How can you have a machine with
64K of memory in the address range is always 64K. So you've got 64K of memory. And that's
all you could ever get. Where's everything stored? Where's your basic interpreter? Where's
the system? If you've got 64K of memory, there's not enough room to store the system. Well,
this is what it did. It gave you all the memory and they said, actually, no, I need this bit
for my ROM. I need this bit for the SID chip to do the sound. I need this bit for my kernel.
So essentially, you don't have 64K of memory. It's all hidden by the ROMs. But there was
an instruction you could call, which was that. And it would basically say, yeah, I know there's
a basic ROM over there. But really, I know machine code. So just ignore the ROM. And
it just switches the whole ROM off. If you don't want to use the kernel or the system
ROMs there to do the rendering to the screen, you can just say, well, I know where the screen
data is, I'll just write to it directly. So you can turn that one off as well. And essentially,
if you're prepared to go the whole machine code route, you can just turn it all off.
And you've got 64K of memory. It was the only way you could have done it. So what are the
other mentions that we should do? Well, I should probably mention the X81 again, because
it is just an amazing machine. I also have to mention the Game Boy again, obviously,
not because it's a brilliant emulator, but one of the talks later on is about the Game
Boy emulator. And they're in the room and I don't want to offend them. Isn't that right?
The Spectrum, the jet pack game. There's a couple of things I'm using about this game.
One very good game. The people who wrote it later became rare, but did golden eye. This
drew the screen backwards. Most people think when you draw a screen, you start at the top
and you go down to the bottom, right? That's how you do it. Well, they couldn't do that
because their code was a bit slow. So what they realized is if I'm drawing the screen
this way, if you don't get to the bottom of the screen before the TV gets to the bottom
of the screen, you only ever get half a screen. So what they did is they drew it backwards.
You start at the bottom and go up to the top. That way it doesn't matter if your game's
too slow. You're only ever going to get the crossover once beflamed. Worst case scenario.
So as the screen is refreshing this way, you're rendering that way. And if you ever see a
little black line when you play jet pack, that's what it is. It couldn't render the
screen quick enough. And it's just missed the flyback code. The other thing is it's
also 16K game, which means you can fit it onto a cartridge and this cartridge can take
the place of the Spectrum ROM. And this was a very unpopular thing. I mean, you think,
you know, games lady, look, who remembers cassette tapes? I've suddenly realized we
might have an audience that have no idea what cassette tape is. These games were loaded
off cassette and they would make a screechy noise. Yeah, that sort of thing. That's a
good rendition. Let's play. I'm sure somewhere somewhere can actually sing the sound tunes
from the Spectrum and actually load them into a machine. That's probably possible. I don't
have pitch perfect, but I'm sure it's possible. So they think, why would I want to listen
to seven minutes of screechy noises? Sure, I just want to put a cartridge in. So Sinclair
made a cartridge system. It had 10 games on it. And that was it flop. But because it fitted
in 16K, it could be done as a cartridge. And because it fits in the same memory as the
ROM means you can't use any of the Spectrum ROM capabilities in your code. The Acorn BBC
Micro, popular for anyone who was in the UK during the 80s, because this was the computer
we had at school. It was deemed educational enough to be allowed in the classroom. What's
nice about this one is that they have a little credits page in the ROM. Now it's very difficult
to see that on an actual real world machine. Because when I showed you the Commodore 64
and the ROM was overlapping the RAM, the same thing is true of the BBC. Its ROM was overlapped
by something else. So you can't read the thanks to page. But because of emulation, you can.
And you can see all the people they thank. Pretty much everyone and their wife. And they
thank the city of Cambridge. No, nop. No operation. No operation. It doesn't do anything. It's
an assembler instruction that pretty much every machine has. Just does nothing. So why
would you ever code that? Well, when you're poor, like what I is, you don't have an assembler.
Most people, you know, you have an assembler, you type in some reasonably Englishy type
things into the assembler, it would convert it into machine code and then the machine
code would run on the machine. I didn't have an assembler. So I had to hand assemble everything
by looking up in a reference book and saying I want to do this instruction. This is the
number I need to do. And I typed that number in manually to my machine. Now when you do
a jump that goes backwards, you have to write it in two's complement. And a jump like that,
say f0 is back about, what is it, about 16 instructions about. But I can never remember
if it includes the instruction itself or not. So this instruction is two bytes. So is this
going back 16 or 14? No idea. So all I would do is I'd put a big stack of nops. So wherever
it jumped to, it's going to be a safe instruction. And it's not going to mess up the machine.
Turns out I wasn't the only person to have ever done that. Microsoft basic. If you type
wait 6502, it prints Microsoft on the screen. Because these bytes are hidden in the computation
for the sign function. But that's not ASCII. If you mask off those bits, shift them around
a bit, subtract something else, then it's Microsoft but backwards. And it was Microsoft
and Apple put a lot of these sort of things. Steve Jobs was very scared. And quite rightly
so. Loads of people were trying to copy the Apple 2. Very, very popular computer, particularly
in America. So Steve Jobs put a thing in there where if you went up and you pressed a special
combination of keys, it would put up a big icon saying stolen from Apple. I was going
to put that on the slide. Unfortunately, copyright means I can't put it on the slide. But I can
show you Microsoft's, one of Microsoft's many little things they put in there. So with
that I shall end. My beer is getting seriously low. I will update my FOSDEM scorecard. There
we go. You'd think after 23 I'd be good at this by now, right? So with that in mind,
I'll open the floor to questions or even if you've got nice stories about old computers,
this is a talk where it's acceptable to use the phrase, this is more of a comment than
a question. So with that in mind, I'll say thank you very much and over to you.
How are we doing? Yeah, we've got eight minutes for questions. All general chit chat. Whatever
we have. There is one over there. Can I tell you on the what's right? Oh, yes. So I'm
not going to be able to do that. So what about Amstrad? Amstrad as a company, if you loved
Amstrad on I think the fifth of June 1984, you hated them the day after because they
bought Sinclair. In America there's a show called The Apprentice. In the UK we have a
version where Alan Sugar, who created Amstrad, essentially, he bought he had his own range
of machines, CPC 6664s and things like that. They are surprisingly good machines for a
machine that sold a couple of million copies. It doesn't sound like a lot nowadays. But
back then that it was a really good, well made machine, surprisingly enough. Unfortunately,
I don't have one. You have and keep it so. Yes, they did. There was meant to be that
their chips are called Roland and Dave, I think, named after the designers. Yeah, so
it's another that I do machine. Yeah, the spectrum and what it spawned really did sort
of say, well, we already know that at so we're going to go and set up our own computer company
and use the ZT again. It's not that it was the best machine or the best processor, but
the ZT did get used in so many things. So it's this is kind of disproportional to its
value as a chip. But it's good to hear some Amstrad here. Yes. Yes, it was. So the question
is about the I didn't I didn't realize I was doing funnies. Yes. So the Commodore 64 was
called Vic 40 in sort of pre production prototyping. ZX Spectrum was called ZT2 during its prototyping
stage. Not unsurprisingly, it came after the ZX80 and ZX81. The bits which I'm so glad
you brought it up because it's something I forgot to mention earlier. The ZX80 that Sinclair
produced was named because of the Z80 chip. It was Z80 chip with the extra special ingredient
ZX for extra. ZX81 was called 81 because it came out the year after and was therefore
was related to the year not ZX80. The spectrum was called the spectrum because it had colour.
Therefore, ZX81 is probably the only computer ever named for its year of release. I've never
found another one. Except probably a gateway 2000. But that's a PC and they're boring.
So I have a feeling that it's predominantly Western devices. You also know some like non-Western
one like Russia. Yes. So the question is, do I know anything about non-Western machines,
Russian Chinese machines? And the answer is no. Because I'm of that sort of age, I remember
when there was an iron curtain and it was called an iron curtain, whether that's politically
correct or not, I don't know. But we couldn't get those machines into the West and they
couldn't get our machines across. So they would essentially either smuggle some in or
they would find circuit diagrams and then rebuild their own. And there is a massive
scenario of clones and copies and variations from what used to be the whole sort of Eastern
block. They are all impressive. They look like they're homemade and they just look
amazing. It's just the physicality of the machine. You know, they are carbon copies
of the other spectrums and things of their ilk, but they are lovely.
In Japan, I think Japan was Western enough. Apparently the company, which was known for
making mechanical games also released the console, was supposed to be an electrical
console but was an electronic mechanical. It was a home console actually. So I can't remember
the name. So repeating the question for the cloud, something, something, something, Japanese
stuff, tell me, electromechanical computer. How do we do? Okay. I think you're about to
kick me off, aren't you? Almost.
Just a comment. I don't know if you are aware, but reading the keyboard on the spectrum,
the last eight beats actually select each of each row of the keyboard. So you can do
very simple routine to read. Is any key pressed by just doing a single read?
Yes, press any key. If it's quick, think.
The youngest machine I've made an emulator for. Tricky. It probably is a spectrum or
something like that. Yeah, I mean, one of the first ones I did was a chip eight emulator,
which is an interesting one. Everyone, if you want to write an emulator, write chip
eight emulator, because the machine never existed. There was things like the COSMAC
that was it back in the 1970s. This machine would actually run a sort of a simulator or
an emulator inside itself to run the chip eight code. Chip eight doesn't exist in the
machine. It was an interpreted language that was being run on a 70s processor. If you see
any little TV games where you'd sort of play a version of punk, the chip inside that is
probably an RCA 1802, which would run the simulated chip eight language. So sorry, I
went the other way with the question from the youngest to oldest, but maybe. OK, any
other we got? We got two possums.
It was an Apple one story I wanted to get in, but I didn't think I could get that in
in the time frame. And it's about the Apple two ROM. Sorry, the Apple one ROM, it doesn't
do much. It's just basically write data into memory, read data from memory and execute
a program. Use a jump if carry flag, because the carry flag is always going to be set in
one particular way. So it acts like a different type of jump because that different type of
jump didn't exist. But yeah, I didn't have quite the room to include everything because
my time is up. Get lost. Go home.