All right.
We are ready.
We fix it.
We broke again and we fix it again.
I didn't do anything.
The green shirts did.
All right. So next we have Francisco Iglesias.
No, but we're going to start good.
Yes, sir.
To me at least, just going to rant.
But to me, it's always interesting to see how
Imlation is used in the enterprise.
People say money world.
So we're not.
So let's see how it goes.
All right.
Okay. Hi everybody and welcome to this presentation.
My name is Francisco Denan.
I work at AMD with QMU Development and System C Development.
Can you speak up a bit?
Yes, can you speak?
Okay. So I'll try.
I have a little threat problem.
But okay. So today I will be speaking about
our open source co-simulation solution.
The agenda of the talk then.
It is first I will give a short introduction into
what co-simulation is and thereafter I will be speaking a little
about AMD Xilinx QMU itself and proceed with introducing
Live System C, LM-SOC and
the sister repository System C, LM CoSim demo.
Lastly, I will show a short demo where QMU is co-simulating
with a couple of RTL memories
using the infrastructure in
the system C, LM-SOC.
Sorry, can you speak up a little bit more?
Even more. Yes.
Yes. In this slide,
I tried to capture one of the trade-offs that is done when
you choose simulation technique for your RTL
and it is the trade-off between speed and design capacity visibility.
We see that the three techniques that is used for RTL development,
RTL simulation or remulation,
FPGA prototyping, they all come with a different cost on the simulation speed.
On the left side here also,
we have the virtual platforms that are fast and great for software development,
but they do not help with pure RTL debugging or development.
So an approach that can be used here to try to leverage from the two worlds here is
to place a portion of interest in the portion of the RTL,
on one of the RTL simulation techniques,
and then keep the rest of their system modeled in one of the virtual platforms.
This way, you will then keep most of the system simulated at a quite fast speed,
while still keeping the visibility to this portion of RTL that is in focus.
So this is what we mean with co-simulation that you're mixing these two worlds.
In our open source co-sim solution,
we have the Xilinx Q-mu where we model the processing systems of the FPGAs,
and then we have System C that we use for modeling the programmable logic,
and LIM System C, the LAM System C,
it has bridges that allows us to connect the System C models of RTL,
and also FPGA prototypes and the hardware emulators.
I will be speaking more about the bridges shortly.
But first, a little about the AMD Xilinx Q-mu fork.
So this is where we have our improved support and modeling for the Xilinx platform system,
and today it is based on the mainland Q-mu version 7.1.0,
and we upgrade it around once a year to a more recent mainland version,
and the AMD Xilinx Q-mu then has some extra functionality.
One of these is that it can create machines through a hardware machine,
a hardware DTB, and this allows us for having a more flexible machine creation and modification process.
And the AMD Xilinx Q-mu also has an implementation of the remote port protocol.
This protocol is the protocol that is used when we co-simulate both different Q-mu architectures,
and also when we co-simulate with System C.
This is an overview of this, where we see an AR-64 Q-mu co-simulating with a micro-blaze Q-mu,
and also with a System C application on the side.
Continuing with the LIB System C, the LMSSC,
this is a project that was started by Edgar Iglesias 2016, and the license is MIT.
One of the core features is that it has the remote port protocol implementation in System C,
that is then used for connecting with Q-mu and co-simulating with Q-mu.
And going together with this, it also has System C wrappers, what we call...
these are wrappers for our syncs in Campi Versa, for also Net-10.
And the short description of a wrapper is that it wraps Q-mu into a System C module,
so that for the rest of the System C application, the interaction from the other modules with Q-mu
is done through the standard System C interfaces, as TLM and signals, etc.
The library also has TLM bridges into Axi 4, Axi 3, Axi 4i, TPB, A-slide, CHI6X, CXS, TLP, XDM-II.
And a bridge converts the communication from the TLM side into the protocol-specific side.
So here's an example of the TLM-II Axi bridge, which translates TLM-II Axi.
And this bridge is what allows us to co-simulate, for example, in this case an Axi, DUT,
that has been generated from RTL.
So we see here that the System C wrapper communicates through TLM to the bridge,
that then converts this TLM to Axi signaling, and communicates through this Axi signaling with the DUT.
And this is how Q-mu on the left-hand side can access the DUT.
There are also RTL bridges in the library for Axi 4, 3, Axi 4i, CHI, and CXS.
And the RTL bridges have two components.
The first one is the bridge itself that is placed on the FPGA or in a hardware emulator.
And the other component is the driver of the bridge that is placed on the System C application software side.
So the way it goes is that the TLM transaction enters the driver,
which then configures the RTL bridge to replicate this transaction as an Axi transaction, for example,
inside the FPGA or the hardware emulator.
And this is an example of when these bridges are used with an Albeio U250 card,
where we have between the bridge and the bridge driver and the bridge,
we have some infrastructure there, a PCIe that the FIGO PCIe next to the emulator.
And one can see these components as a transport channel
for where the driver accesses go through towards the RTL bridge.
And looking at how it looks inside a hardware emulator is very similar.
But instead of PCIe, here the vendor bridges are used for this transport.
In the library, we also have protocol checkers for Axi 4, Axi 3, Axi 4 Lite and A-Slite CHI.
And the protocol checkers, they are connected to the signals and monitor the signals
and try to find issues, violations to the protocols.
Also in the library, we have modules that can be used for generating ACE traffic.
So we have ACE, ACE Lite masters and ACE interconnect.
So the masters here, they generate ACE transactions towards the interconnect.
And the interconnect will then, when required, snoop the other masters
and otherwise forward the transaction to the TLA memory at the bottom.
We have a similar setup for a CHI where we have request nodes that generate CHI traffic.
And a CHI interconnect that does snooping when required
or forwards the request to a slave node at the bottom.
Also in the library, we have a tool called PySimGen
that can generate simulations from IP exec descriptions.
And there's a basic TLM traffic generator that one can configure to generate randomized traffic
or provide a description of transactions to issue.
And there are some simple easy co-simulation examples
that one can have a look at as a starting point.
There's a lot of documentation for all the components
and we also have an extensive test suite.
The system seat, the LEM co-sim demo is also a project that was started by Edgar Iglesias, 2008-16.
And the license is MIT and this contains several Q-MU co-simulation demos
where we co-simulate the CMP Q-MU and Versal Q-MU with PL model on the system seat side.
And there's also a RISC-V demo where a RISC-V Q-MU is co-simulating with an open source
Ethernet controller core on the system seat side.
We have several x86 Q-MU that co-simulate with PCA endpoint models on the system seat side.
And there is also a PI-SimGen demo where the system seat side of the co-simulation
has been completely generated from IP exact.
And this demos they demonstrate how to embed the LEM system seat library in an own project
and how to use it.
So for the demo that I'll show now, it is a...
Here I will be launching a Linux system on the SYNC-MP Q-MU.
And it will be co-simulating with a system seat app where that includes a couple of RTL memories.
One of the RTL memories is has an ACSE-4 interface.
And the second one has an ACSE-4 light interface.
On the ACSE-4 light signals, there's a protocol checker connected.
And I also modified the ACSE-4 light memory here and injected an error so that we can
see that the protocol checker finds this.
So let's see them.
I'll have to...
So we see here that on the...
This is the left terminal.
This is where Q-MU is being launched.
And on the yellow terminal on the top is where the system seat application has been launched.
And we will start by doing some accesses to the ACSE-4 memory.
And thereafter, here comes the accesses for ACSE-4 memory.
And then thereafter, we will do an access towards the ACSE-4 light memory that has
an error in it.
And here we see that the protocol checker found the error and outputted some description
message.
After the simulation, you get a trace that we can inspect.
And we can see here, follow the ACSE signals and look at the transactions just issued.
See that it is the expected data that we're seeing in here.
And you can see those at the bottom here.
That these are the data that we were writing to the memory.
Then the protocol checker's error is also connected to a signal in this case.
So for a transaction that failed, it can be found when this signal has been asserted.
So this is seen at the bottom here, where there is the asserted signal.
And then we can look into the transaction here and find the problem.
And that is all about what I had today.
And so thank you for listening.
We were here today and
we knew you were here and again.
with me. Yes. So how do we decide the features that we implement? And it's
actually the demand that drives this. So if we see that some team
internally at AMD Xilinx needs a feature in QMU then we implement it. Or if we see
this a feature that might be useful later going forward, not
right now but perhaps in a year or so, then we will consider implementing it too.
And often it ends up that our demands are pretty similar to all other
developers or all other demands. So if we implement a feature it
often becomes useful for others as well, not only for the Xilinx, AMD Xilinx.
And a small follow-up, do you guys probably do agile like the rest of the world?
I'm curious about how do you guys refine the story like this in agile terms.
Yeah, okay. How do we use agile development in this?
I don't care about agile, I really care about refinements. I don't like agile action.
How do you guys brainstorm together on a feature? What do you put on paper?
It needs to be this, but how do we do this? Because it's not
always comparable to something that already exists with AMD Xilinx.
It's usually something that's never been done before.
I'm really sorry about this question.
Yeah, no, it's a very good question and I have to admit that I'm not sure if we have such a process
that we're probably looking at here. We get a request in our group implement.
We need this feature from, for example, one of the RTL groups. They need a feature
where they ask us and we implement it. So we don't have really a process where we
kind of do this very agile in that sense. This is our team. It might be different in other teams.
So Chris, how do you get the System C model from Verilog and does that also work for
Cogen generated IP which might be encrypted?
So how do we get the System C model from Verilog?
There's an open source tool named Verilator that will Verilog and create the model for you.
But that's not going to work for the Cogen generated IP which is encrypted and which Verilog can't process it.
For that time I'm not sure how to do that. Sorry for that.
There's no free line.
I don't have to speak on that because I have to admit that I'm mostly on the QEMU development side.
But if you pick me up afterwards I can take your card and see if I can contact you, give you a correct contact.
Is there something for VHDL as well?
I think there are tools that do this.
But if there is a tool that automatically generates the System C model from VHDL,
there are tools apparently. I'm pretty sure there are too. But we have not used it.
Are you limiting yourself to the synthesable subset of System C or do you not care?
No, we don't limit ourselves to System C now.
I'm coming from the world of open source software defined radio. So I have low graphs where I have data processing blocks that are running in software on an MP SoXR64 core.
And what I want to do is I want to take a block, accelerate it by implementing it in some RTL and getting it to run on the FPGA card and getting the data in and all.
So how does that work? I have some part of software that I want to be accelerated by an FPGA accelerator. What's the workflow using this tool?
Yes.
Yes. So in that case you could repeat. Yes. How do you get a random acceleration implementation of software?
How do I go from software acceleration to hardware implementation?
Yes. So I have to admit that I'm not an expert hardware engineer, but I think that the way I would have done it is just to go ahead and create the Verlut code.
And with this tool it's very it's pretty sweet because you can connect it to the system.
You can launch your real software in QMU that interacts with it.
How do I exchange data with the library? What's the interface? I see internally it's QMU because of system C, right?
Yes.
And what's on the surface? How do I get data in and out?
How do you get data in and out of the simulators?
Perhaps I would have needed a better overview picture, but you can get how you get data in into your system C application.
We don't have any magic for this.
The remote port protocol is just a protocol that transfers transactions from QMU into the system C side or to another QMU.
And so it's not really a way to that will allow you to load in a bunch of data into the system C application.
Yes.
And I think afterwards and I can.