Thank you.
Hello everyone. I am Nizamuddin and I am with Anakush. So we are here to cover a little about operating SEF from the SEF dashboard past present and future.
Since we couldn't give the presentation live, we are recording this separately. So this is a two part presentation. The second part will be covered by Anakush.
So the part one will include the introduction, why and who needs a dashboard, the history, the architecture of the dashboard, the key features that we delivered on QNC, then the roadmap to the reef release.
I will try to cover a short demo as well.
So just a brief intro on myself. I started my career at HAT as an intern. At the time I was working with Rook and OCS operator. Later on I became an associate software engineer and got assigned with the SEF dashboard.
I have been ever since in the SEF dashboard team and last year I became the component lead of the SEF dashboard.
Recently we got moved over to IBM as part of an internal transition and I am now working as a software engineer at IBM.
So we all know what a dashboard is right. What I want to cover is what I want to reiterate over here is like why SEF dashboard is not just a dashboard for SEF.
Because SEF dashboard is not just a tool that is limited to monitoring only. SEF dashboard is a fully fledged management and monitoring web UI tool.
It has all the functionalities of management like you can manage host, OSDs, or pool management, SEF affairs, RGW, NFS, all these kinds of management functionalities are available in the SEF dashboard.
Then why we did not change the name from SEF dashboard to something else right. Because when it was initially introduced that is like a long time ago it was just a dashboard.
We can only do monitoring activities in it. Then later on with the introduction of the dashboard version 2 things started to change.
But it was deemed too heavy to replace all the code and documentation references. Hence we just kept with the SEF dashboard name all alone.
So the distributed systems are always complex. It is not just a single piece of software right. It is comprised of a big software ecosystem.
So if you take the example of SEF it is comprised of all these software like the Redos, KNL, RBD, RGW. It is a combined system of all these components.
So to install this you have to scale out and this causes infrastructure and configuration management and also monitoring becomes challenging.
The configuration of SEF involves around 2000 settings which gets incremented on each releases.
And then the operating on each of these pieces is like you know each of these components has its own CLI's, API's or workflows, differences of things right.
And maintaining the whole cluster again is a challenge. If you want to maintain, if you want to do maintenance activity on like one host it can affect the rest of the cluster.
So a proper maintenance should be holistic and not be restricted to per component monitoring.
Troubleshooting, analyzing the issues, requests going through or inspecting multiple architectural levels like the hardware, networking, logs etc.
Also the SEF CLI doesn't provide a unified user experience.
The SEF, all these different components has its own CLI. SEF has, the SEF CLI, Redos has the Redos CLI, RGW has the Redos gateway admin, RBD, then this FATM.
Don't get me wrong, CLI is great. If you are experienced with CLI then most of the things will be easier.
It has a few scripts and you can do wonders with it. But when you are new into this ecosystem like me it gets complicated.
Like you have to consider many different things and you have to understand many different CLI ways.
So for me or people like me it is easier to go through a UI where you get a unified experience. You can do anything like you can create NASW and RBD in similar fashion to forms.
So it gets easier with the UI.
And we have the whole SSH vs HTTPS discussion, the comparison.
HTTPS is more ease of use and it's more easily configurable and the access control is better with the HTTPS.
CLI vs REST, REST is more standardized and it follows an open API specification. Then the whole text vs graphics discussion. You can choose it, which is better.
So where do we come from?
CFS board in 2006 and later on it's mostly the CLI and 2013 the Calamari or the Inc. Tank or the OpenITC version of the dashboard got released.
Then the VSM, then the CFS dash and in 2016 the CFS manager got introduced and along with that the first version of the CFS dashboard is also introduced to the community.
In 2018 CFS dashboard version 2, 2019 with the introduction of CFS orchestrators like the CFS ADM, the management activities or the management in the UI got increased or improved.
Then 2020 we introduced the workflows in UI. So workflows like the expand cluster or the OSD creation wizard, which allows a more simpler cluster expansion process or the OSD creation processes.
Then we have the, I think we mostly focus on the service abilities, which includes the introduction of the features like the centralized logging.
So these are all the usual suspects in the CFS dashboard. Not the CFS dashboard, I mean the CFS GUIs.
As you can see the CFS dashboard is mostly supported by the CFS community itself. So it's been here since 2018 and it has a very advanced set of features.
And it mostly utilizes the CFS manager APIs, which makes the communication between CFS easier.
And along with that we also use technologies like Python and Angular for the front end.
Then we also take use of the Grafana to populate all the Prometheus metrics.
These are some of the examples of the early CFS GUIs, the Calamari one, the OpenATIC one, the VSM by Intel, Inkscope, the CFS dash, which is an open source project.
Then we have the CFS dashboard version 1, CFS dashboard version 2, which is the one you can see in the current CFS.
This is the CFS dashboard version 3, which is a work in progress feature or a work in progress UI.
And we are trying to push this to the reef release. So it's more or less there. So this is as you can see from the main cluster or the main branch.
Then how CFS uses monitor the CFS. This is like a survey done by the community some time ago.
As you can see from here Prometheus is predominantly used for monitoring the CFS, but it is closely followed by CFS dashboard around 50% or 49% of the users use CFS to monitor the CFS dashboard.
Since Luminous CFS offers what's needed to develop a fully featured and smoothly integrated dashboard. CFS manager provides an in-memory cache for all core CFS data.
It also provide a highly efficient interface to CFS based on Python calls. CFS mod provides a highly available backsource persistence for small datasets.
This is the architecture of the CFS dashboard. We have the CFS cluster at the beginning and then we have the client side, we have the front end, which is an Angular application.
So when the Angular request something from the REST API, you know, REST API gets in touch with the CFS manager module APIs, which talks with the CFS cluster and the database information in the cached status and given back to the front end.
Manager module APIs also export the metrics through a Prometheus exporter, which is given to Prometheus and through Grafana we get a nicely viewable graphs and these graphs are also shown in the front end in the CFS dashboard using an iframe component.
So these are all the features that are available in the QC release. As you can see from this chart, we are all we are almost achieved in some of the components like the pools or the configurations or the OSDs.
So we almost achieved a parity with the CLI. We support most of the features that are available from the CLI.
And we also provide some extra features like the, you know, some of the important features that I highlighted at the bottom, like the cluster expansion wizard, the internationalization, then we have the increased security, the CFS logs or the role based access control, the built-in Grafana, the REST APIs.
So these are all some of the features of CFS dashboard.
And these are all, you know, what we tried to achieve on the RIF release so far. So in RIF we release some of some new features and we again increased the parity with the CLI.
So we introduced a new OSD cluster, OSD creation wizard from the dashboard which simplified the OSD creation from, you know, if you are using CFS dashboard.
Then on the RVD side, we introduced the RVD snapshot mirroring or we started supporting the RVD snapshot mirroring from the dashboard.
With the RGW we introduced the RGW server-set encryption in the dashboard.
And also with the RIF release we are trying to introduce more features, more RGW features like the multi-site, the some users or role policies.
So those stuffs are still in work in progress.
We also have a tool new feature called centralized logging. So with just one view you will be able to see all the CFS logs or container logs like the manager,
or whatever component or container you have set up. Also we also tried to achieve WCAG level AA standardization with the accessibility.
So these are some of the goals that are beyond a RIF. So we are constantly trying to improve the usability experience.
So that's like a constant effort from the dashboard side. So we also something called the low code initiative,
which we will talk about later on in the end of the session. So we are trying to replace the Grafana with some built-in charts.
So instead of populating the charts with Grafana using the iframe components, we are trying to directly populate the charts using some chart.js like frameworks.
We also have a plan to improve the CFS integration in the dashboard. Currently we have all the monitoring pieces settled in the dashboard.
But we still lack some of the management activities on this CFS area. So we will focus on that later on.
And then also the multi-cluster monitoring and management. That's also an important feature that we are planning to deliver from the dashboard.
And also trying to achieve this feature parity with the CLI. So I will try to show a quick CFS dashboard demo.
So here is the login page of the CFS dashboard. And if you log in, you will be greeted with the landing page or the dashboard page where you can see
where you are the status or the information regarding your cluster. You have the cluster status, which is showing a warning for me.
You can click that and see why the cluster is in a one state and all other information regarding the cluster can be seen here.
I have let two RGWs, Daemons, and all other information. Then if you go to the cluster host, you can do all the host management activities.
Then we have the inventory or the physical disks part.
So you can see all the OSDs attached to each of these devices. You can identify the device by blinking the LEDs.
The monitors, all the services that are available right now in the cluster, you can create more services and edit or delete these services.
Also, you can restart or restart the Daemons if you go into each of the services details.
There are also service events. The Daemons events are also there in the OSDs. You can create OSDs or you can also have this new OSD creation wizard,
which has some pre-optimized deployment options there. Or you can also go with the advanced mode and create a tribe group specification of your own.
Also, there are different set of activities that can be performed on each of these OSDs, like sending the flags or deep scrubbing,
marking an OSD out, parsing or eventually destroying the OSDs.
Then the cluster-wide configuration, you can set flags to all the OSDs at once. If you select one of the options here,
the recovery priority, PD scrub, and if you go to the overall performance, you can see the overall performance of the OSDs,
which is a graphana itself. This is a graphana chart, which is integrated into the dashboard using an iframe component.
We have all the configuration listed here, the crushmap viewer for seeing the crushmap tree, then the manager modules.
We can start or restart, we can enable or disable a manager module from here. This is the SFX auth user management.
Right now, we support listing the users and creating a SF user.
In the logs, we have the cluster logs, the audit logs, then we have the daemon logs, which is the centralized logging that I was talking about before.
So in the centralized logging part, you can browse through the logs.
If you click on one of the container logs, let's say I want to see the manager logs and if I put show logs, it will display the logs from the manager of the Ceph node 0.
You can also put this in a live, you can also put this live and you can see the logs populating in a live, logs populating lively.
Right now, it's paused and we have the monitoring. This is directly consumed from the Prometheus and the alert manager.
So if there are any alerts in the cluster, it will show up here and it will show some integrator in the navigation pane itself.
Then we have the pool management, again all kinds of pool management like pool creation, edit, delete, the overall performance. You can see all the pool performance in the overall performance.
And if you want to see individual performance as well, you can see the performance details of each of the pool individually.
Then we have the block, the RBT section. So if you have no RBT pools available, it will show this message.
And if you want to create an RBT pool, you can go and create an RBT pool by selecting the RBT application from here.
Then we have the RBT mirroring. Right now it's not configured on my cluster.
So if I want to configure it, you can click on this configure RBT mirroring and this will configure the RBT mirroring.
And the ISKCA section as well, the NFS management. So you can go and create NFS export.
So if you don't have an NFS cluster created, so it will show this info to create it or add a new NFS service.
We have the file systems. Again, I don't have a file systems set up right now.
So we have an RGW section as well. So if you go to the RGW daemons, you can see all the daemons that are available in the cluster.
The overall performance of each of the daemons, you can create and delete users and edit the users.
The buckets creation or the bucket management section over here.
Also has the REST API, which you can see if you click the API, you will get redirected to the Ceph REST API.
Then we have the whole notification system here. You can see all the notifications coming from different components of this Ceph at one place.
You can also report an issue from the Ceph dashboard. So it will directly go to the tracker.ceph.com.
So if you have to enable the feedback module, you can go and enable it from here.
So once you do that, you provide this, you are a Ceph tracker API key and you give all this information.
Then you submit that, it will create an issue in the tracker.ceph.com.
Then you have the user management, the telemetry configuration and that's more or less about the Ceph dashboard.
So that's all from me, from my part. I think the second part will be covered by Ankush.
Hi and hello everyone. Thanks for the wonderful demo and part one presentation.
Let me introduce myself. My name is Ankush. I am working as an engineering manager in IBM team.
I have expertise of more than seven years in delivering the management and monitoring solutions for software-defined storage,
on a containerized or an uncontainerized environment in an open source system.
So today I will be taking you to the part two of this discussion where we will be discussing two major aspects.
First of them will be how you can contribute to the Ceph dashboard and the second one will be the Ceph dashboard community and how it looks like.
Moving on, I think discussing how you can contribute in the Ceph dashboard as a user.
We'll be talking about as a translator or documenter and also as a developer we'll be discussing how you can contribute.
First as a user, Ceph dashboard is by default enabled when you install Ceph via the CephADM and you can use it from the get-go.
But if it is somehow not enabled or if you are facing some issues while enabling the Ceph dashboard,
you can follow these steps that I mentioned over here or you can follow the documentation link.
Once the dashboard is enabled, you will see this is the first screen that you'll see where as a user you need to log in.
And once you are logged in, you will be able to do a couple of things from the Ceph dashboard,
from the management of the whole Ceph ecosystem to monitoring from alerting, logging and all those things you can do on the Ceph dashboard.
But somehow if you see any issues or if you have any suggestions for any of the things that you tried out
or if you have any feature requests that you want to put in, you can also go into a report and report an issue in dashboard itself
and you can report that issue and it will open a bug in a Ceph tracker where we'll be following up with you.
Also, you can directly share your experience on the Ceph user's mailing list that is mentioned over there
or at the IRC channel that is Ceph dashboard, you can reach out to us and we'll be happy to help you out.
So second part of that is how you can contribute to Ceph dashboard as a documenter.
So this is the documentation that link that we have and if you see any issues or if you have any things that you want to suggest,
you can directly go and report a documentation bug from the documentation link or if you want to do an edit yourself
and submit a pull request, we'll be happy to help you out on that.
You can click on this edit on GitHub link directly and then you can submit a pull request
and the team will get back to you on the reviews on that pull request.
As a translator, how you can contribute to Ceph dashboard is you can look into this link
where we already have a lot of translation done in the Ceph dashboard side.
I think more than 10 plus languages are already there but we still have some gaps that can be filled.
So you can look into that link and help us out on the localization and internationalization of the Ceph dashboard.
Moving on, as a developer, how you can contribute to the Ceph dashboard.
So firstly, what you can do is you can subscribe to this dev at the rate Ceph.io mailing list.
Second is the IRC channel that we already talked about which is Ceph dashboard.
We also have some documentation link very generic to Ceph but also to the dashboard.
You can follow to set up your dev environment and play around with the Ceph dashboard.
Moving on, let's discuss how the code looks like.
So we'll talk about two major things over here.
One is the backend, one is frontend.
On the backend side, we use Python 3.6.
And on the frontend side, we use Angular 12 with TypeScript plus Bootstrap 4.
But we are planning to upgrade it to Bootstrap 5 and also we are planning to upgrade the Angular version to adopt the new features.
As a developer, there is another initiative that is taken by the Ceph dashboard team where we understand that not everybody knows how to code in a frontend languages like HTML, JavaScript, TypeScript, CSS,
and all of that ecosystem.
But what we have done is that even if you don't know that, you can still contribute to Ceph dashboard using a low-code initiative where you can write your descriptors in this JSON kind of an format that will create a route for some page.
And then in a Python code, you can write how your page should look like and then put together can work and generate a page, something like this for you, where you'll have a UI generated from a Python code itself.
I think we have the first of our kind feature that is already written in this is a Ceph Auth management.
But I think in the next release, we have a couple more features coming in, which is following the low-code initiative.
And it is being discussed in the community right now.
I think the second part of this part to presentation was dashboard and the community around it.
So let's talk about dashboard in number of pull requests.
We have 2700 pull requests that are there in dashboard.
We have 4200 comments and these many lines of code, most of them are written in TypeScript.
But second prominent predominant language is Python.
And the last but not the least is HTML we have behind the Ceph dashboard.
There are a lot of great minds from different continents, different countries that contribute to Ceph dashboard.
And these are all majorly, I think, discover all the people that are working from different countries and continents and helping us grow.
Moving on, as you have seen that we have a big community spread across the world, time zones and all that stuff.
So we have tried to come up with something that works for everybody, but can be difficult for somebody at some time.
So we have a daily stand up at 11 a.m. CIT time or option.
Why not using that happens on Tuesday for tonight at 2 p.m. CIT.
And the face to face used to happen three pandemic times for almost three, four days at different locations.
It has happened, not happened after the COVID pandemic.
Now we'll see some glimpse of how our face to face looked like.
This is the first one that happened in Newenburg.
And all the community members are present.
Most of the community members are present over here.
And these are some of the images from that.
There was another Ceph dashboard, a orchestrator face to face that happened in Berlin, Coroia surface.
And these are images from there.
And the second Ceph dashboard specific face to face that happened in June 2019 in Fulda.
The Ceph dashboard community is doing some team building activities and enjoying work together.
I think that's all for today from my side for the part two presentation.
We'll be happy to take any questions if you have.
Otherwise, thank you for joining this meeting and also this presentation.