All right. So people, thank you all for being here. We're not going to keep it long. Maybe
just a couple of words to wrap up. This was the fourth edition, and we are very happy
that it was again physically. It's a hugely different experience. And I think we are doing
very well as a community, as an open source community on just execution. I think we are
doing well, and that's something to celebrate together. There's only two things you can do
with computing. One is to restrict the user to things like digital restrictions management,
DRM, and the other I think, and that's the future, is how can we secure user data. And
to do that, I think the only way forward is open source and free software. So let's keep
the pace up together as a community, and hopefully we gather again here in Brussels next year.
And I think Fitz also wants to say something. Yeah, I just want to wrap up and saying thank
you to everyone to join. Thank you for the nice questions. I think it was nicer than
the last years. Please send us feedback. Send us words about what you think about also the
online part of it, because we're not sure if we want to keep this hybrid version of
it for the next year. So please send us any thoughts of whether you think the online part
was actually worthwhile. I think this part will always be livestreamed by FOSDEM, but
we're not sure whether we actually keep it in hybrid. So please send us any thoughts
you have, and please also reach out to us if you want changes made for next year's.
We really want to make this more of a community event, and maybe also get a full day next
year. So thank you a lot to everyone, and have a great evening. Thank you for being
here.