Yeah.
Yes.
And they will talk about
computing on IBM actually.
We have heard a lot about AMD and Intel and even
these five now, but let's see what IBM guys
have out here as well.
Yeah.
Hi. My name is Claudio Imbrenda.
I am one of the maintainers for KVM on S390.
I'm Stefan. I'm contributor to the kernel on S390
and also maintainer of the S390 tools.
Yes. And we are here to talk about the same thing
that the previous person talked about, but for S390.
So a few months ago, a colleague passed from my office
and said, hey, there's a confidential computed track at
first time. Maybe you should submit something.
By the way, the deadline is tomorrow. So I did.
I went to the website and this was the call for paper
and it says, all my major process vendors and there's
Intel, AMD, ARM, ARM, power, and like,
so we are here to fix that.
The, how are we going to do it? Overview.
First of all, an overview of how the whole secure
execution works.
The life cycle, a small glimpse into how we handle
swapping and then Stefan will talk about attestation
and confidential dump. So let's get started.
So what it does, confidential virtual machines,
prevents the untrusted hypervisor or host from
looking into the guest or touching things into the guest.
It does not protect the guest and either service attacks.
It does not protect the guest from doing stupid things
because we want to protect maybe the machine from
malicious operators, hypervisors, compliance.
If you're here, you know what I'm talking about.
Right. So yeah, this is the grand scheme of thing,
which I think looks like most of confidential
computer solutions because, well, yes.
So we have the, what we call, Ultravisor.
Everyone has a different name, so we call it Ultravisor.
It's the, the trusted entity in the whole system.
It's the only entity that has complete access to
the whole system and it's implemented partially in
hardware and partially in firmware.
Then we have the guests, which are trusted for themselves,
as in they can shoot themselves in the foot if they so want,
but otherwise they are, if they don't do stupid things,
they can, they will be secure.
Notice that a secure guest can only access its own memory
and the hypervisor can not access the guest memory
or Ultravisor memory. Nobody can access Ultravisor memory.
In fact, the line is dotted because memory can be shared,
but this will be seen now because of course IO,
surprise, and non-secure guest is non-trusted like the hypervisor.
So yeah. So this is not news.
So again, Ultravisor memory is inaccessible.
The guest memory is not accessible unless shared and
attempting to access guest memory or hypervisor,
Ultravisor memory will just result in an exception.
So there is no memory encryption like in MDS, CV involved.
It's just that the page will become inaccessible and in any
way, shape, or form, not even IO or stuff like that,
would be able to access the page.
Which is like basically, yeah.
The guest decides which pages to share.
So it's the guest that decides, for example,
a bunch of pages at the end for bounce buffers,
which were mentioned earlier. Yes.
And for everything else, there is direct interaction with the
Ultravisor. So the guest host mappings are also secured
and enforced by hardware because of course this is also
important if everything is secure,
but then the host could like swap the mappings for some
pages at runtime and things could break in the guest
and we don't want it.
So the host can change the mappings,
but then it will crash basically the guest.
So it's fine.
And for everything else, it goes to the Ultravisor.
So all the other interactions that go from the hypervisor to
the guest or from the guest to the hypervisor,
they go through the Ultravisor and the Ultravisor will check
and proxy the interactions.
So make sure that, for example, in some cases,
some instructions are only allowed to return specific
return codes.
If the hypervisor is returning something that is not supposed
to be returned, that will not be allowed.
The hypervisor still has lots of things to do,
like the actual I.O. device models handling some of
the instructions, like I said, I.O. some other instructions
that are actually not handled by the hypervisor,
but the hypervisor need to be notified that the instruction
happened because otherwise the guest will not be able to be
executed correctly, then scheduling a memory management
of the usual stuff that is still there.
So what can we build with this?
We have basically an almost unlimited number of secure
guests at the same time.
It's not unlimited, but you will run out of memory before
you run out of guests.
We're talking millions.
This is very important.
The boot image is encrypted and it can contain secrets.
So the boot image is encrypted.
We can swap.
We can have remote attestation, although it's not needed
because the boot image is encrypted.
But we still have it because there are some cases where it
can be useful and host initiated dumps.
We do not have line migration.
We do not have device pass-through.
We do not have huge pages packing and we do not have
nested secure guests.
Eh.
Maybe one day.
So what happens when the host starts?
The first thing that the host does is to check if the
ultravisor is available and if so to query the ultravisor to
know specific parameters, like how much memory needs to be
donated, for example, and then donate a bunch of memory to
the ultravisor where a bunch of information and details and
metadata about the pages are kept, which rings a bell.
It's from the previous talk, maybe.
Yes.
That memory now belongs to the ultravisor and it cannot be
touched again ever until the host reboots, basically.
So it's gone forever.
I mean, forever, relatively speaking.
So the boot blob is encrypted.
So you can either have a custom image for a specific guest or
you have your image and you put, I don't know, the looks keys,
for example, inside the E30 and then you just boot it and it
will boot safely or maybe you have a generic image because of
some kind of orchestration that you're using or because it's a
vendor image and you don't want to touch it and then in that
case you will need remote attestation.
The boot image is encrypted using a public key.
The private key is inside the hardware safely embedded and
so nobody can decrypt the boot image except the hardware.
The boot blob contains the kernel in E30, the kernel
command line, some more keys provided by the owner, which
can be used later for other purposes, for example, dumping.
And, yeah, so let's see, as a simplified view of the guest
lifecycle, the host creates a guest or the host asks the
Ultravisor to create a secure guest and by doing so also
donates a bunch more memory to keep some more hostkeeping and
more metadata about guest pages.
The Ultravisor will at this point create the secure guest
and then the boot blob is passed to the Ultravisor which
will then make the pages inaccessible, decrypt it, verify
the H mark, verify the hash and if everything is all right,
if the image is correct and has not been tampered with, then
it can be finally run by the host.
Now this is a slightly less simplified view which if you're
watching the stream or if you watch it later, you can pause
and have a look at it.
I will not explain it now, but it's just for convenience,
for reference.
So memory donation, I talked about memory donation, so we
have the UV based storage which is that big chunk of memory
which is donated by the host to the Ultravisor at very early
the boot, in the boot process and can be big and it's
absolute memory which we call absolute means physical
memory basically, so it needs to be done very early at boot
because otherwise you will not find a very large block of
physical memory, a contiguous physical memory.
Configuration based storage and CPU based storage configuration
means guest in S390 speak, storage means memory in S390
speak, so those are small pieces of physically contiguous
memory, so it's not a problem to find a few pages.
Configuration virtual storage can be big, it depends on the
size of the guest and this needs to be contiguous but can
be contiguous in virtual memory, host virtual as in kernel
space, kernel outer space virtual memory, so it's also
not a problem, you can just do VMALOC and you go.
The configuration and CPU memory that is donated will be
taken away basically until the guest is destroyed, once the
guest is destroyed the memory can be used again by the host.
Swapping, let's have a look at how swapping works.
So when the host wants to swap a page, is this readable?
Oh, actually yes, cool.
When the host wants to swap a page it will do an export
page, basically asking the ultraviolet to please make the
page accessible.
The ultraviolet will first encrypt and save the hash
somewhere, somewhere means one of these regions that have
been donated when the guest was created.
Once the page is encrypted and hashed then it's made
accessible which means that it's not usable by the guest
anymore at this point because it's not secure anymore.
The host can then unmap the page, swap it to normal stuff.
When the guest tries to use it again the host will get the
usual page fault, you unswap the page, you map it back, you
run the guest again but the page is there but it's not secure,
it's still encrypted.
So the guest tries to use the page, the host will get a
fault again, a different type of fault and this fault will
trigger an import.
Import means the ultraviolet will make the page accessible,
decrypt it, check the integrity that if everything is all
right then the page will be accepted and the host can run
the guest again and the guest finally will be able to run.
Yes.
Next is the station.
So let's talk about our station.
Give me a sec.
So Claudia just said it's optional, then why should we use
it?
So for IBM secure execution we do not require the explicit or
external attestation to prove that the guest is secure as in.
We encrypt the image, we verify the integrity and if your image
contains a unique secret and if you want to use a stock kernel
and a stock image you can use a unique public SSH key and if
you can connect to that image using your fitting private key
your successor logon will attest that is your secure execution
image.
But there are some cases where you might not want or cannot do
this.
For example, the explicit attestation is useful when you
want to provide to a third party that you're running on secure
execution without passing that private key to that other
party or you want to verify that you're not only running a
specific image but the specific image instance.
So if you have your image multiple times you want to differ
between those probably.
Or to be more general if you want to have trusted information
about your secure execution guest or the execution environment
it's running in.
Also another point would be if you have a generic image from
a generic stock from your supplier probably you want to
first prove that this image is really secure and then deploy
your instance dependency.
And the workflow, the first three steps are as Claudia
talked before we start the host will start the secure
execution image, the altruizer will verify the hashes and
start the image and the guest transition into secure
execution mode.
And we have a trusted system on the left and on this trusted
system we will generate a request, attestation request,
and this request will contain a public ECTH key and an
encrypted measurement key.
We do a measurement with that encrypted key later.
This request is also encrypted with the public key of the
altruizer similar to the image.
Then the request will be sent to the secure execution guest
and it will trigger an altruizer call to the altruizer.
The altruizer will do a measurement.
That measurement mostly contains the hashes used to verify
the image and a configuration unique ID, unique for that
instance.
Then the response travels back to our trusted system and
the trusted system we can redo the HMAC and if they are the
same we can be sure that this image is tested and running
on a secure execution.
If they are not the same something went wrong.
So for dumping, we are here talking about hypervisor
initiated dump.
So there are two types of dumping.
The guest can dump itself.
It has a pro of that you do not need interaction between the
guest and the hypervisor.
However, you have to provide memory in the guest beforehand
so that is not always possible.
In that case if you do not want to know the memory or if your
guest is in a very badly crashed state and also the dumping of
yourself modifies your memory.
The other way, the host initiated dumping is that it
works regardless of your guest state.
It can be very badly crashed.
It will not modify your guest state and the guest does not
change during dumping.
However, you need access to the guest state and we promise
that the hypervisor never has access to the guest state.
So how do we do it?
First of all, confidential dumping is an opt-in by the
guest owner.
So if you want to be very paranoid you can just say I
don't want my image to ever be dumped.
But it is a reliable and secure way for hypervisor initiated
dumping.
Every guest state the hypervisor receives is encrypted.
Also, no QM API changes so you can just issue your
version dump as normal.
And the S390 tools contains a tool, set get dump, that will
handle the decryption later.
And then the decrypted dump can be used as normal using
crash for example to analyze the dump.
So for a hypervisor perspective, if the dump was requested,
the hypervisor stops all vCPUs and then import all guest
pages, export it to different ways.
So we will export all our guest pages.
And then, so the guest has no access to the pages anymore
but they are encrypted.
It will call the initiate configuration dump
hypervisor call.
It will initiate the dumping process and set up some states
in the hypervisor.
And then we need the state for each CPU.
We'll dump the CPU state for each vCPU.
We'll get this encrypted CPU state.
And then we need a metadata for the memory to encrypt it
later.
So we have isxts tweaks for the decryption later.
And in the end, we just need some bunch of keys and
initialization vectors and seats and nonsense to decrypt
the memory later.
And that's all written into an VM core else file
with some extensions.
So we zoom out a little bit.
During the generation of the secure execution image,
the user or the image owner has to first opt into the
dumping and then provide a customer communication key,
we CCK.
That key is later used to decrypt the image.
After the generation of the image, the guest owner
transfers the image to its cloud provider or to the host.
And we'll start the image and verify the image using the
altruizer and the image will be started as a secure
execution guest.
At some point, someone will request a dump.
It can be by the guest image owner or by the hypervisor.
Doesn't matter.
The key will trigger the confidential dump
and the hypervisor calls I had in the slide before and
the hypervisor will create the confidential dump
encrypted with CCK.
The encrypted dump data in the VM core else file is
transported back to the trusted system and then in the
trusted system, you can decrypt the image using the get dump
and your secret customer communication key and then you
can use a decrypted normal looking dump to analyze.
So just a quick summary.
The current status that you require an IBM Z15 for that,
for secure execution and if you want to use
adaptation or dumping you need a Z16.
And from a software perspective, everything is upstream.
Just to summarize the content of our talk, confidential
accounts for S390X is we create a secure image that can
have secrets in it.
We support swapping, implicit and explicit attestation
and also a host and actually dumping.
And now we have a bonus slide.
Yes, bonus slide.
We are working on confidential containers based on
secure execution.
There is a pipeline kind of working including attestation
and everything except for the secure part.
But the secure part itself works.
It's just a matter of putting these together.
So that's coming soon hopefully.
Yep.
So the question is about how to build basically the boot image.
So you need the public key of the machine you want to run
or the machines you want to run the image on.
So if I have 5,000 SE machines.
If you have 5,000 SE machines you need 5,000 keys but you
probably will not have 5,000 SE machines.
But then you need...
You probably hope so.
By all means buy 5,000 SE machines.
But in that case, yes, you will need 5,000 keys.
But you can encrypt the image I think with multiple keys.
So you don't have to have 5,000 images.
So I can have one image signed by multiple keys?
Yes, you can have one image signed by multiple keys.
I mean encrypted with...
Yes?
Could you elaborate on what the endorsement mechanism for
the software is all about?
So how do I actually obtain the public key for a particular machine?
How do I know that I'm using the right key?
So the keys are signed by an IBM MasterKey which is published somewhere.
I don't exactly know the details about that.
But somewhere there is a way.
There's a certification authority and you can know that there is a...
The keys you're getting are real keys for an IBM Z15 or Z16 machine.
So to be more specific, during the image generation or the
administration request generation, you provide the IBM signing key
that's signed by a DigiCERT CA signing key that's signed by some root key.
And we also have obviously a relocation list for that.
So you can be trusted that you're really signing with a hardware key.
Maybe one question from my side.
One of the things that have been very useful in technology like SGX is
TCP recovery, right?
These are bugs.
You've seen that they can recover from that.
And I'm wondering with the type of other station that you have here with a
hard coded private key, there's no real way of knowing that I'm running even on a patch.
We have some sort of micro code patch or something like Meltdown Foreshadow.
Can you go forward from that?
So I think we do support some versioning so that you can refuse your image to be run on an older machine, for example.
I'm not sure about the rest.
But I mean, there is a revocation list if a machine gets compromised.
It's on a per machine base.
There is no notion of a machine can be in a compromised state if it loads an older micro code version.
You cannot roll back, I think.
So the firmware is per machine and controlled more or less by IBM.
So either the whole machine is compromised or nothing.
So that's not per guest.
We have no firmware per guest.
So if you notice that there's a bug or whatever, you just relocate the whole key, so the whole host key,
and update your firmware with a new key.
Or you generate a new key.
It depends where you have the key, because you mentioned in the slides that it's in hardware.
No, the private key is in hardware.
So it's not, a firmware will have to read it, obviously, to process it, though.
So if that one is leaked, it's game over?
For that machine.
For that machine, it's game over.
If that is leaked, for that machine, it's game over until the machine gets patched.
Okay, but you can decrypt the damage, right?
With the key, you can decrypt the boot image.
But if you didn't have secrets in the boot image, then you're safer, I guess.
Excuse me, I didn't get the details.
How it's possible that the key, private key is in hardware, but are they taking a fearwater?
Is that the key?
No, no, you don't change the key.
In that case, if the key is compromised, you need to change the hardware as well.
You update the firmware to get rid of the bug, but the key is compromised, you need a new key.
You send us the hardware, and then we'll basically give a new key, basically.
Yes?
So we have a bit of a break, so if you'll go around, I still have some questions, so if you don't mind.
By all means.
There's a bit from the audience, so.
So when doing logic, you mentioned there are two exceptions in a row.
So the code don't have a participation fold?
Yes, the first is a page fold.
So when VM notices that the page is not properly secured, why do you have two exceptions for that,
and why do we not do it?
Okay, so the question, I don't know if the stream is just going, but I still repeat the question.
Okay, then I repeat the question.
So the question is why do we have, by swapping, we have two different, here, we have a page fold,
and then we have the other fold.
Couldn't we just have one fold?
In theory, yes.
It could be like, you mentioned there's an import, but it also does come from it, and immediately import a page?
You can export it and import it immediately, but I don't know.
Wait, okay, first, let me answer the first part first.
So, yes, we could have skipped the second fold by exporting the page directly, by importing the page directly.
The point is that when the page fold happens, we don't know if that is for a secure guest or not.
The page fold handler would need to be so much more complicated, unnecessarily complicated,
and importing a page takes time anyway, and the overhead of having an extra exception is not so big,
compared to the amount of code we needed to write.
So what was the second question?
Okay, okay.
Okay, sorry, another question here?
Oh, sorry, I thought it was.
There's also a question from the online stream, so I'm going to read it to you guys, and then you can handle it.
So, Muhammad is asking, in the flow shown, can you explain why is the measurement key a part of the evidence?
Why is it needed?
Is the attestation flow specified somewhere?
Maybe, Stefan.
So, the measurement key is generated by the trusted system owner, and then encrypted with the public key of the firmware or the hardware.
We needed to do an HMAC, so it's a signed authentication.
And only the person who has the key or the machine who has that measurement key can reliably create the HMAC.
Okay.