All right, our next speaker is Andrew Jeffery from the Earth of Cambridge talking about
LSKB.
Hello, so yes, I'm Andrew Jeffery from University of Cambridge.
Email is there if you want to email me about any questions that I can't answer today.
As a brief kind of precursor, I kind of come from the distributed systems world, not necessarily
confidential computing world, so this is kind of like a hybrid of both worlds here.
So today we're going to talk about LSKB, aiming to democratize confidential computing from
the core.
So first of all, we've got to work out what this core actually is that we kind of want
to start replacing.
And so we're going to start working with distributed key value stores.
In particular, we're going to look at etcd.
And as the etcd website defines itself, it's a distributed, reliable key value store.
And importantly, it's for the most critical data of your distributed systems.
So etcd runs as a cluster, it's distributed.
So you have this one leader node, and you might have some more followers in this setup
as well.
etcd is also not alone, it's the core, so you have some applications around that.
Some of those applications might be some sort of orchestration, so using Kubernetes on top
is like one of the main candidates.
Otherwise you might use M3 or Rook or Core DNS, and there's other applications that use
etcd internally as well.
So effectively, it's really widely used, it's quite a critical piece of a lot of infrastructure.
And so you have to interact with etcd in some way, even if you're just using one of these
services.
And so primarily you use some key value operations, like you can put, so you might write foo1
equals bar into the data store, and it keeps some history, so you kind of have this revision
system.
When you do that first write, it'll be stored at, say, revision 5, and you write to be 6,
7, 8, going on like that.
So after you've written, you can get something back out using the range queries.
And with this, you can say, I'd like all keys between foo and foo5 in history, so you'd
be able to get multiple keys at once.
And you can also specify the revision here if you wanted to go back in time just to see
what it was at some previous point.
After you've read something, you might no longer need stuff, so you can delete it.
So you can also delete with this range as well, so you can delete, say, foo2, foo5.
Transactions are a nice ability here, so you can do some kind of conditional logic at the
data store side.
So you can use put range with leads or more nested transactions internally to do bulk
operations here, so you can say, right, foo2 and foo3 in the same revision.
Additionally, you can have leases on top of the data store, so these can be used for building
high-level primitives and distributed systems, primarily you might want some leadership mechanism.
One final thing here is the watch API that etcd provides.
Similar to ranges, you can do a range between a start and an end, and you can also do a
watch at a certain point in history.
So for watches, that history is where you start watching from.
So if you start with revision 5, you'll be notified that foo1 equals bar, and then you'll
be notified of the things in revision 6, foo2 and foo3, and everything that comes in after
that as well while you keep the connection open.
This is just like a really cool API that's used by lots of these other systems, so this
is kind of something we might want to mimic if we want to replace etcd.
So etcd is a big system, we want to run it somewhere, primarily lots of people run it
in the cloud.
We don't always want to trust this cloud, because it's run by cloud providers, they
might themselves be trustworthy, but the things that they're operating might not be, so if
a hypervisor gets a weakness, then it might get attackers going through to the lower layers
being able to access some of the hardware themselves.
Clients that are interacting with your service might be within the cloud themselves, they
might have already accepted some of the cloud primitives.
They might also just be outside of the cloud and just having to use your service for some
reason, so they might not be able to use the cloud directly themselves.
Additionally, they might not necessarily speak directly to your datastore.
Lots of things they talk through a proxy.
So if you're in Kubernetes world, you might have kubelets and kubectl.
They speak through the API server, which basically terminates TLS connections before passing and
doing some logic back on the datastore itself.
And so today we're going to speak about two problems.
Problem one here is this etcd cluster that's running in the cloud.
If we're not trusting this cloud, then all of the data in memory is currently unencrypted,
and so we want to be able to do something about that.
And problem two is this proxy.
If this proxy is terminating some TLS connections, we don't really want that to be able to happen.
We'll actually see how the proxy can be a bit distrustful with our interactions.
We want to be able to show when it's not being very trustworthy.
So diving into problem one, so we've got this etcd cluster.
etcd, like any storage service, has some storage, it has some memory and some processing application.
It's also distributed, so we have some TLS connections between the peers.
And effectively, as you can see in yellow here, we have some level of security.
So recommended setups have etcd communicating for etcd nodes over TLS.
And we also can have this optional sort of file system encryption that gets put down
to storage.
One main problem with this, all of those keys are in memory.
So the TLS key that we were using for TLS is now in memory, so the attacker's got that.
And they've also got the private key for any file system encryption.
So that basically renders our TLS connections and our storage encryption pretty much worthless
if we're not trusting that someone can't access our memory.
So if we actually swap out etcd for LSKV, which is our data store, we run LSKV inside
of an SGX enclave, which gives us those confidentiality properties that we just mentioned in the previous
talk.
Then we can build some of these derivatives to be a bit more trustworthy.
So now that our memory is encrypted and interpretively protected, we can store our TLS keys and file
system keys there and trust that they're not going to be able to be accessed.
The actual application itself is running in a secure enclave, so we can show you that
it's not going to be able to be modified.
Our TLS connections, we can be sure that they're actually secure TLS because our TLS keys are
in memory.
And we can actually upgrade those to a tested TLS, where rather than just trusting the other
application over end, we can make sure the other application is running in a secure enclave
as well.
So it's in the same environment that we trust.
And finally, we've got this file system key in memory, so we can trust that anything we
write to disk is actually going to be encrypted properly as well and safe.
So this is one nice solution to that problem one.
So if we delve into a bit of what LSKV is a bit more, we can see that it builds on something
called CCF.
It runs in the SGX enclave, and like most services in the cloud, it will run on top
of a hypervisor and have some memory and storage and other resources attached as well.
So if we quickly jump into CCF, which is the Confidential Consortium Framework, it's a pretty
nice project that basically splits up the interactions and the management of it into
three distinct roles.
So the first role is the operator.
So this is the cloud provider, the person who's standing up VMs for you.
You might say, I'd like one LSKV node to run with, and then you might later want more to
join into the network.
And so this operator is untrusted, so all they can do is stand those nodes up.
They can't do any sort of giving those nodes access to the data in the cluster.
They don't auto-join the cluster.
That's the responsibility of the governance, who we partly trust.
There's a few of them, and so any interactions they do have to be done in some sort of majority
way.
And so these people will be responsible for things like once a node has been stood up,
except checking the configuration of it and finally accepting it into the network so it
can start serving application requests and handle some of the data in the cluster.
And finally, we have users that need to actually access the application that we're running.
And so these are treated as kind of trusted towards the application, but the application
itself can have internal access controls inside.
All the data is stored on an encrypted ledger that gets written to the disks.
These requests are stored publicly in this ledger, and they're also signed so that everyone
can see those and verify those.
User interactions that go through the application are normally stored encrypted by default.
You can make them public if you have certain use cases for those.
So LSKV actually has an ACD compatible API.
This slide might look pretty familiar.
It's basically the same API at the core.
One asterisk is that this watch is at the bottom is currently requiring a patch on CCF
because it hasn't got RAM to be merged in yet.
But that's something that should be fixed and should be expected to work.
So effectively, this basically means that we can switch out etcd for LSKV in most cases,
solving problem one.
So before we quickly go into problem two, we've just swapped out etcd and LSKV, and
it might not always be as simple as this.
So some quick trade-offs.
LSKV is actually optimistically consistent in the way it replicates data rather than
ACD is strongly consistent.
Otherwise, we have the normal things we might expect that LSKV actually gives us confidential
algae properties of our data, makes more operations transparent.
So those governance operations we can see.
It also has this ACD API at its core.
It also has some extra features that we're not going to cover too much here.
There's one later.
So quickly on this optimistic sense, rather than replicating data in a synchronous way,
when you write to LSKV, it will replicate asynchronously.
And in turn, you get an ID back.
You can later follow up with this ID to say, was this replicated properly or was it not
allowed?
This basically puts the decision at the client's side.
So they can either be optimistic and say, I'm going to trust that that's fine.
Or they can come back later and say, no, I wanted to make sure that was replicated first.
So this is just a key difference.
If we go quickly onto problem two, we have this proxy that we might want to communicate
to the data store too.
So in this instance, Alice wants to write 500 pounds into an account.
But the proxy is going to intercept that and write that money into Bob's account instead.
LSKV is none the wiser here.
It's just gotten a request.
It's going to post that request and handle the response.
The proxy in turn has an opportunity to return to the client and say, OK, Alice, we've written
your money into the account.
Now hopefully you can see here that Alice is not equal to Bob.
And so she hasn't actually got the money.
So LSKV gives us this receipt functionality where we can actually expose untrustworthy
proxies.
So when the client first does the request to write money into Alice's account, they
can also ask for a receipt for that operation.
This goes through the proxy.
The proxy can rewrite the normal write request as normal.
So LSKV actually puts the money into Bob's account.
But we still want to get that receipt back.
So when the receipt actually comes back from LSKV, the client can actually detect that
either the proxy's manipulated this receipt in some way so it's no longer valid because
it's a signature.
Or it is valid, in which case it says that the money went into Bob's account, which is
not what they wanted.
So you can use this to flag to someone else that this proxy is not trustworthy.
And you'd probably stop talking to it.
So that's also how we can solve problem two quickly with LSKV.
Just a quick summary of things here is now that we don't think current data stores are
really suited for confidential operation, primarily looking at CD.
We don't think that lifting and shifting them into confidential environments gets you all
the properties that you necessarily want.
You get some memory encryption and integrity just by running them in enclaves.
You don't get some of the other properties that we get from building on the ledger and
also having a different trust model compared to what some systems have.
We've introduced LSKV, which is a new confidential data store built on CCF.
It actually has an HCD compatible API, which basically means that you can swap out HCD
for LSKV in most cases.
LSKV is also able to highlight these untrustworthy proxies using receipts.
And yeah, it's kind of fast.
Thanks to that optimism, it basically has a higher throughput and lower latency than
HCD.
If you do replace HCD with it, hopefully your performance of stuff will start increasing
as well.
That's pretty much me.
So I'm around for a few questions.
And please check out the GitHub repo.
It's open source and everything.
My email is there if you have any questions after the talk.
So thank you.
We definitely have time, so feel free to go on the daisy.
You have a question.
On the proxy side, the receipts, is there an API extension or is there an API change?
If I'm using the proxy, I switch it to LSKV, do I need to change my application?
Yeah.
So that's a question about the HCD API.
Does that include the write receipts by default?
No, it does not.
There are a separate GRPC service on top.
So your clients would need to be manipulated with that.
Either your clients or you'll build that into the proxy.
So you could say, because the idea of the proxy is that it's exposing different API
to your clients, right?
So if you do a write request to your proxy, your proxy could by default ask for a receipt
and present that to the user as well.
They might need some extra functionality to be able to verify that.
I don't know how the receipt works, extending the HCD API to have some sort of non-sore
or request for signature.
Is that something that you're planning to?
Would it make sense to extend the actual HCD API for this?
The question is, would it make sense to extend the HCD API for receipts?
We don't really think so.
We're not really planning on doing changes directly in HCD, just primarily because HCD
has a different kind of threat model and trust model.
So some of the things that we have, HCD doesn't necessarily support against.
So that's one reason we're not going to stop putting some of this back into HCD itself.
It's kind of designed to be a separate service.
Yeah.
When we have the use case of using LSKD in a Kubernetes scenario, I'm wondering how the
authentication would work.
Like if I have confidential services, and only those should be able to access the confidential
storage, how would the mutual authentication work?
The HCD should just give out secrets to those confidential services, and the confidential
service should know that they access the correct HCD storage essentially.
By HCD storage, you mean a key?
I mean the LSKD as an HCD replacement in a Kubernetes state.
Okay.
So I think your question is about how do you make sure you access the right HCD cluster
from a confidential client?
Yes.
So you'd be speaking through the API server rate in Kubernetes?
Yeah.
Or you're saying you want to connect directly?
Maybe you have a confidential controller or you connect directly, I guess.
Okay.
So I'm not sure if we can do that directly in LSKD.
It has a cluster ID like a normal HCD cluster, so you can go about trusting that.
But I definitely would really work through that use case directly.
The main thing is that if you want to write a proxy around it, then you might want that
in the proxy.
Okay.
One of the things that LSKD, we have to be careful of as compared to like HCD.
In what context?
Like what are the things that LSKD need to be taken care of that DTC don't take care
of?
Okay.
Why do you need to do that?
Yeah.
So the question is about what are some things that LSKD kind of supports that HCD doesn't.
So one of the main things is storage.
In HCD, everything gets written to disk straight away and that's part of the consensus process.
You won't get returned until it's written to disk.
In LSKD, that's not the case.
We don't write to disk asynchronously, which basically means that we're not trusting this
host to necessarily persist our data or even give it back to us correctly when we ask for
it.
It's only used for disaster recovery scenarios.
So that's like one primary difference, which basically means that ACD is open to rollback
attacks.
So if you trust the host to do the data, they can cut them off and when you load back, you've
got a subset of what you had before.
Okay.
Yeah.
So I saw in the tradeoffs that LSKD cannot have a strong replication, like HCD.
So what was the cause of, why was LSKD to be able to do that tradeoff?
Yeah.
So the question is about why does LSKD not have strongly consistent replication?
Basically, if we're not trusting the host, then A, we don't want to write things to disk,
like we just said.
So that's one reason for that part.
And then on the replication side, we're not trusting the host, so we don't want to block
everyone on wanting to replicate everything.
So it does do the replication and you can follow up again with that ID from your operation.
So if you do care about it being strongly replicated, you can just follow up the ID
and wait until it's committed, which is kind of giving the user a bit more flexibility
in that operation choice.
Okay.
So I have one more.
So Tom will set up in the last question.
Yep.
I have one more.
So I was actually surprised by your performance numbers because 50% latency loss I expect,
but then three and a half times gain in performance is something I didn't expect.
Can you say why that is or how well it kept them?
It's actually consistent.
Maybe I missed that.
Yeah, of course you don't see the slide anymore.
Oh, that's a good slide.
Yes.
So the question is about why it's so fast.
Unfortunately, it was a consistency slide, but yeah.
Even the slides are confidential now.
But yeah, slides are on there for some.
Yeah.
So primarily you can replace entity with LSKV at the moment.
If you took the clusters and swapped them, the entity API is still there.
Your things will still work.
If you wanted to take advantage of the extra things like the receipts for the proxies and
things you would need to add some logic into your proxy or into your clients.
There's not currently apps that support those receipts and extra bits at the moment.
We haven't got that bit.
It's just on the data store focus at the moment.
Cool.