So, I'm Tom.
I'm a first year PhD student at the Carre Lueve and I'll be talking about the research
we have done in the last year, a year and a half.
So to sketch a bit of context, we are researching on cyber-physical systems.
Cyber-physical systems are systems that interact with the real world, for example, air-compressive
robotic arms.
These systems have a controller with safety-critical applications.
However, in the recent years, the industry is moving to including a commodity-less like
Linux to facilitate software updates and third-party applications for monitoring of the cyber-physical
systems.
However, as you can imagine, to keep the safety-critical applications safe, you have to put this on
a separate processor so that the commodity-less may not influence it, but this becomes very
expensive.
So what industry wants to do is that they want to integrate both these things on a single
processor.
So that's basically the requirement that the industry has at this point, but a few problems
result from it.
The first is, I think, the most obvious.
Whenever there's a bug in the commodity-less or an attacker, they can influence the execution
of the safety-critical applications, which means that the safety-critical applications
cannot be guaranteed to have their availability.
So the safety aspect is completely lost, which is not acceptable for these cyber-physical
systems.
The second issue that arises is that the safety-critical applications have real-time execution requirements.
Although there is some support in Linux, for real-time execution, this is mostly not what
industry is looking for.
So they want to have a real, low latency real-time execution scheduler as well.
And the third issue that arises is that industry also wants to share the peripherals between
the safety-critical applications and the commodity OS, because these monitoring applications
should be able to read out the peripherals.
However, industry doesn't want them to be able to disable the peripherals, because then,
again, availability isn't guaranteed.
For example, if the train wants to break and the peripheral for the breaks is disabled,
no break can be pressed.
This is quite an issue.
So out of this, our research question was formed.
Can we ensure availability for safety-critical applications while running a commodity OS
on the same system with little developer impact?
And to repeat, we need isolation of the critical applications.
We need real-time execution of these critical applications.
And we also need a transparent sharing system for the peripherals.
As an aside, the threat model that we assumed was that there is a strong remote adversary
with root privileges in the commodity OS.
They want to launch a denial of service attack on the complete system.
And we assume that the hardware, critical applications, and peripherals are trusted,
and everything else is not.
So jumping into our first requirement to isolate the critical applications, we chose to use
ARM TrustZone, because it's integrated in high- and low-end devices, embedded devices
as well.
It has existed for quite some time, so the chance that the industry already has a processor
deployed with ARM TrustZone on it is quite high.
So ARM TrustZone is actually just hardware-based isolation.
It creates two worlds, as you can see the normal world on the left and the secure world
on the right.
It does this by defining two security states with their own address spaces.
In that way, we can ensure confidentiality and integrity for code and data in the secure
world, because the hardware blocks any access to these address spaces on the secure world
coming from the normal world.
We use OPTEE, which is an open source implementation of ARM TrustZone, and it works together with
Linux in the normal world.
So our architecture, you can see again the normal world on the left and the secure world
on the right.
All the gray boxes are the boxes that were already there in OPTEEOS and Linux, but the
white boxes we added.
So for requirement one, of course, it's on TrustZone.
Requirement two, we added a secure scheduler and a secure interrupt.
For requirement three, we added a driver in the normal world and a secure driver in the
secure world.
And then we also have developed a use case where we monitor the Linux kernel, and that's
also in the secure world.
But I'll talk about that later.
So for the real-time scheduler, so for the real-time execution requirements, we basically
need two things.
We need a periodic interrupt, and we need a scheduling system.
For this periodic interrupt, we use a hardware timer on the board.
It's very simple.
We set the interrupt to be the highest priority of the complete system, and we protect it
from the normal world so that the normal world cannot disable it or reconfigure it.
So when an interrupt is triggered by this hardware timer, it gets caught by OPTEEOS.
OPTEEOS checks if it's a scheduling interrupt.
If so, it passes on execution to Free charters, which is a well-known, relatively small real-time
operating system which supports task prioritization and preemption, which is very useful for industry.
So whenever Free charters gets control, it will schedule a task, its tasks, and after
all tasks have executed, control will be given back to OPTEEOS so that the system can function
as normally.
And then for requirement three, we have a, so this is obviously the normal way that an
application on user level would interact with hardware peripherals.
However, these peripherals need to be in the secure world.
So we also need to move part of the driver into the secure world.
So this is called driver splitting often.
We basically introduce a secure driver in the secure world at kernel level, which is
the liaison between the normal world and the peripheral.
So this secure driver then to keep the developer efforts minimal should not contain a lot.
In fact, very little.
Only hardware accesses can be put in the secure driver, but you can also put some security
policies in there.
So for example, if a user application in normal world wants to read something, it will get
a lot.
But if it isn't allowed, for example, to disable the peripheral, the secure driver is able
to just stop the request and nothing will happen.
The secure driver may also include some logic to share code or to share the access between
the normal and the secure world.
For example, if you have a screen as a peripheral, the secure world's contents of the screen
will always be displayed on top of the normal world content.
And the nice thing about creating such a system is indeed only the developers of the driver
at the kernel level in normal world need to care about any changes made to the system.
As far as the user level applications, no, nothing has changed, which is fairly useful
for industry as well.
Of course, you need read and write access.
And this is given by a set of APIs included in Optio OS called the global platform APIs.
These are a standardized set of function calls to facilitate calling into the secure world,
providing data and getting data back.
We've measured this to take on average 123 microseconds, which is plenty fast enough
for industry.
But of course, secure peripherals might also want to return an interrupt, might trigger
an interrupt.
And this interrupt must also be returned at some point to the normal world.
So for this, we developed a notifier system that consists of two parts, one in the normal
world, one in the secure world.
So what happens is that if an interrupt is triggered at the peripheral, it will get forwarded
to the secure world notifier by the secure driver.
Then the secure world notifier will trigger an interrupt in the normal world, which will
be caught by the normal world notifier.
And this will forward it to any driver in the normal world that wants to know if such
an interrupt has happened using a published subscribe system.
So now we solved all the three requirements.
But then we got on to thinking what can we do with this.
So we developed a use case where we tried to monitor the Linux kernel running state,
if it has crashed or not.
So we adopted a very simple system to do this.
We basically challenged the Linux kernel using a notification from the system we just built.
We expect a response back in a certain time frame.
If you got a response back, Linux is alive.
Otherwise it's not.
It's as simple as that.
The things that we can do with this is, however, more interesting.
Whenever Linux doesn't respond in time, and we know it's dead, we can, from the secure
world, we can dump the kernel state, normal world memory, and we can even reboot Linux
kernel while still keeping the safety critical applications running.
So we did that.
It will show a demo where we reboot Linux.
So whenever the monitor in the secure world notices that Linux kernel is dead.
So first, to go back a bit, first we store the kernel image at boot time, because then
we know that Linux is in a good state and it's up and running, because we need access
to the normal world file system.
So we get the image, we store it in the secure world, we protect it from normal world memory,
so that no access from normal world is possible anymore.
So then when Linux crashes, we notice this.
We disable all the cores, because we are on a multi-core system.
We disable all the cores, except for our own.
We write the image back again to the normal world, and then we just jump to the kernel
start address.
I left some tricky things out, because OptiOS needs to do some resetting of its own systems
as well, but that's not that important.
So I have a demo that basically demonstrates this.
So again, on the left, if you can see it clearly, we have the normal world isn't very important,
but you can see that the most important thing is on the right, in the secure world.
You can see on the top that that's the output that the monitor is giving every 500 milliseconds.
So every 500 milliseconds, it's selling a challenge to Linux and getting a response
back if it's a response, it's obviously green.
So now if we go into Linux, and we make, or we cause a crash in the system, a very simple
crash kernel panic, we immediately see that the monitor notices this.
It will start rebooting process, and keep in mind that the secure world is still executing
its task in a real-time fashion with a given known latency.
And after Linux has rebooted, we again see that the monitor notices that Linux is alive,
and we, oh, if after we wait a bit, we get again a shell which we can use like any other
Linux system.
So this is the demo.
Thank you.
So then to conclude, again, our research question, can we ensure availability for safety critical
applications while running a commodity on the same system with little developer impact?
We do believe so.
We did this by leveraging trust zone isolation to isolated critical applications.
We introduced a secure scheduling system with free arthors, and we introduced also a transparent
peripheral sharing system.
We have some documentation online.
I put it as a tutorial, but you need this board to be able to run it.
So it's still ongoing research, and we will update this tutorial whenever we update, we
get new stuff in our research.
You can also look at the documentation for Opti as well, and if you have any questions
at any time, just contact me at this email address.
I'd be happy to answer them.
So that was it.
I hope you enjoyed the presentation, and if you have questions.
Yeah.
So one of the problems I'm really, I work at NARA, and I'm a feeling that Opti is one
of the problems I see with this approach is that you move the device to the secure world.
They basically have a seam layer to make the kind of talk to the device you move to the
secure world.
Yeah.
The problem is, we've been discussing this for a while, but the problem is you expose
a bigger back surface in both the, which is the drivers.
Yeah.
Basically breaking the main assumption of Opti that we don't trust link, right?
So you have a buffer that you feed it into your driver, and you kind of start to trust
that buffer, because it ends up being hard work, so that it needs to be some kind of
arbitration or a rationalization process during that thing.
And have you thought about it?
Yeah, of course.
So the question was indeed that if we move a driver into the secure world, we increase
the attack surface considerably, of course.
And we solved this, or we thought about it indeed, and we came to the conclusion that
it is indeed a problem.
However, if you get secure policies, which you know in advance, so for example, we know
that a peripheral can be read only by the normal world, but not written, because of
course you design a system like so.
You can see based on the actual requests that are sent by the normal world, if it is allowed
or not.
So if it's a, for example, a write request to an address, we know we cannot allow this.
However, if it's a read address, we know we can just execute it and return the data.
However, vendors would just listen and have a hardware that responds to do memory address
cases.
Yeah, but that's not the case, sadly enough.
The thing is that there's an RFC that we haven't been able to reason about it, which we don't
have a workflow, like you have an open, but what we do have is that once the candle comes
up, we measure portions of the text area of the candle.
We take a text, and then we periodically randomly take it, if that hasn't changed.
Now, arguably that's not a very strong back against recent, you know, rocks and stuff
like that, but you should check that out at some point.
Yeah, we are considering this for other research projects that we have running at the same
time.
It's a question that keeps coming back.
How do we authenticate the normal world or the Linux kernel to the secure world?
How do we make sure that it is running correctly?
Because the kernel, when it comes up, we basically change the bounds of the master code that
you want.
Yeah, indeed.
And there is some research going into attestation, so not remote attestation, but locally, and
also some continuous attestation, but it's still an Linux kernel, which is very difficult
to attestate.
The right thing is the kernel itself, right?
So when you write it to memory and then reboot it, you need to have some kind of cryptographic
set, right?
Because the trend in the whole chain of trust is, you know, you boot with the F-level,
so that it verifies your kernel, and then you add the same kind of memory.
So, yeah, of course, yeah.
But if you load the kernel and jump to an entry point, first of all, you need to cryptograph
it.
You verify what you're doing.
Yeah, of course, yeah.
And there's been some code and development going into EFI, where if you jump to the kernel
entry point, and not the EFI entry point, you lose the bound of security services.
Yeah, of course.
So this was a proof of concept, indeed.
If you just write the kernel image back to the normal world and jump to it, it's, of
course, a big problem.
So if you want to actually build such a system in a secure way, you will need to do checking
your image at boot time when you store it in memory.
Once you've checked it and stored it, you know that it's safe.
And then whenever you want to reboot, you can set up the normal world completely so
that it is, again, in a well-known secure state, like at boot time, and then write the
image in there.
We can talk.
Of course, yeah.
There's more problems, right?
Because, for example, if you boot like that, A is a lower-world problem, at least in our
system.
Okay.
Okay, we'll have a good discussion.
Yeah, go ahead.
Maybe a follow-up question to this initial observation about the sort of security aspects
of kind of sharing responsibility for the peripherals.
Another reason why you would want to partition the peripherals rather than to keep control
competed with trust service also performance, right?
Because essentially now you're saying that for any peripheral access, you need that to
go through the...
Yeah, so there is...
I'm sure some latency numbers...
Yeah.
Did you evaluate the overall performance degradation on the Linux?
Yes, indeed we did.
I did not include the slides.
Oh, yeah.
So the question was, if you evaluated the complete latency of sharing peripherals between
the two worlds, yeah, we did indeed verify it.
Yeah, don't have a slide for the graphs.
But if you look at these numbers, you can see that to go to the peripheral from the
normal world, it takes around 103 microseconds.
This is however in a standard call in OptiOS.
There is also something like a fast call, and then you will get six microsecond latency,
which is very fast, certainly fast enough for the requirements set by our industrial
partners.
And also the 68 microseconds to go back is also quickly enough for these systems because
these systems often have a control loop of one millisecond.
So that means that even with these numbers, you have like 95 or above of the original
performance or time of execution in the normal world.
So this is...
We think this is a cost that we can totally take in developing these systems just because
it gives us so many benefits on security level.
Is that good?
Okay.
Yeah.
Go first.
So all aspects of that were traditional hypervisor and VM phase.
So...
For example, like Siemens has seven 1,500 software controllers do essentially the same
thing, I believe, except they do it on x86, and they just have like a secure world and
a hypervisor.
And I guess for example, the system and the VM, how does that compare?
So the question was, how does this system using a trusted execution environment compare
to a hypervisor implementation?
We are at our research group in this synapse.
We are working with very low end embedded devices.
So this is our proof of concept on quite a high processor.
It would be possible to do it in a hypervisor.
I don't know how to do it because I haven't taken a look at it that closely.
But on these very low end embedded devices, it's mostly not useful or it's even damaging
for the lifetime of the device to use a hypervisor because you have also quite some overhead
and a very limited lifetime battery.
You have a very limited energy budget.
So on these slower end processes, there is an arm trust on implementation that is also
very energy efficient.
So if we would of course not use OptiOS and Linux, but take the same principles and apply
it to such a chip, we believe we could stay in the energy budget that the slow end devices
have.
And we don't think it's something we can immediately do with hypervisors.
But of course, it's not my research area.
So that's something that can of course be very interesting to research.
There was a question in the back.
Is there an instance of this hardware that we can use on the cloud to try it out?
I'm afraid not.
So there is no instance in the cloud that is available to try right now.
However, I don't know if you know QEMU, possibly you do.
So QEMU.
It does support arm virtualization.
So we actually first started using that to develop our system.
And we very quickly moved on to a hardware device because of our industry partners.
So the code as this won't immediately run on QEMU.
But if you change the interrupt numbers and the things that are different, it should be
relatively easy to reproduce the same results on virtualized system as well.
Just to continue on the question on virtual machine versus Opti.
I think one key difference is that Opti is actually a real trusted execution environment
in the sense that compared to a virtual machine where the hypervisor would have access to
the address space of the protected application with OptiE, it doesn't.
So anything that runs on the secure world does not see that the physical address space
cannot access.
Well, I guess an example of a question like the CIMU software controller is actually the
hypervisor is not Windows or Linux.
It's the custom hypervisor and that also has access like software.
So if it is an hypervisor that uses hardware virtualization, it does have access to the
address space of whatever VM is running on the machine.
If it's based on Arm64's virtualization extension, it will have access to the address.
And OptiE, the address space is only accessible to the secure world.
It's controlled by the secure monitor which is running in a very privileged level, which
is more privileged than the hypervisor.
So the hypervisor does not get access to the secure application whereas with the hypervisor,
the hypervisor could just mess with the nested page tables and do whatever it wants, access
to the secure field.
Yeah.
Maybe to kick in here then, I love this.
So that's what the copyright now is in the next floor, so please continue this discussion
but just for the general audience, we'll have like a 10 minute break now.
I won't call it a coffee break because there's not enough time to run downstairs.
You will come back up.
But in 10 minutes, we will continue with the next talk but exactly use for these type of
one-to-one entry.
And we can continue the discussion in the next 10 minutes.
Yeah.
One thing I wanted to pitch in.
Talking about hypervisor.