So before the 25 minutes, you mean?
So you scheduled to stop at 1445?
So you give me a give me a heads up.
You can do it up to 35.
Okay, yes.
Sounds good.
Okay.
All right, people.
Let's do the second block today.
I'm very happy.
I'm actually excited about his talk.
So Samuel from the
Heavos company will talk about what's going on in this 5 landscape.
And I think I'm excited about the next step in our community.
So take away Samuel.
Thank you.
So yeah, I'm Samuel.
I work for a company called Heavos.
It's a startup that does RISC-V things.
And today I'm going to talk about confidential computing with RISC-V.
And how do we want to implement an open source implementation of confidential computing?
The previous talks have mentioned things like OptiE.
Some of them have mentioned things like SGX or SEV.
Those are all hardware implementation of the security attributes that the first talk talks
about.
Confidentiality, protection of memory, confidentiality of data in use.
And this talk is really about how we want to achieve that with RISC-V and the difference
between the RISC-V implementation and all other existing implementations that everything
is done in the open.
Everything is open source.
And everyone here in that room is free to come and help and contribute to that implementation.
So that's why I think it's interesting.
Hopefully I'm not wrong.
Okay.
Who was in the RISC-V dev room before?
So that's needed, huh?
RISC-V.
What is RISC-V?
RISC-V is a free and open ISA.
Not open source ISA because there's no source.
It's an ISA, an instruction set architecture.
So it's free as in everyone can use it, can build a CPU out of it without paying in license,
any fees or anything like this.
Actually everyone is free to take half of the specification, implement some weirdos,
CPU.
It doesn't matter.
You can take whatever you want out of this specification.
And it's open in a sense that everything is defined in the open.
So all the specs that are frozen, that's ratified and accepted by the RISC-V international foundation,
they're ratified and some modification can be added to it, but it's more difficult.
But between the time they start to be specified and the time they are ratified, everything
is open.
So it's on GitHub.
You can go and put some comments and some pull requests on CPU specifications that are
actually used in the real world.
So it's quite interesting.
And yeah, the specifications are released under an open source license.
There are two volumes for the specification.
It's fairly small.
It's actually 300 pages, which is I think almost the same amount of pages that x86 uses
for documenting the move instruction.
So it's a good comparison.
So yeah, it's very small.
It's easy to read.
Just go ahead and grab it.
And yeah, the spec is split into the unprivileged and privileged specification.
And I'm going to talk about this next.
Why is the RISC-V ISA interesting?
So first of all, it's simple, as I just said.
If you look at the specification, if you read the specification, there is no micro-architectural
dependency.
So the specification tells you how the ISA must look like.
It doesn't tell you how it must be implemented.
So everyone is free to go and implement the ISA the way they want.
There is no dependency on a specific implementation.
And probably this is why it's small or actually smaller.
It is modular.
So it's the same specification for everyone, RISC-32, RISC-64.
And it's the same implementation for the developer boards that you can find in the market and
the upcoming like the Ventana, multicore SOC, actually massively multicore SOCs.
It's the same spec.
So it's modular.
Everyone uses the same thing.
And it's stable.
So there's a base ISA and a set of standard extensions that are frozen.
That means that you can rely on this to implement your UCPU and you'll be able to use whatever
applications are running and using those extensions.
Those are frozen.
They're not going to change.
And if they change, they change a backward-compatible way.
And extensions are optional.
So you don't have to implement all extensions to be called a RISC-V CPU.
And this here is the base ISA.
So that's the entire base ISA.
This is small.
It's very small.
It's easy to read.
Well, kind of.
Not on that slide, but it's easy to read and it's small.
I talked about the spec being split between privilege and unprivileged parts.
And I'm going to talk about privilege modes, which is what is defined in the privilege
specification.
I'm going to talk about this because it's relevant, really relevant to the confidential
computing implementation.
So there are three basic privilege modes for a RISC-V CPU to run on.
The user mode, supervisor mode, and machine mode.
And you switch between those modes through two mechanisms.
Actually through instructions.
E-Call and M-RED and S-RED.
So if you're in user mode, if you're a CPU running in user mode, which is typically an
application, you make an E-Call, which is a S-Call, basically.
So to implement S-Calls, you're going to use the E-Call instruction.
And if you're in the kernel and you need firmware services, you're going to make another E-Call
and you go down in the privileged level and you're more privileged.
To go back, to go up and move to a less privileged world, you're going to call M-RED from the
firmware world, from the machine mode, and you're only going to call S-RED to get back
from a system call.
And as I said, those modes actually map to real use cases, what we typically used to.
So the user mode is the application mode.
Supervisor mode is where your kernel is going to run.
And machine mode is where your firmware kind of thing, UFI kind of thing, is going to run.
One very important thing for the confidential computing implementation is the two additional
modes, actually three additional modes that have been added with the hypervisor extension.
So there is an extension to the base RISC-V ISA, it's called the H extension, H as in hypervisor.
And this is an extension that's been added and is frozen, so it's something that is not
going to change for supporting virtualization.
So the mode that I've been adding is the H-HACE mode, the VS mode, and the VU mode.
So you can see in this diagram you can run your application as usually in U-mode, and
then you're going to have your hypervisor, your host kernel, when the X extension is
enabled, it's going to run not on S mode, but on H-HACE mode.
So hypervisor, supervisor mode.
This is where your Linux KVM or Zen kind of thing are running.
And then when you're going to create the virtual machine, the virtual machine is going to be
split, if it's a full Linux virtual machine, it's going to be split into two different
modes, the VU mode, the virtualized user mode, and the virtualized supervisor mode.
So your guest kernel is going to run in a virtualized supervisor mode, and your guest
applications are going to run in a virtualized user mode.
All right.
So confidential computing.
I just did like a scratch course in five minutes of RISC-V, so I hope this makes sense.
But anyways, I needed to do this to kind of explain where we want to go with confidential
computing on RISC-V.
So what we're defining currently in RISC-V for confidential computing is called the Aptie
RISC-V specification.
Aptie as in application, processor, trusted execution environment.
So it's a technical group where everything, again, is open.
So there's a GitHub repo for this technical group.
All specifications are there, the discussions, the minik notes, everything.
And it is not ratified yet, not frozen, so this is a work in progress.
So again, feel free to come and join and help and provide some feedback on that specification.
But it is aimed at becoming the reference confidential computing architecture for RISC-V.
So it's currently in a pretty late state.
It's going to be ratified, not ratified, but accepted pretty soon in a few months.
But it's going to be the reference confidential computing architecture for RISC-V.
It's not an ISA specification, so we don't add to the RISC-V set of instruction and architectural
definitions.
But we do identify a few ISA gaps.
For example, what we call the confidential memory attributes, which I'm going to talk
about later.
And just to clarify things, because we talked about Aptie, and for example, there's an implementation
of Aptie for RISC-V.
The Aptie specification for RISC-V is not aiming at the same set of use cases.
Aptie is really trying to do and support the same use cases as TDX, for those who are familiar
with TDX, or SEV, for those who are familiar with this AMD technology.
And basically, this specification is defining a new class of trusted execution environment
for RISC-V.
And these new class are trusted virtual machines.
So same as TDX, so same as SEV.
The goal is really to run full-blown virtual machine in a confidential computing environment,
where you will have memory and data, confidentiality and integrity, as explained in the first
talk.
And the goal is really for people to take their existing workload, their existing virtual
machine, their existing Kubernetes nodes, and move that into a confidential computing
TE.
The same way they're doing this, or they aim at doing this with SEV or TDX.
So they're really two different set of use cases, and Aptie is aiming at this specific
set of use cases.
So there are a few architecture components that I'm going to talk about.
A Aptie beats per heart, sorry, I didn't mention this, but a heart, H-A-R-T in RISC-V terminology,
is actually a CPU core.
It's a core, it's called a heart.
There's a few components that I'm going to go through.
The security manager, the TSM driver, there's a dependency on the hardware root of trust,
and there's a structure, a non-ISA-specified structure called the memory tracking table.
And to go through all these components and kind of explain what they are and how they're
put together to reach the goal of memory and data protection and integrity guarantees when
it's in use.
I'm going to take an example of how, from a cold start of a RISC-V SOC, we could actually
build a trusted virtual machine with the confidential computing architecture that I'm trying to describe.
Okay, so we have a RISC-V SOC with a few components that are mandatory.
We need an IOMMU, we need a root of trust, we need an MMU obviously.
This is all dependent on the H extension on 64-bit RISC-V.
It's basically RISC-V GC, which is the general purpose specification, plus compress, but
we don't need compress, it's just the G part.
But yeah, it's a full-blown 64-bit RISC-V SOC that's running there with an IOMMU.
We do need and mandates the presence of a hardware root of trust, and we need some sort
of memory protection.
So an MMU, a memory checker, something like this.
The first thing that the root of trust is going to measure and load is called the TSM
driver.
So that's the first component of this confidential computing architecture.
And the TSM driver is the trusted component that runs in M mode, in Fermot mode, that's
going to split the world in non-confidential and confidential.
And the TSM driver is a confidential world switcher, and it's the component that basically
toggles a bit in the RISC-V SOC, the AFTEE bit, to tell if the heart is currently running
in confidential mode or non-confidential mode.
So there is an AFTEE bit that is part of the specification that tells at any point in time
if a specific RISC-V core, RISC-V heart, is running in confidential mode or non-confidential
mode.
And the TSM driver is the component that's going to make that switch, is the component
that is going to toggle that switch.
So it's part of the TCB, it's a trusted component, it's a software trusted component, and that
runs in M mode and it does that.
And basically the TSM driver is going to switch from, for example, non-confidential to confidential
when something in non-confidential like a VMM or KVM or your Linux kernel is sending a
specific TE call, which is an E call, basically a call that allows you to move from supervisor
mode to machine mode, so basically from Linux kernel to TSM driver.
The TSM driver is going to trap this and then is going to toggle the AFTEE bit, which means
it's going to atomically switch the CPU into confidential mode, and then it's going to
move to something called the TSM, the trusted security manager, the TE security manager,
sorry.
And to do that it calls the M-RET instruction and move to TSM.
So we are in the kernel, the kernel makes an E call, the TSM driver toggles the CPU
from non-confidential to confidential and then starts running the TSM, and we're going to
talk about the TSM next.
This is what the TSM driver is mostly about.
The TSM driver, I'm going to talk about the TSM right after this, but the one very important
thing that the TSM driver manages is called the memory tracking table.
The memory tracking table is a piece of memory and the structure of this memory tracking
table is not specified in the confidential computing specification.
It is up to any implementation to decide what it puts in this memory tracking table.
What the specs tells is what this memory tracking table is for, and this is what I'm going to
explain now.
The memory tracking table is enforcing, and just to take back, the memory tracking table
leaves in confidential memory.
So the memory tracking table leaves in a piece of memory that is protected from the non-confidential
world to actually see or tamper with.
So it's encrypted, protected, integrity protected memory.
So the memory tracking table enforces the confidentiality memory attribute for each and
every page on the system.
So it's what we call a PMA page tracker.
So it defines if any memory page is confidential or not.
So you take a physical address, you give that to the MTT, to the memory tracking table,
and the MTT tells you if this address belongs to a confidential page or a non-confidential
page.
So with this memory tracking table, any time you want, for example, the non-confidential
world is trying to access physically a page, the memory tracking table is going to be used
by the CPU to actually check if this page is confidential or non-confidential.
If you're trying to access a confidential page from a non-confidential world, if you're
trying to read memory from your trusted virtual machine from your VMM, from your QMU, from
your KVM, then the memory tracking table is going to tell you this is a confidential page,
and that's going to generate a CPU fault.
And it gives you memory protection.
Depending on how you want to implement memory encryption, basically, to protect your memory,
the memory tracking table will be able to tell you which key you need to use to encrypt
or decrypt that physical page.
And you can decide how you want to implement this, how many keys you want to support, if
you want to add one key per TBM or multiple keys, or it's up to the micro-architectural
implementation of the specification to decide what it does with it.
Okay, so the TSM driver managed the memory tracking table, which gives us memory protection
and integrity.
And the next thing the TSM driver is going to do is going to load and measure the next
component, the next trusted component that now runs in less privileged mode, the TSM,
the TE Security Manager.
The TSM lives at the same level as the Linux kernel, as KVM, as the hypervisor, basically.
But it lives in confidential work.
It lives and runs out of confidential memory, and is only run when the RISC-V CPU is running
with the ATEE bit on, which means it's running when it's in confidential mode.
So the TSM, I don't know if people here are familiar with TDX, but there are some similar
similarities here for those who know TDX, unfortunately.
So TSM, it's the TE Security Manager.
It's a trusted piece between the host VMM and the TVM.
So the TVM is the trusted virtual machine that we're trying to build through those steps.
And nothing from the confidential world can actually touch a trusted virtual machine without
going through the trusted, the TE Security Manager, the TSM.
One very important thing that the TSM does is it manages all the second stage page tables.
So the page tables that allows you to translate TVM physical addresses to host physical addresses,
those are managed by the TSM in confidential memory.
So with the confidential computing implementation, KVM no longer manages the second stage page
tables for the trusted virtual machine.
It's all handled by the TSM, which is trusted in confidential memory.
So that's a very important piece of TSM.
And something really important to understand is that it is a passive component.
So it implements security services that are going to be called by the host VMM.
It doesn't run by itself.
It's not something that schedules a TVM or handles interrupts.
It doesn't do anything like this.
It just replies to security requests that are coming from the host.
The host is in control of the machine.
It's not in control of the trusted virtual machine.
It needs to go through the TSM.
And the TSM is only responsible for this, getting security requests from the host, from
the host VMM, and replying to it.
And we do have an open source implementation for this.
So it's called Salus.
It's on GitHub again.
And it basically implements everything that I just described, plus a lot more different
things.
It's all in the specification.
And it's all open source.
So go there.
Yes.
The TSM also manages the NTT.
So whenever the TSM adds a page to a trusted virtual machine, it's going to add entries
to the NTT.
And it's a little bit more complicated than this because it needs to go through the TSM
driver.
But basically, the NTT is something that is owned by the TSM driver and by the TSM.
OK.
So TSM driver started.
It loaded the TSM.
At some point, we have a host OS by Linux kernel with KVM that starts.
It boots some non-confidential virtual machine.
And it's going to be, well, at some point, someone is going to be starting a trusted
virtual machine, a virtual machine that runs in confidential world.
And to do that, there's a set of ABIs between the host VMM on the left, the non-confidential
world, and the TSM.
And that goes through the TSM driver.
The TSM driver is the trusted piece that actually proxies each and every request from the non-confidential
world to the confidential world, to the TSM, basically.
And those are called the T-E host ABIs because there are, it's a set of binary interfaces
that are called from the host to actually manage and request security features from
the TSM.
Everything is proxied through a TSM driver.
So the TSM driver traps the host sending E calls, SBI calls.
And basically, it traps the calls from the host VMM, from KVM, for example.
And it then schedules the TSM to actually run and handle those calls.
So a few examples, creating and destroying a TVM context, converting non-confidential
memory to confidential, and vice versa, mapping pages from non-confidential world to a TVM.
All those security features, they are requested from the host VMM, from KVM, and they are
managed by the TSM.
So KVM itself, obviously, we don't want KVM to actually take a page and add that to a
TVM, a trusted virtual machine address space.
It has to go through the TSM, which manages all the page tables for this TVM.
And for example, if we want to create a TVM, which is what we're aiming or trying to do
here, it goes through a few steps.
And all those steps here map to an actual T, the host ABI, the ABI between KVM and TSM.
And there are basically seven steps.
The first one is to create a TVM context.
So KVM will ask for having a context so that it can use that context and then start configuring
the TVM.
The next thing the KVM needs to do is to allocate some memory from physical pages to the TSM
so that the TSM can actually build the second stage page tables for the TVM that it's going
to create.
Those second stage page tables are living in confidential memory.
So they cannot be handled.
They must not be handled by KVM, by the host VMM.
So KVM donates pages to TSM, and the TSM is going to use that to build those page tables.
It's not meant to be used by the TVM memory.
It's meant to actually track the second stage page tables for the TVM.
Then KVM is going to tell TSM that some memory region needs to be reserved for the TVM.
So that's basically the TVM address space.
And then KVM is going to allocate pages and move those pages from non-confidential to confidential
and ask TSM to map those pages in the memory region that it just asked for creation in
step number three.
The next thing that KVM needs to do is to create TVM CPUs.
Because basically all the CPU state is contained and managed in confidential memory as well.
All the CPU state that the TVM is going to run on top of is managed by the TSM in confidential
memory so that KVM does not see a TVM general purpose registers values and cannot mess with
it, obviously.
So this is all handled by the TSM as well.
And KVM finalize the TVM and eventually ask TSM to start running the TVM.
And this is where your TVM is starting to run off confidential memory with a VCPU which
state is also kept in confidential memory and protected.
So we have this.
TSM just created a TVM upon the host VM request.
And the TVM can also talk back to the TSM.
The TVM never talks back directly to the host VM.
It only talks back to the TSM.
The same way a non-confidential VM exit would be trapped by the host VM, a confidential
TVM VM exit, for example, or any service that the confidential VM needs will be managed
by the TSM driver or the TSM.
So there are a set of ABIs between the TVM and the TSM.
And for example, I think that I didn't talk about, but attestation is something that is
being requested by the TVM.
So the TVM is going to ask for an attestation evidence.
And this is going to be serviced by the TSM through those ABIs here between the TVM and
the TSM.
So the TVM asks for an attestation report, a signed attestation report, an evidence that
is going to send to a line party to run the full attestation dance whenever it wants to
do that.
And the part of the specification, the confidential computing specification, defines how this
attestation flow is going to be running and more importantly, how the attestation evidence
is going to be built out of which measurements and how this is going to be formatted.
Unlike TDX or SGX or SEV, we do use a standard format.
We use X509 certificates for building an evidence.
So each layer on the chain here from the hardware to the TSM loads, measure, and certificates
the next layer.
So this is based on a specification called TCG DICE.
It's a layered specification for building attestation evidence.
And this is what we use with the RISC-V confidential computing implementation.
Usually the TVM, when it asks for attestation evidence, it will get a certificate from the
TSM.
So the TSM builds the certificate with the entire attestation evidence that is part of
the certificate as an X509 extension.
And this certificate is routed back all the way back to the hardware world trust for a
relying party to then verify and attest or not.
Last thing I want to talk about is IO.
I didn't talk about IO because it's a chapter on its own.
There are two kinds of virtual machine IO.
There's the pyro virtualized IO, also known as VRTIO most of the time.
Doing VRTIO with confidential computing, confidential VM, TDX, SEV, or RISC-V is challenging because
basically the VRTIO device implementation is done by the host VM.
So typically your virtual IONet is going to be done by QMU or by an external process running
out of the host user, for example.
So you must share memory between your TVM and your host VM.
So it's complex.
It's actually not very efficient because you need a software IOTLB and you need to do a
buffer bouncing between confidential and non-confidential to be able to share stuff.
You need to harden your guests so that you can actually somehow trust the host implementation,
et cetera.
So there's a lot of discussion around this.
If you go to the Linux Coco mailing list, it's a Linux kernel mailing list.
There's a lot of heated discussion right now.
And the other IO, surprisingly, the other IO form is direct assignment.
That is even more complex.
Direct assignment basically means you take a PCI device that you don't know, that you
know nothing about, and you add that to your TE trusted compute base.
Basically you're going to say, I want my NVIDIA GPU to be part of my trusted virtual machine.
And to do that, you basically need to attest and authenticate the device that you want
to plug into your TVM.
So there's a lot of specification, not a lot, but a few specification, PCI specification
called T-disp, an IDE for protecting the ID link between your device and your TVM.
You need collaboration from the IMU.
It's a very complex topic.
The first one, Virtio.1, is very much in progress.
The direct assignment one, it's still being defined.
So I rushed that through.
I'm done.
Thanks a lot for listening.
I hope it was useful.
Thank you, Seong-ho.
I have time for questions.