Okay.
Hello.
I'm Johnny Bradley.
I work on the Tiki project as a developer and have done for about 20 years, I think.
But I'm not going to do the usual, this is the new stuff in Tiki 25 talk because there's
a lot of it and I thought I would concentrate on something more collaborative.
So this is about markdown.
I'm assuming everyone knows what markdown is and uses it.
If not, we can work it out afterwards.
Sorry, there is a microphone because we can hear it.
Yeah, it's a microphone but only for online people.
Okay.
Yeah, sorry.
I'll try and project.
In the old days, we had BB code starting off which was like HTML with square brackets and
media Wiki obviously everywhere then I found Tiki had its own syntax.
It uses little quote marks instead of asterisk that kind of thing and each time you change
to a different platform, you have to look up in the cheat sheets.
How do I do underline?
Is it underscores?
Is it asterisk?
Whatever.
And more and more in the last few years, we've been finding markdown has appeared more and
more mainly from GitHub and GitLab and the best thing would be if there was just one,
one syntax to rule them all.
In the very olden days, early noughties, there was a project called Wiki Creole which XWiki,
TikiWiki was nearly involved with.
We didn't implement it but XWiki I believe did.
It's based on Wiki Creole.
Right.
Just do that.
Okay, cool.
TiddlyWiki which I always like the name.
DokiWiki, lots of other friends and yeah, but the project stalled.
It didn't quite make it.
I think apparently because MediaWiki just had too much stuff that they couldn't migrate
to a different syntax so it'll ground to a halt.
There was about the same time there was the PHP pair classes which you could do an interchange
with Wiki Creole to MediaWiki to Tiki.
We still use that even though it's not supported anymore.
Oh yeah.
So we need another standard and Jean-Marc insisted that I should put this cartoon in.
This is the original script.
So let's have one more standard.
Here comes Markdown and this was the reason for the title of this talk is I just had this
idea of Markdown taking over the world.
A bit like Godzilla destroying a city.
Markdown was started in 2004.
It was basically a pearl script I believe and over the years more and more people implemented
different versions of it and it became a bunch of different standards.
So then CommonMark project was initiated about 10 years ago and that seemed to be the best
of breed.
It's a Creative Commons definition of how it should work with a test suite and basically
that seems to be the standard adopted by most people.
But obviously it doesn't do everything so many people extended it mainly GitHub so GitHub
flavored Markdown seems to be the generic standard for most places and that is now used
by GitHub, GitLab, Stack Overflow, People Without Logos, Next Cloud we just heard were
there early on.
Discord, Icon Broken, Bugzilla and now even the proprietary softwares like Facebook and
WhatsApp, Telegram, Signal and so on are using it and so we thought Tiki should use it as
well.
So in Tiki 25 we've adopted Markdown, we've always had our own syntax so that carries
on working and now its default is off but you can enable it and it's a little bit alpha
but improving.
The next release hopefully it will become the default syntax and then at some point
in the future Tiki syntax will become read only and will be Markdown like the rest of
the world we assume.
And of course we need our own flavor of it.
One thing was a little surprise to me that you can't do centered text in Markdown that
is outside of the scope of it but all our clients will want to do centered text so we
use, misleadingly in Tiki these are called plugins but you don't have to plug them in
they're just in there.
They're more like WordPress shortcodes I guess.
So yeah you want to center something, you want to do it in a box, formatting tools,
user lists and so on.
I think there's about 250 plugins in Tiki which will carry on working but in Markdown
scope.
We also use CKEditor for our existing WYSIWYG offering.
We decided to review that partly because the licensing changes of CKEditor 5 or 6 is it?
Seems to be a little more challenging.
So we went for ToastUE which is a native Markdown WYSIWYG editor.
Seems very promising.
Again 25.0 it's a little alpha but does the job.
That's about it I'm really under time aren't I?
So yeah you can find out more about our Markdown there Tiki25 which I could go on to.
We have a lot of new stuff in there.
You can play with it on demo.tiki.org and a recap of everything on our wiki page.
I just wanted to say thanks to Mark Laporte who was Tiki leader for a long time and is
still looking after us and he's sort of spearheaded this initiative.
Markdown WYSIWYG editor who did a lot of the backend coding.
I have a MOBA group who initiated the whole thing because they wanted better WYSIWYG and
some mysterious third anonymous benefactor.
That's about it.
Are there any questions?
We have some nice reports that you are most welcome and we have I believe 16 minutes.
16 minutes yeah I should have done more slides.
Yes, yes we have.
So the question was can we can we convert from Tiki Markdown into Markdown Tiki syntax
into Markdown and back again.
Yes we can.
The more you do it the more the page will go weird because there are some things that
are supported in different ways in the different languages but yeah each wiki page has a little
cog icon you get a little dialogue saying do you want it in WYSIWYG or plain editor
and you want it in Tiki or Markdown syntax and it's surprising we weren't expecting
that for Tiki 25.
We're quite pleased that's working already.
Again that will improve.
Yes sir I looked at the common mark specification and basically lacks things which I used from
PHP Markdown extra like tables definition list.
Is there any current Markdown which implements those?
Yes GitHub flavored Markdown sorry yeah repeat the question repeat the question.
So specifically you're asking about tables and other features whether those are supported
in Markdown they're not in the core common mark specification but GitHub flavored Markdown
adds tables and a bunch of other things.
Some things that GitHub do like references to other commits and pull requests and so
on we don't use.
Again Tiki flavored Markdown has our plug-in system so there's another 250 so you can do
search results you can build quite complicated applications.
We're still working out what's missing so I guess we'll get feedback over the next few
months as to what people want to do and still can't.
Yes sir.
First one remark if people are interested we have a converter in XWixi with XWixi rendering
supports many many syntaxes and is able to convert from one to another including from
HTML so if you can convert something to HTML you could actually convert it to any of the
syntaxes that XWixi rendering supports including Markdown common Markdown, GitHub, and many other
like Tiki etc.
I have a question on the did you have a problem for the WYSIWYG with the allowance to do inline
HTML in Markdown to make WYSIWYG go back and forth to come back to the Markdown syntax?
Yes in the Alpha sorry yeah did we have a problem converting from one syntax to the
other where you get little stray bits of HTML creeping into the wiki markup which we obviously
sanitize afterwards.
I think we've nailed all those yes there were some challenges with that in the Alpha stages
and I kept on finding that a bold Markdown tag would then suddenly appear as little HTML
bold tags.
Part of that I think is Toast does some of that.
Then it's the initial release and it's still marked as experimental so yeah I found I don't
know yeah I found Toast community to be a little bit sort of read-only.
I haven't found much of a chat if anyone knows where to talk to the Toast developers better
then I would like to do that and I did the Toast implementation but yes it's something
we're watching out for.
Yes Sean?
The nice thing with common Mark is that there is an advert for public specification with
tests and all that which is quite tough.
Is that all leaving?
Are we?
Is it possible that there will be a version 2?
Because we can't be the only people wanting to add good lists and tables.
Yeah the question was is there going to be a common Mark version 2?
I don't know anyone else got any ideas?
It seems to be is designed to be very complete and it's designed to be very simple so possibly
not I guess we have to wait and see.
As an aside I found out the MIDI you know the music interface system that is still version
1.0 and that started in the 80s so maybe it doesn't need upgrading.
Hello.
I'm just now playing around with myself generating HTML from Markdown.
I was wondering if you have any advice on how to go about it, what tools you can find
yourself.
Depends which language you're writing it in.
Oh yeah sorry.
Are there any tools and libraries you're asking to convert Markdown to HTML?
Yes there's a lot.
We're using the PHP League, common Mark because we're a PHP application, which does most of
the Markdown to HTML conversion and I believe the HTML back to Markdown because again we
go via HTML when we're doing conversion process.
Which language are you in?
I think for me it would be Python.
They're bound to be surely.
I don't know the Python world that well so I'm guessing there'd be a link on probably
on the common Mark website, commonmark.org, you should have a list of all of the libraries
and implementations.
Okay so spend the rest of the half hour as you wish unless there's any more questions.
I'll leave it to it.
Thank you.
Indeed we'll have a short break.