All right, so thanks for coming to this talk.
I know there are a lot of interesting talks for
interesting things put in this one.
So I'm gonna talk about search, more specifically,
about how to deploy one within an organization, okay?
So in this today's talk, I'm gonna cover these topics.
So it all started with engineers using multiple content management tools.
And I'm gonna talk about how searching became a problem and
how we use an OSS tool to address their problem and the limits to its tests.
And how we overcame some of the problems with this.
And I'm gonna touch on contribution side of the project and
I'm gonna share some insights and observations.
Okay, so here's the list of chapters, so let's go.
So just quickly, me and the team.
So I'm an engineer at Toshiba.
I've been recently maintaining the company's cloud infrastructure and
just trying to increase the scope and range of automation through these
activities because otherwise without increasing the automation, we are kinda doomed.
But more importantly, here's the list of very capable,
hardworking engineers that made this project possible.
So I have a huge respect to them.
So now on to the background.
So in large corporations like ours,
we typically have lots and lots of companies.
And our team's job as software engineering center is to deploy and
provide tools to other Toshiba companies,
like product development departments and R&D departments.
Now we have about 200 units of deployment and
we have these tools that are basically sort of heavily OSS based.
And now let me turn on the user point here.
So we have a few more, but these four are like a very,
like a core of our tools.
So now as we diversify with the tools,
the searching became increasingly a problem.
And there were two major reasons.
For one thing, there is no easy way to search laterally.
That is, sometimes we want to search all of these places exhaustively
to make sure that we're not missing anything.
But there's no easy way to do that.
And one more thing is, one more problem is that as we found out,
these tools are not quite cut out for
searching inside certain binary files like PDF files and
office document files, which are really something we use quite often.
So what all of these lead to is that ideally,
what we want is single search box that given a query,
searches all the places and like really no matter where they are and
where the documents are and what the formats are.
So that's what we are going for.
However, this is not a, this is gonna be a daunting task though,
because such a tool would have to be,
not only be able to solve the two problems that I talked about,
but would have to have, like you would have to come with
all the essential features, both on the user side and on the admin side.
That is, we have to be able to easily set up crawlers and
all those things and run them and maintain them easily.
So, but there is a tool specifically designed for
this task and the name of the tool is FES.
So next, I'm gonna quickly talk about what this tool is and
what it's like to use it, as I don't think this is particularly a well known tool.
So FES is, as read me on the GitHub repo sets,
a powerful but easily deployable enterprise search server.
So an enterprise search here describes software for
searching information within an enterprise as opposed to web search,
like Google and DuckDuckGo.
Now, FES uses Elastic Search as its search engine,
meaning that indexing certain binary files like office files and
PD files are more or less automatic.
And one notable feature of this tool is that it comes with several types of
web crawlers.
There's one for web pages and there's also one for
file system like a directory hierarchies.
And there's one for a database as well.
And all of this is to get data from many different kinds of sources.
And if you look at the screenshots, there is a search box and
also they have admin console.
And the search engine results page looks only familiar to many, I think.
And this tool is developed by a company named CodeLips,
which is a company that develops in open sources tools.
And they have a lot of experience engaging with OS's community.
So, and let's take a quick look at how this tool works by looking at
one of its core features, which is a web crawler.
And I think it's a,
a web crawler is basically a backbone of this whole system.
And I think the concept is familiar to everyone.
It basically crawls and indexes web pages,
web page contents and uploaded files.
So the way you create web crawlers on Fisk is you go to admin console and
then set these parameters for web crawlers.
Now there are quite a few parameters here, but
I'm gonna focus on a few important ones.
And first there is, of course, URLs field.
And then you can include and exclude certain URLs.
Fisk respects robots.txt, but certain robots.txt file
doesn't disallow certain not so relevant pages.
So in this case, in that kind of case, this comes in handy.
And there are also fields like depth and max access count,
which you probably want to set to a very high, large value so
that crawlers are not gonna stop pretty much surely.
And then we came to the permissions parameter.
And I think this one needs a little bit more expansion.
So this, this parameter is where you can implement per user access control.
That is, when you, I think the, I hope the phone is versioned up, but
when you list users like that, and let's say the crawlers index everything and
search is ready, then, and the users search something,
only the users listed there see the results.
So but notice that this setting is per web crawler basis,
meaning that if you have 100 projects on GitLab, you're gonna need 100 web
crawlers, which is a lot, so clearly some kind of automation is necessary.
And I'll get back to this point later.
One more quick, one more thing to mention here is that user name here
can be either users on Fisk, Fisk has its own users and
groups, but can also be users authenticated by LDAP directory service.
There's an option to configure this on Fisk.
So I hope that gave you the like some feel on how things work on Fisk.
So let's move on to the customization part of the stock.
So no tools are perfect and Fisk is not an exception.
So we have to customize and patch Fisk in a few ways.
So just quickly, here's a list of patches.
So our dev team engineers over time wrote more than a few patches.
And the general quality improvement patches and bug fix patches
have emerged upstream, but they're also more like experimental and
patches that are very specific to our problem.
And those are kept proprietary.
And I'm gonna talk about two of those patches.
First one is the authentication for web crawlers.
Now, most of the pages of GitLab and Redline are behind login pages.
And Fisk has, so the web crawler has to authenticate itself as it makes its way.
Now, Fisk has a mechanism for this.
That is, you can create web authentication objects and
patch it to each web crawler.
This works in some cases out of the box if the login form page is fairly standard.
But our GitLab uses SAML.
And then as it turns out, Fisk does not support this.
We have to do some patching.
To just go over how the patching works at the conceptual level,
what we did is we defined extra optional parameters that
admin can write on the console.
That is, if there were parameters starting with SAML underscore,
the patched parser of this form is gonna pick them up and store them.
And later, web crawler is gonna see these parameters and
recognizes that SAML authentication,
SAML login needs to be attempted and
runs extra SAML specific logic.
So that's the patch one.
And then the second one is about repository contents.
So many of the repositories we have on GitLab are several gigabytes in size.
So, and both GitLab and
Redmine have pages to view repository files.
So in theory, if you wait long enough,
web crawler is gonna index all these contents through those pages in theory.
But this turned out to be a complete non-starter,
just because it's too slow and quite understandably so.
And the reason is, it's just so
the web crawler is gonna make HTTP requests and
GitLab features the file, just one file from repo and then renders it to the web page.
So there's just too many steps to just get the content of one file.
So what we did is to first clone the repository contents to local file system.
And then run, this is file crawler,
which is a crawler for directory hierarchy and do everything locally.
Now this more or less solved the problem of speed.
But one problem is that since everything is done locally,
when the search indices are stored, the things are, the path is,
the file system path is, so we had to remap these to the URL so
that later when the user clicks a link, it takes the user to
the repository file page on GitLab.
So what we did is, again, we defined custom
optional parameters that the admin can write on the console,
config parameters field, specifically this prefix URL and
this particular URL parameters.
And when these parameters are present, the parser's gonna pick them up.
And then later, the web crawler's gonna see these parameters and
then if these are present, it will perform remapping.
So this is the conceptual overview of how this patching works.
So, yeah, and now most of these parameters
are related to the web driver client on this.
And there's information about this web driver client and
phase 14 issue as since the web driver client is
sort of like discontinued on phase 14 and phase 14 is latest.
And phase 14 has playwright based crawler,
which is still in development and the information in the appendix.
Now, I'm gonna talk about another important subject and
which is automation.
And as you might have guessed, our configuration grew more and
more complicated as it always does.
So for instance, we have way more than quite a few configurations for
each phase instance and so there are lots of manual edits of config files.
But these are taken care of by Ansible and Dockerfile and
I think that's standard.
But perhaps more interesting instance is we have to create
several web crawlers per phase instance.
And the reason is typically on GitLab you have projects and
for each project you have members.
And what you want to make sure is when users search something,
you see only the resources they have access to.
And so to automate the creation of web crawlers in such a case,
Pest has APIs just like GitLab APIs.
So to explain how this is handled,
to look at the sample script, you can kind of combine the GitLab APIs and
Pest APIs.
First you can use GitLab APIs to get all the projects and
then for each projects you can get the list of members.
And then for using that list of members, you can create web crawler.
And this is where Pest API comes in to create web crawler.
And then you can also create web authentication object and
attach it to that web crawler.
So the Pest APIs are mostly like GitLab APIs and
for those who have used them, I think they'll be fairly intuitive.
So that's the quick intro to the Pest APIs and
I'm gonna share some insights and observations that I can make.
So the first is did Pest solve our problems?
And the answer would be definitely yes.
So the users can now search across tools and inside binary files.
And this turned out to be quite powerful as, for instance,
even if the file is like a docx file or even if it's a legacy doc format.
And even if it's in a very obscure location,
in a very old repository, deeply nested places,
users can actually find text inside the file.
So this turned out to be quite powerful.
But it's not without a problem though.
So one problem is the performance.
If you wanna index contents of GitLab,
which have say several hundred projects and
several thousand issues using Pest instance running on this
level of computing resource, it takes us about a couple days to index everything.
And this is something we are trying to improve on.
Like how to incrementally index contents and
using some other techniques.
But for now, that's it for this talk.
So thank you so much for listening.
And I wanna open this up to the Q&A session.
So, any questions?
So you have a different type of resources, right?
So every resource has different properties, I guess.
So I do indexing the same properties for every resource.
Do you have a set of properties to index?
Are you only indexing content?
So I'm trying to understand the question.
Yeah, so when you're indexing documents,
you are indexing the content of the document, the text of the document?
Yes.
Or are you indexing also some of the properties like the name,
the title, the author, the-
I would say yes.
I think, so I think, let me repeat the question.
The question is whether this, you know,
this index only the contents, like the text inside the file,
or does it index things such as metadata,
like title field or PowerPoint or like they have like several metadata.
Yes, it does.
It indexes those metadata as well.
And those are handled by most likely by elastic search.
But yes, on the-
the- we, you know, those metadata are indexed.
And actually, it shows the metadata title
if they are present on the search results page.
So yeah.
I guess, yeah.
The second one is a quick one.
So are you accepting contributions?
To the project?
It's an open project and you are accepting contributions and new blue ones?
I'm sorry, I'm trying to get it.
So your question is whether we are accepting contributions to the-
Sorry.
It-
Not-
On our side, I don't quite think so.
So you have a catalog of connectors to all of this and so on?
To elastic search and so on?
So for instance, I was thinking on CMIS that is an standard for content management.
So I was thinking on trying to continue this new connector, the best project.
Is that an option?
I'm sorry, I'm trying to understand the question.
You said something about connectors, right?
I mean, in that connector, but I don't know if connectors is the right word for you.
I mean, so you have a specific router for every different assistant, right?
You have a router for elastic search, a router for office, a router for set options, right?
So we can add new router for different assistant?
Yes, yes.
I mean, first has several different crores for different types of resources.
And so the question is that are we going to- are we accepting new types of crores as contribution?
Is that the question?
Yeah, it's the one right there.
We're kind of like a cooperation and working as a- on our side working as a project inside a cooperation.
So we buy ourselves a knock at the moment accepting like a contribution to the project, but yeah.
Okay, perfect thing.
Another question?
Are you going to publish the slides that you presented?
The slides that you presented, are you going to publish them somewhere?
There and there will be a convenient program.
Yeah, they're on Fozdom website, so you should be able to download them.
I'm sure I have a question.
I have a short one.
You said indexing is about several days for this project you have.
What about re-indexing?
So if content changes, re-index all the time, but you index, making the whole index new,
or is it faster to just re-index certain documents?
So the question is, let's say, you know, like after index everything,
and then in the subsequent run of web crores and then what kind of crores,
are they updated like, you know, incrementally faster, or do we have to re-index everything?
So the FIST tries to sort of crawl and, you know, like efficiently,
that is, it tries to ignore the contents of web pages that haven't been updated.
It checks the, I think, the last modified field.
But so this, the mechanism of incremental crawling is not very sort of, it's not very ideal.
For instance, the last modified field are like, it's not quite well-imposed, for instance.
It's only the certain types of static web pages use it.
And so it's, you know, like, so there are a lot of unnecessary re-indexing happening,
but there are some mechanisms to, you know, only index things that have been updated.
But I gotta say that that mechanism is not very well-run, and there are a lot of re-indexing,
and then the subsequent crawling is not, you know, not as efficient as we want.
And then, you know, it is, yeah.
Yes.
Okay, thank you very much.
Thank you.