Great. Again, I hope everyone's had a great first day at
Fostem in person again and thank
you for staying to the last presentation.
My name is Lauren and I'm a software engineer at
Condor Labs and I work on the open source project Zulip.
I'm going to be talking about how you can collaborate
via chat, hopefully transparently,
efficiently and asynchronously.
So as a collaboration tool,
and we're thinking especially here as open source communities,
open source software projects, open research projects,
what are some of the benefits of chat that we have?
Really, I mean, we have so many collaboration tools
and communication tools.
We have e-mail, we have our issue trackers.
But chat can really be a place of
generating some community and connection.
Also, it's a low friction,
lightweight place to connect and create some of those things.
So it can be a really beneficial place for our projects,
but it comes with some challenges.
So who here works with
some folks that are maybe in a different time zone than them?
Yeah, me, I definitely do.
So that can be really challenging if you have
a chat application going because we think of chat as being live.
We're all sitting down at our computers together,
but if you're working with someone in a totally different time zone,
then your chat is not going to be synchronous.
It's going to need to be functional in a different sense.
So that's a challenge of chat in our communities.
Also, in our communities, we have so many things going on.
We have new features that we want to implement.
We have bugs that we're fixing issues that we're dealing with.
We have releases to manage,
conferences to attend.
So we've got a lot going on and that can
really make chat become very overwhelming very quickly.
We have a lot of different folks in our communities,
and they all have different needs and play different roles.
So we're going to go through an analysis,
and I encourage you to think about your open source community,
your open research community maybe,
and these roles and what their needs might be,
in addition to the ones that I've specified here.
So project leaders, the folks who are leading the charge of your project,
the people who are making it happen.
What are some of their needs and challenges with chat?
Well, they want to be there and have
those connections with the community in chat,
but they also really want to make sure that they're not missing anything in chat,
if they're not there.
So there's this balance between connecting and also being able to step away from it,
that we have as project leaders.
We have our core contributors.
I'm a core contributor to Zulip.
When your core folks come on,
they're working more often,
they're checking on a chat more often,
but they really want when they check in with chat for it to be relevant to the work they're doing,
and helpful that they're participating in chat.
Then they also want to be able to go away and focus on their work,
and then come back to chat.
So it's again this coming and going that becomes a challenge.
Our casual contributors, folks who are maybe invested in our project,
but are not there day-to-day.
Folks who are checking in maybe on the weekends or once in a while.
So what about these folks?
Well, honestly, if the chat is just a big volume of messages that are coming in,
and this huge stream,
they may not even use chat as a collaboration tool,
because when they come in and see that there are
hundreds and hundreds of unread messages that they have to sort through and see through,
they're going to say, hey, I'm going to go somewhere else to collaborate.
I'm going to look at the issue tracker,
I'm going to be on the email list or whatnot.
They're not going to really know what's going on in the way that chat is.
So that can be really a challenge.
If we want our communities to grow,
we need new folks coming in,
new contributors, new people getting invested in our projects.
When they come in, we don't want those people lurking, hiding.
I don't know what to do, what's going on.
We want those people to be able to feel like they have a space to step
forward and start participating, have a voice,
and not be this shadowy person in the background until they figure things out.
We want them to get a sense of who our community is,
what they're doing, what we're doing together, what we're building.
We have end users,
the people who are using our projects.
So when they come into a chat,
again, it is overwhelming,
lots of conversations going on,
and they have a question or a doubt or maybe some feedback to give.
They may not choose to do that in your chat if there's not a space for them,
that they feel like their voice is going to be heard.
So if it's this chaotic,
loud cacophonous like chat,
hey, what's going on, lots of things going on.
They may be like, all right, no,
I'm not going to be able to engage here.
We really want to create a chat space that they can have these needs met.
Of course, we're talking about interacting with these people,
but there's 20 minutes going on.
These are three characteristics of collaboration and communication with chat that I've identified
as being core to serving open-source, open research projects.
That's as well as live,
having an asynchronous ability to chat,
having an efficient chat experience,
and having a transparent chat experience.
So something that we're working on together.
So going back to Zulip, again,
I'm a contributor to the Zulip open-source project.
It's 100 percent open-source,
modern chat application.
We have many contributors from all over the world,
lots of people making their first time contribution to open-source
through an internship program like Outreachy,
or Google Summer of Code,
or just for their own interests.
Folks can choose to self-host,
obviously open-source their own server with their own chat application,
or we also host Zulip Cloud for folks who want to be organizations on the Cloud.
So let's start talking about tackling those characteristics that I talked about.
So Zulip has this unique topic-based threading model.
So you're probably familiar from chat applications,
who has, everyone has a chat application they're using,
right, with some shape or other on their phone or whatnot.
So we have maybe, we call them in Zulip,
we call them streams.
You might be familiar with channels or rooms,
and this is the big buckets that we set out for conversations that we're having.
The thing about Zulip is we create another layer of context in our streams.
So for example, I have an image here of a stream for our annual summit that we're having.
We're going to have a great time at our annual summit,
and we've actually within our annual summit conversation,
our stream, we have topics that are coming in and binding those groups of conversations together,
kind of like an email subject line would have.
So it's the end of my day.
I've just got my CI passing on my issue.
I'm super excited, but I'm going to sign off.
But I signed into chat just before I go,
and I look and I have 78 unread messages in my annual summit stream.
I was supposed to check in about this today,
and I'm looking through and I open up the topics and I say,
you know what, they're having a very lively discussion about a bouncy castle at our annual summit.
But you know what? I don't like bouncy castles.
I could care less about the bouncy castle.
I have no interest in bouncy castle.
I'm not going to be jumping in the bouncy castle at the summit.
So that is 48 messages that I know right there from the topic.
I don't need to read right now.
I can save those for later.
I can mark them unread now, whatever I'd like to do.
But I can look at these topics and say, you know what?
I'm really interested in the catering because I know some people attending
our summit have some nut allergies that are very severe.
I want to make sure that's part of this discussion focused on our catering.
So I'm going to look at that topic and that focus conversation context there.
If no one's brought that up in those four different messages,
then I'm going to put in a pertinent question there.
Hey, do we know that people are coming with nut allergies?
Are we making sure our catering is accommodating that need?
So by reading through my topics, topic by topic,
I can focus on what my interests are,
where I can add value to the chat,
and it makes the whole experience much more manageable.
So topics really make asynchronous chat work.
We now have folks all over the globe who can participate with
more contextual feedback when they're online.
So again, they really care about that bouncy conversation that happened.
They can still jump in and add their feedback there.
Again, we make some space for people whose voices might get lost,
new folks and users, and so chat becomes more useful for them.
But of course, topics are being used by humans.
Humans do not always work.
We don't have conversations in straight lines.
We don't always make sense all the time.
And we need to make sure that they work with the humans that are working with them.
So at Zulip, we've made a number of tools to work with
the patterns of conversations that we have.
So for example, maybe we have this new feature we're implementing,
we're having this really intense design conversation in our design stream,
and somebody has this really great new idea right here.
What we're going to do is take that new idea message,
we're going to move it over here to its own topic with the new idea.
We're going to create a link between these two topics in the same stream for the design.
And now we have two parallel topic conversations going on in
the same stream about design that have context.
We can go back, we can connect them.
Maybe we're having this really intense conversation about the new release,
and we have a really excited new contributor jump in and say,
hey, my name is and I'm really excited.
And what do we do? How do I get things done?
And we can take that message, move it over to the new person stream,
say introductions, hi, welcome, we're so glad you're here.
Please read our documentation, let us know if you have questions.
And this really important release conversation that's going on in
our release stream continues uninterrupted and we keep our flow organized and efficient.
Maybe you have some come in with a help question, right?
They're asking for help.
They're working on upgrading to the new release.
They have some questions, they've had some issues.
Some of our sysops who look it on,
work with them with a question and they come to a resolution.
That user can then mark that topic as resolved.
A big check mark will show up in front of that topic visually.
And now we know that that question has been answered and resolved.
And so we have this kind of,
they have the ability to step out and say,
hey, you know what, my question was answered, thank you so much.
This is done.
So again, creating organization within our topics makes things more efficient.
People can prioritize their time,
we can move conversations forward,
and people have agency to say, thank you, I'm done.
Or, hey, this unresolved this topic,
we thought we fixed it, but we didn't, it's still an issue, let's unresolved it.
And we're building up all of this,
these conversations are happening, they're branching off here,
they're branching off there, they're branching out there.
We built this big tree, this repository of knowledge.
Now our chat is not something ephemeral,
happening in the moment.
We're really starting to create a repository of
knowledge that's there for everyone to share.
So we've got this asynchronous conversations,
we've got this repository of knowledge.
What about the transparency?
Right? So in our most recent Zillip release in November,
6.0, our public access feature was landed.
And what public access makes basically is,
is an organization with a Zillip can decide, you know what?
That help stream we have,
that's really important information we want to share with everyone.
So we're going to make that web public,
which basically means that anyone on the Internet can access
those conversations without signing in and without logging into your Zillip.
So that now is information that's on the Internet available to anyone.
Whatever their questions are, whatever, however they get there,
they can start accessing that information,
those help questions right away.
Maybe we have our design conversations and we don't put those in a public.
So people know what is our design ethic,
where are we moving, what are we working on?
And we can make that web public and people can engage.
Maybe we've had this really great conversation about
a new feature that we're implementing in our chat,
and we have over here in GitLab our issue tracker for that feature.
We can actually now,
if that conversation happened on a web public stream,
we can take that, make a link to the chat.
And again, anyone who gets to GitLab and looks at our issue and says,
oh, there's more information here,
click relevant chat conversation and now all of
that information without logging in is available to that person.
So again, we're really taking our chat with the public access and moving it beyond
our community and making it relevant to anyone who's curious about our open source,
our open research projects, like what we're doing.
This is a value of open source that we have.
So again, if we're making decisions in chat,
this is available for people to see.
New community members can start learning before they even sign up.
And we have this repository,
this tree of knowledge that we built that's now out there in the wild,
in the forest of the Internet that we have that we're sharing with everyone.
So really creating that transparent and chats becoming much more
relevant beyond just an ephemerable conversation.
So as I mentioned, Zulip is 100 percent open source,
free, you can start your own server.
And we also have our Zulip Cloud which has a free level of support.
Similarly to Slack before they made their change this summer,
which is like limited,
you have a certain history of messages.
With non-profits, open source projects,
academic research, we actually offer sponsorship on our Zulip Cloud standard,
which is normally a paid platform.
So you get even more history available to the public.
It's not limited.
That public access is there.
So we really are committed to being part of the open source community.
And making sure that all of our projects have great connection,
collaboration, and are engaging all of the people who
want to be involved in the organizations.
Again, thank you so much.
That's about it for me.
I have some great links that are in the slides here.
The community's directory is a directory of
organizations on Zulip that have opted into the public access already.
So if you're curious, that's a great place to start looking.
You can find me at Zulip Development Community.
That's where we are talking about Zulip and
the features that we're implementing and what we're doing.
We have some case studies, etc.
So I want to open it to questions or I can jump into one of
these open Zulip instances if anyone's interested.
Yeah. So thank you.
Thank you.
Yes.
So for topics to work efficiently, you need to be really strict with
moving messages around.
And that means that moderators, I guess,
would have to scan every message and move things around.
Yeah, yeah.
So the question is, for topics to work and
removing things around and when people come in,
you take on a lot of moderators who have to kind of be very active and
efficient in that.
Yes, definitely my experience in Zulip Cloud.
It depends on your organization.
You can actually set that up.
So for example, just moving topics within the same stream,
like maybe somebody didn't name it very well.
You can actually set that permission level to a generic user right now.
And we're actually working on our user groups so
that they can be even more designed to be unique to the organization.
So those permissions can kind of be shared throughout your user base.
So we actually have this in our New Year's.
There's a lot of times we're coming in and to Zulip who want to contribute.
And they're sending messages in very quickly.
They'll start actually, if they see a message kind of go jump into a stream and
interrupt a conversation, they'll even just move that out, right?
As a person maybe who was there for two weeks.
But it does require that kind of communal engagement.
But you can disperse that so
it's not just on your core contributors or your moderators.
It can kind of be dispersed and hopefully with user groups,
which is a feature that we're working on and planning.
That'll be even more, can be fine tuned to your organization and
how the community you want to create with your Zulip chat.
Other questions?
Yes.
It's a big one, but the feature that we shared content with the public,
it's really interesting.
But I was wondering, how do you handle privacy?
And is there a way that you can control this kind of things?
Right, so each Zulip organization is deciding.
So the question is, how do you control privacy with public streams and
what's going on for the folks listening at home?
So definitely your organization is deciding what streams are web public,
right?
So that is definitely kind of when you sign on and you're posting in those
streams, it's kind of like this information is available in general on the internet.
There are private streams in Zulip.
There are streams that are public within your Zulip organization that people
have to sign in.
So for example, on our Zulip development community,
the stream for asking help for new contributors, getting help with development,
that's not a web public stream.
Because that's kind of folks being vulnerable and maybe asking questions and
saying, I don't know how to do this, can someone help?
Obviously, that's not something, I mean, that's super brave of them and
we're proud, we want that as public within our organization.
But we're not sending that out to the internet.
So we've made that choice culturally as an organization.
So each organization that decides.
So I believe the REST language that's using the public access feature,
they've decided that all of their streams are web public.
So basically, when you sign up to be part of that chat discussion on the REST
language community, whatever discussion you're having there is available on
the internet.
And so that's just part of the culture of each organization that you're setting up.
You can definitely set it up so there are more privacy focused organizations.
But again, thinking about open source communities and
the fact that we want to be having, there are definitely certain parts of our
conversations and chats that we might want to be having as publicly as possible, right?
So, yeah.
Any other questions?
Yes.
Do you have any integration API?
Yes, yes, we have lots of integrations.
I mean, it's just my company, they try to remove a slack and use things.
And only engineers say, what was that?
It's useless.
So I guess that you have also this kind of integration.
Right, yeah, so you can move from Slack to Zulip, for instance.
Or GitHub to Zulip and so on.
Yes, yes.
Well, GitHub for tracking issues and Zulip as a chat application work together, yeah.
So we track our, we're on GitHub for our open source,
that's where our code is, and so our issues link and
we use integrations for bots to communicate and stuff.
So, but definitely there are lots of integrations and
such that one can use, lots of different authentication methods, etc.
It's a fully fledged modern chat app.
Yeah.
Other questions?
Curiosity.
Again, if your, your,
QISU's been for your open source projects, please, I'll be around tomorrow or
come on the Zulip development community, check us out.
We have lots of public streams and I'm just been really excited to see everyone
here at Fostom, and thank you for having me.