So my name is Joz, I'm a co-founder of Nextcloud and I talk about Nextcloud aka I do marketing.
And today I'm going to talk about what's new in Nextcloud.
Now this became a little bit of a mess because we usually do about three releases a year
and I kind of made up three releases here but there are actually only two.
I just mixed up our own product naming so that was a good one.
I hope nobody is confused but we'll simplify it going forward.
So I will simply go over the products and what's new.
As I said I can't talk about all the features because this is just what's new which is already
as I said 84 slides although we're already on the third so we'll get there don't worry.
I'll do my best at least.
So Nextcloud Hub 2 there was somewhere in March, April.
We introduced user migration that's the first thing I'm going to show.
File locking, automated file locking, load database load, always performance that's always
important I think.
Improvements in talk, desktop integration and a couple of improvements in the group
ware app.
Now I'm going to try and show a couple of these things but there's not a lot to show
or of user migration it basically does what the name suggests.
You can export your account.
This depends a little bit on what the app supports so we have support in a couple of
the important apps like for example files and it'll of course not just export your files
but also the comments on the files, activity history, what your favorite files are so these
metadata gets exported.
Of course your account itself gets exported so you know your profile name and picture
and date all this stuff and the idea is that you can export your account and then go to
another Nextcloud server and import it there.
Nextcloud is hosted by tons of companies as well as on your own and if you say look my
Raspberry Pi isn't pulling it anymore I need something a little faster then you can move
to something bigger.
So yeah apps need to support this so it has some limitations but you can just choose what
you want to turn on so you can say okay export only my files or export files and my email
configuration export this don't export that.
It's fairly simple just download to a zip file.
So what else is new in Nextcloud files we worked a ton on performance I'll get to that
in a minute.
We introduced a search API for indexing that's basically an API for an external indexing
tool like Elasticsearch that can then index the content on Nextcloud and show it to you.
Somebody for open project there looked very happy excellent and we introduced kind of
a little thing but if you share something by mail you can then give it a password and
then email them the password but of course well they already have something kind of unique
which is their email address so we now have a token option that they can simply say hey
I have this email address they will receive a timed token and then they can log in you
don't need to give them a password or something like that.
So I mentioned performance and there are tons of things basically too much to talk about
so I have a couple of details that are just semi randomly picked out.
If you view a folder in this release we got the number of database queries down by 75%.
You can configure cron jobs so you have this background jobs that are running and you know
if you have a very busy server and the cron job hits just at your most busy time that
might not be helpful so these background jobs you can now configure a little bit that you
say hey this is a very heavy task please don't do this at like 11 o'clock or at 9 o'clock
when all the employees log in for example.
So there's a bit more configurability there and it also turned out that our server was
very busy generating avatars in different sizes like one application for next cloud
set can I have it at 65 by 65 pixels the next one wanted 66 by 66.
This is actually a ton of work so we now just offer it in a few sizes and then you know
you can resize it in the browser I mean that works fine and that made quite a difference
you'd be surprised.
What we also did is we separated image preview generation so if you have you know 100,000
photos and you want to scroll in that folder then the next cloud server gets very very
busy generating about 100,000 previews in of course multiple sizes if you do that in
advance that's very nice but then that means your server is simply busy at another time
so what you can do now is you can have an external service that does this so it runs
on a separate server it doesn't bug down your primary next cloud server.
It's little things makes quite a difference now I mentioned file permissions so one thing
we also did is just we made the permissions a little more well advanced and you can very
specifically pick out if you don't just give edit rights but you can say I want you give
the ability to upload but not edit or not delete etc.
Other improvements were like searching for files by the tag of the file, improved group
folders you can now use the viewer app on public links so you share somebody a PDF or
an image and then they can use our internal viewer app on that public link and lots of
other little things there.
So the next step in X.Hub 2 was groupware we did just a couple of features a lot of
under the hood work the features are just a few one is accept and decline directly in
the calendar app that just makes a little quicker you already then see the calendar
item you can just accept it and decline it.
What we did in the mail app is we introduced the ability to send an email later and to
undo send so you have 30 seconds to realize that well you were a little too quick with
that email.
In talk we did again under the hood work also introducing reactions which is of course always
nice to zoom into then we did a media tab and we integrate in the desktop client so
when you get you know talk notification you can click there and the latest version of
the desktop client is even better because if you get like this operating system notification
you can just click reply there and then right there already answer.
Lisa works on Mac OS and think on Windows I'm not sure if Linux has that feature maybe
not yet but it's kind of cool and well here's the obligatory zoom in.
With this release we introduce a new user interface in Next
Out Office so well things fairly obvious we tried to make a little more familiar for
people who are migrating from certain other office applications it's optional you can
configure it as user but I think this yeah just makes it nicer.
Honestly I like the UI a bit more myself I use it now so the last menus to search through.
And the nice thing is we introduced file locking already a while ago so if you're working with
somebody else and it's like not a file you can edit the next file but it's a Photoshop
file for example you need to download it edit it I'll get back to how we made that easier
to later but with this release we made file locking automatic so if you're in Next Out
Office you edit the file then it gets locked so that your colleague isn't on the desktop
client locally editing it at the same time and creating conflicts but instead desktop
client will then say this file is being edited online please don't edit it locally.
Depends a bit on the operating system whether a desktop client can enforce this or only
give warnings because on Windows it's impossible to edit a file which is open on Linux this
is not a problem because it's a proper operating system but it gives you a warning then so
at least you know that you're breaking something and then you can of course also right click
on the file on desktop client and lock the file it shows you who has locked the file
if it's locked by an application it'll not say the name of whoever it was but it'll
say the name of the application so you can see on Next Out Text is locking this file
so people are editing it on the browser now of course in desktop client can just right
click and say open in the browser then it just opens the browser window with that file
and meet the editing so you can just join the editing session so it shouldn't block
you for anything that was already up too I'm gonna get to the next one this has a few more
slides than the other one and also a lot more features well you can read I'm just gonna
show it to you so first thing we did actually was to introduce a new design so well it's
more rounded and it also shows you your wallpaper through so people can you know pick a favorite
wallpaper and then you can see through this wallpaper another benefit let me see yeah
we're back another thing is we also worked a lot on accessibility so you have a nicer
even nicer dark mode you can also set forms for people who have problems with while reading
this lecture yeah dark mode can also switch automatically now and a whole ton of other
changes if you use a different background well I can show you some more screenshots
if you like it bubbly maybe you like a little darker you know that's for the real hackers
dark mode with a dark background I now realize that even though I'm not a hacker I do run
this background by default I like it either way well we also did is once again performance
I can once again of course go in all the details but let me quickly first cover security which
we also work on for every release if you use a server side encryption we allow you to
encrypt S3 based primary storage object storage encrypt encryption that works with group folders
which are used a lot and it takes 33% less storage so it used to be there encryption
algorithm really blew up the size of the files by about a third and now well that's gone
so it gets smaller again and a couple of occ commands to manage the encryption on the client
side we also made a bunch of improvements with user end-to-end encryption in the in
the desktop client and the mobile clients it's faster that was very helpful other people
complained with a lot of files it was slow which it was we also made key management a
little nicer so you can also in the browser reset your keys that also means you lose access
to all your files if you forgot your password but you can start over if you made a mistake
or forgot your password and administrative administrators can then say groups of users
or individual users can give them access to the end-to-end encryption or not so it can
be controlled as well I mentioned performance there was tons of stuff I think in core alone
we did 33 separate improvements I'm not going to show all of them I'm just going to pick
out a few of them otherwise it gets a little crazy so sorting of files went a ton faster
because we only sort the recently changed files it's a little thing but if you're in
a folder with tons of files and you want to sort all of them why would you do that if
you just need to sort the newest on top only look at the newer files it's little things
but it gets a lot faster search became about seven times faster and all these things they
add up because by now if you do a prop find which is kind of operation that a client checks
hey has anything changed on the server that is now about 30% faster so you know it's it's
really common operations they don't get of course a seven time speed up but all these
seven times and little things they add up to well 20 30% if you upgrade to this release
you should really notice it because pages load about a third faster and I think that's
kind of where you notice a difference yourself so anyway that's really good stuff there now
let's talk about the features next I'll talk so we introduced pulse I mean that's really
nice also a couple of other things for example you now have what we call widgets if you can
share if you share a deck card you can then see the information of the deck card this
also works with github tickets it works with youtube videos it works with tons of other
stuff even maps locations and such and that also shows in the media bar on the site that
we introduced in the previous release so I think that's really quite nice we introduced
the ability to basically start a call but not send a notification to everybody so if
you're in a big group and you want to have a call with only three members you can start
a call but then not for 60 people their phones are ringing that might be a little annoying
you can do the same with sending messages so you can send the message but if you do
this Saturday night you shouldn't bother your entire team they all get a ping on their phone
because it's bloody weekend why do you do this maybe shouldn't be working but if you
do then at least you can send it without generating notifications of course in next round you
can also configure your availability and just say outside of these hours please put me
out to medically and do not disturb that also helps but still you can control this but then
of course you might actually want to send somebody call notification because you're
in the call with three people you want number four then you can actually ring their phone
this way directly so all the way around we also introduce message expiration the widgets
that I just already mentioned also works then with YouTube we can also directly now create
files and a ton of different ones the poll I already mentioned but also create a new
document and then it just opens up as immediately shared with everybody can immediately start
editing your office document or whatever you created so that's nice and in a classroom
or a webinar you might sometimes want to stop people from talking and we expended the access
rights with this as well so you can now say okay you know you can't post messages you
cannot react you know no talking until well it's time to open that we also work for scalability
quite a bit we introduce clustering to the high performance back end so for bigger calls
but honestly we don't use clustering ourselves we're now using it for webinars we had 350
people couple weeks ago so that works still on one server but there is of course a point
that you want to have a call with even more people and then you need clustering and that's
helpful all right let's talk about group fare for a minute there's always makes for nice
screenshots so we introduced a nice org chart in our contacts app you just define who is
the boss of who and then it creates a graph that you can zoom in and out and all this
stuff very simple but it's nice was done by a community projects was supported by the
EU so yay for our EU overlords here in Brussels yeah the mail app also got a nice overhaul
mostly UI improvements I'll get to a couple of features in a minute well that's actually
right now so less than a minute you can have now images in your signatures you can configure
an outer responder directly in next cloud and we made the UI of the appointment booking
so this is kind of like Calendly I guess that's been a feature in except for a while and we
improved the UI a little so you can create certain dates and times that people can book
meetings with you also updated the create new account wizard attachment viewer is now
right in mail so if you have a PDF just click it you can view it IMAP invite support so
in an email you get an invitation for the calendar you just click accept and then you're
in there etc so all good stuff let's get to office as I have less than 10 minutes left
I know it's terrible so what did we do yeah you can upload custom fonts that's actually
super helpful because half the documents that looks yet in a clever online slash next at
office just look bad because of the fonts it's very simple in many cases that's the
problem with it and well you can now easily out your fonts in the UI what you can also
do is if a document still looks bad or if it uses like really weird features that require
like local data connections between documents and this stuff there's now a button on the
top left that says open locally you click on it it said are you sure you say yes if
you are and then it'll just lock the file open it on your desktop in Microsoft Office
for example or LibreOffice on your desktop you edit it you close it syncs it back to
the server and unlocks the file this is awesome perfect compatibility because whatever you
run locally works obviously this also works for your Photoshop files so you just go and
next out you look up the file you click the three dot menu you click open locally Photoshop
opens when you're done you close it it unlocks the file again and your colleagues can work
again with it too so fairly simple the button is like the one that next to the save button
the third one top left right we also have this app called collectives it's a knowledge
base application we introduced a whole bunch of improvements like an outline that you see
on the left here and tons of other stuff honestly I need to speed up a little bit so I will
skip through most of this but it's a lot of good stuff believe me you can add mentioned
colleagues you can search for the content of these things in Universal search and the
widgets work as well so you can if you have a link to a github issue or to a youtube video
then it just shows you right there the content and here are the fonts by the way I just mentioned
so you can upload them nice and easy next up photos really cool we introduced photo
albums so you can create a photo album and put photos in there without having to you
know actually move them around you can invite other people to it and share them with them
then we introduced image recognition so there's an AI neural network thingy no we're not
sending it to Google it's running local on your server and it'll recognize different
objects it'll recognize different faces different people text them and then you can find them
by text I'll show you a bit more screenshots later super cool also introduce the photo
editor so you can rotate crop and you know some filters all the basic stuff for your
photos so you know Google killed photos so you can move over now I was trying to well
I have lots of more zoom instincts but you have a nice uploader now that shows you here
are the faces that it automatically recognized and then you can click one and then you go
well and you see all the pictures of that person yeah it's fairly simple can even recognize
music genres obviously not in the photos app but in the music app to be clear but it's
really cool and again it's not using a database it's using machine learning so it really looks
well listens in this case and figures out the genre I don't know how good it is I've
heard it's actually surprisingly good so you know really cool and again all this is on
your server no data is sent anywhere else unlike the big clouds even works on the Raspberry
Pi so that's pretty cool I think on the clients we really did a ton of work for this release
you can of course edit files also on your tablet right next to the office will work
on your tablet or your phone etc but we also introduced widgets so you have these widgets
when you open next cloud you have the dashboard these widgets are now also on your tablets
and on your phone if you want them they use the native widgets iOS widgets so you have
these widgets on iOS where you can have next cloud widgets from your dashboard on your
phone on your tablet etc really cool I think I think I have some examples here exactly
so your files notifications changes files shared with you etc on Windows you now get
this so if you have a virtual file system on Windows so you're not syncing all the files
but you view them and when you click them they get synced but at least you get previews
in the meantime that's new as well quite nice androids few improvements iOS improvements
as well I will not go into details because we are really getting there yeah those were
the widgets two other nice things in the last two minutes I think I have left we made it
a lot easier to get next cloud so there has been a docker image for next cloud for a long
time and this was a kind of IKEA inspired docker image I would say you had to bring your
own database and your own file system and your own you know so you're really setting
up like a bunch of docker images it's very nice if you're really into Kubernetes and
this stuff if you've never heard of Kubernetes like most people we now have an all-in-one
docker image you just download this one docker image and well it'll give you a nice overview
it runs all the other containers in there it's super easy to use we even did a because
we made a VM version of it just VM we've done this docker image running in it on Ubuntu
I think which you can then run on Windows if you want so now suddenly next cloud is
available for Windows Server if you so wish it's still running Linux obviously right it's
not going crazy here but even as backup by the way built in bork backup there is by the
way next out backup app but that's using something completely different that allows you to back
up to another next cloud server times up I have to tell you by the way that you can this
deploy this all-in-one container with one click on these platforms so if you really
love the clouds but you want a little more control you can still run next cloud on any
of these with one two clicks and then you have a deployed there so we're in their app
stores basically not all of them are fully finished yet but we're working on it we'll
get there anyway questions sorry only a few seconds over time it's not so bad questions
come on yeah sorry co-authoring co-authoring of a document so you mean collaborative editing
yes absolutely so in next art office but also next attacks are note-taking and also the
knowledge base so if you're editing a knowledge base document you can do it with 20 people
if you like I mean I don't know why you would so well on iOS and the Android and iOS apps
they do it but on the desktop client not that would open in a browser so you do right click
you say add a document and it opens a browser window and then you're in there yeah does
it support does the noise base support markdown yes it is markdown it dreams markdown it lives
markdown everything is marked down while they're in the next at office but it's an extra text
but then in a different way so it has these widgets all the other stuff just like text
they're basically I don't know it's like text but then with a sidebar that lets you search
and you know choose and link to other documents it's just text and steroids yes can you talk
about our service yes multiple ways but next I'll have a federation feature so you can
share a file to the server of your friend yeah so next I'll talk no at the moment talk
is not federated it's something we want to do but I don't have an eta for you next the
photos app is the default photos app with the recognition everything yes yeah yeah for
the recognition of faces because you need to download a gigantic you know AI thing
file there you need to separately install the recognize app and that's about I don't
know I think it's a gigabyte plus because it needs to download this network that can
recognize your pictures or your server it has arm and x86 which should work most places
but this is a separate action but the photos app itself is there yes collect this you mean
the what do you mean with local content you mean you can insert a file in there yes you
can yes enter file document files from next cloud of course if it's not on next cloud
it'll upload it and put it in a same folder yes no not yet but that's something we would
want to do so the forms app you have next out forms apps like Google forms but then
you're not giving all your data to evil America company yeah and the question was can multiple
people see and manage the same form and there's unfortunately not yet possible so the person
who creates the form they can export the data in a spreadsheet but they can currently not
yet give management to other people we'll get there yes yeah yeah
no how many people can see each other so you can control access rights and if you have
infinite network bandwidth and everybody can see everybody in the real world no and it's
purely depends on your network bandwidth here I think the grid view goes to 20 people or
so beyond that you start to scroll to the next page next page but I believe it scales
with the size of your monitor if I have a gigantic monitor on a high resolution again
no it's open source and it's self hosted you are always the limiting factor believe me
it's anything else local talk clients no so we've Android and iOS client for talk at
the moment but stay tuned that's it awesome thank you for being here everybody
always the limiting factor