All good. I don't know if this is working, but it's green.
Ah, look at you. Crikey. Thank you for coming. Look at this. Excitable people. Collaboration.
Well, so here we are with Collabora. I hope this is what you want to hear. One of my concerns
is that I've given similar talks in the past. So maybe we have lots of time for questions
at the end. So I tried to do some different things this time. So one thing that we're
really eager to do is to get Collabora Online reused in lots of different places. And lots
of innovation going on out there. And lots of people have great ideas of how to use documents
and make them look better on the web. And we would love to integrate with you to do
that. So one of the things that we are really useful for is converting documents to different
formats, which seems like an easy thing to do. But it's really tough. And to wrap that
up nicely for you, we have this beautiful REST endpoint. And it looks so simple. You
just do the skill command. Brilliant. And you ignore certificates, so you should remove
that in deployment. And out of it, you get, well, what do you get? You get your text file
turned into a Doc X. That's an easy one. But imagine you wanted to convert a PDF or a PPTX
into a PDF. Or a very common request is converting PPTX into animated SVG. So we can do that
very nicely. We can produce XHTML out of it. You can run in your browser. That's actually
how Collabora Online does its presentation thing. So you can get animations and presentations.
You can understand the structure of your arbitrarily horrible, say, binary PowerPoint file. And
you can dump that into something you can parse and read and interpret and mash up and do
cool stuff with. And the good news about that is that, well, see, people do this already
in lots of horrible ways. So I will pick on someone. I don't know. Is there any, who do
we have in the room? OK, let me think. What integration do I particularly like? So there
is an unnamed open source project. And when it tries to convert its files to show them
in its jitsy-like, remarkably jitsy-like video, no, not jitsy. I forget. One of these video
conferencing systems, big blue button, let's call it. It essentially has a shell script.
And all of the good, beautiful software architecture stops at the point you want to convert a document.
And it launches a shell script which starts a Docker image, which then launches another
shell script in the Docker image that copies a file into it with some horrible command
that then converts it via another shell script that launches an office suite that sits and
talks to a RPC. And then it's just absolute horror. And if any of this hangs or dies or
crashes or burns or uses more CPU or finds that one document that has a real problem,
you're just doomed. You have to write all of this lifecycle management nightmare. And
the good news is, with our beautiful API, you don't need to care about any of that. Deploy
the Docker image. Job done. If it's too big, we'll time out. If it's too horrible, we'll
tell you. And it's all done for you. So that's kind of good if you want the whole document.
Often, though, people have enterprise files they can share. They want to see their documents.
You know, they're fed up of seeing an icon. They want to see what's inside it. So again,
we can convert your document to an easy thumbnail, very trivially. Nice big image. You can shrink
it down to whatever size you like. And that's pretty good. So we're really eager that people
use it everywhere. And so we've written most of the work for you already. So you can use
it. I think it's a patchy license. I'm a really liberal, you know. I'm more of a copy left
guy. But at least I understand. Some other people aren't. So, you know, in the language
of choice, we probably missed our Ruby. I'm going to get in trouble with, you know, Neil
later. But there you go. And we've done a whole lot of features recently. So one of
them I was really surprised and encouraged. I was talking to someone from a European office
full of lawyers earlier. And you wouldn't believe it, but they really love citations.
That's, you know, they're all court cases, of course. I always think academic citations.
But, you know, referring to other legal cases, it's this massive, world wide web of knowledge
about what's fair, you know. And anyway, so we've done lots of things with Zotero. So
one of the things that you can do if you have a collaborative online integration now is
to just to push, you know, we added all this citation stuff in the tool bar here. And NextCloud
implemented this. And all you need to do is provide a box somewhere that you can set this
API key. So Zotero have a very nice REST API. And then we plug into that and you send us
this, we have this user private info. So you have a user info which has things like avatars
and extended information about users that we send to everyone in the UI. We thought it
was best not to send your private key to everyone. So we added this extra tag, user private info.
And so when you connect to collaborative online and embed it in your iFrame, you need three
methods. Get, so we can get the file and show it and render it. And then a post so we can
send it back again when we've edited it. So that's the save. And then there's a check
file info. And that basically tells us about you. So who is this person? You know, we've
got a path thing, a URL for the document. And we've got a opaque identification password
to token. But what's their name? Tell me their name. Tell me their, you know, what they look
like, their avatar and this sort of thing. And so you just send this back there and bingo.
Suddenly you have beautiful integration with all of your citation libraries. You don't
need to run a Java wrap on the side and then talk. It just works really nicely. And updates
all of your citations beautifully with a familiar interface. So that's kind of nice. That's a
way of integrating sort of two things together through a very, very simple REST API into
a nice UI. Yeah. So language tool is something else I love. I don't know if Daniel, Daniel's,
he's probably a rich man. Grammarly, you know, has set a price point for, does anyone get
Grammarly adverts? Has anyone watched YouTube? Has been plagued by, yeah. So, you know, there
are many ways to create value in the world. You know, one of them is, of course, to create
value. The other is to tell people you've created value. And, you know, and I think
often as engineers we forget to tell people that we've created the value. You know, that's
the problem. We do it all and then there's no marketing. I think Grammarly is probably
the extreme example of, you know, marketing versus value. But anyway, so they can sell
somehow for 30 bucks a month, 50 bucks a month, something like that, a subscription to their
web grammar checker that sends all your information to someone else and sends it back, you know,
with grammar checking, which is great. But because they've set the price point, there's
a great company in Germany, I think based in Potsdam, that make, well, they already
made an open source grammar checker. They've done the whole create the value bit. And so,
but they now sell these lovely plug-ins to people and you can, you know, for much less
money, get a better open source product and they have some of those nice AI things in
there, you know. And AI is cool. Of course, for checking an ISBN is valid, probably not
the best use of AI, I might argue. But on the other hand, sentence structure and human
language, you know, that can be pretty cool. So, they're taking on Grammarly. And the nice
thing about that, of course, is you can get a Docker image and you can deploy that in
your Kubernetes, you know, whatever and connect it up to Collabora Online. So, all of your
grammar checking stays in-house. So, you get the benefit of all of that goodness. And,
you know, from a European free software company, I love it. And they're doing well and they're
growing really nicely. So, nice to see that happen. Very easy to set up. And they even
document the API nicely, which is kind of cool. So, you can see all of the, you know,
number of features exposed in some of the JSON API they have for that URL. Again, very
simple endpoints. You know, you just send your stuff to check and you get some answers
back and we show it. And then, of course, you can configure that as you like. And they
have a web service. I mean, another example of just sending text and getting text back
is our DeepL integration. So, another easy thing there that's often useful for people.
And yeah, it's a bit interesting this. So, obviously, they want to try and retain formatting,
which is probably one of the big advantages over pasting it into your web browser. But
you can buy an enterprise key for DeepL and use that, but you're not going to have it
on premise, I guess. And then, trying to really get styles through HTML and map them back
properly is more challenging than you might imagine. And we haven't done a very good job
of it. So, if anyone wants to improve that, they're very welcome to, you know, to come
and contribute. But I think this idea of, you know, ask the computer to improve my document
and stuff, that interaction thing is there and working nicely. And there's lots of easy,
low-hanging fruit if people want to help do cool stuff. So, one of the other things we
try and do is we try and integrate outside the iframe. It's interesting. So, you create
virtualization, for example. And almost all of the interesting thing about virtualization
is the bit that isn't virtualized, you know, the bit where you can punch through the magic
to not virtualize something and, you know, run the command inside the, anyway. So, similarly
with us, you know, the integration is probably the most interesting bit around the edge.
And it's much the best if you can do that. So, we've written a huge SDK so that you're,
it's easy to do, which you can see online. And so, when you save as, it seems easy to
save as, right? But I just explained to you how it works. You know, you do a get and you
do a post and that's kind of easy for us. But if you want to save it as something else,
it's more tricky. So, but yet people kind of want that if they're editing a document.
They, you know, often people load a document and they continually save it as through its
lifetime. So, the document you get actually started in 1995, you know? And it's been saved
as ever since, you know, with a nice template and the WMF preview of Windows Metafire in
the top right corner and all of that good stuff. And often we see the macros in it.
I mean, we're analyzing government macros and we routinely see, like, the Windows, the
Office 95 macro API had a compatibility when Office 97 arrived. And we're still seeing
that in macros, you know, the word basic dot something thing. Just extraordinary. Anyway,
save as is used. So, we should do that. I talk very quickly. Who has got lost? Does
anyone, you know, know, you're, I'm sorry. Okay. So, we need a file picker. So, how are
we going to get that? Well, I mentioned this check file info thing that tells us what you
can cope with. And if you say, well, we can do insert remote image and we can do this
right relative thing, then we'll send you a post message when you click save as. We
send a post message outside the frame saying, hey, we want a graphic from somewhere, you
know? And then you can do what you like. You pop up your nice file picker, come arbitrary
image creator, ASCII art, you know, whatever thing. We don't care. And when you're done,
send us this action insert graphic and just a URL to it and we'll put it in the document.
That's kind of cool. Or we'll save as and reload and, you know, create a window for
the new document. So, that's really useful and easy to do. And we're using, I think,
the same hooks for our new export stuff. So, there's a whole lot of work in accessible
PDF creation and PDF UA. And I mean, look at all these options. I mean, I hate options.
But, you know, apparently you need all of these. So, we've added loads of them recently
and you'll be pleased. And, of course, repub, it's very, very useful for accessibility.
It's kind of an extended HTML dialect. So, you know, you can integrate easily and get
all of this richness suddenly. One of our problems, of course, is that interoperability
is really, really key in what we're doing. And people really care about that. And one
of the challenges we have at the moment is our competition really is not great at interoperability.
They're spoiled by interoperating with themselves a whole lot, which is easier. And so, when
we save, I mean, we love ODF, right? But if you save in an ODF file, and hey, Neil, it's
good to see you. And then you sort of download it somewhere else and give it to someone on
a Windows machine, like it's not, they'll load it in Word. And it will completely mangle
the document. You know, they even have a big list of the things they break. You know, there's
a, I don't know if it's a thousand pages. It's a very large document that explains all the
things they don't do, you know, change tracking. I mean, why would you want that? You know,
what kind of features? Anyway, so, so lots of it is dropped on the floor, which would
be fine, because obviously that product is awful. But it's sad to be blamed. You know,
for someone, I mean, like, you know, the user perception is your product doesn't interoperate.
You're like, are you sure it's me? You know, like, I don't know. So, of course, if you use,
if you use the doc X file format tragically, you know, we can interoperate better with
the other, other world, which is a shame. But the good news is you shouldn't need to
do that. You can use it all online in the browser and you can feel happy and relaxed,
knowing it's an ODF format on your server and you have a full feature experience. But
anyway, I was distracted. Remote font management. So, so that's all very good. But if you've
ever written slides, what you'll notice is that, you know, that you change the wording
of this, this line here until it just about fits in and doesn't wrap horribly, you know.
And that's great. But of course, it's highly dependent on the font being used. And if you
change the font, be it ever so slightly, you know, the text can grow and then everything
looks awful. And of course, my slides look awful anyway, just because I'm a hacker. But
other people have beautiful looking slides. And so anyway, we decided it was very useful
to be able to configure fonts and that brings a whole load of interesting problems. But
anyway, to make this even easier, we have remote configuration. So, so one of the things
that's nice is to be able to deploy lots of images on Kubernetes and demand scale and
more and more of these things. But it's a bit of a pain to configure them. And particularly
for a large hoster or something, you know, you have customers that arrive quite regularly
and add things and how you're going to deal with that and do you restart all the note?
What do you do? So, we have this remote configuration endpoint now. So you can cut a whole load of
your config out and collaborative line just go, hey, tell me my config. Oh, has it changed?
And they pull it every minute or so and update a whole subset of those settings to make it
easier. And one of those courses, the font, font setting. So it's easy to have then a
path to font. So if you have a file sync and share thing and you can manage files, you
know, just create a folder and drop loads of fonts in it and then we'll notice. And,
you know, we just get this kind of JSON come out of that font endpoint, this thing we can
figure in that tells us where they are and ideally some time stamps so we don't, you
know, continually fetch them. And then we can just build a whole set of fonts. And in
the background it's very funky because we have a fork hit. So you can't fork if you
have threads and it's kind of useful to have threads. So we initialize LibreOffice in what
we call the fork hit whose job is just to fork. And we pre-initialize everything, load
our configuration and then we fork and copy on writes huge amounts of our static data.
So if you started LibreOffice and thought, well, it took several seconds, what am I going
to do online? Because that's the instant we fork within, you know, milliseconds and we
have a document there ready to load and open. But the problem is it really needs all the
fonts and we really don't want to handle all of those fonts to the child processes and
we really control this very carefully from a security perspective. So anyway, after lots
of work we now restart this, respawn, load files and pass them in and patch lots of infrastructure.
I was actually just talking to Leonard and a few minutes ago about, he was telling me,
oh, you've got to mount proc, you have to mount proc, you'll get screwed over, you have
to mount devices. Otherwise, something will go wrong in your stack somewhere and we're
like, yeah, well, you know, we tested that and we, you know, fixed and we patched around
those things so that actually, you know, our jails have almost nothing in them. No proc,
only two devices in slash dev, no shell, you know, they're pretty well locked down. So
we like that. Oh, and then I've got a few minutes so I'll just show you a whole load
of gratuitous features we've added just in case you like features. The users do, it turns
out. So I'm a big hater of the blockchain but Devdow actually sponsored some of this
work, so we like that. And the European Commission as well, so getting our columns into our spreadsheets,
lots of them, has been happening and it's got rid of this very annoying dialogue that
played lots of users for a long time, so that's really cool. Oh, and there's even the proper
credit for the NGIA Dapsey. So the European Union Horizon Research Program is actually
really cool and anyone who's not knows about it, if you have a good idea, the traditional
way of getting funding from the European Union was that if you have a really good idea, you
need to find 15 other people across 27 countries and then try and persuade them all that their
idea is the same thing and then get someone to write the proposal and submit it and then
you don't get it because it's all inconsistent. So the good thing about the NGIA Dapsey, the
Horizon Research thing was that they said, hey, let's do something that's good for Europeans
and so they would just give money to single vision of stuff and our vision was, well,
let's fix interoperability. So we did a lot of that and they paid, which is awesome. Look
at that. That's, yeah, you know, it just makes life so much easier, doesn't it? And probably
good for Europe as well. So anyway, so form controls, creating lots of nice rich text
folders, much better PDF export with creating real editable PDFs actually built into the
product rather than having to layer things over the top afterwards, starting to theme
colors so that you can select different bits of your document and change the theme and
see how that impacts the whole document and we're doing lots of work here to extend that
to writer and calc. Chart data tables, you wouldn't believe it, but these things at the
bottom of charts are very popular in presentations. Some people like lines and other people like
numbers and now you can do both in the same thing. It's a key interoperability thing.
And then also other random interrupt things, you know, precisely anchoring your images
and reflowing your text very nicely in the browser, improving our formula input bar,
accessibility checker to try and find problems in your documents for the visually impaired,
prettier dialogue functionality, so happening in the client side and lots of this is now
JavaScript in the client side to make it more accessible and performance. We completely
reworked the tile serving thing, so instead of sending new tiles when things change, we
send very small deltas of them, so we find the pixels that change and then we Z-standard
compress them, so we switch from big PNGs with like even headers in them and crazy stuff
to much smaller Z-standard compressed things thanks to Facebook. I just need to thank Facebook
for helping us all get digital sovereignty back, you know, that's important, you know.
Good options, so you can put passwords on your files and various attributes, lots I've
mentioned the PDF things, embedded video playbacks if you like, if you like that sort of thing.
And the last silly idea I think in the few seconds I have left. So we've done a bit of
a concept for running Collabor Online in the browser, so when you go through your tunnel
and my hip is that tunnels get better connectivity, but you can then click a button and in theory
run this thing offline. So we have a prototype now of Collabor Online, if you're interested
in that, there will be talks in the LibreOffice track which is I suppose somewhere nearby,
that then allows you to edit offline and there are a whole lot of interesting problems there.
If you like wrestling with massive multi-gigabyte linkages and horrible nightmares, do get involved
with that, but there's a little prototype there that will allow you to work on that and
play with Wasm. So yeah, come hack with us, we have Hackfest. So there's a LibreOffice
Hackfest if you're excited about LibreOffice and you should be. The cool kits are all using
LibreOffice technology. Come to our Hackfest this Monday and Tuesday. We have a community
dinner tonight with Pastor at the Business and Technology Incubator and there's a great
link there. If you take a photo of it, you'll have it for later so you can come along. And
beyond that, we're running our Hackfest in Clarecorage, Cambridge in March 28th and 29th,
which is not only LibreOffice but also Collabor Online and it would be lovely to see you there.
If you want to come and stay in a beautiful Cambridge College and wine and dine at our
expense and have some team building and get stuck into Collabor Online, we'd love to have
you with us. So thank you for your patience. Are there any questions? Yes, sir.
When can we expect a chat GPT integration with Collabora?
Well you know, like I say, yeah, when can we expect chat GPT integration with Collabora?
I'm sorry, I have to repeat the question. Yes, so this is a really good question. I mean,
ultimately, you can select some text and we can send that to you and you can send it back
quite easily. But yeah, I mean, I think AI brings a whole lot of interesting challenges
and I think, I don't know if you've looked at Office 365 and the AI slide improver, which
I obviously should have used, you know. It makes your slides look pretty but the question
is what are pretty slides? And you know, the real problem in AI is of course the training
data. And one of our problems is that we like this digital sovereign world where we don't
spy on people all the time to work out what they're doing to their documents, right? So
Microsoft doesn't have this problem. They have Office 365 and they're constantly watching,
you know. So they know how to make pretty slides just by watching millions of people
go, colors a bit, and also offering you options of different ways to break or improve your
slide and seeing what you choose. So yeah, I mean, how do we build the data sets to let
us do this in an open source way? And I think AI is fantastically interesting and Bradley
no doubt will come up with a Farrow AI license, you know. I'm sure this is happening because
the source is banal beyond belief in most AI, you know, things. It's the data and the
training data and the model you build. So yeah, it would suck to be an open source company,
100% open source code. It's just this massive binary blob that not even we understand that
you have to buy, you know, to make it useful. So I don't know. We're working on the problem
and there are a lot of smart minds thinking about putting AI and keeping that sovereign
and on premise, but I don't have a perfect answer. But it's a fantastic question. And
if you want to do a chat GPT, we should talk, you know, come and see me. I did mention we're
hiring people. I'm probably not supposed to, but we love C++ hackers. If you come and see
me, you know, we're growing fast and doing some cool things. Other questions? Anyone
at all? No? More? Yeah? Well, that's very good of you then. Come and see me afterwards
if you want to chat. Please do. Thank you so much.