I am Gabor Sarnas and I'm here with David Proha.
We work at CWI Amsterdam and we're here to
present you the IDBC social network benchmark.
What is the IDBC?
The abbreviation stands for Linked Data Benchmark Council.
It is a non-profit company founded in 2012,
and its mission is to accelerate
the progress in the field of graph data management.
To this end, it designs and
governs the use of graph benchmarks and everything we do
is open source under the Apache version 2 license.
From an organizational perspective,
IDBC consists of more than 20 members
who all have some vested interest in graph data management.
We have financial service providers like the end group,
database vendors like Oracle, Neo4j, and TIGR graph,
cloud vendors like AWS,
and hardware vendors like Intel.
Also, we have individual contributors like David and
me who contribute to the benchmarks.
So to put things into context,
the last two decades has seen a rise in
the use of modern graph database management systems.
Typically, the data model used in these systems is
called the property graph which is a labeled graph,
where both the nodes and the edges
can have an arbitrary number of properties.
For example, this is a small social network consisting of
five person nodes and the single city node,
which is the city of Spa.
The properties can be on the nodes.
For example, here the nodes have names and the edges have
attributes like the date when the friendship was established.
We can see that Bob and Carl met in 2015.
If you want to run a query on the system,
we can use a graph query where we
look for matches of a given graph.
So here, the query says we want to start from Bob.
We want to use an arbitrary number of edges to reach
some person who lives in Spa and we want
to do an aggregation to return the number of those people.
If you want to evaluate this,
we then start from the person Bob,
push to all the people transitively,
which are known by Bob directly or via multiple edges.
This means all four people here.
We shrink it down to the people who actually live in Spa,
then add up the results and get the result too.
So graph databases use something called a visual graph syntax,
also known as the SKR graph syntax,
which is similar to the popular cipher language of Neo4j.
Here, this query is actually really
similar to the graph pattern that I have shown.
So there are similarities in how the nodes are formulated,
how the edges are captured in this text,
and also how the transitive closure of
the little asterisk is captured in the query language.
So this is a very intuitive and concise way of formulating the queries.
If we deconstruct this query,
you can see three main components.
The one is relational operators.
Obviously, we still need relational operators.
We want to be able to identify people by filtering.
So we filter for Bob,
we filter for Spa,
and also we want to sometimes aggregate.
So the count aggregation is part of this query.
The pathfinding is really elegant in this formulation because we have
nodes asterisk which captures that we can use an arbitrary number of edges.
The pattern matching which connects the person to Spa is
also very concise and readable.
So what is interesting from a future of our perspective on graph databases?
Obviously, relational operators are quite well known at this point,
and there are endless papers and techniques on how to implement these.
But we believe that pathfinding and pattern matching is really good in
graph databases compared to traditional relational systems because they provide
a more concise syntax and better algorithms and implementations.
Interestingly enough, even in the last 15 years,
there have been lots of papers on better BFS algorithms,
better factorization representations for graph patterns,
multi-waver, squares optimal joins, and so on.
So we believe that this should be adopted by more and more systems.
To this end, we designed benchmarks that try to push the state of the art and
force systems to adopt better and better techniques.
David, we'll talk about these benchmarks.
Yeah. So I will give an overview about the social network benchmark.
So first, we'll go through three steps of this benchmark.
So the datasets, two example queries,
and the update operations done in this benchmark.
So here we see a small example of the datasets where on the left side,
we see persons with friendships, forms, and network,
and these persons post messages on the social network and can
reply to each other forming a tree-shaped data structure.
Now, we will do one query on this very small dataset example.
So with query nine, we want to retrieve messages posted by
a given person friends and friends of friends before a given date.
The dates are here short for simplicity.
So if we would start with Bob,
we will traverse through their friends and friends of friends,
retrieve the messages, and then filter out the ones that are actually before Saturday.
Then we touch upon 10 nodes in this data.
Suppose we would start from another person,
so for example, Finn,
and we traverse again to their friends and friends of friends.
Here we see that we touched upon five different nodes,
so half of the one of Bob.
This difference can actually be troublesome
since run times for the same queries are different,
and therefore, it doesn't help in understanding what's happening.
So for this benchmark,
we actually want to select parameters that have similar run times,
and also to actually stress the technical difficulties in these systems.
So we select the parameters more carefully.
So here we see a example of when we do not select the parameters carefully,
just a uniform random,
and we can see here a trial model,
a distribution by model, and one with many outliers,
and we don't want that.
So in the datasets,
there are also statistics provided.
In this example,
for each person, the number of friends and friends of friends,
and then we want to select persons with
similar number to get more predictable run times.
So if we do that,
then we can see here example that we have unimodal distributions,
a bit very tight run times,
and that improves also in understanding these behavior of the queries.
So now we're going to the updates,
and for example, if we have an GI who wants to be friends,
we insert a nose edge,
and this is then formed into the network.
Suppose that the next operation is inserted in comments.
So GI comments replies on a message posted by Eve,
and both messages are posted on the same date.
Then we have another problem,
because when we are executing these operations concurrently,
it can happen that the reply is earlier than the message in such a network,
closing an error, and to mitigate this,
we introduce dependency tracking.
So for each operation,
and also includes the edges,
but just for simplicity,
the notes are here with the dependent dates.
We include for each operation a creation date and dependent date.
The creation date is when it's scheduled to be executed,
and the dependent date is the one that's like,
in this case for M6,
is the creation date of M3.
Here, we can see actually that each operation is dependent on
each other forming a whole chain in the social network.
Suppose now that Eve wants to leave the social network and removes our account.
So we start with deleting the notes Eve,
and this will trigger cascading effects,
but since we then need to remove the edges connected to Eve,
the messages posted,
and also the replies to those messages.
We can actually see like there's this huge cascading effects,
and that can actually have a large impact on the data distribution,
and also therefore the executability of these operations.
Furthermore, it also influences for selecting the parameters,
which we have shown before,
and we want to include this deletes because it prohibits
appends only data structures in databases,
and also stress the garbage collector of these systems.
Now, we are going to give another example to also stress
the temporal aspect of this benchmark.
So suppose we want to find a path between two persons.
So we have a start person and destination person,
and for example, Finn and Gia.
Then we can see here that we have a four-hole path between these persons.
But at one point in the benchmark,
it can happen that a note edge is removed,
and then there is no path anymore.
It can also happen that there's another edge
inserted between Carl and Gia,
and then we have a path again.
So for the same parameters,
we can actually have three different outcomes.
To mitigate this, we do temporal parameter selection.
So each parameter is assigned in a time bucket to actually ensure that
we have similar results and therefore also similar run times.
Now, going through the benchmark workflow,
so we start by the data gen,
and the data gen provides us with
a temporal graph spanning of social media activity for three years,
and it is simulated similar to Facebook social network.
It's a Spark-based data generator that can generate data up to 30 terabytes,
and it contains skewed datasets,
for example, with the notes and person data in this data.
So the output is a dataset suitable for loading into the system on a test,
updates which are then executed during the benchmark,
and statistics where we can select parameters.
This election of the parameters is done in the parameter generator,
and this ensures the stable query run times,
and assigns parameters into a temporal bucket.
So a parameter, it may include parameters that once are inserted
into the datasets or before they are removed from the network.
So then we have a benchmark driver who schedules these operations,
and it ensures that they can be executed with using the dependency tracking,
and this is especially important when executing the operations concurrently.
Lastly, we have the system on the test where we have, for example,
graph databases, triple stores,
or relational databases, and now,
Garber will go further into the workloads.
Okay. So graph workloads are actually quite
diverse in terms of what they are trying to achieve,
and our benchmark reflects that by having multiple workloads.
We have the social network benchmark interactive workload,
which is transactional in nature.
So it has loads of concurrent operations.
The queries here are relatively simple.
So they always start in one or two person nodes,
the same as David presented before,
and here the systems are striving to achieve a high throughput.
So the competition is getting as many operations per second as possible.
We are happy to report that we have official results from the last three years,
where our system started with slightly above 5,000 operations per second,
and have sped up exponentially,
now being close to 17,000 operations per second on a 100 gigabyte dataset.
The other workload of the social network benchmark is called business intelligence.
This is an analytical workload where the queries touch on large portions of the data.
For example, this query in this slide shows a case where we start from
a given country and then find all triangles of friendships in that country.
It's easy to see that this is a very heavy hitting operation.
It may touch on billions of edges in the graph,
and it also has to do a complex computation to find those people.
So here, system can use either a bulk update or a concurrent update method,
and they should also strive to get both the high throughput and low-query run times.
This benchmark is relatively new.
It was released at the end of last year,
so we only have a single result which was done by a collaboration of Tiger Graph and AMD.
We're happy to report that there are more audits underway,
so we are going to release more results in 2023.
So probably you can see from this presentation that
these benchmarks can get fairly complex and implementing them is not trivial.
So we did our best to provide everything our users need.
For each of the workloads that we have presented,
we have a specification,
we have detailed academic papers who
motivate the design choices and the architecture of these benchmarks.
We release the data generator as well as pre-generated datasets,
and we have benchmark drivers and
at least two reference implementations for each of the workloads.
Moreover, we have guidelines on how to execute these benchmarks correctly,
how to validate the results of a given system,
and how to ensure that the system will not lose your data or mingle up the transactions.
So we have asset compliance tests and recovery tests.
This leads us to our auditing process.
Similarly to the TPC,
the Transaction Processing Performance Council,
we have a rigorous auditing process where vendors can
commission an independent third party who will
rerun the benchmark in an executable and reproducible manner,
and they will write up it as a full disclosure report so that
the benchmark is understandable by whoever wants to see that result.
This is important because ad-dbc is trademarked worldwide,
and we only allow official audited results to use the term ad-dbc benchmark result.
This is not to say that we don't allow people to use this benchmark.
Researchers, practitioners, and developers are welcome to use the benchmark.
They can run it, they can report the results if it is accompanied by
the appropriate disclaimer that this is not an official ad-dbc benchmark result.
I would like to talk a bit about standard GraphQL languages.
This is an important topic because this has been
a pain point for Graph systems for many years.
It's a bit of a tower of Babel out there with many languages,
both of them using some visual Graph syntax,
but always with slightly different semantics and a slightly different syntax,
which makes it difficult for users to adopt these techniques and may put them in
a position of being locked in by their vendors.
So in the next couple of years,
there are going to be new standard query languages.
These focus on pathfinding and pattern matching.
The first one is called SQL-PGQ.
This is an extension to the SQL language,
and PGQ stands for property graph queries.
This is going to be released next summer,
and GQL, the standalone GraphQL language is going to come out in 2024.
We are happy to report that even though we have two new languages,
the pattern matching core of them,
the visual Graph syntax that we all know and love is going to be the same.
So users can port at least those bits of their queries.
To give you a taste of how this will look like,
here is query nine that David presented in
the social network benchmark interactive workload.
This query can be formulated in SQL.
It's not too difficult, but the new variants,
SQL-PGQ and GQL can represent it as terms of a graph pattern,
and this is a much more concise formulation.
The difference is even more pronounced for query 13 with the path queries.
Here, we can see that in SQL-PGQ,
the pattern is really similar to the visual representation.
It just has a source,
a target, and arbitrary amount of
nose edges denoted by nose asterisk in between.
In SQL, this is a lot less readable,
hard to maintain, and it's even less
sufficient because it just implements
a unidirectional search algorithm instead of doing
a bidirectional search which has a better algorithmic complexity.
The way IDBC is involved in these new query languages is manifold.
First, it had the G-core design language released in 2018,
which influenced these benchmarks.
Then IDBC has the formal semantics working group which
formalized the pattern matching core of these new languages.
The IDBC is doing further research to
conduct to advance the state of the art on graph schemas.
We have an industry driven and a theory driven group,
and what they do will end up in the new versions of these languages.
An outlook is the IDBC Graph Analytics benchmark.
This is a more wide benchmark because it can target analytical libraries like
NetworkX, distributed systems like Apache Giraffe or the GraphBlast API.
So this is everything that has to do with analyzing large graphs.
Here, the graph is an untyped,
unattributed graph so there are no properties or no labels.
We do use the IDBC social network benchmark dataset,
but it is stripped down to the person,
knows person, core graph.
Additionally, we have included a number of
well-known datasets like Graph 500, Twitter, and so on.
The algorithms that we run are mostly well-known graph algorithms.
There is the BFS which starts from
a given node and assigns the number of steps that need to be
taken to all of the other nodes to reach them.
We have the famous PageRank centrality algorithm which highlights
the most important nodes in the network,
and we have the local clustering coefficient,
community detection using label propagation,
weekly connected components, and shortest paths.
So this benchmark is a bit simpler than the social network benchmark.
It does not have a rigorous auditing process.
We trust people that they can run this benchmark efficiently and
correctly on their own infrastructure and they can report results.
If they do so, they will be able to participate in
the GraphRitix competition which has
a leaderboard for the best implementations.
So wrapping up, you should consider joining
the IDBC because members can participate in the benchmark design.
They have a say in where we are going in terms of including new features.
They can commission audits if they are vendors,
and members can gain access to these ISO standard drafts that I mentioned,
CEQA, PGQ, and GQL.
Otherwise, these are not available to general public.
Pricing-wise, this is free for individuals and there is a yearly fee for companies.
So to sum up, we have presented three benchmark,
the social network benchmarks interactive workload,
it's business intelligence workload,
and the GraphRitix graph algorithms workload.
We have more benchmarks.
There is semantic publishing benchmark which is targeting RDF systems.
Set in the media and publishing industry.
There is the financial benchmark which is going to be released this year,
which targets distributed systems and it uses
the financial fraud detection domain as its area,
and it imposes strict latency bounds on queries.
So this is quite a different workload from the previous ones.
Of course, graphs are ubiquitous and they have loads of use cases.
So there are many future benchmark ideas
including graph neural network, mining, and streaming.
Thank you very much and we're open to any questions.
Yes.
So in this one overview,
that was the graph dataset and the updates were separated.
Is there a possibility to create a graph dataset where the updates are included in
the dataset so that nodes and vertices get timestamps when they were deleted or when they were added?
Yes. So the question is, is it possible to create something like
a temporal graph with the timestamps of when the specific node is created and deleted?
This is actually very easy because this is the first step that the DataGen creates.
So when David said that it creates a social network of three years,
that has everything that was ever created or deleted during those three years,
and then we have attributes like creation date and deletion date.
Then we turn it into something that's loadable to the database.
We hide deletion dates because the database of course shouldn't be aware of this.
But this is something that the DataGen supports out of the box.
Okay. But then also to get this dataset with the deletion dates because you've already said it's hideable.
It's hideable but we have one which is called the row temporal dataset and that is available.
We even published that. So that's something that has a lot of
chance to be influential in the streaming community I believe.
All right. More questions. Yeah, Michael.
Do you plan to extend to other domains from that perspective?
So you have to social network one.
Yeah.
But it's an interesting one.
It's for the retail or Netflix,
Spotify, these user interactions on a more product and come out of one.
I mean, you could map it to your style,
but what are the other networks that are types of network?
So the question is, can we extend to other domains?
We usually emphasize that social networks is not really
the domain that is the actual primary use case for graphs.
We just use this because this is really easy to understand.
We don't have to explain person to person.
You can put in all sorts of interesting technological challenges to a graph domain like this.
It would make sense and sometimes we are approached by our members saying,
we want to do a new benchmark in the domain X,
and we then send them the process that is
required to get one of these benchmarks completed,
and that's usually the end of the conversation.
But we are definitely open to have more interesting benchmarks.
Of course, a good data generator is worth gold
to all the researchers and the vendors in this community.
So that's usually a hard point and I would be
definitely interested in having retail graph generator.
Carlo?
Hi. Question is basically,
what do you see the impact of this will be on the industry as in it's pushing into,
or it's more of a paradoxical evidence if
the system would have improved or a system will get more robust as in that you detect stuff,
just doing things and stuff get fixed or what was the?
Yeah. So the question is about the potential impact.
What could all this achieve?
We believe that it will help accelerate the field in the sense that systems will get more mature,
because if you want to get an audited result,
you have to pass all the asset tests,
you have to be able to recover after a crash,
and ideally you would have to be fast.
So that is hopefully one of the other things that systems will take away.
They will have better optimizers,
improved storage, better query execution engines.
We have seen this in the aftermath of the TPC benchmarks.
So those resulted in quite a big speed up.
So that's one area.
Of course, there is pricing.
We would like that users can get more transactions per dollar.
The third that we are personally quite interested in is the new accelerators that come out.
So especially in the field of machine learning,
there are cards that do fast sparse matrix multiplications.
Those could be harnessed specifically for the analytical benchmarks that we have,
and that would be interesting to see how big of a hassle it is to implement,
and how big of a speed up they give.
Cool. All right.
Okay. Thank you very much.