Okay, welcome everyone.
As you've seen from Adam, two people in notebooks are very important tool and tool that over
each data scientist.
But using graphs, within a notebook has some challenges for visualization.
And so Guillaume will talk about Ipile Zigma today, which is a tool to use ZimaJS as a component
in a Jupyter notebook to put that in the box.
So I'm really looking forward to that and look forward to that.
Thank you.
Well, first this time I'm actually not Guillaume.
Oh, sorry.
Guillaume is sick and so I have 20 minutes.
So I apologize in advance because I'm not the creator of the tool and so I will do as
much as I can to present it.
But Guillaume can answer ZimaJS or by Twitter or any other means if you have more questions
than what I can actually answer myself.
So I will just start by a brief remember of why we sometimes want to use graphs and actually
visualize them and not only do statistics on networks and actually visualize graphs.
And so why do we do visual network analysis?
It actually goes back very old to 1736 and the Bridges of Callebir, which is a classical
mathematical problem that was solved thanks to visualizing the graphs that it was showing.
Later on in France, Moreno did the social grounds where he tried to visualize how a
connected were students in a classroom.
And recently, thanks to the computed, assisted tools, we can do those kind of visualizations
but with massive graphs and try to do computed processing to try and automatically specialize
nodes on a map and also identify clusters within it.
So that brings a different need to actually analyze graphs and actually this helps a lot
understanding and we are coming at Piedra from the field of social sciences and we use
a lot of graphs to interpret social issues in general.
And we use them actually as maps.
So it's not maps in which coordinates make sense.
X and Y don't mean anything and you can paint the map.
But basically what you see on the plane indicates information on the localization of each node
that makes a sense compared to the other nodes.
But I guess that's another example of a map that was made a long time ago on the Nazi internet.
So to do that, there's been over the past years a lot of things that have been developed
including the first desktop ones.
So this tool is in direct heritage of this long lineage which started with Geffi.
I believe later today there will be a condition of Geffi Ocean 1 which finally will go out
soon after there was so many versions already.
So you probably already know Geffi.
But recently we could switch from the actual desktop analysis to actual web representations
thanks to a variety of libraries.
This tree that JS proposes to do it.
But there's also Cytoscape and a bunch of others.
So our community works with Simba and Simba has been developed by people actually close to the people of Geffi.
I don't think XE is here today but XE.jakomi is a small brother of Maturjakomi who speaks about Geffi.
He's the one who invented Simba.
And Guillaume is the co-poster of Simba with XE.
So please take a look at Simba.
I will put the slides to the conference and refine links to all the slides.
And then thanks to Simba we could build a lot of Geffi-like tools but for the web.
So that we could do all those interactions that we do in under Geffi but directly in a web page.
There's been a long history at India Lab and a round of trying to build such tools.
Minivan was one of them.
There's also Nancy which is a very small publishing oriented way of displaying graphs with very small few options.
So that you can just put your GEX file or GraphML file and very easily do what you want to do.
Latina is the one developed by people at Westware right now and is very rich in a lot of features.
And soon I think Matthew and Matthew will talk about it briefly in the next talk about Geffi version 1.
There's a Geffi-like version that's currently being developed and that should come in soon.
Which brings me to all those tools are very nice.
We have all those that are interactive and for us to visualize, explore, publish, manipulate all those graphs.
They all require pre-processed graphs.
You cannot just work with your graph while you're visualizing it.
You have to pre-code your file, using JSON or GEX or GraphML.
Then you load it into the tool and then you can explore it.
But we would like to be able to do that at the same time.
So that's where the idea of I-by-Sigma came from, to try and put within the Jupyter notebook a widget that displays a graph using C-
So that's really easy to install as long as you have Jupyter.
You usually need a tool to work with graphs under a title.
There's two main ones that you might know already about, NetworkX and iGraph.
I-by-Sigma is built to handle both formats of graphs from both NetworkX and iGraph.
So you just install I-by-Sigma in addition and then I just finished the brief demo.
Maybe a seat.
So we'll do two small exploration of graphs.
There's the first graph that I were working on right now, which is on the, what I call the open source,
I mean, actually larger than that, open access, open world.
It's like FOSDAM, but just in France and the French communities working about that.
And so we built this network of websites, links, together of those French communities of free software.
And let's take a look at this graph.
So first I will import the context.
Then I'm reading the graph that I built already.
So that's all this first example.
So here we have a graph with 621 nodes and 7000 edges.
Let's look at the node.
So the first node, I can see that it's far from Asia.
It's half way dot-out.
I don't know if French people are in the room, but I think people should know that half way.
It's from France.
It's a main NGO in France, about all the tools and the sort of graph.
So we have this image.
That's all the data that was collected while making the graph.
And then let's try to just visualize it by just loading i5-sigma, importing sigma and appearing in the graph.
Here, just bind it with the graph, which is randomly specialized.
We have metadata information.
So we can run the forecast on it.
So very easy.
You see your specialized graph.
Just a few seconds, and then you can pause, and then you can also apply some work.
The graph is too dense for that.
But that's a demo effect.
So yeah, but right now it's just a graph, and we don't have much information.
It's very stuff that we're readable.
So let's go down and try to add a few other options to the sigma code.
So we can set the outside constants.
Let's use the number of pages for.
So here I can see that for this purpose, we code a lot of pages on some specific websites.
Let's forward a little bit more and try to adjust the sizes of the nodes so we can adjust the range of the values for instance.
Here it's a bit readable.
So we get sizes.
Let's add some columns.
So I by sigma proposes some internal metrics that we can compute on the front.
So we want algorithms that generate clusters, and we will apply columns to do that.
I mean we will apply those
We do not have any data as columns.
So here we get the same graph as columns this time.
We can see that there are plenty of communities.
As knowing this network and knowing this community, I can tell you that basically
Here we got the open data, open columns community.
Here we got uphill and basically the NGOs working on open source.
Here we got Gil and mostly a lot of software.
Fedor and all the Linux distributions.
Here we got FFDA, my production, and all the activists working with all the open internet.
And I guess here is more the...
It's also a population.
And all the other stuff.
All those speaking to something?
Yeah, I guess a little bit.
Okay, so now that we got this, let's try to make it a little bit nicer.
We can add, for instance, some column columns.
So something more like a different.
So I just propose to see a stronger column from all of the graphs.
We can also try to do like a Gephi, like a curve, like edges.
All of those are in options.
I guess I'll show you a little bit later on a list of different options.
Here we also put like a picture scene font.
Basically you can do a lot of things.
But all of that so far is mostly like Gephi.
There's no real new thing.
But here's something that we actually propose or something else.
So right now we can see one graph.
But let's try and see multiple ones.
So I buy Sigma Proposis, what we call a Sigma Grid.
And so I will put the same graph, but it will trickle up.
And those will be common options that I set for all version of the graph.
But then within the grid I will add three different version of the graph.
Using different metrics for the size of the node.
So the one on the left one, and we see the ending grid in the middle of the grid, and the right one on the left.
So here are the three graphs which are all synchronized.
It happens at the same time.
If I over a node I will see it on the three different versions.
And then if I zoom a little bit, I guess we can see that...
Well, what can we see?
We can see that
Froma Soft, for instance, is very connected most globally.
But especially it has a very strong in degree and not so big out degree.
Why is that? Because Froma Soft is such a reference in France for open source tools.
It gets a lot of links from the whole community.
And all websites of the Free Software community point to it because it's like a resource.
Whereas, of course, they cannot point to the whole rest of the community.
On another note, I guess we could find...
I think there was Linux.org, the opposite.
It's a media that pretty much talks about anything that happens on open source in France.
And of course, they are the ones having the most outlinks.
All right, so that's just a small example.
Then I can show you maybe another notebook that will show other things.
So this one is a notebook that was built out of data collected by Laura Miguel,
which is a trainee at Media Lab right now.
And she scraped the first-name website, the agendas, to try and get all speakers and rooms over the past 15 years.
So here we will have to build the graph progressively.
We just had a CSV that she scrapes of the data of one speaker and one roomer.
Disclaimer, those speakers have been anonymized.
I mean, pseudonymized.
So you won't find a name that you know about, but they represent actual people.
So let's take a look at, for instance, three examples of the data.
So those are the three first lines.
I mean, that's one line and two other lines that I picked specifically.
This one is one speaker, and she talked about within this track.
Here it was a talk that was shared between two speakers.
So sometimes we get speakers separated by a pipe.
And here is obviously someone that was pseudonymized, but that should be in my seat right now.
And we did many talks in the past, including in this room.
So we will build the graph using networkX.
So for those unknown networkX, it's quite simple.
You just create a new graph.
And then for each row in our CSV, we will, if there's no speaker, we don't take it.
Then we take the track and the year we add a node for each track.
And for each speaker inside the talk, we add a node for the speaker.
And then we had an edge in between those two, and we increment it as a count if it's the second time that we meet him, for instance.
And we also upgrade the year to get, for the edge, the last year that was used.
So by doing that, I built a new graph that has 5,000 nodes and 6,000 links.
Let's take a look at my alternate speaker here.
He was supposed to be a speaker, and apparently he is linked to, in year 2018, to two talks in the graph room.
Yeah, he spoke twice in the room back then.
In JavaScript in 2019 and in 2020 in the open research tools and technology room.
So let's take a look at this graph now.
Yes, there's a comma missing here.
Here it is. No, still.
Yeah, I tried to add this earlier, but I'm not expert enough with it, so I'll remove this.
So here it is.
So this time it's a bipartite graph since we got two kinds of nodes, the tracks and the speakers.
So I decided that the node color will be attached to the part type.
And if I take a look at it, we should see all big dots in blue are the rooms for them, and all pink ones are actually speakers.
And so we can see that there are a lot of lightning talks, of course, every year.
But there are some rooms that have way more speakers, talks than others, probably also because they exist for way longer.
So maybe we can try and explore that.
And that's the main idea.
So, sorry, I don't remember what this one is.
Let's just run it briefly.
I guess it's the same.
Yeah, it's the same. Sorry.
So copy paste.
So what we could do is try and apply other things.
So let's do a grid again.
But this time we'll try and display for each node a gradient of color that will indicate the intensity of the node at this moment.
So to do that, we will, like, for instance, take a look at the year 2012 and the year 2022 and use the strengths of the ALO,
depending on how many talks were associated to this node for this specific year.
So both graphs should show the intensity of the talks during those two years.
So let's show it again.
And here we can see that in 2012, the main rooms that were filled were actually more on desktops, modular lightning talks and embedded.
Whereas in 2022, there are way more rooms that are actually filled and spoken.
Then what we could do is continue working on our graph and continue exploring while working with it.
So at Media Lab, we also have a tool called Polot, which allows us to do a bunch of metrics and calculation on a.
So it's already installed, it's doing faster.
And for instance, it can do a monopartite projection out of a bipartite graph.
So I'm just running this and then we can try and display it.
And here, just in a few lines in Python, I can just see the alternate graph that is the monopartite version of the graph
and just see the links between the rooms depending on when they are co-spoken by speakers.
Let's continue.
And the problem is that if I look at this graph, I can see there are a bunch of nodes isolated.
And so usually when I want to visualize a graph, those are a bit annoying because they take a lot of space in the visualization.
I don't want to see that.
So let's just use Polot's crop to largest component function that will remove all, will keep only the biggest component of the graph.
So then I can display this graph but without all of those single nodes.
And that's a rough idea of what could be done.
Then we can work with the graph and just visualize on the fly.
And I guess I'll conclude by just showing inside the GitHub page of the tool,
there is all the visual variables that are available.
So I showed you already node color, but you can also play on the saturation of the nodes.
You can play on the size we saw, but you can play with the label size, of course, the label color.
You can adjust the border ratio, how big it is.
So basically all visual ways to better help you interpret your graph can be proposed.
You can also add pictograms, use shapes for each node.
You can use halos, like I showed earlier.
And play most also, a lot of those apply to edges.
So you can play on the edges of colors, the form of them, and so on and so on.
And I guess that will be it for me.
And I will take all of your questions.
Sorry, I'm just scrolling back to things that are nicer.
Also a few. Yes.
Can you preserve the layout between the different steps?
That's a good question.
I don't think it has been planned yet.
Yes, sorry.
So the question was, can we maintain the layout from one cell to the other
and not having to re-click to apply the layout every time?
I don't think so.
And what I know is that the layout, the way Forza class works, has some chaos.
But here it's always instantiated on the same scene.
So whenever you run it, it will always generate the same exact layout.
So that's something.
But it won't reuse the one from the previous cells.
That could be something that could be added here.
Yes.
And do you have any numbers on the upper limits of this system?
And the size of the graph, if you can imagine?
Okay, you're in the values of noting this one or the limit.
So the question is about volume and amplitude and how big of a graph we can display with this.
So I believe the limit is actually the one of your browser.
So it will depend on your GPU and your CPU and your RAM.
But I know that SigmaJS properly endoles graphs with, I would say,
hundreds of thousands of nodes and links, I guess.
I know I already displayed one with a few million links and hundreds of thousands of nodes.
It takes a bit more time, of course.
Do you support something like collapsing nodes and expanding them?
So for instance, in these kind of network graphs where you have communities, they could collapse it.
What type of ones?
I mean, they could be selectively expanded as well.
So the question is, can we aggregate and exploit nodes that have, for instance, the same group?
To me, it would be, I don't think it's built-in within SigmaJS for sure.
But maybe in Palette, the library we're showing, the monopartite projection is pretty much this kind of ID.
I don't know. But it might be in Palette.
Yep?
You might find that in the GPU.
Is it using the GPU for...
Yeah, SigmaJS. Sorry.
The question is, does this use the GPU to display the graph? Yes.
SigmaJS is heavily relying on the WebGL.
The previous version of SigmaJS was proposing to choose between Canvas and WebGL.
Right now, it's only WebGL.
So it won't work with all browsers.
But nowadays, most browsers know to work with the GPU.
So, yes.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.