I'm looking at this from the angle,
how can I manage such a large graph in any good way?
I'm looking forward to that. So, Nikolai.
Thanks. Thanks for the introduction.
You have to speak up because the audience only for the-
Okay. So, my name is Nikolai Kondashov.
I work at Red Hat on the CKI project,
which is building one of those Linux kernel testing systems
for Red Hat and for Upstream.
I also work in the kernel louder.
Okay. I also work with
the kernel CI Upstream community on the KCIDB project,
which is the source of this presentation,
and I do electronics and embedded as a hobby.
Wow. Okay.
So, I'm going to walk you quickly through
the kernel contribution workflow,
through the testing systems,
and what we're trying to do with KCIDB at kernel CI,
and then how we want to solve the problem,
and what the actual problem is with the kernel CI process in general.
Then I go briefly through the data model,
and what kind of a few questions,
what a few queries that we need,
and how it went with Neo4j,
and what we can do instead.
So, the kernel contribution workflow,
I don't know if everybody's familiar with that.
I hope not because it's not very pleasant.
But basically, you do your changes,
you commit your changes, then you make an e-mail out of that,
and send it to a mail list,
and to a maintainer for them to review,
to give you feedback, then you repeat that again
until everybody is satisfied,
it was a maintainer, whoever is concerned with that change.
After this, your patches get merged into
a sub-tree for the particular subsystem that you were changing,
and then sometime later,
this is getting merged into the main line,
which Linus maintains, and you're done, basically.
But at any point in that process,
you can get some test results for your change.
It could be if you're lucky,
you can get it before it even gets reviewed,
or sometimes it gets reviewed,
or after it was merged, anytime.
So, there is a whole bunch of kernel testing systems.
This is just a sample.
Each of them is trying to solve their own problem.
For example, CKI is Red Hat's system.
They will test particular hardware that our customers use,
particular features that our customers request,
and make sure that they work,
that the distribution works.
Intel tests their hardware,
their graphics cards, and make sure that those work.
Google fuzzes system calls at the sys caller and sys bot.
Okay, FT from Linaro, they test arm boards,
and finally, Kernel CI is aiming to be
the official CI system for the Linux kernel,
it's supported by Linux Foundation,
and they're trying to run tests on
the whatever hardware others can provide, we can have.
You can see everybody has their own interest in that game.
So, this is how your various email reports can
look from those systems correspondingly,
and this is their dashboards.
From different systems.
So, Kernel CI is, as I said,
is striving to be the DCI system,
and we have the testing system,
and the hardware management,
and the framework, and everything to run the tests in various labs.
These labs can be located in different premises by people
who have some hardware to run them on, the tests on,
and then that gets collected and put into the database.
Then we have various other CI systems collecting
their results and sending them to the KCI DB database.
KCI DB was conceived as a system to try to reduce
the effort that all CI systems have to put into
their dashboards into their reports and instead have
one dashboard and one report if possible or close to that,
and as well to save the developers attention,
which is a precious resource because as you see,
it's not so easy to investigate every report
and from different CI systems,
because there are different different format of the emails,
different data, different dashboards,
you have to look at them this way,
that way, and you have to figure it out.
So, that's KCI DB is therefore to bring
this one interval the whole.
So, conceptually, it's very simple.
The CI system sent JSON which can consist
of various objects in any combination,
and we have the database, we put them in,
we have the dashboard to display that,
and we have a subscription system where you can give
some rules and say, okay,
I want to see these results from these tests and from
this tree or for this architecture or whatever,
and we can generate reports based on
that whenever you need it as the data comes in.
One important note about this is that compared
to a regular CI system where you control everything,
in this system,
the data can come in any order.
In a regular CI system,
you have the results come in the same order as commits come in.
So, you know, like if you tested something earlier,
that means for an earlier commit,
if you tested something later,
it's for a later commit,
and you can have a line of history with those results.
But for case IDB,
since there's different CI systems,
they move with a different speed,
they get in any order you wish.
So, we have about 100,000 test results per day,
a few thousands of builds and
hundreds of hundred revisions per day tested received
by the case IDB database.
Well, actually, I think, yeah, that's correct.
That's the correct scale. Yeah.
So, it looks something like this is Grafana.
It's like a prototype dashboard.
We're thinking about building a new one,
but I don't know how soon that's going to happen.
So, Grafs, tables, all that jazz.
This is our prototype reports look like this.
So, what's the problem with the kernel CI in general,
not with the kernel CI, the project?
So, first of all,
kernel is intended to be an obstruction layer for hardware.
That's this whole purpose,
and to make it easier to write software, right?
So, in theory,
to make sure that it works,
you have to test it to the every piece
that you abstract away from.
But that's not possible, of course,
and hardware is expensive.
So, it's a natural scarcity in this whole system.
Then the tests, since you cannot get
all the hardware at the same time,
and you cannot possibly run all the tests on
all the hardware for every commit that people post.
It means that sometimes the tests run on this hardware,
sometimes on that hardware, sometimes they don't run.
The tests themselves are not so reliable
because there's a lot of
concurrency management in the kernel,
and that's hard to get right.
In general, things happen at the same time in the operating system.
So, then sometimes they're not so reliable.
So, you can get a pass on your change,
even if it's broken or get a fail on your change,
even if it's not broken or even if it's
somebody else's change to broken, basically hell.
So, it's hard to remove noise from those results.
For developers, it's hard to investigate even a valid change.
While it's a kernel, you have to meet all the conditions,
and well, sometimes you have to get the right hardware,
or ask people for the right hardware,
or ask them to actually run the test and send you results,
like over e-mail takes a while.
So, if we start sending people e-mails with results that are not valid,
that are false positive, false negatives,
then people get pissed because of that,
because it takes such a long time to reproduce them.
So, a lot of AI systems resort to human review before sending those reports.
Like they see the failures, they say,
okay, let's go send this to this mail list,
and then they send them.
Only a few manage without that so far.
So, obviously, nobody stops the development to fix AI,
because there's just so many developers,
and if one system breaks something,
like another subsystem doesn't want to care about that.
Feedback loop is just too long.
So, tests keep running, keep failing,
and it takes a while to fix them.
So, instead of the ideal case where you can move past,
only move past the tests if they pass,
and then do all the stages like review,
and then it's merged, and it's fine,
and then you can upstream it,
you get something like this,
where test fail, okay,
it's probably not our problem,
not have time to investigate it,
or we just didn't get any test result, we move on.
So, what we're trying to do is we got to fix this, right?
So, we got to fix the test results.
So, we fix the test result.
We look at the test output conditions, etc,
and we add the rule to the database saying like,
okay, well, this failed, but we know about this.
Here's the bug that was open.
So, don't complain to developers,
don't waste their attention.
And it looks like this, shiny and sparkly,
but after a while, we get this fixed into the test,
and we repeat the process with another issue.
So, these things are already working in
separate CI systems like the CKI.
There's a UI screen for an issue in the kernel,
it says like, okay, look for this output in
the test of this string in the test output.
If you see it for this test,
then you can see that the kernel bug and don't raise the problem.
Okay. So, or bug logs,
the Intel's CI system,
they have like a huge form for filing this.
You can see another string that is,
you're supposed to look in the error output and
the conditions and what kind of status you
want to assign to the test, etc.
So, here's a dog tags for you to take a breath.
For me to take a drink.
So, I'll take the model.
We start with checkouts which basically just specify
what kind of revision you're checking out.
We have very taken it from repository branch and which commit,
and if you had patches supplied on top and
the patch log and everything like that,
then we aggregate that to get the revision data
like from multiple checkouts of the same revision,
we get the same single revision.
We have builds which link to the checkouts to say like,
oh, we tested this checkout and therefore link to the revision.
The builds describe which architecture compiler and
the configuration output files and logs and everything.
We get the test results finally,
and yeah, builds can fail.
We have failed builds all the time and it stops nobody.
So, we have a kind of test which we are running
the environment to train on.
What kind of result was the status result,
the pass fail, etc, and the output files,
logs and stuff like that, very typical.
Then we get the issues which describe like which bug it is
and who is to blame that like the kernel,
the test or the framework,
and we will have the pattern there matching the test results.
Okay, this test, this output,
what you saw on that screen.
The status that it should have and the issue version
because we want to change those issues over time.
Finally, we have the incidents which are linking
those builds and issues together.
So, saying like, oh, this is the issue with this build,
and things like that.
So, that's all we keep in the relational database,
but then we got to talk about the revisions.
So, revisions could be just commits and
a Git history and here's your graph.
So, that's a basic thing that we've tried to do,
but we also need to have revisions of patches supplied on top,
and somebody post a patch on the main list.
We take it, apply it to some commit which is pointing to,
and we test it, we get the results,
and we know it was applied to this commit.
Then somebody reworks that patch and post a new version,
they got the link, both the commit we tested upon,
and to the previous revision of the patch set.
Then there's this weird thing when
maintainers keep a special branch for CI,
for the testing systems to pick up.
They're working, testing send them results,
and they just keep pushing there like they're working on something.
They push there, they get results after a while from testing,
then they push a new version,
and then they get new results and they got to say like,
okay, this is the Git commit history,
but we also know that we checked this branch out previously.
So this is the child of that branch, of that previous revision.
This is basically it.
As you probably all know,
this is a directed acyclic graph.
So tests directed edges and it doesn't loop on itself.
So that's about what I know about graphs.
Bear with me. Finally,
I think that there's just too many build and test results to
put them all into a graph database, at least so far.
I might be wrong, but that's my idea.
We obviously need to keep the graph of
the revisions to be able to reason about them,
but we might be able to put issues there as well in
the same database if it saves something.
So this is just a short list.
Basically, what we want to know,
okay, as the data commit comes in,
test results, you got to trash them and match them
against the issue so we can say, okay,
we found an issue here so don't trace the flag,
or something like that, like similar.
There's no issue here in test result,
but we want to raise the flag because there's actually an issue.
We cannot possibly trash all the issues against
all test results because there's going to be a lot.
So we have to build a priority for those issues,
and then we have to cut off that priority somehow,
and say like, okay, at this moment,
we can tell the developer that we've
basically trashed these results.
We can go take a look,
but we can still continue and
trash those issues as the time goes on.
So we have to base that on one of the criteria that we might need
is how far, for example,
that revision is from the current situation.
Like if this issue only appeared somewhere,
I don't know, like a thousand commits ago,
or a thousand is not that much for the Linux kernel,
okay, 10,000 commits ago,
then we don't need to trash it right now.
We can tell the developer, okay, it's fine,
and then we'll continue trashing,
and if we find something,
then we can raise the alarm.
Then we can ask,
like what were the last access results,
like for this particular test,
for this number of commits to be able to say,
okay, this test wasn't often failing.
Okay, it was failing sometimes, but that's okay.
But if it suddenly starts failing more often,
we got to raise the alarm,
or if it stops failing so often,
we got to also raise the alarm and see what's changed.
Then we need to track the performance trends,
of course, over the history of the development.
Once again, we cannot do this just based on time,
because CIO systems move at different speed,
and some CIO systems might start to decide to,
okay, we're going to test this old branch,
because some of our clients wants to base their BSP on it,
wants to base their release,
release some software with that kernel,
and we got to start testing it,
and it starts coming in like the last year's release
or something.
We cannot just take that data into account
for testing the current releases, or vice versa.
Or for stable kernel maintainer,
if Greg wants to release a branch,
he might want to see like, okay,
which issues were discovered starting
from the previous release in this branch.
Just for the dashboard, like, okay,
I want to see issues in this branch,
or which branches contain this issue.
That's what we tried to do with Neo4j.
I did basic things, so I wrote a little script to get
the Git log in a particular format,
and then generate the data for commits and for relations.
It was a little over a million commits.
Looked like this, and it was a little more relations,
because as you probably know,
a commit can have more than one parent in Git,
and it looked like this, very simple.
So I loaded this into Neo4j with something like this.
This is updated to the latest release.
It was different from the start,
then created an index for hashes,
and then loaded the relations.
And it worked fine, but not a few days ago,
when I tried the fresh Neo4j release,
it just hung like this forever.
So I don't know, I could not give you a fresh data
how it works right now, but I tried it last year,
and I couldn't get answer a simple question
if these two commits are connected.
It was just go on forever, then run out of RAM.
But with Epoch, I could do that.
I could get the answer, it was okay.
But if I wanted to get the nodes between those two commits,
it would do the same thing.
But with Git, I complete that in milliseconds.
So here you go.
I think the problem, well in my opinion,
is that the graph management databases and software,
they are aimed at a general graph problem,
and not tuned to DAGs.
Git does that, Git is tuned to DAG,
they have a lot of optimizations for that,
and there are tricks to make like,
repositories like the Linux kernel work.
So I don't know nothing how you do this.
This is magic to me, and this would be new to me,
this book, but from a purely engineering perspective,
I would have liked to see something like
a support for databases that are restricted for DAGs only,
and that apparently could be done
with not so much computation.
And then once you have that, then you can do some branching
and say like, okay, if you are a DAG database,
then we can do the optimizations and do the fast thing
with them.
So the fallback plan is obviously just push everything
in Git, put the commits and the patches
and all the branches and all the subsystems.
It's gonna be giant repo.
Maybe we can manage that and then query it with libgit2,
which is the library that Git uses to work with the data.
And then, well, shuttle the commits
to the relational database, okay?
We want to see if, between those releases,
we have issues and we take the commit hashes from Git
and then query the database with that.
That's all.
Thanks.
So we can help you with the Neo4j things.
One aspect is text index is for full text indexes.
It's not for strings, it's for full text.
It's just like literally this string, this length.
No, it's text index is for full text, like for.
Oh, okay.
Well, it was just this one thing.
And the other thing is also,
so do you have to data somewhere to try it out?
Of course, of course.
And there's a link from the slides to the script
that you can use yourself on any Git repo.
Well, same product.
Yeah.
Any more questions?
Yes.
Did you try any other graph data bases?
Did you try any graph or?
Well, I looked, the question is,
did I try any other graph databases?
Yeah, I looked at a bunch of them.
Some of them require like so much setup
that I was just floored.
But I read the documentation.
I couldn't see any indication
that it would be any different
because nobody says anything about DAGs,
any optimizations or anything.
I tried memgraph before this talk,
but I had the same problem with loading revisions, I think,
for some reason.
Because like previously, I could load revisions.
I guess like the, in Neo4j,
the syntax for indexes has changed since then.
Maybe I did create the index incorrectly
as I was just hinted at.
But I could load them in a reasonable time before
in Neo4j and everything fine and like in query,
but except that thing.
In memgraph, I just hit the wall
because like it's a different syntax slightly.
It was slow, but yeah, not such luck.
And it took like four gigabytes of disk space.
So, not too bad, okay.
I don't remember now.
I think it was, if I take a look now, I think I.
I think version will also be successful, just research.
I tried one Neo4j desktop 1.4 before, 1.4.15.
And that worked.
I don't know which version it was included.
Any other questions?
Thank you so much, Nicole.
I had the first question.
Thank you.
Thanks, everyone.
Can we look at the graph database?
I think that's actually a good fit for a graph database.
And so we can make it work.
And then, next thing you can come back
and we do some fun large scale analysis on it.
Okay, that would be great.
But you can look up to book them.
Yes, thank you.
Cool.
Thank you.