I'm Linus from the Sustaq Foundation in Europe.
I'm a
developer there and I also work with other projects like Detective, which we want to
be an open source solution to make European public tendering data, procurement data,
explorable for people who don't know that much about procurement data.
So I want to do a couple of things in this talk.
First I want to describe why procurement data is interesting, why we should take a look at it.
And I want to discuss some problems of how this data in EU context is currently accessible.
And then I want to show you our project of alleviating some of these problems with Detective.
And then I want to show you how you can actually contribute to the project if you find it useful.
Still very much in the early stages and just getting going.
We love the opportunity to show this now so people can actually contribute even in the earlier phase of the project.
So what's TAT? TAT's in the name. And what's TAT?
So TAT stands for Tenders European Daily.
And it's basically a data set that's published by the EU Publications Office.
And they published this data for a long time.
They've been publishing this for a long time.
Since 2015 actually they've been providing this freely on the internet.
And it's data about basically who buys what from whom. Like which public institutions do you buy what or what tries from which organizations.
So it's really data about the relationship between business and government.
And if, so for example your local school or some ministry in your country in the EU wants to buy something that's above a certain threshold.
They're defined in EU legislation. You can look them up in the link here. I will publish the slides afterwards.
It needs to go into TAT. And it will be in this data set.
And there's at least $670 billion per year in value that's kind of encapsulated in this data.
And there's more than 700,000 notices that they publish each year.
That describe this entire process of probably for sure in the EU.
Sorry Greg, that's something you wanted to...
So you could think, well Greg, publish it. So what's the problem with that?
I mean the way this data is read accessible is via this UI.
One funny thing is, this button statistics mode, I still haven't found out what that does.
Let me show you from the view. You can illuminate.
But basically you have to really know what you're searching for in the first place in order to be able to use this kind of interface.
And there's also a lot of other problems with accessing this data.
For example, you can't really search by organization, which would be interesting.
I mean it's about the relationship between government and business in follow the money terms.
So why is there no option to search for organizations that I'm interested in?
I can only really do a full text search over these huge XML files, which are really complex.
And I can do some other stuff, but there's no type of tolerance, for example.
None of the really nice search features that we've been used to.
And most importantly, there's no ability at all to readily visualize the results that I get.
Like if I type something in here in a search mask, I get back a list of HTML,
basically just an HTML list of notices that I need to understand what's a notice
and what are the different types of notices that I'm interested in.
So it's really hard.
It makes a test right now because accessibility is really bad with this data.
So why is the data needed?
In the past, there have been a number of attempts to look at this data
and transform it into a more manageable or readily analyzable format.
And we weren't really able to identify a single, freely available solution
that was published under a free software license that allows you to explore this data
even if you don't have domain expertise or data science expertise.
And you kind of need both now to be able to make some sense of this data.
And we thought this would be interesting.
So why isn't this more readily available?
So we applied to last year's EU data form with this idea, basically,
to make this data more accessible.
And this is what we told them.
So we have, as any type of, let's say we have a public servant
who finds out who buys what from within Germany or within their state,
who buys from Microsoft, Georgia,
and how much they spend on free software from this company.
And yes, maybe make the case of how much they can save if they use free software.
Or let's say you're a journalist who wants to investigate
some of the recent purchases made by a foreign authority.
You could do that now with a tap interface,
but very, very difficult.
And you can jump a lot of hurdles to get there.
So we want to take it as to be an application that you use,
which lowers the barrier of entry to analyze.
So we thought let's present the publications of this concept
with free software, and it's giving it very simple.
So we built something roughly with this architecture.
So you have this XML file,
and this was very quickly built just for this data.
So I'll go through it quickly.
So we had this XML file.
I transformed it to JSON for whatever reason,
which was a very bad idea.
And then I parsed it in Python and put it in some ad hoc schema in Postgres.
And then I used the Neo4j ETL tool to put it to a Neo4j database.
The data I was interested in was relational data
between the chosen relationship between business and government.
And then I used NeoDash to visualize that.
And that actually already gave people a few days
a chance to see what might be possible if you open up this data.
So I'll show you a little demo of how that looked.
So basically this is just an overview.
I parsed the data for roughly three years, or two and a half years.
This shows you the activity per country.
This is just some general overviews,
like roughly a million vendors.
And then it's not optimized yet.
You get a, basically you search for Microsoft Germany,
and then you have this graph.
You have a geographical distribution of commercial activity
that's related to Microsoft.
And you get this nice graph of relationships
between Microsoft Germany here in the center as an entity.
And then the yellow or red ones are tenders.
So here they sold something to some institution of German government,
in this case here.
Mostly because Microsoft, Deutschland, mostly sells to the German government.
And the red ones are tenders above one million euro.
And that gave you a very quick overview
of the commercial activity and the relationship
between government entities and business entities.
I do the same with, you get more information here.
You can actually go to the Deutsch website to see the notice
that was analyzed.
Yeah.
A short question.
You search now for Microsoft,
but usually they work with might be server providers
that help to their direct relationship.
Is that something you've been there?
Yeah.
Can we go back to the challenges that we face
that you can all help us overcome?
But that's certainly one.
So again, I do the same with the Polish order authority.
Here's more like who does an entity buy from
over the past two and a half years.
You can see what kind of like fence and weapon and ammunition stuff they bought.
I mean, I'll have to get through this because,
yeah, this is actually another problem that I'll talk about
towards the end of the talk.
It's deduplication.
So in TAD data, as it's published in these external files,
there's no deduplication of entities at all.
So you can have Microsoft, Deutschland, DMP,
Microsoft Deutschland, just Microsoft, whatever that is.
And like you can see here, Microsoft Ireland,
like there's all these different.
So I did some very naive deduplication attempt.
I also put that data in the Neo4j graph,
but there's much more to be done on that front.
And it's very interesting problem, I think.
Also because you need to think about it from a policy side as well.
Like is Microsoft Deutschland a different entity from Microsoft Ireland?
And if yes, what does that mean for my data analysis?
Should I analyze them together?
Because they're really operating as one entity.
So there are interesting questions connected to this that are not only technical.
So let's go back to my...
So that was obviously limited in scope because it was really at all.
It was pretty main and there were lots of problems with how I find this data for this implementation.
So now we're at the stage where there's actually a lot of interest in this,
in the MSAP doing this.
I heard from a lot of people that they would be interested in analyzing this data
and being able to explore this data.
So what's next and what's already implemented?
So there's the open contracting data standard,
which is something that actually came after TET was first published.
So I told you already TET was first published in 2015.
I think the OCPS started being developed around 2018, 2019, something like that.
And if you now build any kind of public procurement platform,
you use this data standard because it's just a very nice way for people
to put a lot of thought into how can we display this entire process of public procurement?
How can we put this neatly into a data structure?
And so now we're building detectives with this data structure at its core.
And the first task will be to parse this TET XML jungle
into this nicely specified OCPS.
So I built a relational database that roughly captures OCPS.
You see a lot of JSON-B in the process there,
because some things I didn't, there were many to many or many to one,
but JSON-B for now makes it much easier.
Otherwise this table would not have been presented to.
And now, I mean, this is the graph system step-through after all.
The next question, because I think analyzing this data,
analyzing public procurement data, analyzing these relationships between business
and government, this really lends itself to being capsulated in a graph database.
So this is really the core of OCPS that's interesting,
and that would be interesting to model in a graph database like Neo4j.
You have these tender, like a tender is basically a company says,
like we're talking about, we go and the public entity says,
we want to buy X or Y amount.
And then an organization, another organization can apply for that.
They're usually like something commercial.
They say, look, we can furnish the standard, like we apply for the standard.
And that's interesting data in and of itself,
who applies for which tenders and which regions and stuff like that.
And then there's awards.
That's basically who gets the contract on the wall.
And so that would be a very simple place to start with, with a graph database,
to just have this, have all the tech data going back from F15,
parse it into OCPS, and then take this subset of what's really central
and put it into a graph database and really start exploring this visually.
And that's what we want to do.
And part of it is already done.
So I'm currently working, we are currently working on parsing this data,
this XML, use XML library for that.
It's really nice.
And I punch this into a relational database.
And I specify the OCPS data schema with SQL model,
which is really cool for the library.
Basically gives you high-dentic models and SQL LBB models in the one entity.
It's really cool.
It's really nice to work with.
And then I want to create CSV export to be then able to input that data
and Neo4j, put it back fast if I'm scaffolding around that,
and then also build some UI, which we are currently researching,
which framework to use, and I'm also here to find out which one would be the coolest one.
So I'll stay here, because I think there will be some problems in the JST.
Yeah, but there's also Reactforce Graph, and yeah,
it's really like a nice UI that's specifically geared towards that use space
of analyzing public procurement data.
And yeah, then, had the back end backed by these two,
like the relational database and the Neo4j database,
and then choose depending on the query which data source you actually use.
I'll go through the rest really quickly,
and then I'll go through the rest of the process.
If you want to get unboarded, the documentation is still up around the edges.
I'll do my best in the next days and weeks to really make the project approachable to new developers.
What we find is interesting is I want to work with me and the MSP on this.
So some key characteristics that we want to really put a focus on with Detective
is reuse compliant, that means like every file has the license header and copyright header,
so that it can really be easily reused.
And we want to make it for the people, so like a lot of my work in the next weeks
will also include speaking to people who analyze public procurement data
and ask them what kind of queries they would,
what kind of questions they would like to ask, because that's really important for the design
of the system that you ask people that are later going to use it.
How could this be helpful?
We have done some of that, but we will do way more of that,
especially now because we start building the UI.
And we want it to be interoperable, so everything that the Detective uses,
every data that it uses will be also published under RBCC 5.0 license
and there will be open API interface, there will be publicly available,
obviously some limits get too crazy, but we will think about that when the problem arrives.
And also we fundamentally believe that link data is more interesting,
because once you have this data in the OCS format,
you can start making it with other data sources based on
if you have an undergrad database, you can start linking it with other data sources.
Things that come to mind would be open corporate data
where you can really enrich the data that you have in organizations
with data that's in this public database of corporate entities.
Open sanctions would then allow you to flag people or companies or entities
that are on some sanction list and stuff like the offshore leaks database
would allow you to highlight things to offshore companies and stuff like that.
That's a basis for your analysis.
So this would be a future possibility that I'm really excited about,
but the first step is obviously to get this into a nice format
and that's to think about extending.
Some of the challenges is re-cleaning this step data,
because some of it is quite old, like if you look at data that was published in 2015
and there's a lot of typos in there and there's huge XML files
that didn't currently do much validation of the forms
that were used to take input this data.
So in some places it's very messy.
And OCS helps a lot actually with starting this data,
because it's very well defined standard and there's a mapping concept
of OCS that some people have published, so it's really cool.
And then the next big problem that we would be dealt with
is depuplication of problem.
Which I already have online, and yes, we're very cool.
If you have good ideas on that, I think that's really good.
Because I think that's really central to take the theme helpful.
So how can you get involved? All the code lives on our git instance.
At the moment you can only really contribute your PR issues
if you make an account and I'll get this free.
It's just a couple of weeks, but that's fine.
Nobody manages that and we'll think about mirroring on GitHub.
But let's try this first. Maybe there's federation coming for the...
for the git forges.dariat, as I understand.
There's also websites with the documentation
and then you can also write an e-colon to...
this will always reach the retailers.
So, yeah, I'm looking forward to your questions.
Thank you very much.
APPLAUSE
That's it.
Regarding funding, did you try to icon-text the official European institution
so that you can have funding for this UI
and that it becomes like the default UI for that in Europe?
So I know that...
So the question was whether we asked the publications of this
or funding for this.
Not specifically yet.
I know that they are working themselves on a huge reform
of the entire ecosystem.
So they do this, what they call e-forms now,
which is supposed to substitute what used to be TED.
But e-forms still isn't OSPS.
There's discussions around that that I fully understand all the time.
And they're also rebuilding the TED website.
We should get the complex with them.
I have the complex because we won this data bomb
and we have the... I have taken some context there.
We should make use of it.
And this will happen.
It will be all in OSPS format.
Honestly, I don't think anything else makes sense.
So it's just data that...
We will republish this OSPS.
There's some place like Open Tender, which was a component project
which also does this republishing of the data that is OSPS.
But it's not consistent in how it's regularly uploaded.
It's not a complex database.
It doesn't seem very active in any time.
I have a question.
When you look at these headers and the companies involved,
are you also able to extract what the action tender is about?
So is there an analyzed structure?
This is about, I don't know, classroom, furniture,
and this is about military equipment.
So that you can correlate, or by item,
or by contract project?
Yes.
Should I repeat the question?
So the question was whether there's also data about
what is being procured and details about what's being procured
by public institutions.
And the answer is yes.
There's usually a title that's fairly descriptive.
And a description, sometimes in English, sometimes in other words.
And then there's CPD codes, which is a common procurement vocabulary
that specifies what kind of category this procurement is in.
But some stuff is excluded by this legislation.
For example, like military personnel is not published in this data.
Sorry, can't talk about open procurement in the context yet
because there's still lots of sensitive data
that's not being included in that.
Do you plan to host it publicly?
Yeah, yeah.
Do we plan to host it publicly?
Yes, yes, absolutely.
It's just at the moment the API is down because I re-vector it.
So many things.
But it will be.
It will be after again.
Yeah, of course it will be publicly available,
but if everything crashes because there's so much interest in it,
then we'll have to think about limiting it somehow.
But there's a system.
Exactly, yeah.
So we'll see, you know, if there's really that much interest.
I have a question.
What have been the biggest challenges you've had
when you did a new university?
So what was the biggest challenge in cleaning the data?
So I would say one is just finding if there is an English translation available,
finding that for the specific, because we really lay out in this XML file
that we can translate around and where is, if a translation exists,
like where is it in XML?
Like what other, like what does it apply to?
Another one was languages that I didn't know the alphabet of,
the hard to parse, and yeah, that just in general,
that company names that they didn't have for a long time,
I mean any validation on what you could put in there,
which makes it really hard.
It would have been very easy to implement upstream,
but now it's because you found space.
Thank you.
.