The next work is on graph aggregation, graph grouping, especially on streaming graphs.
Graph grouping is a really interesting challenge because we've all seen individualizations,
hairballs, and complex graphs.
When graph grouping allows you to split into these graphs, group them by certain attributes,
and you have these better nodes that then can be selectively expanded, but you can also
then, on a group graph, which is mostly a molar-type graph in many cases, you can also
run graph analytics, which is a really interesting problem.
I'm really excited to have Christopher here because both working on the streaming graphs
as well as on temporal graphs, with graph grouping is a really challenging and interesting
aspect, so I'm really looking forward to the talk.
With our full schedule, welcome to the graph bedroom.
Thanks.
Here's a thanks for that introduction and also thanks for accepting my abstract for
this talk.
My name is Christopher Grost.
I'm a PhD student of the University of Leipzig.
I'm currently writing my thesis, so I'm glad that I bring some free time to doing this
talk.
Yeah, so about us or our team, so that's me and I have also a master's student working
on this project we called Graphstream Zuma, and this project is a result of two master's
thesis of our university from Elias Daman and Radha Nuridin, and I think it's also nice
to show the result of a master's thesis here at the FOSTAIM.
At the top is our professor of the database department, just to say that.
Okay.
I want you to take away from this talk, so you will see what the property Graphstream
is and why it's important to have the streaming idea inside the graph topic, and second why
you should or should not group a Graphstream, and then you will learn what the Graphstream
Zuma's specific project is and the main idea behind it and which specific project you want.
First we provide the Java API to do that.
Okay.
Let's just start with an event stream.
I think I can skip that, so we say that anything that happens at a specific time and that can
be recorded is an event, and if an event stream is now a stream of these events, so a sequence
that is ordered by time.
I think everyone knows why we need event processing, so we cannot store everything into a database
or whatever to analyze it, so I want to identify these meaningful events and respond to them
as quickly as possible.
Okay.
What is now a Graphstream?
A Graphstream is an event stream where each event is a graph element or some graph update.
Yeah, that could be edges, could be vertices, triples, or whatever.
And a graph update could be a modification of this.
For example, the addition of an edge, the removal of an edge, the addition of a property
or to an edge or whatever.
Yeah, so this is just an overview.
Okay, why should I use now a Graphstream?
Because I can execute on this Graphstream all algorithms and also all mathematical stuff
from GraphTeary on this stream of graph data.
For example, calculate patch strength concurrently with the evolving graph of the Graphstream.
Okay, I can update my analysis results with a low latency if I combine that in a stream
processing engine and my goal is to monitor the changes or monitor the changes in the
graph or to create some notification or some reactivity.
For example, if something, some average goes over a threshold, then I create a notification.
Okay, by now the Graphstream could be very heterogeneous.
That means consists of many different types and it can also occur in a high frequency.
So it is advisable to summarize the graph elements in a specific way.
And we can summarize graph elements by three criterias, for example, by time, that means
graph elements that belong together, for example, the time window, we group them together.
By structure, that means, for example, edges that share the same source or target vertex
can be grouped together.
And by content, that means vertices and edges that share the same label or a specific value
of a property.
So and we introduced for our algorithm, so-called grouping key functions, that means it is a
function that maps a vertex or an edge to a grouping key.
And that could be everything that is inside this vertex or edge.
It could be labeled temporal information, some kind of property or whatever.
So you can map everything that is represented by vertex or edge to a key function or to
key and on this key, we group the graph.
So that means at the end, the result is again a graph stream, but the grouped representation
of that.
Now you can question, OK, why I need this?
So what are the applications of that?
You can think about it as a preprocessing step.
For example, before you calculate the patch frames, you just group the vertices to the
city attribute of users together or something like this.
You also use it as a preprocessing step.
Second application could be as a postprocessing step.
For example, after you apply the cross stream analysis, for example, community detection,
you can now group on this cluster ID with our grouping algorithm to summarize the different
communities together.
You can also use it to understand the cross stream in more detail.
For example, OK, just to know which vertex or edge types exist in my graph stream, how
frequent these different types arrive or how vertices and edges with different characteristics
are connected together.
So just to get deeper insights or if you use our aggregation functions or aggregation,
for example, counting or calculating an average on that, you can also get or reveal some hidden
information that you would not see in the graph stream itself.
OK, so this is an introduction.
Now I explain the ideas behind this graph stream zoomer application just by an example.
And then afterwards I summarize this.
OK, for example, we're using bike rental data that can have two different graph schemas.
I named them A and B. So the first graph schema A is that a bike rental is an edge between
two station nodes.
Yeah, you see it on the left side.
So a station has several properties like the name, the number of bikes, latitude, longitude,
and so on.
And the trip edge has properties like the user ID, so who rented the bike, which bike
was used by the bike ID, and from and to.
So when this trip happens, until when, and the duration, for example, in seconds.
So this is schema A on the left side.
On the right side we have a more heterogeneous schema.
So we have also stations and trips as vertices here.
And we have also bike nodes and user nodes with several properties.
And I just divided into this because I can explain the examples that follow a bit better
compared to just using a simple schema like here on the left side.
Okay, so how a graph stream of these schemas could look like this.
Of schema A I have just these trip edges between two stations and all information inside.
And from schema B I have here the trip nodes connected with all the other vertex types.
This is just an excellent review of how a stream of this graph data could look like.
Okay, so now begin with a very simple example of our grouping algorithm.
So the input of the grouping is the graph stream, I think it's clear, and we need a
grouping configuration.
And the grouping configuration consists of five attributes.
The first is the window because we are doing windowing on our graph stream.
So I can define a window size, which is here, for example, 10 minutes.
And then VgKey are the vertex grouping keys, that means the key functions that leads to
the grouping of vertices.
VgKey are the edge grouping keys, that means the key functions that are needed to group
the edges together.
And we also have a collection of vertex aggregate functions, this is VagG and EagG are the group
of edge aggregate functions.
So the four on the bottom are like just an array of several key functions and aggregate
functions.
Okay, and now having the input stream and applying that grouping, we get a result.
And just looking like this, because we defined for the vertex grouping keys a function that
maps every vertex to an integer value.
And that results in, it doesn't matter which vertex exists in our graph stream, we group
everything together to one vertex.
And that's the white one with an empty label.
And the same for edges, that means every edge that exists in our graph stream, we group
them together to a super edge, we call them super vertex and super edge.
With that is displayed here in gray.
And because of the count aggregate functions, we add a new property to the super vertex
with the count of all the vertices that are grouped together, and a new property to the
super edge with also the count value.
And this is now our result for every window that we defined on the graph stream, for example
here the first window, second window and so on.
That means we are creating a stream of grouped graphs here.
Okay that is for schema A, and that's the most zoomed out view, so I group everything
together that exists in the graph stream.
For schema B and same grouping configuration, it looks the same, because it doesn't matter
which type label exists, we group everything together.
So we have just different counts, because we have a bit more vertices and edges, and
also for the second window it looks the same.
Okay so this is my first example, so the most zoomed out way.
The second example are called a graph stream schema.
So that means now we are using as a vertex grouping key a function that maps a vertex
to its label, and a function that maps the edge to its label.
And what's the result here, now our node has a label station and the count, because the
count aggregate function stays the same, and our edge has a label trip.
So it's more or less the same, because our graph streamer has just one node type and
one edge type, and that's it also for the second window.
Now it gets a bit more interesting when we are using schema B.
The result here with the same grouping configuration as before is now this.
That means every vertex is grouped by their label and every edge is grouped by their label,
and now I have a schema representation of my graph stream.
And again with all counts, because we are just using count aggregation.
Okay and that's for the second window and so on and so on.
I just left here the properties.
Okay the next example, we stay with the vertex grouping keys and edge grouping keys, but
now I added several aggregate functions to vertices and edges.
For example I say okay for the vertices I want to calculate the average of all available
bikes for these stations, and for the edge aggregate functions I want to have the minimum,
maximum and average duration that a trip between two vertices has.
And the result would be this, so same grouped graph, but now I have three additional properties
on the edges, minimum duration, it's in seconds here, maximum duration and average duration,
and the average bikes available on this station also as a new property.
Same for the second window.
And now my last example, it is, I called it, well not the last example, there is one more.
So I added now here a second vertex grouping key function, and that's an important thing
of the graph stream grouper, you can also implement your own grouping key function.
For example this one called getdistrict consumes the latitude and longitude property of the
vertices and then calculates like a district identifier, for example here of Prusall whatever,
so in which district that belongs to.
And then the graph is grouped on this representing district identifier.
And we also say that for the edges we want to group the edges on the user type, that
means for every edge, so in this data set we have a user type subscriber and something
else we will see it shortly.
That means for every edge I get new now two edges, one for this one user type, one for
the other one, and also here some aggregate functions added.
And the result is something like this.
So here exemplified for three stations, so you see here the district ID one, two and
three, and the average latitude and longitude, for example for visualization, proposes to
place it on the map, and for the trips between two stations or between two district representers,
we calculated also the minimum, maximum and average duration and counted them.
And you see here the green edges are for the user type customer and the red edges are for
user type subscriber.
So the last example is then this one here, if I say okay, as vertex grouping key functions
I say please extract me the identifier of that, that means every vertex that exists
in the graph stream is placed here, and also for the edge identifier, that means since
we all have unique identifiers, every vertex and edge is placed here, and this is more
or less like a snapshot of the current state of this graph stream for the specific window.
So therefore I call that zoomed in, it's the most zoomed in configuration that you could
use.
Okay, you could imagine implementing this is not that easy, so the master students found
a way using Apache Flink and its table API, so everything works distributed since we are
using just the API functions of Apache Flink, but we also figured out several implementation
challenges.
So first was to find a good graph representation, second one is since we are creating a workflow
of this graph stream we have to ensure the chronological ordering of every step in this
workflow.
As a third point is also do you want to ensure the scalability, since if we scale out this
algorithm the scalability should be also high, and also keep the state as minimum as possible,
and provide a low latency and high throughput.
So these were several challenges the master student solved quite well, and at the end
we created a grouping operator looking like this.
I don't want to get into details, it's just an architectural overview of every Flink
steps we used.
What is quite interesting is that we created an operator encapsulation of this, that means
the operator consumes a graph stream at input and has a graph stream as output, that means
you can combine several of these grouping operators, or if you define another graph
stream algorithm that produces a graph stream as output you can just put them before.
So you can like chaining these grouping operators together.
And like I said so this consists of the mapping of the input data, the deduplication of vertices,
grouping of vertices and edges and then mapping it to an output graph stream.
How an API would look like, so it looks a bit messy but I think it's quite fast here,
what's happening here.
So first you have to define, I don't know if I see my...
First you have to define the execution environment of Flink, then we read the data from some
streaming source, for example a socket source or some Kafka stream or whatever you want,
our Flink supports in our case, then we map it to a graph stream object which is the internal
representation of our stream and here's the interesting part here, you define the grouping
operator.
So in the middle, that's the grouping config I showed you in the examples, you can define
it here by an API, you set the window size, you set the vertex and edge grouping keys,
you set the aggregate functions and so on and at the end you just execute this operator
on this graph stream and then you can define the thing or just bring it to the console
or whatever you want.
So that's the operator call, how you define it in the API and current state, so we are
about, all the students are about at 90% of the complete implementation of that.
There were some, we figured out some bugs at the SQL or at the table API of Flink that
were not fixed yet, so we had to define some workarounds that cost us time but yeah, like
I said, we found a workaround and the next steps are that we plan an evaluation, so how
is the latency and throughput of this complete system and we want to test it on real world
and synthetic graph streams and maybe then publish some results, so let's see.
And also the user defined key and aggregate functions are still under development.
Okay then that's it, that's all folks.
Please check out our GitHub repository or maybe you want to contribute, so we are open
for this.
The two links here at the bottom are also the icons are two other projects, the one
is Gradube, this is a big temporary graph processing engine also based on Apache Flink,
so there were also a main contributor to that project which was initially created by Marty
Nungen, who is now a worker at Neo4j and yeah, also the temporary graph explorer is a user
interface for that system where you can play around with the evolution of a graph but in
a historical dataset.
Okay, so that's it and please ask questions.
Thanks.
Yeah, please.
On one slide you said a problem was to decide on the 520 I think is all, the optimal graph
representation in the streaming model?
Yeah.
What's the answer?
So the question was, so we had this challenge to find the optimal graph representation and
what was the answer?
The answer was a triple stream but a rich triple stream we called it since two property
graph vertices are connected with an edge, that means every vertex consists of the label
and possibly a big set of key value pairs as properties and the same for the edges.
And this was our optimal because you can then model everything with this model but the counterpart
of this was in here that we have to do a vertex dedeplication.
For example, if you have a self-loop, so from one vertex to another one, we have a duplicate
of that vertex, so we have to dedeplicate it afterwards for this model, so this was
one counterpart, but we figured out that using every concept of the property graph model
there as a triple is now the best choice for the students.
So another?
Yeah?
Could you comment a bit more on the scalability, like what's the graph size, the distance,
all in one?
Yeah, so the question was some words about the scalability.
The scalability is an open point of future work, so we don't have concrete results of
that, so we tested it with some city bike data that we interpreted as a stream, so some
historical data and we could process, I think it was about 600,000 edges in a few seconds,
but this is just some first results and we have not tried it on big and high-frequent
graph streams on a cluster, because we have huge fling clusters at our university, so
we can benchmark the scalability of that in a later step.
Yeah, thanks.
Yeah?
These aggregate functions, they part of, you know, do you, like a Java API and how do you
define them exactly?
Yeah, so the question was how we define the aggregate functions, so we have a set of predefined
aggregate functions like the count, average min max, and then you have an interface you
can implement against, so there's an interface called aggregate function and then you have
to implement, I think, two or three functions and then you can define your own and use it
then here on, yeah, there, where you say, where you give the classes of count and average
probably you can give your own class and then it will, is used, yeah.
Yeah?
I have a question.
Could you elaborate more on the real-life use cases or real-life applications?
So the question is if we elaborate more real-life use cases and real-life questions.
So applications.
So since, yeah, so we are in, so I'm at a university that means we are missing real-world
data a lot and we need also some input from companies to provide us with real-world data
that we can use.
So use cases could be, we also have to, we only have this bike sharing stuff or Twitter
data and whatever and I think if you have something like this aggregated function like
here an average property you can use because at the end it's a time series of changing
values for example of the average property and of like defining a threshold and get the
notification afterwards.
I think this is maybe one good application afterwards.
So for example if you have network traffic you see, okay, now the average, I don't know,
packet size is increasing, now I get notified for example like this.
This could be an application, yeah.
I was thinking about something like, I would say, like they can be made in a video, something
happened in a video because it's a frame could be considered as a graph and it could be taken
like an event happening in the video stream of video.
Yeah.
Yeah, interesting application.
Yeah, so the idea was to use like a video stream for that but then the question is how
much graphy that is, could that maybe not be done just in a regular stream processing
way.
So I think this is just advisable to use that if you have some quite complex relationships
between entities then you can use this system besides just an ordinary stream processing
engine or complex event processing engine.
So I think the unique point of this is to have the graph aspects into the streaming world.
So any further questions?
Yeah.
So currently events are already edited, right?
So you can only add to the graph but not delete from the graph by history.
Yeah, so at the moment everything is interpreted as an insult only but since Flink supports
everything like also updates and also deletions it is thinkable about some future work that
we also can support this because at the end the result of us is also since we are using
windowing it's an also an insult only stream at the end but if we maybe think about to
remove the windowing aspect so they have something like a continuous aggregation or whatever
then we need to support like a continuous addition on the end so to update already existing
aggregating results.
Okay, any further questions?
Go out of line then.
Thank you again.
I appreciate it.