Thank you all very much. Thank you for coming along.
My name's Jeremy Bennett. I'm chief executive of Ember Cosm. But Ember Cosm is an engineering
heavy company. We only have one full-time non-engineer in the whole company and it's
not me. So I actually am a working engineer as well as running the company. And we develop
open source mostly compiler tool chains but we also have some open source AI and we also
have some open source operating system stuff. And because most of what we do is pre-silicon
we do an awful lot of open source silicon chip modelling. But I'm also here with another
hat on which is that I am chair of the open hardware groups software task group. So I'm
responsible for all the software developed for the open hardware group. And I'll talk
a bit more about them in a bit. And this talk is part technical but it's partly about the
actual practical side of how we go about developing complex software for an open architecture like
RISC-V. So let's tell you a bit about the open hardware group. So it's a not-for-profit.
It's a member-driven collaboration and it's a mixture of industry companies like mine,
some big companies that you will recognise. NXP is a member for example. It has academics
so quite a few universities are members and part of it. And it also has individual members.
You can contribute as an individual and we have a number of, some of the work I'm going
to talk about has been just done by people who are individual members. And the goal is
high quality and that high quality is the key thing, open source hardware development.
The sort of open source hardware that you can put in a commercial chip and be confident
you can send it off to be fabricated. So it's collaborative and it's open. It's an open
development model. So all these things are open to all. Now the organisation's the open
hardware group but its cores are known as core 5 or core V. So we have a huge family
of processors. I'll talk about them. Everything from the smallest RISC-5.32 to the biggest
RISC-5.64 designs. And these are standard RISC-5 cores but with some customer ISA extensions
for RISC-5. The chief executive is Rick O'Connor and those of you who have been around for
a few years will remember Rick because he was the first chief executive of RISC-5 International
and he's moved from the open source specification world to actually delivering real silicon
IP. Let's look at the ancestry. So open hardware group grows out of an academic industry project
called the parallel ultra low power processor project. Pulp. And that was a collaboration
originally between ETH Zurich, the University of Bologna and ST Microelectronics. ST Microelectronics
no longer active in it and it predates RISC-5. The first part of pulp was done with open
risk but for the last many years it's been a RISC-5 project. And the idea is to get very,
very low power multi-core systems. So that's where we come from. And the cores started
off as these academic research cores. And the point about academic research cores is
they are designed to push the forefront of knowledge forward. They're not designed to
be exhaustively tested for manufacturing and use in a commercial deployment. That's not
the purpose of a university. So the natural transition is that open hardware group takes
that as an outstanding technical base and then takes it into a robust standard. We have
loads and loads of members. So I've copied this off the website and it's the wrong format.
I really want a wider and flatter one. But you'll probably see some logos there. You'll
see Ember Cosm's logos there. The astute of you will notice that Ambers and Web Services
appears to be both a member and a partner. I think they transitioned from a partner to
a member and the slide wasn't properly updated. So we have lots and lots of members. I think
it's up to about 70 now. And it might be worth just saying that when you become a member,
yes you have to pay if you're corporate you have to pay a membership fee. But that's not
the big thing. You can only become a member if you commit resource in terms of what you're
going to contribute. And that dwarfs any membership fee. You cannot be a member unless you're
going to do something. We don't have sleeping members. You've got to be active members.
In terms of an organization, it's very lightweight. And this is one of the big contrasts with
RISC-V International. At a technical level, we only have five committees. We have an overarching
technical working group which has the overall responsibility for the engineering direction.
And it has two, it has co-chairs, it has Jerome Cuerre of Amont from Thales and David Lynch.
And I can't remember where David Lynch comes from actually, but two companies joined chairs.
And that meets every month as the final arbiter of technical stuff. And then all the work
of this organization is handled by just four committees. The CORS group headed up by I
am Bink from Silicon Labs. And that is responsible for the tracking the development of CORS.
The work is done by the member companies. But these are the groups that have oversight
and make sure the quality criterion is maintained. There's a verification task group. And verification
is actually separated from core development, even though the two are desperately tightly
tied in. And that's led by Simon Davidman of Imperus. There's a hardware task group.
And this is a slightly strange name perhaps. But the point of the hardware task group is,
though this is fundamentally a group developing Silicon IP, we do have to have reference implementations.
And the first reference implementation should be coming out later this year, which is the
core five MCU. And that has one of the 32-bit cores in it. And lastly, the software task
group which I lead assisted by Yun-Hai Shang from Alibaba Teahead. And that's responsible
for all the software projects. And again, it's oversight. It's not doing the work because
you have to do the work. If you want to be a member, you have to do the work. We do have
a bit of a problem there because we have mostly hardware members and not enough software members.
In terms of the roadmap, we've got a flagship application core. That's the CV-A6. And that's
a 64-bit full-blown RISC-V core designed to run Linux. And that comes out of the top-end
pulp core under development. There is a smaller 32-bit core, the CV-32A5, which is designed
for, which is designed to try and do a small Linux system. Or of course, we've got the
issue of getting Linux running on 32-bit anyway. You probably can only just make it out. Each
of these projects has a target technology readiness level. Are people familiar with
technology readiness levels? A little bit. Okay. So most of these are aimed at technology
readiness level, which is proven in the environment. CV-A5 is a bit different. It's aimed as TRL4,
which is proven in the lab. And we've got other projects which are outside different
levels. But mostly we're aiming at TRL5. Okay. The flagship, the first project was the CV-32E40P,
which is a microcontroller class 32-bit RISC-V implementation. And the first version of that
is complete. The second version is under development. And actually the work Nandni was talking about
with built-ins is primarily focused at CV-32E40Pv2. You will see sitting there, there's something
called the CV-32E41P. And that's a bit unusual because it's actually only going to TRL3,
which is proof of concept. And it's being developed by Huawei under this group in order
to test out the ZC-Star extension, the new compressed extension, and the ZF-INX, where
you have a shared register bank for floating point and integer. So it's only a proof of
concept chip to verify that those work. And then we have a couple of more forward-looking
ones. CV-32E40S is a version of the original CV-32E40P aimed at security applications.
And the really exciting one is the CV-32E40X. That's a bit further out because the X is
a generic extension interface at the hardware level. So this is designed so you can take
a call. It's really easy to add in a wide range of extensions. And indeed, to the extent
you can do the floating point extension through the CV-32E40X. So that's the roadmap we're
sitting on. So what about the software projects? Well, I'm going to focus on the tool chains.
So the LLVM tool chain, the GNU tool chain. And because we haven't yet got silicon, I'm
going to focus on a couple of software projects, QEMU and the Verilator model. We have other
projects. So I'm responsible for eight projects in tool. There's the SDK, the software development
kit that's actually joined with the hardware group. The hardware abstraction layer so that
we can actually make our software more easily portable as we do more and more of these chips.
Free RTOS with micro-controlling. If you're going to go for an RTOS, the obvious one to
start with is Free RTOS. And Linux, which is really aimed at the CVA6. So we've got
eight projects under our belt. We have a rigorous engineering process. So those of you who work
for big engineering companies are familiar with gate-based processes. So all of the way
we manage these projects is through a gate-based process. You have a project concept gate.
It's where you propose a project. You want to work on this project. You explain what
it is and why we need to do it. And the project will only go ahead if it's voted for by enough
members. And members can't just vote and say, hey, that's a good idea. I'll say yes for
everything. You vote for it. You're going to commit resource to it. Critical thing is
this is a doing organization. So, OK, you're then going to explore it. And then we got
to a project launch gate. And that stage, not only do you know what and why, but now
you know how you're going to do it. What do I need to do to get this? And then the big
one, the last one, is plan approved. And plan approved means you've resourced it. So you
know when you're going to deliver it. And that's quite a big hurdle for some projects.
And then away the project work goes. I mean, this is a bit simplified. We all know work
starts a bit in advance. But the way the project goes, and eventually you get to project freeze,
OK, where it's all done. Now, this is brilliant for hardware, OK? It's a very hardware-centric
view of the world because a freeze means something. It's when your chip's gone off to be fabbed,
OK? Doesn't work quite so well for software. So we've modified it for software, OK? And
the first two stages are quite generic because typically we're working with a big block of
common software. We're not writing a compiler from scratch. We're taking the GNU infrastructure,
GCC, binutils, and all that, all millions of lines of it. And that's mostly not changed,
and we're changing a bit. Now, some of that is quite the why and the how. The what and
the why and the how is quite generic. It applies to probably all core five chips, certainly
maybe to all the 32-bit ones. And then for each specific chip, we have multiple plan
approved, which is where we work out when we're going to deliver it for CV30, E40P,
V1, for V2, for S, for X, and so forth. And so we have a whole set. But it's still the
same process of you need to know it's properly resourced and so forth, OK? So we'll see that
a little bit in action. But that whole engineering focus pervades everything, OK? So let's put
the content. Once the compiler toolchain, it's not just the compiler, it's the assembler.
It's the low-level utilities. It's the debugger. It's the libraries. It's the emulation libraries.
It's the standard C libraries, the C++ libraries. And in the ultimate way, if you look at GCC,
this is GCC. It's many, many languages. It's ADO. It's the C, C++ family. It's FORTRAN.
It's Java. It's GO. These days, it's Rust. It's modular to... And of course, we've got
things that sit at the high level like OpenMP and OpenACC. That's a huge lot of stuff. We
have a hasten to say we're a long way off having all of that for the core five. But
it's a lot of code. It's about... It's north of 12 million lines of code and it's a year
or so since I last measured those figures. So it's big. And we're trying to get that
all seamlessly worked through to work on core five. Now, we're not doing it from scratch.
Of course, we're starting from risk five and then we're adding stuff to it. And the humans
say LLVM has the same components but they've got different names and a different set of
languages. So let's look at the ISA extensions for core five. And the core five ISA extensions,
there are nine we're concerned with. Eight of those come from the pulp project. So extra
addressing modes, post incrementing, load and store. Hardware loops. More ALU operations.
And special case branching operations. We've got MAC instructions. We've heard about the
event load. That's a multi-core feature. And then we've got the pulp bit manipulation and
the pulp SIMD. Those are not standard bit manipulation and SIMD. Those are different
ones. But there's been years of development. The reason they're different is they predate
a risk five bit manip and they predate risk five SIMD. And you can see the pulp SIMD is
big. And the reason that Nandni knows so much about built ins is she's done the built ins
to support those 220 SIMD instructions. So she's nearly finished. And then I think she's
going away for a long holiday where she never looks at another built in again. And we've
got ZC star. So we have the first GCC implementation supporting ZC star. And of course these are
standard risk five compilers. You can still use them for risk five. And the hot news is
that core five GCC has a pull request to put ZC star 1.0.1 which is the freeze candidate
support. Once that's been reviewed that will go in there. So we've got a lot. The tool
chain work is all about supporting these pulp extensions. In terms of the built ins you've
heard all about them. But it's a lot of functions. It's not just Nandni. Nandni has a team working
on this. And we've got this naming convention. So we get from naming convention that built
ins for risk five are built in underscore risk five underscore vendor underscore name.
We've got so many we're actually splitting up into ISA extension and name. There is a
rule though if you're you can't just have if what you're doing is a built in is it corresponds
to a standard built in then you must use the standard name. So for example we have in our
arithmetic we have abs so we've got built in abs which is a standard GCC built in.
The built ins actually they have the same name for 32 bit or 64 bit. That is not overloading
in the C plus plus sense because either you're running for a 32 bit target or you're compiling
for a 64 bit target. You have one or the other there. There's not an overload. It's also
the case is built ins are not just another way of doing inline assembler. There's not
a one to one mapping. So for example for the SIMD add scaler there are actually two different
ways of adding scalers in the risk in the core five SIMD. One where the scalers in a
register the other where it's a small integer and you can actually put it is that there's
actually an add immediate instruction. We don't have two built ins. There's a single built
in. And if the second argument is a small constant that fits there it will generate
the immediate version instruction. Otherwise it will load it into a register. And that's
part two of Nandy's talk for the future because that's quite a lot harder to do in a built
in. OK. And there is a specification. It's big. If you put it into if you generate PDF
it's 57 pages long. OK. So. And that's one of the things is built ins built ins are not
quite as easy as you think. There are things you can get wrong there. And you do genuinely
have to think and review it's under review at the moment. That's not finalised. OK. So
testing now if we're going to do full testing of a tool chain. OK. We need a target which
has all these ice extensions. They're not standard risk five. I can't just take standard
risk five QEMU or whatever. OK. You can do some testing. So the standard can you assemble
a test for example don't need an executable target. They are pattern matching. Have you
generated something that looks right. OK. You can do the same with built ins. You saw
it from Nandy's compile time only thing where you look and do a scan assembler to see has
that built in generated just one of the instruction I want. OK. But more generically you need
to be able to execute your tests. OK. So we have two things. One is we have QEMU for core
five. That's a project being led by Wei Wei Li at the programming languages and compiler
technology team at Chinese Academy of Sciences in Beijing. OK. That's a work in progress.
We're expecting that to become available later in 2023. And secondly we're using very later
models. How many people here are familiar with very later. Han show. OK. Most of you.
OK. For those who don't it's a tool that takes a hardware design in very long or system very
long and generates a C plus plus model from it. A cycle accuracy plus plus model and very
later models are really useful because either easy to integrate to toolchain testing and
be they are what's called implementation models. Most models come from the specification of
chip. These are the actual implementation. So we know what your testing is what is physically
going on the chip. And when you have a model it's not just enough to have a model. You've
got to be able to hook to it. So typically you've got to run wrap around some form of
debug service you can connect GDP or LDB. And that's the work in progress. That's due
to be completed in the next few weeks. And then you'll be able to actually run on the
actual model of the actual hardware. Testing policy. LLVM project uses the LLVM into
integration tester. That that is a set of several tens of thousands of tests from source
code down to LLVM IR. Very comprehensive. And we use that. But it isn't a set of execution
tests. Now LLVM does have an executable test suite but it is a set of applications to run
on our own under operating system. And for a small microcontroller they're not suitable.
They need an operating system there. So we can't use the LLVM test suite. So instead
we use a subset of the GNU regression tests to test LLVM compilers. And that's widespread.
That's not something we've invented. That's been done for years. It's only a subset because
there is no point in running the GNU tests of the internal representations inside the
GNU compiler. But things like the torture tests are absolutely fine whether they're
on LLVM or GC. They're compiler agnostic. The GNU tools just uses the GNU regression
tests. Something that we're very hot on is exhaustive testing. OK. It's not just that
oh I tried one thing and it seemed to work. It's a let's make sure we've not missed things.
So starting at the assembler we have both positive and negative testing. By positive
testing we mean testing the compiler does what you want. By negative testing I mean
testing it doesn't do things when it shouldn't. So for example if we're looking at an instruction
that takes a six bit signed constant we will test it with values of minus 33, too small
for a negative number. Minus 32 the biggest negative six bit number. Zero because you
should always test zero because it's a special case. Probably minus seven and plus five and
then we'll test 31 and 32 which is too big. And we will check those bounds. And actually
we added those tests for ZC star and found a whole load of bugs in the ZC star spec as
a consequence. So we do that sort of thing and we also test things like we test the extensions.
I've got the ELW instruction. I test that the ELW instruction is handled by the assembler
when I specify XELW. I also test that it doesn't get recognized when I don't specify XELW.
So that's really important. And one thing I would observe is and I've seen this for
a long time is RISC-V is incredibly weak on its assembly level testing. There are about
ten times as many tests for ARM and x86 as there are for RISC-V. So it's important to
do that. And so we do core five specific, core five specific GNU LD testing because
we're adding some relocations. Do they work? At the moment we've got compilation only tests
of built ins using scan for assembler instructions. But when we've got those models running, the
QEMU and the Verilator model, we'll be adding execution tests. So not only do I generate
the right assembly instruction but it does what I expect. Not only do I generate the
built in but it does what I expect. So we'll be adding those in as well. And that, all
that testing ties into the difference of this is a commercial grade chip, commercial grade
core, sorry, and its associated tool chains. So resourcing. Resourcing is an issue because
software these days on a chip you'll spend twice as much on the software as you do on
the hardware. But open hardware group is inherently mostly hardware company members. We've got
plenty of software members but we're still in a minority. So it is a challenge to get
enough resourcing as part of my contribution and because it makes a lot of contribution
as part of our membership, the PLCT lab in China, they make a big contribution. So that's
coming there. And we actually double up, we use them very much as part of our graduate
training program as well. So part of the graduate allows us to train a new generation of compiler
engineers. But we're also seeing companies like Silicon Labs and Dolphin Design call
out to them because they help to fund those software companies to do the work. So thank
you to both of those. And we do need more of that to come on and I expect it will come
along. Okay. Second is we are not going to maintain out of tree forks of GCC and LLVM.
It's a thankless task. It takes up a lot of time. The goal is to get upstream as vendor
extensions. This is not a new thing. This has been part of GCC since before and part
of LLVM. Okay. And when you have that triple that says what's your target is, that thing
that in your standard compiler says RISC532 unknown hyphen L, hyphen GCC or whatever,
that unknown is the vendor field. And we should be using that. So if you get these tool chains,
you'll find they build as RISC532 hyphen core fee, the vendor hyphen L, hyphen GCC. Okay.
And that's absolutely standard. It's been around forever. You can see in the GCC build,
for example, there are variants of Spark and RISC5 for different manufacturers, for people
who make radiation hardened versions for space and so forth. Okay. That all works fine. RISC5
is designed for this. It's extensible. That's the whole point. There is a missing piece
of the jigsaw, which is in RV32. In the ABI specification, you have relocations. Okay.
There are 256 possible relocation values you can have. The top 64 of those are reserved
for vendors. Okay. That's enough probably for any one vendor, but it's not enough for
all vendors and it requires a centralized way of controlling. So we know how to solve
this problem is that every time you need a relocation to tell you this bit of assembler
when you link it needs adjusting the memory offset, you put down two relocations. One
is to say which vendor you are. And that's just a new vendor. That's just a new relocation
with 32 bits so we can have 4 billion vendors. Okay. And then the second one is say which
of those 64 relocations. But it means the vendor relocations, there's a full set for
every vendor. So we know the concept. One of my other team, Pietra Ferrara, who's sitting
somewhere in the audience, is doing the proof of concept to demonstrate that works. Turns
out the GNU linker is rather running at its limits with the complexity of RISC5. So it's
not a completely trivial task. But we need that before we can fully upstream all this.
The rest of it is all ready to go and it's all done to upstream standards. There's another
thing we found is you noticed I showed you there's two versions of CV32E40P. So we thought
and they've got different instruction encodings. We thought it would be good to actually have
to be able to support both instruction encodings. And if you specify an architecture, you're
allowed to specify my RV32IMAC underscore X ELW. And then you're allowed to say 1P2
to say I want version 1.2. Okay. That's all part of the standard way you name an architecture.
But it turns out it's not supported in the assembler, the GNU assembler. And furthermore,
the GNU assembler is not written in such a way that it's ever going to be easy to support.
And we gave up on that. And in fact, we're only going to support the latest version.
And that probably ties into the way that RISC5 International is going. Okay. So those, if
you like, are the key issues we're addressing. On the upstreaming, we're almost certainly
going to upstream the ISA extensions that don't need vendor-specific relocations. And
we'll put the others up once the vendor-specific relocations are ratified by the PSA ABI group.
So there. Get involved. The projects are all on GitHub. The Open Hardware Group has its
own repository. And if you don't like building from source, you can go to the Embercosm website.
You can download pre-built tool chains for GCC and LLVM, for Core 5, for every operating
system under the sun, all flavors of Linux, Mac, Windows, whatever. Okay. So get involved.
Each of these projects has a project lead. Charlie Keeney leads the LLVM project. Chun
Yul Liao from PLCT. Remember I said how you have different plan approved for the different
variants. She's in charge of the specific project for CV30E40Pv2. Nan Li Jamnadis, who
you heard from just now, leads the GNU tools project and is also actually responsible for
the CV30E40Pv2. Wei Wei Li from PLCT runs the QMU project. And I'm responsible for the
very later modeling because I'm a very later guy. Okay. And part of this is about bringing
on a new generation. That we actually help a new generation on and train. So there is
a half hour call. I'm sorry about the time if you live in America because most of the
people involved are either in China or in Europe. So they're on Friday mornings. There's
a half hour call on LLVM run by Charlie and there's a half hour call on GNU run by Nan
Li. And the idea is that we'll review people collectively. We'll review their pull requests.
And it's as much a training and learning thing as anything. So if you want to get into this
stuff it's actually quite a good way to get a bit of free training. And that's it. So
that's me. That's Ember Cosum. That's the Open Heartbreak Group. Thank you very much.
So we've got a few minutes for questions. I'm happy to take any questions. Yes.
So I'm working in a hardware research group at the university. We do a lot of deepouts.
Previously we've always used the field work from ETH directly or ARABOLINIA. But sometimes
it gives us some troubles. Because for example I'm doing compiler development right now and
then last week I discovered that there was a bug in GDB and nobody is working on GDB
anymore for this specific version that we think now. So I was just wondering do you
maybe have like a time frame for these upstreaming of these extensions? And can we like if tomorrow
we do a deepout should I tell my colleagues to do an open hardware core or should I tell
them to do the stable or the pulp cores in general?
OK. So the question for the recording, the question was about if you're working on the
ETH pulp cores which are still there as fantastic research cores, should you use the old pulp
compiler or should you use the core 5 compiler? So I think there's not a black and white answer
on that. The pulp compiler is a fork of GCC from 2017. So it's quite a long way out. And
that means it hasn't got the latest RISC-V stuff in there. Where we started on the GCC
for this we actually looked at whether we could roll that forward. And it wasn't a sensible
starting point. We started from scratch from the latest GCC.
So in terms of which core you use, I believe ETH Zurich is slowly moving over to more using
the core 5 unless you're particularly big because you might you may as well use these
hardened cores. In that case the obvious thing is to use the core 5 tool chains. And although
they're not yet upstream they're all in the public and there are pre-compiled ones you
can pull up. There is a problem if you're using the old pulp cores because remember
I talked about that version 1 and version 2. The old pulp things are so old they predate
sort of finalization of the RISC-V encoding space. And actually the instruction encodings
trample on future encoding spaces for RISC-V. So the version 2 fixes all that and all the
version 2 instruction encodings are actually now RISC-V compliant. They sit in the custom
0 1 2 3 blocks. What that means is you can't use this compiler because we haven't got the
version 1 stuff because of the versioning issue I talked about to compile for the old
pulp encodings. So that might be a factor you have to bear in mind there. But the old
compiler, I've looked at the old compiler and it comes down to it's a research compiler.
It wasn't designed to be tested and it's designed to prove concepts. And I think I've always
raised its own. That's the job of universities, not to do the exhaustive testing we do. It's
a different purpose. So it's a different type of compiler. But it does mean that occasionally
you get weird behavior. Yeah, so I haven't really answered the question but I've given
you the decision points to look at. I'd love you to use, by the way, I'd love you to use
Core 5 because then you'd be tempted to join in and help here. Any more questions? Yes,
right at the back. Absolutely, yes, I should have said yes. So we have a lot of projects
under there and we bring in that road map I showed. If you look closer you see the dates
were all wrong because some of these have moved out and we've got a load of problems
like the Tristan project that we heard of earlier which are under the open hardware
group. And those of you who use David and Sarah Harris' textbook for design, the WALL-E
processor is being re-implemented as a RISC-V processor and that is being done under open
hardware groups. So your next generation of textbook will have an open hardware group
WALL-E processor in it. So there's more than just those cores I said there. And if you
are working on a core and you think you might want to put it in this framework, come and
talk to one of us. You can talk to Director Rick O'Connor or if you don't know him come
to me and I will introduce you. Yes? I have a stupid question. So I work mostly on applications
actually and in our development we usually, we're starting to converge like developers
and testers are sort of converging into one team. Now you were saying that you actually
have this bit where some people do like the cores and others do the verification. Would
that also be possible to converge at some point? So this is, so the question is why do
we have, I'll paraphrase as why do we have separate core task group and verification
task group? They do work very closely together. This is specifically about hardware verification.
It's not about software verification. Software, the argument is completely different and for
the software the verification and development are closely integrated. I think because hardware
verification is so formally structured there is actually a case to be made for keeping
them separate and having the design team and the verification teams distinct. So it sort
of makes sense. I'm really a software guy. I'm not an expert on hardware but it does
sort of make sense. But the two teams work very closely together but it allows one team
to focus on the UVM based test and verification flow and another to work on the actual implementation
of the chips. Any more questions? Okay. Thank you all very much. That brings the RISC-V
room to an end and I hope you enjoyed it. Thank you.