So, good morning, ladies and gentlemen.
I'm Pavel Pisha from Chief Technical University.
I teach computer architectures for something like 20 years.
From year 2000, we followed the foremost Professor Hennessey-Patterson book about the computer
architectures.
And we have used the original Mipsit simulator, which has been distributed with the book,
but it has got dated.
So we decided we need to do something for our students to have a better experience.
And we started first with the Mips simulator, and then we switched to RISC-V.
And this was work, it has this work of the Yakublu Park, our student.
So I hope that everything is working, and I pass him a mic and the stuff.
Okay?
Okay, so good morning.
Over the past decades, computer engineers have been creating faster and faster computers.
Meanwhile, many software engineers kept writing slower and slower software.
And in many areas, this is fine, but in other ones, we need to process pretty much insane
amount of data often in real time.
And to do that, we need really efficient software that can exploit the capabilities of the hardware.
And only software engineers who understand the principles of the hardware can do that.
So to ensure we will have such software engineers, we need to teach our undergraduate students
at least the basics of computer architectures.
And because nobody wants to learn with pen and pencil anymore, we started using graphical
simulator.
So, and he does it more.
Yes.
So we started with a MIPs simulator, as I mentioned, which was shipped with the Hennessey
Patterson books.
However, it had very limited features, and it only worked on Windows.
So in 2019, Carl Kochi, who is sitting over there, created QTMIPS, graphical simulator
of the MIPs maker architecture.
And it was continued with a lot of work of Dr. Picha here.
And in 2002, myself, my colleague, Max Holman, and again a lot of work from Dr. Picha, we
have switched the simulator to RISC-V so that we could switch all the undergraduate computer
architecture teaching to RISC-V.
So we are there.
The simulator is licensed under GPL-3, and it's native simulator.
We are running under QT5 and 6.
It's developed and available on GitHub.
And to better collaborate on the materials, we have joined forces with our sister faculty.
We are from the faculty of electrical engineering, and they are the faculty of information technology.
And we have created what we call computer architectures education projects.
And you can find all the materials that we have recorded, lectures, slides.
You can find it there.
And furthermore, to collaborate with as many people as possible, the university has joined
the RISC-V foundation lately.
So the simulator is called QTR-SIM, and it is currently used by our university, the technical
university in grads, University of Colorado at Colorado Springs, and University of Porto.
The previous MIPs version is still used by the Charles University in Prague and National
Capitalist in University of Athens.
And this talk will focus on the teaching and user perspective.
If you are interested about how it works inside, at least a little bit of it, you can look
up the talk that we gave at the RISC-V International Academy and Engineering Special Interest Group.
So before I dive in, as Dr. Picha mentioned, you can just open this link and follow the
presentation with the simulator running in your browser.
It is in chat.
Great.
So let's dive in.
When we get students who have never heard anything about computers before, we need to
start really simple.
So what we do is that we start with a very simple single cycle microarchitecture, and
we show them how basic instructions are processed there.
So this is the simulator.
This is how it looks when you open it.
So we will hit no pipeline and no cache to get started, and hit start empty because we
will use one of the examples provided, so file examples and simple load and store work.
As you can see, the program is really simple.
It just loads from one part of memory, stores into another, and then goes into a loop using
branch instruction.
So this is the basic view that we start with.
And on the right side, you can see detail of the program memory with address of each
instruction, hexadecimal code of the instruction, and the disassembled instruction itself, where
the last two columns can be edited directly in this view by double clicking and writing
the instruction or pasting the code.
And furthermore, the left-mode column is a place where you can set breakpoints, so you
can use it like a GDB debugger, or at least the simplest part of that.
And now we can move to the heart of the simulator, and that is the visualization of the pipeline.
So if you look closer, on the left, we start with the program counter, program memory,
and circuits to update the program counter.
We load the instruction, and here you can see the hexadecimal value of the instruction
shown on the bus, and it gets to the control unit, where we send all the control signals
that we need.
So we are showing the low-vote instruction, so we need to send the data from memory to
registers.
We need to read the memory, and we will need immediate value for the arithmetical and logical
unit.
Right here we can see mechanisms for resolving branches, but this is low-vote instruction,
so I think there's a thing there.
And here is our arithmetical and logical unit, which has two possible inputs, either from
registers or from PC, and the other one has higher value from registers or from immediate
decode.
Here we get the requested operation of the allow, and here we get the signal whether
the result was zero for branching.
And finally, here we have the data memory, with address, and data to be written.
So we start executing, and we see that the instruction low-vote was highlighted, and
in the register view that appeared up there, we see that value one through eight was written
into the register bank, which is highlighted by the red color.
If we continue, we move to the store-vote instruction, and now the value needed to be
red, so it's blue now.
And if we go back to detail of the view, we see that we read that value from register,
and we are sending it by this bar to the data memory to be stored.
We also read the address from the immediate decode, and we are sending that to the arithmetical
and logical unit to be added to a register, which is in fact zero, so we are just sending
the value to the memory, and now the memory can write.
So let's see what happened in the memory.
Here we can see the address four or four, with the value written, so it corresponds
to the address we have here and to value we have there, and right above it, we can see
the place where we read the value from.
So speaking of the memory view, right now we are working with boards, but we can work
with other sizes, so you can switch the view for the unit to be either word, half-word,
or byte, which will work with respect to both little and big ndns.
And once we add cache, which will be in a moment, we can switch the memory view between
direct view of the memory and view where we are looking through the cache, so we will
see also the cache data.
Now we move to last instruction of Verlongue program, that is the branch equal instruction,
and we will see that we take the destination from immediate, it's negative, so we are jumping
back.
We add it to the program counter, and here we send it back to the program counter.
In the control unit now, the signal for branching, for the most generic one, is active, and we
see that the branch resolving mechanism determines that the branch should be taken.
So we go to the program counter, and instead of taking the program counter plus four, we
are now instructed to switch this multiplexer and take the value computed by the arithmetical
and logical unit.
So here we have detail of the program counter and the register itself in the pipeline.
And as you can see, we continue to the load bar instruction so that we can keep running
in a loop in this example.
So this is a very basic example just for this presentation, but it gives you an idea how
we start with the simple processor.
And when students have idea what the virus are doing and what it all means, we can start
speaking about how to make the CPU faster.
And what we find out is that the memory is slow, so we want to cache it.
However, that's not that simple, there are many ways to cache it, we can cache data,
we can cache instructions, we can choose different sizes of the caches.
And if you do it wrong, it will be worse than doing nothing.
So we really need to think about that.
So we switch to the second option in the configuration and add in time empty.
But this time, we will hit the button up there, which will open integrated editor with syntax
highlight and integrated assembler.
The other options are to open file, to save file, close file.
This is the important one, this is to run the assembler and upload it to memory.
And if you have some more complex project, you can even invoke external make file, except
for web assembler where there is no make.
So we insert a simple selection sort so that you will use, for example, I put it in a
free column so that we can see the program.
But just a simple selection sort was important here that we have data that will be put into
the L file and later start into memory and that will be the data that we want to start.
So we save the file so that we don't lose it and we move to the memory view.
Right here you can see the data that we have inputted.
And on the right side, new windows opens and it's the detail of the data cache.
It has two parts, statistics of the cache performance and it has very detailed view of
the internal structure of the cache and the data that are there right now.
So if we start running, the cache was empty.
So of course, we need to edit and we will miss.
And we will continue adding the value and right now the cache is full.
So first decision that the students need to understand is what shall we edit?
So right now there is random choice so it evicts the first one and we continue running.
And right now the selection sort will start placing values where they should be.
So it moves the value number one to the first one and you see the yellow highlight shows
us that the value is now written in the cache and the cache is dirty.
So right now the cache is using write back policy just to show you the highlight.
And we can continue and now we switch one with five.
And there was a simple example so the array is now sorted but we still need to go over
it because the CPU doesn't see that, it needs to check it.
And because we use the write back policy we also need to run fence instruction to make
sure that everything is stored back to the memory.
So you see there is no highlight anymore and the cache is empty.
And this is a time where we should look at the performance data and we will see that
we have quite an improvement.
Of course, it depends on how fast memory we have and fast cache we have.
So in the configuration you can set the penalties for hits and misses so that this data will
look according to what you need.
So this is the configuration of the data cache.
You can see that we can select different shape of the cache which means number of sets, block
size, degree of associativity and then we have two policies, replacement policy which
is out of random, last recently used or least frequently used.
And write back policy which can be, you can see write back write through, two options
there.
So here is how the detail of the shape of the cache looks for two different configurations
which in fact have the same amount of data there but they will probably have quite different
performance and also your right one, yeah, your right one, it's way more complicated
so the students can examine what this will do to their particular programs and data loads
that they will have.
Of course we have also program cache and I have added this very stupid design where we
have just one cell and well in program you never go to the same, other device so you
can see that we always missed and it's actually worse than doing nothing.
So just an example of that.
And I mentioned that the windows can just appear so if you prepare some example code
for students we can insert special pragmas to make the windows appear so that the students
who have not seen the simulator before can just start with all the tools they need so
we can show any part, we can focus address in memory and so on.
So now we have improved the speed of the memory and we look at the CPU again and we find out
that most of the silicon is just lying there doing nothing most of the time.
So we want to utilize it better so we see that most of the parts are somewhat independent
so we split it into five parts.
So let's go to the third option we will choose pipeline without cache and you can see that
the image got somewhat more complicated however if you remember the previous it's all the
same.
So students already invested some effort into understanding what the image was supposed
to mean so we don't want to move things around we are just adding the minimum amount of things
that we need so that we can continue with the more complex stuff.
So you can see we display all the instructions in each stage of the pipeline we are adding
the interstage registers and the colors are not random we are also using that to show
but which instructions correspond to each stage of the pipeline in the program view
so you can see all the stalls and branches nicely as they progress through the pipeline
and of course we needed to add animated windows to each stage of the pipeline for each file
for both control and data that we have and now we find out that this is not all we need
to do because up until now we assume that okay we process one instruction instruction
is done we continue but right now we start processing instruction but it will take what
former cycles because before we get the result so we have something that's called data hazards
and that means that if you do nothing we will get all the data because the data from the
instruction that we depend on is not already yet so we can have hazards spanning two cycles
in the next instruction and the hazards spanning one cycle in the instruction after technically
there is also hazard in the instruction that is after that but this is something that we
can solve inside the register file without breaking the abstraction of the pipeline so
we will ignore the last days and so what can we do about that well we need to detect those
problems and we need to counteract them in some way so we are adding a hazard unit to
the CPU and it has two options first option is okay we will wait for the data but we said
we want to build a fast CPU and waiting is well not fast so we also have option to forward
the data as we need it so yeah it's in the core tab and it's the option so this is the
CPU with added forwarding paths so what we have here is we are adding path from the right
back stage to get it directly into the execute stage and the multiplexers got bigger and
we are adding second path to forward the data from the memory stage so here is the difference
there is some extra wiring the CPU looks were simpler but it will wait and that's what we
want but it will cost us more to build it because it needs more components so let's
see some actual examples we are again learning the selection sort I showed you before so
we start running this instructions and right now we have our PC instruction that is producing
its value to register 10 and the hazard unit started screaming it doesn't like it so it
tells us it's not very very visible but the text in the red is forward so this is the
hazard that we have here and what happens is that this multiplexer gets value to use
the forwarding bar from the memory stage and instead of using the actual value from registers
we are taking the value for the red path and we get here for the arithmetic logic unit
value hexa 200 which is what we want but you don't know that it but remember that video
it will be imported later okay we don't want to add the extra hardware so we will stall
insert instead so this hazard unit is screaming again but this time it cannot forward so it's
screaming to stall but you can see that the instructions were right next to each other
so that was the first case and we need to actually stall two cycles so we will run next
cycle another knob is inserted and again the hazard unit is screaming so right now we have
any tune-ups but what we have now is that the instructions are far apart enough and
we can continue so we get value thank you 200x again and we are happy well and then
the simulator of course supports the most simple option we do nothing and what happens
here we have the hazard and we get value zero because the registers were initially empty
what is the purpose of this setting is that we will task the students to play the hazard
unit as and play the compiler so they will have to rearrange the instructions and insert
as less knobs as they need to make sure that the result will be correct this will typically
be some kind of homework so we don't want to control that manually so we have a command
line interface which can look something like that and will give you output like that so
the capabilities that we have here is to assemble file to set a configuration to trace instruction
in each stage of the pipeline trace changes to memory and registers also at the end to
dump the memory and registers which is the most useful part because we want to make sure
that the result is the same as it should be for example when the hazard unit is not available
and finally when we want to plug in some data for example when the students are supposed
to sort they should not know the data so we have special option to load data into the
memory and right now we have CPU that for undergraduate students it's quite fast so
but it's quite simple so now instead of making it fast you will make it more complicated
and we are adding memory map peripherals and some very simple operating system emulation
so if we open the templates again you can see that there is template for operating system
and it really does nothing special all it does is prepare for calling system call which
is equal in risk five and we will print how word to file the file is connected to a terminal
so what we actually do is after running the now we get the equal detected you can see
that there is something correct written that is detected syscall so we will stop fetching
new instructions so it's more clear for the students and once we get to memory here is
our hello board in the simulated terminal and you can see that the pipeline is empty
because we are looking at this from the perspective of userland so the operating system is emulated
and we don't see the instructions in the pipeline we just see that the pipeline was flashed
before it was written to us so this is the system calls that we support it's not much
but it's enough to show the basics to the students and this is all the peripherals that
we can play with mainly using the system calls so this is not peripheral but we have control
and status registers well some basic support of them we have an LCD display the terminal
I have already shown you and there are some general purpose I will propose two LEDs three
knobs with buttons and this might seem a little random to you it's not because we also have
this valuable board that has exactly the same peripherals and the simulator is set up in
a way that you can take the same code well not assembly code because unfortunately the
board is ARM but you can take the same C code and run it both on the simulator and
on the real world board and you can move back and forward so I said C code so we can't use
the integrated assembler anymore and we did not implement C compiler so you can use clang
or GCC to compile the file into elf which of course is to be statically linked and what
we do now is instead of hitting the start empty we will here insert the elf executable
and we will hit load machine so this is example of some program that writes to the LCD display
I will not show you the code here because this is one of the tasks that we give our
students but I can show you this code this is available on our D-Lab we write link here
and it is test suite simple formula from the new lip so you can link your code to the new
lip and use it in our simulator or at least some basic parts and we have tested that with
malloc so you can run this and it's connected to the terminal so we can see that some dynamic
allocation takes place and some checks take place and the tests are running successfully
so now you can use actual dynamic allocation inside your simulator and now some conclusions
so frequently asked questions is the simulator cycle accurate that's very important one yes
kinda the thing is we always assume that the memory has enough time to finish and if it
doesn't see people will wait we will not like insert stores or anything we just the memory
will finish but that's the only exception otherwise it's inside written in quite similar
style to Verilog system so it is compliant with the official risk five tests and yes
I can please see this yes in the previous version we have added that and it's integrating
into our CI so every new changes are tested against that we support the graphical parts
so it supports the risk five I with multiplication and also with control and status registers
instructions the command line also supports 64 bits however I yet need to find out how
to fit the 65 bit values into the visualization because it's already quite full and we don't
have a virtual memory yet but somewhere here in other room there is a student who already
promised to take care of that in the next year so in a year he might be presenting the
change here so we'll see so what we plan for the future if we are very close to adding
interrupt support we would like to add compressed instructions and support because that's quite
key part of risk five the only trouble there is it's pretty hard to I'm not sure how to
fit it into the program view because then it needs to be processed sequentially and
I'm not sure how to show it that the students see that it's really half of the size so that's
plan also the instruction encoding in the risk five is somewhat special is especially
around immediate so I would like visualization of each components the blocks that the instruction
is composed of so that that can be seen for each instruction and inspected and edited
we want to interest we want to be able to run a very minimal risk five Linux target
I mentioned the 64 bit visualization and the program here that also the memory it another
nice thing would be to visualize the utilization of the pipeline the image that is typically
in every book when you have squares for each instructions and you see the spaces where
no instructions were executed so it would be nice to add and also even when I made these
slides I would really love to have option to step back because I went one instruction
you know too far and it would be really hard to do it with all memory and everything but
at least for the visualization of the pipeline I would really like it at so if you are a
teacher represent educational institution and you want to use the simulator please do
if you have some problems contact us you'll be happy to cooperate on that if you are a
student or developer this is open source project we accept your request and usually the way
it works is that students do their final thesis on this project so far free and if you are
distribution maintainer you could help me with making putting in the official packages so
you can get the source at GitHub and we also provide where executables for Windows, Linux,
and Mac and we have packages using the open source build system for Ubuntu and Launchpad
for Ubuntu, SUSE, Fedora, and Debian and there are also packages for our and next packages
because those are those that I use and as we mentioned we have the online version as
well so if you would like to read more we have some publications the thesis and our
paper from the Embedded Board Conference last year so those are available and we have this
subject and you can find a lot of the materials at the comparch it's some of the materials
videos some are in Czech many are in English and that's all from me so thank you for attention
for so many people coming.
Please.
How tightly coupled is the simulation of the processor and the visualization?
I was thinking would it be possible to somehow connect something like model sim with the
HTN model or would that be very very difficult?
Sure, so the question was how tightly coupled is the visualization and the simulation so
it's a separated project that is linked together and it's only connected with some data passing
and QT signals so we already have the visualization and the command line that are completely separate
and they are just connecting to the same signals so it's quite well separated but it's not
at all stable.
Any other question?
Okay if you have no other questions we do not work only on the simulators but we do even
the design of peripherals so for example we have open source can every staff we work on
open source replacement of MATLAB and Simulink okay it is toy but we work on such stuff so
if you have interest we have the links to our other project we have experience with
motion control I have about set the errors of experience with embedded system design
including infusion systems for medical applications I have contributed to RTMS project which is
used in European Space Agency and so on we do VHGL design for the experiments of space
grade FPGAs and so on so this is the work which we do to help us our students it is
a lot of work something like eight manières of work in the simulator but it is only for
our students but we do even the stereo stuff for the world for example in socket can in
mainline Linux kernels are our oven stuff contribution drivers and so on okay yeah so
yeah yeah well this is your or no no it is ours yes the visualization that you see is
actually an SVG file that has special annotations which connected to the core previously it
was done by handwritten QT objects but I was not like okay to work with that so I switched
that to the SVG version when you can design it all in graphical editor and then you just
connected to a simulator so that's completely ours.