Great pleasure to be here. Can you all hear me at the back? All right. Can you? Yeah,
thank you. Yeah, wow. What, FOSDEM? Thank you to the organisers and for the staff for
inviting me here. It's a great pleasure to be here. And, yeah, if you asked me a year
ago would I be here, I'd be like no, because I hadn't actually heard of FOSDEM. Apologies,
at that point. Secondly, if I'd be told that I'd be talking about Rosegarden, which is
something I've not worked on myself for a very long time, not contributed to, I'd be
doubly surprised. However, I think it's important to look back sometimes. And I've called this
talk a slumbering, yeah, Rosegarden a slumbering giant. And I thought, I didn't really think
when I was putting this submission in as well, so I thought a slumbering giant, that made
sense to me at the time. Who knows what slumbering actually means? Okay. I should explain that,
because I was thinking about maybe changing. So slumbering actually means not quite sleeping,
but also not quite awake either. And it's kind of in relation to the fact that Rosegarden
has been around for a very long time. Maybe just as a show of hands as well, how many
people have used, okay, let's start off simply. How many people have used computers to make
music? Okay. So we've got about 20 maybe. That's pretty good. Keep your hand up if you
use Linux to make music. Okay. That's actually more, I think. It's weird. Okay. About the
same maybe. So how many people have heard of Rosegarden? Okay. That's not bad. Not impressed.
Okay. Good. Good stuff. So Rosegarden started actually longer than 20 years ago. Let me
show you. So this is the kind of current Rosegarden. This is how it looks kind of now. And if you're
familiar with music software, by the way, I've got a pointer. Can you see it? Yeah.
It's cool. I usually just use it to torture cats, but this is the first time I've actually
used it on a presentation. So yeah, if you're unfamiliar with digital audio workstations,
I'll give you a little tour. So we have down here some instruments, and you can map to
those tracks, and they're either MIDI tracks, which is musical instrument digital interface
tracks, or you can have audio tracks too. And this is how Rosegarden essentially works.
It allows you to compose. It allows you to record into it from a digital instrument or
from an analog instrument, and then you can edit it on the screen. Just to go back to
the beginning, the talk today as well is going to be about the history of Rosegarden. It's
going to be about how I believe that good engineering practice, it was an interesting
talk, the last talk from Brian, about using the latest tools and technology to understand
how open source software can be better. So as part of this talk, I'm going to look at
how Rosegarden was put together in the first place and why I believe it's still around
because of the way it was put together and because of some of the design decisions that
we made during the creation of it. Oh, yeah, if I didn't mention, there's a QR code there.
If you want to scan that, you can go to a page where there'll be some links. I'll also
share this at the end. Rosegarden was really a kind of a labour of love. It was almost
an accidental success, but it was kind of done deliberately in a way. That doesn't really
make any sense, but Rosegarden came about originally from a university project. So it's
actually a lot older than 20 years. It's almost 30 years old. In fact, it's over 30 years old.
And then it became something of its own thing. So just diving back into how it looks these
days again. So we've got a piano editor on one side and a notation editor on the other.
And this was one of the great powers of the original Rosegarden, as well as both notation
editing and MIDI editing too. And this is the current Rosegarden homepage where you
can download it and see how often it's raised. Up here you can see there was a release in
December. The current maintainer, Ted, works very hard on these. And when I'm talking about
the engineering processes that go behind it, you'll see towards the end of the presentation
that there's a lot of manual work involved still. So some of the best practices that
we get through our day jobs can actually help us understand how we can make software like
this more maintainable and easier to release. It's not untypical as well for large software
projects like this to have slow release cycles. And typically once it's released, it goes
into the usual repositories where it can be created and packaged for download on various
different distributions. It's been translated into around 20 different languages, including
Chinese, Japanese, Italian, Spanish, Finnish, German, loads. And over the last 20 years
it's been downloaded from all over the world as you can imagine. And this is some stats.
So interestingly enough, we're still on SourceForge. That's down to the developers having a certain
way of looking at things. So SourceForge is the preferred way of looking at things for
a lot of the developers because they've been involved in it for a long time. And perhaps
they're a little bit behind the times. So they like to dig their heels in sometimes
when it comes to what is acceptable in terms of the technology that is being used. So the
good part about it is that we have all the stats from the beginning of time basically
all the way to today on how many times it gets downloaded. And this is source packages
only essentially as well. So it's not bad. I mean, its height, it was 5,000 source package
downloads per month. And even with the last release it was still around 2,000. So if you
add that into the mix with all the prepackaged stuff that happens for the distributions,
then it's a pretty tidy amount. So who am I and why am I here? So I worked on Rosegarden
between 1995 and 2004, 2005. I'm now an independent consultant and I kind of specialized mainly
in software delivery and customer focus. And that means that over the years as a professional
software engineer, I've learned various techniques which has helped me understand, okay, well
maybe we could do things slightly better. And I'd like to talk and write about this
right now. And this is how this talk I suppose kind of came about because I was thinking
what is the project that gave me the most pleasure over these years? And when it comes
down to it, undoubtedly Rosegarden was the thing. And some of the takeaways I believe
that we can get from this is to understand how open source software becomes important
and how it stays important as a social and commercial, well not commercial, it can be
commercial but as a social enterprise. So this is really a story about motivation and
why we do things the way we do. And how open source software becomes something that can
take over our lives as well. So just to expand on that a little bit, I've kind of broke it
down to three areas which I believe are the core components of how open source kind of
gets good, how open source projects become a thing in the first place and how they then
sustain themselves. And it's mainly, spoilers, mainly around the social exercise. We do it
because we kind of want to, we're driven to do it. Of course we do it as well because
we can't do it by ourselves. So that's number one for me is the effort that it takes to
build something. So when you look at something like Rosegarden or any other huge open source
project, you end up with hundreds of thousands of lines of code and lots of contributors
from all over the world doing various different things, either writing code themselves, becoming
developers, doing translations, helping out on the website with documentation. And this
is a snapshot from the Rosegarden website of the contributors that have been involved
over the years. Secondly, you can't do it without effort, you can't do it without support.
This is a picture of the time that's elapsed between when I, no sorry, when I stopped working
on Rosegarden and pretty much today. This is my son, Sam. He was one when I took a photo
of him and put him on this poster, so to kind of, to be used at one of these sounds expos
that we did in 2004. And this is him last year as he graduated from high school. And
this was probably the reason why I stopped contributing to Rosegarden this time because
I went off to have a family. And of course the family is important for support, so they
have to keep you going, maintaining your energy to be able to do stuff. In addition to that,
we also see how the working world comes into play. One second. So after university, I went
into, sorry. So how does the working world shape our experience and our perception of
what goes on in the open source land? So after university, basically, after Rosegarden first
came out, going into engineering and becoming a person who would actually grow as an engineer
and then be able to feed back into that project. So this is taking, this is the start, basically,
of Rosegarden. So I went to Bathurst University between 1990 and 1994. Rosegarden started
as a university project by a couple of friends of mine, Chris Cannon and Melissa Wilson.
And they did it for a final year project at Bath. And it was written for John Fitch, who
was one of the computer science professors there. And it's his idea to come up with a
Unix sequencer and notation editor. I think it was the combined thing that he came up
with together. So Rosegarden itself was born of a university project in around 1992. And
the name is a bit strange. So Rosegarden, where does that come from? It's actually,
thanks to these guys, a band called Bauhaus who come out of Northampton in the UK from
1978. And Chris Cannon, one of the lead developers, the originators of Rosegarden, he was a big
fan of Bauhaus and he had one of the songs called Rosegarden, The Funeral of Soars, which
is actually a song by John Cale. And he, being a bit of a wag thought, it's probably going
to be crap, this notation editor. So we'll call it Rosegarden after Funeral of Scores.
Ha ha. Scores notation. Get it? So yeah, that was the origination of the name. So 1992,
it was written on Unix. It was written on SGI originally, under Irix, with the Athena
widget set. It was a modified Athena widget set, written in C. And it looked pretty good.
I mean, I think Chris did a pretty good job, actually, despite the fact he thought it would
be terrible. This is actually Rosegarden 1.0, the source code. However, I believe this screenshot
comes from Rosegarden 2.1, which was the first Linux port of that source code. And as you
can see, it's got a piano roll editor, an event editor. It's also got the notation.
Oops. And it also works together on the same screen like that. So it was pretty advanced.
And it worked via the Irix device. So it would actually send out to a MIDI device from the
SGI, the Silicon Graphics workstation. That was it, number one. That was done for a final
year project. So what happened next? Well, what happened along the side of that was that
we ended up spending a lot of time mucking around. So in 1992, 1993, I was still at university.
Chris and Melissa were peers of mine, friends of mine, too. And we used to hang around in
the spark labs, as they were called, at Bath University. And we played too much X-tank.
Anyone know X-tank? Yes, very good. Too much fun. And too many late nights. And that was
the thing about coding at the time as well. It was a social enterprise. It's exactly the
same these days as well. I look at my son. I say to him, okay, why have you not learned
like, why have you not learned? He starts, okay, so now he's going to university, he's
starting to learn computer science at university. And when I was growing up, I had a computer
probably like some of you here. I started coding because I was interested in it. Him
absolutely zero interest in coding until he got to university. It's all been gaming.
I'd be like, why didn't you build a website? No interest. But yet he goes on to study computer
science. And annoyingly, he's really good at it. And he picks it up in no time at all.
So now I'm getting WhatsApp saying, dad, what about this node problem? How do I fix that?
Okay, fine. But to be honest, looking back, it's exactly the same now as it was then.
Because we just mucked around, too. We spent a lot of time in the spark labs playing X-tank.
We spent a lot of time learning command line or learning about Unix processes, how they
work. We learned stuff off each other. So at university, I learned Unix command line
solely from mucking around. I learned C and X11 from doing some university courses, some
of my minors. But the majority of it was from, yeah, just hanging out with people, exchanging
information. So that was Rose Garden 1. And then we left university. We went off into
the working world as a peer group as well. So I ended up in London eventually. As did
Chris and Melissa. They were working for the same company, actually. And we ended up hanging
out. And somehow, I don't know quite how this happened. But we got to a point where Linux
was a thing. You know, I think I've got a picture next. Where is it? Okay. So I've been
working for a little bit. I've just skipped ahead. I'll skip back. I've been working for
a little bit. I managed to save a bit of money eventually. And I bought my first PC. And
it was one of these gateway 2000s. Came in a cow box. I can't forget it. And it was so
exciting because I never had my own PC before. And the first thing I did with it was buy
Slackware 3.0 and put that on it. And that came out of, yeah, working. So going back
to this picture. The working world. And that was really where things started to kind of
fall into place. Because when you're working in a proper company, you have responsibilities.
And that was one thing that work really taught me. You're not just mucking around in the
Spark lab anymore. You can't stay up late to do your coding and have a lot of fun and
sleep late. You end up doing that anyway when you're a young engineer sometimes. But if
you're working for a company like this, like I was, a telecoms company, and we had responsibilities.
So we created network management software. And also software for multiplexers. And my
first boss, she was great. She sent me out on a customer visit. Straight away. She said,
okay, get in the car. Get up to Sheffield in Yorkshire in the UK. And go and be on
site with Yorkshire Telecom whilst they're upgrading their multiplexers and upgrading
software with our new network management software. And for something like that as a young, just
out of university, graduate engineer, it was incredible. Because it finally gave you that
connection between all the stuff that you do, all the hours that you spend on a piece
of code and the customer themselves. Because if one of these cabinets fell out of the network
or the upgrade didn't work, then someone would have to be sent out in a van. So the street
cabinet to reboot it and then you have to watch it in the control room to make sure
it came back up again. And that was, yeah, the real kind of visceral connection.
So this is the first, you might call it a learning, that I had. I didn't even realise
it at the time, of course. You don't do it. It was the fact that you need to serve somebody
with everything you do. Well, I felt that anyway. Because sometimes you might just want
to write some code for the hell of it. But unless someone's using it, where's the point?
You know? I felt that really, really keenly. So, yeah. Cow box. Actually, just to go so
back to the last one as well. So the cow box arrived. I got a P75. I think it was 95. So
a Pentium P75. It wasn't particularly flash. It wasn't top of the range. But I installed
Slackware 3 on it. And then there was a tarball of the Rose Garden source code knocking around.
And I think Chris and myself knocked it together. It might have been Melissa as well. Knocked
it together into the first kind of release on Linux of Rose Garden. And then just after
that. One second. So it was kind of a heyday of music software, really. Everything got very
exciting very quickly. So I bought my first PC. I was working. I was working too hard.
But having fun. But after a while, hard work became too much like hard work. I was on pager
duty. And back in those days it was actually a pager as well. And I remember the first
night I was on pager duty. I was lying there in my bed. And I put the pager right next
to my head. And I was just staring at it. For the whole night. I couldn't go to sleep.
I was just so scared in case it went off. What would I do? I had my own hardware at
home. I had my PC. But it was I'll come to this. It was on a 14.4 modem which I had to ask
someone to buy for me at work. They wouldn't even otherwise I'd have to drive into the office. I
had another car. So it was basically you were trying to offer support to a global product
from a very basic setup whilst being on pager duty. And the pager duty lasted for a whole week
as well. So you'd have a week on and then maybe two weeks off. And that was really stressful.
So between that and working and everything else and probably parting a little bit too much,
I just felt burnt out after a year and a half of this. So I kind of moved jobs a couple of
times. I bumped up my pay a little bit. And I got to a point a couple of years later where
I could actually take some time off. Oh, God. Let's relax. The first thing I did was buy some
music software because it was the thing I wanted to do. So I've been building software and I've
been getting into being an engineer. But what I really wanted to do was make some music and be a
rock star. So seriously. So I bought a load. Well, I say bought. I probably ripped. I definitely
ripped a load of stuff and put it onto my Windows PC like logic audio, Q base, rebirth and reason,
all these great tools that are available at the time. Digital audio workstations, which meant
they would record audio. You could put plug-ins into them. They would make great sounds. And also
things like rebirth, which was like a TB808, simulator, emulator, whatever. Lots of fun.
Lots of squelchy fun. So I spent a couple of years understanding these tools and having fun with them
and recording. And what I didn't realize I was doing was I was learning the domain. And if you
kind of look back from where we are now and you've kind of studied OO, object oriented design,
and you've maybe read Eric Evans' book or listened to Vaughan Vernon speak about DDD, domain driven
design, you understand that that's what you're doing is you're learning the language, the ubiquitous
language of music software and then you're learning to talk and feel the way that musicians do when
they use this software. So around the same time,
so around the same time, we had Rose Garden 2.1 already, but we hadn't moved on since 1992.
This was around 98 at this point. We did kick around a few ideas. So we, I mean mainly Chris
and myself and also Guillaume, a French developer who came on board, I think off the back of the 2.1
work, again it was a bit hazy. We started kicking around some ideas. We want to rewrite this thing.
Well, how are we going to do it? So I got this domain knowledge. Chris was an amazing software
engineer and still is to this day and still works in audio and in audio software. And me piggybacking
on his genius and also Guillaume's genius was a way to understand how we could build a whole
new version of Rose Garden. It was an itch we wanted to scratch. And we discussed a few things
and technology was quite fluid at the time. So we were like, could we do it in Java? Not really.
There was no sound system or there was a very basic API. To be fair, the Linux sound system
was not particularly advanced at that time either. It was just about coming out but it was mainly
OSS before that. So Rose Garden 2.1, just used open sound system which was just a device essentially.
So you could, there was no internal routing of MIDI events or audio. It was all straight out onto
the device. Java had the same problem. It was kind of slow in catching up. It wasn't slow. It was just
the fact that it hadn't been written yet, you know, a lot of these interfaces. There was a
immediate API for Java but Java was never my forte. Didn't like it. Didn't like the stack traces.
We also discussed IPC quite a lot with interpersonal communication. We discussed
CORBA. Anyone remember CORBA? Yeah. Anyone forgot CORBA? Yeah. Terrible. Well, at the time it was
very exciting. There was an alien book. You read it and you thought what the hell is this? It's
really complicated. So it was too heavy weight. But I think actually Rose Garden 3, the missing
number between 1, 2 and where we are now with Rose Garden 4 was an IPC, a CORBA based thing.
We might have even written in Java or something. It was crazy. That didn't last very long. It was
back of a fag packet type stuff, as they say in the UK. But we had a few other ideas. We thought,
well, it wants to build it on Linux. It has to be on Linux. We're both quite proficient in C++.
Let's do C++ maybe. Build a nice data model. And also we saw that Elsa was emergent. Jack,
which is the Jack audio connection kit, is still I don't think it was invented until a couple years
later, maybe 2000 or so. That was a flexible audio routing system, which is very cool. We
eventually implemented. But we knew another thing, that the UI was going to be vital. Having worked
on X11 and a thing of widget set, very basic X11 widget sets, there were two very exciting
Linux alternatives coming up, GTK and all the various wizards, all the various parts of it.
And KDE based on Qt. And the debate probably didn't take that long, but it felt like it went
on forever. But eventually we decided, I think as a kind of a three of us, on taking the most
pragmatic attitude, and that was we're going to go with KDE. And initially we decided to go with KDE
because it seemed to be slightly more mature. And I think we all like Qt as well. We didn't
know Qt particularly well at that point. The tool kit that KDE is built on. So.
We come to KDE years. So this was the real start of the real build of Rose Garden 4,
the thing I showed you at the top. So we finally got here. From what I say here, KDE 3 was released
in April the 3rd, 2002. And I think what we'd done between then is we'd started probably in 2000 and
we'd started writing some stuff. And eventually we got to a point where we had to kind of go with
the major upgrades. And KDE 3 felt for the first time, I think, when we were finally kind of getting
there. It felt like it was good. We were using a little bit of... Have you already seen that picture?
Yeah. I'll just stick on here. So we were using a little bit of
decop, I think it was, which was the communication interface for Rose Garden. We were running two
separate processes. The Rose Garden sequencer and the Rose Garden itself. Rose Garden GUI,
basically. And they communicated via... Well, we were going to use the KDE mechanism. We didn't
in the end. I think eventually we ended up on a memory map file which was suitably good for both
processes to access at that time. So, yeah, as you've seen, we ended up with quite a flexible
architecture. So this kind of maps the core. I'm not going to go into the core of the core of Rose
Garden, but I can point out a few things. So there was the two processes which underlay it behind.
The GUI communicated with the shared memory map file. The sequencer did all the running of the
stuff, the in and the out and the whatever. It was all controlled via the transport down here.
And it had quite a flexible mapping so that we had any instrument here could be mapped to any
of these instruments there. And they could be a MIDI device or an audio device. And we kind of
created an abstraction layer there which would allow us to map those as well onto either MIDI
devices which users could create called device files which allowed our users to actually get
involved with creating specific configurations for their own setups. So if you had a particular
type of keyboard or a MIDI device somewhere else, then you'd be able to create a device for it
and be able to map those sounds to your Rose Garden setup. Similarly, the segments themselves,
so these blobs are all segments. And you could slice those up and they'd all have parameters
associated with them too. So there was design obviously going on underneath the covers.
And that was from quite an early time as well. I believe that we didn't actively sit down and
plan it all, but we spent a lot of time refactoring. And that was one of the biggest
pain points I think we felt whilst we were working in the early 2000s.
There was all these great tools available. Coming out of working in industry where you had
all the compilers essentially before then, the end of the 90s or mid-end of the 90s,
it was typically you had to buy a compiler. So you had to buy a license for something.
You'd have to buy your library so the standard template library for C++ wasn't,
it was still kind of getting there. You'd have to buy Boost, I think it was, or whatever it was
called. There were various things you had to pay for. GCC and G++ were still getting there as well.
G++ 3 I think came out around the same time. So the toolset was shifting. There was also
the shifting media layers as well in Linux. So we were talking to people on various main lists
basically about like when is the new version of Alsop coming out with the stuff that we can use to
actually get some realtime stuff working on Alsop. So all of these layers underneath we were waiting
for. Plus the tooling was a little bit kind of getting there too. Plus all of the UI toolkits
were also growing. So we were kind of growing alongside all of this stuff. And it made it
quite difficult. We didn't have any CI. We had like a couple of machines. We had some basic
source control in SourceForge, which was probably CVS at the time, not even subversion at that point,
which worked. But typically even with three of us working on it, there would be breaking
changes the whole time. We didn't have any tests per se. We just downloaded the latest bit of
source code and building it at something would break. So when you're refactoring our core area,
even with three people, and you've got all of these dependencies moving, it makes it very
difficult to get anywhere. So we struggled, to be fair. I was working for a couple of years. Well,
it probably felt like a couple of years. It probably wasn't. It was probably more like six
months. I did take some time off and I worked on it full time in a little basement with
multiple computers, with distcc running on various computers to try and speed up my builds
and stuff. And it was a real struggle. Mainly because we were refactoring and breaking stuff,
but also because we had a kind of unstable base. Still, through much effort and through much time
and through much dedication from not just a core team, a growing team the whole time, but also some
really passionate users who came along quite early and have stuck with us the whole way through.
So we've still got people who have been using it for 20 years who just love it because
they don't think of any other way of working with it, basically. It's brilliant. They will compile
it and they will run it on their own kernels or they'll download it as part of a package or
they'll have a machine which they haven't touched for years purely because they want to run Rose
Garden. There are other alternatives, of course. There's plenty of other alternatives, but what
we've done is we kind of found our people, I suppose, through the way that we'd built it,
through the way that we'd gone about building it maybe as well, and the thought we put into it,
and the love maybe, we've kind of built something which has stuck around. And as you can see here,
it does, this is doing some audio and it also plugs into this thing I mentioned called the
Jack Audio Connection Kit, which is a way of routing audio around internally on Linux and
various other platforms too. So it's actually like an audio bus. Here's a virtual synth as well,
which you can route to it. So it works with virtual synths, external synths, etc.
So what we saw was an emergent architecture, as I mentioned various things. I need to speed up a
bit so I'm going to go through a little bit faster. I've also mentioned the Rose Garden
Studio concept. So this was the thing about the device files. And I think this is another powerful
feature of Rose Garden, one that's still used to this day. So we've got over 100 device files,
so people have gone off and they built them for Yamaha synths, for Roland synths, for various
different types, and you can just download those and install them into Rose Garden, and you can
map all the voices basically straight into it. Additionally, we've got, as I mentioned, the Jack
integration, the support for Ladsper and also DSSI plugins, which are native plugins for Linux,
and other platforms, as well as the VST plugins, which are the standard music,
more standardized music plugins, audio plugins for Windows and other platforms.
Additionally, of course, notation markup and printing using Lilypond as well. So very high
quality score export from Rose Garden, which has been very much appreciated by some of our users too.
So with all that rambling, this is one of the learnings that I found was that just the
architecture itself is difficult because of various reasons, communication mainly, but also
what do we want to build. Secondly, organization around that is difficult too, and we saw that
with refactoring that we had to suffer essentially. Maybe with better tooling or maybe with more
stable platforms that we were building on, it would have been simpler, and in hindsight it
seems almost trivial, but at the time it felt very difficult.
Secondly, this is something which really stuck a lot in the claw, in the throat, which is everyone
has an opinion on UI, everyone. Users, developers, even developers who don't profess to be UI or UX
experts have an opinion, because we all use the software, right? And if you change anything,
then you break a workflow. And that's a difficult lesson to learn. You may be a great coder,
but again it becomes the social angle between what are we trying to build and how do we keep
people happy, because it's even happened on the Rose Garden developer list in the last couple of
days. Ted's released a new version before Christmas, but he's released a patch version
the last week, and he changed one of the theme set-ups so it defaults to something that no one
likes. So there's a mini uproar going on. On the flip side, when you do get it right,
when you do spend the time getting your architecture right and you're thinking about your code and your
core, then sometimes big features that you might have thought impossible even a few months ago are
almost trivial to implement, and suddenly those points you go, oh, thank God, we got it right,
and you actually feel that that is something that was worth spending the time on. Doesn't happen all
the time, but sometimes it does, and it feels great. And yeah, fourthly in this little block,
literally all you need is a small number of users, and there need to be loyal users to keep you
going. So even though you're not getting paid for it, if you've got passionate users, it can mean
everything. Okay, talking of passionate users, we'd spend some time in basements and online,
of course, building stuff, and we and Chris thought it would be a great idea to get out there
and start showing it. And around the same time, 2002 or so, there were Linux expos starting to
happen in the UK. So through contacts of ours, we were involved with Linux user magazine, I wrote
for them at some point or other, and we managed to flag a stand at one of the first Linux expos,
and this is us looking all ruddy and young and lovely and wearing kind of branded t-shirts.
Look at that, made that myself, fantastic. This is my friend Mike, unfortunately not with us
anymore, but he was a great inspiration and helped us a lot and encouraged us to get set up.
And this is Chris. And this is our fantastic set up, isn't that just Stella? So today, I mean,
and yesterday walking around, looking at people sitting behind desks, exactly not better desk,
to be honest, with much more impressive set ups, it really takes me back to those days when we were
doing the same thing. We had our software, we were excited about it, and we went out there and
showed it to people. So, yeah, we were doing lots of things, writing, went to trade shows,
we went to conferences, well, not hundreds of them, a few, a handful. We started approaching
vendors, so there were people who were building music software PCs, and we talked to them, maybe
they'd be interested, we talked to Roland, we talked to Yamaha, we talked to loads of people,
talked to AMD. There's a book, it's in my bag, there's the, one second. So Michael McIntyre wrote
this whole guide which was published, the Roser Garden Companion. Yeah, and then we started talking
to partners as well, so there were people at the same time who were betting their careers and their
livelihoods on Linux being the next big platform. Obviously, everyone thinks this year is the year
of the Linux desktop, you know, but there are still people out there, well, then there were people out
there who wanted to build Linux-based hardware as well. We talked to a creator of keyboards in
Italy, we flew us over and we talked to him, it was a fantastic couple of days, met his family,
his mother made us a lovely pasta for lunch, and we saw his workshop where he was building these
incredible multimedia platforms and keyboards in his garage, basically, his garage business,
fantastic. So yeah, we got out on the road. Also, we launched a product, this was called Studio to
Go. So Chris and I, we formed a company and we built a bootable CD which enables you to basically
have an entire studio on your CD, you could put it into a Windows machine and you could boot it up
and boot it into Linux and you'd be ready to go, basically. You could also install it on your
Windows machine too. This is Chris, the year later, so from the previous photo, this is a kind of a
level of professionalism higher, we look more relaxed, more kind of in the moment, they're,
yeah, again, I think more relaxed. And then if we look another year further, this is us,
the kind of the high point of our career with Fervent Software and Studio to Go.
This was at the Sounds Expo in 2004, I believe, yeah.
So we weren't in this by ourselves, there was an organisation called Linux Audio,
as well, which is still around,.org, and in fact, I looked on the website yesterday and
apparently I'm on the board of directors or something, anyway, it's not a company and I'm
not on the board of anything there, but it was like a kind of an open source collaboration group
with a guy called Daniel James as well, who also I work with in journalism, he was a big proponent
of another Linux audio platform as well, which is still being sold, I believe. So working together,
we managed to get to a Sounds Expo where it was not just Linux stuff, it was also Windows and
the rest of the vendors there too. However, at that point, it was getting clear that we weren't
going to make a living out of it, Chris and I, so we kind of, with a family coming along,
and that's why I mentioned it at the beginning with a photo of my son, it was like a decision to say,
well, what can we do now? Because we tried a kind of business, it didn't make enough money for us,
and we didn't really have the insight into what we should do next, so we just said, okay, let's
call it quits for the minute. I dropped off from Rose Garden at that point, but loads of people
stepped up. And one of the biggest things that they did in the next section, which is the QT years,
was to port it from KDE to QT, which meant basically ripping out the KDE stuff sounds
simple enough, but took about a year and a half, which led everyone to understand that major
dependency upgrades are very hard. One of the good things to look at from the source code of Rose
Garden now is that of the source files that we have, about 1400 C++ files, most of them are
pretty small, so under 500 lines, that's including comments, so that's a good sign too. Healthy code
base. So, I'm skipping now from 2008, 2010, and I'm kind of looking towards what's happened
the last ten years, but also the future. Ted Felix came on board in 2010, and by his words,
I spoke to him in the last week or two, by his words, he said it suffered from a lot of
stability problems. We have a GitHub as well, as well as a source for, and GitHub is downstream,
so it allows us to do some nice visualisations. So, this was around the first bit of work that
we did to stabilise the initial Rose Garden. This was around the studio to go time, lots of work
there, and then this was around the KDE to QT port, so lots of work went in there too. After this,
when Ted came on board, he said basically he spent a lot of time stabilising, basically getting rid
of bugs and making sure that there was adequate performance, and doing that, I think it was not
unaided for sure, but focusing on that a lot. And you can see this also represented in the way that
Chris and Guillaume were very involved here, and Ted was involved later, and this is my contribution.
And also we see, again, from GitHub, the churn that was going on around the same time,
so studio to go product, QT port, and then stabilisation after that. But if you then look at,
I'm just comparing us to Muse, which is another Linux audio workstation as well,
and this goes up to 40 on this axis and up to a bit higher on this one. So, in terms of contributions,
we're not far off what Muse is doing as well, which is really encouraging to see.
So, I would say the product is pretty healthy, it's been stabilised, it's still being used by lots
of people, you don't hear about it a lot, but it's still there. And I'm going a bit faster now
because I need to wrap up, but the number one thing has got to be people, and that's why I
mentioned at the front of this talk. People to do the work, of course, people to support you
whilst you're doing the work, and the expertise that you build together when you're designing
something. So, that's why I see Rosegard now as still surviving, and still something that we can
contribute to. So, top five things for open source, basically, I would say this as well.
So, good architecture and good toolkit choices are super important, and they help with defining
equality and defining how far you can go with any one thing. And if you're not getting anywhere
down a certain path, then just rip it up and start again, or refactor, or think really hard
about your design. Also, Ted's jumped in with some stuff here. As he's mentioned, the stringent
requirements are merging, so making sure that you don't allow anything to merge. And in fact,
recently there's been a fork of Rosegard, because one of the developers has got a bit annoyed that
he's not getting his stuff reviewed, and it's fair enough, everyone's doing it in their spare time.
It's still a labour of love. Also, I mentioned earlier, refactoring and unit testing. I did
actually manage to get the unit test code coverage the other day on Rosegard, and it's 8%,
which is not good. Okay, there are some challenges with a UI base, whether with a GUI, but it should
be higher than that. So, I imagine one of the things that I might be looking at as I dip my
toe back in a little bit is to maybe write some more tests. So, number one, quality. Number two,
coding is social. I mean, that's one of the things that we don't realise is that we think we go into
OSS, we can just hide maybe online or do some coding by ourselves, but increasingly it becomes
social. It's a different type of social ability maybe to working in an office. But open source,
I believe, is much more social than working in an office, because working in an engineering job,
a software job in an office. Because you can just focus in on the one thing that you're doing. You
don't have to be maybe told that you need to be more interactive in a certain way of working.
But in OSS, you have to be, there is no question about it. You've got to be
able to defend your ideas and maybe persuade other people too.
Also, related to this as well, it's the social side of the customer engagement. It's the
the the fact that you do have customers or end users, however you define them,
and they will have opinions whether you like it or not. So you're putting yourself out there.
Thirdly, and this is something I've come across in the last year or so, this guy called Seth Godin.
He's an American marketing guru and his approach, I really like his approach. He's got a great
podcast called Akimbo, A-K-I-M-B-O, you should check it out. He writes and he speaks really well,
really pithily on lots of subjects about marketing. He's not like a slimy kind of marketing dude,
whatever kind of feel. It's like it speaks to me as an open source person. One of the things,
one of his key phrases is this, people like us do things like this. I think that's what it means to
connect with your audience, to find your audience and to keep connecting with your audience at the
right level. So yeah, we might spend some time arguing about how a UI should be or what how we
should architect this or if we should refactor that. However, it's worth it if we connect with
each other and we connect with our customers well at the same time. And also he talks about audience,
importantly, because you don't need to solve all the problems in the world. All you need to do is
solve a few problems for a few people. Fourthly, use all the tools. So we're just so lucky these
days. We've got all these amazing tools. We've got GitHub, we've got CodeCove, we've got Cloud,
whatever it is, lots of stuff. You know, Sonar Cloud, etc. All these great things that we can use,
Sonar Type. So use them. Use CI, use unit testing, use TDD, use all of the great
engineering advances that we've come up with over the last ten years to make our code better.
And finally, don't take it too seriously. One of the reasons that I got involved in OSS was that
I could do it from what we could do ourselves. You know, we could put our little imprint on the
world or do something fun. And that's the point. It needs to be fun. It needs to be enjoyable.
So when it stops being enjoyable, don't do it anymore. And that is it. Thank you very much.
Any questions?
Are there any questions? Oh, yes, there are.
Please raise your hand. Okay.
Hi. Thank you. I can't wait to give the software a try when I get back out.
I might install it later. But was there any possibility of you playing a bit of music,
maybe? No demo today. I should have said that at the top. All right. Thank you.
Okay. Any other questions?
Okay. Seems it. Thank you very much. A big round of applause.