Hello, you all.
Morning creatures.
Good morning.
We're about to start the talks of the day and I'll leave you with to be as Augsburga,
who will be talking about how open source can leverage more sustainability in the technology.
So welcome, welcome.
Yeah, welcome also from my side.
So I'm actually working in atmospheric science.
So by education I'm an aerospace engineer.
I'm in my day job calibrating satellite instruments for atmospheric science.
But let's say in my private time I do this professional hobby so I'm actually investigating
with some other people how does open source can have a significant impact on environmental
sustainability.
And we created this project within a small community called Prototypes that is actually
investigating multiple ways how to increase the sustainability of our environment with
different open source projects.
And this project was started with a friend of mine and me about two and a half years
ago within a pandemic so we had a lot of time and we realized, okay, there's actually no
overview about what open source really means in environmental sustainability.
And so we started to create a huge list, an awesome list, I think you know what this is,
it actually lists all projects that we can find in this domain.
And quite soon I really joined this project because she did a similar development four
years ago and we were thinking about, okay, we created now this huge list and let's make
a study about this, how can we quantify and how can we also find quantitative ways to
investigate what actually open source means in environmental sustainability.
So I really was actually funded by SUBAC that is Accelerator Program to open up data in
climate.
And after that Josh Hopkins from Open Corridor joined us.
He is interested to integrate multiple of the projects we investigated in a larger software
project also for environmental sustainability.
So what does environmental sustainability in general means?
It is actually the goal to preserve the natural resources that we all depend on for future
generations.
But what does it actually require?
So it requires the intelligent intention to understand, predict and manage the stability
of our natural resources.
And that means that you need to understand that actually we depend on nature and the
natural resources that have been created over a million of years by the nature itself and
the natural earth systems that we see here.
For example, you see on the right hand side an atmospheric simulation by the open source
project called SCREAM.
They are investigating how does the content of water vapor change and how does water vapor
actually change the climate in the future when our earth is heating up.
Because when the earth is heating up more water vapor will be in the atmosphere.
And this is a huge problem because it actually accelerates climate itself because water vapor
is itself a greenhouse gas.
So we see there an actually accelerating process and software is there very important to actually
predict and to understand how this will be in the future.
So the core question of the study and analysis that we did is what enables open source software
and environmental sustainability.
So I think you know that open source is now dominating all software industries worldwide.
And there are studies from synopsis that shows that actually in 79% of the code bases worldwide
you can find open source code.
And they did it because they do security auditing.
And they look into the code and they see okay we find it everywhere and it impacts all our
software that we depend on worldwide.
So what we did in our study is we started with the state.
So what is actually the state of this ecosystem?
And we created multiple insights but we also wanted to derive some principles based on
the multiple projects we investigated and interviews and people we talked to.
But we also wanted to create some visions.
So what are actually opportunities?
What are strategies?
What is the potential that we are missing that actually open source delivers us in environmental
sustainability?
So let's have a look about what are applications of environmental sustainability in open source.
And one very important aspect there is the environmental intelligence.
So you get satellite data all around the world from multiple satellites, from another satellites,
from either satellites.
And most of this especially satellite data that deals with the environment, that is really
looking at the environment is actually open to the public.
And you can process it.
There is a lot of open source tools.
And with this multi-spectra and also with images and with the high spatial resolution
and temporal resolution of those satellites, you can derive multiple aspects of our environment
like the air quality but also how our forest changed and also how noise actually is changing
with our cities.
You can measure but also and that's very important point source emissions.
That means who is actually creating emissions.
And you can directly point it.
This is the company who creates this amount of emissions.
And this is getting more and more an important topic because we have now multiple aspects
that are coming like CO2, taxes and carbon trading where we actually need traceable data
about what is the amount of emissions somebody created.
But on the other side there's also things like biodiversity that you can measure.
Like satellites create images with not just RGB but they have a huge amount of different
colors that they measure.
And if you combine those colors you can actually derive the change of biodiversity of forest
or any living being on the planet.
Another important topic is also the urban vegetation.
So how do we lose our urban vegetation?
And in combination with the heat islands because where we lose our urban vegetation you have
at the same time so it means with climate change it will get very hot in these areas.
But there's also the application directly in our real world technology that we're seeing.
And we found very amazing projects like a complete 50 megawatt wind turbine that was
being released open source.
So that means there's the blueprints, how to build this wind turbine, there's the simulation.
So all the software that actually is needed to design this wind turbine has been open
sourced and in combination with multiple American and European organizations.
But you will also find interesting software libraries that help you to predict where do
you place your photovoltaic and what is the perfect orientation of your photovoltaic in
relation to the sun so that you have the most efficient of those solar panels.
But and there was also a talk about PIPESAR yesterday.
We have now with open source, we have now a complete simulation of the world energy
grid and all those energy systems that are within this huge network of different power
plants but also of the renewables.
And you see here, for example, the power grid of India, how it was simulated with PIPESAR.
So what we actually did is a methodology that from my analysis, nobody did before in open
source in general.
So the first thing we did is we compiled this list and it took me two years and I think
more than 500 hours to investigate all those projects worldwide and we used multiple ways
how to do it and you find it in the study and report that we released some weeks ago.
It was a combination of researching on GitHub, GitLab, searching on different papers, doing
data mining but we also just looked on the stars of different people on GitHub.
So what are the people starring that are working in environmental sustainability?
So this was a huge effort but also the community helped us a lot.
So we had more than 30 volunteers that contributed to the list and helped us to curate this list.
And we really were focusing on projects that were aiming on environmental sustainability
at their core.
And the core idea was to keep the list in a way that it is possible.
So we really tried to list GitHub projects because it, and also GitLab projects are every
kind of repository where people can participate into.
So first step was creating the list and after that we created some scripts to automatically
gather the metadata of all those projects and we created some targeted interviews with
all those domains we investigated.
And the domains actually were derived within the study.
So this is our perspective on this ecosystem and the naming that we use there.
You see here in the middle that's actually the core project open sustainable technology
and around this are the fields and within the fields are different topics that we put
the projects into.
And after that we did a cooperative report and cross-validated actually the qualitative
and quantitative insights that we derived from this investigation.
So here's the overview of the dataset.
And you can see we have in total 1,339 projects.
This was quite some work.
And most of them were actually GitHub projects, some were GitLab projects.
And I must say actually the numbers here are all dealing with the GitHub projects.
We could not integrate so far the GitLab API into the study.
I hope to do this in further studies and also to integrate other platforms.
But to keep it simple, the first study was really focusing on GitHub.
And actually on GitHub we also found most projects.
You see here also that we list here the active project.
So within the study we tried only to list projects that had one closed issue in the
last year that one commit and that are documented and have a certain kind of quality.
So we did a small quality analysis of the project.
Is there some documentation?
Can people actually build the software by their own and use this in their own projects?
This was very important within the investigation.
And yeah, you can see here we derived the total number of stars and the total number
of contributors but also other quantities to just show, give you an impression about
how is the ecosystem in itself, how in this direction does it go.
What you can also see is that we list here some inactive projects.
So actually this was the hard part of the study.
As you maybe know, most open source projects die very soon.
So within the project actually 192 projects actually got inactive.
And this was also my impression when we do this analysis, most projects were really inactive.
I have no clear numbers but I think it's more than 90% of the projects we investigated were
inactive.
They were just academia projects where somebody released the paper and then it's just over.
That's it.
It's like throwing an open source project to the wall and hope somebody maybe can use
it.
But this is not where we want to focus on.
We really wanted to focus on a project that you can use and that you can reintegrate into
newer projects.
So the first thing that I realized when doing this investigation is there's quite a low
popularity in environmental sustainability.
So even if it is a hot topic and you see it multiple times in the media and everybody
is talking about it and yeah, it sounds very trendy, we could just find free projects that
have more than 1,000 stars.
And in total on GitHub you find 38,000 projects that have more than 1,000 stars.
So it's just and that's also what's my impression.
So most people are really not appreciating those climate models or, for example, those
biodiversity models that have been created and that are actually being maintained by
different organizations worldwide.
So on the left-hand side you see actually the color bar that is community health index
that we created.
It's called the development distribution score.
And we realized that actually the most important aspect of an open source project is how much
is the knowledge and the development distributed within the project itself.
So we created just a very small number by the comment that is just we take the number,
the comments of the strongest contributor and divide it by the total comments.
And you get an impression how much does this project actually depend on one developer or
is there actually very community behind it.
And you see the A-B street that is the most popular project is really one man show that's
actually a project where somebody's tried to do a gamification of cities to improve
our transport system to do it more sustainable.
After that it's a very famous project and also it is a for-profit open source project
that is called electricity map.
And after that you see project like open farm or the SCA fund that is actually a green software
project.
And how dealing with different kinds of aspects, how do we investigate and create knowledge
about our environment and how can we improve our society so that we create less impact
on our ecosystem, let's say negative impact.
But you see also there some in popularity some climate models like or let's say earth
science models and frameworks like Pangeo and it's or very models that are actually
also very important like the WRF.
So on the right hand side you see the contributors.
So the total numbers of contributors that we could find within a project and electricity
map there is again the let's say dominant project.
And electricity map is actually a they combine the so-called carbon intensity of all different
electric grids worldwide to give you an impression or give you a number about when I'm consuming
this amount of electricity at this point on the earth how much carbon do I actually release
to the atmosphere by this power consumption.
And this is really let's say one of the very few larger communities that we could found
where a lot of academic and for profits and different organizations were coming together
to create this.
Another project is actually the open food network where people try to create trustable
knowledge and information about how what what is the information of food itself so that
you can have trustworthy information.
And this is also a huge community project quite all.
And you can also see here the screen project very larger atmospheric project.
But in general you see the total numbers of contributors if you compare it with our open
source projects are quite low it's not that big.
And for me personally actually the so this project itself has 1300 stars so we are actually
one of the most popular open source projects in the never meant sustainability and this
is not a good sign but because I'm just we are just some random dudes.
We are we are actually we have no foundation we are just a community and people were coming
together you know and that's what I wanted to show with this slide.
So within the open source community there's a lack for it of popularity in environmental
sustainability.
So if you look at the license and language of projects we see there's a lot of MIT license
actually so it's actually easy to integrate those projects into for profit not that hard.
But there's also let's say a good portion of free open source license like GPL 3.0.
But what we also could find is that with the data analysis we could not always really invest
automatically investigate what is actually the license of the project.
So that's the custom license and this is always problematic so if you release open source
code use a standard license that people know about.
They don't need a lawyer to actually see if they can actually reintegrate the software
into maybe a commercial project because we want to and we need to go with such approaches
into commercial projects if we don't commercialize environmental sustainability we will never
achieve environmental sustainability.
On the right hand side you see the proportions of the programming languages and here we can
see that actually data analysis and data driven languages are really on the top.
I can imagine that you expect Python here but also R is here very prominent because
in environmental sustainability it's a lot of about statistics and processing a lot of
data but we can also find here Fortran and C++ and those languages are used in the large
scale simulation of our earth so if you want to really be efficient in your calculations
that's the programming languages that you use and the high portion actually of Fortran
shows us that many of those software projects are quite old.
This is really sometimes coded as 20, 30 years old where our earth and our atmosphere, biosphere,
hydrosphere has been simulated and this code has been reintegrated into new software projects.
Yeah, another, JavaScript is here not that important so but that's what we also did is
from the we actually derived from the projects all the organizations behind it so what is
actually the namespaces of the projects and from the namespaces of the projects we had
a little bit smaller list and this was actually hand labeled so we went through all those
organizations and created actually the location but also the continent of those organizations
and we see there's let's say Europe has quite a good standing here and also North America
we found a lot of project that considered themselves for organizations that considered
themselves as global so but unfortunately I have to say actually from Asia and I did
a lot of investigations I could not find a lot of open source projects that actually
originate from the Asian continent whereas there really an organization behind it.
It doesn't mean that there are not people involved into this.
I just wanted to say that we could not find it and I did there are a lot of research on
this.
Yes, what we also did is we labeled the forms of organizations behind it so and it was surprising
for me that actually the community based projects like we are the strongest so community we
labeled when there was no legal structure behind it just some people coming together
doing stuff.
This was considered community and after that academia has a very important role there because
they did a lot of this research investigations in our environmental sustainability but also
government agency are very important in this domain.
Unfortunately I have to also to say for profits and that's a general trend are not that prominent.
We did I did a lot of investigations into the kind of do we find actually commercialized
or for profit applications of this kind of software and I told you about electricity
map that's maybe let's say the most one really successful project that we can find but besides
that there's Microsoft is actually doing some good open source project in the environment
sustainability like the planetary compute framework and so there's some other good developments
but compared to the problem that we are dealing with this is a little bit disappointing.
So it cannot be that this is just been an academia community thing with some maybe some
government agencies so there needs to be more for profit organizations and I think we see
this also now with commercial open source software is becoming more and more important
and there's really no billions of dollars going in this kind of development but we're
missing there totally in this domain.
So you can see here this is all project that we mapped scattered over the project age you
see here the topics and they are actually ordered we also created a size score so that
we can order them see the strongest was actually a biosphere but this was also because we not
separated actually biosphere so strongly if you would combine climate data processing
and the climate models actually climate science I would say it in general would be the most
strongest area but also what was quite interesting is that actually hydrosphere so the people
dealing with our water resources they were also very strong we could find a lot of strong
projects there it's all the same for soil it's about air quality it's about agriculture
and nutrition so really that what is really describing the state of our environment there
we know a lot there's a lot of information about what is actually the state where we
are going but if you go more into let's say the technology area if it's if you're talking
about batteries if you're talking about hydrogen bioenergy carbon capture and removal there
it was super hard to find good projects that we could list and also most surprisingly for
me in the area of sustainable investment because sustainable investment is really something
that is started with and there's a lot of huge companies behind it that gather information
that a lot of they have a lot of models and ways how to consider what is actually sustainable
in our investment and there was actually two or three really strong projects but they were
also at the beginning and compared to the problem we are facing this was also a little
bit disappointing other areas like also carbon capture and carbon offsets were also not that
prominent and I would say if you're more interested in the quantities that we created we created
much more about the growth about different kinds of communities and we created a lot
of quantities and plots for you you'll find us in the report so I would stop here to talk
actually about let's say the quantitative analysis and go more into the ins into the
suggestions into the recommendations that we derived from our analysis and from the
interviews and from the people that we talked to and also I must say the discussions we
had within the group lead to a lot of interesting aspects and recommendations so sustainable
rating investment is really getting a huge and important topic and it influenced all of you
because this is where actually your future is going into that means there's actually
the United Nations principles for responsible investment this was created you see here 2006
and decorated some really baseline for what and how do we actually do sustainable investment
and you see here that actually in 2021 we are not talking about 100 around 140 trillions
of dollars that are invested based on those principles so there's a huge amount of money
going in this direction that needs to be because we actually want to transform our economy
to a let's say sustainable system so the problem is that how I was very interested in this
domain and I did a lot of investigations I talked to people about this and we analyzed
how this is done so how it's actually sustainable rating and assessment being done and actually
it is a big black box to summarize it you have some sustainability reports that are
actually self reported by the companies and then are there's a lot of news about sustainability
of companies and a lot of marketing that you know and this is actually being combined and
so-called sustainability assessment and there are multiple companies that are doing this
and there's really not so much known about really how this goes and you see here also
how actually greenwashing works it's very easy you create very beautiful reports that
really look very good nobody's really trace it's really assessing if if they are really
based on science it's really that you do self reporting about your environment sustainability
and then this sustainability assessments also take into account news about those companies
actually so how is there good news about the environmental impact of those companies or
bad news and they also take a financial news about those companies and this is always being
combined in sustainable sustainability assessment and then there comes a magic number and based
on those numbers 140 trillion of dollars are invested somewhere okay that's crazy from
my perspective and I digged it a little bit into this and I realized oh there's a lot
of scientists that realize that actually this is like throwing the dice what this rating
companies are actually doing you see here on the bottom that's actually the value of
the benchmark rating from one company called system analytics and then you see here the
divergence of this ratings and if there would be an ideal world this would be one line okay
they would all agree on environmental sustainability but and actually they do not agree so you
just have to go to the right rating agency and you can make every company actually sustainable
today very easily been done and you also have to see that actually the rating itself has some so
you don't get normally the very bad rating or a very good rating right so in general it is you
just have to throw the dice and also the offer saying addressing ESG rating that means environmental
social governments because this is actually a little bit a combination of different kinds of
ratings they do environmental but also a social sustainability rating and governments rating
the word is requires addressing is derating divergence requires one to understand how the
data that underpins ESG ratings are generated so nobody knows how this data is generated and
I think you know already the solution so when nobody knows our data is generated and we have
a big black box yeah then you normally take open source but it is not happening because people are
also doing the same thing in the so-called carbon offset so if your company is actually creating a
lot of emissions and you want to be carbon neutral and you see this labeled all over the place now
everybody's carbon neutral and it's great that they all actually want to be carbon neutral but
there's actually study being done by the Guardian and they investigated how much of those carbon
that is actually released in the atmosphere is actually been stored back into our soil and into
our ground and you see this on the right hand side is actually the carbon cycle that is driving the
co2 into the atmosphere it is actually a natural let's say there's a natural cycle that actually
is going on and this the cycle was created by actually it took millions of years to stabilize
our atmosphere by this carbon cycle so that we have a low portion of carbon with no atmosphere
and this way a stable weather and stable climate and a predictable earth systems that we all can
depend on but yeah the Guardian found out that the real emissions that are actually stored in
the ground are much lower than actually what they are claiming for so actually they say that over 90%
of those carbon offsets people are claiming for actually claims that's what the Guardians is saying
here but you see another problem Guardian is just showing you a plot and that's actually the core
problem of all of this they just at the end show you a plot and then believe my plot I did great
science behind it just trust my science and that's let's say the core problem I want to
investigate with you a little bit more so because we're talking about here about safety critical
decision-making the we know exactly and I showed you this also with the topics and with the numbers
of people that are investigating we know very good with open science that is traceable for all of you
you can go into this climate models and they're very good examples for in simple Python you can
but you will also find larger climate science and projects that you can just run on your machine and
they all come to the same result that we are actually on a very bad path on with colliding
with the earth actually and this is very clear to us so there's no doubt so if you if you don't
trust into climate science just go into the repositories create an issue or deal with the
software that you find there so opens the problem that we are facing now is that the decision-making
the assessment of sustainable and sustainable investment there we have no clue what we actually
do and there's no open source software and not much open source software that we could really find so
but there's help and especially in the energy sector we found a lot of good projects that that
really understand how to get rid of those problem of traceability because when somebody just is
showing you a plot I think hydrogen will be the future of energy of the energy sector and there
comes somebody else and shows you another plot this cannot really come you cannot really create a
discussion about this and this is really everybody needs to be at least able to discuss about this
right and what they did in in actually in the energy modeling so the this pipes our project
actually I showed you at the beginning they release those models and in this way you can create
proof and show hey I calculated this if you don't agree with me show me your model and if you don't
show me your model I don't trust you that's that's how it goes and this is really let's say a very
important idea that I found here it's that you you need to understand that you can actually prove
how much conclusion has actually been open and traceable you just have to see how much open data
is there and is there uncertainty is actually also in the data that is comes with the data is there
open source models are there is there actually an open execution possible of those models do you
find open results of those executions so it's the artifacts actually create by its simulation is
this actually also open source is there a way to participate can you go into the guitar
repository can you go into a conference and ask the question how you had has he done this and is
this conclusion with uncertainties at the end so is there a plot that shows what is actually my
unknown my uncertainty what or is it just a single number and if it's just a single number
it's a problem and we can propagate the uncertainty is through such a thing and that's very important
for traceability then what we found out that actually openness itself and that's let's say
one of the core findings of the whole study is the indicator for sustainability itself so if you
want to know and it's very important to understand we sometimes don't know today what is actually
sustainable but if there comes somebody and says I personally don't know if I'm really sustainable
but I show you how I calculated why I think I am sustainable this show sustainable intention
and this is what we need today because then you can go into and discussion you can go with people
into some maintenance of code you can improve your own code and that's why actually openness
itself is the core and it's really the key indicator for sustainability itself you see also
despite a picture this was chose the standing on the shores of giants but from my perspective
really describes very good open source in open source or let's say the technology that we built
that is this blind giant and we are standing on the shoulder but we can see father by the giant
but you cannot but the giant itself is blind but we can see much much farther and we can and the
giants get bigger and bigger and we can see and predict the future in a much better way and that's
why open source and actually the math and the models that we create there are so important to
predict the future so one interesting aspect that I found to get rid of this problem is actually
spatial finance it's the idea that we can use those whole earth observation data that we have to
track down companies about their environmental sustainability so does all those software in
earth observation all those open source software and there's a huge amount of open source software
and earth observation can be used by rating agencies and all of us to actually track down
companies on their environmental impact that's not that hard and there's actually an Oxford
group that started the spatial finance and what they started with is they created a map of the
whole fossil fuel industry where you know the whole supply chain so where are they located where is
the fuel supply chain that helps you to on the one side simulate it but also to check satellite
data and track down okay this company has a claim that they're actually sustainable let's have a
look you have suddenly a sensor that is measuring the sustainability and that is needed so here's
my let's say that's how I would actually improve the rating of environmental sustainability and
how we can actually get rid of those problem is to actually integrate earth observation into this
processing chain and very importantly where the assessment happens we need open source code and
that's actually just one from the Linux Foundation one project that is starting to do this but this
is really everything very early stage and then suddenly we can maybe in the future get sustainability
ratings about companies that have some uncertainties but it would be also very great if companies
itself would use open source code to do environmental sustainability rating within the company so for
me personally I would like if ExxonMobil would say we would go open science now or every company
that is goes open science about their own environmental sustainability had would have such a massive
impact on the industry because finally you have the information and data to to to really measure
sustainability within a company because so far this is all the black box for us so yeah I would
like to say that open source is from my perspective the most underestimated climate strategy or climate
action it is there's so much opportunity there that we created a whole list of recommendations
how open source can have a significant impact so actually we were thinking about what could be
follow-up projects and we had so many ideas about follow-up projects that we just were starting to
list them all down as recommendation I think it are more than 50 no I just showed you two of them
in combination actually so and yeah my final words would actually be and that's I think we need to
understand we need to build an operating system for environmental sustainability it is for this
for things like carbon offsets or the rating of the environmental impact of companies you need to
connect all the spheres all those open source projects together to get one to bet get a better
conclusion about what is the state of our environment and that's why and that's I hope
and that's what we hope to start and hope to build in the future is really such kind of an
operating system yeah thank you so much well thank you Tobias for your brain splurging
presentation we have you can type your questions in matrix or you can just raise your hand and I
will bring you the microphone oh gosh okay I lost you in the crowd hands again please
inspiring presentation can you hear me and I absolutely agree that open source is very much
underestimated as source of sustainability and a question can you suggest any ways how can developers
collaborate better so for example I know that there are some gaps in climate modeling in bridging
between climate modeling and energy modeling and it would be very helpful if energy modelers would
know better about climate modelers and vice versa do you have any ideas can you suggest something
to improve this situation can you hear me yeah I think what is really missing is the community
behind it that is cross over the topics actually conference you need somewhere where these people
meet and talk to each other that's what is missing and we realized and that's why we actually would
and also the topic of environmental sustainability is always a side topic in open source conferences
somewhere but we need a conference actually there that's the point where this this connection
between the software projects is starting at the beer in the evening maybe where these people are
connecting they are not really good connected with each other that's why this list is so successful
they could not find each other to be as you mentioned that's a very low for-profit organizations
currently yes but this if they increase we have also the lobbyists problem again because they are
much more trained to get money for their already existing projects do you see some chance that
new open source projects in this scope will also get paid contributors it death is also an opportunity
yes it's not I'm not the biggest fan of commercial open source software I see there's some opportunities
there are good ways bad ways depending on topic and a climate model should maybe not be in a
for-profit but if it is maybe about the rating yeah there should be a company behind it so
sometimes it really depends on the kind of project we are talking about so for example if you if you
want to create a wind turbine right a wind turbine that is open source completely you need a company
that maybe gives you 40 years of maintenance and it needs to be sure that this is maintenance and
miss maybe this is better with a for-profit but depending on the project maybe on with a
nonprofit it's not an easy question what is the right organization for an open source project
it's very complicated