Hello, my name is Kai and I'm going to talk to you about Everest AC and DC electric vehicle
charging with open source software and hardware.
First, a few words about myself.
I have a background in computer science and robotics and I've been working at Parionix
on the Everest project since early 2021.
So how do you actually charge a car?
Most of you that have electric vehicles will probably be familiar with these methods, but
I'm just going to recap them real quick so everybody is on the same baseline here.
You have your basic AC charging when you have a portable charger at home that you just plug
into a wall socket or maybe you even have a wall-mounted charging station that can charge
your car with up to 11 or 22 kilowatts.
In public, you sometimes still see these slow AC chargers where you maybe even have to bring
your own cable.
Just plug that one in, plug into your card and you authorize with an RFID card or maybe
even an app and then charging is properly built to your account.
There's an alternative to that, which I would call the smart AC charging with ISO 1511-8
or maybe even plug and charge, which is a much more secure way of authorizing your charging
session with a backend provider.
What's probably for the crowd at this presentation very interesting in the future is the possibility
to have B-directional AC charging.
Think about vehicle-to-grid, vehicle-to-load scenarios where the car can be used maybe
as a solar battery for your home that you can charge when the sun is shining, when energy
is cheap and then you can use that energy in times where the grid is stressed a little
bit and you want to reduce your demand on the electricity grid and then you might be
able to just discharge your car and use your car as a battery for your home.
Also something that people will be most familiar with is the DC charging using the DIN spec
and the ISO norm again.
These are usually the big highway fast chargers where you can charge with up to like 200,
300 kilowatts.
But there's also smaller units for the home.
Think about like DC-DC solar systems and things like that.
Also here what's probably very exciting for all of you is upcoming like B-directional
DC charging and taking energy back out of the car again.
What is Everest?
It's a complete software stack for EV chargers.
It runs on basically any embedded Linux platform out there.
It is released under the Apache 2.0 license and the aim is to support as many different
hardware platforms as possible.
In this talk we're going to mostly focus on building our own charger with an open hardware
designer that I will present later on.
So some of the features that Everest has, it's built on a very modular architecture
where different modules can do very specific things and then they can communicate over
MQTT with each other.
There is also a graphical setup web interface that you can use to configure different topologies
of chargers.
You can see some examples here on the slides and you can also use the same web interface
to do energy management configuration as well.
Next I'm going to quickly go through the steps that you would have to take to use this graphical
setup interface to configure your own charging station.
First we start with an EVSE manager.
This is a module that owns a charging connector and takes care of the charging logic and the
whole charging session handling and it orchestrates all the other modules access to this one connector.
Now we add a board support package which in this case is the ET driver module which will
handle all the control pilot handling the access to the relays and the reading of for
example the RCD currents.
Now we add an energy manager.
This can be just a very simple configuration, a more advanced one I will show you in a few
slides.
Following that we need an authentication mechanism.
Here we add an authentication manager as well as two token providers that will be able to
authenticate our charging session with.
In the next step we can add some cloud connectivity.
In this example we add an OCPP 1.6 JSON module as well as a power meter via Modbus and a
system module that supports the rebooting and the firmware update of the charging station
via OCPP.
And in the last step we add an API module so that external applications can talk to the
average system and read out some pedametry but also control the charging session.
As I mentioned before you can use the same graphical configuration interface to also
configure the energy management.
You can see a more complex energy distribution tree to be able to load balance multiple charging
stations.
Here we add an energy manager as a root node, add a 22 amp fuse to our grid connection and
then as children of that fuse we can add smaller fuses that then connect to the EVSE managers
underneath it.
And these EVSE managers now have different cars connected with different charging goals
and the energy management system is able to schedule charging via a global optimizer so
that every car gets its, yeah gets the most optimal charging schedule assigned to it.
Everest also comes with software and hardware in the loop simulation facilities and it implements
a lot of protocols that are relevant in the EV charging space at the moment like OCPP
2.6 with 2.0.1 support coming very soon.
We have support for ISO 1511-8AC and DC for the DIN spec for the basic PWM charging.
We also have the possibility to do communication with Modbus devices, think about external
power meters for example and also an API over MQTT where you can get some data about the
charging session to maybe integrate into your home automation system.
Everest itself is written in C++ 17 but there's also language bindings for Python and JavaScript
available so you can write modules in all of these three languages whichever suits your
needs the most.
So let's talk about the basic PWM charging.
The car and the charging station can communicate over the so-called control pilot signal.
This is just a plus minus 12 volt signal where the car can lower the positive part of the
signal by adding load resistors and a diode to specific to lower this voltage to a specific
voltage.
For example, 9 volt signals that the car is connected, 6 volt means that the car actually
wants to charge.
Since the charging station then can use a PWM duty cycle to encode the available current
for the car to draw, this is typically between 6 and 32 amps.
So how do you actually build one of these AC chargers?
The good news is an AC charger is not a complicated battery charger.
This part happens on the on-board charger in the car.
The AC charger is just a smart relay.
So what you typically only need is a power path, so a mains connection, some relays,
an RCD for safety, optionally maybe a power meter if you want to know how far your car
has charged already, plus a microcontroller to interface with this control pilot signal.
If you want to do some more advanced things, Linux port is usually a good idea to have
as well.
I'm now going to talk about our open hardware design that we've released, the Yeti and the
YAG ports.
They are available under this GitHub repository and are released under the CERN open hardware
license version 2 in the permissive flavor.
This hardware design has been developed to be as developer friendly as possible, so it
includes a lot of features, but it's obviously not optimized for cost savings or ease of
manufacturing in mind, but it has a lot of very exciting features so you can build all
kinds of charging stations on top of these designs.
It's been designed in keycard 6 and case design files for 3D printing are also available.
So let's talk about the first of these hardware designs, which is the Yeti power board.
It is a 22 kilowatt AC 3-phase power board.
Here on the low left you can see a block diagram of this power board and on the right some
pictures of the upper and the lower side of the board.
Let's talk about the features that the Yeti board has.
It is capable of doing the control pilot signal generation as well as the control pilot signal
sampling in sync with the PWM signal.
It also has onboard relays for 3-phase power switching with welding detection and a 3-phase
power metering support with up to 8 kilohertz of sampling.
There is the possibility to measure voltages, currents, power frequencies of all phases
plus the neutral.
There's an RCD module integrated which can detect DC ground faults as well as AC faults
and it can output the measured leakage current as telemetry.
There's also a 10-pin connector for a high level board to control the Yeti board over
UART.
This is also then used to connect the Yeti to our YAG high level board design which I
will talk about later.
If you want to use the Yeti as a standalone charger which is totally possible, there's
also an external connector for a small LCD.
You can also add Modbus devices for external power meters.
We have some external GPIOs on this board and the board itself can be powered just by
the 110 or 230 volt mains connection with an internal power supply then which is also
capable of supplying the YAG board.
But you can also connect an external 12-volt supply if you so choose.
This board has also a lot of more features which you can then just look up under this
link.
The Yeti comes with an STM32 microcontroller on board and the firmware for this microcontroller
is also available on our GitHub page.
It's licensed under Apache 2.0 license and the purpose of this microcontroller firmware
is that it can control all the devices on the Yeti board and all the electrical safety
relevant code is encapsulated into that firmware.
On top of that, it also does all of the communication of the Yeti board over the UART using protobuf
with a high-level communication board and then with the Everest software.
How do you use this Yeti board?
You can either use it as a standalone charger or you can use it as a power path for a smart
charger.
You can also configure it to do automatic switching between these modes in case the
higher level Linux board fails for some reason.
You can still continue as a standalone charger.
If you want to use the Yeti board as a standalone charger, it is a complete AC charger for electric
vehicles supporting the basic charging I talked about earlier.
This means it contains the complete charging load trick that you need and a car will charge
immediately when you connect it to the board.
There's also some UART connection that you can use to observe the status of the charging
session and also to have limited control over the charging session such as pausing and resuming
the charging.
This mode is what we call the high-level control mode of the firmware.
But you can also use the Yeti board as a power path for a smart charger.
Here you would then switch it into the so-called low-level control mode just with a UART command
and here you must provide the charging logic externally.
Only the basic state machine remains in the microcontroller which is essential for electrical
safety.
An external board is then capable to set the PWM and duty cycle and is able to read back
the control pilot events.
And this is also the mode that Everest then uses to enable the so-called high-level charging
using ISO 1511-8 or the DeanSpec.
I will now explain what this high-level charging mode is.
It uses a power line communication on top of the control pilot PWM signal.
It literally uses the same wire using the Homeplug GreenFi standard and the following
steps need to be done to create a successful high-level charging session.
First a logical network between the charger and the car is set up using a slack.
Then IPV6 link local addresses are set up on both sides.
The car will then send a UDP broadcast to find the charger and the charger replies with
its IP address and port number.
A TCP TLS connection is then created from the car to the charger and over that the ISO
1511-8 protocol is then spoken, which is encoded in some XML data in a binary XML representation
called XE.
Now I'm going to talk to you about the YAK high-level control board.
Here on the right side you can see a few photos of one of these boards assembled and on the
left side you see a block diagram of this high-level control board.
This is used to run Everest on an embedded Linux system.
Some of the features of this YAK control board is that it can receive a Raspberry Pi Compute
module 4.
This is basically your system where you run your Linux on.
It has a 10-pin connector for a direct connection to the 80 board, a real-time clock with a
backup battery, a power line communications GreenFi modem for doing the high-level charging
communication with the car that I just talked about.
There is also a UART and power connector populated for popular RFID modules and there is also
RS485 Modbus connectivity.
You have a Canbus available, you have Ethernet, wireless LAN, you have Bluetooth, USB ports,
there is even a USB client port to be able to flash the flash storage of the compute
module 4 and of course you have lots of external GPIOs to play with.
Now we have everything that we need to put together a basic but also smart charging station.
From right to left you just need a mains free-phase power-in plug.
You need one of these Yeti power boards.
Plug that in, on the other side you plug in a Type 2 connector to your car.
If you then plug this into your car you are already good to go and you will be able to
charge your electric vehicle with up to 22 kilowatts if the vehicle supports it.
If you want to do some more interesting things like try out some of the smart charging protocols
and maybe develop some interesting solutions on top of that you can add this high level
control board and then just start working on some interesting implementations.
Another exciting project that we are working on right now is a DIY B-directional DC charger.
If you have paid attention over the last couple of minutes you will have noticed that the
YAG board already comes prepared with everything that you would need for proper DC communication
because the DC communication is done over the same control pilot wire using the high
level charging protocols and the only things you really just need to build a proper DC
charger is some power electronics and an isolation monitor and then they are pretty much good
to go.
Obviously this is a lot more complicated and we are still hard at work for creating a good
design here but you can definitely stay tuned for more coming in the spring or summer from
us.
If this was interesting for you here is how you can get involved with the Evers project.
You can check out our code on the GitHub organization.
You can also check out the hardware designs and microcontroller firmware.
We do have a maining list if you want to ask some questions.
There is the project page on the Linux Foundation Energy website.
We do have a quick start guide to help you get started with development and on every
fourth first day of the month there is a technical steering committee meeting where we talk about
what we implemented in the last weeks leading up to this technical steering committee meeting.
It's always being announced via the main list and recordings are made available shortly
after on YouTube.
There is also a weekly developer meeting where you can join Evers developers, ask questions
and start contributing.
This meeting happens every Tuesday between 10 and 11 AM Central European time and the
meeting link for that is sent out by our meetings.
Thank you very much for listening and I'm open to receiving questions now.
Hello, I see there is at least one question right now that if you can purchase these boards
pre-made somewhere right now.
I think not yet at the moment and I also don't know if I want to do too much advertising
here but yeah, I think something will be available at least from our company at some point but
you can also totally build your own here.
So, Niko is asking how many of these boards have been produced or tested yet.
So like a few of our developers have had charging stations based on these boards at their home
for way over a year now.
So they've been tested quite heavily.
I'm charging my own electric vehicle basically every day with a charging station based on
this design here and yeah, so they're already well tested.
Especially if you would want to build a product with these boards, you would have to go through
the certification processes because your designs might differ a bit but yeah, the functionality
wise they've been tested quite heavily.
So Thomas is asking if there are any plans on scaling up production.
Well, I guess that kind of depends on the demand.
Right now this kit is thought of as a basis for development, especially doing like Everest
development but I could imagine if the demand is like crazy high that some scaling up of
production would occur at some point in the future.
See some people typing questions.
ERD Junker asked if the DC will be CCS, yes for now the DC would be based on the CCS connector
but it's just because we're based in Europe and that's the common plug here.
I've heard of some people working on something with Trademo at the moment but I'm not completely
sure what the status there is.
So Thomas is asking if there's already an idea how competitive this could be with regards
to commercial charges.
I guess this also kind of aligns with the next question from Buki that the boards have
a lot of functionality on top so I guess a run would come off as quite an expensive charge
and that's true.
Like I said in the presentation the boards are definitely not designed with cost saving
and as less features that you need to build a charging station in there but it's more
like a development kit that probably costs much more than like off the shelf mass produced
charging station would cost but that's also not really the goal of this board.
It's to enable development and to have as many things to play with as possible like
think of the in the SDR space you have these boards where you also have a lot of features
on them but they're not as cheap as like your typical cheap television receiving stick that
you plug into your laptop.
I see still see some typing going on so maybe there's some more questions coming up.
Yes, as Buki is saying there that's also our feeling that especially he said it is a terrible
shortage of open EVSE kits out there and we think so too there are some projects like
you mentioned but definitely a fully featured project especially with a nice open hardware
design that you can just play around with and integrate into your own designs and maybe
even like strip out half of the functionality that you don't need I think is a good thing
especially if ever is being released under such a permissive license with the Apache
2.0 and the hardware designs themselves being under discern open hardware license this could
definitely open up a lot of possibilities for people to play with their own charging
station hardware.
Please ask if this is targeted more towards commercial vendors or more towards hobbyists.
I personally would say it's targeted towards both groups like of course commercial vendors
for the big DC charging stations you probably don't want to build something like that in
your garage at home but you can use the same software stack and like I mentioned also parts
of the hardware stack for that but for hobbyists as well like if you want to integrate it into
your home automation system or if you want to dig in deeper in communication with the
car especially with the ISO 1511-8 coming up and the bidirectional charging possibilities
that will soon open up to many vehicles out there.
And yes as Marco also mentioned obviously academia is also an interesting part there
so you can imagine yeah like students working on EV charging there and things like that.
All right looks like normal questions.
I will definitely be around for a few more minutes in the public room afterwards and
yeah looking forward to some more questions.