So hello and welcome to my talk about green software engineering and more specifically
about building energy measurement tools and ecosystems around software.
My name is Arna and I work for Green Coding Berlin, which is a company that specializes
in making open source tools for energy aware software measurement.
I would like to take you on a tour today of a concept for a possible future ecosystem
we imagine where energy consumption of software is a first world metric and available for
every developer and user.
So let's have a look at a hypothetical scenario.
So Windows 10 operating system typically comes with a minimum system requirements.
So if you look on the vendors web page, you can see it has a processor that is needed
1 gigahertz, 1 gigabyte of RAM, a particular amount of hard disk space, graphics cards,
etc.
However, what is never given is the power on for instance idle that this operating system
uses on this reference hardware that it apparently already specifies.
So this should be pretty doable, right?
Also something like the desktop activity.
So how much power does it use just to go around in the operating system, opening the file
explorer using the taskbar and stuff like this on the reference system, for instance,
that Microsoft specifies or on a reference system that we or the community specifies.
And imagine then you can make could make informed choices.
So by just saying, hey, I'm looking at Windows 10 and I see that it has 45 watts an idle,
but apparently my computer is mostly an idle.
So it might be more interesting to use Ubuntu, for instance, which has just 20 watts an idle
or desktop activity is even lower.
So why not choose this operating system with energy is my main concern.
And this is what I what I cherish the most in the operating system or which is an important
metric for me.
If you think this process even further, you can think about comparing energy of applications
very specific, not only in the idle scenario or in one scenario, but in very specific usage
scenarios that are ingrained to how people typically use such an application.
What you see here is two radar charts on the left side is WhatsApp and on the right side
is Telegram.
Please keep in mind that these are concept pictures.
So this is not actually the energy that these applications use for this use case.
But let's say your use case is that you message a lot with an app, but you don't do that many
video calls.
So if you look at WhatsApp, you see here that it has quite a high energy budget when it
comes to messaging, whereas Telegram has quite a lower budget.
Telegram is however very bad when it comes to video where WhatsApp could be for instance
better.
If you say that you are mostly doing messaging with your application and you would like to
keep your battery life or maybe use Telegram on the desktop, your desktop energy consumption
low, then with such metrics, you could actually make an informed decision if WhatsApp or Telegram
is the better app for you if energy is an important concern.
And imagine as a developer, if you think even one step further, that you go to GitHub or
to GitLab or wherever your software is hosted and you look in the repository and you see
right away with something like an open energy batch, how we call it internally, to see how
much the software, you see it down here, how much the software is actually using for its
intended use case that the developer of the software had in mind.
So you can compare one software that maybe has very limited use case to another software
or library just by the energy budget because you have the metrics already available.
We actually try to build these tools and I would like to take you in this very short
timeframe that we have been given by Fostem, so just about 20 minutes, I would like you
to take a tour through our projects that we are doing more as an appetizer so you see
what we are working on and what we think could be possible or a possible ecosystem in the
future.
You will be presented with a view that looks like such, so the Green Metrics tool, EcoCI,
Open Energy Badge and Cloud Energy.
So the Green Metrics tool is what I would like to talk about today mostly because I
think it is the tool that outlines our concept of transparency in the software community
the best and then we'll talk about later about our approaches for CI pipelines or restricted
environments like the cloud.
So first of all I think it makes sense, although I know people tend to hate diagrams or flowcharts
to some degree, but I think it makes sense to quickly go over how the concept of the
tool works from a high level perspective.
So in order to measure software we follow the container based approach.
So we assume that your software is already in a containerized format or can be put in
such a format.
So for instance even a Firefox browser if you want to measure desktop applications can
be put in a container and be measured with our tool.
Also machine learning applications, simple command line applications but also web applications.
Typically when you develop software you already have infrastructure files like Docker files,
Docker compose file or even a Kubernetes file available which our tool can consume in all
fairness, Kubernetes is still a work in progress but Docker files it can consume.
And then the tool basically orchestrates the containers and attaches every reporter that
you want in terms of measuring metrics.
So here we are still very similar to typical data logging approaches like Datadog does
it for instance or other big players.
So the memory, the AC power, DC power, the network traffic, CPU percentage, CPU and RAM
is all locked during the execution of what we call a standard usage scenario.
So in the first couple of slides I have shown you the concept of looking at software from
how is it typically used.
And people already have thought about this concept quite a lot when they make end to
end tests with their software because this is a typical flow that a user goes through
in your application or unit tests which might be very reduced amounts of functionality that
is tested in a block or benchmarks that are already inside of the software repository,
session replays, shell scripts, build files that basically measure where we could measure
your build process.
All of this is already available typically and our tool can consume these files, will
run these workflows and then tell you the energy budget over the time of this run in
particular.
This slide is more just if you're not too familiar with Docker the idea is just to have
every service or every component of the application in a separate container so that we can later
on better granularize the metrics and better look at which component might be interesting
to look at if you want to do energy optimizations in particular.
When you use the tool and I will just go quickly over that and then probably go with you through
a live version of what we are hosting at the moment you will get a lot of metrics so you
will obviously get something like the CPU utilization or the average memory that was
used or maybe the network bandwidth that was used but what is interesting for its dashboard
and basically its USB is that you get also the energy metrics from the CPU, from the
memory, you get a calculation what the network has used in energy and you get convoluted
or basically aggregated values where it makes often sense to look at CPU and memory in conjunction
or it makes sense to look at all the metrics that you have available to get something like
a total energy budget.
Then you obviously can look also at the AC so at the wall plaques so not only what is
your CPU and your RAM using but what is the total machine using or something that we have
in our lab as a setup you just look at the mainboard so not on the outside of the PSU
so what is basically plucked in the desktop computer but only the power that flows directly
into the mainboard and here you can see that our tool automatically calculates the CO2
budget based on the energy that it has used for this run.
The tool also shows you which reporters have been used in an overview and then it tells
you a lot of charts so this is a sample chart and what the tool can basically give you is
not only an overview capability but also an introspection where you for instance are interested
in the idle time of the application so what is my application doing when no user is interacting
with it is it actually using energy and is this too much energy for my belief or for
the belief of the community so for instance here we have an example of a setup of a WordPress
setup that we have done with an Apache, a Puppeteer container that runs Chrome and also
a MariaDB instance and you can see here that here are a couple of requests that have been
done to a WordPress instance and then we are basically just idling but still the web service
doing quite some work and there have been no web sockets active so why is there server
and database activity here?
Is this valid?
Is this maybe some caching, some housekeeping or is this unintended behavior?
We picture that our tool could highlight such energy, hotspot or energy malfunctions as
we call them to better understand how software uses energy.
You can also look at energy anomalies so we work sometimes with features like TurboBoost
which is typically not turned on in cloud environments but very often for desktops which
brings a processor in kind of like an overdrive state so that it can react very quickly in
a frequency above its normal frequency.
However, what we have done here in this example we have run a constant CPU utilization but
as you can see here the CPU clocks at different frequency over the time and sometimes it uses
exponentially more energy for the same task so it finishes quicker but it uses more than
only a linear amount more of energy to do the task so this is a very interesting insight
that our tool can for instance deliver when you try for energy optimizations of your software.
So what is the whole idea that we have behind all this project?
And let me move myself down here a little bit so you can see the full slide.
We want to create an open source community or a green software community that focuses
on the transparency of software so that you have basically an interface which we call
the usage scenario where you can measure software against and then ask later on questions against
a database or against an API which has measured all these softwares.
Questions like how much does this software consume?
Is there a more carbon friendly alternative or is there a software that makes less network
requests?
The idea if these softwares are available in your country so YUKA to my knowledge is
for instance from the US and code check is more like a German application is we want
to be the YUKA or the code check of software so we want to deliver answers to developers
where they can ask questions about the energy budgeting of a library of a software or of
a functionality by providing a framework to make these measurements.
So let me move up here again and then back to the slides.
So let me show you our other tools that we believe are needed to build an ecosystem around
green software because software is not only running in desktop environments or is not
only on a single machine it also runs a lot in the clouds where these measurements that
we have and I would like to encourage you to read a bit on what sensors are available
in our tool but where these sensors are not available which is for instance in the cloud.
So let me bring up my browser again.
So if you are on the homepage and here you've seen the green metrics tool that I've just
talked about you also see that we have the cloud energy project and the EECO CI project.
So EECO CI focuses on measuring the energy of software in a continuous integration pipeline
that for instance runs in a virtual machine.
Our focus is currently on GitHub actions.
In order to estimate the energy in a virtual machine because you cannot measure you have
no access to the wall plug in the data center you have no access to sensors and the CPU
or whatever you have to estimate the machine based on measurements that you already have
for the same hardware.
If you click on cloud energy you can see here that we have based our machine learning model
on a research paper from Interact DC and the University of London and they have basically
taken the data from the spec power database which is an open database for servers that
have been measured just with a fixed workload to compare it against each other and based
on this data we can create a machine learning model which is also free and open source to
use that is just a Python tool which you call with the information that you have.
So let's say you have the information that your CPU is from Intel that the frequency
that you're running is 2.6 gigahertz you have 7 gigabytes of RAM and you know the CPU has
24 threads but you don't know any more info you don't know if it's a Skylake processor
or a modern a more modern Intel processor you do you have no more information because
the hypervisor limits this to you so you if you give the model more information it can
give you more accurate estimates but it can also work with the limited information in
the cloud and then it spits out to the standard out the current watch that you have been using
and then you can reuse that in a tool that we build upon that.
So now that you've understood that there is a machine learning model behind the idea I
would like to bring you to EECO CI.
So EECO CI is a GitHub action that is based on the work from the cloud energy project
that can give you in a GitHub action the information of how much a CI pipeline has used in terms
of energy.
So if you go for instance to the GitHub repository you can also go to the marketplace so we go
one step further and here you can see you can directly use it.
It is very easy to use it just needs two calls to initialize a tool and then one more call
whenever you want to get a measurement and what it does for you so let's quickly go to
our repository where we actually use GitHub actions to measure every of our workflows
in the tool so we click on actions let's say we go to manual test run virtual machine we
click on main and you see here I've run this run yesterday it succeeded so our log tells
us hey all tests have to work fine so to run a work point fine and also the API and for
this run in the Azure cloud where GitHub actions runs its virtual machines I have used 650
joules of energy and you get a nice ASCII graph over time we are a bit limited here
in the graphs we can display in the GitHub actions overview but you can see here at what
point in time the energy for instance is the highest and then maybe look at the later tests
if they if you deem them to be more energy consuming then for instance at the start where
it was using only a fixed amount of energy so this gives a developer and also user the
information how much energy is not only the software using but also the development of
the software is it maybe using more than we want as developers or maybe even as a community
and these are our concept tools to just get a first start of what we what we think could
be possible what we think could be possible in a new future where software is basically
measured and the data of the of its usage is constantly published by developers also
the idea is then to have something like an open energy badge that is basically in every
repository that tells you for this software and for this usage scenario that comes with
it so be it for instance running the tests or be it for instance building the containers
or the intended use case of the software so let's say the NumPy library of Python has
an energy badge where it says hey for a 1000 times 1000 matrix multiplication this software
uses this amount of energy on the reference system that we have specified and when you
use the same reference systems to compare software against each other you come to a
scenario that we have basically shown from the starters in the first slides where you
can basically tell is the one software more energy hungry than the other one comparing
the same use case so let me quickly get back to my slide deck so let's wrap up measuring
software energy consumption we believe is still too hard the goal should be easy as
starting a docker container and it should happen transparently therefore we have created
the green matrix tool which can reuse docker files and infrastructure files to make it
very easy to orchestrate your architecture and then in a flow that you already have be
it a puppeteer file or be it just a shell script you can run that with our tool just
as a parameter appended and it will tell you how much energy has been used over this particular
scenario that you feed in measuring software is also very complex so this is what we have
integrated best practices or tool like pausing between measurements letting systems idle
before you actually use them turning functionalities like SGX off looking at if turbo boost is
on and very more features just inline measuring like data dog or other providers are doing
it at the moment we believe is not enough and is too arbitrary to talk about energy
software must be measured against a standard usage case so we provide standard usage cases
for software as an interface but we ask you the community also or we need to see over
time what are the standard usage cases we can all agree on a software must be comparable
to another similar software in terms of energy this is why we need these standard usage cases
to make it comparable this also means it must be measured on reference machines that everybody
has access to that we want to provide for the community as a free service energy metrics
must also be available in restricted environments like the cloud so I've talked about estimation
models that need to be open source and available and for everybody to implement and energy
must be transparent and a first auto metric and order in developing and using software
so people should know before they use software how much energy it is consuming and this is
what we are trying to achieve with the tools we are developing I hope it could pick your
interest in our work and in the tools we are developing some as concepts some already production
ready and I thank you for listening and now I hope it's time for questions