All right, thank you for coming. So I'm Pierre and I'm going to talk to you about Kazarman,
how we tried bridging activity purpose metrics. So we talked about a lot about interoperability
even two years ago. We found it sad that we talked about interoperability for proprietary
platforms not with our alternative decentralized networks. So we tried doing that. Kazarman
is hosted on GitLab. It's using the license Edge GPLv3 and it's done in Elixir. So we've
shown that there was some stuff that hinted at building it. There was some article on
the metrics guide saying that you could bridge two decentralized networks. And there also
was a hackernews comment by Matthew saying that there could be an activity pub bridge.
And there also was a metrics client library made by UHooray that we wanted to use and
also an activity pub client library that was extracted from Playroom R and made by the
MoodleNet people and then by people at Bonfire. So the idea is to bridge those networks by
creating puppet users. So Kazarman is both an activity metrics server. It is an application
service like other bridges and it's also an activity pub server. So we on the activity
pub side we create puppet actors and they can talk to activity pub users. On the metrics
side we create metrics puppet users that can talk to other metrics users. So we wanted
to both build an application service that you can deploy alongside your home server
and also to have a public bridge so that other people on the federated metrics network can
talk to activity pub users even if they don't have Kazarman installed on their server. So
that's what I'm showing here. And we as I said you can also be installed on your home server
and then you have nicely displayed user names for instance just you know one characters
that changed. We made the web front end to help people see the bridged addresses. We
also show here that we can display rooms that we'll talk about later. We started by bridging
the chat that had been implemented by play Roma. It's only a one to one conversation
chat so we use the direct rooms of metrics to do that. We then try to bridge direct messages
like on Mastodon. Those are posts that are only sent to people that are mentioned in
it. So there we used private rooms in metrics. So there are no end to end encryption in
activity pub. So for now Kazarman only works on unencrypted rooms. It could work on encrypted
rooms but then it would just bridge by the encrypted messages. And then we also wanted
to bridge activity pub public activities by creating public rooms where public activities
are just bridged. It was something that wasn't really well sold out because we thought that
it was a good idea to start bridging public activities as soon as activity pub users are
searched for. And so we made a relay actor that started following people quite immediately.
It turned out that the activity pub Fediverse had bad experiences with follow butts as they
say because there were people trying to index the Fediverse. So there were angry people
that started defecrating our staging instance. But there were also nice people who came in
our metrics room and we thought about ways to make it opt-in. For instance by having
the relay bot send a direct message and wait for a positive answer or by having it wait
to be followed to then follow back. Here are an example with a peer-to-peer video where
we can use a reply to have people post comments on the video. We also did something pretty
nice with Mobilizon where you have groups and then we found that we could have people
invite metrics users and it would create a private room and as soon as people joined
the room then there would be members of the group and then you could use the same activity
types for discussions that happen in Mobilizon groups. So as a summary we bridged the user
search, the profile, we bridged multiple activity types, post chat message, video and events.
Activity pub rooms are still to be finished. We also started to build metrics user rooms
so people could ask the relay bot to make a room that their administrator offers as
an ad-book room and then it would publish what they say as a public activity pub activity
so they could be followed and appear on the Fediverse. There's also something to be
thought again about that because on ActivityPub you need to have a way to see the activities
that are sent from the instance when they were sent. So we made a webpage for the activities
that are sent but then there's a thing of also showing replies like that and it's not
something that's really nice to also display activities from other instances so we need
to think about it again. As I said the Mobilizon groups, the private
room has direct messages and the direct room has pre-homes at chat. We have replies, attachments
and mentions. So there is still quite some things to be done but you are welcome to come
and provide feedback or maybe contribute if you would like. I've also shown as it's a
developer room some parts of the application service library that we made in Elixir. So
we just need some configuration like the one on the application service configuration file
and then you can use a nice feature in Elixir like pattern matching to just select the messages
that you want to act on. Here's an example. So just to finish I'd like to thank NGI0 and
Net that funded us and we are in the process of having yellow to sponsor some servers for
our public instance and we've got hints on security by radically open security and then
accessibility by accessibility.nl. We've also started to create an organization to work
on Kazama on other projects that are mostly built on metrics so feel free to come follow
us and maybe support us and I think that's it. Thank you. Are there any questions? Are
there any comments? I'm not so much into social media such as
a video verse but I got the attention that there's much more public conversation going
on than is useful on instant messaging. So if I got a somewhat closed room type in matrix
and there's an interaction here at Bridge to field Kazama, would it mean that the whole
conversation can become a public conversation on a favor side? No it wouldn't. If there are
something that are bridged as public it's only because it's on public rooms and the
other way around too. So if we use private rooms it's only for private messages. It's
the same type of... Yeah absolutely. Thank you. You didn't mention the delete event of
course. I forgot to mention it but we already support the delete event so deletions are bridged
on both sides of networks. Could you talk about the choice of the
next field? Did you think it was a language for this application or just a different language?
It's a language that I love but it's also with the framework Phoenix. It's also a great
language to build HTTP APIs and that's something that we do on both sides of the bridge. So
it worked out pretty well in the end. Another question. Is it already in such a state that
we can just, as you proposed, install it next to our home server and it will just run or
is it still some rough edges? I think it's not yet ready but it's really close. I'd really
love to start by deploying the public bridge so that people can start using it and provide
feedback as a public beta first. So I think it's not yet ready to be deployed on your
own server. Plus the fact that we started to work on the features of the public bridge
means that there are still something that could be bridged that are not supposed to
be bridged on a private bridge. So what's the prospect on end-to-end encryption?
It's very cool that it supports unencrypted stuff but I'm a bit curious on the activity
pop side. Is there anything happening there? I don't really much know. I know that people
have been talking about but I'm not sure what the state of it actually is right now.
Yes. So in terms of bridging, is it being encrypted and non-encrypted in the chance?
Because we said that if you have a private encrypted chat in matrix, it will bridge that
database or whatever you can still read. Yes, absolutely. That's something that I think
is a choice to make. I think that it's also, there are some features that are added if
we add support for unencrypted rooms because it still gets unencrypted on the home servers
and federated on server on matrix but it also could give a false sentiment of security.
So that's something that we really don't know about and still needs to be decided.
Okay. No question or comment? Thank you very much.