Okay, so hello everyone.
My name is Dan.
I'm from CJRACE project.
Thank you for showing up.
I will be pretty fast, so the rest, if you have any questions later, please, and if you
don't understand something, the slides will be available later.
So I'll do just digestive slides, whatever.
So the company itself sitting behind the project, we are located in Germany and with some back
offices in Romania and Albania.
We did both wholesale as well as real-time retail business.
So we understand by now what means a system outage.
CJRACE, it's a real-time enterprise billing suite.
It's pluggable into existing, it's designed to be pluggable into existing infrastructures.
You can accommodate easily new services and new ideas.
So it's not only for telecommunication, built, you can extend it like the new industries,
IOT, electricity, we are going towards energy as well.
So you can build anything you like.
If you want to sell cars, you can just do it.
And it should be non-intrusive into existing setups, so it should not make you change the
way you are doing things.
We are sharing information with your switch, your router, whatever infrastructure you are
using over there.
It's all open source software.
It was made in born actually in 2010 and we published first sources in 2012.
The sources are available on GitHub.
It's all 100% written in Go, one of the early adopters of Go.
And we have nothing in private repositories.
Of course we appreciate community.
It's performance-oriented, three branches, all three supported.
Our customers, they tend to be like all telecommunication, a bit conservative with upgrading.
So test-driven development, again very sensitive to billing and data, and modular architecture.
It's quite feature-rich.
You can find all this information in the internet, so I don't have to market it to you.
This slide is complex a bit, but I wanted to show you because it relates to the subject
in my talk, how to integrate with your existing infrastructure.
So on the left side here, you see quite a number of agents which we support.
This mostly are developed by us.
There are also other agents like OpenSips module which is built in their software.
So you can build very easily and replace any of our agents.
So what you will do in the end, you will send your API calls because CIGIRAID is all about
APIs.
You will send directly to our session module which you can also see it as central point
of entry.
After that, you will reach other modules of ours or subsystems, although they are also
a standalone API server on their own, but you will be using them through our sessions
where we implement easier integration for your stuff.
So how do you do that?
First you have to load the data.
This is data specific, so you have to follow our format into loading your rating, your
accounting data in case of doing prepaid and postpaid.
We have also some extra subsystems data, but you will be mostly focusing on rating and
accounting.
After you are done with building your data, then you have to understand how we support
sessions.
So you can choose all of these steps or only one which is the last one and the most important
session CDR.
So you can do building in real time via sending us various messages, various APIs, or you
can directly send us the end CDR for building it.
So for example, session authorization, you have the opportunity to extract from the billing
engine, maximum session duration, resource authorization, various session properties,
even password you can retrieve it from the engine site.
And you can also do session routing because we also support LCR on our site.
Then sessions start when your session starts, so you tell us start billing in real time
or start debiting in increments.
You can choose the way, for example, the mobile networks, they are using session updates via
diameter so you can implement your own triggers for incremental debits.
Or you can do like we are doing with open source software we support like FreeSwitch,
Camayilio, OpenSips, send us session start and session stop and we will do the magic behind.
And then there will be the session CDR which can be stand alone or can correct the session
information from real time.
So both will work.
And these are some examples of APIs.
So if you want to implement in your own application like your own switching software or your own,
I don't know, WebRTC application, all you have to do is send us this JSON RPC blobs
and we reply you, for example, this one is replying with the, we by the way use nanoseconds,
you can also get back seconds if you want but we want to be very verbose.
So this one will just retrieve the maximum usage of a session.
And the same with initiation, same you send us the information in your events.
This is fully configurable, flexible, so you can add any number of fields inside.
Same session update and terminate.
And in the end the CDR sample and blob, same story, all API driven.
So this was fast.
Thank you.