What is the best way to get your sleep?
The first time, everybody will be tired and wasted.
Then I'm here with a dog with sheets full of text and some really interesting policies
combined with some technical questions.
So that's a nice way to get you all to sleep and not leave you for them anymore.
I'm Winfried Tillanes. I'm a privacy consultant.
I'm also a member of the XMPB Standard Foundation.
And I'm long-term and more and more also at the brink between technology and policy.
So I tend to look at acts from the European Union and things like that.
And this act caught my eye. You may have heard about it because it also has some more news.
It's a digital market act.
And it has some interesting things because the European Commission can designate big companies as gatekeeper.
And you have to think about a meta with WhatsApp and Facebook chat.
You can think about Apple's chat, about Google's chat, Instagram, maybe perhaps Telegram
because it is also quite big user base.
Companies like that might be designated as gatekeepers.
And when you're designated as gatekeeper, there's a process that will be in the second half,
which will be started in the second half of this year.
After you've been designated, you have to open up your chat within three months.
Two years later, you must also open up your group chat.
And four years later, you also must have your video enforced calling opened.
And right now, in the start, it's okay to open it by just publishing an API.
But the European Commission in all its wisdom may decide to draft a standard for interoperability.
And if they do so, then all these, their own API won't surface anymore.
Then you have to follow that standard.
And they also said that standard has to be drafted by European standards organization.
So it has to be the SIN or the ETSI.
Also interesting, they say some more nice things about it because that API or that standard
must have the same security features as their own product of the company.
And it must be neutral, so it must not be crippled in such a way that nobody wants to use it
or that there are some conditions to it that really puts it backwards compared to their own products.
Well, I read this and I had a dash of food.
Because some years ago, the Dutch Ministry of Health had a problem with interoperable security.
So they asked for a standard about yet to make it interoperable and secure.
And they gave that assignment to the NAND that did standardization institute.
And I happened to be chairing the working group, drafting that somewhat.
So I went in all kinds of things and questions and things that happened there.
So I thought why not combine my two experiences of this experience with what the European Commission is aiming at.
And let's have a look on what we are dealing with.
When I think about the European Commission, it's about the question what do you mean by secure?
Fender A says we are secure because we offer the best end-to-end encryption in the world.
Nobody can eavesdrop. This is the most secure solution you have.
Fender B says we monitor all communications and feel all harmful content.
So everybody is safe on this platform.
Well, tell me, let's put your pants.
Would you think A is the most secure one? Would you think B is the most secure one?
Nobody. But even the European Commission is sometimes aiming at security like B.
So there is a big misunderstanding about what do you mean by secure.
And it's kind of difficult to add A to B, isn't it?
And end-to-end encryption does have its drawbacks because both clients must support the same end-to-end protocol.
So you can't have one do end-to-end encryption based on the matrix or OPPGP and the other one on OPPoVispo or something like that.
It must be the same with all the key exchanges and everything.
And spam detection, harmful content detection, we may like it or we may not like it.
It is a thing and it is an important part of the security model of some platforms.
And there's also one interesting thing that I thought about.
Well, nice end-to-end encrypted platform opens up with a nice API.
I can connect to that API. That API is also end-to-end encrypted.
Before it was open, they had their own clients that sent and received the message.
So they knew what was injected into the network.
And it was in such a way that nothing went wrong when it was received by the client.
And now I can write my own client, maybe even a first-in-client or something like that, and inject whatever I want into the network.
So they may even get a security risk because they can't monitor, can't filter out all the nice attacks I inject into the network.
So that might be quite interesting.
And end-to-end encryption may also have intellectual property issues.
When there's some proprietary encryption protocol that the vendor bought a nice license to, like Potsy update,
then they may say, well, here's the API. This is the protocol. And if you want to use it, buy your own license.
Well, that's an interesting business case from Maximilian's bike.
So there's quite a bit of issues of already once being secure.
Oh, that was going too fast.
What's really important here to understand, this is a political decision.
The European Commission may say what they mean with secure and how end-to-end encryption would fit in that picture.
If they don't try to push it to a standardization organization, then it will be mayhem.
And I can tell from my own experience, I can also reveal the standardization project in the Netherlands failed
because they didn't define what they meant by secure.
But we did come up with a standard in the Netherlands.
It was for healthcare, so it is quite a specific use case.
We standardized to secure servers.
So the premise was that when a healthcare organization sets up a certain server or buys a certain size server,
that server was meant for this job and secured in a proper level.
No end-to-end encryption because some of them had a security model that relied on securing the data on the server
and not keeping anything on the client.
And the whole network between the whole healthcare providers would be authorized.
It won't be an open network.
And exactly that last point was where the project was killed because some vendors wanted to have another direction there.
And then the next question is, when you say interoperable, interoperable with VU,
may you publish an API? Is it sufficient to publish an API so clients can connect?
You said, nobody knows. European Commission didn't say anything here.
Maybe when you read the law quite close, this is maybe not exactly what they meant, but they're not really clear about it.
It would also mean that when you write a chat client, it would be interoperable with all vendors,
that it needs to implement all those APIs.
Or is it like we did in healthcare, is this a server-to-server with limited parties?
So a walled garden of some systems that are interoperable with each other.
Or is it really open federation, a server-to-server for whoever sets up a server and connects to it?
No idea. But it's quite hard to start standardization process if you don't have any idea about what's happening here.
And I'm good in time.
Then there are the big questions about functionalities.
Because chat isn't just chat.
When you look at whatever chat client you use, you have all nifty features, starting with slash me,
and then repeating your own nickname up to all kinds of fancy stickers being sent around of emojis you can add to a message and things like that.
There are lots of functionalities that a chat can have.
And certainly when you enter encryption, you can't have the server in between translated or say,
well, I handled this in this way, that must all be done by the clients.
And that means for all of these functionalities, you must make a choice about how you're going to handle it.
Is this an obligatory functionality that must be part of the protocol, that must be implemented then by all clients?
Or is it optional?
And making a functionality optional means that you need to have something like service that's going for me.
Or do you say, no, this is not part of the standard and you don't have to be interoperable for this functionality.
And well, we are talking about what kind of functionalities.
So, big.
Almost. I did leave things out.
Mainly because there were things, for example, like services go for me, certain ways of connecting, how you standardize exactly the connection.
I guess that's in a player and not on the functionality layer you have to choose.
But this is the kind of things you're talking about when you start standardizing this.
And I have a nice time to discuss some of them.
When you look at attaching an emoji to a message, well, you think emoji, that's part of the UTF-8 character set.
So you can just say, this is the message and then put this emoji to it.
But some clients don't support all kind of emojis, either in sending or receiving.
They have only a limited set of emoji you can attach to a message.
And also to get something like that done, you maybe need some services go free to check what emoji are available at a client.
And then you can tell your client these are the emoji you can send.
Or maybe you just send an emoji and notice it doesn't work.
Not really the best way of interoperability.
And then there's also something like, oh, no, that was the wrong one.
I need to tap another one.
So you need to correct that one or delete it from this.
It was inappropriate to do this.
So let's get it out.
So when you start looking at attaching an emoji to a message, it looks like a quite straightforward functionality.
When you start thinking through interoperability context.
Then it might be quite interesting.
Quite a nice thing.
I also like to move notification.
When you send a message to somebody on platform A, that you can get a response back.
No, I'm now somewhere else on a different account on the same platform.
Or maybe on a different account on a totally different platform.
It's a nice one to standardize maybe.
I don't know if all platforms would like that.
And if they'd like to cripple that one or not.
Well, are there some?
One minute?
Yeah.
So is there one other one maybe I should talk about or should we just go straight on to the questions?
So thank you.
So first in the back, that was the first sentence raised.
Something that I maybe missed, when exactly is some party designated as gatekeepers?
As soon as you provide any sort of dead service or some amount of users?
Can you repeat the question for the recording?
The question is when is the party designated as gatekeeper?
There's a whole set of rules.
And it mainly means that you have a big market share, a big turnover on it, one way or the other,
either on advertising or on just paying customers.
And it looks really like the list I mentioned at the beginning will be the list that will be designated and others not.
But you really have to be very large and be one of the biggest players in the field to get that nice status.
You mentioned that the Dutch initiative failed because what was meant with security was not defined.
But why didn't somebody in the group say, okay, we're going to define security like this and go ahead?
Well, I did.
Oh, yeah, I said you'd be. So the question is why didn't somebody in the group define security and just go ahead?
Well, I did. And that was exactly the moment that it failed.
That is a lesson in it.
The issue was really from commercial perspective. There are some vendors on the table that had different reasons to say, well, I don't want this definition of secure.
And they made big mess. I got really I wasn't really prepared for that meeting that I really was totally furthered by one vendor.
There was all kind of confusion raised in the group.
And then we needed to do some new cycles about what's how to get out of this.
And that was the moment that the government said, well, this takes too long.
We're gone. Well, this part of the problem was they didn't define what secure is.
So a lesson learned. And I think it's a very good question because we should do the same trick of the be careful for the same issue and maybe be clear to the European Commission.
Tell us what you mean by secure. We can't standardize if you don't tell us.
I saw two fingers there or probably basically saying so.
So my question was, did somebody ask and he said the problem with asking is that they might actually tell you and they might actually tell you at least if they don't tell you we can dream a little bit that it might be a.
The point is in most standardization situations, you have a bunch of vendors who are intrinsic transiently motivated to cooperate and to work together.
And then they can discuss nicely about the good questions standardization like this is with vendors.
We don't want to. And that's a big also big issue when he pushes to a standardization organization because they're not up to it.
But if you're sitting there with vendors, we don't want to. They will blow up the process.
So the only way to avoid it is to make sure that somebody sets the limits makes clear.
You have to do it this way and otherwise you can leave the table, but you will still have a stand that you have to adhere to.
Sorry, guys, for time.
I switch.
Yeah.
I would go to the old age and be a terrible question.