Okay, I'll start because the 10 minutes apply to me as well even though I wear this nice
blue shirt.
So please sit down and I'll start right away.
So I'll be talking about social audio applications that you may want to re-implement with Janus.
If you want quick slides about me, nobody cares.
What is social audio?
It's basically whenever you have something that is primarily audio and not strictly video
as part of their form of communication.
So whether it is messages or podcasts or virtual audio rooms or stuff like that, you may have
heard about stuff like Clubhouse, Twitter Spaces, Reddy Talk.
They are all examples of social audio.
So people talking with each other, maybe they take turns and then they broadcast to a very
large audience.
And of course it does seem like a very good fit for WebRTC, especially for the real-time
kind of participation.
And you didn't hear about me because I don't know if there is any secrets about that, but
actually Twitter Spaces uses Janus for the live part and then they distribute it somehow
else.
And how do they usually work?
So as I said, they are typically live conversations.
So you have a limited number of people that talk to each other, exchange ideas, they take
turns.
So it's not always the same people talking for two hours like a podcast, for instance.
And then you may have possibly thousands of attendees, like for instance, anytime Elon
Musk speaks in a Twitter Space, there's a million of people listening, let's say, things
like that.
And there are of course different challenges to tackle because for the live conversation
part it needs of course to be real-time because it needs to be something that happens as fast
as possible.
For the distribution to the audience, you may want a bit of latency maybe okay and this
is why for instance they take advantage of CDNs or stuff like that most of the times.
But of course there's a problem that of course the more latency you have for the audience,
if somebody from the audience needs to come into the conversation there may be a bit of
latency there.
And so that's something that needs to be taken into account.
And so you may want to use WebRTC for everything but then there's scalability issues at play
there.
And so I wanted to check whether or not Janus, which is the WebRTC server that I work on
for a living, could be used for the job.
And I came up with a few potential ideas.
And one of those may be relying on the audio bridge plugin.
The audio bridge is basically an audio mixer that lives within Janus.
So you have multiple people connected to the audio bridge plugin.
They create a single pair connection that the audio bridge mixes all the audio streams
so that you send one stream, you receive one stream that contains the audio of everybody
involved except you.
Which is really nice because for instance it's easy to bring C pinpoints in if you want
using the plain RTP functionality.
You can play jingles for instance you have your own show, your own context that you want
to play something in there or maybe as an iPad from another conversation.
If you do stereo mixing which you support you can use spatial positioning of participants
to make it easier to understand for people.
And of course this takes care of the live conversation but we want to make it available
to other people as well so to a wider audience.
And so what you can do is take advantage of RTP for worders which is basically an easy
way by which the audio bridge plugin sends a plain RTP stream towards an address that
you specify containing the mix that is being mixed there.
And the nice feature in the audio bridge plugin is that you can also tag participants so that
you may say don't send me a mix of all participants but only the ones that I tag in a specific
group.
For instance this one may be a technician so those two need to hear the technician who
gives tips but all the attendees only need to hear those two.
That's basically the main idea.
And of course whatever happens in here is basically handling a mixed stream.
So there may be a script here that sends this mix to Icecast to make a very simple example
or to YouTube Live for audio or to whatever platform you want to use as a CDN for distributing
the audio if it's not WebRTC.
If you want to use WebRTC you can use something like this.
So you have your active participants connected to the audio bridge they are talking to each
other.
You're RTP for word to the streaming plugin which is the plugin in Janus that takes care
of broadcasting RTP to a wider audience.
And then the streaming plugin is what distributes the audio which is the greatest advantage
that you don't have to perform specific mixing for these participants.
They are already receiving a mix of the stream.
All people connected to the audio bridge instead have a dedicated context for mixing because
they need to receive everybody except them.
So it's not the same audio for all of them.
And whenever you want somebody from the listeners to join in the conversation they mute the
streaming parts.
When they join the audio bridge temporarily they become active participants that everybody
else can listen to because they are now mixed in the audio bridge.
And of course for scalability purposes you can just RTP for word to multiple streaming
plugin instances on multiple different instances of Janus.
How you distribute it is entirely up to you.
You can use a tree based distribution however you want.
And you can also take advantage maybe of Multicast because of course if it's just a plain RTP
stream that you are for wording if you for word it on a Multicast group then multiple
Janus instances can all pull from that Multicast group that same mix of audio and can distribute
it more efficiently.
And one added value is that using this approach if you want you can also do something like
interpreter services.
You have two different audio bridge rooms for different rooms.
You have the speaker join the room of their language and you have an interpreter on the
other room.
And then you distribute those two streams separately and then you allow the audience
to listen maybe to the English channel or the French channel and depending on the language
you will speak in you will hear the translator or the actual speaker on either one.
So which makes little sense for an actual social audio application if we want it's maybe
more for a conversational scenario but it's still a good side effect of that.
If instead you don't want to mix in Janus for a few reasons because you don't want to
terminate audio there mixing a CPU intensive or whatever you may want to use the SFU approach
instead which means that participants in the conversation now need to establish maybe one
single peer connection not necessarily more than one but they are exchanging multiple
audio streams.
So they are sending their own and they are receiving as many as there are other participants
in the room.
And you can still externalize this conversation via RTP for worders as before but now audio
is not mixed so you have different audio streams for each of the participants there.
So if you have three participants in the conversation each of them is sending one and receiving
two and you have a separate component that is receiving the three different audio streams
from the different participants.
And so if you want to distribute something via regular CDN that requires a single audio
stream to distribute.
And so that component receiving RTP for worders needs to act a bit like a mixer acting live
basically.
So and once this happens so once you have a mix there everything is pretty much as the
example as I made before you have a mixed stream you can distribute it via CDN or via
Janus as we said before if you don't want to mix for the attendee as well you want something
closer to a regular webinar or something like this.
You can still do that but then you have to take do you have to use that approach that
I was talking about for wording to the streaming plugin for each of the different participants.
And so something like you have the presenter set contributing audio to the video room this
becomes an audio broadcast for that specific presenter in the streaming plugin and people
listen to that participant over there.
You can again involve multiple streaming plugin instances if needed so that you can widen
the audience if you want.
But again if you have multiple participants speaking you have to do the same for each
of them because otherwise of course since the audio is not mixed you would only listen
to one single participant which means that the audience need to create subscriptions
for more than one participant at any given time and of course you have to make this dynamic
in case there's presenters that come and go basically which is what is expected in a social
audio kind of application.
Which means that it's probably easier to do something like this where you still do some
sort of you keep the audio conversation using an SFU for WebRTC participant because it gives
a better audio quality between each of them maybe but then for distributing the conversation
it's okay to mix it and so even mix it for WebRTC usage so that you distribute a single
audio stream instead which makes which makes sense.
But again if you want to do that that works for instance this is what we do for our virtual
event platform for meetings so that definitely works anyway and again you can also do this
sort of multicast distribution if you want to take advantage of a wider distribution
of the media.
And if I spoke too fast which is very likely I did write a blog post about this which goes
a bit more in detail and explains things a bit more precisely than I did right now and
I think I managed to stay on time and these are some references so you can find me on
Mastodon mainly I'm still on Twitter but who knows for how long and that's the blog post
that I was mentioning before so that's all thank you.
Okay there's time maybe for one or two questions if anybody is curious so I don't know if you
have any.
Okay.
So any ability to do like energy level like to say which user are more important or less
important when you are making the mix in this region.
Not specifically in the audio bridge but this is something that you can enforce at the application
level if you want so for instance you may decide that some users always need to be there
and some users so for instance you may have the concept of the actual presenters and panelists
that come and go for instance this is more of an application level context than the mixing
context as far as mixing is concerned you just mix.
Yeah exactly so any other question or can we move to Sagu?
Okay then.
Thank you very much.