Well, alright. I'll get going since we're here. My name is Saul and today I'd like to
talk to you about our little project P10K or how to get 10,000 participants into a
GTSI meeting. I...
Sorry? My voice?
No, it doesn't go on the loudspeakers. It's just for the recording. It is, but it is.
Sorry, I lost my voice. I'll try. I suppose most of you know what it is, but for those
who don't, it's a WebRTC compatible video conferencing application. I'd like to say
that I can think of it in three ways. A set of open source projects that allow you to
either deploy it or, you know, piecemeal it and build something with it. It's also a set
of APIs and mobile SDKs so you can embed it into your existing application and it's fully
open source Apache 2 license and we have a pretty vibrant community that helps us build
some stuff. So I've talked about scaling GTSI meet a couple of years ago here at FOSDEM
with what we did during the pandemic. Also at ComCom about how we reached 500 participants.
But then of course somebody will ask, how do you do more, right? So that's what I'm
about to go on today. A quick TLDR on what the trick is to scale up is mostly to cheat
because it turns out that you never see 10,000 participants at the same time. So you need
to paginate and not show all of them at the same time, not load them at the same time.
Also on the back end, you don't want to be, you know, taking care of 10,000 things at
once. You want to be really careful avoiding re-renders on the React side of things, so
on your front end. You definitely don't want to have 10,000 things. And very importantly,
reducing the signaling. And this is kind of the crux of the thing. So with all of those
things we ended up getting 500 participants in a single meeting. All of them are fully
functional bidirectional audio video participants. They will never all have video on, so that's
sort of fine.
I'm going to go a quick run through our architecture. So when we dive into XMPP, we know what we're
talking about. XMPP is our core signal protocol. You heard it from Matt for chat. So all the
participants joined an XMPP muck, so a group chat. And then our focus, Jekofo negotiates
a session with each participant. And then they all end up mixed in the JVP, which is
where we allocate the media. So this is like a back of a napkin design level, but it's
pretty accurate. Prosthodies are XMPP server of choice. And Jekofo is the one that will
allocate sessions here and then establish sessions with the users. So they all end up
having this connection.
Now how do you go about solving 10,000 participants? Well, first of all, we do some research. And
what we knew is that presence is Tansa. So XMPP presence was our Achilles heel. So we
needed to sort that out. And intuitively, when you need to support many of something,
you think of, well, I'll partition it in smaller chunks, and maybe that's how I do it. So there
is federated muck for that. So we thought maybe that's where it goes. And turns out
the military had sort of researched this problem as well. And there is this cool white paper
called Federated Multi-User Chat for military deployments. And one of the things they got
there is how to avoid these presence flooding. And they do that with the visitor role. And
that's where we got the idea from. So the idea is that we're going to have two types
of users, the active users and passive users. And we don't need to know about all these
passive users. All these audience, we just need to know the number. We don't need to
draw a tile for them. They don't need to be as apparent that they're participating in
the meeting. They're just viewers. And this is what the visitor role in XMPP muck lingo
means. So a passive participant can then become an active participant by switching the role.
Because we're not building live streaming. So what we want to build is a way to actually
actively be able to participate. Anybody of those 10,000 participants should be able to
take the mic anytime. Scenarios for this, earnings calls on publicly traded companies,
just because we can, you name it. So step two, how do we test it? Because if we build
it, we need to be able to know we have accomplished our goal. And in order to test 10,000 participants,
you need, well, 10,000 participants. So we use a big-ass lineum grid. And we created
some lightweight clients so that we could have a lot of chumps to join the call. They've
got no UI. We spawn multiple browser windows with multiple tabs with multiple of these
clients. And a recent trick is we use insertable streams to drop all media. One thing you can
do is modify it. And another thing you can do is drop it. So they say nothing. And then
they are a lot more lightweight than our Selenium grid. Otherwise, it would take millions just
to test if what you're doing is right. There's a PR by Philip Hanke actually to do something
like Chrome would say, black frames, very tiny ones. So maybe that's where we go in
the future as well. And we also delay track creation so that we don't create tracks. If
you join muted, we don't need to do the whole create a video track that is useless and things
like this. And the next thing is we scale the signaling. And the way we do it is we
ended up having multiple prosody servers. This is one node, but it could be spread to
multiple nodes. So we have the main prosody server, which is where the active participants
join the meeting. And then we have up to five extra nodes which we call visitor nodes, where
people join in this visitor role. So the presence is not broadcasted. Jikofo will decide which
one you join, usually depending on the capacity. And the trick to actually become an active
participant is to just join this one, join the main one afterwards. And we can do that
very fast because you don't need to recreate the XMPP connection. So now in order to establish
this sort of mesh, we ended up using Federation, even though it's like within a single server,
but still. So there's server to server bidirectional connections to avoid having duplicated connections.
So custom modules, that's where prosody shines because it allows us to do all these customizations
to mirror chat messages that have been typed in a visitor node to the main node and back.
So to kind of fake it that they are in separate instances actually. And as I said, becoming
active is fast because you don't need to recreate the XMPP connection, just you need to join
a different MOOC. Our step number four is to have an improved topology for media routing.
Currently we have Octo, which allows us to spread the load across multiple bridges. But
this doesn't work very well for such a large load. You need like a tree style topology
where some people are just receiving and a full mesh for those who are actively participating.
So both loads can be spread. And last, we need to fix up the UI, let's say. So we don't
need to render the visitors. We just need to know that there is, you know, 100 people
and then 9,000 visitors. And that's it. So we want to refine the UI a little bit. We're
thinking of using like the raised hand functionality to become an active participant. So you raise
your hand, you are approved and then you become active. That's how we're thinking about it.
Now some of it is in the present, some of it is in the future. So how is it going? We
got there with 51 bridges. We got 10,009 participants. So it worked out. There's still some work
to do. So the UI is not yet final. We're polishing up a little bit. And we're still
need to add some more modules to mirror all the data we want, like the polls and other
stuff. And we're thinking that maybe we don't really need to support 500 active participants
because that's a weird conference, really. So that number could actually be lower or
pretty much configurable. So you can say, I want this very many active participants and
the rest, it will be visitors. And that's that. And of course, we need to make it easy
to deploy for everyone. Right now, this is a bit held together with Duct Tape. Before
I go, I'd like to give a shout out to the heroes that worked on the gaps of this. You
may know their names from our community. Boy is Demento and Jonathan. Incredible characters.
And I'm relaying the message. I know the words, but they did the work. And I'd like to share
the love we have for Prosody. We wouldn't have been able to do it, I think, without
such a flexible piece of software. They help us. We help them. It's a very nice relationship
we have with the project. We love Matt and team. So shout out to them. And since that's
all I got, you can follow the progress there. We have documentation actually how to deploy
the existing way of doing things. Again, early stages, but it's there. And if you have any
questions, well, I'm around here. Or find me online. Thank you very much.