Okay, we can start. Thank you for attempting to this meeting, which is about Linfon and
video conferencing. My name is Jean Monier. I'm involved in the Linfon project since 2010.
And I'm also part of the company which is backing the Linfon project since 10 years
almost. So first, I'm going to provide you with a quick introduction on Linfon. And then
I have a couple of words around video conferencing with SIP, followed by an introduction on the
selecting forwarding unit, which is the art of the modern video conferencing systems. And later,
to talk about what is required on the SIP client part to be able to interrupt with this kind of
video conferencing system. And finally, the conclusion. Okay, so just a couple of words
about Linfon. Linfon is a voice over IP client implementing the SIP protocol, which started in
early 2000. It's available on Linux, Android, iOS, Windows, and Mac. It uses SIP as the base
standard for almost everything, including audio, video call, and instant messaging presence.
Everything which is required for real-time communication. And it also provides some end-to-end
encryption for messaging based on the signal protocol more or less. The Linfon team developed
the Linfon software, but also SIP rover, which is basically a SIP proxy. And if you want to use
SIP account, it's possible to create them on our website for testing purpose mainly. Okay,
video conferencing with SIP in a couple of words. It's around a couple of standards. The first one
is SIP, basic SIP with invite, refer, and buy to create conference, join the conference to be
able to invite other participants to the conference. And it's almost based on the RFC 4579, which
defines how to create the conference and how to join the conference. And there is also some
interesting standard, which is the RFC 5366, which is about defining the list of the participants of
the conference. So it's for the establishment of the conference. And the next important standard
is what we call the conferencing events package, which is based on the subscribe notify RFC. And
the idea is that when a participant joined the conference, it initiates SIP subscribe to the
server and the server then notified to every participant of the conference, which are the
states of the conference within who is going to join is their audio, video, everything which
is related to the status of the conference. On the media port is regular RTP. And for this video
conferencing project, we added the support of two important RFC, which are about bundling all the
media stream into the same socket in order to avoid to have too many RTP sockets, RTP stream per
supply. And regarding the security, it's a regular CPTLS for the for the signaling and for the media
path. It's either SDS where the symmetric key is set in the SDP or the RTP or even SRTPDTLS. And
for the RTP itself, it's a standard AES. Okay, now let's introduce what the selected forwarding
units. And I'm going to start with the description on what we used to have for conferencing server.
So in the past, the media mixer received the video from every user, decode the video stream,
perform the mixing, it could be mosaic or any layout, and then re-encode all the stream to be
sent to every participant. This kind of software exists since 30 years, maybe 20. Here I just want
to show you a page that I saw in the RFC 7667, which is about the RTP topology of
the
RTP stream, which come from the media server to each client and its server side that everything
is decoded, mixed and sent back to client. The advantage of this approach was that it
was very simple from the client side as the calling a conferencing server was almost the
same as calling a regular user agent. The drawbacks of this approach was that video layout was
defined server side, so you could have one or two different layouts. It requires a lot
of CPU resources server side as every video stream has to be decoded and then re-encoded.
The end-to-end encryption was not possible due to the fact that video was decoded. Now
if we go to the selecting forwarding units, the idea is that the media server is no more
decoding and then encoding every video stream, but is more switching video coming from every
device to every other device. It could be done depending on several policies like active
speaker or mosaic. For that, we also need some information coming from each client like
the volume of the audio stream in order to be able to know who is talking without having
to decode the audio stream as well. If I go to the same schema, still from the
RFC 7667, now you can see that from the RTP standpoint, you still have one RTP stream
for each client going to the media server, but now you have also one incoming video stream
per participant of the conference. If we follow the audio, the video stream from the client
A, you can see that it is copied to client B, but as well to client F. It's no more a
media mixer, but a switching matrix more or less. What are the advantages of this architecture
is that video layout is no more defined server side, but the client can decide where to display
every participant of the conference. It's an application choice, no more a server choice.
It scales very well as there are no resources which are used server side to decode or encode
the video stream. Finally, it's opened the door for end-to-end encryption as the media
server no more has to know the content of video stream.
The drawback of this approach is that it requires the client to be able to manage the stream,
which was not the case for standard one-to-one calls. For the CPU's agent, what we had to
change are the following mainly. It's mainly about multi-stream requirements. In the past,
the C client was able to send one audio stream plus one video stream. Now, it requires the
client to be able to send one, but most of the time two video streams, one for high resolution
video and another second one for thumbnail, as well as being able to receive one video
stream per participant of the video conference.
Just an example of the SDP to show what is involved. So, bundle mode, as I said, which
is required, RTP mux as well, is to limit the number of sockets used for the media.
This extension is related to audio level in order to be able to display who is talking
and also for the server to be able to select which video stream is talking. It still uses
IC to be able to limit the usage of media release. From the video part, what you can
see is that there are two video streams in the receiver only, one for the high resolution
of the camera and another for the thumbnail. So, it means that we encode two times the
video. It could be replaced by some video encoder like H.264 AVC, which supports the
multi-layer functionality. But if you want to be able to do that with a simple VP8, it's
better to encode two times the video.
And for the receiving side, there is one video stream because in this example, there is only
one participant in the video conference. But this part would be multiplied by the number
of participants of the conference.
Okay, so this is for what we have done on the LinFone project for this feature. It could
be tested with the Flexi SIPsurf, SIPsurf, which is currently running on our infrastructure.
So you can create a video conference thanks to this Conference Factory CPU-RI. And using
LinFone client with version above 5.0, it's possible to join a video conference. Okay,
thank you.
Conclusion.
Okay, so now LinFone is capable of joining video conference into modes, modes like an
active speaker using a selective forwarding unit, which allows us to scale. Possible evolution
that we have in mind is to implement the XCON Conferencing Server in order to be able to
manage conference from a website or to have something more advanced. We are also thinking
about adding end-to-end encryption to this video conferencing server and why not to provide
a compatibility with WebRTC, knowing that the media protocol that we use are very close
than WebRTC.
Useful link if you want to have more information about this work, you can go to the LinFone
website and to have a look on our GitHub. That's it if you have a question. Thank you.
Are you aware of any other SIP client that implements multi-party video with SoundCloud?
Not yet, because the work to move from a regular SIP phone with only supporting one audio stream
and one video stream to support this multi-stream is very significant and I'm not aware of any
work in progress so far. So if you want to use it, you have to go with LinFone, even
if it's fully standardized, if we are following SoundCloud.
Thank you.
Not yet, but we are quite confident that it's going to scale as we have removed all the
needs for audio or video encoding server-sign. So it's really about switching of packets.
Maybe the question might be around the network on the client side.
One network on the client side, we are sending two resolutions from the client, high resolution
and low resolution. In the case of active speaker, we only send back to every client
the high resolution of the people who is currently talking and low resolution of every other
participant. So it highly limited the needs of bandwidth.
On the client side, you now decode more than one stream?
Correct.
Do the codes support this?
It's almost the same answer. We decode one high resolution and many low resolution and
the CPU resources depend on the resolution of the video that you have to decode.
One quick question about the SDP that you showed before. So there were two receive-only
streams for the client. Was that from the client perspective?
It was from the server.
Okay, yeah, because it looks like the client.
My bad. So the server received two videos from the
client, one in high resolution and one in low resolution and sent one video to this
client as there is only one participant in this conference.
From the client perspective, when you switch from big resolution to low resolution, you
still use the same M line that you have on the board for two send to the client.
Yes, exactly.
Okay, thank you very much.