I'm here, thanks. Yes, hello, good morning and nice day for Fostem. Hope you had a nice
evening. Yes, let's start with the talk matrix RTC matrix beyond instant messaging. Let's
get that. So first of all, what is matrix? Maybe we have some redundancy a little bit
here but for the sake of the recording I might repeat some of what Matthew already showed
us. So basically the idea is an open and federated secure and decentralized real-time communication
network and the use cases are many fold. So the obvious one is of course an interoperable chat
but we are also aiming for voice over IP applications or even VR applications but
you can also think of something like IoT data. And this is, so most of those use cases you're
quite familiar with and what's the well-known event layer. So for chat for instance you have a store
and forward semantics. However, the cool thing about matrix is that it is constructed such a way
that it is decentralized, it is federated and what's for me pretty cool and important is it's
replicated and end-to-end encrypted. So for instance if you're a client and one of those hosts here
and you're attaching to one home server and you're joining a room from another home server,
at that moment the room's replicated and everything is end-to-end encrypted. This is pretty cool.
It's like a git clone, something like that, similar with an automatically
synchronization mechanism on top of it. I'm quite sure that you're very familiar with it.
You could also summarize that matrix is a distributed real-time database and I can
recommend this talk here from my colleague Andy. It's a very nice overview of the specifics here.
On the other side, this talk today is about matrix RTC and now what is the definition of matrix RTC?
What's it? So basically it's the world first decentralized federated real-time channel or
communication platform and it's backed in MSC 341 and MSC 3898 and it's depicted here what basically
the idea is. From a client perspective you have a peer-to-peer semantics and we don't have a store
or persistency in it but you can exchange data with a low latency and a low jitter from one
client to the other. Another interesting thing here is that the business logic is owned by the
clients. In most recent RTC platforms or video conferencing platforms you have something like
an SFU and an application server and here the idea really is the business logic is
in the clients. Let's have a look at some use cases. So the most obvious of course is video
conferencing. This is what everybody would assume when you talk about RTC. But we can also have the
embedded version here so let's just take a normal matrix client and put a widget into it and then
have audio video conferencing or go to the VR world or the matrix interpretation of the meta
words which is called third room. Everything can be realized using matrix RTC.
And the cool thing here is that you can also think about a hybrid use case. So for instance
imagine we have a whiteboard like we have this here. So we can use for fast UX the matrix RTC
layer such when I make a stroke now that it's more or less immediately at the other whiteboards
but for persistency we can just use the room, the distributed database.
So what are the base building blocks which we use to create matrix RTC? So first of all of course
we need something like a real-time communication framework and the obvious choice at the current
point in time is web RTC because it has a quite good adoption. It's in all the web browsers and
there are a lot of a lot of SDKs around we can use but going forward maybe you can also think
something like web transport or web codecs to replace it. So we are not mandating web RTC but
for the time being that is of course the framework to use. Then for the signaling that's quite
obvious that we use matrix for iterates and then to make it scale you might optionally also want to
use a back-end component, a focus. This could either be an MCU or an SFU.
So now as I stated the back-end component is optional. Let's have a look on start
matrix RTC without an back-end component. So having a look at the connection models.
So the obvious and the simplest one to start with is peer-to-peer right? That's just easy. You create
a peer connection and then you have a data layer and then you can play around with matrix RTC.
It's getting a little bit more complicated if you want to have an RTC session with more than two
people so then we spin up a full mesh and then it really depends on the use case how many people
can join. If you have a look maybe at the use case of a video conference then you would need to
distribute N minus one media uplinks and downlinks which is then limited by your internet connection
and if you have at least in Germany an average DSL connection it would scale to up to five to eight
participants. This is something we are currently using in Element Call. So Element Call at the
current point in time is based on this full mesh setup or was we have some news today.
The vision which also really scales and would allow a large scale RTC sessions is what we call
cascaded selective forwarding units and it's depicted here. So what you would have, you would
have a selective forwarding unit alongside with your home server. It's optional but you can have
it and by this we then would allow further scaling and can really, using the cascading concept
to dynamically crawl to any size. We have to test it but that's the theory so far.
The signaling here of course is also carried out over matrix and for the specifics for the SFU
we have this MSC3898 which handles then all the magic of the cascading and so on and so forth.
From a setup perspective if you want to scale large network and large RTC network the idea is
that you place the SFUs as close as you can to your customers or to your clients
and to ensure a proper internet. So this ensures a proper internet connection with low jitter,
low packet loss and then you have the SFUs placed in a strong network center and have a
good interconnection and by this setup you have, yeah, that's the best you can do in terms of
media quality.
So what we did, we started with an SFU which is capable to speak the matrix flavor of RTC.
It's a prototype which was handed over from Sean from the inventor of the PINEstack
and it's a Golang based WebRTC implementation. We added the matrix bits to it, we wrote a lot of it.
It's early stage but we have support for audio channels, we have support for video channels
and screen sharing and on top of that recently we also added so-called simulcast support.
Simulcast is, as you can imagine, that maybe you have to go step back. So in the full mesh mode you
have a literally a peer-to-peer connection to each of those clients and by adding some signaling you
can, the receiver can tell the sender, oh I'm struggling with a network connection, can you
please adapt your network bandwidth from the encoding side. This is a little bit harder if
you're having a central point, an SFU, so here the trick is that the sender will provide several
or media quality levels and then on the SFU the client can decide which one to choose,
low quality, mid quality and high quality and this is called simulcast and we already have
basic support for simulcast in our selective forwarding unit.
Matrix is known for privacy and end-to-end encryption and in the full mesh setup of
MatrixRTC that's quite easy because you have the transport layer which ensures end-to-end encryption.
But if you terminate a peer connection on an SFU the transport layer is of course terminated
and hence we need media encryption and this is the missing part here. So using insertable streams
we need going forward to implement end-to-end encryption on the client side that such that
the media is encrypted on the client sendover and then it's not an issue on the SFU.
For this specific topic MatrixRTC and cascaded FOCI or selective forwarding units
we have later a dedicated talk from my colleague Szymon, it's the in-depth talk cascaded FOCI,
it will be in this room, not in this room, it will be online at 2 pm this day.
So now we have an idea of what the vision of MatrixRTC is and what we can do with it, we have
seen so far the use cases. Let's come back to element call, I think we demonstrated it last year.
Yes, very early. Very early and after one year you could imagine something happened.
So first recap, what's element called? So initially it was developed on a green field
as a single page application and the cool story here it's just a matrix client.
It's not for chat, it's a matrix client and the implementation was using the full
mesh so without a backend component. So what's new? So after this year, first of all in our
site or not site project, our partner project Hydrogen we also have call support right now
and it's also working in Drop
Call. We have a group call experience, we just press the group call button and we have dedicated
video rooms which is pretty cool. So the semantic of this room is that when you click on this room
you're asked to join the conference immediately. The question is how to embed element call into a
matrix client in general. So in theory you could just implement the MSCs but that would be very
expensive because then you need to implement in each platform, expensive in terms of engineering
bandwidth. So all requirements are one implementation which fits all and the idea is that we embed
element call or the embedded element call needs to share the same underlying matrix client and room
in order to not waste resources or to have device proliferation. So the idea is quite obvious,
let's use a widget for it. Also a short recap on widgets. What is a widget? A widget is basically
an application living in a matrix room. It's simply an embedded iframe and it's a small
form factor web application, HTML, JavaScript. The widget is embedded within a room and can
communicate with matrix clients and therefore from the matrix client through the widget API.
And this widget API is a defined post message API basically. A widget is able to request permissions
to perform actions on the user's behalf, something like posting into a room, receiving specific event
types and so on and so forth. To have a more easier way of approaching widgets, we also have
a widget SDK which is written in JavaScript and TypeScript. It's basically a web app.
And now here we have an overview about element call and the various flavors. So in the single
page application mode, it's just the matrix client using the client server API and in the
widget mode we're going through the widget API over the underlying matrix client and then to the
host server. The abstraction layer client server API versus widget is really thin. So from a
development perspective that was really easy to implement. Yeah, so the solution is it's just a
widget. It's WebRTC in a web view and this is the nice thing. So the whole WebRTC stack to implement
on various platforms is quite painful. But if you can just a WebView where this is included for free,
that's a thing. We needed to extend the widget API to add some missing bits, specifically where
the 2D vice messages and to access the turn server, also spec'd in the MSCs. And this whole concept we
call Matroska embedding where we have a WebView hosting widgets and the various clients and that
could be a web client but it could also be the native clients like the iOS and the Android items.
And hence we have the solution, one implementation that fits all.
Let's have a demo, right?
So what you see here basically is just the desktop application of Element, Element Nightly.
On the left hand side you can see the various rooms with various flavors. So here this is a
general room and here's already a conference started. So if you press it you will join it.
And at the top here we have a so-called video room and if you join it, you're directly prompted
to join a conference. And what you can also see here is a chat. So let's join it.
Hello, I erased the volume here. So, hi Enrico, hi Simon. Yeah, welcome to Fostem.
What we can do here right now is that we have various flavors. So we have a new layout here
which we call large grid design. And you can change the tile sizes. And I also added here
some debug information and you can see that the small video on the top left receives the
low-quality stream whereas the large tile on the bottom receives the mid-quality stream.
Hey Dave. Hello. So, now we want to carry out an experiment. I have a QR code here.
Hopefully I find it. And I encourage everybody to join the call and to crash our SFU. Let's
low test it. Sorry. With Chrome?
Yeah, yeah, I really do.
It's the resolution of the projector, good enough. We'll put the URL in the
frame. So let's see.
Let's see.
I'm getting video from Ben Key. Refresh. So of course if it's not working then we can blame the
Wi-Fi here, right? It's slightly unhappy now.
I don't know.
Oh no, no, no. It's recovering. It's recovering.
So we plan a second demo later the day with the talk from Shimon. So yeah,
but so how many do we have?
Depends.
Okay, let's say I leave it in the background, play around with it.
And we go back to the talk.
Okay, so what's next in the matrix RTC ecosystem? Of course we want to implement the whiteboard,
at least the hybrid version of the whiteboard. Then the very important thing really is to start
with the insertable streams to also have the end-to-end encryption in case of using the SFU.
With respect to the selective forwarding units, we need to implement the focus selection logic.
So if you remember the graph where we had the, or the picture where we had the
home servers alongside the SFU's alongside with the home servers. We sketched out a nice
algorithm where you can automatically choose the right one. And this is something we need to
implement right now. Yeah, and then obviously the cascading. This has not started the implementation,
but yeah, we need to carry out. On the simulcast layer, we also have some optimizations in mind.
For instance, I think it's only a good idea to upload your video to the SFU. If on the other
side someone consumes this video stream. So this is an optimization we can add. And I think also the
the switching point where when you change the layer from high quality to low quality,
there's also some room for improvement. On top of that, we need to care a little bit more about
network bandwidth rate control. This is an important thing we need here, such that the SFU
also feeds back information back to the client, such that the client is then in a good position
to adapt the local video or audio encoders. And finally, we want to extend the call support in
hydrogen and add the SFU bits to it. And now maybe some of you are wondering a little bit
why Matthew is sitting here with his classes. Yeah, and now let's head over. So what we have
so far seen was the obvious use case for matrix RTC, which is a video conferencing solution.
But I told you earlier that we also have something like the metaverse interpretation of matrix.
We call it third room. Yeah, and in a half minute. Yeah, any questions though on the
florians? Yeah, the short Q&A part.
Hopefully this thing is gonna work.
Apologies for being the idiot with a VR headset on.
I'm going to start streaming in a second. So I wanted to talk about third room,
which is the social collaboration platform that we have built on top of matrix. And I'm going to
slightly mess around with trying to get this to work at the wrong resolution, because it's going
to let crack if it's not on the right res. How do you change the resolution these days in macOS?
Anybody know how to actually change the refresh rate? Advanced? That's not helpful.
So
that's not me. Yeah, and is that your fault that it's live streaming?
Oh, it's the wrong one. Thank you. Too many dev rooms. You should play the using the same one.
And 2001.
Online dev room. No, it's not the online dev room. Normal dev room.
I can't spell matrix. This is going well. That one. Right. Thank you.
Okay. Are we sure that looks totally squashed? That's literally what I'm trying to fix right now.
How can it be to actually set a resolution on this thing these days?
How about I press that button where we're going to go to.
Yeah, so it's gone to four by three, but it wants to do four by three everywhere,
but it's not four by three. It's 16 by nine. Let's go to that.
So I'm coming in on the stream. All right, just check this. It'll be worth it. Don't worry.
On the plus side, the Oculus thing kicks in, which is good. Right. Yeah, this is looking good.
Yeah. So let me actually bring up third room. So the point of third room is that it's a tiny team.
It's sorry.
Okay. Hi, everybody. Welcome to my talk on third room, which is a project,
a tiny project done by three people, Robert and AJ. AJ also famous for doing Cine as matrix client,
which is trying to show people that matrix is way more than chat and VoIP. I know that it's cool to
look at 3D stuff these days and go, don't like 3D. But honestly, I think this is incredibly
interesting in showing the potential of what we have to build on top of matrix today. Now,
the way it works is that you've got hydrogen SDK going and basically providing a plain old matrix
client. And if I jump into this room here, which is hash presentation on thirdroom.io, if people
want to play along at home, feel free to come and jump in and heckle my presentation. And you can
see that this is a virtual world going and sitting in browser. If I pull up the frame rate, which is
obviously control shift s, you can see it's actually going at 60 frames a second. I'm ending
you're stuck in the floor. It's running at 60 frames a second in browser at 1080p, as we all
just saw, which is pretty impressive for a fairly complicated scene that we have going on here. And
the way that thirdroom works is quite unusual. And it's properly multi threaded in browser.
It's using an entirely new game engine that the team basically put together. And I should
hasten to add, I've basically been encouraging people rather than actually working on this,
Robertson and Sam Fran. And so it'll be cruel and unusual to get him to do this and talk.
And I've even got some slides here. And it's showing the scripting that is built in that
I'll talk about in a minute. Now, the interesting thing is that we're using
shadow raid buffers to go and share data between the main thread and a bunch of worker threads
using post message between these and then the atomic APIs in the browser, so that you can
actually have probable multiple threads in order to have the rendering thread running completely
independently from the gaming thread that does physics and the main thread that does react and
does hydrogen is with embedded hydrogen in the react app here, as well as matrix. So if I go
into the next slide, here are the main threads, we've got react, matrix and web RTC happening.
And we have spatial audio in here. So if I actually unmute myself,
I've got first for myself on my own talk, that's annoying. Let me
pause that. I'm still out there somewhere. You want to come over and say something to me?
Somebody else. I'll go over to you. Say something.
You hear me? Yeah, okay. So if we had headphones on at this point, and I turn this way and you say
something, it's coming out the left speaker and you have to believe me and look the other way.
And it's coming out. Honestly, it helps the immersive experience massively that we're
going using spatial audio to go and position where things are here.
Whilst we're wandering around here, you can see that we've got at the moment, generic avatars.
But if you walk around a bit, you can see her moon walking backwards for whatever reason.
I'm sure you can also go forwards. There we go. And fly for that matter. And
so the B button lets you fly in this, so you can go and jump around like so.
And so you're spoiling my talk. So if we go down here, then on the game thread, we've got
a bunch of rust. We have the ability to run arbitrary WebAssembly scripts, which are sitting
in a sandbox, which allows you to basically add any arbitrary functionality into the world.
From a pure matrix perspective, this is probably the most exciting thing here.
Now, if you remember, I'll see in Merck scripting, the ability to run arbitrary scripts on your IRC
client, this is effectively allowing you to define bots and arbitrary functionality and matrix,
which run inside your client, inside the sandbox, and the actual data is stored in your room.
Now, this whole thing is a matrix room. If I go and hit enter, then you can see a bunch of users
there. I can say, hello world. And if I go back to my element client, and if I literally join
presentation on thirdroom.io for matrix.org, then you can see, I'm then saying, here. And I can say,
here to you too. And hopefully, hang on. Well, we've got traffic running one way.
Interesting. Well, we should be seeing messages coming into the room as well, because it is,
oh, there we go. It's just a plain old hydrogen overlay that is being rented in React for the
contents of the room. Now, the actual geometry of the room, if we start flying around some more,
looks like this is actually a big GLTF or a single GLTF asset. This thing is just sitting
in the media repository in the room. It's just a file that is GLTF, the transfer format for openGL,
that has been uploaded there, and also any scripts in the room, like the one which is executing the,
let me press on the buttons here. Again, there's a bit of, I think, JavaScript, using the quick JS
engine that has gone and compiled down the JavaScript to WebAssembly in real time. It's
pretty cool that you literally write it in JavaScript, and then the engine sucks it up,
turns it into Wasm, and runs it within that sandbox. So you could argue it's a little bit
perverse to be taking JavaScript, compiling it to WebAssembly, and then running it from within a
JavaScript environment. But it gives you a hell of a lot more safety than you would if we were just,
I don't know, having random blobs of JavaScript running here. On the render thread, we are using
WebGL2, and we're using FreeJS to manage the actual driving of WebGL. But the scene itself is
the scene itself is managed using a really cool technology called BitECS that was actually created
by Nate, one of the developers, before he started working on, before they started working on Third
Room. And BitECS is a entity component system where you basically track the state of the world,
the objects that exist within it, their transformations, and it's done with arrays
in JavaScript. And it turns out that if you stretch your arrays intelligently enough in JavaScript,
you can get as good as WebAssembly performance. And it's one of the other secrets to the crazy
performance that we have here. So this isn't an scene graph API under the hood, like a frame,
if anybody ever played with a frame, instead, it's using the BitECS. Then another thing which
is interesting here is that everything is triple buffered. So in a kind of traditional game engine,
you just have one sort of buffer that you write data into and the renderer reads it out,
and you have some kind of locking system to make sure that it doesn't collide. Whereas here, we
have lot three data structures, letting things go as rapidly as possible with the various different
bits of the engine writing into these shared triple buffer as a shared array buffer, which
is then juggled effectively between the various different threads. And it means that the render
thread can run at the native speed of whatever device, which is particularly useful if it's a
less powered device than my MacBook Pro here. And then the game engine that is actually rendering
what's going on can go at its own speed. So you totally decouple the two, and you get as high a
frame rate as you can. And I think that oh, yeah, and finally, lots of fun stuff going on with
optimization pipeline. Particularly the textures have been highly compressed using these fun
codecs, I think it's called universal basis, format from Binomial and KTX. And one of the things
we've done to cheat to bootstrap third room is to build a pipeline from unity, where you can take
existing unity assets like this scene here is one that we bought off a unity asset store, and then
export it as proper open standardized jotf somewhat liberating the contents from the slightly
proprietary world of unity in order to get content in more rapidly, and then compress it down. And
there are lots of fun things like the has instancing support built in. So if you start
generating lots of objects like the physics engine here, I know going to create a whole bunch of
objects and attack the various people who are wandering around in here. I'm sure they love me
for it. And then this is basically just the same jotf asset. What are you doing?
Going and being created multiple times, all the textures are sprouted. So there's just one great
big thing. There's also some really interesting extensions to GL that we've contributed by the
chronos group. And particularly, if you look at if we grab one of these miracles, which many use for
debugging purposes, let's grab that one. And if I run around with it, while I fly around with it,
you should see that the reflection changes. There we go. If I go between zones there, it's not
it needs to be tuned a bit. But basically, rather than ray tracing, which would be incredibly
time consuming, instead, we have lots of different probes hanging around the scene
that allow you to I'm hitting myself in the face with the ball. A common problem. But as you run
around, you can see the reflection changes. It's pretty nasty if you do it rapidly. But if you're
doing it more slowly like this, and it's a quite a subtle but nice effect. And it's even better
when it's on not perfect miracles. If you look at say, Dave, if you walk backwards, if you can hear
me, or go into light or out of the light, then you'll actually see a fairly subtle shadowing
effect as it's gone and figured out where the shadows are there. Right, it's good to see all
the people running around in here. So what else can I show you one of the so we're going to launch
some tech preview to this next week. And this is the first time anybody has seen tech preview two
and I have 10 minutes left. And tech preview one is sort of what we've been looking at here,
except it didn't have scripting, we've already shown some of the scripting here. But one of the
big things that have been added and let's pray that this thing works is web VR. So hopefully, if I
go to the Oculus streaming thing, which I had a second ago, I should have possibly cleaned this
up first. Of course, it stopped working. Well, I get this thing back in again. And everything is
going wrong. Apparently, I've got to recalibrate the entire thing. So I apologize, apologize for
using proprietary technology, but unfortunately, there aren't any open source headsets which do
the trick yet. And we go. And let me try to cast this up. And unfortunately, it takes ages for the
screen casting to kick in for some reason. But I'll go as quick as I can. Bump and cast and computer
go. Right. So WebXR is a really cool technology. It's been there for ages now since about 2017,
built into browsers like Firefox and Chrome, obviously. And also, interestingly, the browser,
the Oculus Quest like this or Quest Pro has built into it, which is based on Chromium.
It has awful screen casting support, as you can see, that I started at screen casting and
something is happening in the depths of Facebook, trying to figure out how to actually get this
onto the screen here. But hopefully, it will come through. I've got internet connectivity. Here it
is. Thank God. And I can start talking. And I apologize for I'm going to focus on oh, very
interesting. So I'm going to focus on flooring rather than embarrassing everybody else.
But let's just use a stationary boundary. Confirm. Right. So the browser here sits there.
I'm not going to update this right now. But here is third room. And if I continue into third room,
as guests, you can see this is just a static boring web browser just sitting here. Worth
noting that third room uses OIDC entirely. So this thing here is actually a skinned key cloak.
I'm going to say I'm not a bot. I'm not going to bother giving myself a name.
And then capture failed. Brilliant. Thanks, Google.
I'm going to have to type in third room except caffeine and stress means my ability to use a
stupid keyboard like this is going to be fun. Okay, back to third room here is a streaming. Okay.
Okay, brilliant. Let's go to login. Go out third room continues guests.
This time hope that it's not gonna make me pick stupid things right good continue.
You accept the T's and C's. Honestly, the using key cloak for this is really, really fun.
And very anticlimactically, we end up with eventually want to look connectivity.
A 2d version of third room just sitting right here. So isn't it amazing? By the way, that just
loaded from index DB local storage. But the fun thing is hopefully, come on, you can do it.
You can see it's actually struggling quite a lot. And this bit if I press the old X button,
there, that's I have to close the welcome to third room dialogue. It is
come on, and to XR. Thank God for that. Then I can see flooring Hello,
Florian. But more excitingly, hopefully, if I stay in the right place, there we go. You can see that
I'm actually in the third room environment right now. And this is genuinely cool. This is running
at 90 frames a second for me right now. And if I go and press some buttons to create some Oh, God,
some crates like massive crates, let me get rid of that. You can see it's actually hooked up to
the normal physics engine. So I can go and pull that and I can confusingly throw it into the
audience, which is no way surreal to be going and flipping back and forth. And then back in the
normal world again. At the moment, we've just got basic things like the joystick and hung up,
hooked up to it. It's got a kinematic controller. And I'm running out of Oh, no, thank you, Florian.
Um, what else can I show you? You can jump, we can spawn more objects. I can go up to that glitter
globe and sorry, mirror ball, except it's running faster than I can run after it. That's awkward.
And theoretically, if I was a little bit closer to the bloody thing, I'd be able to grab it and
pick it up, etc. So this is pretty cool. Honestly, it's as good as the native non web VR and closed
stuff that Facebook or meta horizons does. And the entire thing is open. And I built on the
surgery mentioned how am I doing for time three minutes in which case I will very quickly go and
sorry, thanks. I will start looking at random overseas, go back into this and just look at some
other things we've done. In fact, this one is really cool. Let's just flip into this one,
because this is a really complicated bit of wasm. It's actually an audio reactive widget,
which is setting here, as you can see, as I yell at it, it goes and changes size. And this is a
whole bunch of C code that has been compiled down to wasm to show how you can have interactive
things sitting inside the scene. Another example is slightly less exciting new chat box echo service.
So if I go into here, and say, Hello, and then do echo, hello with a slash command, it says hello
back to me. Now the echo that's happening down there is actually being done from the widget API
of matrix going into WebAssembly, talking to I think a JavaScript service, and then echoes back.
And you can see we have a slight bug sometimes with scripting where it loads two worlds at the
same time. And that's pretty surreal. That's what happens if London got combined with miles.
So, final thing here, I was going to show you, oh, yeah, is this guy, which is a bit silly, but fun
anyway. And this time, I'll remember to refresh as fun as it is to have the scenes combined. So you
might recognize this from a certain film. And if we actually look at the script for this particular
room, if I can figure how to get out of full screen mode, the script here is again, just sitting in
the media repository, it's a little bit of JavaScript, to use the Web Scene Graph API,
which is a new API that we've created. We hope it will become a W3 standard for
manipulating scene graphs. It looks a lot like DOM. You basically get a node by name, the TV,
and then every frame, you'd see if the TV is being pressed, and if it is, then you enable the matrix
material. And the end result is if I go here, and I click on the TV, then predictably enough,
you end up in a matrix style world. And I've got it in third person view, which is also new with
tech preview two, and click back and forth. This is super early, but you can imagine this is
basically a platform for doing any kind of real time collaborative app could be Figma on this,
it could be multiplayer blender, it could be a game, it could be digital twins, it could be,
I don't know, smart cities, GIS applications, it's as powerful and as flexible as the web,
but for real time. Thank you very much. And we have no time for questions.
It will be coming in the next release after tech preview two. I mean, the hard bit of actually
rigging up the engine and doing all the inverse kinematics. And if you run around with the current
avatars, you can now trip over things, which is very important. But suffice to say, we're focusing
on the engine rather than the assets. And also, this is at a point where people can start
contributing things. So if you've got amazing assets, if they support the mixamo rig, then they
should just drop straight in. Cool.