All right, well, hello everyone.
You'll notice I'm not Ben, this is Ben.
Hi, I'm Ben.
There's three of us here to talk to you about different things, all about improving clients
and making them as fast as you would normally expect them to be.
So first of all, my name is Keegan.
I'm going to be talking about sign sync.
And then you've got Ben going to talk about the Rust SDK and Maro about Element X.
So first of all, sign sync and a bit about myself.
I'm a staff software engineer at Element.
And I've worked on many different projects over the years and more recently working on
things like Dendrite and Peer-to-Peer and sign sync.
But first of all, what even is sign sync?
So for context, sign sync, the current sync mechanism in Matrix is really, really slow.
So if you have, you know, you go and open up your mobile app after a weekend away or
something like that, it takes a little while to sync.
It could take 30 seconds or a minute, depending on how many rooms are on your account.
And this is kind of bad, right?
We'd like it to sync instantly.
And the whole point of sign sync is trying to make that happen, trying to make it sync
instantly or virtually instantly.
There was a talk last year on the online FOSDEM.
If you want to know more information about the deep dive of how sign sync works, and
there's a QR code there.
But I'm not going to be covering too much detail about how sign sync works, other than
enough to kind of fill in the gaps if you have no idea what this is.
So at a high level, sign sync works by sorting and filtering.
So you can see here, you've got all the rooms on the user's account.
And then you can filter that set of rooms down in some way.
So for example, you could filter it based on like, I want encrypted rooms or I want
DM rooms, things like that.
And then you can apply some sort of sorting operation to them.
So you might say, sort them by the room name, or you could say, sort by recency.
So like the last timestamp in the room or by the number of notification counts, number
of unread messages and stuff that mention your name and that sort of thing.
And then you can request the first five rooms, 10 rooms, 20 rooms, and things like that.
Also the rooms themselves, you can filter the room state using sign sync.
So in normal sync, you will go and get all of the room state.
And if there's a lot of room state, that's not great.
So in sign sync, you can specify, I'm only interested in like the topic of the room and
whether it's encrypted or not.
And that's it.
This is a pretty big change to how matrix works today.
So how is this actually going to, like how are we actually going to do this in practice?
So in practice, there is a go process, which is the sign sync proxy, which I've been working
on for over a year now, which has a Postgres database attached and it will go and do sync
V2 requests on your behalf to an upstream server.
It could be Synapse, could be Dendrite, whatever, it doesn't really matter, it could be conduit.
And the important thing here is that this proxy exposes a sign sync API.
So it exposes a new endpoint, a new sync endpoint, and then a client can go and try the, you
can actually try the sign sync API and see how it feels to them.
So they don't need to have a particular implementation on Synapse.
So we'll wait for these implementations to land.
You can try it on your own server if you run a proxy.
In terms of a protocol level, what this looks like is you can see here, you've got like
some lists, it's a list subject, and then you can specify things like things we were
talking about before.
So you can say you've got the ranges there, you've got, so that's how many like the top
end rooms that you want, the sort ordering that you want, as well as any filters you
apply here.
And here you can see we're filtered by is-dm-true, and that's going to be used to populate the
people tab, say, on the web.
You also have these things with room subscriptions.
They are kind of like the room lists, but this is when you know the specific room ID.
So if you follow a permalink, which may include the room ID, or if you refresh the page and
you know that this person was currently viewing this room, that room may not be in this list,
right?
So you would need to subscribe to that room directly because you know the room ID.
And typically, though, as well, the kinds of information you want here is different.
So in here, we are requesting all the state in the room and a much higher timeline limit
because this is being used to populate the actual full room view.
The response is very similar as well.
So you have a list object here, and then you get a list of room IDs that are used to populate
the correct ordering here.
And then you also have a top-level rooms array, a rooms object, and then that's just the key
value maps where the keys are the room IDs and then the values are all the data that
you requested.
So these all get aggregated together, which I will speak about a bit later.
In terms of what's new, so if you followed SidingSync, then you might be like, okay,
I know all this, but what's actually happened over the past year?
We have clients from SidingSync.
So this is from Element Web.
It's got a nice, scary warning there.
So it's great.
It all works on web, but also it actually works on mobile devices as well, thanks to
the Rust SDK, which I'll leave for Ben to talk about.
So there's also a whole bunch of new extension MSCs.
So extension MSCs are an idea of trying to break up the complexity of SidingSync because
the sync API is by far one of the most, not the most complicated part of the client server
API, and trying to put everything into one MSC is going to be doomed to failure.
So we're trying to specify a core part of the MSC, the core part of what is syncing,
which is the syncing rooms, and working out the sorts and the filter arguments, and then
we're leaving two extensions, all the extra stuff on top.
And the idea is that you can opt into any of these things.
So if your client doesn't do receipts, then great, don't subscribe to receipts.
Don't even enable this extension.
Briefly how these extensions work.
So these two extensions go together because they ultimately are used to make encryption
work in encrypted rooms.
So you can see, well, actually you can't see at all.
Here is an encrypted event.
So there's basically, you have to trust me, there's a psychotext here with lots of gibberish
effectively, and then you need a room key to go decrypt it into your normal text.
The way that works is that you need to get keys via your two device messages.
That's why they go together.
The other thing here is that it implements another MSC called Dropping Sales Sent to
Device Messages.
You can barely see it on here, but this is an output from Postgres, which is trying to
work out how many unread or unacknowledged two device events are there for a given user's
device.
And you might think that might be, say, 100, maybe 1,000 tops.
It turns out this can be a lot.
This is several hundred thousand unread or unacknowledged two device events.
And it turns out when I analyzed a lot of this, this was almost entirely down to room
keys being requested and then either canceled or successfully sent.
So this MSC 3944 basically says, hey, if you request a room key and then you subsequently
cancel that request, you're going to go and delete those two device messages so they don't
just keep stacking up in this way.
And that obviously really helps reduce the amount of bandwidth for sign sync as well.
The other thing we've got is account data.
If you wonder what account data does, if you've ever used the breadcrumbs thing at the top
here on Element Web, that's synchronized using account data.
Also account data is really, really useful for working out accurate notification counts.
So at the bottom here, you can just about see that you've got some messages here.
You've got a message in a timeline.
This is encrypted.
And it says here notification count one.
Notification counts are the gray numbers.
And you've got a highlight count of zero, which is the red number.
And yet on the UI, you can see that it's a red number and it's gone to one.
So some things happened here where the client has worked out that, oh, I should use this
as a highlight count, not a notification count.
It's overridden what the service told it.
And what's happened here is that the client has decrypted the message.
And then it's checked the message to say, hey, is there any app mention or any specific
keywords based on your push rules?
And if that is true, then it knows, ah, OK, I need to actually make this a red highlight
rather than just a normal gray and red count.
And that's done using push rules.
And push rules is stored as an account data.
Final two ones are receipts and typing.
Thank you.
So hopefully you know what receipts and typing notifications are.
And the main changes for sliding sync is that the receipts are lazily loaded.
So you might think, well, what does that mean exactly?
Well, if you get a time limit of 10, then you will get those 10 events and then you
will get the receipts for those 10 events and you won't get receipts for any other events.
And you might think, hasn't it always done this?
Well, not really.
So here's some JQ for Matrix HQ, which is this room ID.
And it's just pulling out the receipt EDU and then kind of checking roughly how many
receipts there are.
And you know, Matrix HQ is quite a big room.
So you might think, you know, 100,000.
No, there's quite a lot of rooms, quite a lot of receipts in there.
And this is not great from a bandwidth perspective, right?
We don't want to be sending 53,000 read receipts, particularly for events which you are unlikely
to ever view, right?
Because this could be, these could be for events that occurred like a year ago.
So starting sync also fixes that.
So with all these performance optimizations, a very large account with 4,000 rooms can
take less than a second to actually sync, which is down from 15 minutes on SyncV2.
So very happy with that, but it's still not really good enough where, you know, we're
trying to go big or go home kind of way, kind of thing.
So we want to make it even faster.
So it is literally instant.
You don't want to have to be waiting a couple of seconds.
It should just kind of open up, just like most other best-trained clients, you can just
open them up and they just work.
The problem is that things are going to get a lot worse here, which I will talk about
in a moment.
So we've added in a bunch of tracing to the proxy server.
So things like, this is runtime trace.
So you can see exactly the control flow.
There's some spans there, and you can see various optimizations that were done.
So this is identifying so bits of code.
Lots and lots and lots of commits.
Sometimes it's just you forgot to add an index.
Sometimes you should be doing things in bulk instead of doing things sequentially.
So lots of work has gone into this.
And also, if you were going for 100 milliseconds, kind of aiming for 100 milliseconds, the actual
amount of data you send is important because this starts to become quite a large factor
in the total time it takes.
We can do simple things like de-duplication and enabling gzip for large responses, which
we now do, and as well as that we can aggressively cache things in memory wherever possible.
So we don't have to query the database when clients send a request.
So there's three levels of caching involved at the proxy level, whereas a global cache
which contains information which doesn't change for any user, it's a constant.
So things like the number of joined users in a room, it's the same if you're Alice or
if you're Bob.
It's always going to be the same.
Whereas things like the user cache or things like what's the unread count for this room,
well, that's going to change depending on which user.
And then the connections are things like which room subscriptions have you got or which lists
like what are your top end rooms or whatever your sliding window is.
Interesting thing to note here is that the room name is actually not global data.
The data that's used to calculate the room name is global data and is the same for everyone,
but the room name itself isn't because of DMs.
So if you have a DM with Alice and Bob, then from Alice's point of view the room name is
Bob, but from Bob's point of view the room name is Alice.
So just very, lots of optimizations have been done.
So with all of this, we're now getting less than 100 milliseconds, which is what we wanted,
but it's still not good enough because things are going to get a lot worse because clients,
really, it's all up to the clients because clients are not flying support and they want
instant access.
They don't want to have to be having to do a network request to, when they click on a
room they want to just see the list.
They don't want to see a spinner.
And in the best case you have a spinner for half a second maybe and then it loads, which
is not great but maybe acceptable.
But then if you're on a mobile app and you go into a tunnel, then it's just going to
spin it forever and then you're sad.
So users expect these things to work instantly.
And you can, you know, Sizing Sync has ways that you can fix this.
So if you want to go and instantly see the room timeline, that's fine because we can
pre-cache the room timeline.
You can use a higher timeline limit and then you can go and pre-cache that so you see the
room list you click through and immediately you see all the events, at least a screen's
worth of events.
For the other thing, which is you want to scroll the room list instantly and smoothly,
well you can opt out of the sliding windows entirely and you can just request really small
stub information like I just want the avatar, I just want the room name and that's it.
And then you'll know the position, the room name, the avatar and then you can just request
all the rooms entirely.
So that will scale with the number of rooms in the user's account.
But it's, you know, it's possible.
And you can use something like this to say timeline limit of zero.
But there's a problem here, right?
Because you have a timeline limit of 20 on the first one, then a timeline limit of zero.
So you kind of want a bit of both.
So it turns out what clients really want is delayed data delivery.
So the API wasn't originally designed for that a year ago.
So we've made a lot of changes to support this kind of idea of delayed data delivery.
So one of the things is timeline trickling.
So what timeline trickling is, is that you can initially request a set of rooms and you
can say I want only the most recent message in this room.
And then at a later point you can say, okay, now I want the last 10 messages in this room.
And then it will go and effectively back paginate those messages for you.
Likewise the clients want all the rooms in the accounts.
And they want maybe more detail on the rooms that are in the viewport.
So again, you can support this by having two lists effectively.
You've got one list, which is just the visible rooms.
That might have more accurate information for like room previews.
So you got room preview, you might have typing notifications, you might register for typing
notifications in those rooms.
But then you're not really interested in typing notifications for rooms really far down the
list.
In the background you can just have a separate list which just kind of in the background
goes and gets all the other rooms and all the core information that you need.
So this has kind of been a huge trade off, right?
On the one hand you've got sync v2, which is getting everything and is super slow.
But it's got fantastic offline support as a result of that.
And on the other side you've got sliding sync.
It's super fast.
You're only literally getting the data that you need.
But there's compromises to be made there because you have to do network requests all the time
and things can be slower.
There's only so fast you can do.
There's only so much you can optimize the server.
So really I think Element is kind of aiming to do something like that.
So it's mostly kind of sliding sync, but the arch compromises and trade offs that are
being made to try to give a really good offline experience as well.
So in terms of what's next, we need to add threads.
Because there's no threading support at all in sliding sync.
And threads obviously only recently landed and was enabled everywhere.
Threads is complicated because threads are changes fundamental answers to questions like,
is this room unread?
Because normally you could just be like, well, what's your read marker?
What's most recent event?
OK, it must be unread.
Whereas now you could have scenarios where the most recent event in the room is on a
thread.
So if you were just to click on a room and you see the timeline, they're all messages.
But in a thread three days ago, there's actually a newer message.
So adding support for threads is going to be quite tricky to get right.
And we'll have to probably iterate on it quite a lot.
But it is coming.
The other thing we're going to be adding in is this concept called Delta tokens, which
unless you've read the MSC, you'll have no idea what it is.
Basically what Delta tokens are is to, sliding sync has a problem at the moment, the proxy
server, because it has amnesia.
So it will time out your connection if you don't use it for, say, half an hour.
And it will clean up all that in memory state.
All those caches and things get cleaned up.
And the problem is that then when you reconnect, even though your client has stored those rooms
and stored a lot of the timeline and stored a bunch of room state, the proxy server doesn't
know this.
So it's going to resend that information to you.
So the point of Delta tokens is to say, hey, remember me, I already know about these events.
And then those events aren't sent to the client again in duplicate.
Few more API optimizations.
We recently swapped to using lists as keys, which basically means that instead of representing
the requests and response lists as an array of lists, they're now just a big key value
map, which makes it easier because you can then reference an individual list by the list
key name.
So for things like extensions, this is great because you could then have a way of expressing,
I want typing notifications, but only on these named lists.
Whereas before that was very difficult to express.
And we also really want to have comprehensive client support.
It's getting reasonably stable now, and it's certainly very performant.
And element web uses sign sync natively in the JS SDK.
But obviously that doesn't really work for mobile.
And it would be nice to have some sort of SDK that could be used for Android and iOS
and maybe even web at some point.
I think there is.
Yes.
Let's talk about the rest SDK.
So this is, sorry, overall a very technical talk.
You've already noticed that.
But I'm going to lighten up a little bit more.
But first about me, so I'm Ben.
Hi.
My name is the only name in the presentation.
I don't know why.
These guys have more work and show more stuff.
I've led the rust SDK team for the last year for element.
And I've been working in decentralization, decentralized tech for a couple years already.
I worked at Parry Tech before with leading the substrate client team there.
If you know blockchains, it's one of the most favorite blockchain building systems.
I'm going to be working as a technique for actual global where we're building on top
of the rust SDK, an organizing app for NGOs and civil society.
So I've been working in this for over a decade.
You might know me from almost not at all threatening talk I gave at Jason like 2017.
That was already about like, how do you do decentralized privacy first technology.
Enough about me.
Let's talk about, let me tell you a little story.
We're back in 2019, 2020.
And it's the state of the clients.
For the sake of argument, I'm talking about element clients here because I think there's
exceptions to what I'm going to tell you.
But let me tell you two truth and a lie.
And you can tell me if you can spot the lie.
So truth number one, many clients out there don't actually implement end-to-end encryption,
which is pretty sad because it's a very fundamental part of what we're working on.
That is mostly because it's hard even if you use the most widely used library.
That is a C library.
There's always a slightly dated, like a lot of knowledge that has been built up that is
not easy to ingrain in this existing library anymore.
Clients usually implement the entire HTTP or at least most of the state machine around
room, room state, who's allowed to write as well as entire messaging mechanics themselves
in their own language, in their own environment.
Or because we have that, clients are super fast.
It is totally integrated into the system that they are.
And it's just a smooth experience.
I don't have to ask you, you know which one of this is a lie, the cake is a lie.
At this time, enter our hero.
Our hero is Damir.
Damir is working as a crypto dev for Element.
He's a Rust enthusiast.
And he knows the crypto in and out.
He's intending to rewrite a plugin that he's using for an ISC client, which is called WeChat,
that connects to matrix.
Because of simple problems that are limitations in the Python implementation that WeChat offers,
he wants to rewrite it in Rust.
But he doesn't really find a good place to build it on.
This is not an actual representation, but we're going to use it for now.
So he goes out and says, okay, let's write this.
How hard could it be?
He quickly realizes, okay, so the crypto side with the C, I would like to have that in Rust.
I'm going to get that Y in a second.
And he pulls that out later, which is now called Vodosimac.
You might have heard about that, which is our crypto implementation that we're pushing
forward as a live-all mis-deprecate.
But he figures out the stuff around that to make crypto work.
Not the encryption itself, but the entire thing of how do I know which messages to encrypt
with what key, in what room, what if a message comes in and I don't have the encryption key?
All of that state management around that is actually as complicated and as problematic
as the actual crypto.
And that is why a lot of people try to use the crypto, but then fail in doing all of
that, making it a really terrible experience.
And then I drop it and say, oh, let's not do encryption.
That's too hard.
But he continues and pushes on because he really wants that for WeChat and starts out
with what we know as the Rust metrics SDK.
So why did he pick Rust?
I'm not talking in his name, but I'm going to give you some reasons why.
If you heard about Rust before, you probably heard about it because it's the most popular,
most beloved language.
Six years running now on the Stack Overflow system.
So who here has heard about Rust?
All right.
Who has used Rust?
Keep your hands up.
OK.
That's fairly good.
And while that is definitely true to some degree, like there's a lot of love for that
language, it's even bigger in crypto because encryption, building encryption and building
that safely is really hard.
At the same time, you're not you can't really go for Python or that kind of stuff because
it's, well, too inefficient.
So most information used to you see Rust seemed like such a nice alternative.
So inside crypto and encryption, Rust is already a big thing.
So that's probably the main reason he chose it because he wanted to use it.
But there's also a good amount of actual reasons why Rust makes sense to build this with.
This is a screenshot of the website of RustLang.org from yesterday.
I'm going to break it down a little more because we have to understand one key thing.
Rust was invented by Mozilla to build a new browser.
They had Firefox 2010, 2011.
They were like, there's so much C, C++ in here.
It's so complicated.
We barely know how we can change stuff ourselves.
And it's like it's still Netscape code base in there, right?
Like it's like 20 years of stuff.
So they were like, let's build a new browser.
And it's called the server project as a recent research project.
And through that, they realized like there's certain things we'd like to have for new languages.
And they started building their own language to build a browser.
That project still exists.
It's server.org today.
Mozilla has handed off the management to the Linux Foundation.
It's still a research project.
I recommend if you want to start with Rust.
That is a really good community to start with.
But the key point here is that it was a language built by practitioners for practitioners.
They didn't set out to say like, hey, let's make a theoretically proven language.
Let's make a really beautiful looking language.
All of these ideals were not existing.
They wanted a language that they can use that they're more efficient in building a browser
with, which is already quite hard.
If you say like, I want to build a browser, that's a lot of stuff you have to do.
And so they set out to build this is the previous claim that Rust had, which is a type safe
systems language.
So systems language like level of C, C++ with zero cost abstractions.
Built by practitioners.
So it's a modern language.
It reached 1.0 in 2015.
It is S, B, D, S, C, and C++.
Sometimes it's B, D, R. The most famous example is rip-grab.
If you go for that, it's like 10 times faster than the next comparable implementation to
grab over a lot of files.
And it does all of that without any garbage collector or VM.
Again, the goal is to have zero cost abstractions.
Any abstraction that Rust gives you and a lot of the abstractions that the community
also gives you in their own crates has the idea of like, we can lower that down at compile
time to nothing.
It doesn't actually exist.
Or like garbage collector cycles, no.
VM below that, no.
It should work on an embedded system.
That rules out a lot of places.
But all of that without memory safety bugs.
Just probably the biggest concern for any security researcher.
Like buffer overflows are non-existent effectively in Rust.
Very famously, like a couple of days ago, Google announced that since they have been
shipping Rust in Android, I think a third of the code that they ship in Android is now
Rust.
Their amount of memory bugs has halved even lesser than that.
And that is their main concern so far.
Most of that happens at compile time.
So at compile time, the compiler is a little more annoying and telling you, like, you need
to tell me where this memory is going to go.
I said in this thread on that thread, but it also means that after it compiles, it runs.
But again, because it's built from practitioners for practitioners, it's not just about the
language.
Like, you need to be able to actually work with that.
That means that it's very famous for its very good tooling.
It has a really nice compiler that very famously when people jump from other languages and
they run through the first error, they see the compiler complaining, they switch immediately
back to look at the code.
In Rust, you don't do that.
The compiler is probably going to tell you what you need to change, or at least what
things you need to change to make that run.
That is a completely behavioral change.
The compiler is your friend telling you, look, you need to just tell me, is that in this
thread or that thread?
This is what I assume you would want to do.
It can be wrong, of course, because you have higher level abstraction that you need to
work with.
But overall, it's pretty good.
The same for Cargo, which is the package management system and build system, but also Rust up,
which is the meta version of organizing your own Rust installation.
All of that, it provides with being built against the LLVM backend, which means it's
more or less instantly portable.
When you can run it and you don't have any specific architecture code for your Mac, it
will compile for Windows as well.
You basically just have to say there's another target.
The way that LLVM works, it has an abstract syntax tree of its own in between.
We compile basically Rust compiles to that.
Then everything that LLVM supports as a target, it can compile to.
That is pretty amazing.
It lets to Rust being the very first language that had native support for WebAssembly as
a target language.
Because it was just switching on, oh yeah, the target for that.
At the same time, sorry, my voice isn't still losing the stick.
It allows you to have a C compatible lib interface.
That makes it really nice to embed it into other stuff and use it as a library.
All right.
That's Rust.
What currently do we have in the Rust SDK now, a year later?
The idea is essentially that everything you need to have to build a matrix client, it
should be there.
Better is included.
That specifically means we have an async type safe API.
Like requests you do, they're type safe.
They come back.
The fact that the JSON comes back is what it needs to be.
It has a full featured room state.
So for every room that you're in, it can tell you can you write in that room, what kind
of messages can you write, what are the other users in the room, what is their avatar, what
other states do they have.
All of that stuff, it is managing for you.
You don't have to bother too much about that.
It has a persistent storage layer support.
So you don't have to worry about caching it or putting it somewhere locally.
You can still do that on your own if you want.
It is a pluggable interface.
But it already comes with a native version which is deprecated, slapped, replaced with
the SP lite which is still partially there for crypto but not from the other side yet.
But it also has, for example, support for Web, for index DB.
So you can run it in the browser.
One of the examples is an echo bot that runs in your browser in Wasm.
It's pretty awesome.
And for us, almost the most important part is that it has transparent end-to-end encryption
support.
When you're in a room and that room is encrypted, it's going to send the messages out to get
the keys that you need to allow you to verify with a different device.
But from the point that you join with a new device and you send, you just say room send
and you give it the message, it's going to send an encrypted message.
That's it.
For the most part of it, unless user interaction is required, you don't have to bother about
that.
It's going to store that information.
It's going to make sure that when you start up the next time through the storage support
that you have all the keys there.
You don't have to bother about there being an additional end-to-end encryption that you
have to take care with.
Already mentioned that it has Wasm and Web support.
And because of the C layer, we're also able to offer support to different bindings out
there.
So we have two bindings that are used in the next generation of element apps.
We're going to see that later for Kotlin and Swift through UniFFI.
But there's also custom bindings for Node.js and for JS on the web as well.
I think there's Python bindings out there, but they're not maintained by us.
This all allows us to go beyond what we have so far.
It allows us to ingrain more of the stuff that different clients and implementations
have been using, but that has barely cross-pollinated.
If you had a really clever way of managing your timeline in Android, the iOS people wouldn't
know.
That all converges into this singular place now.
That allows us to do a lot more things a lot quicker.
One of the things that we currently do is we offer a new experimental timeline API that
manages the state for you.
Back in 2018, 2019, editing messages came around, and that fundamentally changed the
idea of an event in matrix.
It's just not a stream of events anymore, but events acting upon other events.
This changes a message from a previous thing.
With a new timeline API, you don't have to bother.
We're just going to tell you, oh, position 17, this is now this.
The same is true for redactions.
The same is true for reactions.
Out of these things and soon threads, I don't know how we're going to do threads yet, but
that all is supposed to be right there.
You don't have to bother about the state machine changes that this requires.
It's just going to tell you, hey, you need to render a different thing now.
The other thing that was mentioned before as well is support for sliding sync.
Both of these are still experimental.
You have to actively switch them on because it's interfaces that we're not confident with
that are going to stick exactly the way they are, but there's implementations out there
using that.
All right.
Does it work?
Does it live up to the promise?
Let's see.
In order to build sliding sync, I built a small testing UI.
With sliding sync right now, this is Mr. Big, my test account.
I don't know how many rooms, but usually loading it on element web is like a minute for the
initial sync.
With my timeline, with sliding sync up and this testing system, it's 200 milliseconds.
It's 200 milliseconds to render the room.
You can see this down here.
To pull up all other rooms, it's like another 30 milliseconds.
So yeah, it's fast.
It does what it's supposed to do.
Is that actually true?
I'm a core developer.
Of course, the thing that I'm building here is hopefully going to work, but how plausible
is that as a SDK?
Maybe I'm just building a lot of stuff.
Let's take a look at the thing itself.
The implementation on top of the Rust SDK for this UI is a whopping 2,000 lines.
It's pretty small.
Most of that is actually two-e-realm stuff because actually two-e's in Rust are not that
great, so you have to do a lot of state management.
The actual implementation of managing the Rust SDK is less than 130 lines of code.
Everything else you saw, including that this stores it on your hard drive, totally abstracted
away.
I don't have to bother about this from that perspective.
I would say, yeah, definitely.
It does SDK.
But again, I'm a core developer.
Hopefully it's easy for me to build this.
It should be fairly okay to build something as quick.
But of course, it's supposed to be working for you.
For that, we've also brushed up our game a little bit on documentation.
One thing I would like you to look at... I have to check the time.
It's all right.
We have reorganized the repo a little bit to make it a little cleaner.
You can see there's a bunch of stuff around that.
There's X-TAS, which is our task manager, benchmarks, testing that should be self-explanatory.
We have the bindings in the uniFFI bindgen to organize bindings.
We have the labs, which is also where you find the Jack-in implementation if you're
curious about this.
But the main stuff lives in crates and contravers, other things built on hub.
We have an examples folder exactly for this kind of stuff.
So let me quickly set a puzzle, roughly.
I put the slides into the dev room if you want to look at them.
Quickly run through the SDK bot 101 thing.
It allows you to directly use that from the repo with that command.
What you see on the first screen is just the imports that we need.
You see mostly Rust SDK stuff, some minor managing around that.
If you scroll down, if you're familiar with Rust, you know that binary has this main function.
We use Tokyo here.
It's an async function.
Told you, async API.
Most of that is just parsing in a very ugly way the command line and then handing it over
to login and sync.
This login and sync sets up some minor stuff.
You see that we have a lot of information about this in code comments right here for
you.
It does even set up a flat store.
You can call the login username.
You can give it a name for the bot that is the device that you will see.
It logs in.
Going further, I don't have the time to go through the entire thing, but it explains everything
here.
This bot does two things.
For every room that you ask it to join, it will automatically join, which is this first
event handler.
The second event handler is reacting on messages.
An event handler in the client is basically just a callback that you can say, like, when
these kind of events come in, please tell me and then I react to this.
Those themselves can be async again pretty nice.
Then it just starts syncing.
That's all it does.
Which means it's running the sync loop.
This does not at this point use sliding sync.
As I told you, it's kind of experimental.
Let's look at the room message.
When we receive a message, we can again mention it before.
It's going to give us the actual room message in a typed format.
We can rely on the compiler here to make sure that things are as they should be.
We make sure that we are in this room.
We try to figure out if it's a text message.
If it's a text message, we check for is it a dollar bank party?
If so, we're going to respond with the message.
That's all the thing does.
In reality, it looks like this.
I'm showing you this is just regular main at the moment.
If I run the bot, this is slightly capped so you can't see my password.
I'm here connected to that bot.
You see that I'm in here.
I added two more prints that are not in main right now to make it a little cleaner.
I'm sending a message.
We see that this message is ignored.
If I send bank party, you can see it's reacting.
It's sending this.
Most importantly, this is an encrypted room.
I didn't have to do anything to build a bot that allows me to live and interact with an
encrypted room.
That's an encrypted message.
I didn't have to do anything.
You saw that there was no setup.
I hadn't to manage anything.
The Rust SDK did all of that for me.
If you want to learn more, you can find all of the code at metrics.metrics.slck.
You can join our developer and talk about the Rust SDK room.
The example you just saw is inside the examples folder, getting started.
Jack in.
The other clients you saw before is in the labs.
All of that code, obviously.
I really recommend going for the getting started.
It has a lot of documentation.
I also want to send an honorable mention to Benjamin, who was working on Trinity, which
is built on top of the Rust SDK, a bot framework, I would say.
It allows you to write some very small Rust that is compiled to Wasm that it runs in the
client that can react to messages.
You can write just the message part and say, I have a bot that reacts to messages.
This is one.
Oh, yeah.
The element is hiring.
If you are interested in working on this full-time, element IOR charisma.
We're going to have time for questions later.
We have to get through all of these first.
Let's see what you can actually build with this.
Thank you.
That's a long one.
You want time?
Yeah.
So hello, everyone.
My name is Mauro.
Honestly, my colleagues at a slide where they presented themselves.
I don't have such a thing.
So I have to be brief.
I come from Italy.
Naples.
I'm a software engineer.
Work at Element.
I mostly work on the iOS side of things and started working also on some Rust implementations.
Today, we're going to talk about the new client ElementX.
So this new client is pretty much being built with the idea of well-defined goals.
The first of them is pretty much user experience.
The thing is that we really wanted to improve over the user experience of the current element
implementation.
The thing is that Element was started as pretty much a showcase for what metrics were scalable
of.
It was a bit like an app made by engineers, for engineers.
So yeah, not everyone is into this kind of stuff.
So sometimes it's a bit hard to use for the average user.
And we want to improve over this.
Also, we want, of course, to have a performance to be another very important goal, actually
just as important as UX.
We're actually, thanks to the slide and sync implementation on ElementX, we're aiming to
actually launch the app in less than 100 milliseconds.
That's pretty much the thing that we're aiming for.
And of course, also optimize the bandwidth usage.
Also we want to build an app that is reliable just from the start.
So testing code coverage is pretty much right from the start of the project, a niger priority.
And also we want to build the app in a way that is actually relying on shared components
pretty much.
The Mattress Crisis Decay is just one of them.
But of course, we're planning to build more components that will be shared across different
implementation, across different platforms, different projects.
So not even necessarily ElementX.
It is that we will be able to use them.
And of course, anyone in the open source community will be able to use them.
So why are we writing the Android and the iOS app?
That's actually a good question because some of these goals could also be achieved with
a very big refactor.
But let's go more in depth on why we want to do our write.
So let's start with Element iOS.
Element iOS, it's quite old.
It started in 2015.
Essentially it was, as I say, pretty much a POC to showcase what metrics was capable
of.
It started as being named the Metrics iOS console, in fact.
And it went through a bunch of identity crisis and changed name three times.
I guess it was first console, then Vator, then Riot.
Now it's Element.
Let's hope it's going to stick with Element.
And it was built by engineers to showcase pretty much what metrics was capable of.
But the thing is that, first of all, as I say, the user experience was not great.
Second, it was made with some very old components, written on Objective-C, that used some very
old architectural pattern, like MVC, which should stand for...
What would be a controller?
But it stands more for a massive controller because you're not fighting this massive
controller.
It's just a huge mess and you start looking at 60,000 lines of code in a controller and
you're like, oh my God, why am I alive?
And so, yeah.
You don't want to see that anymore, pretty much.
We want to move to a newer architecture.
And also, even if we did a lot of refactors on the Element iOS implementation, you essentially...
Yeah, we were essentially not able to change all the old implementations since they were
very hard to maintain and we still relied on these components a lot.
So yeah, core components are still using these old implementations.
Half of the code is still in Objective-C and core coverage is quite low.
So we decided to experiment a bit in Q2 2022.
We decided to pretty much build a minimum client using the matrix process decay and
pretty much the state of the art frameworks provided by Apple, like SwiftUI, but not only
that, like, not so async-await and things like that.
So yeah, and we were actually able to build this new minimum client that had a room list
timeline.
And it was, it was a technical success.
It was super fast and amazing.
So we decided to build on top of this second POC by giving more focus on the UX because
I just said, yeah, now we have a performance client, but now we need to have a simple client
that anyone is able to use.
So Element iOS was then born.
On the Android side, things are slightly different because technically speaking, the Android
application already had to rewrite in 2019.
So we had two choices.
We could essentially just take the Android SDK, put it on the side, and pretty much replace
it with the Rust SDK.
That would be okay.
Or maybe just rewrite it from scratch and using pretty much the state of art frameworks
that Android provides right now, like, for example, Jetpack Compose.
In the end, we decided to go for the latter for two reasons.
First of all, I mean, if we're building an application on iOS that uses the latest frameworks,
why do we want to do the same for Android?
And second, UX.
As I said, UX was a very, very important concern.
So even if you wanted to rebuild the app from scratch or rewrite it to just pretty much
change some stuff with the existing app, it would still require pretty much a huge UX
overall, which in the end made the rewrite even more sense.
So pretty much obviously the architecture of element that's structured.
Well, we have pretty much the backbone of the client.
It's pretty much all sitting in the magic Rust SDK.
It's all there.
And the magic Rust SDK through UniSFI is able to expose WIFT bindings and Kotlin bindings.
It's interesting because, as pretty much Ben said, it's exposing objects that are reactive,
that the client is the only thing that needs to care about, that needs to care about the
events of the events, the newer events.
It just needs to know that the event has been changed and it's in that place.
It needs to know that it's a new event that came afterwards and so on.
So the idea is that these objects that the bindings expose are actually already ready
to be displayed essentially.
So you just need to render them on the UI.
And that makes development way, way easier.
And of course, the sliding sync is pretty much a requirement on element tax.
And since it's been built with the idea that sliding sync will be pretty much next standard
for the clients.
And so it will only work with servers that implement for now the sliding sync proxy essentially.
So this is an example of how the code is pretty much translated from Rust into Zwift and Kotlin
through UniSFI.
As you can see, there is this the timeline item.
I would say this is pretty much an object that is pretty much like a view model.
It's already ready to be displayed.
I just pretty much need to take the presentation data from this object and render them on the
UI.
And that's it.
Which will make implementing clients for the future with the matrix Rust SDK way, way easier.
So the bindings are pretty much in a separate repo.
Anyone can download them as a file, a year file for Android or as an XC framework for
Zwift implementations.
Or you can just pretty much use a package manager like Maven Central on Android or Zwift
package manager on Zwift implementations essentially.
I think it's Zwift implementations because actually it's interesting.
But the matrix Rust SDK is capable of running on any Apple system target.
So I really can't wait someone crazy enough to build a client for Apple Watch or Apple
TV.
I'm pretty sure that the 10 people in the world at Apple TV will be very pleased that
there is a matrix client on.
On the Apple TV.
So yeah.
But of course, ElementX is going to share more than just the Rust SDK.
We're pretty much trying to build other components that we hope to share just across ElementX
but across multiple projects.
For example, we want to build an OpenID Connect component, an element called component.
And of course, since the two apps are pretty much the same up on different platforms, they're
going to share translation, they're going to share design tokens.
So why don't we just pretty much make a component to share these elements already.
And we're actually also building an interesting component which is called rich text editor,
which is essentially an SDK of written Rust that then exposes these bindings in Zwift
and Kotlin through edf5 and also in WebAssembly.
And it's essentially a UI framework that you can import into your client to render rich
text in what you see is what you get fashioned, essentially.
It's something that is going to come also into ElementX.
So keep an eye for it.
But hey, what's this slide?
Oh, actually, it's already there.
Oh, but this is not ElementX.
It is Element.
The rich text editor is already an element right now.
But in iOS, Android, and Web, you can enable it in Labs.
You can just go to Labs, enable it, and test it.
And if you're able to break it, just send us a specific deck and we'll try to fix it
as soon as possible.
It's a project that I've worked on.
I'm very proud of it.
I think we actually did something really great because it's a very simple way to pretty much
it's a way in which you can create rich text without need of using markdowns and see all
they look like, which will make life easier for you to create something like this.
Because I challenge everyone to make something like this with markdowns.
You'd go crazy with that.
So yeah, the good thing is that this rich text editor SDK that we built, I mean, it's
not just for metrics, metrics client.
I mean, technically speaking, anyone could use this.
Maybe you want to make a note app.
You want to make, I don't know, like an app that is your diary, whatever you want, you
can pretty much implement this.
And if you want to test it, you can scan the QR code.
You will get pretty much to the latest main implementation on web.
It's a test debug version there.
The one on Labs is more stable.
This one is more to play around with it.
It's cool because this one, it allows you to pretty much see how the rich text is transformed
into a DOM representation, which is in Rust, and then transformed back into an HTML, which
is the one that we are sending over at metrics clients course.
So of course, testing for liability, another important keyword.
It's something that we want to pretty much improve.
And so pretty much we built a very, yeah, very stack test infrastructure that we hope
is going to cover all these areas.
It's already covering most of these areas.
And yeah, pretty much make the app more reliable and the project way, way safer.
So yeah, ElementX actually has come with a lot of benefits.
First of all, on the tech side, it's way, way faster.
But because the metrics versus decay, I mean, it's amazing.
Makes things easier, both for the development standpoint, because you just write it once
and deploy it everywhere.
But at the same time, the fact that you just have your models already ready to be displayed,
it's amazing.
And also, slide-insync.
And of course, the use of the collective UIs like SwiftUI and Jetpack Compose makes development
time actually faster.
And actually, also easier to test, I would say.
But also, the UI performance also has been improved, actually.
Also sharing components is something that will benefit not only just ElementX, but pretty
much any client that wants to implement a metrics client.
But actually, we hope that some of the sharing components that we're building will not just
benefit the metrics community, but the overall open source community.
So yeah, the major benefit actually should not focus just on the main benefit that we
are offering on the tech side.
We actually want to focus on the benefit we are really offering to the users, because
in the end, the main focus element tax, yeah, it's performance, it's tech, it's sharing
performance, but of course, it's making the app more usable, more accessible, easier to
use.
We want to make an app that is not just...
We want to make an app that essentially also can be used by your friends and family to
chat with you even casually during the day.
So not just for people that essentially want to keep their conversation safe and secure
for the metrics protocol.
Roadmap.
Pretty much, this is the present and the future of element tax.
For now, you can log in, check the room list, timeline, send messages, edit, reply, react.
But there are some restrictions.
First of all, of course, as I said, sliding sync is required.
So if your server doesn't look at it as a sliding sync proxy, yeah, you can pretty much
use the client on that server.
Also it only supports authentication.
And authentication, it's only through the metrics protocol.
We want to support also IDC and registration, but when we will build the IDC component,
we will support that.
Device verification is there, but only for emoji.
So no QRV education yet.
And also no messages to the description.
Yeah, this is pretty much where you can find the element X iOS version repo.
There will be a public test flight coming soon.
And actually, Matthew, we'll demo this in...
We'll demo this this afternoon?
Okay.
That's the plan.
And regarding the element X Android, it's a bit behind the schedule because, as I say,
it was developed after element X iOS.
So it's more in a state of being set up.
But of course, you can try to run it to check the state of the repo.
If you want to play around with it, this is pretty much where you can find the actual
repo of element X Android.
This is pretty much the roadmap on what we plan to do.
It's actually more than a plan.
It's more like what we...
Let's say it's more like... it's not a deadline.
It's more like what we imagine we're able to achieve in these dates.
And I was also told to be as vague as possible.
So for the release date or the public launch, I will just say that they will come sometime
in the future.
Oh, all right.
Okay.
And that should deal with it.
So yeah, that's all.
And we can do, I think, a rapid QA session, right?
Yes.
We have 10 minutes.
Oh, okay.
Nice.
Retro schedule.
Okay.
Yeah.
It's split around.
Please go ahead.
If I remember correctly, the sliding sync option in element web said that you can't disable
it in the warning.
Why is that?
So the question is, let me repeat it for the camera.
Why can't you disable the sliding sync labs feature in the current version?
Mostly because of end-to-end encrypted messages.
You would risk being unable to decrypt your end-to-end encrypted messages in that session.
So the reason why is because when you log into the proxy, it's going to be syncing on
your account, right?
And it's going to sync forever.
Well, until the access token gets invalidated.
But it's going to be syncing on your behalf.
If you toggled sliding sync on then off, if you turned it off, then your element web would
be using the V2 sync as well as the proxy.
Because the proxy didn't know you toggled it off.
So that means you've got two sync loops for your account.
And that's going to cause problems when it causes a race condition.
Because two device messages, when they're acknowledged and they get acknowledged by
increasing the synths token, they get deleted on the server.
So if your element web was super, super fast and managed to race ahead slightly of the
proxy, then it would go and get all the two device events and the proxy would not.
Or vice versa.
And vice versa is the problem that's trying to warn against.
So if the proxy was ahead, then you would not get a certain two device events.
And therefore, you may potentially lose room keys and therefore may potentially be unable
to decrypt messages.
Hopefully that's good.
Do you have any data on whether sliding sync significantly impacts server load?
So the question is, what about server load on sliding sync?
Do we have any data?
I need clarification because do you mean at a proxy level or do you mean in like a general
sense for native implementations of the server?
Does using sliding sync improve server performance?
A native implementation, yes, it would.
So that's one of the reasons why the existing sync implementation is slow.
It's just because the servers have to do an awful lot of work.
And obviously I've been developing on Dendrite.
I know exactly what things are slow there.
So a lot of the API that's exposed to the clients are basically efficient ways that
you can do it.
So you only get the current state of rooms.
You don't tend to need to go back in time.
You don't need to remember all your synths tokens since the beginning of time.
These are things that slow down the processing.
So yes, a native implementation, but a proxy implementation obviously is a sync loop that's
going to be made so that will increase load, right?
Because that's going to be constantly syncing on your account.
In the back.
Is there any plan to handle multiple accounts in a client?
So you have like an account on your local server.
How can you use both in the same thing?
That's an element X question, I guess.
Wait, let me repeat it first.
So the question is about multi-user account support in the app.
It's something that we're discussing, but for now there is no definite plan.
Yeah, we'll do it.
It's a little cool that we don't have it today.
From the metrics SDK side, I can tell you that you can do it.
That's not an issue.
So I think you were next.
Saul, you.
So two part question, one is how far out do you think sliding sync is from actually being
like urged and finalized as a spec?
And then second part to that is are there plans to do a native implementation for those
APIs and synapse?
You want to repeat the question?
Yeah, so the question is basically how long it's going to take for sliding sync to land
and will we get native implementations and synapse?
You will get a native implementation in synapse.
I don't know when.
And yes, we're going to try to merge and land it as soon as it's practically possible, which
there's a lot of things we need to fix.
Things like threading and stuff just doesn't work.
That's actually one of the biggest blockers at the moment from us trying out just defaulting
element web to sliding sync on by default is that for compatible service, obviously,
is the fact that we don't have threading support so you wouldn't have feature parity.
So when we do have feature parity, then there could be element web clients which enable
it by default.
There could be in labs, will be enabled in labs by default.
So we're getting there, but I can't give you a time, unfortunately.
Thank you.
You're next.
I saw you.
So the question is the authentication parts in the rest of the SDK.
So yes, we have login via user name and password.
We have implemented OIDC in general, but I don't think it's fully tested.
And we have an SSO feature as well.
So we ask the server, the specification says that the server tells us what is possible.
And then we allow you to use those.
So generally, yeah, if your server is SSO, you can use metrics SDK with it.
Jan here.
Question from the internet.
I heard about them.
Are there any plans or what is the status of the matrix RTC in the RUS SDK?
So the question is about RTC in the RUS SDK.
If you followed the RTC talk before, you notice that most of the RTC part of the RTC is actually
offloaded to WebRTC in the current implementation.
So going through a web view.
For us, as RUS, that means we don't have to bother about most of that.
There's only some signaling that happens on the actual metrics protocol.
So we don't have at the moment the plan to implement an actual RTC our side.
I wouldn't see where you would want to do that for other than that view.
So currently, it's not on the roadmap, at least for our site.
Any thoughts about IoT?
Now that you have that, like users don't have the ones.
Yeah.
So that's a common one.
As RUS is very, so the question is about IoT devices.
Could you do that with RUS?
I see you can.
Yes.
That is generally possible.
We have because of the storage systems and some other things in there, and because metrics
itself is still quite heavy as an overall protocol, we have tried to get it into an
actual embedded device.
That is not at the moment possible.
We would have to improve a lot on the way that we use RUS.
RUS itself provides that, but we can't do that.
But you can use it, for example, on an Android, not an Android, you know, because there's
a, but a Raspberry Pi.
We know of people that run Raspberry Pis that have signals coming in and then they use the
RUS SDK to send it over into rooms.
That is definitely possible because it's more or less just a bot, right?
From our perspective, it's just a bot.
So that is possible, but you still need a significant amount of memory at the moment,
and that would make it not possible for actual embedded devices yet.
If anybody wants to do that, come to me.
I can show you and mentor you and help you because it would be very exciting if we had
possibility to do that.
Jan, another question from the internet?
There was a question about the element X, what you see is what you get editor.
Is it still possible to use just markdown if you want to just use markdown?
So the question is about the element X.
With your big editor, can you still use markdown if you want to use markdown?
Yeah, actually, even on the current element implementation that is on the client, you
can actually also still use markdown.
So there's an option that allows you to turn off the rich text and turn back the simple
text.
And when the simple text is on, pretty much you can use markdowns.
But when it renders, I guess, in what you see, what you get, fashion.
The question is about does the markdown then render in the WYSIWYG?
No.
When you're using the simple text version, it's rendering pretty much like a simple text
with the markdowns.
So any plans?
Or maybe in the rich text with the markdowns?
Currently not.
We're pretty much trying to build the rich text editor as it is with just the rich text
using the formatting toolbar to be the most performant and good and simple to it as possible.
But it is something that for sure when we have a very stable product, we will work into
it.
We will look into it.
No question, Amir?
Will this finally unite the markdown subtexts that you can use in different element clients?
Will that finally reduce the amount of different markdown syntaxes that you can use in element
clients?
I'm not sure about the question, actually.
Okay.
Will the WYSIWYG editor in simple text mode use one unified markdown implementation so
you don't have to remember different variants of markdown and different clients?
But you're talking if we are going in the future to support the markdowns inside the
WYSIWYG directly without turning off the rich text?
This is what you mean?
In simple text mode, if you enter markdown, will it parse the same way on element iOS,
Android, and web?
So I think there's a confusion here.
You switch on the WYSIWYG editor, then you get the WYSIWYG.
If you turn it off, you have a simple text mode.
You can do some markdown, but it's not going to be rendered inside of this.
It's going to fall back to the existing implementation.
So therefore, yeah, to answer your question, it's falling back to the existing implementation.
So no, they will still be incompatible.
We might switch to use the markdown for roundtripping, because at some point, I think this was the
previous question, that people are going to want to roundtrip between the markdown implementation
and the WYSIWYG one.
And to do that consistently, you're going to want to use the same library.
You put that in the Rust layer.
And then finally, we get out to the nightmare of common mark versus GitHub-flavored markdown
versus whatever random libraries the different element platforms have.
I think Android is still out of sync with the others.
One last question.
Where can we meet you today or maybe later if we have more questions?
I think we're going to hang around here, right?
Yeah, for sure.
We'll be able to stand.
We have a stand in K1.
I'm just going to be around here lurking, so just talk to me.
Yeah, same for me.
I'm going to be here.
I'm the guy with that hat.
All right.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.