Our next speaker is a specialist in the animation industry. Please welcome Frank Rousseau.
Thank you. So hello first them. My name is Frank Rousseau and I'm going to introduce
you to animation movie pipelines. So before going further into the presentations, I'm
going to introduce myself a little bit. I do web applications since 25 years and I do
free software as a professional activity since 10 years and I'm the founder too of a company
named CG Wire. We are a bootstrap company. We are a team of five and we do a product
that is aimed at providing project management services for animation studios and this product
is licensed under LGPL. So now let's talk about pipelines. So what you have to understand
first is that when you do an animation movie, you have to follow a very industrial process
but all the people working on it are creative people. So their main focus is to make beautiful
pictures and they don't really care about the rest. So you have to deal with that two
contradictory aspects and the first thing is to describe the main steps of the needed
to build a movie. So here I'm going to take a simple example that covers the main aspects
of a movie but of course there are subtleties for every movie. But the main idea is that
in every animation productions, you have some elements named assets that will be displayed
in the movie all along the movie and you have the shots which every time the camera frame
is changed, there is a new shot. So the movie is divided in many shots and the asset will
be used in the shots. So when you do, you build an asset, for example, a character,
you have several steps. The first one is the concept phase. It's a 2D step where you will
draw the idea of how you look at the character. Then the next step is to consist in sculpting
the character, making it in 3D. Then you have to paint it. So you have to apply textures
and physical materials. So we named that step shading and the other important step is the
shading. Basically you add bones to your mesh, to your 3D model and you make a puppet of
it. Then once you have all your elements that are animable, you are going to build your
shots. So first you have to, you need to have the animatic. The animatic is basically an
animated storyboard. So it's a super rough version of the shot. Then you go to a 3D
version of the shot, but it's still very rough, which is named the layout. It's more direct
or thin, so to check that everything is well positioned. The second and the third step
is to animate. The goal of the third step is to animate the shot. So here you have the
very precise animations. Here your shot is almost done, but you have to render it so
you add some lights and you make you bring all the elements. You need to do the render
in the same scene and then you run the rendering. Once you have the rendering, you add some
2D effects on top of it and it's a compositing step. After this step, you have the final
picture. So now I talked about 3D animations, but animations can be done in 2D. It's a very
popular style too. So here the steps are a little bit different. We still have the concept,
but then we have the design part. Basically we draw exactly the elements we need in that
step. We have two of the main elements that are used in 2D are the characters and the
backgrounds because every shot has a different background almost. And after that we have
another step where every character will describe all the poses that a character will have.
So it will be easier for the animations that will happen afterwards. And when we do the
shots, we still have this animatic step because if you remember what I said in the previous
slide, it's a 2D, it's all radio 2D operation. Then we do a kind of rough layout and then
we do the animation. The animation happens only on the traits of the elements that are
moving because you know when you see a 2D movie, you always have a beautiful background
and simpler elements that are moving. So we animate the traits, then we color them and
then there is a compositing step which assembles everything, the backgrounds, traits and colors.
And to make sure, and then it gives the final image. So now that gives you the main steps
needed to build a movie. But now the question is how we build the movie. So of course we
use software and in the animation industry there is a strong culture of IP, secret and
proprietary software. So we come from very far on this aspect. And because they are really
using this thing, it's likely things that the image should not be stolen, that they
should, it's better if no one sees the image before the images, before the movies is displayed.
And so basically they are not really friendly with everything which is a point source, but
things tend to change because of several phenomena. The first one is that Python is replacing
every proprietary script language. I didn't mention it on the slide, but FFmpeg is widely
used to do some video operations. And the Academys software foundation is maintaining
many projects around pivot file formats. So it makes easier for studios to collaborate
together. And of course we have Blender which is getting more and more adoptions, which
is getting more and more popular and which perform always better. So all these elements
combined push the industry to change its mindset about collaborations and open software.
Now there is another interesting actor, which is Krita. Krita currently is not widely used
in the industry, but we still can feel the same phenomena as with Blender. There are
tons of tutorials. The software works pretty well and it keeps on improving. There is a
good community. So we can guess that at some point we will have some interesting stuff
that will come from it. Krita is mainly used for digital painting, so it's more interesting
to end everything related to backgrounds or to do textures for 3D. So if we go back to
our building steps, we can apply, we can match a software with every step. So for the concept
we can use Krita for the modeling of Blender. As you will see, Blender is widely used to
manage most of the steps. The shading is a combination of both because Blender will manage
the materials, can handle the texture drawing too, but Krita is a little bit better for
that. For the rigging, Blender can be used. It's not an awesome software for that, but
they want to change everything for their upcoming releases. If they are able to achieve what
they want, it's going to be really awesome. For the shots, we see just right after that
it could be used for the animatic. For the layout, of course animations, it performs
very well, but there are still some steps where it's not yet the right software. For
everything related to FX, there is still a software named Udini that is widely used by
the industry and people won't change it for Blender right now. For the rendering step,
they have a very nice rendering engine, but when I talk with people from the industry
who does really, really complex images, they told me that it's not powerful enough for
the moment, especially because they don't have what we name San Assembly features. The
idea of San Assembly tools is to bring everything that is needed to build a scene, add some
light and have the capability to handle a lot of vertices and animation keys. For that,
there is no right software. There is no competing software to do that. The proprietary software
are much better. We have the same issue with compositing where there is Netrun, which is
a very interesting software, but they have governance issues. I don't know if it's still
maintained and the software currently is not as powerful as proprietary ones. About 2D,
there is something new. It is that Blender recently introduced green spins here, so it
allows to do 2D inside Blenders. It's really a huge change because prior to that, there
was no software to do 2D animations in the open source world that are efficient. Now,
it allows to use Blender on the world pipeline of a 2D production the same way as we use
it on a 3D production. There are still some limitations about every vectorized picture.
People still prefer Illustrator to Inkscape. I used Inkscape personally for some design
stuff. It works pretty well, but it seems that Illustrator is still better. Krita has
many good things, but it's still too limited. But people told me to manage big images. I'm
not sure, but this is what some people from the industry told me. Like I told you, Netrun
is nice but not as good as the competition. There is no good software for effects and
no efficiency in assembly tools. Now, let's talk about the pipeline because
I talked a lot about the building steps, but there is another important part. It is the
glue between all these steps. First, let's see this very cute rabbit because this presentation
is way too serious. I wanted to add this. It's not made with mid-journey or similar.
It's with pictures. I apologize for the author. I totally forgot to mention it and I forgot
the name. I'm really sorry for that. The rabbit is super cute.
Now we can go back to the pipeline. The first brick that is needed to build an efficient
pipeline is a production tracker. The name is very misleading because it's not about
tracking. It's about collaborating. People use it to dispatch tasks, to ship deliveries,
and then to talk around it. There are many single-page applications and they have a strong
API to allow every tool to connect to it. It's very important because there is tons
of interesting data for every user in the studio and it's important to be able to access
all of them. Basically, what allows a production tracker, it's a very simplified version, but
production managers dispatch tasks, artists do the work, direct us with the deliveries
and send feedback to artists who end the iterate together and tools grab and post new data
into it. The other main element is the asset manager.
The asset manager is basically what we... Sorry, I just do it the other way. You can see the
animation production as a big graph. Every elements are tied together, especially because
when, for instance, you do an animation, we'll need all the several models to run the animations,
but we will need specific versions of every model and you have to represent that way or
not. Every node can be considered as the element, the delivery. The links, it depends on how
you want to represent things, but the edges, sorry, can be the operations or the links
between the elements. Of course, everything is stored, every elements are stored on the
file system. Object storage could be used, but in reality, I never seen any studio using
object storage. Everything is saved on shared file system, but still it can be quickly messy,
so an abstraction is needed to manage all these files. Here is an example of graph.
I go fast because I thought that I had 25 minutes to do the presentation. I only have
20, so I'm going to go a little bit faster. Here are some examples of enforce file pass
and file names. What you have to keep in mind is that it should be configurable because
every studio has a different way to store stuff. For asset manager, it's a real challenge
to be able to manage everything. The third part of the pipeline is made of one of the
main bricks of a pipeline is the render manager. In an animation production, you have a ton
of very long jobs to process. For that, you need a render farm that will manage everything
properly and you have a tool to be able to follow each task. You have a suite of small
tools that are used in the productions to have more efficient work.
Now, because the goal of this talk is to build an open source stack for how animation production.
For the production tracker, we use Kitsu. This is a software we developed at CGWire.
With the web applications, we choose very common, very standard libraries and database
to build it. We rely a lot on FFmpeg to normalize all the videos that are passed through Kitsu.
Currently, we don't do crazy stuff with it. The only cool stuff we do is that we push
every FFmpeg jobs into an HICOP, no matter the cluster. I hope that for the future, for
the dimensions, we will be able to talk more about how we manage everything and to show
you that we do super cool stuff with it. Currently, we use it in a very simple way. We choose
a very standard stack to ensure that everyone can contribute and can deploy very easily
the applications if they don't want to use our services and its license under a VPN.
This is how it looks. We have here the list of elements to build, and here we have the
steps needed to build the elements. I won't go further on this because it will require
a full presentation. Then for the asset manager, there is a new tool that is emerging. Its
name is Heian. Formerly, it was OpenPipe. Basically, it allows us to do what I talked
about before. It allows us to manage all the files, but in an abstract way, so artists
can just manage versions and don't think about how it is stored. It comes with many tools
to push things to other tools. It looks a little bit like that. It's a little bit more
or a little bit less sexy, but it's efficient. On the left, you have the file hierarchy.
When you select a step, a building step, you have all the versioning of all the files.
Then you have all the operations you can do on files, which makes it really several times
to everyone in the studio. What you have to understand is that artists are really focused
on making beautiful pictures, but they don't. If they are not senior, they don't think about
if their production is usable by the next step. These kinds of tools, we help them to
do cleaner stuff that are reusable by their colleagues. There is another interesting software,
which is Libroflow or Cabaret. I like it especially because it's really a community thing. It was
done by a technical director in a studio named Supermonks. Another studio named Le Fespatial
used it. Together, they built that software. It's fully open source, so it's community-led.
Two previous tools are company-led, and this one is community-led, so it's very cool to
see that alternative emerging. For the render manager, we have Flaminco
by Blender Foundation, which is dedicated to small teams. We have OpenQ, which is managed
by the Academy Software Foundation, which allows bigger studio to rely on the first
solutions. Here, it's an example of a full open source pipeline, almost full open source
pipeline used by Le Fespatial on a feature film named Sciren, which will be soon in theaters.
And here, it's almost a conclusion, but here, it is how animation of open source stack.
Now we have it. It's very new for the industry, so I'm super happy to be able to show it to
you today. To conclude, now we have an open source stack
that covers almost all the use cases needed to build an animation movie. Of course, it's
mainly led by the Blender Foundation, but there are not much alternatives to Blender
and the open source work, but it's great that it exists, and the work they do is really
amazing. The pipeline stack is covered by what I described.
People don't see that aspect, and we tend to forget it. There are still some changes
in FX, vectorials, drawing, and scene assembly, and compositing, of course. But yes, soon
it will be fixed, I hope. Thank you for your attention, and if you have
any questions, I will be glad to answer after them.
Any questions from the floor? Do you think that Blender will at some point
with no geometry nodes will get to the effects of the thing it will be able to obtain?
Do you think that Blender at some point will be able to compete with Woudini?
I know they do a force on that aspect. On a regular basis, they had some features about
this. The community is very active, so at some point it could change. But I think their
focus is not on it right now, but I cannot talk for them because I'm not part of the
Blender Foundation, but we talk a lot with them. Is there any other questions?
You mentioned Krita, but not GIMP. GIMP is not a good reputation in the animation industry.
I don't understand why because it's a very nice software, but I think that people doing
very complex stuff can find what they want. But from my experience of GIMP is that they
keep on improving it. They really improved the UI, so maybe at some point we will see
more and more usage of GIMP. But I hope because I really love this software too.
Do you have similar stuff for sound?
Do we have similar stuff for sound? I don't know. We are only focused on images.
Thank you.