So our next talk is about 4K HDR video with AV1.
Please welcome Vibhuti.
Yeah, thanks.
Hi everybody.
So this is my first post-dub talk.
So the main idea for this talk is that I just want to have a brief introduction about 4K
HDR with AV1 and to know how it actually works.
That's the main idea for the talk.
And to give a brief introduction about myself, I am currently a PhD student.
My second year, currently working on video coding, trying to learn how video works.
And I'm also involved in open source multimedia since 2018.
Start with video and zip and AOM media.
So what are we going to do today?
Okay, this picture was captured when we were trying to play multiple streams at the same
time for K AV1 HDR stream.
So this was some snapshot of that.
So main idea is that we want to talk about the main technical challenges when we want
to play back AV1 streams, which is in HDR and to retain the same colors as such.
That's the main idea for the talk.
So before I get into that, I just want to have an introduction about HDR.
We all heard about that and there are multiple aspects of HDR right now, which is happening.
So first aspect of HDR is let's break down into multiple parts.
So first aspect is that it has brighter pixels.
So here is a snapshot of an image, which is tonemap down to BT7094 display.
So this is in SDR, even though the picture was in SDR.
So what happens here is that you could see, I don't know if I can see the cursor.
So somewhere here it's like super dark at like one nits and somewhere here it is super
bright at 1000 nits.
So in theory, the picture is at like 4000 nits, but our display is only capable of showing
at 1000 nits.
So that's captured at 1000.
And on comparison for a normal standard dynamic range images, it's usually in 100 to 200
nits and flat panels, more than flat panels go like 500 nits or something like that.
But in theory, HDR can go up to 10,000 nits, but most of the displays can't do that.
So second aspect of HDR is that it has more bits.
So in the, so this is a representation of same brightness in 8 bits, 8 to n SDR and
in HDR.
So you could see that there is a lot of quantization happening when it is in SDR.
So if you want to show a code something like 200 or 200 nits, you could get away with something
like 8 bits.
And when you want to go to something like 1000 nits, 8 bits is not, it's not, not to
say, it's not, we need more than 8 bits.
So that's one aspect of HDR.
So that means we need more bits.
So what happened is that we need a mechanism to combine both nits and bits.
So that's how this transfer function was born.
So what happens is that our human eyes is quite sensitive to dark and mid gray areas
and we are okay with bright sports.
So with keeping this in mind, different standard bodies and organization tried to create something
called transfer function where they tried to spend more amount of bits in the bright
and low mid gray areas and spend a lot of spend, have a coarser quantization for bright,
bright areas.
So that's how this transfer function is born.
And in HDR, one of the common thing is perceptual quantization PQ, which is based upon human
perception of banding.
So I'm not getting into details.
So main idea of HDR transfer function is this and there is multiple transfer function, but
the core idea is that spend more bits on darker and mid gray areas, right?
Then comes the color.
Color is complex.
I don't know what the color is.
So how to say is that to keep it simple and short.
So display technologies since standardization of HDR, which was like back in nineties or
early 2000, has evolved quite a lot.
And now the display technologies can, is capable of displaying more brightness and more colors
and things like that.
So if you see this diagram here, right?
So to keep it simple, what happens is that this shaded region is the standard dynamic
range and SDR range.
So that is this SDR and what happens is that in HDR domain or not in HDR, the white color
gamut domain, it is expanded to be something like this.
So it can have more wider colors to have a quick background.
So you remember the picture, which we were talking earlier about a picture, which we
are talking.
So in this picture, when we actually check the color distribution of how it is actually
spread out.
So you could see this was manually measured with the help of a color library.
So you could see that the trees and the green areas in the picture is actually beyond 709.
So in this picture, you could see that this red triangle is the standard dynamic range
in SDR and the green one is the BD2020.
You could see that the greens is in the wider region.
So the main idea to keep it simple is that there is reds and green are wider range and
blues do not change much.
So that is why most of the HDR pictures and videos which you see might have vibrant colors
with reds and green.
That is one of the main reason for that.
So now comes the question, where do you find this HDR sequences?
Again these are tone map sequences just for representation.
So in practice or in reality, this may not be how it looks.
So there are a bunch of sequences.
Netflix has raised some of the sequences as open content, which is available in public
and some other broadcasters have also published some of them, which is pretty good.
And lately, maybe like early last year, Academy and Academy Software Foundation and partnered
with American Cinematographers also produced proper cinema grading material with different
color spaces, which is also available.
I haven't tried tested that I found that like last week.
Right.
Kalayonana, let's come back to AV1.
So I had given a brief idea about HDR.
Now talking about AV1, JB has given a brief idea about the current storyline of AV1 decoding
to have a quick refresher.
So for people who didn't know, so AV1 is a current video coding standard developed
from Alliance for Open Media around 2018.
And it claims to be around 30 to 50% more efficient over predecessors.
And that's around 200 K line.
So it was an old number which I wrote.
So for the video decoding and playback, David was there.
So David is quite popular from video and released that.
And even major browsers and also operating systems supports that, including Apple.
Yeah, I don't know how to use AV1 in Apple.
No, I don't know if anyone was able to actually use AV1 in Apple, even though Apple ships
that.
So that's the storyline.
So that sounds good.
So what's the actual problem when it comes to HDR and AV1?
We see that it's able to play back and things like that.
So the problem is playing back signals, playing back HDR videos with correct metadata and
signaling them correctly on a display is not actually easy.
So if you break down into three first parties like the macOS, we know that the display
support is there, latest macOS has the support.
The OS is having support for signaling that.
That's good.
But the problem is video output drivers and playback in natively macOS is a bit problematic.
And most of the players try to do tone mapping and others try to do, others have support,
but they are very limited.
So you are not be able to actually visualize them as you want.
And in Linux, I believe we can't do because protocols are still work in progress.
And in Windows, if we see that there is display and voice level support and also players do
support that with the help of direct drivers.
So we could drive HDR playback in Windows and it works fine.
But the problem I noticed mainly was like the display transition is there when you play
an HDR window, windows try to flip from SDR to HDR that takes a few seconds and sometimes
some black screen.
So that's a problem which I noticed when you try to do in Windows.
So that's a problematic thing which I noticed.
So what we did is that we took a different approach.
So this is kind of not too many people, probably most of the people in this room.
But we took a, this is the most common approach used in broadcast and standardization body
industry.
So that we are just using playback capture, playback cards to play the video streams.
And we are using a black cards from the Blackmagic.
We use something called Decklink 8K Pro.
So it can play the streams with and it can send these signals with the help of SDI as
output and to play them, we are using FFmpeg and G Streamer for driving the playback.
So we can work in any operating system if there is SDK support for that.
So that's good.
So we found a solution for playback.
Now comes to the question like how do you display that?
So first thing is that we need to display this HDR signal with little to no changes.
So with the playback card we can send the signal, that's good.
Then we need to make sure that the TV is not doing any sort of funky things when doing
the playback because most of the TV sometimes tend to do some sort of tone mapping or try
to play with the brightness and things based upon the ambient display.
So we need to make sure that there is no sort of tone mapping and TV is not playing with
that and it should be calibrated as per standard.
So that's the other thing and it should have minimum of 1000 its brightness.
So that's the main requirement which we have for HDR testing, right?
So what we went is that we went to the reference monitor.
So we use something called Sony's reference monitor.
So that's a 32 inch OLED panel as strictly calibrated as per the standard and it ticks
all the boxes which we want and even we can force the signal metadata on the playback.
So that's good even though that's an expensive guy.
So the main idea with the reference monitor is that once we establish playback with HDR
we know that this is the source of truth or ground truth which we have.
Once we do that we can now show that this is how it actually look then we can extend
to normal consumer displays which says to have HDR support, right?
So that's good.
Now how do we say that the signal and video which we play is actually HDR or how do we
say that that's the actual thing, right?
So we need to confirm that thing.
So first thing is that we need to confirm the brightness part and so confirming the
brightness part we are using the European broadcasters has released a chart called EOTF
chart.
So it is going from 0 to 1000 nits.
You won't be able to see that here anyway.
So the idea here is that so with this chart if you play back in your stream you could
see the peak brightness which is available in your display.
So that's the first part which for confirmation for the streams.
The second part which we need to test is that what's the viewing area which you were able
to see that.
So when you're playing in a consumer TVs some TV says that they may have something like
4500 nits.
So in theory that 4500 nits, I mean in practice that 4500 nits might be only for like 2 percent
area for few minutes or few seconds of your whole screen and it goes back to something
like 2000 nits or 1500 nits on other times.
So we need to be sure that what's the actual area which you are able to show that.
So that's one thing we can use this.
So European protocols has again released bunch of test patterns which you can confirm the
maximum viewing area.
So next comes that to confirm the signal which you are sending from the screen is okay or
not.
So for that we are just using a cross converter monitor which can it's just check the existence
of the signal.
You pass through the signal through this and it just says what's the signal which you are
sending is okay or not.
This is just to make sure that the cables which you send and the is correct or not because
sometimes cable can mess with you.
So that's one thing which you can try.
Then comes the color.
This is the most important because it can play lot of tricks to you and you don't know
how what's this ground truth.
So for that in the reference if you had the privilege of reference monitor then the reference
monitor has such settings where called gamma marker.
So it's actually essentially turns this some as like something like a zebra line on top
of the screen if it is above 709 that's the main idea.
But we may not be having reference monitor all the time right.
So we need some other mechanism to validate this thing.
So we had to use some we tried to use something called spectroradiometer.
So this is a device which is used to measure something called radiance from the screen.
So with this device we can measure the color volume that is the color space and also the
brightness.
So with this device you can just point to the screen which we are playing the screen
and we know that this area might be in HDR.
So once we point to the screen and measure the color you can know that whether this is
in HDR space and what's the is the pixel above 709 or not and what's the actual brightness
which we are seeing and things like that.
Based upon the brightness it varies.
Brightness in the varies in the sense like the time it takes to capture that it varies.
So next important part is that the making sure the whole pipeline which you are using
is in 10 bit.
So this is a very important thing which might be bit tricky to see in real life because
most of the to give a background right.
So if you have a so to make this easier so the main idea here is that we make custom
code a 10 bit image having 1024 levels of the brightness.
So once you send that and if the if the whole pipeline is in 10 bit you won't be seeing
band and you will be having a smooth gradient and if it is not in 10 bit you may see some
ramps here like this.
It's not visible here so essentially you will see some ramps here.
So when in practice when you send a signal and if you try to do in consumer displays
even if you may even get the color volume and brightness and things like that but it
can be still in 8 bits that what I am talking is like it can be an 8 bit PQ.
It's a real thing.
I didn't know that when I before starting this.
So with this you can be sure the reason for saying this is that if you have some noise
in your signal and due to TVs debanding and dithering algorithm and all the other things
which I don't know what TV is doing it can make the bands not visible and it can be smooth
as this 10 bit even though the video might be in 8 bits.
So that's the main things which we focus to say that for testing the HDR things we
need to do at least one of them from for each of these things brightness, signal, color
and bit depth.
So next question comes up that can we extend this to consumer displays.
Yes we can do that because we now establish the ground tooth and it works then we can
use an SDI to HDMI converter then we can send the HD we can play it in a normal consumer
displays but that comes to the question that whether the consumer TVs can actually signal
the metadata or whether this playback card or the FMV drivers which how you play can
actually transport the metadata.
So in the TV modern consumer TVs can force the HDM metadata that's okay and if you don't
have that there is some device which we found recently but it's there in industry for many
years that's called doctor HDMI.
So this guy is like you plug in HDMI and it will insert the HDM metadata how we want with
a web server and it's like it's a magic device I would say and fun fact it can even do Dolby
vision with 8K 60 FPS it can even fake Dolby vision metadata to the TV so that TV will
be happy and this device is like less than 200 euro.
So it actually works for consumer TVs and old TVs we just have HDR this guy is magic
and most of the time many people who do HDR demos have this in the background in NAB or
IBC.
So that's one part now comes to the question that is this okay for HDR so with the HDR
right the viewing environment is crazy so that's one thing and based upon the viewing
environment you had different perception of colors so main things here is that you just
need to be sure that what's the display panel technology which you are using like I mentioned
previous test would be happy for that would be you can have some sort of confidence with
that then comes the ambient lighting condition on how you view that if your room is getting
dark and based upon your ambient lighting this varies so you need to be sure what how
what's the lighting in your room when you are watching the HDR videos and again video
materials plays an important role and lastly perception of color there different people
are different tolerance of color so that's one thing and last important fact which I
need to talk is that based upon viewing environment and certain individuals can experience different
fatigue and dizziness when you watch HDR that's a true thing and because of the super bright
and super vivid colors you need to be careful when you are watching HDR videos for a long
time so ITU has laid out some methodology when you do this for scientific testing and
subjective testing environment it's not strictly written for HDR but if you follow that it
works on big picture just keep it under 30 minutes when you watch HDR videos continuously
so this is some snapshot of how these set up scientific testing environment which we
went and when we had a person to view that this is how it happened so yeah so the main
things what I was talking here is that HDR signaling HDR metadata and things are different
and one of the main two things of HDR is that there is wide range of brightness due to different
quantization scheme and white color gamut this was an entirely different concept now
the current HDR videos and things has clubbed together and that's these current standard
says so that I enhance the colors and last thing is that setting up the whole set is
subjective testing environment and things or scientific testing environment is non-trivial
and it's accompanied by high cost even though this is standard back in like 10 years back
the whole HDR and the viewing environment plays an important role currently we are doing
some sort set of subjective test for HDR viewing and things like that so I have put some references
if you like to read more and that's it thanks would be like to hear more questions and I'm
still learning these things so I could be wrong please correct me if there is anything
wrong.
Any question in the room?
And also I have put some additional resources how you can do these things some more information
which I skipped in this thing.
Yes, not sure which pipeline I would.
Okay this one right so this one you're talking so what happens here so what here I'm trying
to convey is that the HDR videos like I mentioned earlier is coded in 10 bits or more than 10
bits so the whole pipeline which you are trying to so what have to boil down so the TVs or
some devices can decimate 2 bits and make it 8 bit when you play that it can be so you
may see in HDR in 8 bits so when you have it in 8 bits the whole nature of HDR in 8
bits you can represent 1000 nits brightness so HDR having like quite high wide range of
brightness and when you have less bits you can't actually view that so you just that's
the one thing which I mentioned here.
Yes.
Because HDR is 10 bits right now but there are plans to make 12 bits in the future.
So how are you going to extend your calibration and scientific testing equipment to code with
2 bits?
I don't know.
Can you please?
Yeah so sorry yeah so he was asking like in future HDR might become 12 bits so how am
I going to extend this whole setup for 12 bits I think that's after like six years
right yeah so probably the capture.
It is still 10 bits.
So already compliant with 12 bits.
Yeah but in.
It's also both the same capture.
Yeah okay so probably I think the capture card can do 12 bits and probably I probably
would do something similar I need to dig up how would can we actually differentiate between
10 bit and 12 bits I actually don't know.
Yeah it's difficult to differentiate with 10 bits already.
Yeah 10 bits yeah.
So probably it's going to be.
Yeah it would be bit tricky but we'll find some way for sure.
After this like if I do a waveform monitor like there are tools you'll look at the wire
on the signal.
Yeah.
You see if you look at the brain I can see the actual YE values.
Yes.
Can you repeat what he says to the mic?
Alright so he was suggesting we could use something like a waveform monitor to monitor
the signal yeah so that is part of something like this I know more advanced device can have
that so this thing is like a cheap device but even though it's one grant.
So this can show some waveforms so yeah he was suggesting we can use more advanced tools
to show waveforms.
Yeah.
Can you give us a method to repeat this setup in every other place so that you have a common
reference system.
Yeah so.
You have exactly the same calibration.
So that's a tricky thing so we know so we just so if you are repeating this for other
setups we just need to make sure that these this for some of these things are like test
patterns should be used to make sure the peak brightness is there in the maximum viewing
area then we can use the spectroradiometer to make sure that the signal is in HDR and
to so make sure that's okay and I think this is repeatable in other places even if you
don't have reference monitor because we tried this on a normal consumer device with the
same setup and it worked.
Yes.
Why is the view on less suitable for HDR?
Is it only because of the compression?
Yes I would say so and.
So, sorry sorry again so he was suggesting why is AV1 better suited for HDR?
So I don't know if AV1 is best suited for HDR also it's one of the good codec which
can do better compression so natively it can do lot of contents which is in a better quantization
and the things are which bit better compared to other codecs compared to predecessor codecs
and so due to that nature it's okay to do HDR content but still there is lot of work
to do in AV1 to be better compile and with HDR because other codecs have way better handling
for HDR because most of the codecs right now even though they have HDR they don't treat
the HDR signal or HDR videos differently.
So, it's still a research and development process currently which is happening in codec
development to treat HDR differently and AV1 is slowly trying to do that.
What are these?
So codecs in the sense like HEVC has some other extensions which can handle HDR in a
different way with help of having different quantization for colors and things like that
AV1 is slowly add so current AV1 master has that feature I believe so it's slowly in development
research and development process all right.
We still have time for one or two questions.
Is there a big difference in power consumption when a TV goes into HDR modes?
Yes, so the question he was asking is that whether is the power consumption is higher
in HDR or not I actually didn't measure but I know that when I play HDR and if I keep
my hand on top of the screen I can feel the heat.
So, the OLED is really burning so if I keep like this distance I can feel the heat in
my hand so it's really bad I would say.
Yes, so he was asking why is it.
Why is dark here?
Why is it dark more darker?
So to answer that question I was expecting this I have some.
So I have us doing a subjective test for the same thing for a dark video with bunch of
people I didn't include that this was this request more background and explanation to
explain so took so this was a dark image so this is in HDR so in actual setup and proper
environment you could see that clearly but now this is purely washed out in blacks.
So because on HDR it can do why is it like that so I don't know because in HDR you can
spend more bits right.
So people tend to focus the importance of the dark videos and things like that so I
think it's just that you can exploit the wide range of luminance and brightness and
quantization scheme of HDR when it is in dark.
So what I'm here trying to show is that this is bit complex to explain so like like the
perception of this is very hard and if you have a different lighting condition the blacks
and darks would be entirely different so I think it's just the nature of the content
and they just want to utilize the HDR to be that I'm not exactly sure how to answer that
I don't know.
So I just like this what I'm here trying to show is that even though you had different
videos with different brightness and all this is like a dark video and when people try to
view this in this environment and when you have the worst compression and the best compression
people like these are different kind of noises people just thought that they are same even
in the proper environment so that's a whole different storyline so it's a bit hard to
answer why is it is like that and how we can do that probably in another time I could explain
this in a clear way but I don't know but yeah thanks.