We'll talk about AVX-512 in FFmpeg.
He's also the co-organizer of this bedroom.
Please welcome Kirano.
So yes, I'm going to be talking about AVX-512 in FFmpeg.
What is AVX-512?
AVX stands for Advanced Vector Extensions.
There'll be a lot of acronyms and jargon, unfortunately, in this one.
But I will try and explain all of them.
So AVX-512 is a relatively new single instruction, multiple data instruction set for Intel CPUs
from about 2017 and more recently in the last six months or so with AMD CPUs.
In particular, it has a larger 512-bit register size, many new instructions, which we'll talk
about in a minute.
Top masks, we'll talk about in a minute.
Comparisons, which are quite new.
And also lots of other things that are not so interesting in multimedia.
Cryptography, neural networks, and I'm sure there are other people at FOSDEM who could
talk a lot more about these kind of things.
As I mentioned, lots of fancy words, but the thing to bear in mind is in FFmpeg, high
schoolers have gone and written assembly.
This is heavily jargon-centric.
It sounds complicated, but actually quite a big, reasonable chunk of assembly in FFmpeg
has been written by people who are in high school.
Why is this relevant now?
So yeah, I have mentioned AVX-512 has been around since 2017.
So why it's 2023?
Well, Skylake was the first CPU generation from Intel to have AVX-512 support, but it
had very large performance throttling when you use them.
So your effective CPU capability speed went down quite dramatically.
And so this was fine if you were doing high performance computing in academia, for example,
like Fluid Dynamics, where you were using these instructions 100% of the time.
That was fine.
But in multimedia is a mixture of assembly and C code, where you're not necessarily always
using these instructions.
So this relative remains unused for the last couple of years.
You could still use these new instructions, though, with the smaller register sizes.
And I'll show an example of this later.
The first Intel CPUs not to have throttling were the Ice Lake 10th and 11th Gen Intel
CPUs.
They were the first to have no throttling.
And this meant these ZMM-based instructions could be first-class citizens.
How to get started?
One of the tricky things as well in the last few years has been actually getting access
to devices that have this.
And unfortunately, Intel have not made it easy.
From their 12th generation CPUs have actually removed support in consumer equipment.
It's still available on AMD, Zen 4 CPUs, though.
And if using the cloud is your kind of thing, available also from many cloud providers in
the server CPU range, such as AWS or others.
Personally, I think the easiest way is to buy an 11th generation Intel NUC.
That's what I did for FMPG.
I bought two of them for the project and host them.
It's the easiest way.
It's only a few hundred euros.
It's quiet if it's under your desk.
And that's the easiest way to get started.
You get a full AVX-512 stack.
So let's look at some of the existing work in multimedia that's using AVX-512.
And probably most importantly, we had a sort of introduction from J.V.
earlier today, the David project, which is an AV-1 decoder.
This added AVX-512 support, I think a year or two ago.
It's particularly beneficial in AV-1 because AV-1 has large block sizes, sort of in comparison
to more traditional standards, traditional codecs like H.264 and others, which are smaller.
So AVX-512 in David gave, I think, 10% to 20% overall.
So not just the functions themselves.
The overall decode performance was improved.
And it's actually been a running topic, which is quite interesting.
AVX-264 today is an FFmpeg that we use and David and also we use this classic FFmpeg X264 approach
to assembly, which is no intrinsics, no inline assembly, no special SIMD sort of libraries
to make life easier.
It's raw assembly language.
And I'll show some examples of that.
And also we don't also compile them in and force you to have a particular CPU generation.
I know this is quite controversial.
I think it's MongoDB, for example.
They forced one year a particular CPU generation and this was super controversial because not
everybody had that.
So what we do in FFmpeg is we detect CPU capabilities and I'll show the function in a minute.
And then we use function pointers.
So we set them once at the beginning and therefore the overhead of doing that measurement is
done once, but doing the capabilities is checked once.
And then those function pointers are executed after that.
And unfortunately, though, on Intel, there's a very messy Venn diagram of capabilities.
But in practice, we really, so far, they may change their mind, but care about these kind
of two things.
So these are the CPU flags you get in FFmpeg.
There are others, but the AVX-512 related ones are broadly speaking legacy Skylake and the
newer ICL I put in bold for Icelake.
But you can see there are actually a lot of different subcategories in there.
But in practice, it's at the moment one or the other.
But as I mentioned, Intel are very keen on adding and removing features and possibly
even charging your subscription for certain features is one of their new ideas.
So it could be that newer additions to this are subscription based or you buy and pay
for it later or something much more complicated.
So who knows?
So I guess unfortunately, there's some sort of dependency in explaining a few of the topics
and some of the benefits without explaining some of the backstory.
So historically, in old AVX, you had all the 256-bit registers.
And these were split in practice into lanes.
So in practice, you've got 228-bit lanes.
And instructions, broadly speaking, operated in these lanes.
So if you ran in a structure and it worked on data and it was actually quite difficult,
it was possible but difficult to move data between these lanes.
And it's one of the historical limitations on existing AVX and AVX2 code that we have
in FMPG is lane crossing and all sorts of trickery that essentially cost CPU cycles
to take up this time.
Sorry, that takes time to compensate for the lanes.
I have to talk a bit about K-mask registers as well.
So AVX-512 has this new set of registers called K-masks, K0 to K7.
And this allows a destination register to remain unchanged.
So for example, underneath, you could have an addition but actually have a simple case
and you wouldn't, obviously, you could just add zero and it's unchanged.
But you could actually use the K-masks to say, actually, I don't want addition to be
applied to these elements.
I want this to be a pure pass-through.
Or you could even force some of the elements to zero if you wanted to.
There's a specific, I think it's a flag that lets you do that.
And there's a whole set of new instructions to go and manipulate these K-mask registers.
And certainly David, in particular, makes good use of K-masks.
So now that I've sort of explained some of the back story, I think it's fair to say one
of the most important instructions, if not the most important instruction, is a shuffle
in multimedia.
Also known as permutes.
And there might be a technical difference between a shuffle and a permute.
Someone might be able to correct me.
That might be some mathematical difference.
But these are the most important or one of the most important instructions in multimedia.
And as you can see on the right, basically, it lets you, shuffles let you have various
bits of data and rearrange them in any way that you want, duplicate them, as you can
see, or even set individual elements to zero.
And this is, for example, famously one use case of this is in the ZigZagScan of FFmpeg,
which groups a larger coefficient in a block together.
But the way that that's done is via a ZigZagScan.
The thing about VPIRM B, which is the new AVX-512 instruction, is it lets you cross
a lane.
This wasn't something that was possible in before.
And as I'll show you later, this makes things substantially faster in many cases.
PSHAF B, probably one of the most commonly used instructions in all of open source multimedia.
You do git grep, PSHAF B. There will be a huge, you know, that your screen will be full
of PSHAF Bs.
They'll be used everywhere in open source multimedia.
PSHAF B had a kind of useful benefit that if you set the index to minus one, you had
a automatically did a zeroing out.
With VPIRM B, this isn't the case.
You have to actually use a K-Masks to do that.
So that just makes things slightly more complicated.
There's all sorts of other interesting permutes that AVX-512 offers.
I think David also again makes good use of this VPIRM 2B.
So you can actually not just have one set of data, you can actually permute from two
different registers.
So you could have IJK, et cetera, et cetera, in a different register and your output could
be a mixture of both of those.
So that's kind of interesting.
Variable shifts.
You have now variable right shifts.
So I've given the example of a VPSRLVW, logical right shift, and VPSLVW, variable left shift
logical.
Big letter soup, quite confusing.
In effect, when writing this slide, I misspelt the word shift.
You can have a think about how that may have been spelt.
Thankfully the rehearsals will pick this up.
But this word soup is exceptionally confusing both when writing slides and writing code,
it seems.
So historically to do variable shifts, so if you want to take off just a step back,
take an element and shift each element by a different amount, this was quite complicated.
There's various bits of trickery, various idioms that people use to try and emulate
that, but they had limitations.
I think for example, you were not shifting by zero, possibly wasn't allowed in one of
the various bits of trickery.
And so if you needed a zero shift, you had to do it a different way, et cetera, et cetera.
But now you have this variable shift and it's all usable.
Particularly on the left shift, the naive way of doing an emulated left shift is just
to multiply, but these instructions are actually faster than to multiply, so there's still
some benefit.
VP turn log D, this is a, I think no presentation about AVX 512 could not fail to mention VP
turn log D. This instruction is literally a kitchen sink.
It's quite remarkable in what it can actually do.
You can literally program a truth table within an individual instruction itself, and in theory
could replace up to eight different instructions.
So you could do a whole presentation on VP turn log D, so I thought it would be best
to try and pick one of the simplest ones, which is a ternary operation.
So this is a bitwise equivalent to the C ternary operation.
So in each register, each bit is iterated through, and you can see, for example, one,
the ternary operation, so if that bit set chooses this or versus this, and you can see
the output of that is that.
And so essentially it's a bitwise operation of ZM zero, ZM zero is equal to ZM zero, question
mark, ZM one, ZM two, but on a bitwise level.
And there's all sorts of other interesting things you can do, and this article's very
good.
So there's all sorts of interesting things you can do, bit selects, all sorts of various
different operations that you can do, multiple XORs, for example.
So yeah, also very interesting.
So let's look at a real world example.
I don't know how well you can see that.
I was hoping the dark mode would actually make life easier, but maybe it's made things
worse.
But I'll talk about some of the, how's it going, mouse?
Is it a mouse?
No, you can't, because the mouse on the Mac is dark.
But anyway, this is V210, Inc.
It's probably one of the most simplest assembly functions in FMPEG, but what it does is it
takes three 8-bit samples from different memory locations.
Sort of as part of its work extends to 10 bits and then packs those three 10-bit words
into 32 bits.
So what's interesting in this function is we're already starting to do lane crossing
that wasn't possible before.
So we load the Y samples, so the Luma samples, into the lower 256 bits.
We do the U section of the chroma into the third or the second if zero indexed portion
of the register.
And then equally the same for the V. And then we do one, excuse me, and then one single
V perm B can rearrange all of that in one go.
This was a lot more complicated back in the olden days.
P MAD sub SW is some trickery that unfortunately is not going to be enough time to explain,
but eventually is a multiply and add and we use that to emulate a shift.
And then the, but then for the second element in the three elements we need to do a D word
shift because it actually spans the middle.
So then, but therefore then we have sort of conflicting bits in each register.
How do we do a bit selection?
And this was quite a, I think it's a two or three even operand two, three different instructions
in the previous code.
And this can now be done in a single VP turn log B. So essentially C turnery B or A. So
if bit C is set, choose the bit from B or choose it from A otherwise.
And you'll see in a second that actually provides quite a big, well certainly a measurable speed
improvement.
So these are the benchmarks.
So this is a, so I wanted to show a bit about how you can get benefits from AVX 512 even
on the older hardware with the shorter existing registers.
These are not scientifically benchmarked.
I just ran them yesterday.
When you do benchmarking you should run them 10 or 100 of times, average them, do standard
deviations, et cetera.
But just for the simple case, you can see that the C code versus the AVX2 code is around
10 times faster.
And you can see just by replacing, I think it's a set of two or three different P ANDs
or various Boolean functions, you can get a measurable increase just with a small, just
with one instruction replacing three, even on the older YM registers.
The way the big gains come are on Ice Lake.
You can see the C code versus the AVX 512 ICL.
There's a huge difference.
So by using VPIRMB and the ZMM, you can already make the legacy AVX 512 twice as fast.
And if something was 10 times faster, that now becomes 20 times faster.
And I often have to say that's not a multiply, that's a times.
So it's massive improvement.
This was code that could, if you have a large resolution file, take up an entire CPU call
and now it takes essentially 5% of a call.
It's really tiny.
What AVX 512 code is next?
Anything really that's line-based or frame-based such as filtering or scaling, I think the
next thing we're working on is deinterlacing.
Anything involving comparisons.
I haven't really talked about comparisons, but there are bits of code that often need
to do comparisons.
That's going to be an obvious place for AVX 512.
Lots of places that do triple Boolean, multiple XORs or multiple XORs and ANDs.
And I think it's almost always as possible to replace that with a VP-10 log D.
Likewise, in the code base, there's various different idioms and trickery to try and emulate
a variable left shift and right shift.
Or multiplies for the left shifts and trickery for the right shifts.
This could be used with the word suit, the sort of letter suit instructions to try and
reproduce that.
Intel provides an official manual to all of this.
It's very verbose, which is great in many cases because it provides really precise detail
of how the instructions work.
But unfortunately, it's not at all approachable.
There are a few websites that try and simplify things.
I think this website on officedaytime.com is some kind of Japanese website, but it's
in English.
It tries to group all the instructions in some kind of logical ordering, and that makes
it a lot simpler to understand.
Any questions?
Hopefully, I'll be able to answer them.
But thankfully, at Fostem, there's always somebody with more knowledge than you in the
room.
I don't know where they are, but I did see them at one point.
Thanks.
Any questions?
Yes?
Regarding the direct assembly writings of AV-X5 film, there's about 7,000 instructions
for the AV-X5 film.
One, if you choose the direct assembly, then you essentially might miss out on potential
instruction scheduling between different architectures.
You compile this might schedule better, you might get performance benefit in the future.
But then you have to ship a binary for each version.
Sorry, repeat the question.
You have to write in physics, that's what I'm saying.
In order to...
The question is, it's the classic question, can the compiler do a better job than the
human question?
In David, certainly the register allocation has not been very good in compilers historically.
David has got its own...
David has shown this quite dramatically, because it has its own custom ABI internally.
You wouldn't be able to do that with the compiler, like come up with your own internal ABI between
functions.
So there's certainly 10% plus on the individual function speed gains versus doing it in intrinsics.
Some bits of some instructions are not available in intrinsics, like always.
It's a compromise.
Overall, it's been the way in FM-PEG-X264 for the last 10 years.
And I think all intrinsics and inline assembly is banned, and there's only one or two bits
left and there's a very good reason why it needs to be there.
I have a mixed experience about this.
I agree on the...
Ideally, assembly is better, but we had some code in intrinsics, we compiled it with the
latest clunk, 15, and we saw a 15 to 20% speed increase, just for you compiling.
But did you try writing it to begin with?
Yes, it was in...
Write it originally in assembly and compare.
It wouldn't be much...
So for example, some of the bit twizzling in there, for example, a compiler would never
really have the understanding to do...
In fact, I did try chatGPT, and chatGPT at least understood a few of the concepts.
It was quite interesting, because not quite out of a day job, but it is...
I did ask chatGPT to write this function, actually, just to see what...
And it did have some vague idea what was going on.
It didn't need to be helped, which is quite interesting.
Yep.
Is there any collaboration between the multimedia of the people who write the products and
the guys writing the compiler, who tell them, look, perhaps you could target certain patterns?
So the question is, is there collaboration between people writing the compilers and multimedia
community?
Yes, in ARM in particular, I think...
Is Martin here?
No, Martin is not here, but Martin spends a lot of time talking to the compiler community
and the linker community on mostly miscompilations, is more his thing.
And I think there is also some sharing of mostly around the C code, if the C code is
badly miscompiled or thought about the wrong...
This sort of thought of the wrong approach, because you could see actually this...
And in some cases, in some versions of the compiler will really do a bad job on the C,
and it can be 40...
The assembly can be 40 times faster.
I don't know if that's something you can really trust if one day you change compiler version
and a function that you thought was immeasurable is now 40 times slower than it is.
And then the question from the internet is, did you have the occasion to look at ARMVA
SVE vector instructions for a firm peg?
Wow, there's a surprise for this person, because the next speaker is going to be talking about
this entire topic.
Where is the next speaker?
Is he here?
He's over there.
And the next speaker here, Remy, will be talking about this entire topic.
Another question in the room?
There's one there.
Yeah, I was wondering, so obviously the runtime CPU capability detection and dispatching of
the right function is desirable, but I don't think it's necessarily contradictory to having
some amount of abstraction.
Have you, for instance, looked into the highway library that is being used in some places
that is trying to provide some kind of abstraction while still allowing to do runtime dispatch?
So the question was, have you looked into some of the abstraction libraries like Highway
that's trying to do a sort of compromise between runtime dispatch and abstraction?
I think this question was already answered, I think, two presentations ago.
Not with Highway, but I think with a different SIMD library.
But there have been various approaches, LibOil, SIMDEasy, various different approaches.
And again, the result from certainly a firm peg x264, David, has been righted by hand.
It's written once, and you know almost certainly that it's going to be usable for a long time.
I didn't really talk about it, but the abstraction, there is a lightweight abstraction layer in
x264 and FMpeg to try and basically to handle 32-bit, 64-bit, and to handle other things
like the different ABI cores.
The abstraction layer kind of handles some of the future proofing in that respect.
But that's a, well, there's a blog post online from Ronald if he's here, but he's not here.
He explains some of this.
It's another presentation in itself, unfortunately.
I have a question.
For your benchmark, do you know which optimization the C code was compiled with?
Question was, for the benchmark, what optimizations were the C code compiled with?
GCC-003.
Doing versions of GCC in FMpeg test suite, there's all sorts, I think from GCC, there's
a whole range depending on the build OS, but from 4 to 12, I think.
And then maybe some people test nightly.
I think Martin certainly tests nightly for ARM.
I don't know if anyone tests nightly on x86.
Some are LVM as well.
But again, I would be very surprised if the compiler would be able to come up with something
because, like, what a human wrote, because this is involving bit properties of the actual
packing and actually the trick with PMADSW is a kind of trick to try and do a multiply
and a zeroing at the same time.
And it probably doesn't have the level of thinking to understand the bit patterns internally.
Something like chat GPT might one day, which would be quite interesting.
But I don't think the compiler does.
Last question.
I'm just going to follow up on what you said.
If you have a small algorithm, a small function like 10, 100 clients maybe, writing in assembly
might be easy.
But if you have a huge function, like a filter, a variance filter, or something, a GCT, writing
directly in assembly might take a long time.
That's why originally we write it in C and then we try to write it in easy, intrinsic.
So the question is a longer function might take a longer time to write in assembly compared
to C or intrinsic.
Yes, but there are DCTs in FMPEG, but they're macroed.
There's steps of macros to try and help that.
Again the abstraction layer also adds, I think, macros on top of what the normal assembler
does in terms of macros.
The blog post explains, but swap is kind of interesting.
It lets you swap registers, but then continue with them and the layer just handles all of
that internally.
There's also just macros for clipping.
I think it was on the example, but clip, don't worry about this.
But clip is an example.
So clipUB is a macro and on the right target set it will go and use the right clipping
functions if they're available, for example.
And there's a bunch of these, I think transpose, butterfly.
There's a few others like that.
Thank you, Kiawan.
Thank you.