I'll introduce you.
Kiran, are you ready?
Okay.
So we continue with our next talk.
Sorry for all the technical problems we have today.
Our next talk is by Michael Dobrich about modern camera handling in Chromium.
We need to move a bit.
Okay.
Thank you.
So I'll talk a bit about camera handling in Chromium.
I think Wim already teeshared some of the things at the end of his talk.
So you'll notice similarities or reoccurring things that you already mentioned.
But I'm going to dive deeper into how this actually works and the implementation, how
we got to where we are now, and what's still missing.
Okay.
So let's start a short bit above me.
I'm Michael Dobrich and I work for Pangotronics.
I'm an embedded developer, Linux embedded developer.
They're mostly doing graphics kind of things and these stuff.
Okay.
So what's right now in Chromium is basically video for Linux.
Anyone who doesn't know what video for Linux is here in the room?
A few people.
Okay.
Just a few words.
So I'm going to use the kernel API to talk to cameras or add our devices too, but in
this interesting here is camera.
It's relatively simple API, just watch the format and give me a frame.
And if you look at the Chromium code, it's, I'd say, well, there's little development,
but it's basically done.
We'll get to that information a bit later because that's why I'm mentioning it.
I mean, the camera, the API is stable, it hasn't changed a lot, then the camera is working
in the browser, so there's not much to do to change that.
And then I started with a project where I wanted to do a bit more with cameras on a
Linux system.
It was a more less embedded device and the first thing was we want to choose if an application
can use a camera and which camera it's supposed to use or allowed to use.
And that's currently not possible because Chromium directly talks with the kernel and
just picks the camera, right?
And then there were web pages that didn't have the new API to do screen sharing.
They didn't use that.
So we wanted to basically pipe in the screen as a camera into this web page.
That was mostly in the early days of the video conferencing kind of things and more the commercial
applications that they had their products ready and done and didn't want to implement
new kind of things.
It's getting less, but it's still some of the muscle out there.
And then there were some cameras that were only H.264 and that's not supported by, I
don't think any browser on Linux actually can handle H.264 only cameras in the browser.
And then I wanted to attach IP cameras.
So I have the camera maybe back there in the room and I want to use that for a camera in
a video conference call.
If you have a bigger room and they don't want to use a long USB cable, their network would
be ideal, but I can't attach an IP camera to video for Linux, right?
So that's why we're shading.
These are not exactly common use cases.
I was looking for something I could argue, what can I do to bring this to Chromium mainline?
So if I want to implement something there, I need something what's more, yeah, an excuse
exactly to say this is useful for other people too.
So I started looking and the first thing that I came across then was because I was also
looking at or had used the screen sharing part which works with the portal kind of things
and in containers.
That's what my first use case, what I said, hey, these kind of people and that's what
them mentioned earlier as well is we want to say who's allowed to use the camera.
And that was one use case I had in mind to say, hey, we need a new high level API, we
need an API where we can say outside of the browser if the browser is allowed to use the
camera.
And then while I was already implementing these kind of things, actually the camera stuff
came up.
Then also mentioned that in this talk that we have new ways to talk to cameras and there
was no backend in Chromium there and so the idea was to promote and say, hey, let's use
this shared high level API for the browsers and just plug in the camera at the backend
which by the way is already implemented because, yeah, I'll get to that in a second.
So we want to do the authorization kind of thing and we want to do high level API so
we can put something else in behind.
And the solution was already there.
As soon as I really started looking it was obvious because the XG desktop portal kind
of thing that's the portal stuff that Wim mentioned, it already had an API for camera.
It was basically not used I think.
I didn't find any real life implementations that used it in the common case but it was
already there.
And so I said, okay, let's do that.
And I already was involved with pipewire and used it for the screen sharing kind of thing.
So nothing new to me.
I said, okay, let's implement that.
And I started to implement.
But before that I want to say a bit about how it works.
So the browser needs to talk to the portal and say, hey, I access camera.
That's basically the API call to the portal and say, hey, I want to access the camera.
Am I allowed to do that?
Okay.
Yeah, you're allowed to do that.
Great.
Then, well, yeah, I need this pipewire remote to basically create the connection to the
pipewire and say, okay.
And then the portal says, okay, pipewire connect.
We want to talk to you.
And what the portal is doing then is restricting access.
So the browser won't have access to everything that's available on pipewire, but actually
only the cameras because we're only allowed access to the cameras.
There's a lot more details there in the background, but for the Chromium side for the implementation,
we don't need to care about that.
And then the portal hands over the file descriptor to Chromium and Chromium can talk to pipewire
directly and access cameras.
And then Chromium starts sending messages basically to pipewire and says, hey, we'll
need the objects and then the objects show up and I need your properties for all the
objects and basically builds up a list of cameras.
But it takes several round trips between Chromium and pipewire to get to that list.
That will be important again later as well because we're talking multiple processes here
and so it can take a bit of time.
And once we're there, the user selects a camera and says, okay, we want to start streaming,
then we'll start streaming and pipewire sends video frames over to Chromium.
That's basically the easy part at the end, although there is some format handling there
involved as well.
So okay, first try.
I was a bit naive actually at that point.
I started implementing this kind of thing that was basically two years ago and I had
more or less pull requests and it's changed set, I think.
It's changed list, CL, whatever.
And well, I posted it, I had it ready for review and there was not a lot of review going
on.
But I'm not trying to blame anyone here, but as I said at the beginning, the camera
stuff in Chromium was basically done.
So there were not a lot of people working on that.
So then you may be the Chromium camera API and video for Linux, but I had this new pipewire
portal de-burst code in there and none of the developers were actually familiar with
that kind of code.
So it was slow going, there was mostly some high level review for how the integration
worked.
And then there were some issues with, okay, this is not just Chromium, this is also Google
Chrome.
And that's a binary build that's deployed on multiple platforms, so we cannot just link
to the pipewire because it may not be there, so we need to load it dynamically.
But WebRTC, and when I talk about WebRTC in this talk, I'm talking about the implementation
used by the browsers, not the specification kind of things.
So in WebRTC, the pipewire is also loaded dynamically for the screen sharing.
That should have been the right flag for me, but I didn't notice at the time.
So basically, WebRTC tried to load the pipewire.
I tried to load the pipewire in Chromium and that clashed.
There were just architectural problems to do both at the same time.
And that's when we're stuck a bit and thinking about how to work around that issue and the
merge request basically dissolved a bit, and then someone came on the platform, Yang Ruli,
for example, and he was actually someone who knew about the pipewire stuff, about the portal
stuff, and said, hey, well, we shouldn't do that in Chromium, we should do that in WebRTC.
I said, okay, right.
I was actually sitting down with them and with Jan and Mark Foltz and a video conference
and we talked a bit about the architecture side and said, okay, WebRTC is the right place
because if I put it in WebRTC, WebRTC is also used by Firefox.
So Firefox can also use my implementation to do cameras.
So second try, do it in WebRTC.
There is already a camera API that's used by Firefox actually, and on Linux it just
implements Visual Linux.
So the idea was I put a back-end for pipewire in WebRTC and I put a back-end for WebRTC
in Chromium, basically just an indirection.
Yeah, there was an API, but there were some issues.
I mean, it was an API designed for APIs like Visual for Linux, and if you enumerate devices
in Visual for Linux, you can do that basically instantaneously.
Just open a few file descriptors, send a few Iocals and you're done.
So there was a synchronous call to give me all the cameras.
And well, as I showed before, we need to talk to the portal.
The portal may actually ask the user if the application is allowed to access the camera.
And then we need to iterate over the devices found or the cameras found in pipewires.
That's not something we can do in a synchronous function call in a browser.
So I needed a new asynchronous API to do actually this enumeration.
And then for the API was also here's the static function, give it a string as an argument
to select the camera and open this camera for me.
Same issue here, I need or similar issue related, I have this open connection to pipewire that
I need to keep open to access the camera.
Otherwise we would need to talk to the portal again, which doesn't make sense.
So basically need some state from the carried over from the enumeration of the cameras to
actually accessing the cameras.
Wasn't there either?
So needed new API.
And on the other end of the API, the frames that came out of the stack were already converted
to I for 20 some pixel format.
And this included a copy.
Basically WebRTC took the raw frame from the camera, converted or copied it to the new
format and then handed the R to the browser.
But gromium basically assumed that the camera would give it the raw frame from the camera,
converted itself or copied it.
So if I would use that API, which is basically have two copies.
Wanted to avoid that.
So I need a new API to access the raw frame from the browser.
So suddenly my single merge request to just add the camera support to chromium grew a
bit.
So I'm going to add a little bit more than that.
So right.
And at the end of the day, I wanted to do this without causing any regressions.
So the first step is we add a feature flag actually in chromium.
So if you want to use that once it's merged, it will be disabled by default at first.
So if you want to try it, you need to enable this feature flag and says we want to use
pipe wire for cameras.
Okay, if we look at that, then we go to the web RTC and ask the web RTC, hey, there is
a software search basically built what's used by the implementation in chromium and says,
okay, we want to use pipe wire.
So that's why we're going here.
There's also a video for Linux implementation.
That's not used by chromium because chromium has its own video for Linux implementation.
So this way, if we say pipe wire is not enabled, this is actually implemented for Firefox because
we may want to disable the pipe wire stuff in the web RTC from the Firefox side of things
if it's disabled there and then just go this route to the video for Linux implementation
in web RTC.
But that's not used in chromium.
So we say, okay, pipe wire is enabled, so we go here.
That port is the portal actually available.
So we have a build from chromium and at some point enable it maybe always, but still the
Linux system underneath may not have a portal implementation running.
So if that fails, we need to go back, okay, video for Linux is disabled and then we fall
back to the video for Linux implementation in chromium.
And if it works, then we ask the user that may be cached or is often cached.
So you won't see that more than once typically.
But if the user says, yes, this chromium is allowed to use the camera, then we actually
get access to the camera and here is where the pipe wire stuff actually starts.
So you need to set the switch and then hopefully have a working portal set up and then you
can use the camera this way.
Okay, where are we?
I mean, part of this talk is to raise a bit of awareness, maybe someone who can review
more things or maybe add stuff later on.
So let's talk about what's there.
First commit was split-out generic portal pipe wire code.
That was code used in the screen sharing for the portal that could also be used for camera
sharing with the portal.
So we put that in a place where it can be shared.
Then the next part was the rawframe.
I mentioned that earlier we don't want to do the double copy.
That was basically adding a bit of new API.
Then merged I think just two days ago is the actual pipe wire portal capture support within
WebRTC.
That was merged just a few days ago.
So the WebRTC is mostly done.
I'm not sure what Firefox will do.
Basically it's ready for Firefox people to implement things in Firefox.
So I don't know if someone was working on it.
If not, maybe someone here is interested in that so they can do that part.
There is basically just a small merge request left because all this camera kind of things
in WebRTC is not actually built right now if we're building WebRTC for Chromium.
So we need just to do an infrastructure a bit, build these files as well.
That's all the WebRTC is designed.
When we come to Chromium, and in Chromium there are two commits pending.
None of them have been merged yet.
The first is basically, well there is this Linux camera back end right now in Chromium,
which is Vigifilinux back end.
So basically rename it from Linux to Vigifilinux, place a switch in front of it.
That's where this feature flag comes in where I say, okay, can we do a portal or not?
We make space to put a separate back end there next to it.
The second commit is the actual implementation.
Once that's merged, then we actually have the full support.
Hopefully that happens in the next few.
Well, weeks is probably a bit optimistic, but months.
Okay.
What's next?
So for me, I probably won't work on these things in the near future because this was
done for a customer project and it's taken a long time and they're getting, well, they've
been good support about this.
So it's really, there was no complaining, but I do need to get on with other things.
I haven't done this full time.
This was always, I do a bit, then wait for revenue, then get some revenue.
So these kind of things.
But I need to get this finished up, but there are more features to come.
There is some new XG Desktop portal device API.
It was mentioned on one of my merge requests that there's some API stuff coming that's
still not merged.
There's some requests, but once that's in, the idea would be to support that to access
cameras.
And then there are some more features that Chromium supports for cameras like rotation
that are not yet supported by the new backend.
I'm not sure if the whole stack below that already supports all of it.
I'm pretty sure that Pipewire does.
I'm not quite certain, but I think so.
There is API in WebRTC for rotation.
So I think it mostly needs to be hooked up.
So we can rotate the camera image from 90, 180 or 270 degrees.
And then there are also features, basically if you know, with your for Linux, they have
the controls to do panning, tilting, zooming, focus handling, whatever.
And a few of those things are integrated in Chromium as basically image properties, I
think.
And they are hooked up in the for Linux backend.
But I don't think there is an API in Pipewire to access that.
I'm not quite sure.
So maybe we need to add it to the whole stack.
So there's some work to be done there as well.
But my hope is that at some point that gets added and then we can really switch the Pipewire
camera on as default in Chromium.
Because I don't think it will be accepted as a default unless we have a more or less
basic feature parity there.
So still work to be done.
So hopefully maybe someone got interested and will help out there.
Okay.
A few thanks.
That's my customer who sponsored this work.
So I'll put them here there.
Jan Grulich and Mark Fols, they actually got the revenue started because once they got
involved and noticed my patches, they found people that actually could press the necessary
buttons on the review and say, okay, this is accepted.
And they did a lot of review there.
Talked to me about the architecture.
So they helped me get on with it.
And Ilya Adonkalani and Alex Cooper, they did a lot of review as well.
And Kirian Bingham, he's doing a lot of the camera work.
And my work actually last year on the ELC.
But he's done a lot of testing because he's trying out his camera stuff in combination
with the Chromium patches.
So a lot of testing and review there as well.
And probably a few more reviewers that I missed.
I just went over the list.
People that said something on the request went to the longest.
Those seemed to be the most common here.
Okay.
I'm almost done, so I'll come to a question in a second.
So yeah, like everybody we're hiring, all of our companies need good people.
Okay.
So thanks and questions.
So I'll start with you.
Yeah, just a comment that Kirian is going to give a talk on LibCamera in one hour in
the 7-hour room.
Yeah, okay.
So we're giving a talk about LibCamera in which that embedded an automotive room.
So maybe I'll be there.
Exactly.
So any other questions?
Okay, here.
I just want to comment on the discussion for all the bits.
How do we need to keep an eye on the questions from the
director of the webinar?
I don't, if there's a page for all the bits.
I don't have any web page or anything for that, but if you basically subscribe to the
last one, that's the one where it gets interesting, right?
Okay.
Any other questions?
And we're done.