Okay, let's start. So our next talk is about the FSD1 ecosystem done by someone who knows
that very well. Please welcome Jerome. Hello. A bit sooner than Baptiste said, but we don't
speak enough about FFmpeg, so we'll speak about FFmpeg a bit more, but not about a very fancy
codecs. The word is about the lossy compression H265, VVC or AV1, but we will speak about something
a bit more boring. It is the lossless compression. Because some people need to do some broadcasting
and just broadcast and forget the content. People can watch and have a lot of compression
artifacts. If it is visually lossless or if visually it is not so high level of artifacts,
it is fine. But for some other people, having a lossless video coding format is very important.
And also something open, so no patterns and so on. So FFV1 fits a lot of things about that. It is
a very old technology, more than 30 years old technology, so no pattern for sure. There is also
a good reference encoder and decoder. It is FFmpeg. Thank you, FFmpeg. It is widespread, so a lot of
people can use it. We can embed FFV1 in a lot of different containers. The most used are AVI for
all people, MP4, Matroska, MxF also. And FFV1 has a good balance between compression and speed
and also a bit about cost. Because there are some competitions, some open formats, also in FFmpeg,
they can have a good compression, but they are very slow or the compression is not so good.
And outside of FFmpeg, we have JPEG 2000, for example, but encoders are pretty expensive
sometimes and so on. But FFV1 is natively in FFmpeg, the compression is good, the speed
for a lossless format is not so bad. So we use it a lot in some configurations.
Especially because we've opened an open format and an open source implementation,
it is easy to expand depending on the need we have. So with FFmpeg, we have only black and white
or YUV or RGB, and we can also add an alpha journal. We can expand it up to 16 bits per component.
So from 8 to 16, and also if we need 12 or 10, we can adapt a lot of FFV1 format for
being able to support every input we need. With the latest development a few years ago,
we have also a good multi-freed system in FFV1. We have checksum, so we are sure that
when we store the content, we can detect if there is a problem during the storage.
A lot of work was done by Michael Nider-Mayer a few years ago, so he is a main developer of FFV1.
So thank you to him about that. It helped a lot. So we are aware that, yeah, lossless
compression is a very niche market because not so many people need it compared to the
broadcasting or the lossless compression like H264 or AV1 and so on. And these people who need that
are not rich, but it is pretty important for them to have a lossless compression.
And also, actually, it is also for us important because a lot of users who need
lossless compression work in archives so far our heritage in 100, 1000 years, we need to have the
content. And for that also, it is important to keep the content as the best possible.
So no compression artifacts. It is the reason these people, they want no compression, no
lossy compression. And in this niche market from archives, some entities discovered that
paying for FFV1 development inside FFmpeg, for example, is a lot less costly than buying
products on the shelves. Even if the product are there, when you buy a product, it is pretty
expensive. It is a package. You need to buy a package. And actually, if we take this money
and don't buy the products on the shelves and we develop a product inside FFmpeg, it is less costly.
And then after that, other entities discovered that, oh, it is an FFmpeg and it is open,
it is free, off-charge, no patent. The software is also free, open source and free. And there
are a lot of workers for them too. So it is very good for these people. They are not rich. They
need to have this lossless compression and FFmpeg is perfect for that. But yeah, they need to trust
that this choice is sustainable and FFV1 is in FFmpeg, but it is not a standard. So
the archive wanted to have more trust in the format. So it is not only about code, but we need
also to have a standard, for example. And there was a work by the Open Union and there was a project
called Preformer to help archive to have checks on their file. And for the documents in archive,
it was easy, PDF, it is a nice standard, fine. For images, when they do scan, it is also not so bad.
They have TIFF, it is a nice standard, it is good. But now they have a lot of AV content. And for that,
there was no open and standardized format. So they decided to sponsor some work on Matroska and FFV1
and PCM for the audio. So no format for that. So we tried to work with Preformer and we
helped to create an ITF working group. And why ITF and not ISO or SMBTE is mainly because ITF has
no payroll for the standards. So it is very useful for people who are not rich,
a lot of archive are very small. They don't have the money to pay a lot of different standards
and so on. And also, ITF is very welcoming new people, helping them to create a new standard.
So thank you to ITF for that. On our site, we focused on different formats. So Matroska for
the container part, FFV1 for the video part and also for some lossless audio compression flag.
So now with ITF, we are working well. It is a bit slow because we are mostly now volunteers,
but we are still working inside the CELAR working group. So Matroska,
it is still a work in progress. Some part, EBML, the base of Matroska is already published.
It is an AIFC. So it is good. Now we are working on the core of Matroska.
It is on the way and then we will work on the codec, on the tags part and so on.
A lot of work is done by Steve Lom. Thank you to him. And thank you, Steve, you are there.
Also for FFV1, we worked on having a standard. So now the version 0, 1 and 3 are published.
It is an AIFC. So people are more confident in that. And we want to have also FFV1 version 4,
but we still need more development about that. About the flag, the audio part,
it is still on the way. There is an ITF last call. So the specification is nearly ready,
but there is still some review by the ITF to do. So Martin is working a lot on that.
And we hope to have the AIFC maybe next month.
But for video formats, it is not only in the ITF world, it is not only Matroska.
We also need to have it accepted a bit more everywhere. So we asked to SMT to accept FFV1
in MXF. So it is not something easy because SMT you need to register and you need to pay a lot
and so on. But thanks to the Library of Congress, they wanted that to replace JPEG 2000 by FFV1.
So they worked with SMT and now FFV1 is officially supported by MXF. So it is not a standard,
but it is a RDD. So register, disclosure document, a bit like a poor eyes in MXF.
We have the universal label from MXF available for FFV1. It is not a hack. It is registered in
the SMT. So FFV1 is not only in FFmpeg and not only in Matroska. It is also in other containers
and not only the one used on the web. It is also used in MXF. So more for broadcasting.
FFmpeg has support of FFV1 in MXF for demuxing for the moment. And we sent a patch for the
mux in on FFmpeg level. So it is on the way to have a good support of FFV1 in MXF inside FFmpeg
directly. For the archive, it is not only about storing the files. It is also being sure that the
files are perfect compared to the specifications. So we work with an ecosystem. So it is not only
the code. So we create a file and then we put in the storage. We want to be sure that
later it will be readable because it is not just immediate usage. It is for the future. So
a lot of people need to be sure that the file is fine. So we created a conformance checker
called MediaCrunch. And based on the specification from Matroska and FFV1, for example, we can say
that the file is conformed or not to the specification. And before putting the file in
the storage, we are sure that the file is conformed to specifications so that it will be easy to read
it later. But sometimes in the archive, we have different inputs with very different formats and
with some proprietary formats, sometimes about less storage. So for the archive, it is very
difficult to be sure that in 100 years, they will be able to play a file with a codec
available for Windows 95, for example, and it is only 32 bits and it is only for Intel CPU,
but maybe in 100 years, there will be only an ARIN. So it is better to convert. And for that,
a lot of people are using FFmpeg. So thank you, FFmpeg, for that. And archives, the Film Institute,
and so on, they use FFmpeg. They don't develop FFmpeg, but the community needs also to do some
scripts. So they publish scripts about how to use FFmpeg. So we have two examples there about how
archives are using FFmpeg for doing the transcoding. Another practical usage in Film Archives
is that usually they receive from the scanner, the PIX files. So they don't have only one file,
they have one file per image. So it is totally crazy for the file system. And it is difficult
to store. It is very huge. There is no compression and so on. So we can help with open source formats.
So with Matroska, FFV1, and Flak, why not? It is still huge because it is lossless compression.
But dividing by two, the cost of the storage is good to take when you have petabytes of content.
The issue is that not all workflow accept FFV1 and Matroska. So we need something
for doing the conversion between DPX and FFV1. There is sometimes some legal commitments. It is
a bit crazy, but we need to have the exact same file. So if a DPX file comes in, the legal
requirement is to provide the DPX file when it is requested by the state, for example.
So far the compression is not so good because FFV1 compresses the video, but not the DPX header,
for example. So we need a bigger ecosystem than FFV1 alone because FFV1 is about the video
compression, but not everything besides the video content. So we created a tool called Rokukt.
This tool fills the gap between what exists, FFmpeg, and what is needed to save the
DPX header, for example. So with Rokukt, we take the DPX header, we store it in an attachment in
Matroska. So it is also useful to have an open source container format because we can expand it
and so on very easily. And we send the video content to FFmpeg. FFmpeg does the compression.
And besides that, when we need again the DPX, we decode with FFmpeg, we inject again the DPX header,
and we create from that the exact source file. So we have this ecosystem around FFV1, and we want
to expand it to have... What could we do with that? If everyone is good, but speed... Okay,
it is good, but we could be better, maybe. We want to expand the decoder, and encoder
maybe with SIMP or GPU acceleration, but we need to work on that. And then maybe if we have
overnight, we will create FFV1 version 4 inside the IETF system. So as a summary, code is important.
For example, FFmpeg has a very good FV1 encoder and decoder, but it is not enough because we need
to make user communicate and to share the scripts. We need to have a format reviewed
by a standardization body to be sure that the format is fine. With the IETF, when we worked
on having a standard about FFV1, for example, we found some bugs in the reference encoder.
So it was good to have reviewers about that. And we create for that a big committee, not only about
the code, the FFV1 code, but also the users. And with that, we show that open source can also help
about niche needs and not only broadcasting and the big things like YouTube and so on.
It is finished. So if you have questions.
So the main increase was about speed coding. I had that question since before. So maybe the
next version could be comparable to JPEG access. You mean maybe JPEG Excel? There is an access.
Yes, exactly. How is it comparable to JPEG access? So if it is, there was some discussion
between us and JPEG access developers. So JPEG access is actually a bit based of FFV1. The developer
took part of JPEG 2000 and also part of FFV1 for creating JPEG2 access. So there was a path
between something from FFV1 actually in JPEG access. JPEG access is also open, but the
specification is not open also. For FFV1, the specification at IETF, there is a copyright on it
and you cannot modify it. But the version in our GitHub is totally open source also. It is
creative command license. So also a big difference between FFV1 and JPEG access is that
FFV1 is easier to understand about the compression mechanism and also that the specification license
is open also. And for us, it is very important that everything is open, not only the compression
and the decompression, but also the specification. But we need to do more performance comparison
between speed or compression efficiency with JPEG access for sure.
Just to continue on JPEG access, there is also the issue that JPEG access is not royalty free.
So that also is a consideration. But
there is an issue about JPEG access about
royalty. It is not completely sure about there is some risk about patterns, but the
JPEG access developers wanted that it is more or less free. So there is a discussion about that.
But it is based on JPEG 2000 and there was some risk of patterns with JPEG 2000, but the lossless
part of JPEG 2000. So there is exactly some risk about patterns in the compression system.
With FFV1, we are completely sure that there is no pattern because we created nothing about that.
So I didn't really have a question, but I just want to thank the FFV1 project because it was,
I made a free lossless image format at Flip and was quite inspired by FFV1 in the sense of the
entropy coding and the context modeling that is going on there. It was inspired by FFV1. And now
how these things have moved from Flip to JPEG Excel, which is other JPEG standard,
where some of the context modeling of FFV1 actually is used in JPEG Excel as well.
So the remark was about FFV1 helped to create Flip and then JPEG Excel. So it is part, FFV1 was
maybe, yeah, maybe I misunderstood. You talk about JPEG access and I mix up with JPEG Excel.
I wanted to say about JPEG Excel. So sorry about the confusion. So the names are confusing.
So FFV1 was the base of JPEG Excel and now we need to do some comparison between what
is FFV1 now and what if JPEG Excel can help more than FFV1. But for the moment,
it is pretty important for us to have open specifications and not behind the payroll.
So with IETF for us, it is very important to have that.
Yeah, I agree that IETF is much better in that regard than ISO, which puts all the specifications
behind the payroll, which is not helpful. Yeah, one other issue with JPEG Excel is the payroll.
Another question. In comparison to raw video, what kind of compression ratio can someone tap?
We, the compression ratio is between one to three, between half. The average is half.
Sometimes it is a third, sometimes a bit more. But the average compression ratio is dividing
by two, the storage cost. Is the algorithm itself extensible? In the future, let's say you have a
new compression algorithm that gets better ratios. Can you switch that? We could switch. FFV1
is based off the range coder for the moment, but if we find something better, we could switch.
There is a discussion for FFV1 version 4 about what to use instead.
Is there a theoretical limit on how much you can divide the file based on the information of,
for example, the video? Is there a limit about the compression ratio? It is more that the content
itself we need to avoid to lose a pixel. So if you have a black frame, it is very, very small.
So the range coder, you can store in two bytes. If it is only black, it will be repeated and there
is no bit consuming about that. But this is not a use case we have in reality.
How does the output file size compare with other codecs that use high-quality parameters?
Compared to lossy compression, you mean a lot. The files are, if you have...