the
if you already all I've found to this year.
Yes.
So we go on with our next speaker,
Mikaeli, who is talk to us about the FBI improved image viewer.
Please welcome Mikaeli.
So welcome to my talk about using the film image viewer.
Around 2006, I was a user of FBI,
the image viewer for the Linux frame buffer.
I was fond of it, but at some point I thought I really need to
have the VIM arrow keys into FBI,
and I made a patch to FBI.
At some point, I started realizing that I need something more,
like some shortcuts,
bindings, or a small command line,
commands, at some point a parser,
autocompletion.
So hack after hack,
a fork came out of FBI,
which I called film.
So something which takes inspiration from the VIM text editor,
the map, mail user,
and well, sorry, mail user agent,
and the shell languages.
So what is nowadays film?
It's a Unix tool, a Unix tool for one task.
One task which is viewing images.
It's not editing images, so many people confound this.
It's for command line users,
people who like using the keyboard.
It has a configuration file,
because it's nice to configure custom commands.
It uses regular expressions, standard inputs, standard output,
and it plays nice in scripts.
So it's highly interoperable.
The Amoto is like in parallel,
like in parallel, there is more than one way to do it.
I think film plays well with all the hardware.
There are functionalities for caching files or
image from files to load them in advance via prefetching,
so to spare a bit of IO.
The user interface is quite minimal,
so there are no menus,
no buttons, sorry, at the moment.
It works at the moment with four outputs,
graphical outputs styles.
So pixels with X11,
pixels with Linux frame buffer,
and ASCII art with and without color.
It plays a bit nice under SSH or screen in different situations.
So on this picture here, you say a pixel mode,
character mode, and other character modes without the colors.
So you select this when you start the program,
or you let it just being
auto-detected by the environment variables.
The basic invocation of film is more or
less like what you expect from most programs.
So you specify the files you want to open,
and in the case of graphical files,
the magic number will determine which decoder to use,
not the file extension.
However, if you want to open a directory,
or recursively three of directories,
or perhaps even with a background load function,
then filtering on file names will occur.
Again, it's quite intuitive what
the plus minus page up, page down keys do.
So it's what you expect, and this is good.
What they do, usually, of course,
the binding is dynamic,
so you can configure film to do different things.
The defaults are for plus to call the magnify command,
the internal magnify command,
for minus the reduce command,
or apart from commands,
you have also small actions which can be longer,
can be like a concatenation of,
let's say, command argument,
or even a small control flow expression.
So it's quite rich,
what you can assign to single keys.
So in general, this language which I show here in
this red boxes, it lives in the command line.
The command line which hosts this language,
which you can also access with the column key,
just like in VIM, and just like in VIM and other
other softwares with the tab,
you might get some auto-completion of, I don't know,
commands, variable names.
It's not science fiction,
so it can be helpful.
Yeah, and this is the same language that you also use in
the configuration files and scripts.
So that is the film language.
The language elements of film are commands,
alliances, which you can customize,
variables built-in or customizable,
if-while blocks, so to have a bit of control,
and some special syntax like
shortcut expressions or shortcut statements
for some other precise things.
How do I use film?
I don't spend much time programming it,
or programming the usage of film.
Most of the time, I use it
interactively as any other image viewer.
Especially to organize pictures collections,
like I will show later.
Occasionally, I use the special functionality.
So what is really unique to film or the command line,
it's quite rarely when I come up with
some nice workflow which I like.
Yes, then I exchange the configuration file,
or even made, I do an alias in the shell
to reuse some special way of calling film,
which is for me, which is customized for me.
So now we will continue with this talk.
I just wanted to mention that another talk,
which has been recorded,
will go into language-specific topics.
That is a bit more nerdy than this.
This talk here goes about the interactive usage of film.
This is not really a tutorial,
it's not really the documentation,
it's a bit of a showcase,
what I will be showing here.
So I said, film is programmable,
but you don't want to program it here at
this in what I'm showing you here,
but still you want to use a bit of automation.
The base level of automation is
perhaps to simulate a key press.
So when you invoke film and specify minus K,
the name of a character or of a key press, that will happen.
So as you press that key.
So for R, we'll rotate.
I mean, this is what will happen just after startup.
Afterwards, you are in control.
So with R, we'd rotate,
with delete, we'll delete the first image from the list,
with CH, control H,
we'll make help pop up and so on.
You can go further with minus upper case K,
so with key combos.
So if you specify minus big K,
RA, rotate, and auto-scale,
that will happen as the first thing with film starts once.
So afterwards, you're in control.
In VIM, I appreciate that when you're about to press a key,
and you prepend it with a digit or more digits,
the number that you will have specified,
will specify also the repetition of what is about to be done.
So you have this also here.
Of course, now I'm showing you here the command line,
but this is the interactive usage.
So should we do it interactively, this is what happens.
It's the same interpreter who processes this.
But there's also the dot modifier in VIM,
and also here, that instead of repeating twice a particular command,
you can add a dot after what you have just done,
and it will just repeat the last action.
So plus dot, it's like plus plus.
Now, you can combine this with the number syntax.
So if you prepend a number to the dot,
the dot will repeat the last command,
that number, that amount of times.
So this can spare you a bit of typing interactively,
but also in this special mode here.
Of course, this just applies to the last command,
not to the last combo or last series of things.
For more complicated things,
you can use another mechanism,
which is that of simply configuring your VIMrc file,
and there you perhaps bind
a particular keyboard key to a special command.
Then yes, you can use a repetition on that combo which you like,
which is what is useful to you,
and that's the way to go.
So not over-complicate unnecessary things.
Now, I will show random functionality which I like in VIM,
or I didn't bother looking in other image viewers.
So with the double apostrophe,
I have the so-called shadow directory load, let's say.
So my observation is that nowadays,
cameras have a very high resolution.
I don't need that resolution.
Mostly, the pictures which come from
those cameras are too heavy for my purposes.
So what I do is that I have a directory with reductions,
which fit more or less my screen,
and I have another directory with
the heavy image original pictures.
But with VIM, I just say,
hey VIM, in that directory are the originals,
the heavy originals. So be aware of this.
Then VIM offers me the double apostrophe,
the double quote key,
which does something which I forgot what it is,
but you can just check it up with the help.
That will substitute the content of the images,
of the current images with image with a high resolution,
or low resolution, or whatever you have set it up.
So it's a way to substitute it.
Probably, you can use it to create funny games or whatever,
but for me, it's just the purpose of substituting
the low resolution image with the high resolution image.
Because I like using used computers.
I think there's too much garbage on this earth,
and therefore, sometimes I don't need
that extra heavy processing in my everyday usage.
I think this can help many users.
Another thing which is perhaps unique maybe,
it's a simple key to jump
between the last view and the current view.
Why? Because sometimes I watched 100 pictures,
I do a selection of the few pictures I really like,
and I jump between them because I want to see
certain detail from one side, from the other side.
So I like to jump a lot of times between two pictures,
perhaps to catch some detail,
and therefore, I have this key which most of the times,
I would say retains the position you were and the scaling.
So it's really for comparing things.
I find it useful, especially in combination,
as I said, with the short listing functionality
which allows you to make selections.
To shorten the selection of pictures.
Now, another random functionality
is the one of conversion pipelines.
Sometimes you want to load things which are not
properly pixel images like SVG files or PDFs or post-clip files.
There are a few built-in defaults in
theme which will invoke that external program
to convert it in something that theme can view.
So this enlarges the set of
the picture formats which you can watch under theme.
Extending this idea, perhaps sometimes you want to view
all of the images which you are about to load
with one specific filter pipeline.
Here I have shown convert with charcoal filter and
put a label on the bottom.
Yeah, you can specify that to theme when you start it,
and all of the pictures which you will see in
that session will be filtered according that way.
I don't know what this is useful for.
Previews, making fun, you choose it.
But the point is, if you don't screw up this expression,
you will not write to any file,
so just temporary files will be modified.
You can interact with different programs in different situations.
Sometimes you can use the exclamation point syntax to call
an external program and then we
have external program that gets its output.
Okay, it's not that useful.
But still, if you go the dangerous way,
you are not afraid, you create an alias which maybe
calls in the end ExifTool and you say ExifTool,
please remove the ExifData from the file which I'm just watching,
because you can specify that file as an internal variable.
Yes, you will modify the current file, which is dangerous.
You should not do it, but if you really want and you are
automating some nice useful workflow, you can do it.
I have warned you. Okay.
Did you know that with film,
you can even load files from a file name list?
Okay, this sounds boring.
Sounds boring, but maybe it's nicer if you learn that with film,
you can write files with the file name and the description.
Okay, maybe it could be even useful in a few situations.
In my case, I find it useful or I like it
because film has a few captions in
different parts of the displayed window, let's say.
There are a few variables with expando codes,
so like percentage and something.
So you can customize them.
You can view, I don't know,
the comment which are the description which I said before,
or other information.
So you can customize it a bit the way you want it.
More, you can have in this description file,
internal variables. So just for the purpose of giving
attributes to the files you're about to have in the list.
So not only the descriptions, but also attributes.
So the bill will be in the category businessman.
Arun as best, the Brahmin Richard will be in the category activist.
So they will inherit this, those attributes.
Furthermore, there are some shortcut syntaxes
which prepend text to this description,
or allow referring to specific variables in
those descriptions for the purpose of making them shorter.
What you can use it for apart from the caption.
Well, you can use them also for searching
the picture in the file list.
So with the go to command,
or you use a special slash or question mark syntax,
not command line, but search line,
to search and to jump directly to a file which has a description that way.
So if you manage your picture's collection nicely, it can be useful.
For me, it's nice because I have my picture
targeted that way and I'm happy with that.
Or I have custom collections of pictures that way for my own amusement.
Yes. So you have this go to command,
which you can use also in other ways like jumping or controlling it to jump
according to the values of those property variables.
Or you can use this go to jump between to the next directory for instance.
If you load like 1,000 files in different directories where they are,
you can use go to and something very specific,
which you find in the manual,
and this will jump to the next directory inside what is being loaded there.
So there are many shortcuts, let's say,
for doing very specific jumps according to your workflow,
because this is to adapt the way you wish to organize your stuff.
Of course, if you have different specifications to the go to command,
the first one which matches the jump will do the jump.
Before the session is over,
I wish to say the limit functionality,
which I took from Matt.
I find it also useful because you can shrink the collection.
For instance, I have around 20,000 pictures in my photograph collections,
but I can limit them for instance to city equal Brussels
or something like this which is useful to me.
In this case, you see that we have shortened the pictures list from the five,
total five to four,
which matches category equal activist.
Yeah, further, the limit command can do shrink the list
according to duplicate the base file names or the date of the files
or the size of the files.
The base idea of film is that you use it interactively.
You have a few alliances which you perhaps sometimes customize
and assign to specific keys which you like to have.
Yeah, and you write this in the configuration file
and you perhaps share it with others.
You just remember by heart the commands which you use every day.
That's all. So, film at the moment,
I will be releasing the 06 after 15 years,
the 06 version in a few days.
The tarball is out there.
I have to do some promotion and especially I have to say,
give the next version to the Debian guys.
So, there is the version on Debian and everywhere else is old,
but we'll update it soon.
The manual has everything, so everything is written there.
And I hope you enjoy film and perhaps watch the other recording
with more nerdy language aspects.
That's all. Thank you for your attention.
Hello, Ernie.
So, we have some time for questions.
Is there any questions on the floor?
Yeah, so, the collection stuff sounds particularly interesting.
Can you update the collection from film itself?
So, while you're watching it, you'll tag an image so that
while you're watching images, you will update your collection
from within film somehow?
Perhaps. At the moment, I don't have this.
You've write a text file in your...
I'll take a question because they don't hear.
The question was whether film, as I have written,
organised a picture, organised a...
I wrote it correctly. No, I wrote a...
It was a mistake. Film is not an organised.
You have to organise the files by yourself with a text editor.
We have a non-line question here, if you can read it.
Thank you for the talk.
Is there a way, plan, to have a way for film to script
a small step-by-step animation of the actions?
Maybe some sort of slip between the actions.
Yes, there is a functionality which is called...
recording out or something like this.
So, after you exit film on the stand-aloud,
in a specific file,
actions and commands...
Sorry, and timings will be speeded out.
So, there is a slip command which says slip, I don't know,
three quarters of a second, something like this.
Yes, there are three... Yes.
Question on the floor?
Yeah, good question.
What about the descriptions?
Are stored in the same image file?
Are they stored like metadata in the files?
Can they be read by exit tools?
What I have shown here was just the plain things
you write in a textual file.
So, yeah, it takes the...
Apart from this, the exit tags from JPEGs,
or I don't know, I think in other places also you have
exit data, but at least for JPEGs, are being read
and they become internal variables in set film
because I really like to have some particular JPEG
exit data being displayed in the caption
and that occurs there.
Actually, also PNGs and also JPEGs
without exit have commands.
This also drift here.
Yeah, so there are different...
I don't think I'm covering everything, everything, everything,
but as soon as I learn of some extra metadata,
I integrate it into internal variables
associated to each file.
I have one extra slide.
Any other question maybe?
Maybe I didn't have an understanding so much.
The result of modifying this file is...
Modifying which file?
The original file.
Is there still another file?
We don't modify any file with film.
If you do it, it's a mistake.
Ah, OK.
There was one example where I was saying
you can write programs to modify the file,
but most of the times you don't want this.
But if you really want it, you can.
If the file is changed on disk, will film reload it
automatically or will it...
I think there is such a functionality.
Maybe the question is, if you are stuck on a picture
and the picture changes, will the film reload it?
There is some functionality to detect this.
I'm not sure if at the moment it's at default.
In principle, it's like two lines of code.
It's easy to implement this.
I think this is for picture frame situations
where many people use film for picture frames.
I'm not happy with that.
I wish people to use it interactively.
But yes, that's possible.
If you want, I have one extra slide.
So with film, you can even play the little
steganographer or the little forensic investigator
by using the offset switch or the seek magic
internal variable, which do nothing else and saying,
hey, please, don't seek for the image at byte zero.
Between here and here, the picture is there in the file.
So you can use this for looking for the signatures
within the file, which maybe is broken.
Maybe there are a few files which we
concatenate for some reasons.
Maybe it's a tar archive, which actually...
Sorry?
I have an example of this.
So if you look at your Chrome cache, Chrome browser cache,
you have binary files which are a concatenation of HTTP
headers and image file.
And right now, I'm using X-T2 to find the byte offset
and then using image file.
I would try it being the...
Yeah, so film is...
It's the same thing.
So the question is, the observation is actually,
apart from maybe seeking into broken file systems that way,
you can even just look into the certain configuration files,
so certain cache files, like the one from the Chrome browser,
because there actually, there are some special custom file
formats where a proper file is pushed down into another file.
Yeah, the image has an HTTP response
address in the same file.
Yeah, there are encodings, let's say, which simply,
you have a picture, but it's not immediately,
cannot be immediately seen.
But with this, you can, with functionality which jumps or
seeks, looks for a file, perhaps with a signature can locate it.
Yeah.
Okay, the last question.
We don't have any online.
Question on the floor, yeah?
On the left?
No? Okay.
Okay, thank you, Mikaelle.
Thank you.