So we start with the first conversation by Mollibique Haidt, who was the District Manager
of the Union this year.
Hi everyone, I'm Mollibique Haidt. I've been a Digital Developer now for 15 years.
And I'm going to tell you a bit of what has happened in the Digital Community in the last
two years that we last met here. So we've had two major releases, 1.20, 1.22,
quite a lot of merge requests as you can see. And an interesting fact, in 1.22, a third
of the merge of the commits were in the Rust modules. So we've been investing a lot in Rust
and the Community as well as excitement. And that's been a big happening.
One of the big things for us as developers that we did was to merge all of the various
Git repositories into one big giant repository. So now everything is together, except for Rust.
Rust modules are all on the global corner because they're released with the GTK RS infrastructure.
So the rest of these few months. But that's kind of our big change for developers,
but it doesn't change much for the end user because we still release all the packages
in separate card balls, just like these.
Another thing that we did that's with the infrastructure is we improved our build system
and now we can select the elements one by one. Not just the plugins,
but you can select exactly which elements you want in the plugin.
And then we can also link all the plugins, all the elements, all the dependencies
into one giant library. This makes it actually easier to make a smaller build
because we can build only exactly the functionality that you need for a specific application.
So I've fixed several applications, created a big library that only has the attack functions
that are being used, and not anything else. So we did that for embedded systems mostly
so that you can have something a little smaller.
Another area, and there has been quite a lot of excitement in this server
in the last couple of years, is WebRTC. So as for me, all of you are familiar with,
WebRTC is a way to send video and low latency to and from browsers.
And this server has one of the most complete implementations outside of the Google implementation
that's used by the browsers. We were missing one big bit,
and that was a congestion control. And that's been added in the last releases.
So now we have a module that is compatible with what's called Google congestion control,
which is what Chrome and Firefox and Safari use. And this is in Rust.
And to make that work, so we have a WebRTC implementation,
but that did not do any of the actual encoding. It was left separate on purpose.
Now we have a module in Rust plugin that will plug the encoder and WebRTC
and do the congestion control so that you can adapt the bitrate of the encoder to the encoding.
And this is all automatic if you use this plugin.
We also have WIP and WEP. So these are also within Rust there.
WIP and WEP are a way to replace RTMP, but based on WebRTC,
so it's a single request, a single HTTP request way to set up a WebRTC stream.
It's mostly meant to stream to and from a server.
So it's really a replacement for RTMP for low latency video transmission.
Speaking of WebRTC, WebRTC is based on RITP, and this is an area where they're also
been quite a bit of development. So starting with 2022.1, 4D recorrection,
that's a system used mostly for latency broadcast transmission,
and we have the 2D 4D recorrection. So what does it mean 2D?
It means that we do 4D recorrection, which is basically you absorb multiple packets,
and you generate a new one. And if you have any of these packets except one,
then you can regenerate the missing one. That's what the parallel recorrection is.
Traditionally, you would do packets one, two, and three and four,
and then you would generate a fifth packet.
But losses tend to come in bursts in networks.
So with 2D recorrection, we have this kind of traditional version,
and also a version where you do packet one and five and ten, right?
So if you have a burst, you can recover more of the packets.
The other thing that we've added, so just for a long time,
we've had APIs to add RTP header extensions.
That's a way to reach packets to add a little header with something else.
So for a long time, we had libraries to actually write these,
but we didn't have something in the system to easily plug in
something to insert this header in every packet
without having to write application code.
So this is something that we've added,
and we've added a bunch of different modules.
Notable is this client to mixer audio level.
This makes it possible for a sender of audio to say,
the volume that I'm sending is this,
so that the add mixer or some kind of service
can select the person who speaks loudest
without having to decode all of the audio.
So you can know from this level who's speaking louder
and just forward that one.
Then, Color Space.
So this is for VP9.
If you want to send HDR over VP9,
we now have this archive access to make it work.
It's compatible with Chrome again.
So this is a place where people are experimenting with it.
And we have an AP1 header in the builder.
So this is, I think, for the first thing where we've decided
that the official implementation of a major feature
is only available in Rust.
So this is something that we're pretty happy about.
Another thing, so H.264, H.265, they have two kinds of timestamp.
Presentation timestamp, decoding timestamp.
When you send RTP, normally you only send a presentation timestamp.
You need to apply an algorithm to recover the decoding timestamp.
We now have modules that generate that.
We also support RFC 6051, so that's a way to synchronize streams immediately.
So traditionally with RTP, we send two streams, audio, video, separate timestamps.
And then sometimes later you get a packet telling you what the correspondence is.
With 6051, we add the RTP header extension in every packet
so that we can be synchronized from the first packet.
And we also improve our base class for video decoders a bit.
So now it can recognize that there's a corruption
and use that to request a retransmission.
Previously, we did, we kind of applied the error,
but we let the application do the decision.
Now we've added something to the base class.
Another big feature that was worked on,
that we basically rewrote the HLS and dash base class.
So the previous one was over 10 years old
and had been written largely without the specs.
And even when we had the specs, HLS has changed quite a lot the last 10 years.
So now we have what we call a state-of-the-art implementation
based on 10 years more knowledge.
It's much more simple, has fewer trends,
much better control on how we download things on the buffering.
We do a little bit of the parsing in there
because sadly for many of these for us, you have to have two parts
that they stream to handle it properly.
So this is all implemented as one in this decade.
We've put a few things around decoding, mostly video decoding.
One thing I'm quite excited about is the subframe decoding
that has been quite a few years coming.
And this means that we now have infrastructure in our base classes
to start decoding a frame before you receive the entire frame.
So some formats, issue six, version six, five,
we can split the frame in slices and now, from this personnel,
you can actually start doing the decoding.
We have two implementations of this.
One is based on a thing, which you can do with this only for issue six four.
And the other one is for the Xilinx hardware
because they have the hardware features to do that.
So they can super low latency decoding.
We have WebM alpha, so the WebM format.
So each VPE, VPE9 don't have support for transparency built in.
But there's a WebM extension where we basically store
two separate video streams, one with the colors
and one with the transparency.
And now we have an element that will spin up two decoders
and then recombine them into a 1v stream.
We have a DirectX element library, so make it easier
to integrate DirectX 3D element applications in the streamer
to do zero copy encoding, for example, from a Windows application.
And also speaking of Windows, our DirectX 3D element decoders
are now the default.
So they're becoming the choice that will get auto-plugged
if you have them, so you get hardware acceleration decoding
on the Windows that works.
Yep?
What about Mac codes?
Yes, there's also...
We've got a question already.
Yeah, about Mac codes.
So we have a hardware decoder for Mac and iOS,
which is the same API.
CUDA, so some people use proprietary software
and proprietary drivers, so we have now also a CUDA library
so that you can insert more easily CUDA data into the streamer
for encoding, streaming, decoding, all of these things.
We have some more CUDA-native elements,
one that is a converter and a scaler, so using CUDA itself.
We have CUDA and direct 3D integration for Windows again.
And this whole thing basically gives you zero copy encoding
on NVIDIA hardware, especially when you match
with some other CUDA-based software.
But some people prefer free software,
so we also have the API, we have a new plugin for the API.
So we've had this user of the API for a long, long time.
It was getting quite freaky.
It was not based on any of the base classes
that we have improved since then.
So it's been completely rewritten from scratch,
with a new plugin that we call VA.
It supports all the major codecs now,
we've implemented all the ones with VA.
Supports APY, it supports just 5, APA, DT90, MB2.
Encoding, we only have the H2645 codecs for now,
but the rest are being worked on, as we speak.
And using libv, we have a bit more than the API.
We have a bit more features, we have a compositor,
so that's an element that will take two or more streams
and composite them into the same video.
We have the Dinterlacer, and we have a post-prosterer element
with scaling and color space conversion
using the video functionality instead of the GPU.
And all of our work has happened on AV1 also,
in the last two years.
So we have quite a lot now, we have support for AV1,
both in the legacy VA plugin and in the new VA plugin.
We have it for AMD, the coders,
we have it for Direct3D on Windows, using the NPD APIs.
For Intel, using their multiple libraries,
either QuickSync, QSV, or the new SDK.
So we have pretty comprehensive AV1 support,
in addition to the RTD plugin that I mentioned earlier.
Another new thing that we've done is,
this is our first official machine learning integration
that is in G-streamer itself.
So it's a first step.
And we've written a plugin to use the Onyx runtime from Microsoft
to basically take some video frames,
some 3D model and recognize objects,
put little boxes in the metadata,
and then another element that can take these boxes
and draw them on the image.
So this is the first step, a lot of work is happening right now
to have a better video analytics framework as part of G-streamer.
All these things are nice, but sometimes you want to have a UI.
And a few features were recently added there.
We have a GTK4 paintable, so that's an object.
I would say that you can use the GTK4 to actually draw something on the screen.
So now you can easily integrate G-streamer with GTK4, 0.P, playback.
This one is in Rust, which is kind of cool.
Qt 6 also has a theme, so that we have something that is very similar to what we have for Qt 5,
which is a QML item, so that you can integrate a G-streamer sync,
the output width, Qt, and draw in your Qt application.
And the last one is a bit of a niche case.
So we had a Wayland sync for a long time,
and what this Wayland sync allows you to do is basically take the video buffer
and give it to the Wayland compositor directly without going through the toolkit.
So you can use the 2D hardware planes of the platform.
This is multi-use, useful, and embedded.
It allows you to do things like greater performance, not use the GPU.
Unembedded systems or the GPU might be too slow to do.
Up to now, this all works fine, but you have to write low-level Wayland code,
and that's non-trivial.
So we've written a GTK widget that wraps that.
So now you can write your application in GTK, just add the widget,
and you get all of these performance benefits for free.
Last but not least, in this category, we added touch event navigation.
So previously we had navigation.
You could send letters, you could send mouse clicks,
but now we can also send touch events so that you can have elements in your pipeline
that are controlled by the user, such as we have a WebR app,
a WebView, a WebKit-based source.
And we have some new tracers.
So these are tools for developers to know actually what's going on in a pipeline live.
We have a bunch of tracers already, four more were added.
Some of them are quite useful.
We have one to generate, read the buffer lateness, and one to trace the Q-level,
and these will output the information in a CSV file that you can then load
and make nice graphs and understand, like, what's the live performance
of your pipeline, what's going on.
We have one to draw pretty pipeline snapshots.
So for a long time, we had a feature where we could draw a DOS file
to draw a picture of the pipeline, but this required it,
added some code to your application to actually trigger it.
With this tracer, now you can just listen to a Unix signal
and trigger it on the spot.
The last one is the factory tracer.
This is the very first feature I mentioned.
So it's nice to say, oh, I'm going to build a G-streamer,
build specifically for my application with only the elements I use.
But if you use Play
then there's a lot of automated things,
and you might not know exactly which plugins you've been using.
So with this tracer, we can actually trace all the plugins that get loaded,
all the elements that are used, and print, when you use the application,
print the list of what was actually used.
Question about that.
Playbin sometimes tries to use plugin, but it's not related because it is working.
It's going to be listed in a bit.
So yeah, sorry.
Playbin sometimes tries to use something,
but it doesn't work because the hardware is not there or something.
So in this case, the tracer will still list it.
It's everything that is loaded, right?
When they're tried or loaded, you call a function in it and it says no.
So let's just really get the loading stage.
Thank you. Any questions? Yes.
You mentioned the RTP support in there.
So did you also add the SPC extension to that?
I have no idea.
Anyone knows? No.
RTC is only one extension, SVC extension, in...
I don't know if it's there.
We do layer selection of the highest quality right now, but it's not.
There is an external...
There is a dependency in the script turner to the extension
where you can read information about the SPC layers in there,
which is under that.
So you encode the SPC layers into one screen,
then you use these external extensions to carry information about what's in there
and put these in so that you can do a good collection for that.
So that's what I have to do.
None of the RTP SPC stuff, including the VP1,
which is quickly required because there's no SVC inside the screen.
It's not implemented yet. Thank you.
And supervise.
Yes. So the question was, RTP, AV1, SVC, there's an extension
to actually make it really useful.
It's being standardized and it's not implemented yet.
But it will be at some point.
I forgot to mention we have an online question,
an online question at number 43401.
So I'm at home on that question as possible.
But since we don't have any questions, are there any more questions on the floor?
There's one there.
Q6, does it support different rendering backends,
direct picks on Windows and both and on Linux or something?
Will there be QML and then Q6 support those different stuff
because it directly talks directly to QML?
So does Q6 support other backends than OpenGL?
And I think the answer right now is will only support OpenGL.
Are you all pushed in? Yes.
Can you do a statically linked winery?
Can you do a statically linked winery? Yes, you can.
That's kind of one of the use cases,
that we create this statically linked library
and then your application can link to it
and only link the required bits.
That's kind of part of the trick to make it a little smaller.
Q7, there is a congestion control that works as you know.
Yes, you are.
Is it the same feature set as in Google's implementation?
The question is about congestion control in WebRTC.
Is it the same feature set as the Google implementation?
As far as I know, yes, because it's basically a copy of the implementation in Rust.
So they basically re-implement the same algorithm.
So that is compatible.
But it's pluggable, so you could write your own.
There is actually a plug-in mechanism.
The core representation is in C,
but this one is in Rust with a separate plug-in.
One could write a different implementation.
Because there's a bunch of heuristics in there.
There's no perfect answer.
Thank you so much.
Do you have a question? Yes.
If I have an application that does WebRTC signaling over matrix, for example,
would I benefit from switching to WebRTC sync,
or would I stick with WebRTC sync?
So the question is, if you have an implementation of WebRTC
that does signaling something custom,
for example, other matrix, would you benefit using WebRTC sync?
The answer to that is yes,
because it will do all the encoding and congestion control hooked up for you.
And there's an interface that's actually implemented for your own signal.
So the signaling is separate from this WebRTC sync.
There's still a module that we can implement.
We have one implemented for, like, custom signaling mechanism,
where there's a server that's implemented, but people write your own.
In Rust.
Last question? No, just a comment to the question before the QT6 started 3D integration.
There is a merge request for it.
Okay. So Tim says that for the QT, there's a direct 3D merge request open
to integrate that. That's not merged yet, but do test it at home
and complain when it doesn't work.
Last question? No? Okay, thank you, everybody.