So let's start with our next talk.
Sorry we were going a bit late because the project was not running.
We have a brand new TV now.
So the next talk is about high-pile ups is
going to become women.
Just a short talk about box line and current state.
I gave a talk so far ago about power wires and I will just talk a little bit quickly.
So a bit about what it became since last time and what it is.
So it's kind of like a sort of D-Bus or a lot of medium or a core pipeline.
So its functionality is basically show objects in a graph and pass data between them.
So in terms of that we have a section called wire clumber.
We have a couple of services like for example there is a pulse audio service that converts all your clients to barbed wire.
We also have a replacement library to write a jackpot.
The purpose of this is to share all the videos.
So we have video sharing, simple, I'll show you what I made.
But also audio, functionality of the audio.
So you need to do screen sharing in Wayland so you need to pass video from the GPU without touching the CPU to clients.
So memory using file descriptors, stuff like that, zero copy.
So it turned out in the end that it was also going to work for audio.
Audio passing around and then I started working on that.
So the audio part is very much like a jack audio server.
Very simple how it passes the data around.
So that you can build all the existing audio solutions.
So this is the current situation of what we have for audio and video.
So you have the Bluetooth stack with Bluetooth that goes over the e-mails.
There is also the camera now that talks about that to interface with the kernel video for Linux originally.
There is still also the audio stuff.
And then we have the session manager barbed wire there and then the applications that go through.
So it is a replacement for audio server or native or jack lines.
So originally for Wayland screen sharing it was implemented that the motor which is the compositor would expose inside the pipeline graph.
It is called a node which is something, it is like this here it produces a video feed and then you can connect with clients and also that they.
So this is all input process so different process connected to the barbed wire.
So you can branch out, you can mix things and barbed wire make sure that the data flows around.
So for audio support it is like pro audio model like Jack.
So there is one buffer size to the whole graph just like Jack but it is dynamic it can change.
So there is automatic format converted from sources and things.
So with that core layer you can run Jack lines almost with very little translation and with a little server you can run also audio lines.
So it copies basically stuff that was already there to partially from Jack but also from also audio retirement model is also used.
It uses a copy of all the old audio stuff for managing the cards and the mixers and you plug in the headphones that switches things and remembers volume.
It controls the volume styles and all of that that was just copied directly because that piece is very evolved over the years.
So you can run all the Jack clients like that and they will show up like also audio clients which is still up there.
So it was originally started for video with the screen sharing then a little detour to audio but we are actually back now to video and now that it works.
So now we are basically working on the camera capturing stuff.
So traditionally browsers like for WebRPC go directly to video for Linux using IOS
videos and stuff like that.
So it is very difficult to put anything in between there.
This all needs to be rewritten.
This is in the process.
Also newer cameras they need more stuff than what P
eermo gives.
There is a new library called the camera that works to install this.
You can have more about that in your camera.
You can just go directly to video for Linux and walk.
So there is a layer needed.
So we need to rewrite the applications anyway.
So then it is probably going to be written to Piedwars so that we can route the video more flexibly.
So basically Piedwars we can write cameras and you can get them from clients.
So this also means that you can have multiple apps going to the same camera.
So the status currently is it has been in Piedwars for almost two years.
It was API and ABI stable and so far we can make this work.
It was made to default.
We are made against all expectations.
I was a bit afraid that it doesn't work.
That is not expected.
So it became a default.
So for the moment, Jack and Paul saw the feature.
Everything should work as it worked before.
There is a couple of things that are not checked.
There are alternatives to connect multiple Jacks.
All the servers on the network.
It is a very specific implementation.
There are alternatives to the RTP based on which there are more compatible with the hardware.
There are also a bunch of Piedwars that maybe nobody uses.
So right now most of the stores are switching as well or have switched.
I think Debian is getting there.
Wuntu switched for 32.10.
No more pulse audio.
You have to note no more pulse audio.
The only thing that is changed there is the server part.
The client part of pulse audio is still in use.
But it talks to a different server.
It is a re-implementation of the pipeline.
So what are we doing?
If you are on a laptop speaker, you only get it in the right channel.
The right channel is is lapel.
We are trying to work on various things here.
The camera elements, we work on to get it all integrated.
We are going to have a talk about this on Sunday.
It is a whole bunch of things that need to be done.
For example, for the camera, there is also a portal.
We try to hide everything behind the portal that will manage the permissions.
Application can access the camera.
Yes, it is sort of like other computers where you give access to an application.
So that goes through the portal.
We try to route everything to that.
There are lots of applications to be in looking.
For example, in the studio, there is a bit of a test case there for the camera and screen integration.
There are merge requests ready to be merged.
There are some more things.
The result is that if you do a call in one of these browsers in a future version, you can do lots of fun stuff.
You can add filters to the camera.
For example, in the studio, you can do a virtual camera and then you can add that camera.
I am sorry, I have never thought about that.
Repeat the question.
Can you repeat the question for the stream?
The question was, Jack had a network transport and he also allowed compression.
He tried to do the ABS, which is all that can be used.
It is uncompressed.
There are some more facts.
I am just curious.
We have a product that actually uses that component in portfolio.
Since I put it in order, my...
Yes, the green zone.
Yes, following up on that, there is a rock plugin.
The suggestion is that there is a rock plugin.
The rock toolkit is built over the E and also provides network transport.
I do not know, does it do compression?
I do not know.
It is a bit more generic streaming.
Are there any further plans to introduce a second processor?
The question is, are there plans to add echo cancellation or other plugins?
Echo cancellation, we have a module that you can load.
Echo cancellation, we have to see echo cancel and load.
Signal processing, there is also a whole bunch of things.
You can of course load jack tools to do this.
We also have a native module that can load lots of Ld2 filters.
You can use fullstruct filter chains.
There is also easy effects, which is an app to manage the filters for you.
There are quite a few options.
We have an online question, is there a way to visually show pipeline use?
Yes.
For visualizing the pipeline blocks, you can of course use jack tools.
There is also a native toolkit to do this.
You can also load later in the count.
You said you had AES output, are you referring to AES67?
How are you dealing with the clocking elements of AES67?
Are you just ignoring it?
What happens if you don't?
Do people just send garbage timestamps by default?
This is a big problem for receivers that need to look at the timestamps and go,
I need to do something with it.
What should a third party receiver do?
If they have two different clocks, what does it do with the timestamps?
The timestamps in the receiver, what does the receiver do to synchronize itself to the screen?
Basically follow the rate at which you receive data and try to adjust the consumption rate by resulting.
You talked a lot about portals for video, is there also something similar for audio?
Like for example, I want to capture an application using video and audio.
The question is, the portal for video, we talked about lockups, is there also a portal for audio?
The answer is, we are thinking about it, but we don't have anything to change.
Is there anything for networking video screens?
The question is, is there anything for networking video screens?
Last, not sure.
There are lots of things you can do, it's really hard to do.
Thank you.