All right.
Yes, go ahead.
We continue with our next speaker,
which is kind of the follow up of the previous one,
because it's approximately the same topic,
but this time about risk five and arm.
So please welcome Renny.
Renny.
I heard good afternoon, everyone.
I hope you are done with the digestion.
So yes, this pretty much follows up
on Keren's previous speech.
But before I go into the details,
obviously, I work for big companies,
so I have to put this disclaimer.
And then if I speak too fast or if I don't articulate properly,
please stop me.
With that said, who am I?
I don't think it matters much.
Well, this is my 16th time in F
and it's only my first presentation, so bear with me.
Having said that, I don't work in this field at all,
so just a fancy thing for me to do.
So some history.
So has anybody ever seen this?
Outside the computer museum, right?
Yeah, so that's the K1.
It's the first vector processor.
It's from the late or second half of the 70s.
I wasn't even born back then.
But I'm pointing it's the first vector processor
and we all now finally, after almost 50 years,
are coming back to this kind of,
maybe coming back to this approach
to calculations in computers.
But for people in my generation,
this is more what we associate with the SIMD
for multimedia.
So this is a pod, the first video game
that I could use the MMX,
which MMX being the first SIMD extensions
in the consumer business, in the consumer space, let's say.
So as I said, the MMX came in 1997
and that was 64-bit vector,
so you could compute over 64-bit at a time.
Mind that back then, computers was pretty much only 32-bits.
And two years later, I came SSE
and many, many, many versions of SSE, SSE2,
which is more popular in multimedia use cases, 2000.
I'm not gonna go through all the details of SSE
because there's like a billion, million versions.
And AVX1 came in 2008, AVX2,
which Kian mentioned came in 2011.
That was the first to have 256-bits vectors.
Then AVX512, which was the topic of the previous presentation,
officially came in 2013, but as Kian mentioned,
the only real proper CPUs were only out in 2017.
On ARM side, the first SIMD was actually 32-bit
only on ARM B6, 2002.
That doesn't really seem to make sense,
but that's because it's basically calculating
as a four times eight-bit, so two times 16-bit at a time.
Then 128-bits came, there was no 64-bit SIMD on ARM.
128-bit came with ARM E7, so got XA8,
in usually called NEON, officially called Advanced SIMD
in 2005, and on ARM V8, it's pretty much the same.
Now it's not actually compatible on like on X86,
64, 64, the same, but came in,
well, came with basically ARM V8 in 2012.
It's also officially called Advanced SIMD,
and it's also colloquially known as NEON.
As for RACE-5, well, RACE-5 is much more recent.
There is no SIMD.
Problem, and I've only summarized,
this is only a short summary,
there's way more extension, especially on the 86 side,
is that every damn time you have to rewrite your assembly,
and as the question then answers in the previous talks
and even the previous previous talk covered,
this is kind of time-consuming.
So with that said, this was all fixed size SIMD,
so what about viable length SIMD,
which is what we will be talking about today.
So how would you go about doing it?
Well, simple way to do it is to just ask the CPU
what is your vector size,
and if you do S5, this is how you do it.
So control register rate operation,
the vector is called VLANB for vector length in bytes,
and it will store in this case, T0, whatever,
it's one register, the number of bytes in a vector,
and with that you could then iterate.
So if you want to know the number of elements,
well, you have to do a left shift to,
you have to compute the number of elements,
so if you want to have 32-bit elements,
you divide by four, shift by two bits.
You could do it like that,
and then you would write your main,
you would take your C loop,
you would convert it into assembly,
to operate on over many elements at a time,
then you would probably, if you have space in your vector bank,
you'd probably, in order to eliminate,
try to heat up the latency a little bit,
because usually between instructions,
if you operate only on one data set,
you will have inter-instruction latencies,
which are going to hurt your performance,
so you're typically in multimedia and all twice,
so you will do work over two set of vectors
at the same time in parallel,
and when you have done all of that,
you will be working on over many like say 32-bit,
32, sorry, 32-item, 32 elements at a time,
so you have to deal with edges,
because you might not have a multiple
of 32 elements that you are dealing with,
and that's fine, and that's one way to do it.
In fact, as I checked,
that's how Clang LLVM does the tree vectorization on RISC-V,
if you enable it, and so you have,
it literally starts by reading the vector length,
and then deal with edges and all twice,
and if it manages to implement tree,
I mean, if you have enabled tree vectorization,
and you have enabled RISC-V vectors,
but that's not really how you want to do it,
but before we go on how to actually do it,
what vector lengths are we dealing with here?
So obviously, whereas mentioned earlier,
common values are 128 and 512 bits,
so both ARM and RISC-V are ground T's
that even if you have the vibratory vector lengths,
it's going to be at least 128 bits,
and it's also going to be a power of two bits,
which is kind of convenient for our calculations.
So as far as I've seen,
there are announcements for real hardware,
which would have 256 and 512 bits,
that you should be able to buy at some point in the near future.
More crazy stuff, I've seen actually designs also being announced with 1000 bits.
I don't know if they're going to store all those bits in
the physical register bank, but it would be interesting if it happens.
I haven't seen theoretical designs at 4000 bits,
and theoretical to the point that there is a schematic.
Theoretically, in this case, I mean that there are actual schematics of how you could
write a chip and they have
a simulation of the performance that the chip would get into the algorithms.
As to whether it's actually practically implementable in an existing industrial process.
I don't know, I'm not a specialist in electronics,
but that sounds a little bit questionable.
So in theory, on the syntactic level,
so in the instruction and coding level,
you can have up to two power of 16 bits,
at least on H5, I'm not sure about how much you need.
So how you actually do vector length?
Are you supposed to do a viable vector length SIMD or vector processing as it's often called,
particularly vector and SIMD synonyms.
Well, first you have to use predication,
which is very highly prevalent in variable vector length scenarios.
Now, it's not a completely new concept.
Here I mentioned the K mask in AVX,
so AVX also has predication.
But in variable vector length,
it's really essential because this is
basically the programming model on variable vector lengths.
No, loops is essentially built on predication,
and that's true both for ARM and H5.
So a predicate is a vector on Boolean,
so like the K mask in x86,
it's called the P vector in ARM,
and it's the mask vector in H5.
As Ciaran said, kind of repeating,
but it just specifies which of the element in your vector,
it specify which ones you will be loading or modifying or storing out of a given instruction.
So if it's a load instruction which values you load from memory and overwrite into the register,
if it's a store instructions going to be the other way,
which values in memory are going to overwrite versus which ones are going to live as they are.
If it's a calculation instruction vector to vector,
then it's going to affect which results are actually stored into the register,
versus which ones are just discarded.
So on ARMv9 or SVE,
one way you would typically do now your SVE loop instead of say your neuron loop,
is you would start by counting down,
you would initialize say extend to zero,
and then you would,
so you have to imagine here that you have your actual neuron or SVE loop.
So you will check,
you have this funny instruction which is actually called while LTA or while LO,
and you initialize the P0 vector in this case,
which is one of the predicate register,
to say that essentially,
you want to count how many elements you still have in your input data.
So here we have X0,
we imagine that X0 is the number of elements we've been given to this function,
extend is count of of how we've been,
so it's our iterator.
Essentially, what we'll say is as long as extend is
larger as long as the number of elements we still have.
So as long as X0 is larger than the size of the vector that the CPU can handle,
we'll just set the predicate to handle to be clear.
So we'll use the full size of the vector for our programming.
Once the number of elements is more than zero,
but less, strictly less than the vector size in the CPU can handle,
then we'll start basically just ignoring the values at the end of the vector.
So we'll have a bunch of ones and then at the end a bunch of zeros.
This is how you abstract away and hide away the complexity of dealing
with the edge in your loop.
So essentially, by doing this,
you don't care what is the actual capacity of,
you don't actually need at any point to know how many elements are
dealing with any interaction of your loop because it's all hidden away by the,
essentially, the size of the vector and the size of the predicate are matched,
so you don't actually care.
You also don't need to deal with edges because when there's
one or two or three or four elements left over at the end,
you can just deal with them in the lattiteration,
which of course will be a little bit less efficient than using
the full size of the vector but it's still much faster than having
a separate edge if only because you will not be
stressing the instruction cache of the CPU.
So that's predication.
Now, unrolling. If you thought about it,
what I just said with predication,
it doesn't really work with unrolling because now you've counted down,
you've set your predicate vector to count down how many elements you
have still in your total count of elements.
You can't and all because now you said,
oh, I have 10 elements left,
I'm going to use 10 elements in my vector but if you have,
it just doesn't work because if you had one and a half vector left,
you would want to have one predicate with all the bits set
and another predicate with half of the bits set,
this doesn't really work very well.
Yes, it's a bit of a hot take.
Maybe I will never be ever again allowed to write a system pec code after this,
but just don't unroll if you use a viable vector lengths.
Now, there may be cases where you can't unroll because naturally have
parallel some kind of parallel in your design aspect in your algorithm.
But the idea of vector processing is
that we have higher latency and larger vectors,
which in the end result in higher throughput and we shouldn't need to unroll.
I'm sure you will find actual designs,
real hardware, real processor where it will be faster if you do an all,
and how much you need to unroll will depend on the design.
Of course, if you are trying to squeeze the very last MIPS
out of a given specific piece of hardware,
then maybe you should unroll but I think generally speaking,
at least you shouldn't start by unrolling.
Another interesting thing to keep in mind,
which I already mentioned in the previous slide is that you don't have alignment issues.
So one common problem with SIMD instruction set is that
the load and store instructions require over-aligned data,
typically aligned on the side of the vector,
which is very inconvenient when you're operating from C or C plus plus code,
because it's usually C or C plus plus allocator will only allocate
aligned on whatever the ABI specifies which are now on
B8 would be 16 bytes for the stack and eight bytes for the heap.
So usually, well,
at least both SV and RISC-V vectors,
they don't need the alignment,
it is only the alignment of the element and it's not the alignment,
it's not the size of the vector.
So if you are operating on say four bytes pieces of data,
data elements, then you only need your vectors to be aligned on four bytes,
which is a very nice property for dealing especially on the edge,
on edge cases and also you don't have to deal with like,
if you have one input that is
aligned that is perfectly aligned and the output is not perfectly aligned,
then you end up having this weird mismatch and you end up
having to deal with different edge cases,
it's really a mess.
With vector processing, you don't do that.
So you don't actually have to worry about it.
So with that, we've covered generality.
So how is it looking on ARM side?
Then we'll see RISC-V side because it's a bit weird if I would,
I sort of like to put everything together,
but then it becomes a huge mess.
So it's going to be a bit repetitive because of course,
there's a lot of similarities.
But so SVE came about like five years ago,
a little bit more than five years ago,
I think it was announced late 2016 if I recall correctly.
It was pretty much with some intermediate.
It was explicitly meant for all the things like
scientific applications or
engineering modeling and then it's kind of stuff,
my HPC and so nobody used it.
At least nobody in this room used it.
This was fixed with SVE2,
which is sometimes called ARMv9 because it kind of
comes with ARMv9 but it's really called SVE2.
Fixed that issue, they realize that actually this is a good idea.
This pattern programming model is also interesting from
Intimedia and crypto which was also missing from SVE1.
So what they did is they just took,
yes, so which Neomnemonics are missing and added those,
and it's pretty much the same Neomnemonics,
you just add your prime,
the predicate register.
That's what it's of course a little bit more complicated.
But as I mentioned,
you just use a while instruction which
will then provision your predicate,
then you have to pick the element size so that of course,
this adds up correctly and at the end,
you have a new set of branch conditions,
so first element, last element, and so on and so forth.
So the remaining elements will be determined by
the predicate register and the predicate register which
is the condition flag and the while instruction will also subtract.
There is a count, the number of
a processed element from your output register.
Yes, this one stop pretending that I'm missing risk.
How do you detect this stuff?
So there's a processor macro,
otherwise as usual on ARMv8,
you have a bunch of privileged register for the OS to look at,
and then you have also on Linux,
you have a bunch of flags in the OCI vector bits,
so it's all classic,
otherwise you're out of luck.
Availability, so as we said 2016,
but they didn't really work for us,
as V2 was specified in 2019.
But so the real hardware came earlier last year,
so Cortex-X2 and all the other things
from dynamic IQ 110.
So Samsung actually has 2200 and so forth.
If you find your cases are Francis,
they do have SVE,
unfortunately it's only 128 bit vectors,
and it's pretty damn expensive.
But if you want to do it,
you can find the hardware.
So race five, so different model.
Yeah.
There's also the Alibaba one, the Yitian.
Yeah, maybe. It's possible.
It's only available in China.
So on race five,
the prediction is a little bit different.
So they have separation between
element count and the actual predicate.
So in practice in multi-major,
maybe not in David, but usually you
don't use a predicate at all.
So we will instead just count the elements.
This is the instruction you always found at
the beginning of the loop which consider the vectors.
So in this case, what we say is that we
have a certain number of input elements.
We want to get the number of output.
The output of the parameter is the number of element
the CPU will deal with in the iteration.
We then have to say the size of the element in bits.
In this case, for instance, 16 bits.
The group size which is free and rolling,
it will automatically, if you set it to two,
it will use all the,
and you say you want to use vector eight,
it will use vector eight and vector nine
at the same time for instance.
Tail mode, we always set it to
agnostic because we don't really care about tail mode,
and mask mode, we always set it to agnostic.
There may be use cases where you need to do something else,
which might be a little bit slower,
but usually you don't.
This is about how to deal with the stuff that is masked,
or with the element that are at the end of the vector,
which we don't care about. Usually you don't care about them,
so you just tell the CPU you don't care about them.
One cool thing about H5,
the floating point condition are separate from the vectors,
unlike on ARM, so you have more registers available.
If you have hybrid calculations
between scalar and vector side,
but do mind the floating point convention,
and the coding convention when this happens,
otherwise you will screw up your register state and
configure your CPU.
Interesting stuff also about H5,
they have segmented load and store,
which similar to structured load and store in ARM,
but they can do it up to eight structures,
whereas ARM is only up to four.
What is much more interesting perhaps is
stride in loads and store where you can say,
I have this register X which contains
a value and that's going to be my stride.
So for instance, with that you can put
width of your video inside one register,
and you can load all the pixels in a column in an instruction,
without having to then do weird shuffling and whatever.
Does that actually perform a practice?
I think that's going to depend on the design,
but normally it should be in the data cache which would be okay.
We've talked about hypothetical architectures where it could be fostered.
So I'll come to that.
Yes. On the downside,
you don't have transpose or zipping instructions,
which should be the annoying, which is the same.
So you have to replace it with slides.
So it's fine if you want to take
every second element from one vector and so on.
Future detection, they have very,
very detailed pre-processor feature flags.
I mean, you can download the slides if you're interested.
On the other hand, on the runtime detection is pretty crappy,
you have to trust the bootloader to
actually tell it to your OS correctly in the device tree data structure,
and otherwise there is a flag in there.
So the v-speed, so the bit 21,
because v is a 20 second later in the alphabet,
is a vector flag in the auxiliary vector for other capabilities on Linux.
Availability, unfortunately at this time, there is no hardware.
Alibaba has made hardware available,
but it's implementing version 0.71
from about 18 months before the standardized specification,
which is implemented by the Clang and GCC.
So you can work with that and it gives you
some ideas of performance but you're going to have to rewrite
stuff because it's not completely bit compatible,
so it's annoying.
I don't know when the stuff is going to happen,
I'm pretty sure it's going to happen,
but I would guess by the end of this year,
we are going to see hardware available.
Also, I think one note answering or dodging the previous question,
but because we have so many different vendors on RISC-V,
and I think there's more than I did,
I only listed three here,
but I think there might be
big difference between the performance characteristics of
the different vendors with our references.
Yes, I have just a few questions.
I just heard of the SVP64 project from Liver SOC yet,
which is a similar vector approach for PowerPC.
No, I haven't looked at PowerPC at all.
So another question that I have with
my own simply programming work is,
we often have applications that are inherently horizontal.
For example, let's say you are writing
a vectorized string search operation,
or you're doing something like decoding JPEGs,
where you have these A5 blocks,
where you want to do some close-end transform on them,
and they have this fixed size and depending on the vector size,
you either have to break them up or you
maybe can process multiple of them at the same time.
Is there an intelligent way to solve this?
So I've had this case.
Yes. So the question is,
when you have a naturally fixed size data,
the input block, block kind of block
that you want to process at the time,
how do you do this because then you
actually want to have a fixed size vector in effect,
path as in the question.
So yes, I've had this case with
a sample a couple of times.
One way is to just check that
the vector size of the CPU is
big enough and just do one at a time.
If you can try to do n at a time,
because it's always going to be a power off too,
so you should be able relatively easily to parallelize.
I mean, obviously, the ideal situation is to parallelize,
where you will have a problem is if
your data set is larger than the vector,
then it's going to become complicated for you.
On the RISC-V, you can deal with
this with a group multiplier,
which will allow you to use multiple vectors as a single vector.
The last question I have is,
how do you realistically test vectorized kernels,
when the hardware you have only supports one vector length at most?
So you have to probably use some sort of
validation to be set up for this?
Most of the loops will not depend.
So the question is, do you test a different vector size,
for validation, I guess?
Most of the loops don't really care about the vector size,
because if you have the simple case where you follow
the simple pattern, it doesn't really care what the vector size is.
Except for benchmarking, of course,
and you have a problem, but otherwise,
QMU and Spark at this far is to have support
any vector size to give that,
as long as it's a valid one from specification 10 point.
You realistically really test for that,
or do you just say it's simply not going to be a problem?
I mean, personally,
when I've had the situation where I had
a fixed size input and I had to test with different vector size,
and I've tested with different vector size,
in most cases, you don't actually care.
I mean, then it's a matter of choice of duty or testing,
and I know it's tricky one to be with a validation, I think.
Thank you.
We have no one on the question.
Yeah. First a disclaimer,
I'm related to the Liversock project with SB64.
It's related similar to RISC-V vectors,
but not exactly the same,
but they share a lot of the common ideas.
You mentioned a very good point,
that CMD is not vector processing.
In order, we tried to import some code from a NEON to SB2.
It was less than suboptimal, let's say.
We had to revert back to the original C algorithm.