So we continue with our next talk again about CODEC, this time about DVC with two projects
about encoding and decoding DVC.
Please welcome Adam.
Hi everyone, so today I want to introduce you to VBENC and VBdec.
Those are open source implementations for VBC.
Now to pick everyone up about VBC, so VBC is this new CODEC that was finalized just
over two years ago.
And if you want to know one thing about VBC, basically VBC allows you to have the same
quality as HEVC at half the bit rate.
And on top of that it was developed by the JVET, which is the joint video experts group.
And it's called versatile because it's applicable in versatile scenarios, right?
We have support for screen content, HDR as we heard in the previous talk, immersive 8K
and we can do some fancy stuff like doing adaptive streaming with open scope.
All right, so now let me talk you through a little bit of the background of our projects,
VBdec and VBENC.
So of course those are both very, those are team efforts, right?
They are developed by a whole team of researchers at the front of our HHI, mostly in the video
coding systems group.
Now front of our HHI, if you don't know it, like modern video coding probably wouldn't
be what it is if it wasn't for HHI.
And HHI is part of a biggest European research organization, the Fraunhofer Society, which
is a big German nonprofit.
And then about me, so I'm Adam Iskowski.
I've been at HHI since 2016.
I've been leading the project since 2019 and since about a year I'm also the co-head of
the video coding systems group.
So why did we even start the software project?
So basically, you know, there was HVC for which the test model was HM and HVC is a square
block.
So they had this method of indexing blocks within, like within the frames using this
set index method, which is really amazing for square blocks.
And then, you know, they were exploring VVC based on the exploration model, which was
still based on HM, except VVC supports rectangular blocks, right?
So it's more than only square blocks.
And there were really a lot of code for working around the set index thingy.
And at HHI we wanted to do even more than that.
So we started work on our own partitioner and we just decided this is not going to work.
And what we had to do, we basically had to write our own software to deal with it, which
we very creatively named the next software, which later became the VTM 1.0.
And basically the biggest difference is we had one big map that was mapping the position
within a frame to like an object that was describing the current coding block.
So the next software, it became the VTM, which is the reference software for the VVC standard.
And you can see there in the graph how the VTM was developing over time with regards
to the gains over HM with the encoding time, decoding time.
And here you can also see how we started our implementation projects from VTM.
So from the VTM 3.0 super early, we already started work on the VVDec.
And then from VTM 6.0, we started the work on VVENC.
Then in the early 2020, Benjamin Pross became my boss.
Like we basically started the VCS group and he brought up the idea maybe we can do the
projects open source, which we did initially end of 2020 under a little bit shaky license.
But with some back and forth with the headquarters, we were able to change it to like a modified
BSD3 license.
And after some more back and forth, we actually have an unmodified, like a standard open source
license, the clear BSD3.
All right.
So let's talk some more about the projects.
You know, some hard facts.
So as I already mentioned, they are based of VTM.
They are both written fully in C++, but we do have like a pure C interface.
So you can integrate it into frameworks or just use it from a pure C code.
Those are C++ projects, right?
So they are object based, but it's kept very simple.
We try to not hide anything, no getters, no setters, and like have all the control over
what is happening in the memory.
Contrary to some other projects, we do not do assembler at all.
We do only vectorization using intrinsics, which of course has the advantage that we
get stuff like ARM support for free through this amazing Cindy Everywhere library.
Also support for Wasm cross-compilation, so WebAssembly, which we also did.
And what we try to do, we try to make those projects as simple as possible.
So basically we only expose options that are use case relevant, but like the coding options,
everything that's like connected to efficiency, we try to define it for the user to just have
the simplest experience possible.
Yeah, they're both available on GitHub under the PSD3 closed clear license, as I already
mentioned.
All right, so how do we do the development?
The development is done internally without HHIs.
We have our own main Git repo that we basically, from which we push squashed updates to the
GitHub repo.
Why is it internal?
I know many people find it a little bit, you know, there might be issues with that, but
here on the right you can see, or maybe you cannot see, a typical magic list that I would
do on the internal stuff, on the internal repo.
And I think this is just not something that is ready to be released to the public, you
know.
So I would rather hide those kind of hiccups and it just takes too much time to make stuff
nice for being public.
And I also think not everyone at HHI might be comfortable, you know, being like a public
developer.
But yeah, all of the stuff that we have internally eventually goes to the public repo, either
for new releases to fix bugs or issues, you know, if we develop a big new feature, we
would push it.
And you know, if someone was to make a large contribution, of course, to rebase the code.
All right, so VB Deck, the decoder project.
All the highlights, it's fully compliant with the main 10 profile of VVC.
Of course, give or take a few bugs.
So actually it was supposed to be fully compliant since the version 1.0.
But you know, stuff happens, we find bugs, we fix the bugs.
But basically there is no feature that is really missing.
It's multi-platform, so it works on all the major, all the major OSes.
And it also works on different architectures, thanks to ZMD Everywhere, as mentioned.
So we have like x86 support, ERM, I also saw people, you know, doing builds for RISC-V.
So this is very nice.
Also one thing I'm kind of proud of also is that from the first version we have like a
unified thread pool.
So also something that was already talked about.
Basically everything is like all the tasks are collected within this one thread pool
that just balances itself, right?
There is like no frame threads, slice threads, which also means we are multi-threading is
independent of bit-stream features, right?
We don't need tiles, slices to be able to parallelize.
So I think this is a really nice feature.
All right, let's look a little bit into the development history.
So this on the left is like the performance graph for, you know, different resolutions,
different coding conditions, so like random access or all-intro.
And you know, major milestones mentioned 1.0 full compliance with the standard in version
1.3.
We did a three times memory reduction and, you know, I was also asking myself how could
we ever release any other version, how could we have ever released any other version?
But yeah, at least we managed to get it better.
1.4 we got a major performance boost based of external contributions in GitHub.
So this was really nice to see.
And in between, we really had a lot of, you know, small improvements.
And as you can see in the graphs, it does add up.
All right, about the VVENC.
So VVENC, you know, it's an encoder project.
Of course, it's way more complex, way more interesting.
It has way more degrees of freedom, right?
Like the decoder just does this one thing, and has zero degree of freedom, right?
Maybe the standard tells us exactly what to do, and the encoder has all of those choices
that it has to do.
And what I like to say is, you know, it's basically the best open source encoder out
there.
As you can see here on the right, it's runtime versus efficiency.
So you know, for a given runtime, we can have the best efficiency.
And for any of our working points, we can get this efficiency the fastest.
Of course, you know, it's not the best encoder if you want to encode UHD live.
We're not quite there yet.
But you know, at those slower working points, it really doesn't get better than that.
At least not that I am aware of.
All right, so we have five presets on the encoder from faster to slower.
And you can see, this is a single-threaded graph.
You can see more or less how those presets compare to IxO65 in orange.
We have very efficient multithreading, at least like between, you know, up to eight
threads or up to 16 threads with some additional options.
I'm going to talk about this a little bit in two slides.
And we have very good optimization for human visual system based on the XPS and R metric,
which I'm also going to mention a little bit later.
We have really excellent rate control.
So you know, with bit-rate deviations, rarely more than 2%, and like almost never more than
5%.
As I mentioned, simple interface and it's, you know, this thing can be used for academic,
amateur, commercial users.
The license really allows it all.
All right, so we have those five presets.
How do we derive those presets?
Like from an academic point of view, this is actually done in a very interesting way.
So we take all not use case related options of the encoder and we do like large-scale
optimization.
We start with a very simple, very fast working point and then we try to derive which option
should be changed as the next one.
And this is always the option which basically gives incrementally the next best working
point, right?
And this is a huge optimization.
It takes really a lot of compute time.
So we don't do it so often, like every two or three versions, or if we know one tool
got implemented way better, we can like try to only optimize for this tool within the
options space from the last optimization.
We target HD and UHD, natural content, but we do sanity checks for a resolution and like
screen content or, you know, HDR.
And the one issue that we still have is, you know, at the beginning here, you can see that
our curve gets a little bit steeper, right?
So we cannot go too fast because at some point for like every two times speed up, we're just
losing too much efficiency.
This is because, you know, we started from the reference software which was designed
for readability and the efficiency still work in progress.
All right, about the multitreading.
So our multitreading is also, I would say done differently than in many other encoders.
So we do the multitreading over CTUs.
So like the modern macro blocks and CTU lines, like we simulate a wavefront parallel processing
without using the syntax and we parallelize independent frames, right?
If like two frames are independent of each other and the references are already done,
we can do those in parallel, which of course means that, you know, how much we can parallelize
depends on the number of CTUs that are available, which are always more in high resolution or
with smaller CTU sizes.
That's why the faster and fast presets which have smaller CTUs, they parallelize a little
bit better, which you can see on the top right there in the full HD parallelization efficiency
plot, right?
You can see like after eight, it's kind of, well, it doesn't saturate, but like after
eight threads, there might be better ways to utilize the resources than to just enable
more threads.
Exactly.
And how can we improve the scaling?
So we can improve the scaling by enabling normative features of VBC.
So either doing tiles, that is independent regions within the picture, or enabling the
normative wavefront, which allows us to kill one dependency within encoding.
And this is on the bottom right.
So you can see, if we enable those additional features, the multi-threading scaling actually
gets much better, but it costs between three to 5% of bitrate overhead.
But still, even with those added features, the encoder is not ready yet for more than
let's say 32 threads.
So if you have a really, really big server, that encoder will not be able to utilize all
the cores.
Yeah.
And about our optimization for the human visual system, it's based on the XPSNR, which is
a new metric that a colleague at HHI developed.
It has a really high correlation with MOS based on some public datasets.
There are publications you can look up.
There are mentioned on the bottom left.
And it has been contributed to FFmpeg as filter.
And I think it is somewhere in the backlog of FFmpeg waiting to be looked at.
You can see on the right here a lot of graphs.
So basically, in the last JVET meeting, no, the JVET meeting one before last, there was
a verification test with actual human subjects where VTM was tested with the new compression
technology and we submitted VVENC to be tested alongside of it in the slow preset.
So the slower preset has around the efficiency of VTM.
Slow preset is objectively 5% behind.
And as you can see in the graphs, VVENC in orange matches or outperforms VTM, which means
that our visual optimization is well able to at least close this 5% gap, if not even
add more in terms of visual, like subject to visual quality.
So yeah, that's really nice.
All right.
VVENC in practice.
Everyone asks in the end, so what kind of FPS can you achieve?
So we did some encodes onto mobile workstation kind of computers, encodes using all defaults,
which means eight threads.
And for HD versus live, it's like for faster is around times four, like live times four.
So around 15 FPS, medium around lifetime times 30.
All right.
So around two FPS, I'm talking about HD, 60 FPS is live.
For UHD, the faster can do like 15 times live, fast 30 and medium, well, let's just say medium
would only be of interest for like large scale VOD encodings, right?
But you know, FPS also depends on many other factors like bitrate content, you know, your
actual CPU and stuff like that.
So this is more like ballpark numbers.
Excuse me, is this HDR content?
It is not HDR content, but it's 10 bit.
So it should be roughly the same for HDR.
We only do, we only test with 10 bit usually.
It works for eight bit, but it's kind of 10 bit native.
All right.
Also some version history for the VVNK thing, for the VVNK project.
So our first major milestone was the 0.3 where we added frame threading.
And you can see on this multi-threaded efficiency versus speed graph that it was, you know,
a huge leap for us.
In the 1.0, we added a pure C interface, allowing, you know, the integrations into pure C frameworks.
1.4, sync at detection, 1.5, we added like arbitrary intra period, so it doesn't have
to be aligned to anything.
We added a fast decode preset and in the newest version, the thing that I really like about
it is that we added the ARM support.
And you know, every version we add improved ray control, things also to, you know, great
community feedback.
And you know, from one version to another, your encode might be 10% faster.
But if you had the ray control problem and it got fixed, it's going to be, you know,
like, way, way better.
So this is like, this hard to quantify improvements are actually one of the most important ones.
And you know, you can see how the curve behaves.
So extrapolating, I'm sure we're going to get even faster and better in the future.
All right.
About the ecosystem and the community, of course, you know, this is raw video encoding and decoding.
This is really only of academic interest, right?
It doesn't really bring you anything.
That's why we have been looking into FFmpeg support for a long time.
There was an open access paper over one half years ago that described how to do it for
the decoder.
There are some patches in the pipeline with FFmpeg.
We also put in our wiki how to apply them manually if you, you know, if you want to
build it, you know, I've talked about this a lot, but the thing is, you know, if it's
not in FFmpeg, it doesn't exist, that's why, you know, we put up a like how to for you
on how to do it.
All right.
About playback, once you get this FFmpeg with VBC included, you can just link whatever
player uses FFmpeg as its backend and it's going to work.
As far as I know for VLC, you might force it to use the FFmpeg as the demaxer.
Not sure about it.
I'll test it myself.
It comes like from community feedback.
I know there are some exo player integrations going around which allow you to, you know,
to use it in Android apps more easily.
We have a toy web browser example, but it's nothing like the VLC.js.
It's really a toy example.
And for maxing and demaxing, you can just use G pack.
Sorry, for maxing, you can just use G pack since the version 2.0 and I think it also
needs to be linked to an FFmpeg with VBC support.
All right.
For the community, we do are open to external contributions and we wish to get some.
That's also why I'm talking to you, to get some interest.
So we try to make this more easy by stating that the authors of VVENC are also retained
the copyright.
We don't have like a contributors agreement, so this is like the only way we can make it
happen.
We are interested in all kinds of contributions, you know, efficiencies, speed up, and we're
going to try to review this, test, generate, result, whatever is needed, give proper feedback,
merge.
So, yeah.
Please do if you're interested.
To conclude, you know, if you just enter the room, I talked to you about our open source
implementations of the VVC standard and I'm looking forward to, you know, contributions,
also results, tests, if you want to try it out, and general feedback.
Thanks a lot.
Any questions in the room?
Yeah, no problem.
What confused me, because I know a little bit about the backstory, so H.265, right?
Yeah.
Was it super proprietary and the royalties and the Alliance for Media Alarm, the AV-ROM
cabinet?
Yes.
And now the eukaryotes is open source and free, right?
So to recap...
To recap the question, the question was H.265 was a proprietary codec with licensing, AV-1
is a non-propertory codec, and then I'm talking about VVC, which is the successor of H.265.
And there is a small confusion, so I'm not talking about the codec as being open source.
It's about the implementations of it, right?
So you have to differentiate between implementations and the technology itself.
There will be licensing for the technology itself, but there are still open source implementations
also of H.B.C.
So that's kind of the way I would like to see it, you know?
So it won't be like with MP3, but for all of us, it will be completely free to use,
for everyone?
No, it won't.
I mean, the software is free to use, but if you build your streaming service based on
the technology independent of which software you use, you have to pay royalties for the
technology.
Because you have bad patents, bad patent issues.
Yes, I mean, there is this technology cost stuff to develop and people want to get their
investment back.
Okay, disclaimer, I'm doing this in the optimizations for video codecs in general.
My focus is on, and my comment to you is using a library like Cinq everywhere it works.
It's going to give you the initial results that you want, but you will never get the
optimal performance out of your hardware.
We had some really good examples of code, particular algorithms like O-instructions,
Intrinsics, MoveMask type of Intrinsics, but I view it very commonly popular in Intel.
If you try to port them with Cinq everywhere or some kind of obstruction layer to one,
you're going to have to emulate this behavior.
So ideally, you have to provide some way to provide optimized functions for ARM or any
other future architecture.
Otherwise, you're just going to have your Intel layer transferred, translated to one.
It will work, but you will never optimize your software.
To recap the comment, there was a comment that Cinq everywhere works, gives a nice initial
deliverable, but will never match hand-optimized assembler.
We are...
It's even a C, C with the corresponding ARM Intrinsics.
When I say assembler, I mean Intrinsics.
We are aware of it, and we are looking a little bit of it.
There are different kinds of intrinsic kernels that are implemented there.
Sometimes you have two pieces of memory that needs to be added up and stored somewhere
else.
There, everywhere works really nice, but when it's like lookup tables, shuffles, it works
worse.
We are aware.
We are looking into identifying the kernels where there's the biggest potential for improvement
and doing those manually.
We are looking into HDR implementation of VBX.
I'm doing the VNFT optimizations for that.
The way to do the transpose, for example, in 10 is completely different to the way VNFT
is looking, especially with...
Because for AVX2, you have 256 bitwise registers.
You don't have that with me, but you have other instructions to help you try to tackle
the outcome.
My point is that if you are open to contributions with specific optimizations, then you might
find people to help prepare you that.
But if you restrict yourself to only using the library and only use Intel Intrinsics
and then translate that one using the library, you might lose some performance.
A lot.
We are not restricting ourselves to only using this.
It's just because we only have so many resources.
This was the fastest way to do it.
We can play it out on...
Actually, this thing can play out VBC videos with our software.
But totally, I think there would need to be some changes to the build process, maybe to
the structure of the project to enable this.
But this is something really very interesting, and I think there will be a lot of research
going on in that direction.
Thanks.
One last question.
How does it compare?
What are the advantages of AV1 in terms of compression or computation?
The question is, what are the advantages of VBC or VV-ENC?
VBC over AV1.
What are the advantages of VBC over AV1?
VBC is the successor to HVBC.
It was done by people who were really knowledgeable on how to make a standard work.
The one thing, it just provides the additional bitrate savings.
Here, you still see 20% additional bitrate savings over the best case of AV1.
There isn't so many of these initial hiccups.
The HDR support just works.
Immersive stuff just works.
A lot of those things, they just work.
Then we can do stuff on top of that, like doing open-gop adaptive streaming, which allows
you to reduce the bitrate by another 10% on top of that.
With all the other standards, I think the adaptive streaming can only be done with closed
gops, with a prediction break.
I would say more mature, but I know there are different views of it, more compression
efficiency and really versatile mature usability.
Thank you, Adam.
Thanks.