Last but not least, it's Christophe Massieu.
But first of all, I would like to thank him for his work organizing the dev room all day.
Thank you.
Sat here.
Not too much.
Yes, Fostem is a volunteer event.
And Christophe will be talking about distributing multicast channels to third parties, a case
study with OpenSoft software and virtualization slash SR-IOV.
Thank you, Kirana.
And also thank you, Kirana, for co-organizing the dev room with me.
Exactly.
And if next year there are more volunteers, I think we would be happy to have that.
So I'm Christophe Massieu.
I've been in the broadcast business for quite some time now.
And I run a company called Easy Tools.
One of the purpose of this company is to distribute linear channels.
So either we create them or we get them from satellite or from abroad or we get them in
data centers and we deliver them somewhere in the world or to network operators and so
on.
So one of the critical parts of doing that is knowing how to distribute multicast to
other people.
Usually how does it work?
So first I must clarify, linear channel from my point of view at least, it's basically
transport stream, so it's MPEG-TS over UDP or RTP, depends on your religion, both exist,
and generally multicast.
So usually you put seven TS packets inside one UDP frame and you're done.
And it's a continuous stream all the time.
How do you exchange these kind of streams?
Usually you take a rack in a well-known point of exchange.
In Paris there is one called Terre House.
It's very popular, everybody knows that in Paris.
And so you have your rack, you put your switch and you buy cross-connects from your data
center to your peers.
So your peers can be your sources, people who provide your streams, or it could be where
you distribute them, so the distributors, the operators and so on.
So for safety reasons you will want to have each source or each operator in a different
VLAN so that they don't see each other.
From confidentiality and also some content is a little bit critical.
So the question will be how do you copy basically a multicast from one source VLAN to a destination
VLAN.
It's stupid and perfectly easy to answer, but it's not so easy.
There is a pure network solution.
With some switches you have a feature called multicast service reflection.
That's what Cisco provides.
I'm pretty sure there is the equivalent on Juniper and that kind of thing.
But it's not so widely available.
Lots of switches don't handle it.
Only a small range of that.
And so basically you can type a command there to say that you copy this multicast address
to this destination and so you copy from a VLAN to another VLAN.
So it's not widely available.
There are good chances that your switches do not support it.
And also you cannot handle complex use cases like some operators want RTP, some don't want
RTP.
You cannot remove RTP with that.
And some operators also want you to have specific PIDs, specific service IDs, different service
names and so on.
That you cannot do of course.
So generally you will end up using the devices on top of your switch.
You will have to plug a device that will do that kind of job.
The broadcast solution, well the most popular one is what we call DCM.
It's a very popular brand.
You're initially by Cisco, now it's a company called CineMedia.
It's a hardware service with electronics inside and it does all this work of switching.
It can even transcode actually with some cards.
It does a lot of things.
But it's also very expensive of course.
But we have an open source alternative.
It's actually something I wrote maybe 15 years ago.
It's called DV Blast.
I've been doing a lot of talks about that.
In this use case it also helps.
Usually it was written as DVBDMux.
So you have a satellite card or DTT card and you want to get a transponder and split each
channel into a multicast address.
That was the original goal of DV Blast.
But actually with the dash D option you can also read from a multicast channel.
And in the arguments you can also say which is the IP address of the interface you want
to read it from.
So basically which VLAN.
That means which VLAN you will read it from.
So basically that reads a multicast stream from a specific VLAN.
There is a configuration file associated with DV Blast and you can put as many lines as
you want.
So as many distributors as you want.
And for each line you will just put the multicast address you want to send it to.
And you can also optionally give the address of the interface.
Again you want to send it to.
The VLANs you have on your switch they will appear as network interfaces on your server.
So you can decide to which VLAN you want to send and which multicast address.
You have a number of options to turn on or off RTP.
You can remap PIDs, SID, channel service name and you can even spoof the source address
which is very useful in case your peer wants to do IGMPv3.
In that case you ask you to put a specific source address and that's the easiest way
to spoof it.
So problem solved.
End of talk.
Thank you very much.
Now I wanted to add a little something.
You may want to run hundreds of DV Blast on one server but for some reason I wanted to
do some virtualization.
Why virtualize?
Because I have different customers and each of the customer has different channels.
Some of them are doing adult content, some of them are doing children content.
Maybe I don't want to mix that in the same server and I don't have the money to have
multiple servers at ten hours because it's expensive.
So for client installation it's required.
Also some of my clients have direct access to the VM because that's the service I sell.
So again I don't want them to see the streams of the competitors potentially.
So I used Proxmox that's a very nice distribution based on DBN and it's a very big front end
over KVM, very useful.
And in Proxmox what you will do is each of the VLAN you get from the Twitch you will
bridge that and on your guest virtual machine it will appear as a network interface with
the VERT IOD driver.
The VERT IOD driver is the most optimized one.
You can also emulate a network app but it's much slower.
That's why everybody uses VERT IOD driver.
So everything works fine end of talk and thank you very much for coming.
There is just one little problem.
The morning when you get called by one of your big customers and he says I have discontinuities
on what you send me.
Discontinuities that's what every people in broadcast feels and you listen you start another
DV blast on the IP address that you put in and you see nothing.
Everything looks fine and they insist and another customer complains.
So what you do is you rack another server.
That's a use case by the way that's why I'm saving my life.
So you rack another server and you listen to what the other server is sending and then
you see a lot of discontinuities indeed.
And you dig it and you just see that the VERT IOD driver I don't know if it's guest side
or host side reorder some packets.
I mean probably there are several queues inside the drivers and if this packet does not have
any luck and goes into a queue that for some reason doesn't run for some time it will be
pushed there.
So I hear now the network guy will tell me that while there is no guarantee on the order
of UDP packets that's the specification that's true.
But we are in an industry that relies on it because if you don't have RTP there is absolutely
no way you can reorder your UDP transport string.
So I had to find a solution.
I cannot tell my customer no no you have to use RTP and I don't care.
You cannot.
So I found a first workaround is by using another driver.
It's also a driver designed for virtual system, VMware.
But it's supported by Poxmox KVM and so on.
So it's called VMXnet and probably this one only has one queue and it solves the problem.
The only problem is that it uses 30% more CPU and this server is only doing that.
And I already have 64 core IMD APIC servers.
That's not full but more than 50% already.
So there is some kind of need to optimize.
So that's why I started to look at other alternatives and many big some clever ideas that I found
on the net and one of them that you probably heard of maybe is called SR-ROV.
So what is SR-ROV?
So it's a feature of some network cards not all network cards.
Some network cards are that feature.
In a normal installation for the network card is owned by the host.
You have some kind of software switch that is handled by the virtualizer and here you
have virtual interfaces to each of the virtual machine.
In an SR-ROV setup what happens is that the network card will create new PCI devices.
So it's a different PCI device.
And this PCI device there is a feature called VTD on Intel that you have the equivalent
on IMD that will allow you to dedicate a PCI device to a virtual machine.
And doing that the virtual machine directly talks to the PCI device without anything going
through the host.
So that looks quite interesting.
These new devices are called virtual functions, VF.
And so on the VM you just need to have a VF driver which is included in the Linux anyway.
So in my use case I used Intel cards.
They're not the only ones doing SR-ROV but it may be a little bit different if you use
different cards.
Not all cards have the same features.
So using SR-ROV it's a little bit tricky.
First it requires support from the motherboard, the CPU, the BIOS itself and of course the
network card as I was just saying.
You have to enable a number of features in the BIOS, IOMMU but also HGS, ARR which is
some kind of PCI Express routing protocol.
Lots of things and basically we spent a couple hours I think just setting it up.
My personal advice would be for you to upgrade the card from the drivers, the Intel drivers
to the latest version and the card firmware because there is a firmware running on the
card to the latest version supported by the driver.
Once I did not do that when I started my test and I ended up having half of my VLANs working
and the other half didn't work and there is absolutely no way to know what's going on
I just had to reboot and it was in production.
So I had to imagine what happened.
Creating the virtual function is actually quite easy.
It's just echo into a slash this device and with my Intel card I can create up to 64 virtual
functions so that's up to typically 64 VMs.
So the path through is very easy on the Proxmox, it's just a menu and potentially each VM has
access to other VMs.
So that may be also drawback because it sees all the traffic that it can send to any VLAN
can send packets on any VLAN so you have to trust your clients a little bit so it may
not be adapted to all situations.
But it's quite useful because you don't have to create a bridge every time you want to
create a new VLAN you just create a network interface, a new A-1, Q network interface
into your VM and that's all.
So it's actually easier to manage.
Problem is, so everything looks perfectly fine so that the end of the talk, not yet.
I talked about sending to VLANs but how to receive multicast from the VLAN.
That's another problem.
But initially it looks like it works so you put it in production, maybe a bit early.
So how does it work, how does a network card work with multicast?
First I should maybe remind you how it works.
So you have your multicast IP address, you translate that to the multicast MAC address
so the end is the same and the beginning is just dropped.
And then you tell the card every packet that arrives on this MAC address, I want it.
So that's how it works on any normal PC.
That's quite a standard, it's called a MAC filter.
It's quite a standard feature.
The trick is on these cards the number of MAC filters is limited.
And the way they limit it is a little bit stupid.
They take the whole buffer of the card, the whole number of MAC filters they have and
they divide it by the number of VF you have, so 64.
And in the end, according to my calculation, your limit is around 100 multicast addresses.
So 100 may be a lot but I have hundreds of multicast streams in my network.
So you may reach it.
You may think about segmenting your virtual machines not to go above the threshold interval
but it's still a dangerous game because there is a feature of the interdriver that if you
reach that limit, it's scientific phase of course, while you have a message in the message
but nobody reads that.
So you will try again and try again and try again.
And after just a few trials like five, the kernel decides that your VM is crazy and it
won't talk to it anymore.
So you will still receive your multicast but if you have any other command to send to the
card like creating a new VLAN, which could happen, you have a new distributor so you
can't, you have to reboot.
You have to reboot your VM, fortunately, not the host.
So it's not that practical and to be honest, I have a patch in all my installation that
disables the doing that feature and disables using the Mac filter at all actually because
I have found it not practical in reality.
Yeah.
Is there any need for the Mac filtering at all given that like modern switches, you're
going to beat it or not your
So, promise use mode means what it means.
It means UVM will receive all the traffic
that is received by the network card.
It looks like a good idea,
but it dramatically increases CPU usage
because from maybe two gigabytes per second of data,
you only need 200 megabytes per second of data,
and the rest, the kernel, we have to filter it.
So, your kernel will do a lot of job.
And from what I've calculated,
basically the gain you had from going from VERTIO to SRRUV,
you lose it right there.
So, that's first.
The second problem is that,
imagine you have two gigabytes per second on your network,
and you have 20 virtual machines.
The network card will send 20 times two gigabytes per second
to your virtual machines, and that means 40.
And 40 is the limit of the card.
And at that point, you will start losing packets randomly.
Again, silently, you don't know what happens.
And of course, obviously, you only know that in production
because when you first started with one, two, three VM,
it worked perfectly.
So, it's, yes, I have my solution.
And then you put all your load on it,
and then one day, it just stops working.
So, while activating POMICUS mode is actually quite easy,
again, it's an echo in the FlashSYS file.
So, I have found a second workaround,
which is a little bit better.
I'm using it in production.
It's good, maybe it's only on the Intel card.
I don't know if it exists on other brands,
but it's a feature called VLAN Mirror.
And basically, it tells the card to send all the traffic
belonging to VLAN to a particular virtual function,
to a particular VM.
So, that kind of a POMICUS feature,
but only for one VM.
Which is kind of a good practice because it means that
I think most people who have ever done multicast,
when you have a backbone,
you put all of your multicast addresses in the same VM,
maybe with different address ranges or maybe not.
And you expect at the other end that the receiver
will pick up which multicast address you want.
This approach, it forces you to have different VLANs
per customers.
So, it's actually not a bad idea.
But there is one drawback.
One specific VLAN can only be sent to one VM.
So, if you have, let's say a big broadcaster
that is sending you channels
and several VLANs needs those channels,
you cannot use that solution.
Because only one will be able to read from that VLAN.
So, I have a third workaround.
It's just to go back to the good old vert.io.
After all, why not?
The packets in search or the packet in version
were only on TX, not on RX.
So, it works.
Actually, it has also some additional features
because the bridge in Proxmox at least,
but most of the time, it has IGMP snooping.
So, we only receive the multicast addresses
that you subscribe to.
But it's actually a good solution,
but then it means you have basically interfaces
to read the packet from
and interfaces to send the packets to.
Which is a bit of a mess, but still, it's a good compromise.
That's my compromise currently.
VLAN mirror, all this one,
depending on the nature of the VLAN I have to read from.
So, all is good in the best of words.
At the end of the talk, thank you very much.
Not quite.
There is another topic I haven't mentioned yet.
What if I want to read a multicast stream
coming from another VM on the same server?
That doesn't work.
Because when you write through SROV,
just outputs to the switch.
As far as I know, or maybe some of you are the solution,
there is no way to get the traffic back
to the network card and use it in another virtual machine.
You could do that,
but if you don't want to have different VLANs,
if you want to read from the same VLAN,
then you cannot root.
Okay.
Well, there is another solution with the Intel card again.
It's called egress mirror.
You can make it so that everything that's output
on virtual function number one
will be mirrored to virtual function number seven.
So, virtual function number seven will be on
your receiving side and virtual function number one
will be on the transmitting side.
So, that actually works.
And also, I use that in production.
So, conclusions.
Well, multicast on virtualized environment
is no picnic actually, and I'm surprised.
You don't find many papers about that.
I've struggled literally for years on this problem
with a number of problems in production
because you only see the problem in production
because you only see them under load.
And so, this has been a little bit tiring.
Thank you very much for listening to this.
And if you have any questions.
Yeah.
I'm guessing you tried that, but in virtual,
there are ways to actually ask it to be dumber.
Like, I'm not doing some of the floating balls
and I'm not sure, but probably you tried that.
But you could probably have asked them,
they have to say, hey, I just keep them in order.
So, you say in virtual, there are ways to ask it
to be dumber.
I'm not sure.
We are doing packet slide.
Yeah, I'm not sure I've actually tested it.
I'm pretty sure it would have the same effect
as using VMXNet.
And probably you would see an increase in CPU consumption.
And anyway, I wanted to go to SRIOV
because, for all the reasons,
because I wanted to have my VM talk directly
to the network hub, I think it was better practice
than virtual.
I'm going to have to go that way.
Yeah, James?
I think you can back the previous slide, please.
Yeah.
Okay, there was no question.
Yeah?
Just AWS provide the ECQ instance with the SRIOV.
With SRIOV?
Yeah.
Okay.
So, he says AWS provides instances with SRIOV.
But they have to.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I guess so, but I guess in the cloud,
you don't have that kind of problem
because usually you do SRT.
Usually.
And SRT doesn't care if you eat your other packet
because it will.
Similar question to this, gentlemen.
Yeah?
Did you consider forcing, well,
either disable multi-Q on the host
or forcing each VM to a different queue?
So that by definition, you will not be reordering.
Forcing each VM to a different queue,
I'm not sure it works.
A disable queuing probably it will work,
but with additional CPU usage.
Yeah.
So that's what I wanted to,
as I said, I have 60 core APIC servers,
which are pretty big and they're not full, but.
You should be possible to pin,
it's possible to pin a process to the game.
If you do XPS CPUs, you can pin the process.
At the end, I don't know if you can do that.
But I'm not sure if the inversion happens
on the host side or on the guest side.
Disable multi-Q in your host.
Yeah.
So yeah.
Yibei?
Why do you want to use SRUV for,
like, what things differently is like,
what are the other use cases you're thinking about
with SRUV?
So the question is why did I want to use SRUV?
Speed.
Speed is the first argument, actually,
but also some kind of clean design.
Maybe I'm a little bit of a purist
and I wanted my VM to have direct access,
physical access, I mean, to the network.
Also, so if you really want the list of arguments,
the traditional way of doing VLAN bridging
on POC smokes, but probably other environments,
you create a bridge for each VLAN.
And so you have a network interface for each VLAN.
Maybe there is a way to avoid that,
but I didn't look too much into that.
That means you have a limit
because I think you're limited to 32 network interfaces.
The limit is low enough.
You should switch to OVX switch and not to the cloud.
Otherwise you have to switch to OVX switch,
but considering the amount of problems I had without it,
I thought maybe I will not go into that.
I haven't tried, to be honest.
Yeah.
These are probably people,
you don't see papers about the most people
like Apple versus just AT&T,
AT&T and AT&T as well.
Exactly, as you said,
so are you these mainly used by people to do HTTP
or some TCP based.
It depends on using SIOV for non-networking things.
Ah, you may ask if I'm considering using SIOV
for non-networking things.
I suppose you imply GPU maybe.
Maybe, but my question is,
do you envision other places where you meet media
and you could use short GPU is almost obvious one,
but are they, have you ever thought of
this in the policy?
The GPU we've actually tried to,
not sure the one we had supported SIOV,
but that's.
So it's really expensive ones.
Yeah, they have features like VTG, I think.
But in our experience, it did not work well.
But we would like to have the ability to share a GPU
among several instances.
So that you could decode or encode
on different VMs and so on.
This virtual machine that we have at the house,
they don't do that because the house is not the place
to do transcoding because it's too expensive.
But fundamentally, yes, I would be interested in having
that for GPUs as well.
At least GPUs, if you have any other ideas, tell me.
That's not also a different question.
Just mentioning because of practical techniques,
support, sometimes with support as well for
SIOV for record codes and they are expensive.
And it's just landing approximately clearly.
So you can actually play with that.
You can have the way for the transfer plus lambda
and it's like, you have the nearest for like 16
CPUs as well.
Could you use that to do SDI or NDI
path route to get directly to the server?
Yeah, you don't need a SIOV for that.
The question was, can you use that for SDI
or NDI path route?
Well, NDI is network.
But SDI, I think we tried it and you can pass
through the Blackmagic, for instance, device.
You pass it through every TD.
Every TD is one thing.
Every TD, I already pass through DVB tuners.
You can probably pass through DVB ASI, probably SDI.
Even though we don't do that on a regular basis.
But have you tried a different connector on a different VM?
Yes.
You have four inputs.
Different connector on a different VM
that would not be possible with the Blackmagic driver
because it's seen as one device, one PCI device.
So it's not possible.
If you design your own car, maybe,
Siwan, you may want to answer that question.
No?
Yes, we could do it, yes.
There's no technical reason.
Yes, Gav?
Do you have any container technology?
We could use container.
The thing is, as you know, we have our own software.
And our own software is actually delivered as a disk image.
So it can only run as a virtual machine.
The idea to use container is not a bad idea.
There is less isolation, though,
than what you have with virtual machine.
But this is something I would like to try
in the middle term, yeah.
Because there has been a lot of improvement
in the past years, the Galaxy network,
and the next phase.
And you can probably have some direct
Mac-
interface, so I think some kind of physical interface,
we have a direct Mac-
in the container and a direct physical interface.
I think we are running out of time.
Wow, that was a-
$ approve entered an ECLT May