about FFmpeg advocacy because this guy does everything. Please welcome Jean-Réthis Tham.
Yeah, so I'm going to do two small presentation because those are short talks and I didn't
want to take too much time today. So we're going to speak about FFmpeg and mostly FFmpeg
6.0. But then I will speak about a new project called vlc.js, but it's a lie, it's not really
vlc.js. So who am I? My name is Jean-Réthis. Some of you know me, some don't, so I'm president
of Videland. I've been working on VLC for... Okay, I'm close to 40, so 17 years. I've been involved
in index264, which is a Videland project, David, which is an AV1 decoder, and lately a bit on FFmpeg,
mostly on the community management, which is a funny topic. I shouldn't be the one presenting
this presentation, but the people who should present this presentation are maybe in this room
and don't want to present, so that's why I'm presenting. Jokes aside, if you look at the
first damn open media room, there is almost no FFmpeg talk, which is completely insane.
This year is better, thanks to Kiran and Toorimi, but it's ridiculous. If you look also in the
archives, I look in the archives, there is almost no FFmpeg, general FFmpeg talk. Everything in the
community media, in the open source world, and outside of the open source world, is actually based
on FFmpeg. And when I mean everything, I mean everything you see online, and most of those,
like you go to those big trade shows, and they are all amazing cloud encoding, so on, and it's just
like a very nice one to FFmpeg. And of course, when I say FFmpeg, please understand, this is FFmpeg
plus Linux 264 plus Linux 6.5 plus Linux VPX plus David plus all the other libraries that I forget.
So, and like even on our Vueci or Mademoiselle, or like you know those French fashion things that
we have, which is called Hacker News, even on Hacker News, like when there is a release of FFmpeg,
it's not even the top Hacker News, right? So that means that we are doing something wrong,
which means we don't communicate enough on FFmpeg, so here I am. So the community is healthy. We've
had some fights in the past, to be honest. The folks are long gone, and most of the people
working now on FFmpeg are also parts, lots of new people who are not there at the fork time,
but also people from both folks are still working on FFmpeg. That's pretty cool,
especially since we've not seen that many open source community being able to work together
after those type of events. So here I'm just going to speak just quickly about FFmpeg 5.0,
which was around almost exactly one year ago. It was very important because we try to match the
new release schedules that I'm going to talk about, but it's also like, was probably the biggest
API breakage ever on FFmpeg. I think just a train of commits removing deprecation samples was around
130 commits, and the diff was huge. So some APIs were deprecated in 2013 and were removed in 5.0.
So this is probably going to impact a lot of you, because a lot of distributions are still on 4.4,
but 5.0 is a big change of APIs, and mostly there is one big thing, is that it's one API
to decode both audio and video, and not AV codec video decode 4, 5, 6, and so on. All those APIs.
It's not doing subtitles yet, but I was promised that someone will do it this year. Where is Anton?
Yeah. We did a lot of new things. AV frame base appearing in SW scale, new bit streaming filters,
a lot of things to clean. AV format and AV codec is decenting those two libraries,
working on the decoder contacts, etc. You should look at the release notes on that.
There are some people who are doing amazing work, mostly Andreas and James, who are basically
removing all the craft on FFmpeg. So one day the whole FFmpeg will be thread safe.
Right? We believe that, right? And AV codec, any of the formats will be completely split,
yeah, okay. Maybe not, but there is a lot of work to be done, and that's very important for security
reasons. Michael, who is still probably the oldest FFmpeg contributor, is still fuzzing FFmpeg every
day. Slice thread setting is W scale, IMF de-maxing, which is good because so many professionals are
using IMA format, and they usually do weird things on FFmpeg, or above FFmpeg, and then we have to
deal with their shit because it's wrong glimax, so now we're actually getting that directly into FFmpeg.
Dolby Vision, I'm not sure exactly which part of Dolby Vision, because there is, as many of you know,
five or six profiles, but I think at least profile five were there, and of course a lot of things,
and one of the cool things was the integration of LiPlacibo, which used to be the MPV video filtering
framework, mostly GPU accelerated, that is now into FFmpeg, and you can use that without GPU
easily with emulation. So the old APIs, like you know the old APIs, and now we really, what's
interesting is that it's more async-based, and so you don't need to do those horrible weights.
Five dot one, so that was like six months ago, in July, this one is important for you because
it's an LTS, five dot zero is not LTS, so we try, we're going to try to make that, to fix at least
the security bugs for a couple of years, and it, like most of the things that were added were a
lot of features, but one of the major API that was merged was the change of the audio channel
layout API, which was supposed to come in five dot zero, but we missed, and then we said well
it's going to take too much time, so that we did that with five dot one. A lot of optimization on
ARM in that release, mostly on HEVC decoding, a lot of things on AV1 decoding in hardware,
because there is still 25 different APIs to do hardware acceleration, but soon there will be
a new one that is going to replace all of them, which is Vulkan video decoding, and we'll have
14 standards. JPEG XL decoding, and a lot of things on SVTV1. So yeah, the channel layout
API was developed in 2013, I think by Vittorio, I'm not sure he's around, yeah, Vittorio, that was done
during the fork, and it was quite complex, but this is good because it's ready to do what we
called, well, what marketing calls NGA, which is next generation audio, what marketing also
calls Dolby Atmos, right, those kind of object-based audio, and like the new channel layout API allows
to be a lot more flexible, do custom layouts and weird things without us having to do everything
directly inside FFmpeg. So, and I'm still not starting about my main topic, which is FFmpeg 6.0,
I hope when I was submitting the code that this would have been tagged,
and that's important, I think this is even bigger in terms of a number of commits, and mostly in
terms of contributors, because in the last six months there have been around 191 contributors,
that's huge, and that's a lot bigger than the previous release. What is important? There is not
that many important API breakage and changes, but there is new APIs, and also it's a major bump,
so we are going to remove more things that were deprecated in the last few years, and there was
like two new APIs, so that we didn't remove them in 5.0, but we are going to remove that soon.
Soon. One of the major changes, one of the most difficult things that we've seen is multi-threading
the FFmpeg CLI, right? So all those big guys at YouTube and Vimeo and Facebook, and all those
providers of FFmpeg nice UIs are basically one of the things they complained about is the lack of
multi-threading and FFmpeg, so they invent a lot of weird frameworks to do that, so there is a lot
of work to do that directly inside FFmpeg. It's going to go on for the whole year, I think, for
all 2023, but that means that a lot of things will be better for you to use, and of course when you
do that you need to actually care about thread safety and cleanups, so that's a lot of cleanups.
What was done for 5.0 was that the muxes are now in their own threads, there will be more things.
There is now a RISC-V optimization, or at least the framework to do that inside FFmpeg. One of the
things that is important is that you've probably seen that all the big guys building GPUs have
now shipped AV1 encoders, so in 6.0 we've got Intel and NVIDIA and AMD, so you can actually encode AV1
in hardware, and that's actually very fast, right? You can reach 30 FPS in 1080p without any problem
with those cards, and it's actually decent quality, it's not as good as the SVTA V1, of course, but
it's pretty good. There was a lot of work on the FFT code by Lynn, she's over there, she can tell
you about that, and I think it's like, I don't know how much faster it is, but it's a lot faster, so
all the audio codecs and all the audio filters that require the UZFFT, and sometimes is better
than the external FFT libraries that everyone is using. New RPI for reconstructed frame for
encoders, RBI breakage for deprecation, we have, of course, what I hate, lots of new YUV format and
pixel format, because there is always a good reason to add them, and when I'm downstream as
VLT I hate that, but any. Lots of things on channel layouts and H.264, H.274, mostly about external
filters. One of the big parts on those features is everything related to hardware, so I said about
AV1 hardware decoding, a lot of pixel formats, especially for hardware. There is finally the
Android media codec using directly NDK and not with a Java Crap that is directly integrated into
FFmpeg. I think that requires API Android 23, but I'm not exactly sure, and we also have the
encoding and not just the decoding, but also based on media codec. We have the Intel folks have done
a lot of things to have a 10-bit, 12-bit, 4.2, 2.4, 4.4, VP9 decoding directly inside FFmpeg. That's
one of the reasons why we have new pixel formats. In terms of actual features, there is of course
lots of new codecs, lots of new filters. The ones I prefer are the FTR, which is a
annoying company who doesn't want us to reverse engine that, Bonk, APAC, there is a SIM SSIM 360
filter and some very cool bitstream filter for the DTS to PTS one. Look at that one, it's quite
useful. Yeah, so FFmpeg CLI multishreading, as I said. This is partly done in 6.0. It will be
continued on 6.1 and 7.0. It is difficult and it's long, but this is going to improve all your lives,
or at least especially if you want to do a multi HLS dash, multiple transcode, multiple
resolution and do that directly without using third parties. FFmpeg releases, this is a slide I took
exactly from a previous talk and we never talked about that during FOSDAM, so that's why I'm talking
about it. The problem that was like FFmpeg releases were kind of, well before there was not,
right? So we all took the good show one and hope it was great and then we're seeing what
mplay was doing, then VLC was copying and well if mplay on VLC agreed and everyone was using that,
then we started having releases and done by Michael and sometimes they were not very predictable. So
one of the ideas is to start to come to a more predictable fashion, which is one major
API break and API break every year around December, January, so we're in February and we
fucked this year, but that's the idea, right? So one major where we allow API and API breakage,
right? We remove APIs. When it's deprecated, it must be there for two years before we move that,
but we will bump the SO numbers, right? And then one or two releases during the year,
depending on security and what we need, so 5.0, 5.1, and every two years one of the dot one will be LTS
and we'll continue that for two or three years. So the plan was to do FFmpegs.0 in January,
I hope it's going to come next week, we'll see. Yeah, this was not on schedule, so I'm adding a
a shorter talk in the middle of my two talks. David 1.0 was released last year. It is insane.
200,000 lines of handwritten assembly, I don't think there is any open source project that I
had. I'm not sure there is even a non-open source project that has that much assembly. And yes,
handwritten assembly is faster than using whatever version of whatever compiler and activating
whatever amazing feature that is going to auto vectorize something. We still do 5.8,
16 times faster than C, so don't bring that up. It is insane, yet it's necessary, right? So when
you decode AV1, so AV1 is now in all your iOS devices, all your Android devices, all your
applications that decode AV1. It's on MacOS, it's on Windows, it's of course in Chrome, it's of course
in VLC and PV and all the other things. So it's literally everywhere. A lot of work was done in
the David 1.0 about frame-throwing, like there is lots of, please see the talks from Ronaldo
for a few years ago. Wow, okay, good. About the different spreading models that are inside David,
and David 1.0 has everything in a simpler way. We are going to, it's extremely fast, very fast.
Yes. David 1.0, 1.1 releases is coming soon, soonish. A lot of fixing, especially because
there were a lot of conformance tests that we were not passing, and for some reason they got out,
and there is of course lots of new assembly, especially for AVX 512 and here.
Cool. We're going to speak about, well I'm going to do a demo, which is VLC.js, which is actually
not in JS. So what are we talking about? Yeah. So this is Chrome, and this is why I'm on MacOS,
and not my usual Linux for the people who wonder. This is VLC and FFmpeg and all the dependencies
compiled to WebAssembly, and what you cannot see, but this is doing hardware decoding through Web
Codex, right? So what happens here is that what you're seeing is that it's actually decoded on
the hardware through Web Codex, and then you take the output frame directly into WebGL, and well,
OpenGL ES2, which is compiled to WebGL, and display that. And this is a 4K H.264 MP4, blah, blah, blah.
Okay, that's boring, JB. I can do 4K H.264 everywhere. Sure, sure you can. So let's do
something a bit more complex. So this is the same, probably a device, except it's MKV.
The MKV part is done in Wasm, right? It's a normal VLC demuxer. There is no JavaScript involved,
right? I'm not demuxing MKV and remixing as MP4 like H.L.js. Yes, of course, chapters support,
because, well, what's the use of that? But also, if I found my mouse again, no, where is it?
Yeah, you have also chapter subtitles, which are not WebVTT, right? Normal DVB subtitles.
Okay, so that's not too amazing, right? So let's do something more complex.
Okay, 4K VP9 in software decoding directly inside the web browser. Okay, that's pretty much better,
right? WebM on Mac OS, right? So, well, yeah, but professional, they use like actual format,
like MPactS. Let's do, so that's something that is ATSC over the air, right? So that's HEVC,
A-V-3-T-S, right? All the stuff that is not in the web browser, it's decoded and displayed directly
into your web browser. And that's where you realize that the US TV is really dumb.
Okay, but, okay, so that was hardware accelerated or not, because that was its GDC.
As you can guess, right, I can either force web codec or AV codec. So now I'm going to force
software decoding, and I'm going to show you something a bit more complex, which is,
this is Korean TV, which is interlaced, and the interlacing is happening as a WebGL shader
directly inside your web browser, right? So we're decoding H.264 interlaced. Of course,
we cannot do that by hardware, because of course, API doesn't support interlaced codec. So we decode
full in software, and then we display directly and do sharpening and the interlacing of those
very old multicast formats without any change. Okay, and I guess I got no. Yeah, I got one minute
more. So this is DNA-CHD. Of course, the output is not 4-2-0, but it's 4-2-2, and that's actually
interlaced and decoded as M-X-F directly, all those professional formats, you play that directly
inside the web browser. So of course, if we can do 4-2-2 and down sampling 4-2-2-2, 4-2-0 in software,
well, on the GPU, I can also do 4-4-4. So this is YUV, 4-4-4, 10-bit, right? Of course, BBB, right?
But things that are absolutely not possible with any type of APIs. I probably also can show you
that we can do other filters, and this is a 360 movie that we have with the support on VLC,
and of course, all the mapping from the title to Equio CrankDior is done on the GPU. Of course,
that means that everything that we do with Le Placibo in theory should get in, and I'm out of time.
Thank you.
Do we have any questions from the room?
So, an eighth question. So you said you have 200,000 lines of specialized code,
so perhaps there is no slowdown when you flip or rotate the image or do such transforms,
because you have a specialized version for that. Is it so?
You mean on David or here?
Oh, sorry. I cannot differentiate.
So on David, which really the decoding part, David is 200,000 lines of assembly just to do the
decoding. It's around 35,000 lines per architecture, and we do lots of architectures,
that then they give you a decoding surface, and then we use it in VLC,
MPV, FFM, and we do things, and here we would compile it directly inside WebAssembly,
run that in Web browser, and all the transformations are done then on WebGL. So that doesn't change
anything. No.
No, there shouldn't be.
On the dark question.
Can you compile assembly to WebAssembly assembly?
So one of the things that we tried with Lin, again, was what we call an assembly transpiler,
where you take actually the arm handwritten assembly and try to transpise that to
WebAssembly.scmd, right, so that you could use neon, and do exactly the opposite of what the
the web browser are actually doing, where they take the wasm assembly and compile that just
in time for neon and so on. It's a very insane project that I had the idea a few years ago.
It's really not sure whether we are going to be able to do that, because you're transpiling
assembly, like what the fuck are you talking about? But yes, I think that's the right solution
instead of rewriting, again, all the assembly from FFmpeg and David again. If you have time,
please come and help us. I might actually find also some money for that if people care.
Please ask questions. I don't eat people. Yes.
Last time I checked, I'm filing straight into WebAssembly everything that was thread,
POSIX, everything was pretty not yet finalized. Like what is the process for compile engineer?
It works fine, but that's also why you see that I'm on macOS, right, and I'm on Chrome and now
displaying my usual Firefox and Linux, because in order to have threads, you need to have what we
call shared array objects, which is basically common things. And because in the web world,
what they call web work, it's a serialization and deserialization to move data. Now this is
almost done, works everywhere, mostly on Chrome, now works on Safari, it works on Firefox, but it's
buggy. And also one of the things that is annoying is the off-screen canvas, because you want to be
able to read directly in the back buffer before displaying it. That doesn't work anywhere correctly.
And finally, the hardware decoder only works in Chrome for now. But maybe Firefox will do
something, wouldn't it? Sorry, what's the
sign of the payload that the page has to download to get that 25 megabytes?
So the idea is that we're going to, like VLC is a module approach, so there is like a very small
core and 400, 500, 600 now maybe, modules, and so you'll go, what I want is to actually be able to
load, and that's almost working in theory, so you can load the shared objects. So you would like
only stream the core, and then the core will know which one to go and download. Yes, Steve?
I'm not answering that question, thank you.
So the question was, when is FFmpeg community moving to a sane thing which is Geek Lab?
Not my short, right? Like you know my opinion, right? Video Land, VLC, all the iOS on the
Red port, x264 and so on. Even David is on Geek Lab and would like it. The FFmpeg community
prefers to stay on email. So I think it's a mistake because we are losing too many patches,
because it's very difficult to, but that's a community opinion and the community is a majority.
Last question? So if you're rendering in OpenGL or in the VLCJS, you're bypassing the media engine,
right? So how do you do the audio video synchronization? Well, of course we are. So the
answer is like, how are you doing audio video synchronization? Or like VLC, right? Like the core
of VLC was done by this guy and other guys to actually do live TV, right? So the core VLC is a
clock and the clock is basically working on doing synchronization audio and video and resampling the
audio when it's too late and so on. So here we are doing exactly that, right? So we output audio with
web audio. Well, no. A small part of web audio called audio worklets and so we know how much is
actually being played back and then we control the V out, which is basically the core of VLC to
synchronize audio and video. And we're using that there, but I'm not using any type of media source
extension or any other open media, blah, blah, blah. We are really like, it's mostly a video game. Okay.