So let's start. So our next talk is about two very interesting worlds, broadcast and
WebRTC. Please welcome Dan.
Thanks everyone. So yes, merging two worlds, broadcast and WebRTC. So yes, I'm Dan Jenkins.
I've been doing stuff with WebRTC for probably just over ten years now. And I guess very
recently I've been more involved in air quote broadcast. And there are other ways that you
can talk to me. Email, Twitter, that thing that's about to die. And Mastodon. So merging
two worlds, broadcast and WebRTC. So I guess to talk about WebRTC and broadcast, we need
a few definitions of some of the things we're going to talk about. So WebRTC, what is WebRTC?
How many in the room know about how WebRTC really works? Hands up. Okay. About 25% of
you. So that's good. So WebRTC is encrypted by default, sub second glass to glass, open
source completely, two way communications, no defined signaling, which is kind of a good
thing. And it's got a load of required codecs that you have to implement to be compliant.
I use the word compliant. I don't think anyone's actually going. You're not compliant. But
hopefully they will one day. It's embedded in every single browser. So that's the key
thing here. Every single phone in every single pocket can do WebRTC without having to download
anything. And that is the key thing. You can use your own codecs, but you can't use them
from within a browser today. You could build something natively and use your own codec.
But takes away some of the magic. Delivery is over UDP. And it's got a load of nap busting
stuff with what we call ice. And there's one main thing called lib WebRTC that everyone
talks to everyone else about as though it's WebRTC. It's not. There's lib WebRTC provided
by Google, but they don't really provide it anymore as pre built stuff. But then there
are loads of other open source independent versions available in many different languages.
No signaling defined in the specs. So that's a big thing here. It was a good thing when
it got made. When WebRTC first kind of became a thing. We'll come back to that later. So
then there's SRT. SRT is a secure reliable transport. How many people in the room use
SRT or know how SRT works? Probably about 25%. But it was a different 25% than before,
mostly. So again, it's open source. It's used heavily in the broadcasting industry. It is
UDP based. It really requires native apps. No browsers involved at all. It can be encrypted
optionally. Most people use it encrypted. But you can use it without. And it is completely
and utterly codec agnostic. But again, there are usually predefineds that people use. It
can be sub second. But usually it's not. And it can be used within across the internet
or within a LAN. NDI. How many people in the room have used NDI and know how it works?
About 25%. Some of the same crowd again. So network device interface. I mean, who came
up with a stupid name like that? Network device interface. So what am I actually doing? I
always forget what it's actually referring to. It is not open source. And it comes in
multiple forms. So there's pure NDI, which gives you a huge amount of data. Then there's
HX, HX2 and HX3. Designed to work only within a LAN. Yes, you can make NDI kind of work
across the internet now. But it's not really NDI, right? It's actually using WebRTC to
do some of the magic. So ultimately it's designed to work within a LAN. And it's not open source,
but it is free to use. But the licensing is a little bit confusing some of the times.
So yeah, it's a bit of a weird one. But again, it is hugely popular. And yes, it uses UDP
as well. All the good things with media use UDP, right? Then there's RIST. How many people
have actually used RIST? OK. How many people understand how RIST actually works? So for
the recording, I know. 1% of the room, 2% of the room. So RIST is actually really quite
interesting. It is reliable internet stream transport. And to be honest, I've never used
it. But I had to learn how it actually works to be able to confidently talk about it in
front of you guys. So again, it's open source. It's UDP based. It is encrypted. It's RTP
based. And it's relatively new in the grand scheme of things. And it can work within a
WAN or a LAN. The other forms of media transport are not worth talking about right now. Because
they're not really real time. And I know some of you are going to look at me and go, hmm.
But bear with me. So merging two worlds. WebRTC and broadcast. And broadcast and WebRTC. They're
two worlds that have not really come together in the past ten years. I know lots of people
from the broadcast industry look at WebRTC as a dirty thing. It doesn't do this and it
doesn't do that. But hopefully that's all changing for the better. Right? So they can
now live in harmony. Hopefully. Maybe. So because of something called WIP and WEP. So let's
take a look at WIP and WEP. WIP stands for the WebRTC, HTTP ingestion protocol. And this
is how it works. I'm not going to bore you going through that. But I mean, ultimately,
there's an HTTP request, request response, and then media flows. It should be as simple
as that. Right? Then there's WEP. Which is the WebRTC HTTP Egress protocol. Kind of looks
similar, right? So that's really great. And then there's this third one called WOW. WebRTC
HTTP offer answer protocol. I wish it did exist. I think it would be really cool. But
it doesn't exist. I messaged the author of both WIP and WEP this morning and went, we
can just get rid of WIP and WEP and just have WOW. But no. So, yeah, these strangely look
like signaling protocols to me. Right? And I said it was really great that WebRTC didn't
have a signaling protocol. Didn't they? Well, it was great back in the day. It drove innovation.
It drove many, many different applications to do things in their own way that made sense
to them. They didn't have to use XMPP. They didn't have to use SIP. They could if they
wanted to. And many did. Or you could go build something yourself using a JSON API, GraphQL,
whatever suited you the most. Right? There was no defined way of going here's an offer
and here's an answer. It was great. Until it wasn't. I say it wasn't. Because no enforced
signaling protocol meant there was a lack of industry support. So we had all of these
islands that didn't really know how to talk to one another. One of those problems that
Matrix is trying to solve. But ultimately we had the likes of Jitsi and Teams and Google,
Google me and whatever else. All doing great WebRTC things. They're quite great. But none
of them could like interrupt with one another. And that was a real shame. And it meant that
when we came to the broadcast industry, no one wanted to say implement, oh, how do I
talk to MillerCast? How do I talk to Dolby? How do I talk to Flowcast? Whatever. They
were never going to implement these 10 SDKs, 20 SDKs, to be able to talk to specific companies,
services. So, yeah. How do you use WebRTC to deliver media while implementing a different
API for everyone? And the simple answer is you didn't. The broadcast industry as a whole
didn't enjoy WebRTC for many reasons. Not just lack of signaling. But many, this signaling
was one of them. So you used a different protocol that would solve everything, right? Whether
or not it was RTMP, whether or not it was Wrist or SRT or whatever. So whether or not
you're a fan of WebRTC or you're not, it does have its uses. So up until recently you'd
have to use an SDK or whatever and interop was really, really difficult. WIP and WEP.
So yep, WIP and WEP. I'm actually going to try and get Sergio to change ingestion over
to ingress or ingest just so that it kind of flows nicely with one another. And they're
both drafts in the IETF. Drafts are nothing to be scared of. We all know that. Some businesses
don't. Some businesses look at it and go, it's still a draft. We're not going to do
anything with that. But we all know that drafts can be a really good thing. So what is actually
WIP and WEP? Why have you come here today to find out what they are? So WIP. So you
do a HTTP post up to a server. So WIP and WEP are really designed around getting media
from a server, not another peer that's within a firewall NAT or anything like that. It's
designed for here's a client, here's a server. I want to put media here or I want to go grab
media from there. So WIP. You do an HTTP post with an SDP offer and then within the response
you get an SDP answer. And then you're done. That's pretty much it. We can all go home
now. WIP, pretty much exactly the same. You do an HTTP post with an SDP offer and you
get an SDP answer in response. And you're done. They are pretty much not quite identical
with one another. But they are. You do one HTTP request. Well, you can also do I's,
trickle I's using options, requests and whatever else. But in its most basic form, you can
do one request and one response and get media flowing. So what does that really get us that
we didn't have before? Hardware encoders. For me, being able to bake in WIP and WEP
support into hardware encoders and software is the biggest thing. And, yeah, the Talon
hardware encoders support WIP today. With others, I know are about to support it as
well. Software support. OBS. So there's already historically, there's been a version of OBS
that was WebRTC-ified by the Cosmo team. But it was very much kind of designed around like
offering up to MillerCast mostly. But they supported it and you could do stuff with it.
But today there's a pull request open on OBS to add WebRTC support into OBS using WebRTC
Rust. We've heard a lot about Rust in this room today. And that's absolutely fantastic.
So now you'll be able to publish to a WIP endpoint and be able to just do it with a
URL. And that's really quite cool. And then once that's been merged in, the plan is to
add WIP support as far as I understand and then add continuing added extras around extra
provisions around RTP headers, specific things. But at the moment, it's a very basic pull
request. I say it's a basic pull request. It's a very complicated pull request from
what I understand. But you've got to start somewhere without all the bells and whistles.
Software support. Again, so GStreamer. GStreamer now supports WIP and WIP as syncs and sources.
And this is absolutely huge. Again, it got properly released in 1.22. It was released
earlier, but obviously 1.22 is not a development release. And so you can go and use WIP and
WIP from GStreamer today. And there's loads of platform support out there. Dolby slash
MillerCast support it. CloudFlare support it in CloudFlare stream. And then BroadcastBridge,
my product also supports WIP and WIP. So yay, this is great, right? So using WebRTC for
ingress and egress just got a whole load easier. There's now a standard. It's a fairly easy
standard. And we can just kind of get on with our lives, right? So Simulcast and SVC are
both supported. They're called out in the draft. You can do this. Because ultimately,
it's just an HTTP request transferring SDP, right? Anything you could do within your SDP,
you can do within WIP and WIP, basically. Yes, SDP still remains. If you don't know
what SDP is, it's a block of text that magically says, here's how to set up media. And, you
know, it's probably at worst, I don't know, 300 lines of code. I haven't looked recently.
It's huge. It can be huge. Because it can tell either side, this is how I, this is,
these are all of the codecs that I support. These are all of the codecs that, and then
the answer comes in and goes, yeah, we're going to negotiate this. So SDP is a mess.
But it does its job really, really well at the end of the day. And because it's just
SDP, just SDP that we're using with WebRTC everywhere, it gives us the freedom to be
able to do whatever we want. So that's extra codecs. That's being able to just say, oh,
I'm going to make a random codec that does something very, very specific to my use case.
It's not going to work in a browser, but it does work for my use case. And if both ends
know how to talk about that codec, then you can do that. Opus Red, for example, Opus Red
hopefully will become standard in the browser. I don't think it is today. I think it's still
behind a flag. But being able to put in redundant packets of audio is really quite cool. So
hopefully that's going to turn up in a browser soon. But yeah, it also allows you to do RTP
header extensions, like DTX, et cetera. So yeah, I mean, you're all looking at me like,
this is a bit boring, right? And yeah, whip and whip is a bit boring. It's not groundbreaking
at all. And like, sorry, Sergio, he's going to watch this later. He's the author of both
or co-author of both. Yeah, it's not groundbreaking at all, right? It's just an HTTP offer and
answer. It should be called WOAH, right? No traction for that in the room. Okay. There
is some state handling in there as well. Obviously, you have to keep track of things and whatever
else. But I mean, it's really great. So it gives everyone these two common protocols
for send and receive. And that leads to open innovation and open source projects. So there's
already projects out there that do SRT to whip. So you can take in your SRT that you've
been using for the past however many years, and then you can make it whip because your
media server only understands WebRTC, right? There are projects out there, G Streamer being
one of them. There's WebServer from the Meet Echo team. There's WebPlayer from the Meet
Echo team. And Ivan from Sweden. The whip server, again, whip client. These are all
browser-based tools or they're all command line tools or they're all server tools that
talk to Janus for you to be able to make Janus understand whip and whip. So it's a great
time to start looking at WebRTC if you haven't already done so in the past. I've got the
same slide twice somehow. Side note, G Streamer. G Streamer is really cool. It allows you to
point all of these things to all of these things, right? And it's really quite cool
and it even supports RTMP. You don't have to love WebRTC and you don't have to love
everything about it. I mean, I certainly don't love WebRTC every day. There are times that
I literally want to throw it against the wall. But it does its job really, really well and
is incredibly useful. And it is just another tool in the toolbox. Sometimes SRT isn't right.
Sometimes Wrist isn't going to be right. Sometimes you are just going to need WebRTC. So whip
and whip open up all of those possibilities. And I haven't talked in detail about any of
them. But hopefully you've got enough information to get going. So thank you very much. And
oh, one more thing. ComCon2023 is a conference that I run in the UK. And that's happening
this year for the first time in person since before the pandemic. So expect an announcement
on dates and venue soon. And that's me. Thank you very, very much. And we're hiring just
like everyone else. So if you want to do software engineering in the UK around these kinds of
technologies, then go to jobs.everycastlabs.uk. Any questions from the floor? Have you used
the CDI, the WSSDI and JPGetSS? WSSDI, sorry? And JPGetSS? No. It's for real-time streaming
broadcast and compress the video. Oh, okay. I'll comment. So I didn't catch all of the
detail. AWS is... Right. No, I haven't used AWS's product called CDI. I try not to use
anything AWS, to be perfectly honest. Because, you know, when's it going to disappear? But
no, I haven't. So AWS's product does broadcast uncompressed stuff. Okay. Is there any matrix
effort with WIP and WEP? So is there any matrix effort around WIP and WEP? I honestly don't
know. I can't imagine so, because they're designed to like... Matrix is designed to
kind of bridge between media servers. And so they already have ties into those media
servers. So they wouldn't need WIP and WEP, I imagine. But that would be a question for
the Matrix team. But I don't imagine it turning up. You had a question.
You mentioned some new cast and SVC are supported. I haven't read the latest... Do they have
like a way to layer selection on the client? So the question is, Simulcast and SVC are
supported in the draft. Does it tell you how to layer select? No. There's a note that says,
oh, there's nothing stopping you from doing Simulcast or SVC. But as far as I could see
this morning, when I was finishing off my slides, there's no detail. There's no further
detail on that. But yes, we shall see. But there's still drafts. There's still time to
add detail and stop things from happening that we don't necessarily agree with.
Does that hardware you showed support SVC or Simulcast?
I don't think so. From memory. I've not actually used the hardware myself. I've just read the
press releases and talked to people that are using it. As far as I'm aware, they're not.
They are just using a stream that they're getting and one stream with one layer. But
yes, SVC is kind of the future of having options. And so it needs to be a first-class citizen
in whatever we're doing in the future. And it's now released VP9 SVC. And I think AV1
SVC are now released in Chrome. That's going to be released into stable very, very, very
soon. So we're going to have all of these options in the browser natively really soon.
Any other questions? Thank you very much.