All right, sorry for the delays, I've had a little bit of technical difficulties.
My name is Flores van Gheil and since 2010 I'm an open source enthusiast and since 2014
I joined my first FOSDEM as a speaker. After that I became an open source, cross open source fanatic.
So I really, really love and appreciate when different open source projects come together
and they strengthen each other's power. And for RocketChat I'm a community liaison, so
I help to engage with community and support and so forth.
So let's get to the chase while we're here, skating open source real time and messaging
systems for the millions. It starts off with what is RocketChat, who here knows what is
RocketChat? We see a few hands there, like half the room already knows it, so that's
great, lots of engagement. In general people know about this side of the story, which is
like team chat, like you know from Slack or Teams if you use that stuff. There's different
other variants, also open source. The cool thing about RocketChat is that it is not the
master of chat, that it wants to control all the chat, no? It wants to include as much
different chat services as possible. Thus if you look up there is Army Channel, imagine
you have like a company with support or sales offices and those have clients. And clients
they don't want to install yet another thing on their phone. No, what they do, they have
email, they have SMS, they have WhatsApp, they have WeChat, they have whatever telegram,
you name a few, so I'm not commercializing one of those. And it will connect via an app
to the Army Channel, meaning that the people in the backlog who have to process that, they
can directly route it and solve the issues. On top of that you can add bots with bot press
or Rasa and that help to automate the task of the people doing those great chores that
make business. Since version 5 there is the option with the metrics to federate, not just
to another RocketChat, but also to other home services. So it's not longer like we're on
an island sitting and please come to us and chat with us. No? Actively federating and
working and collaborating together, all of us. And then as an extra sauce on the cake,
that has a very extended API, not just the normal service calls that you know for creating
users and so forth. No, it also has a real time API, which means that inside your app
or game you can directly engage with the message flows and with the chat. Then when it comes
down to voice calling, RocketChat is agnostic, it's not part of the core to, we support mainly
the chat. So for voice calling you can make your choices. You can use Jitsi from out of
the box, you can add Big Blurton or if needed for corporate reasons, Teams or Google or
a few others. So that's about RocketChat. Now, RocketChat is built like many other software
architectures as a monolith, meaning that it is one service that's supposed to do everything
and that is pretty nice if you have a medium sized organization. Except when things start
to scale, you get running into issues. So it's based upon MongoDB, that's important
to know. Originally it was built in Meteor because at the time it was the best and fastest
and most efficient route of making a real time chat service. So this monolith, you can
scale it horizontally by adding more and combining more monoliths, which obviously has an extent
and you cannot reach beyond a certain point of users. So what RocketChat did after version
five going into six is re-architecting this monolith into a microservices architecture.
You still have the same MongoDB cluster, but on top of there, there is different services
like authentication and presence and the actual chats. And those get divided and they can
fill individually and be restarted individually. So you don't have a dependency that if one
little thing breaks, that your whole system is down. And on top of that, it has the ability
to keep on scaling this way. In order to change this architecture, a new library was chosen.
In this case, it's called molecular and there is alternatives on the market, but due to
functionality and exchange of libraries and code, this module was chosen. It's an MIT
license, extensible, and the most important part is this part here. We want to use nuts,
but it can also work great with MQTT and other messaging brokers like Kafka. Furthermore,
there's many adapters, caching, and extra great features to add upon. So in this re-architecting,
this monolith was the primary choice. Why is that? So there is options which are actually
faster. You see here this one, Kotel, like faster, but the differences between having
your remote actions, remote calls, and your internal calls. Oh no. Next cloud is acting
off. Sorry for that. And then go back to this one. Still solid. The cool thing about Monocler
is that you can change between these remote and local actions and you can switch them
within a proxy. And due to this flexibility, that's the reason why this is chosen as the
primary driver for the architecture of microservices. And then nuts is pretty straightforward. I
imagine that most people in the room have heard about nuts as a standard. It's open source
Apache 2, very modern, fast. There's very different ways of implementation examples.
And the main downside is that it doesn't support queues. And that is solved by inside the Mongo
queue runner that will take over the division of those queue tasks. And that has also great
advantages due to using these libraries. It is possible to make interactive extensions
for developers. And that's also something that we've been facing with coming from Meteor
to React and TypeScript for the apps is that it's much easier for modern day's developer
to adopt the software. And thus the community has more impulse for growth. Perfect. Two
minutes left. So in results, if we look down, this one is the monolith. It's built on 4K
concurrent users due to the fact that that was the maximum that it could hold and could
serve. And doing so, it has usage of 12 gigabytes of RAM as well as 15 virtual CPUs on this
Amazon instance to test it. And for the new architecture, the microservices, it could
hit over 50K with ease. But for making the tests equally, the test was made with 4K concurrent
users. And then you see that the load on the CPUs and the usage of memory is actively reduced.
It's only using three CPUs and five gigabytes of memory to perform the same amount of volume
of users who are actively chatting. So if you want to learn more about RocketChat, this
is our main place where we communicate within the company. It's open.rocket.chat. And it's
open for communities, open for support. Everything happens in one place. Sometimes there's a
little bit of an earthquake due to some updates or new version which is deployed. But within
30 minutes, that's all okay. That means that we take our own pain and thus not leave the
pain at our clients. And the project itself you can find on GitHub. And if you GitHub
one little bit up, there is many different implementations and add-ons and libraries
that help you to integrate RocketChat within your applications as well as connect with
its APIs and its services. I still have 30 seconds left for questions.
So, but my question is, you mentioned I seem to recall that not that long ago, you guys
announced that you choose to use the matrix as a protocol. What would you say if someone
was thinking about choosing one? Like what does RocketChat add on top of what matrix
provides?
I've asked this question many times at the booth and it's pretty easy to answer. So,
what is the added value of RocketChat compared to the matrix because the matrix is already
really, really great if I translate it correctly. And that is actually within tech-savviness.
All of us here at Fostom, we're all so to call nerds or geeks or very technical people
that can take this matrix and make it work. And specifically if you look at marketing
or sales or other roles that are not so tech-savvy, it's much easier to use RocketChat, specifically
with the omni-channel and engaging with the customers. UI looks a bit like Slack, however
it's more slick and it's faster. So, it's easier to adapt and that would be the incentive
to say, okay, go for the RocketChat. If you have a tech-savvy organization and you want
to deep dive and include WebRTC and have all these components under your own control, go
for the matrix. Both have on-prem possibilities, data interoperability, security and to end
encryption. So, that's not the real cause for making this decision.
Any other questions? Okay. Then I thank you very much for attending this late, the last
slot. And if any questions pop up, feel free to join open RocketChat, contact me, contact
Judah, contact Gabriel or anyone that is within there. Thank you.