Okay, my name is Nuno.
I've been around VoIP and RTC for the last, I think, 15 years.
The last 10 more involved with open source.
And well, right now I'm working at Talk Desk, which is a contact center cloud-driven company.
And we are starting adopting more and more open source technology into the company.
And well, that's what also drives me.
So my talk will be about secure pavements over VoIP calls in the cloud.
It's something that all contact centers probably need.
And in order to do this, we have to follow some rules and specifications.
And let's dive into that.
Okay, so I'll be telling you what PCI DSS is, what was the existing problem, and what
was the solution for our own implementation, the actual architecture of the solution.
And payment card industry data security standard.
Well, it's a standard that was put together by a bunch of companies like American Express,
Discover, Vastacard, Visa, etc.
So they created a bunch of mandatory rules for the industry.
This is called the PCI data security standard.
And well, in PCI lingo, all business that process credit cards are referred as merchants,
which is our case at Talk Desk.
And whenever we are big or small, we have to follow these rules for credit card security.
And basically, there are very different levels for the merchants, the ones that process like
6 million transactions, whatever.
So they are level one.
We contact centers, if they're not that big, they end up in the levels three or four.
Again, SAQs.
So SAQs are self-assessment, questionnaire level.
So we have to kind of answer some questions to see where we fit.
And basically, since we are an electronic processing company, we fit in under SAQA.
And so no face-to-face merchants.
Everything is done with e-commerce or telephone.
So this is where we are at.
So the existing problem and solution, why we did something different.
So in order to do this kind of payments, we were using some proprietary equipment like
SBCs, et cetera.
And everything in the end sometimes had some failures.
There's the usage of DTMFs on this a lot, at least for typing the credit card number.
We need to use DTMFs.
But besides the credit card numbers itself, we have also to use DTMFs like to tell the
partner that the actual partner will be speaking more about it later.
The partner basically needs to know when you want to have your channel secure for the actual
customer to be able to start typing the credit card information.
That is then, was being done by the usage of a PIN on the agent side.
So the agent would basically use his dialer in the screen most of the times to type a
PIN in order to engage with the PCI partner.
And if all went well, the actual customer would be hearing a voice telling him the call
is now in a secure situation.
You can follow up like typing the credit card.
Most of the times this works, but there are a lot of times that the DTMFs are not well
recognized.
Sometimes the SBC failed completely because there was a need, in order, I will be on that
later on again, but there was a need of transcoding the actual DTMF from the RTP to SIP infos
in order to tell the partner about the actual DTMF, the number.
And well, we also have a very hard time integrating the SBC world, the proprietary world with
modern APIs in order to have more fluent scenarios.
The alternative, the solution, basically we decide to use Cameleo and RTP Engine for the
new solution.
It lets us have more easy to adapt and evolve.
It's easy to integrate with modern APIs.
Everything can be done with SIP.
And we will get into the actual architecture next.
So about architecture, the PCI environment itself needs to be contained from whatever
you have in your VoIP for normal calls.
It has to be separate and contained.
So in order to actually use payments, so the phone number that the customer uses to call
and do a payment basically goes through a contained environment.
In our case, we are all in AWS.
So we have basically a separate account just for this.
And for our new implementation, we did everything with infrastructure as code.
And by doing CI CD, we were able to deploy without the need of logging into a machine
or having SSH access or that kind of stuff.
So about the actual architecture for this.
So we have the actual carrier and we have this CPaaS, which are asterisk, can be cloud,
a cloud provider like Twilio or Nexmo or SignalWire, whatever.
And this secure router is what we call this new solution that we developed.
It's basically several possible instances of Camellio and RTP engine.
And there's in the top the PCI partner.
This is the actual partner that processes the payments.
So we don't process and we don't touch the actual credit card data.
And the way this works is basically the call comes in from the carrier side if it's an
inbound one and it goes through like this.
This is the media for the normal call without being still under the secure channel for payments.
So the call comes in, it ends up in the agent on this side.
And whenever the agent wants to, in this case, these blue arrow here, it goes always through
the PCI partner.
The PCI partner injects a new header in the SIP with a token.
So the token comes back down here and it is extracted and is sent to a smaller L per microservice.
This microserver basically then uses an internal API to tell the CPAS and the actual call that
is coming in as that token for starting the securization process in case of a payment
needs to be done.
So the signaling goes always through the PCI partner.
The media goes from the carrier to the CPAS side without leaving.
And whenever the agent on the CPAS wants to start the secure process for starting a payment,
basically he uses the token that was passed into his UI and that triggers re-invites from
the PCI partner down to our secure routers and basically the media starts flowing through
them for the actual time of the payment processing.
So this is basically how this works.
So this yellow square here means that we are under a closed environment just for PCI.
We have to follow that because rules imply that.
And basically some snippets on the infrastructure as code for this.
So we are using a bunch of Terraform with Ansible in order to deploy everything automatically.
Sorry it doesn't read too much here.
Sorry about that.
But here we are telling for in this part it's the dispatcher that we are populating for
Camellio.
There's also some information about how the process of Camellio started, the certifiers
that are used for TLS.
A lot of description for the services.
So yeah.
Yeah, the one before.
Okay.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Here it's a small snippet of the Camellio config file itself.
So in this case, sorry about, it's unreadable, but it's where the actual engage with RTP
agent was happening.
So we have a bunch of ciphers here that need to be used.
But by using this and with containerization, so the actual Camellio is put inside a container.
The container is then launched, mapping an external volume with some defaults.
And that way we don't need basically to touch, human touch this deployment.
Okay.
Another important part, we rely a lot on DNS.
So we use NAPTR records with SRVs for basically describe where our instances are.
So the PCI partner uses DNS to speak to us, the carrier the same thing, the CPAS the same
thing.
And by doing this and without need to be stateful for anything, we can basically launch the
number of instances that we want.
Since we are using AWS and we need basically this kind of deploys to happen in several
regions of the world, we also do that very easily by using this approach.
And as I say here, R-coding is almost not a great thing, but in this case, as I say around
here, it gives the rigidity that we need to fulfill the requirements and the standards
and it proved to work well.
So how it actually works, this is a screenshot of the UI that the agent sees.
So basically these are what we call context cards for the agent.
One of the context cards gives the PCI token that comes in the SIP and then it's extracted
in Camellio and sent to our internal API for the contact center layer and it appears there.
So whenever the agent needs to start payment, he just needs to press a button that will
use that token and the call will be in what is known as a secure state for payment.
Okay, wrapping up.
So something about the certification process and the audit.
Every entity that wants to be processing payments needs to go through this every year.
The certification needs to be renewed every year.
The one that we did more recently was last November and the year before still was on
the old proprietary stuff.
There were several small issues that kept open from last year to this year and by using
the new implementation, we basically passed everything.
The solution is put under the test for pen tests.
It's something that is in the runbook of the audit.
So everything passed, I didn't mention, but the actual infrastructure code also configures
the firewalls in AWS.
So we just have the ports that we need to work with open and we have also ACLs for the
PCI partners that we are using to process payments, the carriers, the same thing.
So that's the way we did it.
And in the end, basically the audit identified some strengths for this.
So they told there was excellent management and procedures in this.
We adopted a risk treatment approach and we always used certified service providers for
carriers and for the partners that do the payments, they also need to be PCI certified
for the carriers.
This architecture basically lets you use any carrier you want, but you have to kind of
decide if you really trust some of the carriers that you put into this because basically if
you integrate this with PBX or so from a client, let's say, you can always intercept the call
on inside and that could not be good.
So yeah, that was it.
And that's what I add.
Thank you.
Okay.
I guess any questions?
There's one over there.
Hi, so the PCI compliance partner that you've got that does the merchant services, do you
find that your solution's been built around one particular payment provider or is the solution
that you've built sort of your benefit as well to work with other ones as well?
Did they follow the same paradigm?
Yeah, there's small differences when you basically switch a PCI partner that processes the payments,
right?
There's small differences between them, but we basically worked with three, four partners
for this and they most use SIP.
If they use only SIP, that's the best option.
The one that I presented here, it's the most complex one because it involves re-invites
sending media to them during the actual payment process, but it will depend.
So sometimes it's more direct and easy.
The case that I spoke about was the most complex one that involved media redirects and that
kind of stuff.
Can you recommend any specifically?
Any partner?
Not really.
I guess all the, if you, I really don't want to say names here, but if you basically look
for the most relevant ones in the internet, they're the ones that will work under this.
Fine.
Thank you.
Yeah.