So welcome to my talk about Trixity, one matrix SDK for almost everything.
I added written in Kotlin a few days ago, so maybe there are some Kotlin fanboys here.
Yeah, let me first introduce myself.
I am Benedict and my friends often see me as a kid when it comes to data prediction
and data security.
But I convinced them to come to Matrix anyhow, so I have 20 users, family and friends on
my own Matrix home server.
My first contact with Matrix was four to five years ago and I gained a lot of experience
with it since then.
And so much I founded Connect2X and this is just a company that is developing a Timmy
and that is a TI messenger for the medical health sector in Germany.
Now let's start with Trixity.
Trixity is a Matrix SDK and it is for developing clients, bots, app servers and servers.
It is multi-platform capable, so everyone thinks Kotlin is JVM only, it is not.
You can compile it to JS and you can compile it to native.
That's important for iOS.
So we all have that target with Trixity.
And it's also developed test-driven, so we have a high test coverage and it is licensed
under the Apache 2 license.
You may wonder why another SDK?
So back in January 2020 there were only a few multi-platform SDKs to choose from.
If I remember correctly there was the Matrix Rust SDK but it was in a very early stage.
And there was the Dart SDK but very likely this forces you to use Flutter in the UI,
so there isn't a real free choice which UI framework you want to use, especially when
you want to use native UI technologies, for example on Android Compose or on iOS Swift.
Additionally, most SDKs didn't have a very strict typing of events and the rest endpoints.
And also the extensibility was a bit limited.
Even if the next point is not that important, SDKs were really bound to its purpose.
So you've had an SDK for a client, for a server, for a bot and so on.
So you have to learn a new SDK for each purpose of application for Matrix.
Why I chose Kotlin?
Chose Kotlin because it is a statically typed language which compiles, as I mentioned, to
JVM, JS and native.
And you don't need bindings.
Like in Rust, when you use JS you get JS, you don't need to make bindings over Wasm
or something.
And on native you can just call it from your Swift or Objective-C code in Xcode and have
access to Trixity.
Moreover, besides shared common code, it is possible to write platform specific code.
You just define a common interface and depending on the platform, the actual implementation
can be different.
This way you have access to platform specific APIs and libraries which can be very helpful
when implementing encryption like AES for attachments.
So you have on each platform can you use the native encryption algorithms the platform
gives you already.
And last but not least, you can define your own domain specific language.
You will see later what I did with that.
So let's start with the core of Trixity.
The core contains all basic data structures of the spec and its serialization algorithms.
This includes events, identifiers like user IDs, event IDs and so on.
And other things like cross signing keys, device keys.
One goal of developing Trixity was the ability to add custom events which are strictly typed.
So this is achieved by mapping event types to just a serializer.
In this example we add a new type of M.PumPumCAD with this of the Kotlin type CAD event content
so you have access to all fields of this CAD event content and don't have to mess around
with the JSON.
The next layer of Trixity is the API layer.
Each API has its model which defines all endpoints of the API.
The actual client and server implementation just use these endpoints and so as a consequence
there is no need to define things twice.
They are using the same Kotlin object.
So a Kotlin object represents an endpoint on the matrix side.
A Kotlin class, not Kotlin object, sorry.
The best way to show this to you is with an example.
This example is the endpoint leave room.
You just implement matrix endpoint, give him the types.
And in this case unit is the response so we don't get a JSON as response, just a headed
HTTP OK or an empty JSON.
And you can also define a request, a URL, HTTP method and all that.
And you can use this to call, to use a client, matrix client on the client side to call these
endpoints.
So you create a leave room object, a request and you get the response.
That's all on the client side.
And the same thing on the server side.
So you define an endpoint, give it the type you expect as a request and in the context
object you have access to the request and can answer with the response.
To make it a bit more easier for developers there is a bit of abstraction on top of that
so you can also just call leave room.
So you don't have to know which endpoint are there existing.
You just type point on your IDE and see OK there's a leave room, I can leave a room.
And the same on the server side so you just need to implement an interface and see all
your endpoints you have to implement to be a fully featured matrix server API.
Regardless of the API there is Trixity Arm and Trixity Crypto.
Trixity Arm is just a wrapper for Lib Arm as mentioned a platform independent implementation
doesn't need to worry about the actual platform specific implementations.
So you have when you use Trixity Arm you don't need to know how Lib Arm is accessed.
So on the JVM I use JNA, on JS this is done via Wasm and on native just C interrupt from
Kotlin.
Lib Arm is also packaged into Trixity Arm so as a developer you doesn't need to ship
the build C library and it is just loaded automatically so you just you don't need to
init your encryption like in other libraries it's just loaded.
My plan is to migrate that to Wodosemic but currently UniFFI we heard of that in another
talk does not support Wasm targets.
So currently I can Wodosemic just only use in Kotlin JVM and native but I also want to
use JavaScript so this project is currently on ice.
Trixity Crypto currently implements the key management and allows to decrypt and encrypt
events and in the future it will be more so you can reuse the completely complete crypto
stuff for example in app services.
Trixity Client allows you to, oh sorry, the most abstract layer are Trixity Client and
Trixity App Service.
While Trixity App Service is still very basic and does not have a persistent layer, Trixity
Client allows you to choose which database and which media store implementation you want
to use.
And on top of that there is something that isn't released yet, we are not sure how to
release because we have to make money with our company.
It is Trixity Messenger, this is just the view model representation of a messenger so
you only have to implement thin UI layer where when the user clicks a button the UI send
this to the view model and the view model says okay send a message or go to this room
or any other stuff.
And with this approach we have implemented an iOS client in a few weeks with one person.
So Trixity Client allows you to implement a nearly fully featured matrix client or bot.
So if you were at the matrix Rust SDK talk you can just use their representation and
instead of Rust you write colon.
So everything that matrix Rust SDK does also does Trixity.
Some features like sliding zoom aren't there because we want to follow the stable matrix
specs so we doesn't implement any MSCs.
So we have all the E2E features, the exchangeability data stores and media stores, we have a lot
of reactive cache on top of that notification, thumbnail generation, all that stuff you need
to implement a client.
There are already some media store wrappers that we implemented for all targets expect
browsers.
We just use the file system and on browsers we just use index.db.
Next I want to talk about how I accidentally created a cache.
So on the left side you see the relation between the UI, Trixity and the storage layer.
And because reactive UIs are really common I want Trixity to give the UI access to the
data in a reactive way.
So if anything changes the UI should immediately know about this.
But the question is how, on the one hand there are a few databases which support listeners
to react to changes to the database but on the other hand this would limit support for
multiple supported databases because finding a common interface for listeners would be
hard.
So I started implementing an intermediate layer based on Kotlin flows.
A flow in Kotlin is a reactive data structure so you have a producer on the one side and
a consumer on the other side.
So if the producer changes anything the consumers immediately know about that.
And what does this intermediate layer, it talks to a very thin database layer which
only knows about save, read and delete data.
And if someone wants data from this layer it just reads it from the database or if someone
changes something in this layer it just writes it to the database.
And the values are kept in this layer as long as they are subscribed from anyone.
So this means that if anyone else subscribes to a value he will immediately get the current
value because there is no additional database call needed because it is persisted in the
intermediate layer.
This goes so far that even if there are no subscribers anymore I just keep the value
a bit longer in this layer.
So if someone asks for a value for example 10 seconds later and the value is distorted
he gets the value and there is no database call needed.
And you can now guess what I implemented, it's just cache.
So as you see with this cache everything in Trickity is reactive.
These are just a few examples so you can just get all users or check if a user can invite
another one.
You immediately get the notification if anything has changed.
As mentioned the database layer is really thin so we implemented many database layers.
So SQL based one via Xposed for JVM based targets.
We implemented one with Realm that can be also used on native targets like iOS and for
browsers we have IndexedDB.
So most of the data changes when a Zinc is processed, most of the data changes when a
Zinc is processed so it is way more performant to make a large transaction around the Zinc.
So you don't have a transaction every time the cache writes something into the database.
Trickity just spends a large transaction around Zinc so you have thousands of writes in one
transaction.
So everything is fine, no, then there was Realm and Realm is just a really fast database
but Realm only allows one write transaction at the time.
So if another one wants to write to the database he needs to wait until the first transaction
ended.
And the problem is that while the Zinc is running it may be needed that we have to wait
for outdated keys to be updated to decrypt on stuff.
So if the outdated keys part of Trickity want to write something in the database he needs
to wait until the Zinc is ended but the Zinc waits for the keys to be updated so we have
a deadlock there.
This is one of the reasons why I introduced ASIMC transactions.
The other reason was that most of the time the Zinc processing as I find out with some
benchmark was wasted due to writing to the database.
So processing ASIMC takes a long time because there are so many I.O. operations that the
user have to wait until all operations are done.
So what does ASIMC transaction Trickity mean that all changes to the database are collected
and processed in the background.
So database operations are decoupled from the cache layer and they are just written
in the background.
If everything fails it is raw baked but that's irrelevant in the normal use case.
So we can process even more Zincs at the same time as if we would wait that the transaction
has finished.
And this gave Trickity a huge performance boost.
Actually I released it last week.
I wrote an integration test which just fails if it is not 50% faster.
So it is always green until now.
The next thing I did completely different in Trickity are timelines.
So normally Zims are sent as fragment from the server to the client.
So one fragment contains a few timeline events and if there is a gap you get a token so you
know as a client okay there is a gap I need to fetch to fill that gap and so on.
And these fragments normally are saved as is to the database in clients.
In Trickity I use another approach.
There I have each timeline event pointing to each other and if there is a gap the timeline
event knows about this.
So this allows Trickity to again benefit from cotton flows.
So we have a producer that is the room starting from a timeline event and a subscriber who
wants the next timeline event to fill its timeline.
So this allows us to go really fast through the timeline and build the timeline under
the top and it makes it easier to fill the gaps because we don't have another layer,
fragments we just have timeline events.
And this way it is also possible to very easy connect upgraded rooms.
So that one I released yesterday I think or two days ago.
So the timeline event just shows through another timeline in another room.
So timelines with room upgrades are invisible for users of Trickity.
You just get an infinite timeline until you reach the oldest room and the first timeline
event.
And finally a small example.
So if you want to write a bot that's a good start to use Trickity just to get a feeling
about it how it works.
You can just call get timeline events from now on and what this does is it subscribe
to the flow that I mentioned which builds the timeline and waits until the timeline
event is decrypted because the timeline itself also is a flow.
So if everything changes it is redacted or there's a reaction or a replacement the timeline
event flow changes.
So this get timeline events from now on just wraps it down so you get a timeline event
that is decrypted.
And you can see we can just check what type it has and when we have checked the type we
have access to body.
And then we have send message.
So when you call send message you don't have to worry about if the room is encrypted or
not.
You can just use the DSL that I created to write text messages in image messages and
so on and so on.
And you can also form relations with that.
So you can say like here yeah this is a reply to the timeline event I just got.
And this has extensible events in mind so if in the future there are other content blogs
that are added we can just extend the DSL and you can very very intuitive write your
content with Trixity into an event and into an extensible event.
So here are some projects that are using Trixity and that I know about.
There is Spotify bot, a manza bot.
Someone has created some extensions to better use it for bots and so on.
And there is Trixity examples.
That is from me.
This is just a ping bot part of it you saw here.
It is e2e enabled.
You can just run it in your browser on your Linux machine or on your iOS client or via
the JVM on Android.
And there is also Timmy Messenger that is our messenger from our company but it is not
open source yet.
We plan to but we don't know how because licensing.
Here.
Just try it out and come to me if you have questions.
I am a bit around.
This is the matrix room.
This is my matrix ID.
And if we have time, I just can show you a small demo, I think.
I made a small performance comparison.
It is not representative because it just runs once on my machine and there was no warm up
or multiple runs.
On the left side you see our Timmy client but basically it is just using Trixity.
On the right side there is Element and in the middle is Fluffy Jet.
And now you can give me your bets who is the fastest.
Let's see.
When the red zoom comes, the response from the server reached the client.
So I just looked into the synapse logs when the response was sent.
So we just wait a few seconds and then we see who is first.
And you can look into opening rooms because we have this caching.
It is very fast in our client but I must say Fluffy Jet is also very fast regarding opening
rooms.
So oh, Trixity was fastest and we can open rooms and you see open rooms is also a lot
faster than on Element.
And there was Fluffy Jet and Fluffy Jet also is very fast.
I also have a desktop demo but there, Naiko is the fastest.
This is Naiko, this is Timmy, Element on the web.
It's a bit hard this comparison because Element runs in the web and does not have the mighty
threading other clients have so Naiko just three seconds.
I can just chat around and the next is Timmy on the top left side.
Also very fast opening rooms and switching rooms because it is cached all the time and
events.
Then there was Element and I think also Fluffy Jet.
Yeah, Fluffy Jet also.
Yeah, okay.
That was my talk.
Thank you.
Questions?
Yeah.
How do you prevent data loss with your ASIC transactions?
The transactions are run each after.
So if one transaction fails, the other transactions are just run and you can, the next thing starts
with the old token.
What happens if say your battery runs out whilst a bunch of transactions are queued?
Sorry, sorry, I didn't answer.
If your battery runs out when all those transactions are queued so they haven't been written to
the database?
Yeah, then they are gone.
Your client have to do the work again but mostly this doesn't happen.
If you close your client, all transactions are written that are just opened but it depends
on your platform if it is killed hardly or he at Trixity have a bit time to write the
transactions back to the database.
But it's still very fast to write.
So it's just a bit snappier on mobile devices which are not that fast.
Like my smartphone from 2016, Element, I can't run Element on that because it's too slow.
Then sending messages, 10 seconds later the message is, oh, okay, yes, yes, now we send
the message.
I don't have this problem because Zooms are just faster than the slow IO writing to the
database we have on old smartphones, for example.
Another question.
I go for a domain specific language over just changing together methods to say add a new
continent block.
Is there any benefits to that, DSL?
It's nice to write.
I like DSLs.
In Kotlin we have them all over the language and it feels very intuitive because your IDE
gives you suggestions what methods there are and it's a lot easier to read, I think.
Do the character.
Yeah.
There's Rust and there's Kotlin.
Is there any way to minimize the amount of things that the user has to learn to use all
the time?
I didn't understand the question acoustically.
There's a lot of language learning to make any progress.
Is there any effort to unify this or towards Rust maybe?
To be honest, I don't like Rust.
I just like a higher level of implementing stuff so I didn't spoke with the matrix Rust
team.
I think we are done with the time.
The last question from the audience would be that we can open the windows and the doors
a bit to get more air in.
Thank you very much.