This is actually my first time at FOSDEM.
I've been meaning to come here for many,
many years since I will.
Lorenzo been bothering me that I should come here and speak.
So I'm glad actually I finally made it.
I run a blog, WebRcHacks for developers.
I got a lot of guest authors and I hope readers in the audience here.
You might also recognize me if you watch
YouTube videos about WebRc stuff or do
an event series and videos at Cranky Geek.
But today, I'm here to talk about some trends I did by
analyzing GitHub and some other repositories.
I'll talk about that in a second.
But before we start,
what are some things that would be nice to
know what's going on in the industry?
I'm an analyst like to watch this stuff and write about it.
So one, is the community still growing?
What are some of the interesting projects?
What are some of the new trends?
Are people using things like WebCodecs yet or not?
So how do you go about doing that?
Well, I came up with a methodology.
It's largely based on BigQuery and there's a bunch of providers
give data to BigQuery or make their datasets public available there.
So you can grab that.
GitHub is definitely the best one,
basically any time, any public repo,
anytime you do any kind of commit,
pull request issue that all gets sent and stored in a BigQuery database.
There's actually some other datasets that are cool in there too.
I've used in the past and I actually used Stack Overflow in this one.
I often cross-reference that with other sources like
there's the Chrome platform status is a good way to see what
actual APIs are being used at least in the Chrome world.
So you get all that data.
I actually like to use Colab which is just
a Google's hosted Jupyter Notebook type ecosystem
to do the analysis and follow things and then when I get
frustrated about coding and doing stuff like making charts with Python,
then I fall back to Excel for quick analysis.
So some of the hard things about this and important to keep in
mind about the analysis, you can't see it there.
But all this is really based on regular expressions and pulling out
keywords to identify a repo as WebRTC or something as one term or another.
So that obviously has some flaws because there'd be false hits in there,
and you have to be careful with your selection.
So a lot of time I spend is actually just going
through looking at the data and make sure it's not junk.
I found in the past there's a lot of bots.
So you got to remove those things and these datasets themselves aren't perfect.
There's always missing data or junk data.
So keep that in mind.
But I've been doing this occasionally,
more frequently now since 2015.
I've been tweaking the methodology along the way.
It's held up so far,
but always open to feedback.
So let's just dive in. How are we doing here in WebRTC?
So this just looks since 2019.
I don't think it's a big surprise to anyone,
but there was a peak during the pandemic.
So you can see here it's actually April of that year.
This particular graph shows distinct users.
So anybody had anyone on GitHub,
just based on unique GitHub IDs per period in there.
So that was over 10,000 in April.
But if you look here, actually,
we're not doing so bad.
This is a bad data that was missing that month.
We're not actually doing so bad here,
but we're only about 60 percent a past peak.
So it's still pretty above where we were before the pandemic.
But another thing I find actually very interesting is,
also because you can look at these events,
who's actually contributing?
You can look at the blog.
I'll have some links to more on the methodology.
But essentially, people doing pull requests,
pull request reviews,
that sort of thing that counts as a contributor.
And actual contributors, if you believe that,
are actually up more than ever.
So first, one interesting point here,
you can see I show there was a peak number of users in April,
but actually the peak contributions was in actually May.
And maybe that makes sense.
Like people during a pandemic,
got interested in WebRCH sees, start looking at it,
they maybe could star a repo,
join it, get involved.
But then it takes them a few weeks actually
before they actually contribute,
start adding things into that repo.
But as I said here,
actually our most recent peak here was actually in August.
And we're not actually too far
off for the rest of the year looking at that.
So I want to look in to see what was going
on and compare these two peaks.
So one is, this is actually from the August peak,
I dug into the sea,
where some of the repos that were actually
having had the most activity.
And one of them, very popular WebRCH project is CoTurn,
the open source kind of stone and turn server.
And actually one of my coworkers, Gustavo,
took over that project.
So I asked him what was going on here,
what happened, why did we have such a big spike in this?
And I wrote a whole blog post about it.
But essentially, that project was kind of stale,
not a lot of activity for a while.
He and Pavel took that over
and then started really get the community involved
and there's a huge spike.
And things were so then I wondered is,
basically is this, sorry,
is the peak the other peaks like in August in here,
are they because of spikes
or is there a lot of like regular activity?
I mean, you can see here, there's,
interestingly you see things like AdGuard
is always high in there,
like people actually applying to block WebRCH
and its usage, right?
But they have a lot of activity every month around that.
But actually it wasn't actually,
you see some commonality, but some difference here.
And, whoa, sorry.
But when you actually look at the distributions
and the change between April of 2020
and August of 2022,
the actual distributions across the top 10,
top 20, top 100,
they're actually not a whole lot different.
So what does this all mean?
It's like actually the WebRCH development
actually not really getting a lot more concentrated.
You can look for a given period of time,
obviously some projects are doing more popular
and doing well, have more activity than others.
But overall, it's not like we're consolidating down
to a few projects, right?
It's the same kind of more equal distribution that's existed
at least for several years now.
So another dataset,
and this is actually a new one I hadn't looked at before,
is Stack Overflow.
So I zoomed in to take a look at that.
And that's to see if this follows a similar pattern.
Now, bear in mind compared to the previous charts,
this goes back all the way to 2012,
so it's a much longer data period.
And you can see here,
this is comments on Stack Overflow questions
and actually the questions themselves.
And unfortunately you can't see the font too much
of answers within Stack Overflow,
but it essentially looks very similar
to the questions side of things.
And you can see very similar here, peak in April of 2020.
Also, unlike the GitHub analysis,
this actually shows a peak
is here also in April of 2022.
I didn't have a chance to dig into to see
what was driving that particular peak this year.
But overall, I think you can see,
it's a little bit harder compared to the other one,
but we're still generally up compared to prior
to the third pandemic in terms of questions and answers.
And actually it's a pretty good sign
that there's a lot of activity there.
And I also wanted to just took a look to see
as a percentage of all the questions on Stack Overflow,
what percentage of them had at least something
that mentioned WebRTC or one of these terms.
And very surprising actually, it's actually very high.
So it's something like one in,
during the pandemic, it was one out of every 1400 questions
on Stack Overflow had something that mentioned WebRTC,
which that seems like quite a bit
because I still consider WebRTC kind of a very
niche sort of thing.
And even if you look today, just in this,
well, the last data point in this one is November,
at that point it was still one in, I'm sorry,
it was one in 900 during the peak of April of 2020.
It's still one in 1400 today,
which is it was still actually very high.
So you can see, you can interpret this two ways.
One, WebRTC is very confusing
and people have a lot of questions.
So they need to comment on it.
Or you can also see there's a lot of people involved.
Like I, both are good, right?
But yeah.
So also very interested, can we look at this dataset
to understand development trends, what's going on
in the market?
And one of the very interesting things
I always like to look at is what are some
of the language trends, programming languages
that people are using.
And this is a jumble and hard to see.
So let's actually zoom in.
So one of the ones I've been trying to track for a while
is JavaScript versus TypeScript.
I've been delaying converting to TypeScript.
And I'm kind of wondering, do I need to,
is it time for me to really switch over?
Can I wait a little bit longer?
You can see here, well, obviously TypeScript
has been getting more popular.
We just, in December, reached the 50-50 point.
Of all these repos, where TypeScript's half.
So I think I'm probably behind and need to switch.
So there's also, at this conference,
a bunch of exciting new languages that are coming out.
So I wanted to zoom in and kind of take a look
to see what's going on with them.
So Go, Kotlin, and Rust in particular.
So I will say one of the challenges,
I didn't get any chance to filter this out,
but this Go jump from November to December is some bots.
It's just bot activity.
So you can, yeah.
I thought originally maybe it's just Christmas
and Go developers don't have anything better to do.
So over the holidays, they're just programming a lot
and starting a lot of new repos.
That wasn't, it actually was some bugs.
But you can see here, this steadily increasing.
It's not a huge, huge spike for these other two,
but it is going up.
And as a new language that's getting popular,
I guess you'd expect to, you're gonna see more of that.
So in addition to languages, also there's a bunch
of the new APIs, some that were referenced earlier today.
So insertable streams is one such API,
and that's actually two sub-APIs,
MediaStream Track Processor and Track Generator.
First took a look on Chrome status
and actually credit to Phippo, Phil Panky
for having a, he built a custom viewer
of the Chrome status information.
They can see here, so compare them both at the same time.
You can see that these are actually peaking quite a bit
towards the end of the year, going up quite a bit.
So I was curious, like who can we see?
Are open source repos actually using these
or is it somebody else?
And looking at it, there's a big spike here,
but it doesn't look like much, so what's going on there?
You zoom in a little bit more, and again,
apologies, it's really small, but like that initial spike,
a lot of that was just pure standards-related activity
of the W3C repos and WebKit and others
that are just basically adopting those APIs
in the first place.
So you see a big jump.
After that, it's really kind of hit or miss.
And I was, I mean, I love working with it
in server streams, what's he do, a lot of fun stuff.
It's hoping to see more, but it's kind of just spotty.
So going back to the Chrome status, what does that mean?
Well, at least people that are using it
are probably someone like Google Meet,
that sort of thing that don't have public repos, right?
Or there's something else outside of the public
GitHub data set that's driving that usage.
So another one is WebCodecs.
It's another one.
This one doesn't have quite the same peak.
It's a little bit, WebCodecs is not quite as far along,
but they're still driving up.
We're gonna see if there's something going on here too.
And again, you see gradual increase, not a ton,
except for this one spike.
And this one spike, again, was largely related to
the initial standards release of WebKit
and W3C type repos and related once to deploy that.
So we see some uptick, but nothing all that significant yet.
And for the last section,
I was also wondering, is WebRTC winning?
Like we don't talk a whole lot about WebRTC
having competition so much anymore,
at least I haven't, but in the early days,
it was always WebRTC versus SIP.
And is it, should SIP, those SIP type developers,
that ecosystem, should they shift over to WebRTC?
And we haven't seen that a whole lot,
but I think in reality, there still is competition.
And certainly during the pandemic, well, it's Zoom, right?
And I actually presented this a couple of years ago
at Dan's conference, an interesting fact where,
there was a month in time where Zoom was worth more
than the seventh largest airlines put together,
at least their market capitalization,
which is still insane when you think about it, right?
But that was a reality.
So I did wanna check to see if that's still the case,
and it's not, right?
So yeah, Zoom is using that to the same data point
and just extending it out a little bit further.
Zoom's down the other 80% where they were
back in February of 2020.
The airlines though aren't actually doing
all that much better, right?
So relative, Zoom's not doing some bad relative
to the airlines, at least those same seven.
But anyway, Zoom, not quite what it was,
but they still really are competition, right?
And particularly because Zoom, as it is now,
is released as Zoom SDK,
and they have a web version of this SDK.
So as a developer, you do have a choice,
hey, I wanna go build
a real-time communications application.
You can choose to use the WebRTC
and all the vendors in Econsistent,
or you can go to choose Zoom for this.
And I was curious, and Zoom's marketing us a lot.
I'll probably have a post on WebRTC,
a Hacks with Thippo, hopefully in a few weeks
that Zoom's been promoting the benefits of this.
And it's a, I'll go into why
that's not completely true during the post,
but I wanted to see our developers actually choosing Zoom
over, or at least mentioning the Zoom SDK over WebRTC.
It was gonna take me a while to dig into all this,
the GitHub analysis, it wasn't clear.
So I didn't include that part yet.
But on Stack Overflow, it's pretty actually clear.
There's a distinct Zoom SDK tag or label
that they have there.
And you can see here, actually, at least for now,
WebRTC is still way more popular than the Zoom SDK.
Two minutes, okay.
And actually, I am done.
So I guess what we would learn here,
I mean, part of it is, what are your expectations here?
I didn't necessarily go into any expectations
other than I was interested to see
what are some of the trends and can we find
or learn things about new APIs or new repos.
And I do go through the list actually,
is interested in seeing new projects.
Didn't have time to fit all that stuff in there,
but again, you can reference some of the blog posts on this.
But overall, my impression of WebRTC
is still doing pretty well.
Obviously, it's not pandemic well,
but given the circumstances were better
than it was before the pandemic,
we have more developers involved.
And it seems that developers that are involved,
it is a lot of measures to say that
that's actually more mature,
they're better developers, right?
They're contributing more than in the past.
And I think that's a great thing.
Thank you.