Welcome, everybody. Good morning to our talk. All the people on stream on video on demand
and of course here in the dev room. My name is Kim and I'm here together with my colleague
Oliver. We are from Nordic and we are going to talk to you about the matrix widgets and
particularly those we develop for the sovereign workplace project in the German public sector.
So, at first, quickly about us, Nordic is an IT consulting company based in Hamburg,
Germany. We are about 40 IT professionals and we, among other things, we develop fast
matrix integrations for productivity software in the public sector in the so-called sovereign
workplace project. We are here today to provide you some insights from that we gained in the
last couple of years. So, what's the sovereign workplace? Let's take a step back and introduce
you all to it. It's a project with the goal of providing IT services to public administration
in Germany and potentially also Europe. It's founded by the German federal ministry of
the interior and community and one of the core aspects is to gain independence from
US cloud services and to retain full control over your data. And there's this suit we call
sovereign workplace which covers many use cases for productivity and it's achieved by
combining the products from many different vendors which you can see on the right here.
But all of this is open source software. So, yeah, you could say this whole project also
supports and maybe funds some of the open source projects here. We could talk a lot
more about the whole sovereign workplace project and that could be a whole talk for itself
on another track but, of course, we are here to talk about matrix and the matrix staff
room. So, yeah, quick overview here. We can see the Univention corporate server and Key
Cloak which implements identity management in the stack. There's Groupware which is done
by OpenXchange. There's Cloud Storage by Nextcloud. There is an office suit which integrates
with Nextcloud very tightly which is Color Barra online. And, of course, there's video
conferencing which is done with JITC right now and perhaps in the future using matrix
natively. And, of course, there's messaging which is done natively on matrix and particularly
using Element as a client. How are we involved in this? Well, together with Element we provide
this real-time communications component which is messaging and also video conferencing.
So there's chat and video. And in particular we are extending this chat use case using
widgets for some specific use cases. So, and this is the crucial part of this talk. The
idea is to provide better integration with other components in the stack and build new
work solutions. So you might be familiar with the concept of a widget and we've seen it
in the previous talks but still I want to summarize a bit. As I said, we can use widgets
to extend the regular chat client functionality for specific use cases and I brought you some
examples here. So essentially it's an option and also this was set before but it's an option
to embed some kind of web app into your existing matrix client and display more functions right
there. So, for example, you can put it in the right bar like Hookshot does here or you
can pin it to the top of the room and it will even adjust to your theme like this countdown.
And there's more there. You can add a lot of widgets at once and see all of them at
once in multiple places. Of course, there's video conferencing which you can also maximize
to view all of the people in the video conference rather than having chat. And, yeah, there's
also this half full screen mode where the chat moves to the right side and you can see
the widgets in full screen-ish style. And there's more. So actually if you're following
Fostom remotely you might find this a familiar site. So you are actually using widgets right
now to watch this and there's this schedule, there's the live stream and also from the
editor side there are widgets to support us. So if you followed closely or you are very
familiar you might have noticed, wait a minute, this is a bit more than just static web pages.
So actually there's a thing called the widget API and that allows your embedded page to
interact with the client but also with the matrix. So for example, from our widgets we
can also send messages, read messages to the room. So one way to explain widgets would
be you could say these are some kind of limited matrix line for a specific use case. And you
can build a lot of things. Really there are endless possibilities and now Oliver is going
to show you a bit more about how that works.
Thanks Kim. So let's head a step back. We're now back. It's a concept that it's a website
that's embedded. So you have an iframe, you'll see it soon. And the iframe is just any static
website and that website has an API that can be used to communicate with the clients. So
for example, in this case element. And then you have the other option that the element
client could be connected to your home server. So it's like I would say a pass through API
which gives the comments of the widget to the home server via the widget API. And with
this API you can do a lot of stuff. So one thing that is important is that this iframe
also allows to have like an isolation. So even though you embed a website there, it's
not like having full access to what the element does. Everything that you do has to be done
via the widget API.
So from the feature perspective of the widget API you can separate it into two parts. So
on the one side you have everything that is related to displaying widget interacting with
the client. For example, Kim showed you that you can have different display modes. There
are also even more. For example, you can have modal widgets that then displayed in a full
screen view. You can set things like always on top where the widget is displayed in the
right bottom corner and it's always there even if you switch to a different room. And
you can do capability requests. I will come to a second what that means. And then you
have the second group of features which is like matrix or room interaction. So that is
everything about sending events, receiving events, state events, room events, or two
device messages as Florian also mentioned today. Some special things like reading relations
and requesting OTC identity tokens that you can use at another service to identify yourself.
So if you go now back to this reading and sending messages, you notice that actually
you could use matrix for non-chat application where you store your data in the room. You
can see it is like a database. We have the term today. And store your stuff there and
have all the benefits of the matrix protocol that you would have for chat two. For example,
you can store your data and have it end to end encrypted. You can collaborate with others
via federation. And all these features are already there and you can see it as like a
nice back end for building collaboration apps. So I already mentioned this word, widget capabilities.
So one issue that you would have if you like provide all these features just to an app
without like having any security, they could do a lot. So actually I could build a widget
that reads all your data and post it somewhere else like which chats you write or does stuff
in your name, for example, it could send messages in your name. Therefore, there is a security
mechanism with this widget capabilities. And it's actually quite similar to what Android
is doing with permissions. So your app, once it is embedded and once you started it, so
every administrator can embed a widget into your room. Once it's embedded, you have the
chance to request specific permissions for your app. And then the user gets a screen
like this. It's quite a long list and can explicitly allow data to be shared with the
widget. And that way you have your control over your data. You don't share anything that
you don't want to share with the third party side. And only then the widget has access
to it.
But maybe grouping and writing better text can help here to avoid this situation where
users just click accept without thinking about what they are sharing. So now I would talk
a little bit about with you about the status of the widget API. So right now it's only
supported completely in element web and desktop. So there is support for widgets in Android
and IOS. But it's more like static web pages without the widget API. And the widget API
is what it gives is this interactivity stuff that you wouldn't have with just a static
web page. Yeah, why is it only supported in the two clients? I think there are at least
two reasons. One reason is that it's not part of the magic spec yet. So there is like a
draft here, which is a spec. But the draft is a bit outdated. It collects some of the
MSCs around it. But a lot of the MSCs are not part of the spec yet. So it makes it,
I guess, quite hard to develop based on it. So it makes it hard for a consumer of the
widget API to develop it. But it would also make it hard as an embedder because you always
have to go through the MSCs, look for stuff that you need and build it. But I think it's
not the only reason why it's not yet fully supported by every client. I think it's also
the situation that it's maybe not the perfect implementation yet. And what I mean with it,
I want to talk about it in the next slide. So if right now I want to extend the widget
API with a new feature, it's not feature complete. So it doesn't support everything you have
in the magic GSS decay. It has a subset of features. But if you want to bring a new feature
into it, right now we have to follow this process. So let's assume that I want to support
uploading content into the media repository. So it would be quite nice for some use cases.
Then I would create an MSC, which I think itself is not a problem. You look into the
current spec of the client server API, look at the behavior. For example, uploading requires
like thinking about Crota, thinking about limits, size limits and stuff like that. And
then how the API responds this information back to you. And so you look at the spec,
copies that behavior. So it's the same. And think about how you integrate into the widget
API. Then the next step you think about like capabilities. How can I prevent users from
doing stuff that they shouldn't do with it? Or how can I keep control about it? And then
you have like a base to start the implementation. You would probably implement it in the magic
switches API repository, which is the API that both embedders of a widget, of widgets
used, but also the widget itself. And the next step you would implement it in element.
And if there would be more clients that support it in all other clients that you want to support
it. And that's actually a lot of work. And just for something that was already there,
right? So if you wouldn't use widgets, you could upload files with the client server
API. And then you notice that you can upload files, how to download them, start the process
over again. So I think it's not the problem with the MSC process, but the problem is that
you have to copy stuff that is already there. So behavior that is already there, specs that
is already there, it would be much better if I could just use the client server API
from my widget. And there's already like the idea of doing that. So there's this MSC that
thinks about how can I share like the client server API with my widget. And it's done in
this example or in this specific MSC by sharing the access token with a widget, which brings
like new challenges. For example, you have to think about capabilities again, but because
if you share the whole access token, then you can do everything. So you would have to
think about how can I restrict the access again. And one idea is there to use a scoped
access tokens that have, there's actually an MSC and I missed it here. You use scoped
access token to create a token that is like only possible, one can only access the stuff
that the user previously allowed the widget. So that's something where you can mirror this
capabilities that you've previous had with a widget API with this approach. So that would
bring us a lot of benefits. So we would actually directly have this feature parity with a client
server API. We can do, yeah, it may be also more performant because now we rely on element
loading all the data and also relaying all our requests to the home server. You could
directly talk to the home server and optimize our challenge or tools. And we would also
assume that's a lot easier to implement because the widget and better, so a client like element
only has to implement the exchange of the credentials to the widget, but not all the
API calls that are available that have to be relayed and capabilities have to be checked
and all that stuff. So it would make the implementation a lot easier and hopefully also bring it to
more clients. There are some challenges. For example, it's actually quite good that element
does all the stuff because as a widget author, you don't have to think about sync. You don't
have to think about E2E, so end-to-end encryption. So it actually makes it quite simple, but probably
that's some challenges we have to solve then. And there's also like this MSC propose to
bring the access token via the URL into the widget, which might also not be the best way.
Maybe OIDC, once it's there, can help us here to delegate the identity and access into the
widget. In the morning, Florian already talked about this Mottoshka mode for element call,
and there they're using the, I think it's called Widget Room Client from the Matix JS SDK, which
is quite cool because it allows you to already start using the Matix JS SDK in your widget,
and it feels like it's a Matix JS SDK, but it's relayed over the widget API and providing
you later on maybe a better way to migrate to this state or to the style of API. So what
would these features bring us or what can you already do with existing widget API? So
you could build really cool, collaborative tools because you have like a real time communication
channel. You can build, you will give some examples later, sorry, I don't give them. You
can build stuff where you would actually normally have to build a backend, a communication layer,
and all this stuff and think about a lot of stuff that Matix already has and brings. You
can use the rooms for data storage. There are actually some tricks needed to do that
efficiently that would be like a talk for itself, but you have the idea that all these
applications that you build could just use it. I talked about real time communication
before, so actually if you use Matix, you have some kind of very slow, real time communication.
It's not suitable for building more complex or more quicker stuff like, for example, a
game or a whiteboard or stuff like that. That's where, for example, Matix FTC comes into play
where you have direct peer to peer connections or via SFUs. If you have access to that in
your widget, that would allow you to build really great stuff. Actually, if you reach
your limits with widgets, you always have the options to switch to more components,
for example, like a bot that is invited into your room and helps you to do stuff that you
could actually not do with just the widget at once on the user side. Kim will give now
some examples for widgets that we built and also does a quick demo.
Thank you, Oliver. Here are our use cases, the widget that we
built. As you can see, there are four of them. The first one we built is the pulse widget.
As you might know, there are pulse in element now. I believe they are coming to the spec.
I think there's an MSC. These allow you to do some simple pulse, but you might have some
cases where you actually need to do some more fancy things, like you want to even use parties,
for example. We built this pulse widget that allows you to cover many more advanced use
cases. In fact, this is already open sourced, the end of last year, I believe, in November,
December sometime. You can find it online under this link on our GitHub.
The next one is the bar cam widget. If you're unfamiliar with the bar cam, the idea is to
meet in a group, collect some topics, and then build a schedule right there and then
have an event based on that schedule. I'm going to show it to you in a minute. This
is our second widget that is also now open source. Further, we are also developing a
meetings widget, which allows you to create appointments within the widget. It will set
up rooms for you and set up the possibility to have a video call right there. This is
work in progress, but will also be open sourced. Then there's also the whiteboard widget we
are building. Again, this is going to be open source at some point when it's finished in
a beta state.
As I said, I want to show you the bar cam widget for a bit. We actually got the chance
to use it productively on Friday at our matrix community meetup. We have prepared a quick
video for you. Right here on the left-hand side, you have the grid. You can, for example,
add tracks. You can edit the track names. You can choose some icons on that axis. Of
course, you can also modify the other axis, which are the different time slots. You can
move stuff around, change the length of stuff. Then once that's set up, you can enable the
topic submission. You and all the other users in the room can create this kind of post-it
cards where you enter your topic and maybe a short description. Then once you send it,
it will appear here on the right in the parking lot. Because this is not yet quite supported
on other platforms than Element Web Desktop, we also built a bot as a compatibility layer,
which allows you to also submit topics through the chat right here. You write a bot command.
The bot will convert it to the event that's read by the widget. You'll see a tick and
it also appears right here in the Select Your Topic button. Here's the first one we created.
At that point, you can even edit as a moderator. Then you just move it into the schedule. Then
you can select the next topic and also review it. Maybe you edit it, maybe you don't, and
put it on your schedule. You have the feature of locking and unlocking submissions for the
non-moderator users in your room. I believe that's it. Thank you very much, everybody.
It's now time for QA. We also have this QR code. If you want to find us on Matrix, you
can use the QR code. You can use this room alias and come talk to us. Of course, you
can also find us in the dev room online.
I think it was two questions. One question was how do users find the widgets that are
installed in a room? Then I think the second question goes more into the direction of integration
managers with dimensions. It's something like that available. Widgets are like state events
in a room. Once you edit it to the room, you have an event with an URL. It could be hosted
on any web server that's embedding it. You have a question about discoverability. Yes,
there are integration managers, for example, dimensions that you can use to add widgets.
At least dimension doesn't have such good support for widgets that use the widget API.
You would probably need something else. I don't know about any integration managers
that support them very well.
Let's just take one of these bar examples. Let's say I wanted to have that widget and
host it.
Right now, you have to have the URL of the widget. Then you can just use the add widget
command and edit to your room. An integration manager would be great. I could just click
and the bottom right of element there is already integration for it.
Then as a room admin or moderator, you even have the ability to pin the widget to the
top of the room, for example, or to maximize it. Then to save that view state for the room.
Then everybody else in the room will automatically also have the widget opened for them.
Also just added additional info. In the sovereign workplace, we have the meeting widget which
is like the start point for creating meetings with widget. There we have some kind of integration
manager built in. It doesn't help for other rooms, but the user already has the option
to just take the widget that they want for the meeting.
I have on my screen in this virtual presentation of the dev room, the widget, which is showing
me all the questions where the people ask the question in there which are most upvoted.
There's a question. They ask me, how do widgets manage the end-to-end encryption? Does widgets
have access to the encrypted routes?
There's a question here. What is the reason why do widgets manage end-to-end encryption?
Right now, it's actually quite transparent to widgets because they don't know about end-to-end
encryption. The client itself does everything and just returns the already decrypted events
to the widget and the other way around. As a widget, I just sent a message over the widget
API and Element, for example, does a heavy lifting of encrypting it and sending it to
the room.
Any more questions?
Is there a matrix RT-C widget?
Yes and no. Element call itself is a widget too. It uses also the widget API and implements
all its stuff, all the semantics RT-C stuff, via the widget API. It's currently I think
the code for that is mainly the matrix JS SDK and then they use this room widget client
to communicate via the widget API with the client and then the room.
Is there a place to discover widgets or is there a collection of widgets where you find
them?
Actually, it's quite hard right now. The question was how to discover widgets. Is there
a place, a central place where you can find them? I would say yes and no. There is integration
like dimensions but it only has a subset of all the widgets that are available built in
and there is right now something like a store or collection where you can easily choose
all of them.
I believe the Matrix.org website either is already or is going to collect a list of all
the available widgets so you can browse them there.
Of course, if you create a widget or any other app yourself, you can make a pull request
against the Matrix website. Please let everybody know about anything you build.
Okay. Thank you very much.