Hi, everyone.
We are getting started right now.
This upcoming keynote is called celebrating 25 years of open source.
Our speaker is going to be Nick Vidal.
Thank you.
Good morning.
Bonjour.
Happy birthday, open source.
25 years.
Yeah.
I had the pleasure to work with the OSI five years ago together with the board of directors.
It was a huge success.
We organized 100 activities across 40 events worldwide.
All the major open source conferences.
We plan to do this again this year.
25 years is a huge milestone for the open source community.
We need you to help celebrate this.
I'm going to tell a bit about the history of open source.
That's 25 years.
Before that, we also have the history of free software.
I'm going to attempt to give a talk about this in about 30 minutes.
Let's see how that goes.
I have a couple of milestones, a couple of timelines.
Let's see.
I've created a timeline here.
I'm going to give three talks.
Three timelines.
Actually three acts.
I'm going to first talk about the past of open source.
Later I'm going to talk about the future of open source.
Finally I'm going to talk about the present of open source.
For the past of open source, I'm going to be covering 12 timelines.
Mostly I'll be focusing on the open source timeline and on the free software timeline.
Let's get started.
I'm going to...
Before talking about open source, let's go to the free software timeline.
You can actually access this.
It's anniv.co.
Let's go here.
Let's go back to 1955.
This is a long time ago.
In 1955 we had the shared user group.
This was part of IBM way back then.
People were starting to share source codes.
This is how this mindset of sharing of codes.
There was no open source back then.
There was no free software back then.
This mindset was already there.
This is key to the human.
They always shared knowledge.
They started sharing codes with the shared user group.
Later we can see here this is a funny one.
If anyone remember the open letter to Hubbets.
Bill Gates was not very keen to people sharing his codes.
He was very angry about them.
So, everyone shared their codes before.
With Bill Gates coming and other companies, they started making the source codes proprietary.
Looking at that, Richard Stalin, he didn't like it.
A lot of developers didn't like this.
They created a movement to go back to how it was before.
About sharing knowledge, about sharing codes, about just making progress.
He started GNU in 1983.
In 1985 he founded the Free Software Foundation.
The next year the definition was free software.
I'm going to go over this.
This is really important.
Probably most of you know, but it's always good to repeat this.
The definition of free software is the freedom to run the problem as you wish.
That's the definition zero.
One, the freedom to study how the problem works and change it.
Number two, the freedom to redistribute copies to your neighbors.
The third one, the freedom to distribute copies of modified versions to others.
These are the basics.
This is the basic definition of free software.
In 1989 it was created the GPL.
A lot of people use GPL still today.
It's one of the main lessons.
We have the software in public interest.
This was very important for Debian projects.
As you see in the open source timeline, the Debian project shares a lot of similarities
with the OSI because Bruce Perrin was there and he was fundamental on that.
We have the software freedom conservancy that was created in 2006.
The GPL version 3 released in 2007 and that's the timeline for the free software.
Of course, this is an overview.
If I miss something, please, this is available on GitHub and you can propose a milestone
to be added.
Let's go back and go to the open source timeline.
Open source is not actually something that came out of nowhere.
It has always was inspired by the free software movements.
Those two are not different.
The open source is a continuation of the free software movements.
One of the key books that was very relevant at the time was the cathedral and the bazaar
that was published by Eric Raymond.
This book compared how software was developed on systems like Linux, which was very chaotic
sometimes but it worked.
How it was developed in proprietary software, it was a waterfall model.
It was comparing those two models and explaining how building together in this distributed
manner still works even for complex systems like Linux or San Mayo.
This book inspired Netscape to publish, to make it open source.
They wanted to attract global developers to help with their software.
And finally, Christine Peterson, she created the open source label.
This is really interesting to highlight how many of you knew that a woman was responsible
for coining the term open source.
Please raise your hands.
You see, I always saw a few hands raised and this is really important.
The reason why we're here today talking about open source is because of a woman.
That's really special.
The reason why she created the label open source is that she wanted to make it really
friendly for business to realize the importance of free software.
The free software label was not very well accepted.
It didn't work out.
But with the open source label, it was really magical and everything just went really well.
The open source initiative was founded in February with Eric Raymond and Bruce Perrance
from the Debian project.
The definition was created based on the Debian free software guidelines.
So as you can see, the Debian project and the OSI has a very strong relationship since the
very beginning.
We had the open source summit happening that year.
As you can see, Jim O'Reilly, he started promoting this as well.
A very good marketing just from the beginning with a lot of key people like Linus from the
Linux, Larry Wall from Pearl, Brian from Apache, Eric from San Mayo, Giddu from Python.
So a lot of very well-known developers got together to promote open source and this new
label.
Of course, not everyone was happy about this popularity of open source.
One example is Microsoft.
So they started spreading a lot of foods and we have the famous Halloween documents as
well that was leaked.
They really had a strategy to cue open source and free software, which was the idea of extending
the software and creating proprietary things that they wouldn't share back and to break
open source.
They really did try to cue open source at the beginning.
So in 1999, we had the OSI lessons list and the OSI logo, the keyhole, was created as
well in 1999 and it's this one here.
At the time, there were a lot of lessons that were coming out and this was challenging from
a legal perspective because this created a lot of confusion.
So one of the very important roles from the OSI was an attempt to bring all those lessons
together, to see which ones were compatible or not, and to highlight only the main ones
so we wouldn't have a proliferation of several lessons, which would be just very confusing.
So the main ones, the most popular ones, are the Apache, the BST, the GPL, and MIT and
they're still very popular today.
Then five years ago, while we were celebrating the 20 years of open source, I'm not sure
if you remember the Commons class and other lessons that came that year, they were trying
to really say, hey, we're open source, but you can't share this, you can't distribute
this.
So this is a case of open source, it's not really open source, and the OSI board and
everyone involved.
While we were celebrating the anniversary, we were really fighting to defend the open
source definition and I think we have succeeded.
So I attempted to give you an overview of the history of free software and of open source
and it's not just that.
So this was inspired and has inspired a lot of movements.
We have the free culture movements as well, highlighted by the Wikipedia.
Wikipedia is about sharing knowledge, about sharing contents, about creating an encyclopedia
that everyone can help and everyone can edit.
You can also discuss the role of open source in business and how this has helped.
So this is a huge timeline.
Suzy, for example, is a very important company here in Germany and it was founded in 92.
Red Hat is celebrating 30 years this year and it was an example that you can actually
create a billion dollar business using only free and open source software.
So this was really important and if you want to check out, there are so many stories here.
So we have Suzy, Red Hat, Ubuntu, Androids.
I think it's important to highlight also automatic the company behind WordPress.
So today we have several people who use WordPress and develop WordPress and provide services
using free and open source software.
And there's a whole bunch of examples here on this timeline.
If you want to check out, that's great.
We also have open governments, how open source has influenced
how governments are run, trying to make the government as transparent as possible to publish
those documents and to allow citizens to help with the city, with the states, with the country,
by really looking and making the government more transparent and more engaging.
Open knowledge as well.
So the Internet Archive is trying to create a collection of everything digital, making
books digital, games, music, and there's a lot of movements around open knowledge as
well.
We have open hardware as well, which is essential.
How open source and free software has influenced open education as well.
We have OERs, which allows people to share contents around education.
The open web, this is of course one of the main ones.
We found on open web, it's very challenging.
So the web has to be open, right?
Linux of course, one of the main applications.
Free software, we already saw this timeline.
The importance of open access and open science and having reproducible science rights.
And lastly, open data, the importance of open data, especially right now with AI, we have
to have open data sets to help this and for people to collaborate.
So this is about the past.
Now we're going to jump to the future.
And I'm just going to highlight a few projects which I'm really interested in.
And I think this is the future of open source.
Of course there are many other areas of interest.
But we have the software build materials.
This was especially due to the vulnerability that has been happening recently.
And the White House in the U.S., they brought everyone together to discuss the role of open
source in business and in government and everywhere and how it's important for us to have mechanisms
that can protect those software.
So one of them is software build materials.
And this is being championed by the OPSSF and other organizations.
This is really important.
And basically, S-Bombs, they allow developers to track the dependencies and vulnerabilities
in software packages to make sure that they are reliable.
We also have SIGSTOR.
And SIGSTOR is really important to make sure they have a package that is authentic.
So it allows developers to assign those packages.
And so nobody can tamper or compromise those packages.
We finally have WebAssembly as well, which is coming along.
So there's WebAssembly on the browser side.
But there's also WebAssembly on the server side, which is gaining a lot of importance.
And one of the reasons why WebAssembly is important is because of portability, security,
and also performance.
And WebAssembly has a huge potential to allow open source to grow.
Something that I'm really keen to working with as well is confidential computing.
We have a dev room that's happening here at Fosdom around confidential computing.
And confidential computing is about encrypting data in use, in memory, in the CPU.
So this will impact how we use the cloud today.
When we use the clouds, there are a lot of security issues.
And by using confidential computing, we allow this to be more secure.
Finally, regarding AI, we have Bloom.
So people here probably have heard of Shat's GPT.
But that's not open source.
And one of the issues of not being open source is that we don't allow researchers or anyone,
any individual, to look into the algorithm or look into the models, the data sets.
And Bloom is an attempt to do that.
It's a European project, mostly.
But it has researchers from all over the world as well attempting to create something, an
open source AI.
And this is really worth checking as well.
And finally, we also have stable diffusion.
This is a project, a deep learning project that you can enter a field description and
it will generate an image for you.
Again, the reason why it's important for you to have something that's open is because you
want to see what are the models, what are the data sets, and research around that.
And we want to have control over this.
So this, for me, is the future of open source, some really interesting projects.
And now I'm going to talk about the presence of open source.
So this is the moment for you to celebrate open source.
And I really want you to celebrate here at Fosden.
So it's who here came alone?
You don't have a colleague.
Just raise your hands.
Did you come with a friend or are you alone?
Okay, we have quite a few hands.
So go to someone by your side and ask, what's your open source journey?
How did you get started with open source?
Try to break the ice and share those stories.
What are you interested in?
What's the future of open source for you?
What are the projects that you're working on?
So celebrate here at Fosden together with your colleagues.
I would also like to invite you to go to the state of Open Call.
This is a conference that's happening right after Fosden in London.
And there are 200 free tickets if you want to attend this conference.
Usually the ticket is 199 pounds.
But if you go to the table of Open UK here at Fosden, you can get free tickets.
And the conference is going to be very close to Fosden and it's nearby.
You can take the train and be there and just celebrate the 25 years of open source.
And also celebrate the open source by creating your own personal timeline.
You can afford this timeline and you can share your story.
Also you can share the story of your projects.
If you don't have an open source project, you can look at other projects and create
a story about your projects.
Organize a party at your organization, at your company, bring some cupcakes and share
those photos with the OSI.
You'll be sharing that with others as well.
So you can share this.
You can either tag the OSI on Twitter, but preferably on Macedon as well.
So this one here is a nice picture of a celebration in Japan where they were celebrating the
20 years of open source.
So they just created, they have a cake from the tux and they just share the photos and
the OSI share those again.
And finally, I want to invite the OSI board of directors here for a special announcement
to celebrate the 25 years of open source.
And so thank you everyone and Juyos Universières.
Thank you.
Well, thank you so much, Nick, for sharing this opportunity.
Hello, everyone.
I'm Stefano Mafouli.
I'm the executive director of the Open Source Initiative.
And it's a privilege to be here to celebrate 25 years in February 1998.
The Open Source Initiative has been focusing a lot in shaping with the open source definition.
We've been shaping the conversations around technology for the past 20 years.
And the definition itself, the community that we have created has influenced every technology
that we have seen from the start of the internet, cryptography, content right management, the
software patents debate, we've been at the center of everything that happened in technology
in our society.
But this is not about only talking about the past.
We are the stewards of the open source definition.
As an organization, we maintain it for the community.
And the community itself changes all the time.
The technology also changes.
And we have to pay attention to these changes in order to adapt.
In the past year, the organization has been looking at AI and how the new technology is
actually looking different from what we've seen before.
Today, I mean, this week and the next week, we're going to have a few announcements.
We're going to publish a report of their findings of the deep dive on AI that we've done last
year, when we have interviewed experts in many different fields from academia, practitioners
of AI, developers, hackers, corporations doing artificial intelligence, civil society, politicians,
policymakers.
And we have collected all the thoughts, all the findings into one document that you can
look at.
And I can share with you today just the very, the most important things that I've learned
from this experience.
One is that artificial intelligence and AI systems, machine learning, reinforcement learning,
all these new modern systems, they require a huge amount of data.
And that is interesting to me because it clashes a lot with the thoughts that we have already
had with privacy, for example, collecting large amounts of data requires, to some extent,
making compromises about privacy and rights of the authors, like the concept of copyright
that we always thought of, something that I've created, I have rights on.
There is a new right in town that is also being regulated.
We have the right to data mining, which is fairly new.
And we have to try to find the strike a balance between these new rights, personal rights,
authors' rights, and availability of data.
Because the other side of the spectrum is that large amounts of data can be amassed
with large amounts of money and resources.
So hackers may not have the availability of creating suitable AI systems if we put too
many restrictions on data mining.
That's one of the aspects of, that is going to be highlighted in the report.
The second one is that the legal systems, or actually policymakers, are extremely interested
in regulating this new field.
Because it comes with, it's extremely powerful, the systems we've seen running are very powerful
and they can create damage, therefore policymakers are paying attention and they want to regulate
it.
We need to find a balance between having too much regulation and allowing innovation.
And the community needs to pay attention to this as it's happening.
And the third and last piece in this very tip of the iceberg is that the practitioners
of AI, developers of AI systems, researchers, professors, the academia levels, are very
aware of the ethical aspects, the use of AI systems.
They are aware of the fact that they can be misused and they can create really bad damages
to people.
And therefore they're thinking very hard about regulating the use of systems.
This is something that the open source community has never really paid attention to, has always
allowed for very freely use of software.
It's part of the open source definition, part of the free software definition, that you
cannot stop, you cannot regulate the use.
But AI practitioners seem to be quite interested into doing just the opposite.
So we have to help them and talk to them a lot to understand their needs and to find
with them social norms, social rules that allow for collaboration, that limit the amount
of damages that AI systems can do and at the same time allow for the collaboration to happen
in a frictionless and permissionless way.
So with that said, I really recommend you to follow deepdive.opensource.org, go and
listen to the podcasts if you have not heard them already, listen to them.
And we have also the report coming up so you will be notified when it comes out.
We have two more announcements to make.
One we will, we are reviewing how, we are renewing the process that reviews the licenses
and we're going to have a conversation in the legal dev room later today at one o'clock.
And we also have an announcement to make for which Deb, our director of policy, will talk
more about.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Thanks again, Nick.
I'm going to do a three-minute announcement.
So I'm Deb Bryant.
I'm policy director for the U.S. and I have also been involved with the United Nations
over the last couple of years, helping them as they were developing a registry for digital
public goods.
Well, I'm very excited.
You're the first to know, so you can socialize this, that OSI is joining as an official member
of the Digital Public Goods Alliance.
The DTBA is the initiative that has created a strategy to support the U.N. sustainable
goals through the use of open source software and open infrastructure.
If you're around tomorrow, there's a dev room that the Foundation for Public Code and the
Digital Public Goods Alliance are co-hosting.
They also have a stand here so you can hear more about it.
But as a public charity, we think it's important for OSI to support those goals.
We're very excited that there's a recognition of the strong ingredient of open source and
creating a more equitable world.
So thanks for letting us share that here.
And I'm going to hand it back to Nick to wrap up the session.
Thanks, everybody.
All right.
And to conclude, every celebration, every birthday needs sweets and desserts.
So we have a box here of Belgian chocolates, of course.
And stickers.
There are some special stickers from the OSI.
So please pass it around and enjoy it.
Thank you.
Thank you very much All through the all!