Hey, everyone. My name is Tom, and today I'll be talking to you about starting an open source
startup. So about this talk, it's directed at early stage startups or people thinking
about starting one with an open source product or people thinking about open sourcing the
existing product. If you were here for the previous talk, it was more about the step
one to step two. Here I'm going to talk about zero to one. You don't have a product yet,
you're just starting out. So what is an early stage startup? For the purpose of this talk,
it's an early stage company that's designed to grow fast, open backed by venture capitalists,
so investors, and aiming for very high revenue. You have to remember, and maybe it's important
to frame the rest of the talk around this, is that this is a capitalistic endeavor. You're
taking money from people and you're promising them to return them more money after a certain
amount of time. You have to remember that all throughout things. It's something that's
so easy to forget, but that's the basis for everything else. It's especially easy for
us to forget because we're so used to giving so much free value to the world with our open
source contribution, and also taking a lot of free value back by using Linux, by using
KDE, by using all of these tools. But if you're out there building a business, taking money
from investors, that's something that's important to remember. So who am I? I'm the founder
and CEO of Zwix. It's a company we started as a business and then open sourced a product,
although that was the intention from the beginning, and also created Ettasync that started as
an open source project and then turned into a business. I'm obsessed with API, developer
tools, been around for a while, worked on Enlightenment, OpenMoco, and a few other projects
as well. So what is Zwix? We do webhook sending as a service. It's an API-first developer
tool. We have companies send webhooks essentially. It's both open core, hand and host a product,
as we do both. We raise over $10 million from top investors, including Y Combinator and
Tristan Horowitz, Adaf, and founders and CTOs of companies such as GitHub, Page
Entity Segment, Lookout, and Flite.io. So why am I even giving this talk? So there are
a lot of resources for how to start a startup online, a lot of great resources, but there
aren't a lot of resources for open source startups, especially not ones that come from
the community, from people that actually understand open source. It's more like an opportunistic
approach that a lot of people take. And also a lot of people have been asking me for advice
over the years, even this weekend, as I figured, why not? Let's make a deck out of it. So before
we begin, why even start a startup? I saw a talk by one of the co-founders of Facebook
many years ago, and it really resonated with me, especially now that I've seen other people
start companies, have started companies myself. And a lot of people think it's cool. You know,
your vision is that you're going to hit launch, you just finished building a product, you
got to press attention, you know, go wakeboarding with Obama, I don't know what you want to
do, rock star. But the reality is that no one is actually going to care at all. You're
going to beg them for press attention, you're going to beg customers to use your shitty
product and really, honestly, you don't have time for press and all of the rock star stuff
anyway. You're building a business. And also a lot of people think that they want to be
the boss. You know, big office, private steam room, make a billion dollar deals, private
jets, all of that stuff. In reality, it's a noisy co-working space if you're lucky,
most likely your kitchen counter. And begging people to try a product again and fighting
for survival. So it's really not that, it's not that what you think. Another thing people
think, well, I'm my own boss, I'm going to have flexibility. I love this quote. As an
entrepreneur, you get some flexibility, you get to choose which 24 hours of the day work
on. It's so true. And for a variety of reasons. First of all, your customers are demanding
and you want to make sure that they're served right. You don't want to lose that deal just
because you're unavailable, even though it's your wife's birthday or some other occasion.
And the other reason is you're really obsessed with what you're building. So you're actually
thinking about it all the time anyway. And you have ideas in the shower and you have
ideas during dinner and you're just dying to go back and kind of like put that into
reality. Another bad reason is that you want to have more impact. Honestly, just join an
early stage start-up. You're going to be working on a product that's already well-funded, doing
well. You're going to grow with the team, become the CTO maybe. It's a great path. Or
a late stage company. I worked at Samsung. My code is being used by millions and millions
of people, or at least devices. That's much more impact than any of my companies have
reached so far. So that's just something to keep in mind. Another thing, you want to get
rich. That's not a good reason because the likelihood of success is very low. You're
most likely going to have a really low salary for many years and then you're going to go
bust. Not a good strategy if you want to make money. Again, join an early stage start-up.
April 50 at Facebook, for example, is a multi, multi, multi-millionaire. Or just work at
Facebook, Google, all of those companies. Again, I don't recommend, but if this is what
you want and you're just chasing money, you can do that. And you have to remember it's
going to be absolutely brutal. So things are going to go wrong. Deals are going to fall
through. You're going to get a lot of no's from candidates, from investors, from literally
everyone all the time. You're going to want to quit. But because you're the founder, that
means that if you quit, the company is going to close. And that means your employees are
going to lose their job and your investors are going to lose the money invested. So you're
going to really like, it's really hard to quit as a founder.
Okay, so we covered all the budget stuff. So why actually start a start-up? And there
are a few good reasons. One, you really care about the problem. You want to cure cancer.
No one else has cracked it yet. You think you have a shot? Go for it. You're really
passionate about your idea. You have, I don't know, Uber for cats. Terrible idea. But this
is something that you really care about. And you want to get, you know, because everyone
thinks it's terrible, I guess, for the laughs, no one else is going to build it. You decide
to build it yourself. And you just want to start maybe your own company. You just, I
don't know, whatever reason, this is what you want to do. Just make sure that your motivation
is long-lasting because you're going to need it for the next ten years.
Another good reason, a bit more altruistic, is that open-source start-ups are good for
the community. Much more money and talent into open-source, great open-source products.
We all going to use them every day. And also, open-source start-ups tend to support the
rest of the community. We support other projects both financially and by upstreaming patches.
We also employ the maintainer of, like, Redis Rust. And, again, great for the ecosystem.
But you have to remember, there are other alternatives. You can join a promising start-up.
You can start a non-VC backed start-up. Much less of the stress that I mentioned. You can
start a side business. I've done that. It's great. Much less stressful. Still stressful,
but much less. Or you can just start an open-source project. Again, I've done that. Many people
in this room have done it as well. It's a great way to just put something out there
without the pressure of actually having returns. So really just be true to yourself of what
you want, because you need to know what you're signing up for.
So let's talk about getting started. The first step in the journey is validating your idea.
So is this a problem that people even care about? Are you the right team to build it?
How will you make money? How will you get customers? How big is the opportunity? You
need to constantly validate your riskiest assumptions in order to not go head-on the
wrong direction. I highly recommend filling in the Y Combinator application. Y Combinator
is an accelerator. Even if you don't submit it, it just forces you to think very thoroughly
about the business from the eyes of investors and from a business perspective. And it's
been very helpful for me.
You know how people say there are no bad ideas? There are definitely bad ideas. Some threads
of common bad ideas are the ones that are very obvious. So for example, oh, I'm going
to start a startup for teleportation. Great idea. I'm sure all of you guys are going to
pay instead of taking the flight back home. But the problem is it's actually technically
difficult or impossible. That's why no one has started it. So it's the first step of
validation.
The other type of ideas is when you have a solution, you built a project, you're really
excited by it. That's what you want to work on. Problem is it's not applicable to everything.
I don't have a good example from the top of my head, but there are many of them. And I'm
sure the more crypto, God haters, we'll use the cryptos as an example for that.
Also another one, I get pitched a lot of ideas about spaces that the 2B founders know nothing
about. I know nothing about cancer research. I'm not going to start a cancer research company.
And one last thing which is actually not a bad signal, people telling you that it's bad.
That's going back to why it doesn't exist because everyone thinks it's bad. And that's
where your opportunity lies. So just ignore the naysayers.
I asked Paul, the cofounder and CEO of Superbase, what is his best advice? And he said everything
should be open source, but not every open source should be a business. And that's so
true. Again, validate, verify what you're building is actually a good business.
In the now immortal words of Y Combinator, you need to make something that people want.
That's it. So when you start, all you need to be focusing on is writing code, showing
it to customers, getting feedback, talking to them, all of that. In the open source world,
we release early, release often. That's how you get things to the hands of customers or
users and you get feedback. It's much better to find a few that really love what you're
doing than many people that are, because the few that love, really love it, are going to
tell their friends about it. And the few that are okay about it are going to stop using
it after a certain period of time. Also, 90-10 solution. So find how you make the most impact
with the less amount of time. Like perfection is really the enemy of good here.
And the last thing, you want to do things that don't scale. So what do I mean by that?
There are certain activities that you can do at this stage of the company that are definitely
not going to work once you have a billion users. But for now, you can do them. So one
example from the beginning of Svix is that I used to send the API keys encrypted to our
customers. We didn't have a sign-up flow. There was no need, right? I don't know if
even anyone wants the company or wants the product. So why build the sign-up role? Why
build the landing page? None of these things matter in the beginning. So just focus on
the product. Another great quote that I love is from Steve
Jobs. So everything around you that you call life was made by people that were no smarter
than you are. And you can change it, you can influence it, and you can build your own things
that other people can use. So it's really don't be scared because it looks, you know,
it seems difficult. Just like go for it. Really just go for it.
So before you start, ignore the naysayers, but be honest with yourself. You know, a lot
of people are going to tell you what you're doing is stupid, silly, bad decision. Maybe
they're right. You have to make that call. Effort counts for nothing. This is not school.
If you don't get results, it doesn't matter how hard you work. It doesn't matter how much
you tried. It doesn't matter how cool your code is. It just doesn't matter.
Again, de-risk the business. You have to listen to advice but decide for yourself. First of
all, it's because it's practice for later stages. You're the only one running this company.
But also, you're the only one with a lot of context about what your customers want because
you've been talking to them all the time. And what doesn't work because you've been
writing the code. So really just decide for yourself. And remember that most startups
fail. Like the vast majority. So if you're doing average input, you're going to get average
output and that means death for a startup. So definitely watch out for that.
Okay. I think that was like the beginning. Now we can talk a bit about the product. So
the first and most important thing is understanding the problem. You need to know your customers,
what they want, what they care about, what they hate. You really have the curiosity of
a child and really get to have as most empathy as you can. A good hack in the beginning is
being your own customer. That really works. But you also have to make sure that there's
a path to other customers that are different than you are. Because if you're just building
a name tag that just says the name Tom on them, that's great. But there's just so many
Tom's in the world. I don't think it's a good business.
Another quote, I love quotes, is from Henry Ford. It's asked people what I wanted. They
would have asked for a faster horse. And that means don't, you know, listen to your customers,
learn about their needs and wants, but don't follow blindly. Say no. It's absolutely fine
to say no. You also have to remember it's about what you do. It's not about what you
do, sorry. It's about what you enable. So people don't actually care about drills. I
mean, drills are fun. Don't get me wrong. But what they want is holes. And you have
to figure out how you give them a hole. And again, don't obsess on the fact that you already
have a drill. And another part about this, as you know, we talked about product. And
that kind of implies, you know, what people actually use. But really, when I asked James
about his experience, he said something that really resonated, which is your old company
is the product. And actually, Zeno also concurred. And from my own experience, like, it's I've
lost count the amount of products that I really wanted to try. And I went to their website
and I couldn't understand really what they're doing. But I thought maybe it's relevant.
And I went to their docs, couldn't understand how to get it started, and just dropped off,
even though I'm sure it's actually the perfect product for me. And it's the same with every
other aspect. So, you know, like, marketing, customer success, all of those kind of things.
You have to obsess with a customer experience. So obviously have great customer service,
as I mentioned, you know, your wife's birthday, but the customer is calling, you may need
to like drop for a few minutes. And but much better than having a great customer service
is actually fixing the docs. Like, why do they even have a problem in the first place?
But even better than fixing the docs is just make the product easy to use. So, you know,
same defaults, great onboarding in the product itself. And all of those things make for a
much better experience. Now, I know this doesn't need repeating and
fostering them, you know, just like looking in this room or looking even outside with
all the stands that the amazing communities that are powering, you know, this whole event,
but maintaining a healthy community really matters for an open source project, because
that's how you get contributors, that's how you get evangelism, that's how you get all
of those things that later on turn into business goals. As I said, capitalistic talk. I'm not
as cynical in real life, but I'm just like trying just showing you the connections to
business value. And so be quick to respond to PRs. The most
annoying thing I opened a PR like two years ago, got a got feedback a few months ago,
obviously never fixed the feedback. I mean, that's ridiculous. There are tools to help
to make sure that you maintain a good community like orbit love and also the community dev
room here at Fostom. Okay. So we talked about a product which maybe
some of you know, maybe some of you already built a successful open source project. But
now the you know, what now what we need to remember is that we're actually building a
business. And we're no longer just engineers. And we should focus our time on non-engineering
tasks, which is so hard. And I'm going to talk about that in a boat in a bit. But the
first step is understanding your business model. And what is a business model is just
a fancy way of saying how are you actually going to make money? There are many different
models for open source and many different models for non open source. You know, Red
Hat and canonical and they're a great example of selling additional services. So training,
support, consulting, packaging, so like packages literally. And another example is open core.
So you release some of the source code as open source and then proprietary stuff on
top. GitLab and Redis both do it. Again, very common. Dual licensing, Suqute and FreeBaidai
do it. So you have licensed your code as copy left or something that is not compatible with
some companies. And then they pay you an extra fee to kind of like unlock it and get an enterprise
contract. And then you have managed cloud, SaaS, oftentimes goes hand in hand with open
core when you have the features only in the SaaS product and again for the enterprise.
But MongoDB both do it. You can either run a multi-tenant SaaS or you can just run the
product for them. And there was a time that open core was the way to go and then SaaS
became the way to go because, you know, the advent of the cloud. And actually open core
is getting some traction again because a lot of people want to sell phones, you know, with
GDPR, with data sovereignty, all of those kind of things. People are looking to sell
phones again. And then another one that's not often talked about is supporting products
and services. So that's kind of like similar to open core. But you're not actually extending
the product but you're providing services on top of it. So good examples are GitHub.
GitHub is open source. GitHub has nothing to do with open source. But they're riding on
the Git success. And Android, Google is selling services over an operating system that was
open and can be customizable by many of the, you know, but all the other phone manufacturers.
You can also combine multiple models. But you should know what your main driver is.
You're an early stage start-up. You probably have like one person or more likely 0.1 person
like working on this stuff. So you really need to focus and see what's the main driver
for you. And now because you're building a billion-dollar business, you're going to have
a lot of competition. Other people are going to see your success, are going to see your
opportunity. We have numerous copycats that have launched since we started. And you have
to figure out how do you protect yourself. So there are a few common ways for open source
projects. One way is the license, obviously. I'm sure those need no introduction here.
Copy left, so GPL. The problem with those is that oftentimes they're not liked by enterprise
lawyers. So it's really hard to sell to an enterprise if GPL is just banned from that
enterprise. So that's something to watch out for. Then you have the permissive ones, which
is what we chose, but they don't provide any protection. And then you have the non-free
or fopen, obviously not open source. I understand where they're coming from. Like, seeing AWS
just take your business, host it, and then take all of your revenue stream probably is
not fun. I don't know what I would have done in that situation, but it's definitely...
I can see how there's going to be more innovation in the licensing space just following the
mega cloud companies. And the last one is usually... It's like CLA is usually tied with
a copyright assignment. And then when you do do a licensing, you need to actually own
the copyright. So contributors assign the copyright to you, and then you can re-license.
If I asked multiple lawyers and founders, and almost all of them said, own the trademark,
your license is probably too liberal to protect you. And the trademark is the reason why Mozilla
can say, well, you know, like, can prevent a competitor from starting Firefox++ or Firefox
Remix, all of those kind of things, because that is actually confusing to customers. And
that's a good line of defense. I think like a few years ago, the founder of OwnCloud actually
gave a talk here at Forstem, and he mentioned that they never had the trademark for OwnCloud,
and that prevented them from actually offering a good hosted service, because there were
so many clones, and there were so many people that claimed to be the official one, and it
was like really hard for them to actually maintain control. Another one is network effects
and ecosystem. So if you look at GitLab or even GitHub, even though it's not open source,
just because everyone is there, that means the new projects are going to be hosted there
as well. That's it. It's really tough to break. But even without a SaaS component, just think
about Postgres. There's so many libraries for Postgres and so many utilities for Postgres
across many languages and across many, like, the ecosystem is vast, so it's really hard
to append Postgres from like where they are. So that's like, again, another good line of
defense. Also remember, you know, plans are worthless. Everything is going to change. You're
going to change your assumption. Everything, it's really in flux. Like, it's hard to understand
like how much things, sorry, how to explain how many things change on a single day. But
actually the process of planning is extremely valuable. You know, I'm going to say a word
that probably sounds scary, which is like financial modeling, but it's really you just
go and download a spreadsheet, fill a few values, change like it to, you know, to whatever
you need, and that will provide you a lot of insight into the levers that actually move
your business. So if, for example, you want to charge people $5 and you think you're going
to be able to reach 2,000 customers, that means that you're going to make $10,000 a
month. Maybe enough for you, maybe not enough to sustain a business, but now you know, maybe
you need to increase the price or maybe you need to have a different business model. So
really just the process of planning is extremely valuable. Now that you know the plan, you
kind of know how you're going to make money, it's very important to assess the business
opportunity. One common wrong way to do it is to say, well, you know, the software industry
is vast, it's $1 trillion. If we do really well, Microsoft has 5% of it, if we do really
well, we can go to 1%, and that's a lot of money. Realistically, that just doesn't make
sense, and there's like so many variables that are hidden here that, you know, it just
doesn't add any insights. Like the much better way to do it is bottoms up analysis. So it's
essentially you saying, well, you know, we make $5 out of each customer. I think we can
get to a million customers next year, and then 5 million five years after, and then
100 million 10 years after. And you're probably not going to hit 100 million or probably going
to change some stuff in the business, that's fine. But just understanding that where you're
heading is a $500 million a year business, that already gives you enough of context and
like gives you investors enough context to know what it is, you know, what kind of business
that you have. It's also important to ask, are you really selling $2 for $1? Like is
your business model is like a losing model? So those are a bit more advanced questions.
It's better to just do the market sizing in the beginning, but that's just something to
keep in mind. And when asked here from Cal.com, like the open source, I don't know if you
know this one. And his top advice, he said that as an open source startup, you actually
need a 10x TAM. TAM is total addressable market. So like the what I said in 10 years, 100 million.
And what he was saying by that is, you know, you're cannibalizing your own business. If
you have a successful open source project, people are going to self-host it, but at least
I hope. And that means that you're competing with, you know, the most formidable competitor.
They're always going to be at least as good as you are. And you're going to lose, right?
So you have to understand that some people are not going to buy the, you know, the extra
paid product. And that's important to keep in mind. I asked Nick from QuestDB, like his
perspective, and for them, they're delaying monetization, actually not charging money.
And that I know, like the reason why I wanted to highlight this one is that that's often
a point of really cool about startups, like, oh, you know, this startup is losing like
$10 million a year. But what you have to understand is that there are two kinds of losses. There
are the losses that don't make sense, and you're just burning money for no good reason.
And then the losses that are part of a strategy, like Nick's, which is saying, you know, we
are only valuable if we actually have an X system around us. We're only valuable if people
actually use the product. And after that, we can figure out ways to make money. We already
know how we're going to make money, but we can defer that. Okay. Now we can talk about
go to market. Again, fancy way of saying getting customers. You know, you have to remember
that at the end of the day, you're a business, and you need to make money, and paying customers
are your business. Again, you can start by non-paying in the beginning, but you need customers.
One common way of thinking about it is if you build it, they will come. It worked in
the past, but it probably not going to work for you. It worked for Linux because that
was the first open source operating system. It worked for KDE. It worked for a lot of
Linux distributions. But realistically for you, you're going to have a lot of competition,
and people most likely, like the market is most likely very saturated. So people are
not just going to show up. So what you can do, though, is do things that don't scale,
again, as we said earlier. What does that mean? You know people. Ask, you know, email
200 people from your contact list to try your product. Or you're here at Fosdom, just go
to a relevant area or a relevant dev room and just chat to people and just ask them
to try your product. There are a lot of easy ways that are definitely not going to work.
That's not how you're going to get to 100 million customers, but that's how you're
going to get to your first 10. And you want to focus on the easy ones, like trying to
sell to Amazon sounds like a very, you know, like, oh my God, they're going to pay me $10
million a year. That's amazing. But realistically, it's going to take six months until you get
anywhere and then it's going to fail. But even if it doesn't fail and you succeed, it
took you a year and you're probably out of business by the time you even like manage
to scratch the surface on that deal. And again, few that love you are much better than many
who like. Go to market is a very common topic with both technical and open source developers.
The reason why is because we're technical. We don't we don't think about marketing. We
don't think about sales. We don't think about those things. And so a lot of people had a
lot of feedback about that one ship as early as possible. Another one learn marketing.
Another one. And, you know, if you're trying to sell to companies, maybe start by getting
the individuals at home first, because that's much easier than getting the approval and
the contract and all of that going on. Now that you kind of like you're starting to get
customers, you know, there's some traction. You actually have to, you know, have some
metrics. And by metrics, I don't mean Google Analytics and like tracking your customers.
I really just mean like knowing our our things are even going the right way. And so it also
actually like if you know if you're tracking the important things, you can also affect
them. You can know revenue is not growing as much as we wanted. I guess we can, you
know, do something about it. And so you really want to track the most important parts of
the business. Often revenue, but, you know, some precursor to revenue can be, you know,
can be a good one as well. And it's really easy to go for vanity metrics. One of the
founders, I'm not going to put I didn't put a quote from him, but he said that they were
tracking PyPy downloads. So like the Python package manager. That sounds great. The problem
is, again, like CI, all of those kind of bots, all of those things actually download packages
from there as well. And they thought they had a lot of traction, but actually had nothing.
So that's something to keep in mind. So there's some good metrics that you can use. You know,
revenue is always king if you're making money. Great. And but also number of customers using
your production. So a few big companies that everyone knows are already using you to, you
know, to serve millions of customers. That's that's something. Even if you're not making
money now, you can probably make money later. Some insufficient ones are GitHub stars, sign
ups, downloads, Twitter followers, you know, GitHub star is really just someone clicked,
clicked the button. Maybe that someone is a target customer. Maybe not sign ups. Maybe
they signed up and then they dropped because they realized it's not even the product that
they want. You know, they're like a lot of really false signals here. And also GitHub
stars don't mean that you have a great business. So this one has like 240,000 stars, like one
of the tops starred repos, but it's it's a set of tutorials and maybe it's a great business.
I don't know, maybe they can spin it into something. And but it's definitely not a business
on its face value. And but a lot of stars can definitely indicate that you're onto something.
And this is from Superbase. They're at 40,000 stars and they're just growing like crazy.
Every year consistently for two, two years, I guess, that's something. And that's just
like an indication of the market share that they're gaining with developers. So I guess
the main question that we need to ask is whether we should even open source. I talked about
all of that. And before you boo me off stage, and I know this is not the right place to
ask this question, but like, you have to understand it's actually a business decision. At the
end of the day, you took money from investors, you promised them to return them more money,
you got people on board, offered them a job and told them that you're going to be around
for five years. So you have to make the best decision for your business. And there are
reasons for both doing it and not doing it. And so one thing is your customers even care.
Maybe not. Maybe they don't even know what open source is. I don't even know. I don't
want to go with some cliche, but they just have no idea what open source is and they
couldn't care less. Is there a business advantage to being open source? So, for example, when
you're a developer tool, that means that people can try your product more easily. That's great.
Maybe go open source. And does it even make businesses? Are you just going to cut yourself?
Or just kill your own business? So ideology is fine. I've done it for ideology as well
with Ettesync. It started as an open source project. But you just have to remember that
at the end of the day, you're building a business. So there are definitely upsides. Engaged community
really helps. Again, so many volunteers outside handing out flyers about projects, really
promoting them. You can also hire from the community. No need to find great developers
if you already have developers that know your code base and have been contributing code.
Service trust, healthy communication that comes with open source, easier adoption, as
I said, with dev tools. And also the product is just more flexible. People can just fork
it and adjust it to whatever they need. There are also downsides, though. Balanced community
and business needs. Does this one go to the open source product or does this stay as propriety
extensions? Maintainer burnout is a good topic. It's a very front of mind topic for a lot
of people nowadays. And it's absolutely true. And the same with support, right? People asking
questions about your product on GitHub, you want to make sure you're going to give them
the best support possible. But they're not paying you in the end. So you're doing a lot
of free support, which is fine. It's part of being a project. But also it can be overwhelming
at times. It's really hard to say no to things because everything is in the open. And also
like startups win on speed. You really have to compete and move fast. And enabling self-hosting
and doing like database migration, seamless migration, all of those kind of things just
makes things so much harder. And maintaining code bases, which you have to do because you
have going to have customizations for specific customers or you're going to have hacks for
specific customers. You're going to have a ticketing system where you're going to say,
well, you know, customer X asked for this. We have to finish it now. You're not going
to be able to do that in the open just because your customers wouldn't want that. And also
your secret sauce may be public. And you're really just undercutting yourself on price,
and people can just self-host. So there are downsides. Another quote that I like is by
Joseph Jax. He said that don't open source something you don't want to commoditize because
you're open sourcing your secret sauce, you're open sourcing all of the internal structure.
It's actually really easy to mimic or even fork, but definitely to mimic what you're
building. So just assume it's a commodity the moment you release it and make sure that
the stuff that you don't want to be a commodity, they stay proprietary. Okay. So now we can
talk about fundraising. I know this is something that people are often mystified by, even just
by the amount of people that asked me about it in the last 48 hours alone. So happy to
cover a bit of it. So the first thing is that you're dealing with investors. And when you're
dealing with people, you have to understand what do they actually care about and understand
how they think. So the first thing to understand is the power law of venture capital investments.
What does that mean? Let's assume for simplicity that a fund invests in 100 companies. Most
startups fail, so that means 90 are going to fail. And they invest a million in each.
So 90 are going to fail. Okay. They already lost $90 million. And now they have 10 live
companies. Let's say five of them are going to return, sorry, eight of them are going
to return 5x. Okay. That's a good outcome. They invested for a certain amount of money.
It's now worth 5x that amount. Great return. So that's $40 million that they made. And
then the last two, so they lost 90. They just made 40. So they're down 50. So the last two,
the last two companies really need to carry the whole weight of the whole investment fund
to actually make a return. So that means the last two probably need to return 100x each.
So if they invested at a value of 10 million, it needs to be worth a billion now. And it
really the old venture model is based on the fact they're trying to find these one or two
companies in their whole fund that is going to be 100x. You know, Facebook was a 2000xer
or something like that. Uber as well. Like there are companies that are definitely outliers.
Apple, I guess, as well if you, you know, you look at the whole 30 years at a time.
So the moment you understand that they don't care about your 5x, because that 5x was $40
million out of the 240 that they made, you really have to like position yourself as that
100xer. And you also have to understand that they have investors. So even though you're
talking to that person and they love what you're doing and they're like, you know, they're
open source developers themselves. They really want the product, whatever. They have investors
to answer for. They told them, hey, I'm going to invest your money and I'm going to give
you that amount of return. And so really you have to make sure, you know, to understand
that dynamic. It's also, it's their job. I mean, here I wrote, you know, stay in touch,
but really it's their job to waste your time. And they want to like meet you. They want
to like know more about the space because they're going to invest in a competitor and
they really want to understand the space better. They want to know about all the cool companies
so they can tell their friends at the country club that, I mean, that was maybe a bit of
an extreme joke, but they want to tell their friends that they've talked to all of these
cool companies that are just doing very well now. This is not your job. Your job is to
build a company, not to waste your time talking to investors. Another thing to remember is
that not a yes is a no. So investors want to invest in the really good companies. As
I said, they want to invest in the 100Xer. It's really hard to know if this company is
that. So what they're going to say, they're not going to say, well, no, this is stupid.
I'm not going to invest in you. What they're going to say is like, oh my God, this sounds
amazing. I need to build my conviction for a few weeks and I'm going to like do some
research and I'm going to like talk to you then. And then they disappear. But if they
see that some big name investor like is talking to you or like there's some traction there,
then they're going to come back and tell and complain to you and say like, well, you know,
I told you I was interested, but really what they said in the beginning was no, and you're
never going to hear back from them again. So it's really important to count that as
a no and not to count that as a yes. And another thing is that you want to believe the no,
but not the why. So again, they want to invest in you, maybe not even in this company, but
maybe in your next company. But they want to invest in the best companies. And if they're
going to tell you, you suck, you know, you're not going to talk to them the next time. So
they really want to say something nice like, oh, you know, this is our fund is like slowing
down its investments so that really this is not the right time for us. But like, let's
chat again in a couple of months. Really what they mean by that is leave me alone. I don't
want to invest. And so like, don't like don't don't count it as a yes in a couple of months.
Don't count it as a no, essentially. Also, like everything, it's a business, you want
to have a plan, how much are you going to raise? What are you going to actually do with
the money? Like, you know, it sounds good. I'm going to raise $2 million. But are you
going to hire people? What are those people going to achieve? You know, figure those things
out. How much of the money are you willing to sell? Are you willing to sell 90% of the
company for $1 million? Are you willing to send 10? Those are all questions that you
have to come in prepared for because you're dealing with professional negotiators that
are going to repeat the shreds if you don't have like a strong stance on any of those.
Another thing is to speak to investors all at once. So investors talk, as I mentioned,
and they will talk about the cool companies that are chatting with. And if they're going
to see that you've been trying like you've been talking to investors for the last year,
and you haven't raised around yet, that probably means you're tainted goods, and they're not
going to want to invest in you as well. So then the right thing to do is probably try
to invest money, like raise capital for like two, three months. And after that, if that
doesn't work out, just stop, go back to building a business. You know, if you're a developer,
you probably don't need that money anyway. You can just continue building the product,
and then I come back stronger in a few months. And, you know, I'm going to rush this one
a bit, but like if you want to find investors, start with angels. You know, don't chase Sequoia.
They're not going to invest in a small company or like they very rarely do. Don't waste your
time. Build traction with angels, like small checks. And find people that are excited by
the space, invest in similar companies, ask your friends. But really the most important
thing is don't take intros from investors who haven't invested. Investors want to look
good, and again, they want to look like they know all the companies. So they're going to
tell you, hey, I'm going to introduce you. I know a guy, Sequoia. I'm going to introduce
you to him. I know a girl, they're that fund. But really what happens is that if they haven't
invested in you themselves, they're just signals to Sequoia that you've attained good because
they wouldn't want to invest in you. So like why should they? So that's a really bad strategy
to accept those intros. Just say that you're cool. You already have enough traction and
interest. But once they invest, by all means, that's the strongest signal. Someone put their
money on you. Have them introduce, have them go on a building and shout to the world that
have invested and get introductions from them. This is actually where I see founders error
the most. Not because maybe that's the most common place for mistakes. It's just the place
that I'm exposed to the most. Is there a dex in their pitch? You want to really keep it
short. You want them asking for more, not going through 80 pages of boring stuff about
whatever. You want to keep it short, short, short. 10, maybe 15 slides. Really on point.
You want to highlight what's most impressive. In your case, it's probably team, maybe idea.
Maybe if you have a really impressive set of customers, that's great. Highlight that.
But most likely you don't need to analyze your $2,000 a month revenue because, again,
they don't care about that. It's not something that they see impressive. So focus on the
stuff that are impressive. Another thing that people often get wrong is they confuse their
customers with investors. So they go to the investor and assume the investor has the problem.
The investor actually really cares about, I don't even know, I don't have an example
at the top of my head. They really care about this topic. They understand the problem. They
face it themselves. They really feel it. If you told them about all the research that
they've done about this product and how you solve it, they're going to really be interested
about that. The most likely scenario is that they don't even know what you're talking about.
It's not their job to be subject matter experts in whatever it is esoteric thing that you're
talking about. They just need you to demonstrate that there is a problem. People really care
about that. People are going to pay you money. This is how much money you're going to make.
This is how you're solving it. Not necessarily a disorder. This is who you are and why you're
the best person or best team to solve it. And obviously, you want to know your business
inside out. You want to be concise. So let them ask questions. Always iterate. After
every call, I would go back and make sure that I get better after every call.
Find the call. Be calm. Relax. Don't look desperate. They can sense desperation a mile
away. When we were fundraising, I knew that worst case, I'm a developer. I can just build
a product myself. I don't need that money. I would love to have it, but I don't need
it. That kind of made it possible for me to relax and show that confidence that they're
looking for. You're also assessing them. Ask questions. Figure out if you want to take
their money because you're going to be with them for the long run if they're going to
invest. So that's important. Also, only the CEO should go on calls. Don't do party conversations.
First of all, just distraction. But also, you're going to get so many no's. It's much
better that less people get pounded with all of these no's and the other people can actually
focus on the business and continue. So the deal, this is mostly a slide for you to read
afterwards, but there are a lot of topics. Is it simple? Is it fast? Or can you spend
like 200,000 on lawyers in this deal? What are the terms for
that? I don't want your services. I'm going to hire my own designers. That is such a ripoff
if you ask me. Avoid those if you can. So final note about fundraising. You only need
one yes. When preparing this talk, I was just like, I was thinking to my head, how many
no's did I get when fundraising? Then I looked at my notes, it was closer to 50, but I really
couldn't care less because that doesn't matter. You probably need more than one yes. You're
probably gonna get like a few investors,
but once you get a yes, the flywheel is rolling.
Ignore the naysayers, ignore the assholes,
you're gonna meet some really shitty people along the way.
They're humans as well, so just ignore those.
Fundraising is definitely not success.
Fundraising is definitely not company building.
You need to actually build your company.
This is not the end, this is just the beginning.
You may not be able to raise, so manage expectations,
be ready for that, have a plan B.
That's absolutely fine as well.
As I said, very hard to fire investors,
so watch out who you put in your cap table
and who you marry.
And another small point is that many investors
only invest in certain locales,
so like a lot of investors only invest in the US.
That's something to keep in mind.
Y Combinator, big fan.
They fund a lot of open source startups.
They've been transformational for us.
I would really consider applying.
We got rejected many times.
Don't let it hold you back.
There are a lot of great open source startups.
GitLab, Docker, Superbase, Hopper,
so really the list just goes on and on.
So you're gonna be in good company.
One thing is that you need to be aware of the siren song.
So the tempting places where things
usually go wrong for people.
So one place is, as I said, fundraising,
or valuation, or money raise,
or thinking that talking to an investor is actually success.
But again, no, you need to build your company.
And another area that people go wrong
is that thinking that hiring more people
is actually success.
So like, oh, I'm managing 20 people.
How big is your team?
I ask me that all the time.
And we're small.
And the reason why we're small is because
that's what we need to build a kick ass product.
And this is something that you need to keep in mind.
Like burning money does not equate success.
And plain startup does not mean building a company.
So going to pitch competition, startup conferences,
startup meetups, investor chats, all of those kind of things.
Fun, chasing press as well.
Maybe fun.
Honestly, probably fun.
But it really just don't mean anything
for the bottom line of your business.
So just don't do it.
And also remember, you really have not made it.
So really don't do it focused.
The only things that matters are customers,
product, team, and metrics.
That's it.
Everything else is just noise or maybe an enable
to get to everything else.
So some lessons I personally learned the hard way
is that you're no longer an engineer.
I really like coding.
That's it.
I wake up, I love coding.
And it's really hard to remember
that this is not why you raise capital.
Like this is not what my job is at the business anymore.
I'm the CEO.
I need to do just business stuff.
I mean, I can help with the code.
I can help with the architecture.
But my main time should be spent on Go to Market.
Opportunities are not gonna last forever.
So just grab them when you see them.
It's very easy to say,
oh, I'm just gonna perfect this landing page
for a couple of more weeks
and then I'm gonna take this opportunity.
But then the opportunity is gonna be gone.
And we missed a few in the beginning.
And people are gonna be trying to take advantage of you.
So just watch out.
You're running a large budget.
So just watch out for those people.
Be mindful and protective of your time.
So a lot of people are gonna wanna chat,
catch up, whatever, great.
But as I said, you're gonna be working 24 hours.
So maybe spare the 25th hour for some fun stuff
or maybe more work.
And the last thing is that
you really wanna surround yourself with optimists.
The truth is that your startup sucks
and it's gonna suck for the longest time.
So the last thing you want is people
that are negative around you.
A few more things.
Team, super important.
Early team sets the tone.
Bad hires can really derail the company.
Great co-founders can make the difference.
I've seen it multiple times.
But actually better to start on your own
than having a terrible co-founder, which I've also had.
And you're really in control of your destiny.
If something isn't working, you can change it.
The only thing you cannot change is the market.
But really just iterate, iterate, iterate.
You can get lucky.
We got lucky many times.
Just put yourself out there, talk to customers,
and you're gonna notice something that no one else has
and you're gonna get lucky.
And it's really a game of persistence.
You can't lose unless you stop.
Obviously I'm not saying go and bang your hand
against the wall.
You have to have some acumen there.
But as long as you don't give up, you're gonna win.
So just a few closing advice.
It's very easy to think that hiring X will fix everything
or customer X once we get them.
That's it.
The business is gonna go crazy.
Or maybe this investor is gonna change
the destiny of the company.
And maybe, maybe some of them will.
But it's really just on to you to actually fix the company
and make it work.
And you have to remember everything is sales.
You have to really get good at it.
You wanna get customers.
You're gonna get candidates.
You're gonna get investors.
You have to sell them on the vision of the company
and the company itself.
Some more sources of great advice.
NYC YouTube channel, library.
I mean, check it out afterwards in the slides.
And yeah, and that's it.
I just wanna give you like a few closing words
before I open the floor for questions.
So make sure that it's really what you want.
I mean, I've kind of like tried to dissuade you
a bit in the beginning because really,
you need to want to start this company
even with my dissuasion there.
And the only important things are to talk to your customers
and build a product.
Nothing else matters at this stage.
You wanna build something that people love.
You have to remember it's a business.
It's not an open source project.
It's something that you have to actually make money.
And this is the primer, but there's so much more to it.
And this is just to get you from zero to one.
Every stage of the company is different
and there's so much more.
And maybe conflicting advice once you get to the one
and once you get to the two.
And one more thing.
It's your job to be the number one evangelist of the company.
And so always be selling.
And in that spirit, if you need web hooks
or you wanna work at a fast growing startup, yeah.
Come talk to me about Svex.
And that's it.
Any questions?
No.
Bye.
No, no.
Yeah, sorry.
A bit over.
Amazing talk.
Thanks a lot.