I'm going to talk about the new breakthroughs that are happening in cryptography, the opening
doors to unexplored spaces.
Yeah, let's raise the volume.
Yeah, yeah, I don't know how to do it.
I think the staff.
But I will try to speak louder.
So the free software movement and Linux at one time had power.
It had vitality.
And then somewhere along the way, we started to play catch up.
We started to try and follow the competition.
Linux on the desktop never happened.
The once great browser, Firefox, its market share dwindled to zero.
Even this conference, which has the best minds in free software community, is funded by surveillance
capitalism, Google, Microsoft.
In this talk, I want to talk about how we can escape the death trap and create the new
paradigm of computing.
It's strange.
This talk is dedicated to Peter Hintiens.
Peter Hintiens was from Brussels.
He was a programmer who wasn't born in Brussels, but he lived and died in Brussels.
He really embodied the ideas of what elegant abstraction means.
Abstraction is something which creates complexity.
Don Well empowers the software developer.
But he was not just a good developer who he made, for example, zero MQ, which is really
interesting conceptualization about how we could build distributed systems.
He was also a theorist on creating free software, the social layer on creating free software
communities.
He taught us that free software is more than just having the code being accessible, but
it's an entire philosophy.
When we create the good, elegant abstractions, it enables us to create software that's composable
while not contributing complexity.
This is the basis of how the Linux architecture is created.
There's components.
Rather than a Windows system where there is a system 32 filled with hundreds of DLLs,
there is a component which people can modify.
In our project, we try to embody his ideals.
We try to carry his philosophy.
Also everything that we use today, the concept of the sockets, the processes, the file system,
was invented in the 70s with Unix.
Since then, nothing has fundamentally changed about computing.
When they created Unix, their vision was something that would enable deep collaboration between
communities.
The infrastructure that they created, the software, ended up becoming the basis of the
web.
At the time, they couldn't take their vision to its full conclusion.
They didn't have the algorithms that we have now, like around peer-to-peer and consensus
and cryptography and so on.
There wasn't huge network bandwidths.
The resources in the hardware weren't as big.
Since its invention, not much has changed.
What is a zero knowledge proof?
A zero knowledge proof is a zero knowledge proof.
If I have a simple function, I call the function on a set of parameters or arguments and I
produce a result, the return value of the function.
If I want to show to you that this value that I've computed from the function is computed
from some parameters that went into the function, then normally the way that you do that, logically,
is I would have to give you those input parameters and you have the function and you would compute
the function yourself and get that result at the end and then be able to verify that
the result is what it claims it is.
For example, in a Bitcoin blockchain, you're doing transactions and everybody verifies
the transactions, that the computation is to advance the state machine so the next state
is correctly done.
There are two very interesting properties of ZK proofs.
First, the ZK proof is succinct.
What that means is the actual proof object that proves the computation that has been
run on the values is very small.
It's smaller than the input parameters that go into the function.
You would expect that it would be some big proof, but actually, we save computation.
When you want to verify that, you save computation compared to if you would compute the evaluation
of the input values, what we call the witnesses yourself.
The proof size is small and the time to verify the proof is very small compared to actually
computing it.
It can be anonymous.
There are some values that you put into a function to get a result.
You don't know what S, X, and Y are.
You know Z, you know foo, but you don't know S, X, and Y.
That enable us, that give us a very powerful technique in our arsenal, in our toolkit of
anonymous engineering.
This is the general schema of ZK proofing.
You have a proof function.
That means that's how we generate a ZK proof.
You have some private values, the input values to your function foo, and you have the output
of the function, which are your public values, and you create a proof.
When I give to you the proof and you want to verify the proof, and you have the public
values from the evaluation of that function, and you get true or false back.
How does it work?
This is obviously greatly simplified, but just observe this property.
If I have polynomials and I add two polynomials and then I evaluate the polynomial, that is
the same as evaluating the polynomials and adding them together.
This is due to what is called mathematically the homomorphic property of the function that
maps from the ring of the polynomials to the ring of the closure.
It works as well for multiplication.
Just remember that homomorphic property.
Then what we do is that function foo, we do this step called arithmetization.
Any code that you write, we turn that code into a set of polynomials.
How do we do that?
Imagine A and B are billion values, either one or zero, so how can we turn those into
arithmetic expressions?
If you notice with those formulas in the top left and these tables on the right, if you
do the calculation, you will get the same thing.
As long as A and B are zero or one, when you perform those formulas, they are the equivalent
to those billion expressions.
If you want to enforce, just as a side note, that a value S is in a certain range of values,
for example, zero or one, it is the same as saying S minus zero multiplied by S minus
one is equal to zero, which is the roots of the polynomial where it would evaluate to
zero.
That would be a degree two polynomial, there would be no other roots of zero there.
We have that function foo, which if you remember, where was it?
It was here, this one.
If S return X times Y, else return X plus Y.
How do we arithmetize that?
You can see below that we have Z is equal to S, X, Y plus, open bracket, one minus S,
X plus Y.
Both of those are equivalent.
We have taken a piece of code, we have arithmetized it as a mathematical expression.
So then we can use this Schwad-Zippel lemma, which is rather than having to give you all
of these huge degree polynomials, depending on the number of equations that you're checking,
there is something that we can do where we can just evaluate a polynomial at one point.
That relies on the Schwad-Zippel lemma.
Let's pretend that we have two polynomials that we're trying to check a multiplication
of.
If you remember in the first slide, we had FG evaluated alpha is equal to F of alpha
multiplied by G of alpha.
These polynomials, if you notice, they're constructed so that they intersect through
a certain number of points here.
The red one goes through one.
X equals zero, the red one goes through one.
X equals one, the red one goes through two.
X equals two, it goes through minus one.
X equals three, goes through one, et cetera.
That's a Lagrange interpolation of those points.
The yellow one, likewise, does the same, but for zero, two, two, zero, two, one, three.
You can imagine those are the lines of our kind of proof or program that we're trying
to enforce.
The first one might be that we want to check that zero times one is equal to zero and two
times two is equal to four and two times minus one is equal to minus two.
How do we construct that proof?
If we multiply the points together like so, we get a new set of points.
Use these polynomials at degree six to create the polynomial that comes from multiplying
these two polynomials.
We need 12 points which are multiplied from both of these, but I've only done six here.
Then we have these points and we interpolate, we draw a polynomial interpolating those.
This is the new polynomial we get, the pink one.
If you remember this relation from earlier, we now have this polynomial fg.
Therefore, if there is a protocol where a random point or a random x value is selected,
then it's sufficient to prove that this evaluation at this combined polynomial fg of alpha is
equal to evaluations of the other two polynomials multiplied together.
Therefore, you can be sure that that pink one is the multiplication of all the individual
points because a random point and the probability of you being able to preempt that is basically
nearly zero.
We can actually see here, if we look at any two points, the top two is the red and the
yellow one and the white one is actually the multiplication of the two points and the purple
one is the purple one.
We've actually created the polynomial which have this property at all points along it.
Because it has this property, it's sufficient just to pick a random point and check that
that's true.
There is another puzzle piece which is the polynomial commitment proof.
Essentially you can create a commitment of a polynomial which is like hashing a polynomial
and you don't know what the polynomial is.
This is where the zero knowledge property come from.
Then there's objects representing a polynomial in your system and anytime you can create
a proof using the polynomial which has this statement on the right which says that F is
a commitment or hash of this polynomial F and Z is equal to an evaluation of F at S.
That's what that open does is it creates this proof on the right and then I can give you
this proof and I can give you the commitment to the polynomial which is just a hash of
the polynomial essentially and you can verify that whatever polynomial is inside of F is
equal to F or evaluated at S. The same principle is true for addition.
We have multiplication and we have addition which means we can construct any NP complete
program inside of ZK proof.
Another technique is multiparty computation.
Using NPC, with zero knowledge proof, I can compute a value.
I can prove a statement about some values that I hold but maybe sometimes we need to
compute or other people need to be able to know certain facts about other actors in the
system and maybe they don't have the incentive to create a ZK proof or to prove statements
about values that they hold.
That's where we use another technique that's called NPC.
I will show how we can do addition of values with NPC.
Alice has some secret number, 110.
Bob has some other number, 777.
Alice now splits her number randomly such that those numbers add up to 110.
If you add them up, it will be 110.
Then sends them to each other's servers.
None of the servers know what Alice's number is but they know parts of it.
They can reconstruct it if they collude but we're assuming they don't collude.
Bob does the same thing.
He sends his numbers.
When we want to compute an addition of the values, each of the server will add the values
together.
Now they get these new values.
If you look, those values added together when they reconstruct it is the answer of adding
the two private values together.
Multiplication is similar but slightly more involved but also it's possible.
NPC is another powerful technique.
We have homomorphic encryption.
Very simple partial homomorphic encryption is simply this function which is elliptic
curve multiplication.
If I have two values and I add them together and I multiply them by the generator of an
elliptic curve or just some point on the elliptic curve, that is the same as taking the value
multiplying it by G and then adding it to the other value multiplied by G.
Homomorphic encryption, the original idea in the 80s was there's a cloud and anybody
can put values into this cloud but they're encrypted and then other people can compute
answers encrypted for a certain public key.
This is the case.
You can use this to make computations on secret values.
From a kind of abstract level, there is this new emerging field of anonymous engineering.
We can compare it to other forms of engineering.
For example, when we have software, we write these instructions that run on a CPU and execute.
When we do cryptography, we try to use deep mathematical laws to try and create primitives
or schemas but the anonymous engineering is actually using those different techniques
like the ones I just showed or other ones like VDF or hash function, public key, asymmetric
crypto, et cetera, to try and come up with schemas that enable certain forms of applications
with invariants to hold.
Let's give a first practical example which is I have a set of values and this set is
just represented by a single hash and I want to prove that my value is in this set of objects.
To do that, we have to construct something called a Merkle tree.
Let's say we have eight values and what we do is we take two values at a time.
We take the first two values and we hash them together.
We get hash of them and let's represent that by a.
Now, let's hash the next two values, we get another node B and then we hash them together
and we get another node.
We get this kind of tree which the root R represents the entire set of values.
This is a simplified diagram.
Basically these might be 32 layers, so two to the power of 32 values will be in the tree.
For example, we had V1 and V2 and we hash them together and we get A. Likewise, we have
V1, V3 and V4.
We hash them together and we get B. Then we hash those together and we get AB and then
we do the same on the right-hand side and eventually we get to R.
If I have some value, any value, but let's say V5, this one.
Let's say we also have R. How can I prove to you that V5 is in R?
What I need is a pathway to be able to get to R. What does that pathway mean?
For example, if I give you V6, then we can hash those together and we get C.
Then if I give you D and we hash those together, then we get CD.
If I give you AB and we hash that with CD, then we get R.
Then I've proved to you that V5 is in R. Instead of needing to give you all of the items, I
give you a logarithmic number of items.
I give you a small number of items.
It's faster.
It's used as a technique, but it can also be used to create an anonymous inclusion proof.
We can anonymously prove that there is some value in R and we can even encrypt that value
or we can prove other statements on that value.
I'll show you some code, how that looks like.
Maybe I can put this mic somehow like this.
That would be great.
I need to speed up.
Here is the proof, you see the Mercale root at the top.
We're saying there's a pathway and we're proving some values in the root.
Then we're re-encrypting the value and we're exporting it.
To compile it, then I compile the proof like this.
It's compiled.
I have the code which actually computes the Mercale tree with the value, but then also
you see it includes the ZK proof code and then creates the witnesses and then loads
the circuit and then constructs the proof here.
Now we get a proof and then for the verifier we do here, we verify the proof.
We can just run that like so.
No internet.
Anyway, let's not worry about that.
We can use that to create anonymous voting.
How do we do that?
When we create constructs the people who are going to vote, we create something like a
coin and you generate a random serial number that's private and you just create this commitment
to it.
Then when you want to use up your vote, then you burn the coin and you make that public,
that secret value S, which means you can't ever generate the same thing again because
that value is deterministic.
Then you prove that there is a C that's a hash of S and that C is in the tree using
the previous inclusion proof.
How do we change that to do anonymous payments?
It's very similar except now this coin, not just being a hash of S, is also a hash of
a value for the coin.
So it's two and four which are owned by Alice.
Then when we want to spend that coin that Alice has, then we reveal those serial numbers
and we compute the partial homomorphic encryption of the two and the four.
We create this transaction with two outputs and we create the two new coins like we showed
before in the previous slide.
But we also want to prove that the value that goes into the transaction is the same as the
value that goes out and we do that using homomorphic encryption like we showed earlier.
You see here, we've got the two plus the four is equal to the three plus the three.
So there we go.
Then we can do atomic swaps with different types of assets.
So Alice constructs her input and one output sending to Bob, Bob takes the transaction,
adds his input and one output sending to Alice, Bob also signs the transaction, Bob signs
and sends the finalized transaction.
We can also do something where you have a network with anonymous spam protection.
So you have Shamir's secret sharing scheme and normally, so basically with this, you
have this evaluation.
I'm going to go fast now.
When you want to send a message, you compute the message M, you compute this X and Y.
If in one epoch, you again create another message, so you're spamming the network, then
you get these values which using the equation on the first line, you can compute what A0
is.
A0 is actually your secret key.
So then that means that whenever you try to send another message to the network in any
other epoch, now you've lost your account, you can never send.
But it also means that messages are unlinkable.
So you have unlinkability.
We can do anonymous auctions using MPC.
So Alice has Bids $4, Bob Bids $6, they do a computation, they compute who's the winner.
We can do anonymous WikiLeaks.
So I have this thing,.jpg, and then there's a protocol where I've made some claim about
what this file is, and it selects a random chunk from the file.
And then we verify, yep, that file is what it claims it is.
And then there's an auction on the remaining chunks.
And the winners of those auctions decrypt the remaining parts, and then the file is
decrypted.
If you go to the Docs section, we have our own peer-to-peer anonymous chat.
There's no concept of identities.
So if you go to the Doc, there's a section called IRCD.
And we have a weekly meeting every Monday.
Also, there's a crypto section, Zcast section, testnet guide.
We're looking for good devs as well.
Also conclusion.
We missed the mobile and the desktop.
Will we also miss the crypto renaissance?
This is like our best chance to capture value for development.
Like this is the biggest problem with creative people is they create value.
They don't necessarily have a way to capture some of that value back.
We now have techniques to do that.
We were promised this future of computing in the 90s, the interface is beep, beep, beep,
whatever happened to that?
Never got it.
Right now, our phones, they're filled with all these dog shit, Electron apps.
That's a failed paradigm.
We're literally trying to copy Silicon Valley.
I'm optimistic that now people are actually going, actually, no, Linux is different.
We're distinct.
We have our own energy.
But we need to rediscover that.
We need to create something that's new because their model is about capturing users under
surveillance capitalism to extract value from them.
Our model is we create infrastructure.
We create economic value for our networks to become strong and as a movement grow powerful.
It's a different way of thinking.
Open source was a mistake.
We discarded the beating heart of what gave us energy.
We need to conceptualize the computing paradigm.
Let's build something new, actually inventive.
If I have a couple of minutes, I'm actually just going to show our website so I can show
where to find docs.
Okay.
I guess there's no internet.
Let's give a tour of our docs.
Here is a book.
I talked about peer to peer distributed IRCD.
You see there, instructions.
There's also crypto section.
See here.
And also implementations.
There's a ZK explainer and also implementations of most of the ZK algos.
Also probably more interesting for you guys, the Z cast stuff, like how anonymous voting
works and also anonymous payments.
I just showed the distributed chat.
You just run a daemon like that.
Open my WeChat.
Bam.
Here we are.
There's encrypted channels as well.
You just set in your config file and encrypted channel and then we have a chat.
See if I can chat with other people.
So yep, that's it.
That's my talk.
Thanks very much.
Thank you.