Welcome, College Mom.
Yeah.
The NOE one.
Yeah, we do a talk about Chegani, about, I'm calling it a collection of applications for
past mobile and past Microsoft.
So, who I am.
I'm a KDE developer since 2018.
I was a member of KDE EV Foundation since 2019.
I started producing to KDE by basically working on websites and the accommodations, and then
I started doing applications.
I worked in multiple key applications, not to learn.
For example, NeoChat, MathiasClients, Contras, the Korshiki applications, Tokolong, Masnol
Client, Calendar, it's like a calendar application, but there's a bit more fun calendar, for
example, Contras and some emails, and IRL, like an EPUB reader.
I work at KADAB, but just a little two years ago, before I worked at Nest Cloud.
So what is Chegani?
Chegani is like a framework.
You actually took it to basically like a real project applications.
It's written in QML.
QML is like a language, a delivery paper, by Qt.
It's a declarative language, but it's sort of mix of Jison and Devasquip, but for a really
good integration with C++, so you can always use C++ often.
It was basically, QML was developed to build mobile and applications in the Nokia times,
when Qt was owned by Nokia, and I'm using that for past mobile, but as well to develop
conversion applications, not only for mobile, but also for desktop.
Basically how it works is that you have multiple pages.
Here you can see two pages.
One has a list of emails, and the second page with the content of the email.
There's also like a Java concept, basically you can have things on the left and right,
additional information.
This is like a figure, oh, it looks like desktop.
And on mobile, you get only one page displayed at a time, like you see of two and only one,
but it's got the same UI.
It's still like the same code, but what?
First of all, the drivers are mobile friendly.
Instead of putting them on the left, you have some sort of collapsed driver.
Basically, there's two ways to have pages.
Either you put them in the column, like here, especially when it's for each of us, or you
can also put them as layers on top of each of us.
On each page, there's some actions.
You can basically add some buttons on the top, details you want.
But basically, how you build the key notifications, there's a few concepts, the pages, and so
it all works, and basically most of the key notifications that they look at.
For example, for short notifications, like your chat, you only have two pages, one left
for the list of users, or chats, and one right with a few chats.
And yeah, it's basic logs.
And basically, our key game we started was 2015.
We are not personal buy, but at that time, we are still using the plasma components.
So basically, the same components that we are using for the plasma desktop, you are
using them to create applications.
But these are squeezing issues because first they got a look of personal applets, and as
in applications, key applications.
Maybe as on the code, not convergence, so you are basically like to build applications
for mobile and other applications for desktop, which are the same for AT.
There's a lot of duplications of efforts.
So I'll try like one year later, we can create micro-matting, and I think of key game, we
created key game to basically only have to build one applications for both mobile and
desktop.
I mean, this is like a really long time ago, eight years ago, seven years ago.
And then we tried to add more integration with the desktop because even at the beginning,
the key applications were more like mobile applications still.
So one of the things that we did first was like to create a team for the desktop, QQC2
desktop team, basically like critical controls, the framework that we are, the QQKML allows
you to have teams where basically can implement the features.
We have like a desktop team, what looks like a desktop applications, normal QQC2 applications.
When you're at our, we did a lot of work as a whole, and so is the colors, but they use
the same colors.
And the desktop, as a QQKML, uses the same colors as normal QQC2 applications.
And before 2020, there was like, I must know, the device that we could use key game.
So the development was quite slow because I mean, there was the Nexus 5, what kind of
worked with, but it was small, all device, but was slow, really slow.
And then there was 2020, pine64 and pinephone.
And I think that's really a way to get the contributors.
And as a way of contributing to plus nearby, it was a natural pinephone.
You add clearly like a device that you can call by and what supported Linux.
And I get here last year, we also launched the QQM add-ons.
I will go more into that later.
Yeah, basically like, in recent times, we like, felt like working new components, like
for the previous settings from Tokodone, the Muslim account, yeah, we've worked with a
lot of chat, there's a list to have a nice look.
But if you do, yeah, and again, the Tokodone settings, we actually see moving from components
to basically like, mostly doing forms, but we are also using that for other stuff, basically
display formations, yeah, still a bit the idea of GNOME for that because they look quite
nice.
And yeah, that also like, basically like some combinations of the forms, one of the last
introductions we added to KGami, we are going to use these tree views, like here it's in
calendars.
I was going to do three, I will detail information as a tree.
It is useful for the test view in the calendar, where you can see the task and the task.
Yeah, another one, last instruction that I created, what I contributed to is a sash pop-up,
it's a nice component where you can basically like have a sash filled with a pop-up, but
appears when you click on it, with the results, it's pretty nice, I think, with the nice animations,
but yeah, that's mostly it.
Thank you very much.
Question, comments.
Yeah, I was interested in how many devices are associated with support of platform on
the platform, can you repeat?
I mean, there's a, buying from, buying from poor, but like supporting intraday, when the
pass-over team doesn't really like to the, or the advent implementations, we focus on
the UI because it's where we are quite good at, but the post-market OS folks, I mean,
everything that's on post-market OS, for example, can run post-market mobile, because it's
basically like just a shell on top of post-market OS, or manjaro, as well as a, manjaro mobile
editions and there's like a lot of over-smart descriptions, I think open source as a mobile
variant and basically everything that's called mainline.
The important thing is what needs to be mainline support, we, at the beginning support it as
well as like not-mainline devices, but we had to stop that because there's too much
work to support both this sort of device and mainline, we had a lot of issues with the
telecommunications stack, because we had the, we were funo, what we were using, but it wasn't
really working well for us, so we switched to a little mobile manager, yeah, with a manager,
and yeah, but basically, yeah, every device that runs mainline Linux has a run, that's
mobile, I mean, you can have a run in the desktop if you want it, I wouldn't recommend
that, but you can do that.
I mean, we have partnership with Pine, 64, so we shipped personal wire on the Pine phone,
but it's quite hard to, I mean, probably no mainstream mobile manufacturer has support
for mainline Linux, and they are not really interested to support that, and they're not
really interested to have something else run under it, so it's a bit, because I mean, there's
not enough applications, I mean, it's one of the issues, under it's ecosystem has a
lot of applications, we can actually like, wait to run applications on past mobile, but
see like, yes, before we can, maybe see like, it's run on, installed on our mainstream devices.
I'm mostly focusing on applications, because that's the thing, it's part where we are
liking the most, native applications, don't really do the pass-master stuff.
Other questions?
Yeah.
I think there is an, as a browser interface, that supports, okay, C++, you know, it wasn't
implemented by UNR a few years ago.
Yeah.
Do you have in Kirikami any support for switching light mode and dark mode?
Basically choosing the color shims API, which basically it works, if you, in your chat it's
implemented, so you can basically switch the color shims, but by default it just follows
what the plasma colors are.
If you have the, it's basically like, we are trying to have the Kirikami applications,
but are quite new and not yet completely mature to like, looks and be exactly like the older
Kirikami applications.
So basically like, if you change the colors, every application we change the colors, the
QT widget one and QT1, but you can also like, implement, especially what one application
should only be one team, one color, it's also possible.
Yeah.
Do you see more KV desktop applications being ported to Kirikami in the future?
It's always like a bit of a controversial team.
I'm in, we find them in basically like, the wording, we foreclose you, the entire, the
same stack as all the KV applications, like a calendar, mail, contact, it's quite a bit
of work.
I think it's worth it because it's, looks a bit more, more nicer, but you see like,
a lot of work to get it completely right.
And I'm, what you only want is basically like, at least the Kirikami applications and the
Kirikami applications, because we can't get rid of all the Kirikami applications and how
about everything in Kirikami, but the integrates, what looks the same, what they work the same,
so when you interact with it, it should be like consistent.
I mean, that's all good because we can't just go with Kirikami.
Thank you.
No more?
If not, then thank you very much.