Hi everyone, I'm Jeroen. Well, I'm going to tell you something about parsing some files
really fast and I work for NL Netlabs. Oh, yeah, yeah, so some numbers. There's some
caveats here. So the 50, I did not do measurements because I made finished slides like 2.8. So
I did the measurements on the train. So, but I think the 50 megabytes is actually slower. I'm
pretty sure the 700 megabytes is correct and we will go beyond and I'm going to tell you how. So,
yeah, so basically the motivation is that currently the parser NSD isn't very fast and
we have an operator where someone only takes the better part of an hour and at that point it's,
well, it stops being practical. So, yeah, that's the motivation. And I'd actually like to take you
on a journey so that I went through. I will also show you the new algorithms but I also want to
show, tell you why parsing some files currently in NSD at least is really slow. And to do that,
we have to, I have to tell you a bit on parsing. So I've included an example with a whole world
C program and the NSD parser is based on Lex and Yack and that's really useful if you want to parse
things like a computer language where each token has a meaning of it in and of itself. For some
files, however, that is definitely not the case. So if you look at the, also in this case I provide
as an example but everyone in the room will probably make out that on the last line I try
to define an A record with a corresponding IP address and then what the zone parser actually
does is it takes the A, it makes that the owner and then throws a syntax error because, well,
an IP address is not really a valid record type obviously. So, yeah, Lex and Yack is not a,
is really not a good choice but then there's also the fact that I think zone files are only more or
less standardized, they're not really standardized and putting in MALI and when you combine the two
that, yeah, that just leads to a lot of trouble. And, well, first thing I did was analyze why the
current parser is slow and the current parser is slow. Well, it's actually inherent to the tool
because they're just not a good fit. Because what the lecture does is it gives you each token and
then passes on to the parser but it does so by matching a whole bunch of inputs and then taking
the longest one, the longest match and then executing corresponding action in which in the
case of the NSD zone file parser means that you can, that it copies the token then tries to
unescape it and for names it tries to, it needs the dots right because they have meaning in domain
names and what it does there is that it actually splits the input and passes each label separately.
That is, of course, copied and the parser then concatenates that all back together and that is
not really a fast process. So, my first thought was, well, what if I just changed the process a bit
and scrap Alex and Yack and got all the memory allocations. That gave us better numbers but
they're not the numbers that I wanted to see, right, because under the eight megabytes is, I mean,
you can express it in gigabytes a second but then it becomes even less impressive, right,
than 100 megabytes a second. So, yeah, I started looking into that and I will show you the
algorithms that we, or that I used and I came up with in a minute but to make you understand
why these algorithms work, it's important that each and every one of you knows that your CPU
is a pipeline CPU and all modern CPUs are pipeline CPUs and what that means is that each executing
each instruction is not a single step, it's actually a multi-stage process. So, there's a fetch and
decode step and there's a lot more to it in practice but this is a mechanism that was designed
so that you optimize performance in CPU and the premise on getting fast code is that you keep the
pipeline nice and full. That does not always happen, especially, or one case where that doesn't
happen is when you get a pipeline stall and that happens essentially when there's, when the next
instruction that you want to execute depends on the result of the instruction that you're currently
executing and in that case the CPU has to stall the pipeline, it has to wait until the result is
written back, it can then go on to decode and then only then execute your instruction and you'll
take a hit of a couple cycles. Then there's of course the well-known pipeline flashes and those
happen essentially if you, if there's a conditional jump, for instance, a NIF statement and the CPU
goes on to load the instructions that come after that and if it turns out it actually needs to
execute other instructions then it needs to flush the pipeline and only then can it go on to execute
your code and there's branch prediction that is used to improve the flow and modern CPUs actually
do a pretty good job of that but well it's prediction so it's not a, it's not always right
and it turns out so if we look at that information then we can analyze why parser is, the process of
parsing is just inherently slow because if we go over it byte by byte like the NSD shown parser
for example then before you can analyze the next byte you have to wait until you know you have to
resolve the new state of your current byte and also it turns out that as far as the CPU is
concerned the zone files are just random right that anything can happen at any time so it's hard
to predict branches in that case. Right so the base of the new instructions that I'm using at
base is a thing called a SIMD or single instruction multiple data and my interest in all of this was
really sparked by the SIMD JSON project and it caught my intention because they expressed their
throughput in gigabytes a second. Now in the next slide I'm going to tell you something about the
algorithms but I'm not going to go into them in grade depth because there's not a whole lot of
time so if you want to know more on that then I would advise you to watch the talk or just read
the paper. But yes in D what that is is actually an instruction set and what it does is it adds
factor registers and instructions to operate on those registers and what that allows us to do is
to classify blocks instead of just bytes. There's some trickery involved and there's a super simple
example on the slide but basically we can classify 16, 32 or 64 bytes in one go depending on your CPU
and then we repeat that multiple times for each input that we actually want to know about and the
ideas that we can cut branches and dependencies. So what's good to know about SIMD is that it's
all vertical non-horizontal so it's really an instruction that is executed for each of the
inputs so you can actually do logic in SIMD and the way to work around that is to convert the
inputs to a mask so we would get a 64 bit mask for each of the inputs that we checked and with
those bit masks in hand then the first thing that we are going to do is to classify all the escape
bits because there's so many files allowed for escaping and this is actually an algorithm that
the SIMD JSON guys came up with and basically what we do is that for each uneven number of backslashes
we take the next character and so that bit then represents the character that has actually escaped
and we need that information so that we can identify the quoted sections or in the case of
some zone files also the comment sections and this was actually kind of a hard problem because
they don't have this problem in JSON documents but in zone files comments can cancel out quoted
sections and quoted sections can contain semi-colons and then new lines they delimit comments but we
only want the new lines that actually delimits comment because what we really want to do is
that we want to find out which of the characters that we identify as structural characters are
contained in quoted sequences or in comments and there's a simple example in the bottom there so
oh yeah what I did a number of experiments but in the end it turned out that if there's a semi-colon
in there in the input we just branch so we have a slow path assuming that there's not too many
comments in zone files which for generated zone files I guess it's okay and once we have that
information all the bits that remain automatically belong to the non-quoted are non-quoted strings
and then and this is oversimplifying it but if we shift right and do it on XOR then that would get
us all the transitions and with that information we can then go on to create indexes of those
because your CPU does not only provide SIMD instructions it's also provides bit manipulation
instructions really fast bit manipulation instructions so the first thing that it does
is it takes it takes the population count to find out how many transitions are actually in your
input block and then we use the trailing zero count to find out the relative position of the
bit and if we combine it with the index then that should give us the pointer to the exact input
byte and there's there's some more trickery involved here because of course for zone files
if there's an error we want to report that error and to do that we need the line count and quoted
sections of course may contain just new lines but we don't want to worry about those in the
parser because that would that would mean that each parse function would possibly need to update
the line count and that would just not be very convenient so what we do there is we take an
unlikely branch if there's new line in a quoted section which really doesn't happen it's it's an
edge case in the case of sum files and we take the slope off to count all the new lines in the
input or at least the one in the quoted sections and then once we generate a token for the actual
delimiting new line we add the number of new lines that we found in quoted sections. Yeah and that
gives us basically that gives us a fast scanner in my initial measurements and I think it's a
little bit fast now that would get me a scanning of two gigabytes a second for sum files at least
with an older.com zone etc etc so there's caveats there too but it turns but it turns out that the
rest of the DNS data because we of course we have to parse it we only now tokenized it we also have
to parse it the rest of the DNS data allows for optimizations using SIMD as well and of course we
want to start with the data that occurs the most and there's of course domain names and with the
SIMD instruction we actually just repeat the scanning process we quickly identify all the dots
we turn that into a bitmask and then use the bit manipulation instructions to go over the domain
name because most of the time if we just fill in the length on the dot then that would give us a
proper Y format and of course there's a slow path for edge cases as well there and next of course
this is the record type and normally I guess you would hash I initially just used binary search
which is faster than just linear search of course but that took away quite some performance
so we want a perfect actually we want a hash but then a hash table is pretty big and so I figured
I want a perfect hash and it turns out we can do we can do that so if you take the first character
of the records because there's not that many record types right and there's certainly if you
take the first character there's never more than that many records never more than like eight or
nine record types I start with the first letter so if you then take the last character and at the
length then it turns out that doesn't give me any collisions so we can also the hash if collisions
occur but I mean for all the record types and what for four years it doesn't give me collisions
so I guess we're good on that front um this is a weird width type with a number no for each record
type someone asked if this only works for record types and then the number and answer is no it
works for all record types because they're all closely they're all really close together right
so they're in their alpha numeric most of the time sometimes there's numbers so if you just
uh I think I could case or down case it and then multiply together a good distribution
and then just add length and that gives me a that gives that gives me a unique key without
collisions and from there I can just do a use in the instruction to do compare equal
so I can do the exact right string compare and that gives me a really nice nice speed up
um yeah and it and the people who worked on SIMD JSON actually do a lot of did a lot of projects
like using SIMD for for decoding base 64 so the plan is to incorporate all those things as well
um and then there's one tricky part um your cpu actually supports multiple instruction
sets at least if you have modern cpu if you have like a pending forwarding you only get sse for
the two but we want our software to be able to run on all those devices without recompiling
so we actually compiled it four times in the case of x x86 then use the cpu id instruction to pick
the right one and then well it's still in progress projects I hope to be a little bit further along
but unfortunately not um it will be a standalone library because it might actually be useful to
other people um and that will make it easy to integrate into other projects it was initially
just intended for nsd um yeah the numbers are so far pretty good at least quite a bit better than
what we have now um I think it's possible to go to one gigabytes a second
yeah so if you want to check it out there's a link in there
and finally I want to uh there's a slide with acknowledgement because these people help me a
lot I just send them unsolicited email at first and then I happen to get answers back and they
help me and they even took a look at my presentation help me there as well um so thanks to uh Jeff
Daniel and all the simdiation people and with that I actually finished in time uh it's time for
questions yes maybe my question was clear what I'm wondering about is the hash collations of the
name the type which are encoded as the word type followed by a number oh no but that's that's a
slow path that they're and exactly they're the hashtags more but that's a slow path
so we do a slow path sorry I should repeat the question what um the person in the audience was
actually referring to what happens if you we use a generic type notation where we start the type by
type followed by a number and obviously it doesn't work there but it does the slow path so we have a
slow path there yeah is the parcel so complete that you can parse an output and you get same
output as you parse them uh really good because I would yeah so if the parser is uh good enough
that uh to give you the exact same output as you put in um no it does not do that there's
well you you I mean do you mean by x to wide space exact or just
just yeah no it doesn't do that no but it's also not the
it's so if you see white space but it doesn't strip comments it does also strip comments yes
yes yes yes
yes how do you handle uh escape decimals because in the example you gave you strip and you have
look where the back slashes are yeah and then take the next character but if you have like backslash
003 then you need those four characters as a single unit to encode in the final um I'm not
actually I just do the uh I just uh really good yeah you're gonna have to I hope there's no more
questions because you're gonna have to keep doing that but um what I do so what happens if um I guess
for a certain type of input I record uh record data you can stick like a backslash 003 which
encodes the bytes with a value three single byte yeah how do you do that with your algorithm that
just takes the next character when you have backslashes um but that's just to just just to
so the question is what do I do with escape characters or with escape sequences um and so
what I explained on the um what I do what happens with backslashes is just to tokenize so I don't
strip any data I just mark out the starts and the ends of each string field and then the parsing
comes after that so there's no data actually stripped yeah question over there yeah sorry if
I missed it but what's the output format is this just memory or is this to store in a database like
in a binary format yeah um so the question is um so the question is what's the output format
and the output format in this case is just DNS wire format so the um the id here is that for each
record it will invoke a callback and it will just give you wire format with pointers to where all
the fields are in the like an internal description of the field so that you know the length and you
know the type of the field yeah using the same method you used to convert to cine instructions
there is definitely value to large effectors because it takes less instructions so if you
can do something so um I did not look into using the GPU um but yeah that might benefit so if you
no I have not no
no
so the question is this is really good
why do why does parsing zone files have to be fast well um because they're they get
reloaded quite a lot of times each time there's an update uh to a zone you need to reload you
need to reload the zone um so we wonder yeah so that happens multiple times like an hour it
it's differs per zone right but in our case um if it takes more than an hour and the operator
actually or it takes the better part of an hour and the operator wants to leave more wants to
reload more often then that becomes a problem right so we just need to be faster but then there's
all the and so there's other benefits as well so nsd for instance we support zone verification
where just before the zone goes live um you can have a focal program uh to verify that your dns
seg data is is correct and there you can use an axfr or you can let the nsd feed you the zone data
in which case you just get text representation and if the zone is big enough then you want that to
be fast because it's in the critical path right last question over there yeah it's splitting the
files and multi-threading something you considered uh well actually uh if the question was if splitting
the files and multi-threading is something that we considered well splitting the files no um but
split on them yeah well new lines um yeah that can be tricky because some files can contain
parentheses which would then mean that if the record continues on the next line um but a colleague
actually did uh did do a parallel uh zone loading implementation um and i guess we can even do that
with uh with this implementation right um because there the it was actually quite a bit faster um
but the scanning process still takes a long time because you go over it by by byte but now that we
have a fast scanner there's no reason why we cannot also include like parallel parsing yeah that could
work yeah did you do any experiments of actually saving this into the database like something
relational maybe and if you did what impact did that happen um so the question is if we did