Five more seconds so you can start.
Thank you very much for having me.
Do you hear me back there?
Yes.
Lovely.
All right.
Okay.
I'm Konrad, and I have the opposite of problems, and I have a million of problems compared
to Geran.
Because Geran had performance issues, that was the thing before, and he tried to parse
DNS zone files really fast.
In the I2P network, which is an overlay network which provides anonymity, we have that few
hosts.
We don't even need to think about performance.
We have, as I said, one million other problems.
Now, the students of the University of Applied Science got the job from me to take a look
at this DNS problem because the I2P network has no DNS.
So welcome to Stone Age.