Hello everybody, this is Stefan, Stefan Borsmeyer of Aethnic.
We will talk about Drink, which is, I guess, an experimental DNS server?
No, not at all.
It's a tri-moist station in Belgium, actually.
I'm already right there.
Well, yes, it's a DNS server.
And you can see here an example of it working out for them.
I asked 2 plus 2 dot domain name, TXT record, and that's extraordinary.
I get 4 as an answer, which is really, really useful.
It was not possible before, but...
Maybe with the sensor, which is true.
Exactly, exactly.
This is authentic.
So you can be sure it's really, really 4 because it's signed with DNS.
So now we are going to see how it is done by Magycto.
So Drink is a dynamic authoritative name server with several services.
The main one, which was the original goal, is to return the IP address of the client.
You have a lot of services on the internet doing this, but all of them are very minimum.
They don't implement all of the funny things of the DNS.
We have also other services.
For instance, ECS, EDNS, client subnet echo can be useful also if you want to know what
your wizard is sending about you.
And you have other services such as the calculator.
The goals to develop Drink were first to learn, to have fun also, and also to implement.
A lot of DNS stuff that are missing from the typical dynamic DNS services such as TCP,
NSID, cookies, DNSsec, of course, etc.
Extended DNS errors, etc.
So that was the idea.
Also it also provides a platform to test IDs at IETF accountants.
IETF accountants are great because you can have T-shirts.
And it's opportunity to test new IDs, new stuff, and modifying existing software like
NSD or BIND or not is not always easy.
So I wanted something which was easier, at least for me.
So as you see, it does not pretend to be a competitor to things like power DNS, NSD,
not, etc.
It's experimental.
So the implementation is done in Elixir.
For the people who don't know Elixir, it's mostly a functional programming language which
compiles to an Erlang bytecode which is then executed by the Erlang virtual machine.
The good thing about Erlang is massive parallelism.
So the virtual machine is really, really good for that.
The syntax of Erlang is seen by many people as a bit of style.
So the Elixir was mostly done, at least at the beginning, to have a better syntax for
the same bytecode on the virtual machine.
Also it's always fun to learn a new language.
I didn't do everything myself.
I had to rely on several existing libraries.
It's one of the pleasures of free software.
You have a lot of libraries with free software license compatible with the one you use, obviously.
And the problem is that Elixir is not mainstream.
So unlike languages like Go or Python which have very, very good Matthew-Mentain-the-debugged-DNS
libraries, Elixir, there are some DNS libraries, typically with the last commit three or four
years ago, sometimes older, and not always maintained and things like that.
So it's a typical problem when you program in Elixir.
When you go to X, which is the main repository of libraries, you always find something,
whatever you are looking for.
But pay attention, is it still maintained, debugged, et cetera.
You have many libraries for the same stuff, but not all of them perfect.
So it's one of the problems you have when you program in Elixir.
Drink can itself call external microservices with HTTP or things like that, which has consequences
for the implementation because external services can be slow or unreliable.
So you have to be careful not to crash, not to hang everything while you are waiting for
the microservices.
It's a bit like the talk about DNS resolution for graphical program.
Here we may, unlike the typical authoritative server which only depends on what is in its
memory, so it's very predictable, on the response time is constant.
Unlike this typical authoritative server, drink has response time on success rates,
which are highly dependent on the external services.
It's free software, of course, because we are at FOSDEM, so I wouldn't dare to present
it if it were not free software.
You are already here, but let's go to the important implementation point.
First one, which is probably the most important, parallelism.
I don't like events.
I think that events are an invention of the devil.
Parallelism, good intended parallelism to be done with processes.
On Elixir, well, Erlang actually, because the one time is Erlang1, Erlang encouraged
you to use massive parallelism.
When I say massive, really massive.
You have anything to do, you create a new thread of execution.
It's very, very efficient.
In drink, every DNS request is a separate process.
When I say process, it's not an operating system process because of course creating
them and managing them would be much too costly.
One of the funny things with the Erlang world is that they have a terminology which is quite
specific.
Words like process or application do not have the same meaning in the Erlang world as everywhere
else.
A process here, it's what Go is calling a Go routine.
For instance, for those who programmed in Go, it's more or less the same.
Basically it's very quick to create and to manage.
Don't exit one of the things that we always tell to the beginners in Elixir or Erlang.
Don't exit it to create process.
Every request is a process.
Every TCP connection is a process.
Everything is done by process.
For instance, logging statistics where it's not implemented yet but control through a
local socket is also done by a separate process.
As I said, there is a process for everything.
As consequences, if you crash, if there is an exception, remember it's experimental code
and it's written by me so there are a lot of bugs, but if you crash, you only crash
one process.
You don't take down the entire server.
That's a very interesting thing because it's one of the motto of the Erlang and Elixir programmers,
let it crash.
If a process crashes, it's not a big problem as long as the entire server continues to
work.
In the same way, if a request is stuck because you are waiting for something, you are calling
a microservice somewhere at the other end of the internet and it does not reply or not
immediately, it's not a big problem for a drink because all the other requests will
continue to work.
Because parallelism is really great and unlike what many people are saying, it's even simpler
than traditional programming.
So for TCP, as a consequence, when I programmed it in the Elixir way, pipelining, meaning sending
several requests over the TCP connection without waiting for the reply of the first one, worked
immediately without me having anything to do at all.
On out of order replies, which are not only allowed in TCP DNS but also mandated by the
RFC, work also immediately.
The first time I tested, it worked without anything specific because every DNS request
is a process.
So, okay.
It works in parallel.
So you have out of order replies.
Remember that for a typical authoritative name server, out of order replies are not
necessary because a response time is typically the same for every request.
So there is not really any point in making out of order replies, unlike a resolver, for
instance.
But drink is a bit special because any request can take some time, a lot of time.
So out of order replies are still very important.
And as I said, parallel programming is simpler.
This is something you have to teach to the students.
Parallel programming is not something very complicated that you see only at the end of
the year.
It's something very simple, very natural.
If you don't use events, everything is fine.
And you don't care about things like, this request may block me.
Yeah, okay.
Let it block.
No problem.
Other process will work.
So here is an example of Elixir code.
It's a functional language, so we use a map a lot.
We don't do loops because loops also are an invention of the devil.
So we have a set of IP addresses, and we just map a function.
The function simply listens on this address with some options.
Then you open the socket.
And for each socket, you create a server which runs this function, TCP loop acceptor, which
will itself create a process for every DNS request received over the TCP connection.
And that's all.
And is the end of the function that you map on the set of all IP addresses.
Okay.
Not even a bug in this one?
No, I don't think so.
Another important point when you write an Internet server, whatever type of Internet
server it is, is of course robustness.
Because as you know, the Internet is hostile.
You see a lot of funny things.
A lot of funny DNS packets, and sometimes even one dom binary sent to the 53 port.
So I assume everybody in the room have read RFC 9267?
Yeah.
It's very good reading if you are interested in DNS implementation, how it works.
Basically, it's a list of the things that can go wrong when you pass DNS request.
It's not a complete list.
So the Internet is a jungle.
Incoming packets can have whatever, literally whatever.
Everything is possible.
And of course, the main example in RFC 9267 are compression pointers.
Because compression pointers can do things like pointing to themselves, pointing outside
of the packet.
So if you program in C in a completely careless way, you can imagine what will happen.
And indeed, it happens in the real world.
Most of the example in the RFC are from DNS mask on the windows, but it can happen to
anyone.
EDNS is not mentioned in the RFC, but it can be fun also.
It was especially fun for me because the DNS libraries that I choose, I discovered later
that it has no support for EDNS.
So EDNS had to be done entirely.
And EDNS options, for instance, are type length value.
So you can have a length which is too large or too small and make the packet impossible
to pass.
Or even worse, can trigger crash of the server or remote code execution in the worst case.
If you program in C, this is the sort of thing that can happen.
So here is an example on how to pass EDNS.
The second line with the brackets.
The brackets are when you handle binary data, you extract the code.
You use for that pattern matching because it's a functional language.
Elixir relies a lot on pattern matching.
So here, the equal here is not an assignment.
It simply means that you pattern match.
And if it fails, there is an exception.
So binary part which extracts the first two bytes of the data is a safe function, meaning
that itself it uses pattern matching.
If there are, for instance, not enough bytes to get the first two, you will have also an
exception.
You won't execute a remote code or go outside in the memory or things like that.
Then you do things.
You extract also the length of the packet and then you read the length.
So if you do this sort of thing in C without paying attention, you can imagine the catastrophic
thing that can happen.
But here, it's safe.
In the worst case, you will have an exception here because not enough bytes.
So here, we trap the exception.
Only with a proper exception and then we will return form air to the guy.
In case you have something unexpected, this back crash, of course, it may take down the
process but remember, each request is a separate process so the other request will be fine.
DNSsec, ha, DNSsec is fun.
Because it's dynamic, you need to have dynamic signing.
On cryptography, one of the things I really dislike with cryptography is that each bit
wrong on the signature is completely off the mark.
So it makes things really difficult to debug because some software tell you that the signature
does not match.
Okay, what's the problem exactly?
Did I forget a field or did I forget something in the RFCI?
Yes, something.
So an example, a bug that I had, for instance, is that default encoding of the DNS library
uses compression for the data which is inside the R data.
So the domain name in the SOA or NS record, for instance.
But the RFC about DNSsec says that the signing has to be done on encoding which is done without
any compression.
So it didn't match and it took me some time to figure out the problem.
Also, the library I used did not allow to encode without name compression.
So I had to redo everything myself.
Like most programming projects, drink was at the beginning, oh, it seems simple, it
will be done in a weekend.
And of course, in the end, it was much longer.
So here is an example of code for signing, again, binary data.
We put all the information that are mandated by the RFC in the pseudo RFC, which is then
encoded by myself, unsigned.
There are a few funny tricks, for instance, all domain names has to be put in lower case,
the sort of problem that you discover when you go through a resolver with those case
one domain name.
That's how you learn.
But the most funny in DNSsec is, of course, negative answers.
So Moses came back from the mountain with 10 commandments and one says that you should
not lie.
But you have to lie here because you have to say that there is nothing between this
name and this name, and you don't know all the names because the server is completely
dynamic.
So drink used something called white lies, which are described in RFC 4470.
So the Nsec record is just a bit before the name to a bit later.
It seems simple, but it's very hard to get at one step, for instance, when implementing
the algorithm of RFC, I had code which worked with unbound or not, but failed with bind.
And I never really discovered why, but after some tweaking, it worked.
Also encoding of Nsec bitmaps, it's quite interesting.
Nsec bitmaps are encoded in a very clever way, but very hard to get right, especially
since the RFC has only one test vector.
So it's very difficult to see if you are on the right track or not.
But in the end, it works with we have everything in Elixir necessary.
Enumerate, it's all the things that you can enumerate.
It's a very generic library.
So you can do things like finding the minimum, filtering to extract some data, map to apply
a function, et cetera, et cetera.
It's cool.
Of course, you need to test Elixir like most programming languages as a framework for testing.
But also I made external tests from a Python program written in Python to be sure that
I don't have the same bug in both the tester and the testy.
So it's also especially important in the DNS to test not only with proper DNS requests,
but also with broken requests to see how the server reacts.
So here is a Python code to create, for instance, an incorrect edns option.
This is a comment on the second line.
The length, nsid has no data, but here we put a random length.
So any server that will try to decode edns stupidly will read too much bytes and something
wrong will happen.
So we create this edns option for the dns packet.
We send it to the server and we hope that the server will reply as the RFC said with
form error.
Otherwise the test will fail.
And that's all.
So time for questions.
Perfect.
I have a question.
On this screen, I will start with the question.
Yes.
That's a, that's this.
I haven't seen any elixir slides.
How is that?
Good question.
I have to think about it.
Yeah.
The question was about byte order because DNS RFC specify byte order for things like
your length in edns packets, for instance, and it's not explicit in the elixir code.
And that's a good question because I don't remember how I did it, but I won the program
on several machines with addition byte order to be sure that it was okay, but I don't remember
how I did it.
That's an interesting question.
This is a code that I wrote.
The last code that I wrote was DNS sec.
So DNS sec is still fresh in my mind.
So rest is a bit more complicated.
I can probably add that when you specify the binary pattern matching, you can choose how
you want it done.
And you can specify the elements and get the default thing.
I don't remember which element.
Yeah.
I was wondering if TCP, the pipeline just worked, right?
How does it handle larger files?
Do you not have that?
Is it always like the answer comes back?
And so there's no chance that a big answer has to worry about a small answer arriving
while it's being sent or anything like that.
Well, the question was about TCP when there are some questions or replies that are larger
than other or takes more time.
So because of the parallelism, because every DNS request is a separate process, they follow
their own path.
The only case where they meet is when they try to send the reply back.
So in that case, it's an error-long virtual machine which is in charge of being sure that
you cannot interrupt a write operation.
So the way it's implemented is that everything goes through a process.
For instance, logging works the same way.
We send everything to a logging process which then serialize.
So we can be sure.
And also writing on the socket is done by the error-long library, not by me.
So it cannot be interrupted.
So there is no risk, for instance, of interleaving replies, if that was your question.
On the error-long socket library also does a few things that are not really important
but are fun.
For instance, when creating the socket, maybe you notice this option packet two.
It means that two bytes length has to be added automatically which is good for EPP or for
DNS.
And also by default, it's in network byte order which is good again.
Ah, performance.
Yes.
With DNS perf, and I compare the drink with the NSD, drink is typically three to four
times slower which is expected, of course, because it's dynamic.
It has not been optimized for speed because NSD is very fast.
So of course, as you know, performance testing is something complicated.
It depends on a lot of things.
So I don't have strong, serious measurements, but the measurements I did on my machine show
that the difference in performance is, in my opinion, quite acceptable.
Three times slower than NSD is actually quite good.
Are you planning to add a small cache in front of it?
Or for any dynamic answer that lowers you the same answer?
The question is, do I plan to add some caching in it because some questions can take time
to retrieve or to compute?
No.
I don't think it's, as you know, caching is one of the two or three complicated things
in computer programming.
So in my opinion, it's not worth it.
Caching can be done by the client anyway.
You can run a drink behind the NSD, if you're willing.
Thank you.
Thank you,ISTER.