Hello, this is Peter Mensik and he will tell you why resolving two names in a GUI program
is hard.
You ever tried?
You know.
If you've never tried, let's say.
Good afternoon.
My name is Peter Mensik.
I work for Red Hat, so I took my hat with myself and this is a presentation about the resolution
of two names in single program.
It's not simple.
So how do I resolve names?
The system offers get other info call and it is protocol and family independent, requires
just host name and service name and returns and this is somehow ordered and works on major
OS operating systems.
It is fine, but it blocks and we don't want that.
We can work on that by using asynchronous libraries, which are usually DNS only.
That might be good enough, but not always and typical applications should not be limited
by that.
So good for servers, not for work sessions.
Because name resolution can be provided also by different providers than a DNS only and
somehow are obsolete, some are not.
So I think application should try to use common provider for any aim.
We have, for example, system of the which provides different protocols, but does it
in a way which makes, for example, DNS only application.
So it's not a good solution, I think.
How do I make multiple solutions from single program?
I can use circuit interface.
It works for DCP, UDP, present on any system, but I can handle dozens of connections from
single program without problem.
I just use poll or select and select only socket which has something ready for me.
So why is blocking problem?
Because the applications use not a blocking loop, but just event based loops and they
are nonresponsive, if any code they use blocks, we want to avoid that.
So modern applications are implemented by just callbacks to events they want to handle
and nothing else.
And then it spent most of time waiting for something and conserved CPU.
So why not just working thread?
Because creating a new thread is simple, but receiving result from finished work into the
main thread is not so simple.
And it increases complexity a lot of any application almost.
So why that is needed anyway?
Same resolution on Linux machine came from multiple modules.
Some are local only on the machine.
Some need to ask local or remote service and fetch, send some request and wait for some
response it may tie or not and extract fetch addresses and return them to start collecting.
And the most important waiting for timeout or activity or socket activity is implemented
by any framework doing non-trivial applications anyway, because they need it.
So how can it be made non-blocking?
I think we should make common code to implement protocol specific plugins and DNS should be
only one of them.
And for example, multicast DNS or so and provide integration with custom loops in different
applications because major graphical applications use Qt or G-REAP, but they may use some custom
loops and it should require relatively small time, small code to integrate with them quite
nice.
So we should rewrite existing modules to use callbacks like modern applications and not
just blocking because current modules are easy to write and maintain but difficult to
use from normal applications.
I think resolution should be simple even in multiple applications.
So what do we need, just ability to add and modify socket into a watch list of events
and be notified after time is up and if no activity occurred and provide some code to
handle those events.
And we don't care too much about time precision because we measure time out in seconds in
DNS anyway, so who cares?
So why not non-blocking?
Because it creates no race conditions.
It's almost unlimited.
We are limited by number of socket is handled at that usually quite high, so we don't care.
And it can allow many queries per thread without any problem.
And resolution would become more easy in a single thread only, not scattered over multiple
threads during runtime.
So we should not care and of course, that's a separator would still make sense if this
intensive applications are run but for small fetches of data from network, it's not necessary.
I think server software should take advantage too.
So unfortunately, there is no implementation yet.
I think Pavel Shimmerda wrote quite a good start, called NetRishov and it provides a
separate load double modules with different providers which can be used as building start.
But its documentation is quite poor and non-blocking API, I try to describe what is needed, is
missing and waiting for me, I think, to write.
But I think we need protocol independent API for normal applications.
And if we add just some metadata to strict others info provided by get other info today,
I think we could handle also HTTPS resource records in library and not require common
applications to handle that and implement it in each application.
I guess there's many applications starting HTTP connection and it should be not reimplemented
in every application doing that.
Of course, some parts are similar and for example, multicast DNS can use the similar
parts and could use the same calls with just asynchronous way.
And that is almost all I had to say.
So are there questions?
No questions?
So you want a solution for this, is there a way for Red Hat to lead this in the free
desktop space maybe?
Well maybe, yes.
Who should lead the initiative?
I am not sure, it's not official Red Hat initiative yet, so it's just my own opinion.
So it's not like Red Hat already has project and involved people and such.
So it's still what I think should be done, but not yet decided who should lead it on
or who should cover that.
I definitely want to talk about in the Red Hat, but it's in fact not clear to me which
main linguist or organization should start and should organize this because it's maybe
should be handled by GLEP people or I don't know.
I would like to talk and hear what other thing about it because I'm not sure myself.
It occurs to me that this problem statement is a lot like the get DNS problem statement
plus things that aren't DNS.
So I guess my recommendation would be why not look and see if you can enhance that API
to include these non-DNS naming systems.
Which API?
Well, the question was why not enhance existing solutions like get DNS for example.
I'm not sure how can you do that because I think that problem I have with system D trying
to do that.
Ah, it's far away.
Here, yeah.
This is a good example how to do that wrong because I think when application wants to
talk DNS only and nothing else, it should be able to.
So if I use the get DNS library and I think it should do only DNS, it should be able to
choose.
So how do I choose whether it's different protocols and how do I forward from get DNS
library, what did it all do from there?
Because I think get DNS expects DNS record types or such things and those are DNS specific.
Those don't work in other protocols.
Does that answer your question?
Well, not so much a question as well as how to get DNS address this.
Get DNS for all its faults is extremely flexible so you can enable and disable extensions.
So you can say by default it does DNS only if you say I want to have a DNS that starts
doing it.
So there is a way to extend it and the same thing applies to record types.
If you say I have a cookie record type, it fits within the framework to have it.
So I think it's not a technical problem.
Yes but, well, was it even a question?
Yes.
Please repeat the comments.
It was a statement, I think statement, get DNS is quite flexible.
Can I adjust to those?
Yes, why not?
I don't say we have to implement it from start but it should be generic enough so it would
be future proof and I admit I don't know details of DNS, get DNS library so I can't comment
details.
I just ensured it can do that.
Why not if it's another library but I think it eventually should land in libc or something
like that after it proves it works.
So maybe.
So you had a slide, anybody else had a question?
No?
You had a slide about callbacks near the beginning.
Callbacks.
It doesn't matter.
Do you expect every plugin to handle things like TLS or would TLS be something?
No, I would like to TLS be.
TLS is kind of special machine but it should be somewhere inside and what the user should
receive should be ready to use socket to work on.
So he just puts inside the name and service name and does the heavy machinery inside and
well TLS socket is something over it.
It's above normal connection so I think it should be extended.
I'm not sure what should be.
It's above that.
I'm out of time.
Yes, and also I think that's perfect.
Thank you.