So, my name is Robin Groszie.
I used to work for TransIP at first and Team Blue after they merged with a bunch of other
companies for about a decade until a month ago.
During that time period, we transitioned from running our own closed-source DNS server software
to running open-source DNS server software.
And just like the talk we just had that happens to be PowerDNS.
So I'll take you through the issues we had going from closed-source to open-source, which
roughly took the entire time I was there, about nine years.
So yeah, let's start.
So how it started for me, TransDNS, which they called the Homebrew DNS software, was
written originally in about 2003, 2004, and it had DNS support added in 2012.
When I started working at TransIP in 2013 as a PHP coder, I was asked to help them
debug a crasher in the TransDNS code.
It basically came down to a buffer overflow because somebody had, one of our customers
had managed to put more than 16 kilobytes of text record data on one single label.
The really ugly quick fix was to increase the buffer to 32 kilobytes.
And one small disclaimer, I was involved in almost all the work that I mentioned here
where there are some things that I didn't do myself or just consulted on, stuff like
that.
I'll try to make a distinction about it, but I might miss some stuff.
Yeah, so back then it was a really basic setup.
We basically had three servers.
They were all running TransDNS.
There was no load balancing.
The signing stack was built using DNS stack tools for those few people who still know
what it is.
And there was a lot of automation on top of DNS stack tools in PHP to make all of that
work and ultimately upload stuff to the registries because we were a registrar, so a lot of the
stuff was automated.
All of this DNS propagation was done to cronjobs, which means it was very slow.
It took roughly five minutes to propagate a DNS change, which back then wasn't really
a big problem, but as we went on, it became more and more an issue, especially when we
got Let's Encrypt that you needed to quickly update your DNS to get your certificate signed.
I think we still have roughly 1 million zones in the setup, most of which, so about 80,
90% are DNS-exigned.
There were very few people back then that actually knew stuff about it and dared to
work on it.
I think maybe three or four people, one of which was I.
It had very bad RFC compatibility, which I will get into a little bit later.
Adding new record types, which Kevin mentioned, like SSHFP was a lot of work because there
was an interpreter in Transdian as itself, which had to be written in C, and writing
interpreters in C for stack strings is not fun.
I fixed that initial buffer overflow block, but the main problem was there was just a
lot of bound checking in the code.
There were a lot of hidden bugs that probably should be fixed as well.
We took a few initial steps.
Initially, because we had the three servers, there was no long-standing thing in front of
that, it meant that if we restarted Transdian S, one of the servers would stop responding
until the restart was done.
The restart took roughly 15 minutes because every single record would get loaded into
memory and since we had a million zones, I think it was like 25 million records or something
back then, it just took a lot of time.
Kind of used the quick DNS zone parts and stuff.
The first thing we did was implement load balancing.
This was before DNS.
This was a thing.
We tried initially, it was relay day, which some of the BSD folks might know.
It did work, but we had a lot of weird issues.
It was really hard to debug.
Eventually we switched to using HAProxy for TCP, which works, nothing more to say about
it.
I wrote something rather quickly, in C, roughly based on the Transdian S code to forward the
UDP stuff.
That worked quite well and actually enabled us to actually iterate on the Transdian S
code because we could do safe restarts without having to worry about queries being dropped.
That allowed me to fix the glaring issues like there not being any bound checking in
the code, so we had less risk of buffer overflows.
I fixed a lot of the EDS comp issues that were becoming a problem at that point.
Eventually when DNS was a little bit more mature, we switched to that because otherwise
I had to maintain another piece of software and I really didn't feel like that.
In the meantime, I did improve the TCP stack a lot in Transdian S because we noticed that,
especially SIDN, the.nl registry, did a lot of TCP queries.
The original implementation was basically just spawn a new thread for every TCP connection,
but once you get to about a thousand threads, that's not a great solution.
I changed to a polling-based model, work rate got pretty high performance, and we never
had a problem with it after that.
The only thing I changed later is when we moved to Linux, I changed to E-Pole.
SIDN had validation monitoring, and we kept getting reminded by the fact that we were
doing a lot of stuff wrong.
We actually had one specific case that basically covered most of the, I think it was about
80% of those errors.
With 62 issues, but they have the same cost.
The first issue was the incorrect handling of wildcards.
If you have a wildcard, for example, star.nl, and you have a record C.nl, and then you
try to resolve A.C.nl, it should not hit the wildcard because C.nl exists, which means
you should return a no data or an extra main in this case.
But cleanse DNS didn't really care, so it would just return the data from the wildcard.
Very useful, makes it a lot easier to configure DNS, but it causes some issues, especially
with DNS validation.
The second issue was basically the same early, the Antinom terminals.
If A.B.C. exists, and you try to resolve B.C., even though there's nothing specific on B.C.,
you should say there's no data rather than it's a non-existent domain, also causes the
inner stack validation errors.
Same basic cause.
The solution was to switch from, in transiting is to switch from an ordered map that used
the type and the domain name as the key to a map that only used the domain name as the
key and have an array in there with the types, which could also be empty.
We would immediately notice if there was a label in our way.
That worked well.
I actually did it, this next slide.
The only problem is we couldn't just deploy that because we might break stuff for our
customers and customers get a little bit difficult if you break stuff for them.
What I decided was, okay, for DNS-SIC, it's broken anyways because DNS-SIC enabled resolvers
would just return errors when you have one of these labels.
What I did is fixed the two steps.
I initially enabled it only for DNS-SIC queries, the correct behavior, and kept the wrong behavior
for non-DNSIC queries.
In between, we just gathered a large amount of queries.
I think I did two days of TCP dumping and mailing it down to the actual unique queries.
Contact what our name-super would respond for DNS-SIC versus non-DNSIC.
For everything that had a difference, we contacted the customers and told them, hey, you need
to fix this.
I think it was only about 20 to 30 customers.
It was actually not that many, so that made it a lot easier.
Then we just, at some point, I decided I'll flip the switch.
There were a few customers that didn't respond, but at some point, you just have to decide
to don't give a fic.
Another small issue with RFC implementation was the NSIC implementation, because almost
all of our zones use NSIC 3.
The NSIC implementation was not as well-tested as the NSIC 3 implementation, so it was wrong.
Really wrong.
I just rewrote it from scratch, and then it worked.
We started to think about moving to power DNS, and the main reason we did was because
SIDN announced that we would no longer get a DNS-SIC incentive for domains using DNS
key algorithm 7.
That's the RSA plus NSIC 3 algorithm.
That would cost us a bunch of money, and that's a very good way to stimulate people to do
stuff.
At this point, we decided to buy the bullet and just start over from scratch and build
a really new, more modern setup.
We picked power DNS partially because we already had some experience with it, and we didn't
really want to deal with zone files, because we had a million zones, and putting them all
on a file system makes things annoying.
Power DNS was the only one where we thought, oh, this allows us to do changes via the API.
We don't need to worry about having separate zone files for every single zone.
We needed to pick a power DNS backend to use, because power DNS is one thing, but you still
need something to put stuff in.
There we sort of hit a problem, because transgene is really fast, because it's literally just
a hash map in memory.
It can basically do instant answers.
Power DNS back in is very nice and flexible, but it's not really fast, especially because
we had a lot of zones that would not get very frequent queries.
They'd have a lot of non-active data, which means the query cache wouldn't really help
a lot, which means that we would have a lot of SQL queries continuously, because they
would get queried sometimes, just not a lot.
The bind backend had the same problem as all the other name servers.
We didn't have API support, and it would mean we needed to use a lot of zone files, which
we didn't want to.
Introducing the LNDB backend.
This already exists at the point that we started looking at it, because Hubert had written
it.
It's very fast, and it has support for the API, which is really nice.
It only had one major issue.
Because of the way that it implemented it, it didn't really allow records bigger than
512 bytes.
We have quite a lot of those.
I decided to fix that in the end.
I wrote a pull request for the Power DNS team, and I think that was pretty quickly accepted
into there.
It also included some migration code, so the old LNDB database would automatically be
automatically migrated to the new LNDB database format.
It also improved performance in some corner cases, but that was not really the goal of
this batch.
Then we started moving over.
We built a setup.
It was really cool.
There's a lot of automation around it.
It does actually do all the zone transfer via HFR, even though Kevin just said it's a
bad idea if you have a lot of zones.
In practice, it works quite well, except for one issue.
Every first day, our updates would take ages to go through, and basically we traced it
down to an enormous bump in the HFR queues.
We would literally have 400,000 HFR queued up.
That was a bit of a problem.
The reason this happens is because Power DNS renews its signatures every first day of the
week.
Very nice.
We don't have to think about it.
The problem is, if you have a million zones, that takes quite a while, especially because
we were running our hidden primary on a VM.
It was also not that quick to answer queries.
We could have just shown more hardware in it, but we decided to look a little bit more
at a more sustainable solution.
Because if it works with one million zones on a faster machine, it will still work if
you have 10 million zones.
I discussed it with the Power DNS guys, and I came up with a solution which is HFR priority
levels.
Rather than treating all HFRs that need to be done at the same level, we gave more priority
to things that are user initiated.
If you initiate an HFR via Power DNS control, it will be first in the queue.
Whatever else is in the queue, that one will be treated first.
After that, there's the API, notified, so refreshed, and signature refreshed is the
lowest priority.
That meant that, yes, we would still have quite a large queue, but we could still process
our updates very quickly.
That was included in the Power DNS hot right-click queue as well, and 4.5 it was included.
We still saw the use queues, but the zone updates were pretty quickly propagated, so
that for us was fine.
We never had a problem with it after that.
Then we had some other issues.
Most of which were either mine ourselves in the load balance layer or just fixed in Power
DNS updates.
The TCP performance is still something I want to look at in Power DNS just for fun as an
open source developer.
It's on my list of things I want to improve.
We had some various smaller bugs in the LNDV backend because it was quite new.
We were not the first one that ran it a really large scale, but we were one of the first
ones and we did see some problems that nobody else had had yet.
One CFE we discovered literally within a day of rolling out a new version.
That was very fun for Peter because he got to roll out a new list a day after he released
the previous one.
We had an issue that there were certain query patterns that we would get that were specifically
designed to target a weakness in Power DNS.
That was a transience we didn't care about them, but Power DNS did get affected.
We eventually resolved this by adding some detection at the load balance layer that would
just block queries for those affected domains.
It would mean that that customer's domain would have limited functionality, but at least
it would still work and all the other customers would not be affected, which was for us the
most important thing.
Some closing thoughts.
Migrating a Home
Back It just really took a lot of time.
We can even in theory add different brands of secondaries.
Currently there's a few issues that would prevent it, but it's relatively easy to solve.
We could just run Not as a secondary, or NSD or even bind if we would want to do that for
some reason.
What I did really, really notice is don't try to do this in one go because it's a lot
of work and you'll make mistakes.
If you do it in smaller steps, the mistakes will be smaller, easier to fix, and it also
just feels a lot better if you can accomplish some things in between rather than trying
to do it all at once.
One thing I wanted to ask, DNSSEC incentives, they work both when trying to get people to
use DNSSEC, but they also work to improve the quality of the DNSSEC because we've seen,
especially in the.nl zone because I've also been involved in that work a little bit, some
very bad implementations that got fixed when the rules were made stricter, including ours
initially, but were even the worst ones.
That is it.
For the people I would like to see, I've open sourced trans DNS before I left the company
so I can see it myself as well still, so that's fun.
It's on GitHub.
I've also put the URLs for the two major pull requests I made.
There's a bunch of other ones, but I haven't put all of them in there.
That's about it.
Questions?
I wanted to remark, of course, you are enjoyable.
Kevin's talk, your talk, all things that you know about, the DNS is hard, getting it right
is e-marred.
The difference being is Kevin is shooting his own foot.
You are shooting the feet of your customers that are paying you not to.
That makes it a bit more of a concern than the UK's.
I used to be a customer, but on the upside, most of these mess apps probably weren't noticed
by the majority.
I think you should take it more seriously if you are a company that actually makes money
out of posting.
The comment is that we both made mistakes.
It was a bit related to the talk, Kevin did, so a lot of the things that we said are related
and the comment is, yeah, Kevin was only doing it for himself and we were doing it for paying
customers.
Yeah, I agree.
When I started, there were a lot of issues and I've tried three years to attempt to fix
them as much as I could.
To be clear, I wasn't hired to maintain trans DNS, that just happened to be something that
got shoved into my lab because I knew some C and C++.
I became pretty passionate about it.
I quickly rolled into the PowerDNS community.
I also added a lot of contributions to DNS when that was getting started up.
I agree with the initial statement and I've tried to fix it as much as I could.
I'd like to make a comment to this one.
Sometimes you set out with certain criteria and you build something that can meet that
criteria and it scales to a certain point and eventually you get to only building customers
and a lot of customers show the company that started off with more customers and maybe
at the time that this was a good system that people thought they needed.
But as the business grew and things grow, sometimes you have to do exactly what you
did.
You evaluate and say, it's time for something different.
It's real.
It's good that he identified that and made the changes accordingly and a great solution.
A brief resume.
He said that sometimes due to scaling, you run into issues that you hadn't foreseen when
you were an agent and he set something up.
Just taking a step to resolve them in the end can be a good thing.
There was a question there.
How did you get your employer to agree with open sourcing?
The question is how did they get them to agree with the open sourcing.
At the point that I open sourced it, I was CTO slash head of R&D of the Dutch part of
the organization.
Also, I only open sourced it after we totally took it out of production.
It was mainly a historic interest thing.
Did you ever consider open sourcing before switching?
The question is, did we consider open sourcing before switching?
No.
I'll tell you, we weren't very proud of, at least I wasn't proud of the source code quality.
I didn't write it myself, all of it.
I only contributed to it later.
I tried to improve it as much as I could, but it's still not.
It's very focused on just doing one thing and it's very good at that, but it's not
very applicable to use by others.
I think it's interesting now to see some of the tricks to make things really fast that
you can see in the code, but beyond that, I would never use it in a production environment
other than the one it was in, because that one was built specifically to run around that code.
One more question.
What was the motivation for implementing the DNS hosting in trans DNS?
Even around the time when you started as a company, there was not a software available
that could have been used.
The question is, what was the motivation to implement their own DNS software?
To be clear, trans DNS was implemented in 2003, so this was roughly when power DNS
started to grow, but the problem was that there were already quite a lot of zones in there,
and it just got a little bit cumbersome using Bind, because that was the primary name
server software you'd used back then.
That was the main motivation.
Bind was getting annoying because you had to have a lot of zone files, and everything
was running on FreeBSD using UFS, so there was a 32,000 files per directory file limit
at that point, which also didn't help.
There's ways to solve that.
That's not that complicated, but that was the main motivation, as well as I think there
were some performance issues in Bind back then that were relatively easily resolved.
The other alternatives would have been GGB DNS, but that had its own things, like the
guy that wrote it, not saying you should use it.
Anything else?
Because we're done.
Okay.
Thank you, everyone.