All right. Hello, everyone. Thank you for packing the room. No pressure. As Peter mentioned,
I'm Kevin Fleming. I've actually spoken at Fosdom quite a few times before, but never
in the DNS room. So this was a bit of a stretch to think that I might even get a talk accepted
here. And I'm thankful both that the team did and that you all decided to show up. So
as he mentioned, I don't know if I called a mistake. I made a decision a few years ago
about something that I wanted to do differently than I had been doing. And as a result, I
am now running my own public DNS server. So this is done for personal basis. I don't do
this for pay or anything like that. It's the zero profit part. Nobody pays me to do this.
In fact, it actually costs money. So it's negative profit, really, if you want to think
about it that way. Also, this is a bit odd, but I wrote these slides in a somewhat unusual
way, where every title of a slide is actually a question from the audience, which I will
then answer in the slide. They get somewhat humorous further into the presentation. So
if someone in the audience wants to play the role of the person asking the questions as
we go to each slide, that would be fantastic. In fact, you could all do it as a group. That
would be even more fantastic. So if you decide to do that, that's great. If not, I will be
happy to read them.
What? Really?
Yes. Exactly. Exactly. Yes. So all right. So start off with everybody in the audience
who currently is responsible for running authoritative name servers that are reachable on the public
internet. Raise your hand and keep your hand up. Okay. All of you. Wow. All right. Now,
if you have your hand up, but you're doing that because you run an internet service provider,
put your hand down. Oh, everybody. Okay. All right. All right. So we're down to less than
a quarter of the ones who had their hands up originally. That's more than I thought,
actually. I didn't think as many people were as strange as I am. So you can see with this
up, I already covered most of this anyway, it's relatively easy to do. Obviously, because
this is FOSLM, it wouldn't be talking about if it required non-free software. It does
not require anything that's non-free software. It can be fun for the subset of humanity that
would come to a room like this. And it's also not expensive to do. So all right. Now we're
ready. We're going to the next slide. Okay. All right. Why would we do something like
this? So the fun part we already covered. The second part is for years in my personal
infrastructure, I had been using your pod off mill with hurricane electric. They're
bigger in the US than they are here for hosting things. But the effort of free DNS hosting
service, which I'd been using, was working fine. And then I decided I wanted to sort
of enhance my DNS usage and implement DNSsec for SSHFP records so I could stop having to
deal with SSH key distribution issues. And a couple of other things, like I wanted to
get real TLS certificates for all of my services. And of course, five years ago, Let's Encrypt
was just a new thing. And DNS challenges were the best way to do that. And blah, blah, blah.
So the things I wanted, the DNS hosting service that I was using did not offer. So I thought,
fine, I'll go find a different one. And I can't even remember where it came from. But
years ago, some wonderful person on the internet used to maintain a Google spreadsheet of all
of the DNS hosting providers, commercial and otherwise, and all these different attributes
of what they supported. And so I went to that spreadsheet. And I filtered down to all the
ones that had the things that I wanted. And there were three or four left. And none of
them were ones I would actually have wanted to use. Most of them, because the minimum
cost was too high. They were designed for large enterprises that are doing this sort
of thing all the time. So I thought, all right, fine. I will consider another alternative.
All right. What do you need? So for those of you who have been around on the internet
for a much longer time than a lot of the people I see in the room who aren't old enough for
this, if you ever had to fill out the actual paperwork to register a domain name with network
solutions and fax it to them, you will know what I'm talking about. For those of you who
went way over your head, don't worry about it. So it used to be a long time ago that
this was a really complicated thing to do. Today, it's not such a complicated thing to
do. So these are the really simple things you need. You need someplace to host the service
that's going to be the source of truth for all of your zones. What do they contain? Obviously,
you can choose to put that in lots of different places. I choose to put it on a private network
that's not reachable from the internet because that's better, more secure that way. You need
a few places on the internet where you can make your zones available to the internet.
Preferably, those are not all in the same machine or all on the same network or all
in the same data center or preferably not even all on the same continent, really. It
would be best if they're geographically distributed, if they're not all going to go down because
you put them all in the same hosting provider and their control plane breaks all the time
in Microsoft and their entire cloud infrastructure goes down all at once around the world. So
keep those things in mind when you decide where to put these things. It's perfectly
fine to put these on Raspberry Pis in your friend's houses if that's something you choose
to do. If you have friends geographically distributed around the world who are willing
to do that for you, that's fine. But there are plenty of other ways to do it as well.
You will, of course, need DNS authoritative server software. There's lots of those out
there. There's a bunch of people in this room who are responsible for PowerDNS, so I'm thankful
for giving me the chance to do this. And then, and this is actually trickier than it would
seem, your domain registrar, the place you host your domains, possibly the place you
bought them from, although they don't have to be the same, needs to let you have the
tools to set this up. They need to be able to let you specify your own name servers.
Not all of them will. And if you want to do DNS sec, they have to let you upload DS records
for your signing keys for your zones. Fewer of them will do that. Many of them that are
especially the free ones do not give you the ability to do that.
Is that really it? Yeah, that's really it. There's not a whole lot required to do this.
Now this is all written from the point of view of me doing this personally. I would
actually be happy to use this same kind of structure if I was doing this for, let's say,
a small nonprofit organization or something like that. I would not go in this specific
direction if I was responsible for doing this for 10,000 domains for a bunch of people who
are paying me to do that. Things would have to be much more complicated in that situation.
Now going back to the way things were decades and decades ago, network solutions time. Back
then, we did not have Google Public DNS, Cloud for Public DNS, Quad 9 Public DNS, massive
ISPs with millions and millions or billions of subscribers that ran resolvers on behalf
of their clients. Back then, if you wanted to host your own zones, your own authoritative
servers, pretty much every small chunk of the internet was going to, if it needed to
know an answer for one of your names, it was going to be reaching out to your servers to
get it because there was no caching layer in between them and you. That's no longer
true. Obviously, lots of us also run our own resolvers.
We are going to be part of the noise that's hitting your authority of servers. But if
you have a website that millions and millions of people on mobile phones are going to touch,
those mobile carriers, resolvers are going to go ask your servers for the answers and
then hold on to them for however long you've told them they're allowed to hold on to them,
a day or two days or a week or whatever is appropriate. So you don't really need big
beefy servers to do this. Really, really tiny little machines are perfectly fine for doing
this sort of thing. Also, even the smallest machines you can get in clouds nowadays have
multi-gigahertz CPUs with very fast RAM. And as I think Stefan pointed out in his last
talk, a normal, non-dynamic authoritative server is very fast. It's very predictable.
It doesn't take a lot of time to come up with an answer. Usually all the data it needs is
in memory already anyway. So these are not, they don't have to be really super powerful
machines.
Why did you do this? Yeah, so I covered some of that already. Actually, I kind of did that
backwards, didn't I? I talked about that before I was supposed to. Darn it. So a couple of
the things that I ran into when I was doing the search was there was quite a few of the
available ones. If you just wanted to host one or two zones, they were okay. The prices
were reasonable, actually considered doing it. At the time, I think I had seven. Now
I probably got 11 or 12 for various different purposes because we all just grabbed domain
names for projects and then never used them for anything, but you keep them around. So
I thought that was a thread on the Fediverse about that. People ran, it's one round of
poll. How many domain names do you own that you've never used? The number was high. So
there were some where, you know, if you went above three, like it was $100 US dollars a
month for the service to be able to do this. There were others who, shockingly, charged
by query volume and not by the number of zones. It's like, well, I can't, I don't have the
control over that. I mean, if someone starts hammering the servers, not paying attention
to the TTLs, I don't want my bill to suddenly be $14,000 for this. This is crazy. So fine.
We're not going to do that. All right. Ready. What do I use today? So like probably a lot
of people at TOSDEM, I have at least one reasonably beefy computer at home, network
storage appliance. So there's a container on that where I run the hidden primary authority
of server. Many people who, there was lots of people who will not, who will choose not
to put things in Amazon Web Services. I'm not going to complain one way or the other,
choose whatever you like. I will say that their ARM based nano virtual machines are
the cheapest machines I could find that were not VPSs, that I could actually install my
own software on and open up my own ports and make them available to the internet. There
are lots and lots and lots of cloud providers out there, obviously. And if you can do this
with a, you know, one CPU graviton2 nano instance, you can certainly do it with a Raspberry Pi
or some other small computer like that. If you weren't trying to use power to you, you
could probably do it with an ESP32, although I don't think I want to try that, but you
could probably do it. So, so I have three, I have two of those. And then I have a dedicated
server in a data center, which I use for offsite backups and running my Mastodon server and
matrix server and all that kind of stuff. I put another one there just because. And
it gives me good distribution. One's on the west coast of the US, one's on a roughly east
coast of North America. It's not in the US, it's in Canada. And then one of them is in
Europe. So that works out fairly well. So, and then in our home network, because my home
network is wildly over engineered, I have two, two PC engines, APUs, which are our border
devices that connect us to the internet and handle all sorts of things. They're the ones
that run the resolvers, the recursive resolvers my wife learned about when she saw the slides.
And then of course, they also have a copy, they also have authoritative servers sitting
right next to the resolvers for a reason that I will talk about in a minute. And now you
don't have to read this because we're on the same topic. So I use Power DNS Auth Server
on all of them. I use SQLite databases because they're really simple and I want to try to
keep all of the machines except the primary as stateless as possible and simple to manage
and deploy. That also means that I use DNS based distribution of the data. So it's not
like a shared mess equal database or any of that sort of much more complicated thing.
But again, since this is why I went back to before, I would not do this if I was doing
this for 10,000 zones for paying customers. SQLite 3 would probably not be the best choice.
Well, actually, SQLite 3 would probably be okay. AXR would not be okay in that situation
because you'd be doing this constantly pushing out zone updates. And then because I use Ansible
to manage all of my infrastructure, and since there was no actual good Ansible modules to
poke at the Power DNS API to create zones and manage them and set up T-Sig keys, I wrote
some which there's a link to at the end of the presentation.
What was that cost?
Oh, I thought you were asking for the Ansible modules. Good job. Good job. Excellent. So
what is all this cost? So you already got the NAS putting another container and it's
free, right? Especially if something is lightweight as a primary, a third-party server, almost
no resources whatsoever. I translated all of the costs on paying AWS into Euro for you.
You can see that it cost me less than four Euro a month to host those machines. Now,
that includes paying for them for up front for three years. So because AWS basically
cuts the price in half if you do that as opposed to paying for it on a monthly basis. But it's
78 Euro for three years. If you decide two years in that you don't want those machines
located there anymore and you're basically throwing away 20 Euro of upfront payment,
that's not the end of the world. We're not talking about a gigantic amount of money here.
And then because I have the rented server and the other data center, putting a server
on that was free as well. The software, of course, is all free and the modules I wrote
are also free. So cost is very low. The half of the cost per month is actually the storage
cost from AWS for the root volume for the VMs. The actual cost of the VM is less than
the storage cost if you pay for, if you do it this way. And it won't let you create a
root volume that's smaller than eight gigabytes, even if you don't need that much. That's the
small, well, I'm using the Debian AMI and it has a hard coded minimum of at least eight
gigabytes for the root volume. So I suppose I could make my own and try to cut that down
by another few pennies or something like that. So what do I do with that? So as I mentioned
before briefly, all of the network infrastructure I manage uses real
transcript certificates for all browser accessible and actually some non-browser accessible endpoints.
I had been using self-signed certificates previously. For those of you who have done
that, you know how painful that can be, having to make sure that everything has the right
CA certificate to trust them and everything has, I don't want to do that anymore. So much
easier to use Let's Encrypt for that. Similar thing for SSH. All of there's 25 different
SSH-able endpoints across this infrastructure. Managing key rotation for them was a pain
because then things that had copies of the public half of the key all had to be updated
and everything else. Using SSH-FP solves that problem entirely except that it requires DNS
set. Well, I mean open SSH requires that it be a signed answer for fairly good reasons.
So I'm not going to try to work around that. And then something I didn't mention before
is doing this not only gives you access to be able to host all of the standards track
RFC DNS records, you probably get to do lots of cool things that aren't actually standards
track RFCs yet. So for example, HTTPS records, which are still just a draft and we don't
even know if they're really going to end up being approved or not, it probably will. And
Firefox and Chrome already know how to use them. I host all of those already for my HTTPS
services because why not? It just took almost no effort to set it up. I do Ansible-based
management for all of this stuff. And then I'm sure that most of the open source auth
servers out there can do online signing with Power DNS auth server. So I don't have to
worry about regularly resigning the zones and handling all the key distribution and
everything else because it does all that for me. So the last thing that's mentioned there,
which I'll get to just a little bit, but I had it on purpose. How many of you know what
catalog zones are? Wow. That's shocking because it's you. You wrote the code. Of course, you
know what it is. So catalog zones made this whole thing much simpler. In fact, we were
joking at dinner last night that there's probably would have had to be three slides in the section
about how to do maintenance of all of this that don't have to exist anymore because catalog
zones take care of the whole thing for you. I just led right into this, didn't I? So obviously,
new software releases have to be deployed. For the moment, although I know Peter's working
on it, there aren't currently ARM64 packages in the Power DNS repos. So I use their builder
scripts to just build them myself and publish my own packages to my machines to install
them. Eventually, I won't have to do that first part. I'll just run app, get update,
it'll install the new packages. And then whenever I need to add or remove zones, I go to my
Ansible playbooks and I change the list of zones that I want to maintain, go run them,
and they poke at the API to do the right things. First of all, make sure those zones now exist
or no longer exist on the hidden primary server. And in the past, they also had to reach out
to all of the other servers to make the corresponding change. So every secondary had to know that
you've added a new zone so that it could know about the data. Catalog zones take care of
all of that for me. So now when I stand up a new secondary server, I only have to tell
it which catalog zones it's supposed to pay attention to and which server those are supposed
to come from. And then it automatically populates its secondary zone list all by itself. And
it's automatically updated every time I add or remove zones. It takes, I don't know, a
minute maybe for all of them to be updated and everything is happy. It's really fantastic.
So there's going to be more cool stuff we're going to do with that in the future. So step
0, 1, 2, 3, 4, put them all together. That first one is the most important thing. Go
find out what your domain registrar supports. If they don't give you the tools you need
to be able to do this, you're going to have to move your domains to a different registrar
or give up. Those are obviously two choices, equally valid. But there are lots and lots
and lots of really good ones out there, different parts of the world. So it's easy enough to
find out. There's a very short list of things you need to be able to do. The biggest things
are the DS record is probably going to be the first thing to check. Will they let you
upload DS records for your own zones? If they won't, you're dead. You can't do DNS with
your zones and that registrar. You have to switch to somebody else. The one I currently
use supports both IPv4 and IPv6 glue records, but only IPv4 through the web interface. IPv6
has to be done via support ticket, which is annoying, but it doesn't change very often,
so I'm willing to live with that pain. So decide which off-server software you want
to use. Obviously, that's going to be an important decision for you. Decide where you want to
put all the stuff, where you want it to live, both the hidden primary and all the secondaries,
and then how are you going to manage the zone list. And as you can see there, if your answers
happen to follow that category, you can do exactly what I did and be on your way.
Now a little bit of bonus here. I did write that as a question. I forgot I changed it.
So on those network appliances in our home network, I run the recursive resolver for
all of the clients on the home network to use to resolve names. And with our last ISP,
we had more outages than I would have liked to have. And once you start setting up something
like this, you forget the IP addresses for all of your own infrastructure. You only know
the names. And when you've made the zone signed and your resolvers can't reach the internet,
they can't resolve any of the names because they can't, in my case, my domain is km6g.us,
so they have to know what's signed at the root, what's signed at the US, what's signed
at all that stuff. So we would have very bizarre cases where things inside the network stopped
working because our internet link was not working correctly, even though the things
we were trying to use didn't use the internet at all. They just couldn't talk to each other
because they couldn't resolve names. So now I have the resolvers sitting right with an
authoritative server sitting right next to them that hosts all of our zones that nothing
talks to except the resolver so that even if that box can't talk to the internet, it
can still resolve any of our internal names with no problems at all. An additional thing
there, I think again to the... What's that? I am, yeah. So what happens here is a feature
in the PowerDS Recursor, which I will say, on a bationally, I wrote, which is that you
can actually tell the auth server to send notifies to their recursors, which is not
something you would think would have ever... I mean, that's something that's normal. It's
really cool though because what we do is when that happens, the recursors says, aha, that's
a notification from the authoritative server that any content I might have in my cache
for that zone is probably stale. Throw it all away. So that means if I've got internal
infrastructure changes, I've moved a container to a different machine and its IP address
has changed, within a minute, everything that needs to use that will get the correct address
as long as it's not running a local cache on the box itself. And then, as I said, over-engineering,
I used anycast and OSPF and all kinds of other stuff to reach the recursors resolver. So
there's a bunch of links. The slides are up on the FOSDEM website, so feel free to download
them. All of these links are useful and you can see even the HTTPS thing, which is not
even a... What's that? No code collection. Oh, you're right. I forgot to put that link
in there. Tell me where it is and I'll add it. Yeah. And that's that. I have two and
a half minutes left. So questions. Yes, sir. You said you wanted to be required to change
DS records. For anyone else who wants to do this, please note that some TLDs require you
to send up the DNS key record and they will hash it to DS. Oh, okay. So he just missed
me a comment that depending on which TLD your zones are under, you may have to send a different
thing for them depending on exactly what they want from you. So that's fine. Thank you.
Don't fight. Yes, that one. Just another comment. Some TLDs are scanning for CDS, CBMP and CDS
records, so you don't have to play with the registrar at all. Right. Emerging technology
that's been around for a really long time. Yeah, so just... So I had just to repeat that
there are some top level domains, not related to the registrar, that will actually notice
the correct type of records in your zone and pick up the keys from there so that you don't
even have to manually update them when you change them or rotate them. Yes. Yes. You
can use the robust infrastructure, but you still use only one DNS software. That's a
good point. I have diversity and robust infrastructure, but no diversity in the software. That's
absolutely a good point. I'm okay with that risk though. Yes, sir.
After you ensure you are not under attack on your virtual machine, you have applied
all CV updates. So how do I ensure that I'm not under attack on the virtual machines and
how do I apply CV updates? So because of I'm a geek every Saturday morning before my wife
gets up, I run this gigantic Ansible playbook that goes and touches everything and applies
all package updates and reboots, anything that needs to be rebooted and all of that
sort of thing. So I'm reasonably good there. Plus on the public facing machines, I have
the Debian unattended upgrade thing in place so that if a really important thing gets a
package update comes in and gets applied, it will do it for itself. So I don't have
to restart that. What was the other question? What was the other part of that one? Oh, the
attack thing. This is really cool. Those particular AWS VMs have a hard cap on the amount of CPU
that they're allowed to use. So if somebody tries to do a DOS attack on them, they just
stop getting responses. So I don't have to do anything. Now granted, that resolution
of my zones would be harmed by that. But these are personal zones. We're not hitting them
all that hard from outside. So that's kind of a neat feature that is just a side effect
of the way those particular VMs work, is you're limiting how much CPU you can use. Are we
out? All right. Thank you.