Tell me when.
Five more seconds.
Okay.
This stuff makes the video cutting process so much easier if we stick to the schedule.
You can go ahead.
Good afternoon everybody.
Thank you for having me here.
Let me start from a short introduction of what Internet of Threats means.
What is an end node of the Internet?
So, which are the communicating nodes of the Internet?
The legacy approach of what is at the beginning, it was the Internet of Hosts.
Internet of Threats were given to each controller.
So, actually the communication took place, takes place between the controllers of hosts.
Nowadays, this concept has been made wider and the network endpoints are virtual controllers of virtual machines or even in spaces.
Internet of Threats is one step further.
It means that we want even just processes, even threads within processes as nodes as in the end zone.
The idea is to give IP addresses, actually IPv6 address, we wouldn't have as many IPv4 address as we need to threads or processes.
The idea can be depicted from this.
Long time ago there were fixed lines and really the telephone number was connected to a place, a room.
It was common to call a number and say, it is Jack Tom.
Nowadays, we use portable phones and the numbers are connected to or mapped to people.
It is very easy.
What do we look for?
We don't look for controllers, we look for services.
The most natural way is to have IP addresses connected to the process with providing that service, not controllers or machines.
The network stack is just a layer between API to the application layer and the API to the data link layer.
Actually, these are two layers, layer three and four of the other stack.
But anyway, it is a slice in the middle.
This implementation is currently most of the time deeply inside the kernel of the machine of the computer you are using.
But it can be seen as a library.
This library can be linked to a user process and this way the user process can directly talk with the network.
We made one further step to this implementation using the libi library for the Internet of Threads.
It is not a library that implements a stack, it is a framework library that allows to load actual implementation for network stacks as plugins.
It provides a unified API to the applications. In such a way, it is possible to run applications that can use either the kernel stack or any implementation of the network stack as a library.
Actually, the actual implementation permits to change the implementation just by changing a string.
The actual stack supported by libi are the kernel stack, woody stack, which is actually a trick.
It is a namespace using a top inside the namespace.
We are borrowing the kernel stack using it at user level. Then a real implementation of user level TCP IP stacks like PicoTCP, the module is named PicoX,
and a working process where I am working to port lightweight IP to this port.
What do we need in the API?
There is a way to communicate. This is quite known, and this is the standard way we use the stack. Open, close communication, point, center. For all of these, there are back-to-sockets.
But it is not common. If you use the kernel stack, you have, as guaranteed, as provided, the definition of the stack as a configuration parameter of the stack,
like which are the API address, which are the routing definitions, and so on. We need to add this support for the API.
The definition of stack needed some syntax, some specific syntax. When using the API, a new stack is created.
It is a pointer to a specific structure that can be used for communication. The only difference for the socket API is that instead of using socket,
there is a new call named MSocket, which has one further parameter, which is the actual stack implementation to use.
And then there are all the other API calls, well-known from Berkeley sockets.
But we needed to create a new stack, so in such a way to do that, we used those calls we have seen two years ago, and the pointer can be used for communication.
And what about configuration? For configuration, there is an RFC used, for example, by the Knynyos kernel, that uses the Addis family netlink to provide messages for configuring the network.
So there is no need of further API entry for configuration. We just need that our stack support AF netlink configuration.
Another point about these sockets, using forum sockets, if it is a library level implementation of the stack, the problem is that this integer could be an internal number of the library.
Instead, we need the thing to be a real file descriptor, because we need the file descriptor to be used, for example, for Paul's socket.
And we have to write a new kernel module in the library, named Vupala, that creates a file descriptor in which the elements can be synthesized.
And so, stack implemented at user level, as a library, can provide real file descriptor, and this file descriptor can be used on select, so on.
So we can use real file descriptor, file descriptor coming from different implementations of the network, and write M and DREAM program altogether.
Just a quick look to give you the feeling of what does it mean.
This is a program just sending a child using a diagram.
This is the legacy way.
This is the same example using internal threads.
Just by changing this string, I can use an implementation I want, provided I have support for that.
Okay, now the core of the presentation, we need an ecosystem around this idea.
A lot of stuff that we currently have in our toolset, but we need them implemented as internal threads.
We need a cause to configure the network.
These are not codes of the internal threads implementation of the library.
These codes generate NetLink messages, so it can be used even for configuring the current stack directly from a program.
Let us pass quickly through this.
We need a library to query for DNS.
Why? Because using the Clib implementation, it uses the kernel stack,
and it uses the definitions in etc.result.conf, and the string etc.result.conf is arc coded in the Clib code.
It is not possible to change even the file to be used.
We designed a proxy for word cache, especially for the internal threads, which are the characteristics of this DNS.
It uses the internal threads, so it can be used for receiving queries or for wording queries, different stacks defined by the user.
But at the same time, they can provide further features specifically useful for the internal threads.
Let us pass through the configuration items, but I prefer to show you some scenarios in which the IOS NMD can be used.
This is a common scenario, a common proxy scenario, like libmasq or similar, but implemented using internal threads.
If we ask the proxy an address provided by a foreign node, we can cache the result and provide it back to the queryer.
Or we can add some specific local addresses. It does not provide a relay from external queryer.
The point is that we have a stack for the query and a stack to forward the query outside.
In this case, in this configuration, I provide the service to all the processes connected to this stack,
and I forward the queries on another different stack with a different implementation.
This is another test just to see that it is able to resolve foreign and local results.
Or it can be used as a delegated subdomain.
It is providing forwarding, defining this pink server as the responsible to the server, dumb, mature, and so on.
It provides back the solution.
Here, the new point is that we can use different stack.
I kept it some time to show you some more ideas. Actually, managing DNS servers for IPv6 is a daunting process,
but it is very error-prone because if you have to write all those huge, long numbers,
it is very hard to not insert errors in the configuration.
That is to create IPv6 addresses using hash code, hash resolution,
using the result of a hash function defined on the full-defined domain name.
This is the host part of IPv6 address for free.
This is the proxy, as in the previous example, the first example.
I can ask the server to solve all the addresses like something hash.local.
I can use any string before hash.local and I get a name resolution.
That means that if I add a new node, which can be a computer or even a process, I just have to baptize it,
to give it a name, and it will be connected on the net without having to write any single line in the DNS server.
The slides are on the website, so if you want to pass through and download the prototype from GitHub, you can test this.
The same things can be done wherever we run, so having a delegated domain that results addresses using hashes.
So we can have a number of local machines that can be seen from the Internet just by giving them a name.
But there is one more result, which is One-Time IP. One-Time IP is a security feature, like a One-Time Password.
One-Time Password means that you have a password that lasts for a short period of time, so if somebody is able to ice-drop the password, it gets useless in a few moments.
The first part of the address is defined by a hash definition that changes during the time.
It is not only the name of the fully qualified domain name, but it includes a password and a time.
So if the legitimate user wants to connect to the server, it knows which is the actual IP address.
Any other user, even if it is able to trace the network traffic, it gets some addresses that will be null in a few seconds.
I think I have no time to show the five minutes, which means time for questions.
We have four minutes left including questions.
Just one point, and then I go to the question.
Name the ACP is another tool which uses DHCP server, but these DHCP servers query the DNS to provide the address to the computer, not the processor whatsoever.
You can just say to your computer, which is the name, and the resolution is provided.
The definition of all the network in configuration is provided, getting replies from the DNS server.
I have to stop. I would have a lot of more examples to give you.
Questions?
What is the overhead of using a different network stack in every thread, especially if you are using the one-time IPs for each connection?
What is the overhead that you get within the application if you have a lot of connections coming in?
For sure, on single connections we have some performance drop.
The point is that the overall bandwidth by all the applications you have on your system can use the entire bandwidth.
You have the experience that you spread democratically, the bandwidth among your processors.
Questions?
What about latency?
Is latency a factor?
The point is that behind the user level stack there is a virtual network, which is virtual distributed internet,
that uses a support like VXVD, which is like VXLAN without VTAP.
Each process is part of the distributed space.
You have a direct UDP connection, a UNICAS connection from end to end, from a processor in one machine to the other.
There is a direct UDP one-to-one.
My idea is to have a new concept of computing elements.
Instead of having your computer read the process, you have a local network of a cluster of computers with all the processors,
which are nodes of different networks.
You have the real network, which is just the basic framework, and you extract this in a number of virtual networks
that connect the processors running in which physical node you like.
That's all the time we have. Thank you, Renzo.