So, actually, I'm going to talk about three subjects, Connect My Name, ProxicoTroll option,
and also a little bit of Rust throw-in at the end as a bonus.
So my name is Philip Holmberg, and since a bit more than a year, I now work for NLnet
Labs.
So the question that has probably been posed by many people is, can you have just a function
that in comes a hostname and a service, and you get a socket back?
And sort of the starting point for this project, because we've got some funding, so we officially
defined that, as Michael Abersom in the ITF one suggested, that some things like that
should be done.
Then of course we want to have options, so we can have a slightly more modern version
where you have a context as the first thing, and it returns an error code instead of overloading
that with a socket, but general idea.
Of course, this is completely bad because this is blocking.
This is what we need to down-front.
Unfortunately, because we only at NLnet Lab basically do DNS when it comes to name resolution,
this talk ignores every other possible thing.
We don't even do MDNS, but we definitely don't do anything fancy.
But it should not be precluded.
If people want to add it, why not?
So to make it non-blocking, the obvious way to extend it is to take an event framework
like libevent, and then in libevent speak it as well.
You create an event base, you do a bit of initialization where you pass the event base
to the asynchronous library function.
You start it, it returns to say, well, okay, I'm busy.
Then at some point it does a couple of callbacks, like this callback function that you pass,
but the main loop is called event-based dispatch.
As long as your entire application is written around it, then the application just calls
this one, and then you can call this connect by name as many times as you like.
If you want to make this practical, more complex, and do release engineering, for example, getDNS
has support for, I think, three event frameworks, and you can define your own event framework
and stuff like that.
I'll ignore this.
The only thing you're going to get here is libevent.
There's a couple of practical things that we would like to add.
So now we get a rather full slide.
So far I said you get a socket back.
Implicitly a socket back means TCP because your DPA is way too complex.
But then in practice, who does TCP anymore?
The thing is if you have a TCP socket, then you immediately call your SSL library and
you want a TLS connection.
At least I hope that people are not writing new code that ships unencrypted data over
the internet.
Within the pfent, you're lucky because they have a concept called buffer event.
That's why the callback there gets a buffer event.
The pfent can transparently do SSL.
So you just read and write to the buffer event, and then the pfent will, if it knows that
it is TLS, then it sends it to openSSL.
And if it's just a normal TCP connection, then it sends it to the socket.
So that solves that problem, and that allows the library to also do a couple of other interesting
things, as we will see on the other slide.
But because we are an organization that is focused on DNS, we focused on all of the complexity
of stuff that you can do with DNS.
So for example, one thing that the library does, I forgot to mention, is that if you
get multiple addresses back, then the traditional way is you write a for loop, you do connect
to the first address and then to the second address, and there's many minutes' time out
on the TCP connection.
So if the first address doesn't work, then it takes forever.
So your library needs to do happy eyeballs such that you start the connect, wait not
that long, and then start the next connect, which also means that any timer system is
not in the order of seconds.
It should be definitely in the order of milliseconds, because it should be within human response
levels and not like, okay, the network is down, we wait seconds.
So that is stuff that this library can hide and that the prototype also does.
But to get to the DNS part, if you have a modern web browser, then the web browser has
an option to configure DNS, and that's highly controversial because it goes over HTTP, but
it's something where applications have now said, okay, we are done with et cetera, resolve.com
and application point of view want to be able to do, decide which is our upstream resolver.
So we added configuration options that you can say, well, I want to have an upstream
resolver that has authenticated encryption.
I don't really like QUIC, and I have no clue, so I said the only allowed transport protocols
is plain old DNS over 53, which will always fail because it cannot do any encryption,
but we do allow DNS over TCP, and we do allow DNS over HTTP, but none of the fancy QUIC
things.
We have a name for authentication, and of course we can go completely overboard and
also do SVC parameters.
So that extends the call a bit because now the context has a way that you can say, well,
this is my DNS policy, and then it goes out and do it.
I mean, basic interface is still more or less the same.
So we worked on connect by name.
We built a prototype, a grant from an LNET foundation.
We support asynchronous resolution.
Well, of course, asynchronous also means that your A or what A query should go in parallel,
happy eyeballs.
Then, of course, the DNS community invented Dane.
So if you do TLS, then you also have to do the Dane query immediately, and I forgot to
list here.
You can also do SVCB, and if you have the patience to configure experimental open SSL
libraries, you can also do the encrypted client hello from SVCB into open SSL and stuff like
that.
The nice thing is you can all hide it in a single library.
So what I would like from the community is sort of one is sort of what doesn't work,
what extra stuff that we need.
But we also have a problem with how do we go further with this.
I mean, we built a prototype, but we cannot really ourselves make it into a product for
various reasons.
So take a look at it if you're interested and let us know if you want to do something.
Current problem for me is it's on top of get DNS.
The DNS is an extremely nice library, but it tries to do everything, so it's also a
very heavyweight library.
So there it is like it's a library that you want to link with potentially all applications
should it be that heavyweight.
So that's how we got to the next subject.
This is sort of now what the ITF has created as what a stops resolver should do.
And I left out a casellian other things because ADD is busy and I don't know, there's probably
quite a few other working groups.
So the stop resolver, which was a very simple thing with a res send that sends a query over
port 53, has to do more and more and more stuff.
So many applications have a stop resolver.
How many libraries will implement all of those transports, especially if it's also implemented
in this way of languages.
It used to be that the stop resolver had basically no state, but if you do the OT, the OA, the
UQ, then you have connection set up.
You generate load in a recursive resolver because if you're constantly setting up, say,
the OT, the OT connections, then it has a way higher load than if it's just a simple
UDP query.
And it's definitely bad for short-lived applications like Bing that have a way higher overhead
setting up a connection to the local recursive resolver than the actual work that the application
is doing.
So the simple way to solve that, we thought, you introduce a local proxy.
That's not really something new because lots of people are unbound as a local DNS proxy.
Well, we also, as part of the GetDNS project created at Stirby, that focuses more on doing
DNS stack all the time.
There is things like DNS dist, DNS mask, systemd, resolve d.
So that looks like, okay, we don't have to worry about that.
We can just talk to a local proxy.
But then if we go back to the example config, I had for Connect by Name for the Firefox
that wants to talk DOH.
How do you tell your local proxy that you actually want to have an authenticated connection?
Well, what if your proxy is just sending it, I don't know, to one of the public resolvers
over port 53?
Maybe that's not what your application wants.
And then this local proxy ID falls down and you get, say, a browser again implementing
its own sub-resolver because it doesn't have any control.
So we thought about it for a while and created a draft in the ITF with a new edns0 option.
And basically when you send the request to your step resolver, then you can encode all
of the stuff that you want to have as a policy in such an option.
So you can be very basic and set a flag like, well, only give me an authenticated connection.
If you can't do it and just report like it doesn't work or you could say, well, this
is the recursive resolver that I want you to use, please use that.
And then applications can trust the local proxy because they can control it.
And that provides a nice way to basically reduce the step resolver footprint a bit by
moving all of the difficult transports to the proxy.
We have a proof of concept for that, though I have to warn you that we revised the layout
of the option in the draft that is listed here and what the proof concept does is an
older draft.
But if you want to play with it with the general concept, then that is there.
Finally, so we decided that, well, we can continue writing code in C and of course for
our existing products like Unbound, NSD, we will just maintain them in C because they
are written in C. But we would like to try to move to a draft
for new code.
And I just copied a little bit of stuff from a prototype.
First thing, uses Rust in creative ways.
And that is something where it's now a prototype and we definitely need feedback from users
of the library.
Like, okay, it's very great that you can have a message builder that takes a static compressor
type and it has a stream target, but probably you don't want to write code like that.
So it's built at the moment to be flexible and use the language, but it should be somewhere
modified to be more usable.
Then here in the middle, you basically get the main thing because the whole thing is
generic if you want to send a query, then you have to go to the question section and
then you say, well, I want to push a question there.
And then there is again a bit of a usability problem where you say, okay, I need this back
to a builder and I need a clone of it.
So then, so this is the part that I experimented with.
If you want to have a TCP upstream, then you say, create the TCP connection.
And the nice thing with Rust is that it can do all of the asynchronous stuff with a nice
syntax.
So basically you say, do this connect here and wait until the connect is done.
But because this function is implicitly asynchronous, as a programmer, you can just write this as
if it's sequential code, but the caller can just call this as an asynchronous function
and you don't have to do anything extra.
Here I have to do a bit more work to really figure out how it fits in the Rust ecosystem
because the thing with, if you have a TCP connection upstream to a DNS resolver, and
I wanted to have this as just a basics for maybe DOH or whatever, is that you want to
set up the connection once, but then you want to potentially send many queries over it.
So I need to have a separate thing that actually talks TCP as a worker thread, but then because
it's all asynchronous, this is basically getting an asynchronous worker.
And then I also say, well, give me an asynchronous query.
And then in Rust, you can say, okay, you have two asynchronous things that you want to do
at the same time.
Just do them both at the same time.
And then normally we expect to be here that we got a reply and then we print a reply and
we are done.
So this is sort of the direction we want to go to, which is also why we have a bit of
a problem developing the connect by name prototype that we now have because it is like, okay,
we don't really want to have a new prototype in C. What do we want to do with it?
So that's what I wanted to tell today.
There is I think plenty of space for questions.
I love the idea of having a function which can deal with not just name a resolution,
but DNS name a resolution and also the cryptography.
But as a distribution maintainer, I have to say that having something, a library function
which makes applications behave differently from all other applications is really a non-starter.
So I think that you need to consider in some way to support the NSS and the NSS plugins
through the libc or however it's better.
You mentioned that probably a daemon is needed to get good performance.
So maybe the DNS part is the less important one that you can delegate to some other component.
Can you summarize?
I'll try to summarize.
You say there's something with distributing this and there is something with if you run
a local proxy, then you don't have to focus as much on DNS.
If I got that correct.
I mean, there are already some projects in this space that you mentioned and they are
expected to work with the normal libc NSS plugins.
And I think that your application, sorry, your library to be universally used, I think
that has to be your goal.
You need to support the normal name resolution, which is expected by any applications.
So it does to support the libc plugins.
So basically, yeah, you say that the library will only be adopted if it supports the libc
plugins.
Yes, I agree.
I mean, that's why we made the prototype because we were looking into what should the interface
to the library be, how should the library behave, stuff like that, sort of the high
level stuff.
I'm fully expecting that any production quality implementation of the library has to take
a lot of this stuff into account and certainly dealing with Nesbitch.conf is, I guess, mandatory
for any production quality library.
For the proxy control option, because there are lots of demons in that space, of course,
it's best if those adopt the option once it is actually standardized by the ITF.
I mean, it's not that we want to write another proxy.
It's just like, okay, we have a very specific problem that we want to solve if we want to
make stuff resolve for a small and still give them access to all of the encrypted transports.
But yeah, if, for example, systemd resolve would also do the proxy control option, then
that would be perfectly fine.
I mean, there's no reason to write a new one.
Leonard is around, don't worry.
Yeah.
So for the proxy control option, is it only the stuff resolved that won't sell the proxy
server that it wants those policies applied or does the proxy also communicate back to
the stuff resolved that is actually applying those policies?
Because in the initial situation where nothing supports it, which you always have.
So the question is, what happens if you send a proxy control option to an older stuff resolver
that may not be aware?
So I didn't want to go over the entire draft.
So we thought about that.
But basically there are some priming queries.
I forgot the exact name.
Is it resolver dot arpa that is proposed?
Something like that.
So try to look up resolver dot arpa, see if you get the right response.
If you don't, then the only thing you leaked is that you were trying to look up resolver
dot arpa.
So you assume that that is safe.
If you do get it, then you know that the proxy understands it.
Yeah.
Any more questions?
Okay.
Yeah.
So there's actually a comment on both this presentation and the previous one.
You're tackling three moving targets at the same time.
You're trying to figure out how to integrate with the event loop.
You're trying to figure out what your API to the application looks like.
And you need to figure out what your integration with an SS or system.
The complexity is multiplicative.
So you're cubing this.
This is a horrible idea.
You can at least remove the event loop integration as a moving target.
There's an existing project called libderto which tries to solve that one problem by providing
four libraries an API to integrate with an arbitrary event loop provided by the application.
So I think you need to remove the number of moving targets, like reduce it, and maybe
the event loop is the one to kick out first and try to put in a separate consideration
how to solve that, and then continue from there.
And if they left.
Yeah.
So the question was basically it tries to deal with too much stuff at the same time.
Event loops, figuring out an API and then also figuring out how to deal with an S switch.
There's an existing library called libderto.
That makes it easier to be flexible with respect to event loops.
That's definitely a good point.
I'll try to look at it.
But I specifically decided to only focus on libd
event to just get Ferto.
To get something a prototype up and running and not try to support arbitrary things like
that.
More questions?
Some more time.
Time for one more.
Okay.
It seems that we have run out of questions.
Wonderful.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.