Welcome to the final talk.
Wow.
So lots of people want to know where to go from here.
Welcome Clayton Craft.
We are really happy his plane made it barely despite that weather and all that.
So some might know him as Crafty Guy in some chat rooms.
Well, I don't need to introduce you here.
So welcome and yeah, happy to have you here.
Thank you.
Yeah, so I'm Clayton, also known as Crafty Guy.
You might recognize me from some of my contributions to post-market OS.
Or you might recognize me from my avatar, right?
No?
I started contributing to this distribution back in 2017.
Mainly because it had initial support for the Nokia N900,
which was the first Linux phone I owned.
And by 2017, I was really tired of the two options for mobile operating systems.
I wanted something that could run a recent Linux kernel that had a familiar user space
and most importantly wasn't trying to like exfiltrate personal information all the time.
And I still feel that way today, which is why I'm here,
because I think that we as a community need to try to answer the question,
where do we go from here?
Because here today, the situation is quite a bit different
and has improved in some ways from the last few years.
For example, there's a number of phones out there now that can run Linux,
some of them out of the box, which is really exciting.
However, when you look at how many phones exist out in the world today,
there's thousands and thousands of them, and only like a small handful can do this.
So I think there's some improvement there, obviously.
There's also a lot more distributions, both Linux and, as you saw in the previous talk,
other alternative operating systems that can boot on these phones.
However, I think there's not a whole lot of coordination between distributions today,
because a lot of these distributions are targeting the same hardware.
They also are targeting some of the same use cases.
And so a lot of them are trying to solve some of the same problems
and have some of the same goals.
And a lot of distributions are kind of doing it on their own
and not really comparing notes and trying to work collaboratively to solve these things
in cases where the work being done to solve the problem
could be used by multiple distros, for instance.
And another exciting thing I think today is there's a lot more applications
that have been created, both with some of the work from Purism
and other folks in the community that lets these applications work pretty well
on mobile form factors.
However, when you consider non-technical end-users
and what they expect for a modern smartphone,
there's still a lot of missing functionality there.
So again, more room for improvement.
And I think there's a lot of people, both inside and outside the community,
who are really interested in what we're doing.
And I think a lot of them are kind of asking the same questions.
Specifically, one question I think everybody's asking,
no matter who you are, is what's it like, right?
What's it like to have a phone that can run Linux and use it as a daily driver?
What's it like to depend on that for navigation and communication?
And obviously, whoever's asking this is...
The answer to that question depends a lot on who's asking it
and where they're coming from.
For example, an end-user, when they ask, hey, what's it like to use your phone
that's running Linux, they want to know, can they message grandma on WhatsApp,
or can they use it to navigate from your hotel to the FOSITM conference,
and stuff like that.
I think myself as an OS developer, when I think about this question,
I tend to think about a lot of the problems I run into
with developing and maintaining an operating system on Linux phones,
and how a lot of these problems, again, are shared between distributions
because, again, we're targeting a lot of the same hardware and use cases.
And I think about how hard it is today to create or solve problems
that can be reused by other distributions without a whole lot of rework on their part.
A good recent example of this is a Libram 5 user, Chris Vogel, last week
was trying to work around a problem on the Libram 5,
and he created some patches for this work around, submitted them to Purism,
and I actually just happened to come across the patches
because I was trying to address the same problem on post-market OS.
And his patches look good from the context of pure OS,
but they were pretty much unusable for me on post-market OS
because of just differences in the distribution, right?
His patches were relying heavily on systemd services
in order to trigger things to apply workarounds,
and I don't have systemd in post-market OS,
so that was a non-starter right there.
I was able to talk to him and give some tips on how he could redo it
so that it would work across multiple distributions, even ones without systemd.
And I think this is kind of like the current happy situation
where he's off creating something now that could be reused, right?
But I think there's a lot of cases where, because people don't know
there's other distributions or know what they need,
oftentimes people run into problems like this
and they create something which works totally fine for them,
but is not usable or not even known to other distributions with the same problems, right?
So, like, I might end up recreating or redoing a lot of the work,
and it's inefficient, right?
I would rather spend the time not solving problems
that have already been solved elsewhere,
but adding new functionality or supporting users
who are using the distribution that I'm helping to develop.
And I think we need a number of things as a community
in order to address some of these inefficiencies
with maintaining distributions that target a lot of the same hardware
and use cases.
It would be really nice if, like, in that previous situation
I just spoke about, there was a place for a developer
like Chris or myself or anyone, right,
to ask for feedback directly from the community
and be fairly confident that they're reaching, like, you know,
critical mass of the community, right?
And also where distributions can sort of, like, provide this feedback.
So when people do solve problems that they're experiencing
or when people are trying to implement things
that they could really use,
that they have the opportunity to provide feedback,
and, you know, the person doing the work can take or leave the feedback
but at least know that they're getting input or have access to this input
so they can create something that's usable by everyone,
and we don't have these cases where people are just kind of one-off
doing the same thing, right?
I think it would also be really nice if we had, as a community,
a list of priorities that we care about, both, like, goals
and also, like, these shared problems.
The main purpose of this is, like, when contributors come along
and they want something to work on or not sure what to do,
they could see this list of priorities,
and, you know, if we come up with it as a community,
we can put stuff up there we care about, obviously,
and when people choose to work on these priorities,
then we all benefit, right,
because they're working on things that we said are important to us.
And so, you know, maybe they'll provide some motivation
or inspiration for folks that want to contribute
and aren't necessarily certain how.
And I think by kind of addressing the first two things,
we'll inherently create stronger relationships within the community,
right, between individuals and projects,
and I think that these strong relationships are critical.
Like, if we want to have any chance of convincing, you know,
businesses or governments or what have you,
or even just end users, right, like,
if I want to try to convince, you know,
a new group of users or something to give this a shot,
we need to be somewhat organized
and have an idea for, like, what we're trying to accomplish
and be able to communicate that well externally
so people know what we're all about.
And these strong relationships, I think, are necessary for that,
and, I mean, it's great, like, meeting people here at Fozoom,
but it's, like, very one-off, right,
and we need to maintain that,
and I think we maintain that by better organizing
and, you know, trying to implement some of the things here
I think we need.
So I'm here to propose forming a committee.
I'm not even sure if committee is the right word for this,
but bottom line is we need to somehow be more organized than we are.
Not necessarily, like, you know,
dictoral or anything like that, but in some ways,
at a higher level, just addressing, like, you know,
having a place for people to get feedback,
and I think a committee or some central place
where distributions and projects are represented
could be a place like that.
I also think, like, as a developer,
I'm not necessarily, like, the greatest at communicating
when I'm working on and, like,
what my motivations are for working on this
and what Linux on mobile or Free Software on mobile
will have to offer.
So I think we should also, like, work on our public representation
and having a committee or whatever you want to call it
be sort of the single point for communicating to the world
what we're doing and why we want to do it would be important.
Like, I know why I'm here, right?
I don't want to have a corporate centralized device
that's leaking personal information,
and I want the freedom to hack on this thing
and, you know, do what I want, more or less.
But again, I think a lot of us are developers,
engineers, and we're not necessarily, like,
the best at communicating that to non-technical users specifically.
So I think, you know, having some central thing
where we can kind of work together to create something
that can educate the world about us is, you know, nice to have.
Now, I know what you're thinking, like,
who is this guy?
Why would I want some oversight committee thing,
like authority telling me what I can and can't work on
during my free time?
Because I know a lot of people here, myself included,
are working on this during our free time.
And, yeah, the last thing I wanted somebody to be like,
here's the priorities for you.
You know, when are you going to have them done by?
Because that's silly.
And I completely agree that's not the purpose of this.
And the point is, I don't really know what this looks like
when it organizes, but I think we need to organize.
And I created a working group.
There's a link to the matrix room on the slide
where I would invite everybody here,
everybody listening online, everybody in this community
to join in, and let's figure out how we can become more organized.
And, oh, I'd like to thank my employer, Agalia,
for sponsoring my travel to come here to give this talk.
And, yeah, any questions, comments, opinions?
Pretty short talk, but...
APPLAUSE
Nothing? Speechless.
Yeah, go ahead.
I was wondering if it's really such a centralized thing
because somehow some mechanism to find,
to find for some issue in other projects
to look at, which might have the issue in common
because you might, for the first time,
copy very different projects.
For example, I start working on the Amazon Uber,
the 200, the glasses, and there are people interested in having a new Android
or something like that on it.
And a common thing needed for both,
for whoever should be put on it, is to how to really start hacking it,
how to access, start something, put something on it, and so on.
So maybe there has to be some metrics,
some network built up along which corners issues should travel,
or should manually check if there is some, if that issue is also...
So if I enter an issue, I would like to somehow get a list of other projects
where it might also be a event, maybe for issue to find things out,
or maybe to find some partners for mainlining stuff, or so on.
Maybe there's some...
Yeah, that's one of the motivations for why I spent way too much time thinking about this.
For problems like that that exist across distributions and whatever,
it would be nice to know about that.
If you're also trying to work on supporting a new device
or improving something in your distro,
and you want to know if other people have had this problem,
and right now it's like you have to know what other distros are out there
who might be working on this thing, and then know where to find information,
and then go search a million different GitLab instances or whatever to figure out,
is this a problem that other people have seen or not?
It's kind of a mess, right?
And the same goes for a lot of other problems I've come across.
So yeah, that's the idea, right?
Have kind of a central place where people can...
Where problems like that can be expressed,
and people who are working on them, no matter what distribution you're in,
can work together on these things.
Yes?
Q&A question?
Yeah, that's tricky, right?
Because in the desktop world,
there's some focus towards Flatpak and other ways to package the runtime,
so then it kind of doesn't matter what the distro is, right?
Because you can reuse the same runtime,
you can try your application, and you target that thing.
I don't know if that's right for us, but that specific thing,
but I agree there should be a way that people can talk about these things
within these distributions we have.
And I think there's a fine line.
We don't necessarily want to try to...
I like that there's a lot of distributions,
and I like that they're all doing their own thing, right?
Because Post Market OS was started by Ollie for a very specific reason,
and people started Mobian because they wanted to run Debian on their device,
and there's less focus on what the runtimes are there,
but I think it's a good thing that there's so much distro diversity
or whatever within the community,
and I wouldn't really want to try to shoehorn any particular runtime mechanism
or whatever you want to call it.
On the other hand, I know it's hard for application developers, right?
Like as you said.
On the distro plans, for example, you can expect it to have some like you
or GTK or something, and this still is not a given on the
one we got very, very close to.
So would it be nice if you had a way to ask distributions like,
hey, what version of GTK are you running or something, right?
And be able to get input directly from them.
So that way, at least you know like there's the minimum version I need to support.
And I know it's not the ideal situation where you just like support whatever you want,
but yeah, basically the idea is like you'd be able to go and say,
hey, Linux mobile distros, I want to target this version of GTK 4 for this application.
If you care about this application, is there like a version I should look at targeting or something?
And so today, if you wanted to do that, you'd have to like,
you'd have to know what all the distros are that might be interested in using this thing you want to create.
And then you need to know how to contact them.
And even when you do, the people who have an opinion might not even be online
or you know, might not be available or maybe ask the wrong person or something.
So it's not great, right?
See, what I'm proposing is like have a way that you could ask for feedback from all the folks in the community.
And people who care about what you're doing can be like, yeah, here's the version I use.
Or like maybe, you know, maybe this person is like representing their distro
and they take it back to the person who knows that's working on their distro
and then they, you know, give you the answer back or whatever.
So it's a way to convey information basically to and from people who are interested in, you know, solving those problems.
Yes?
I like that you mentioned public representation. I'm not that technical and I'm here out of interest because I have to go with my time and install itself and all these things.
I think that's a very important aspect actually, the public representation.
And also to make the importance of this much more known.
Yeah, sure. I mean, I get reminded daily, right?
My wife's like, what are you working on exactly?
And I'm like, oh, some phone stuff, you know.
But I know like there's a lot of people, friends, family, whatever who have tried to search online for like what this Linux mobile thing or free software mobile thing is all about.
And they tend to see like, you know, post by people and projects who are the loudest talking about what they're doing specifically, but not like what the whole thing is about.
And yeah, so like if a business or you or somebody is interested, you kind of just get like this hodgepodge collection of information and it's hard to like figure out what exactly is going on here.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, thanks for proving my point.
Yes.
Yeah, I mean, depending on how.
No, no, no.
Desktop Linux is what I call it. I don't know. There's yeah, you know, like Red Hat and canonical and those folks who are doing desktop and server distributions.
Those are those communities are kind of dominated by certain companies, right, who are out there to make a product and sell support and sell services and sell products and whatever.
We don't I mean there are some OEMs who are doing stuff that are selling products purism is the obvious one.
But we don't really have any big like corporate participants in this community yet.
I honestly don't want to see that happen because I think there's there's a lot of history with trying to run this type of environment on phones.
Right. And I think that some of the past failures were due to, you know, big corporations getting involved, dumping a ton of resources in.
You could argue whether it was like, you know, done effectively or not, but then kind of just giving up when they lose interest because, you know, it didn't turn a profit as fast as they thought it would or whatever.
So, like, I don't want to recreate that. And I also realized, like, we don't have, you know, a ton of money pouring into this right now, which could be a good thing.
So, I mean, this is my attempt to like try to organize without waiting around for somebody to be like, hey, that's a business model I need to throw money at and then just overwhelming us with, you know, like one option and, you know, one or two devices and and sort of just like pigeonhole in the whole community in that way.
So I'm hoping that by bringing this discussion up now, we can kind of prevent that from happening.
And yeah, it'd be cool if like desktop Linux had something like that. But I think we're also kind of in a more unique situation, like people that want to run Linux on their desktop.
The hardware is kind of boring, right? Like it's mostly x86. It's kind of a solved problem. Every so often you'll get like a Wi-Fi module x up and like, oh, wow, you know, unsupported hardware.
But on phones, it's like, oh, wow, the whole platform doesn't work. Right. And then you kind of like start from the ground up and it's getting better as as like Luca was talking about and the work that people are doing on mainland Linux.
It's getting better with device bring up, but there's still a lot of like weird hardware out there. And so yeah, I think like a lot of the organization can benefit some of that because again, a lot of these distros are targeting some of the same hardware.
Like when you run into a problem, it's almost certainly going to be specific to like some some device model or some family of so season. So like as distros, we want to know what those problems are. So we're not having to try to solve them individually.
Hope that answered your question. Yeah.
I think there's two things proposed. And I think on one side, it's how to get ordinary users engaged.
Or like, I don't know, knowing any issues with the game. And the other side is how distros do we work together to more effectively progress, right? Or am I missing a part or? No, I think those are two things I'd like to see happen.
I think they're very much related, right? What I mean by that is, if the distros can get their shit together, then the end user experience gets better, right? I think, in my opinion, people who develop applications for distros and don't necessarily have to think too hard about the distros or can at least like, you know, get the feedback necessary to make something that works everywhere.
Gives end users more choices. They can run more distributions based on, and they may not care, right, in some cases.
But also, like, it kind of sucks using a phone and running into a problem that's like distro specific, right? And you kind of want your applications to work the same, regardless of what distro you have, right?
Because you don't want to have a phone that's running post-market OS that supports, like, you know, these applications and these features and whatnot, and then have a device running Monjaro or Mobian or something else.
And, you know, you have a different set of things that work there, and then you have, you know, another phone with some other distro on there with, you know, some different set of applications and stuff that work there.
So I think by getting all the distros kind of, you know, organized and I don't think it's just distros. I think it's also OEMs too.
And other projects that are in the community, I think, should also be a part of this as well. And by kind of getting our stuff together, then we can help with providing a more consistent experience for end users who, you know, that's what they want.
They want their phone to work.