I'm going to start with the first part.
Perfect.
Thank you.
Thank you, everyone.
All right.
So just to give a little introduction, I need to mute myself real quick.
Just to give a little introduction about myself, my name is Alfred.
Alfred Neumayer.
I've been involved with the UBports project on Ubuntu Touch for about four to close to
five years now.
And I have started out with porting devices over to Ubuntu Touch over to devices that
used to run Android kernels and Android drivers, not mainline.
I used and reused the highly bits that we made up.
And for that matter, I gained a lot of experience with the desktop later on because I started
out with the phone and I really wanted to have this tablet experience with a touchpad
and a keyboard.
I couldn't get it quite right until some later hardware offered the ability to do so.
But in the meantime, I was very interested in the desktop talk and what can we accomplish
with the desktop convergence as the keyword.
And I'm going to mention that one real quick.
Let's see if the convergence thing actually does what it's supposed to do, right?
Okay.
Black screen.
Does it stay black?
There you go.
Okay.
A fingerprint reader doesn't want to work, but this one does.
So yeah, you can actually, with Lemuria at least, you can use the phone as the virtual
touchpad and virtual keyboard just to give it a little bit more presentation feel.
We need to...
Where's the full screen?
Is there a full screen?
Do we have full screen?
Otherwise, that one is sufficient, I hope.
Right?
Yeah, that's it.
That was a really obvious waste running.
Sorry.
Broke it to you.
So the memory on the desktop, the method of the pocket size desktop.
As we can see, it is totally possible to do so considering that we're still at the starting
phase of where this really can go.
So I'm going to talk about a little bit of the history, then about the evil convergence
word, the word that we all like to use, but so many people use in so many different senses,
so many different ways, then how we migrated over a few technology pieces like the system
layer and the windowing protocol, the UI toolkit I'm going to introduce to you, and notable
components that should you be interested in either working with us or taking your stuff
and working on your own stuff, bring it over to another distro, you're totally free to
do so and I will mention a few components that you might be interested in.
So what do we have?
The history.
2013, the year of Ubuntu phone, as we hoped, as some of us hoped, as it did not drop until
it really dropped and that was until 2016.
In 2013 they introduced the Lemire shell, what's now called Lemire, they called it Unity
8 back then as a continuation of their desktop efforts and they introduced MIR, the MIR Server
Library that allows developers of compositors to easily create a new, now a days Wayland
based compositor back then they used their own protocol which caused a lot of problems
for some people in the community, but they turned around, they implemented Wayland on
top of their own display stack, display server, which is Wayland compatible now a days, so
that's something.
2016, five devices have been released with Ubuntu touchpad installed which is quite interesting
for something that was so niche, so yay, that was so niche, that gives me a hint that I
should speed up talking.
So five devices released, one tablet, four smart phones and they all ran like Android
adaptations that they ported over using libhiberz, that's how they quickly made it to market
very easily, I know for some people that's not interesting at all, but if you want to
go to market really quickly that's sadly what they had to do and others before them also
had to do it, even Carson Monk who started the libhiberz project, even him himself he
said, well if you want to do it quickly you need to do it that way.
2017, Canonical gives the Ubuntu Touch project to UB ports, we took it over, Canonical couldn't
finance it anymore, they had no interest in keeping up with the project overall and gave
it over to us and we are since then trying to make the best out of it and we have released
24 OTAs and we're in the process of releasing our first final images of focal based Ubuntu
Touch 2004.
We already have a beta version which you can download and install and select a few of your
devices but yeah.
And Unity 8 gets renamed to Lemiri, why?
Because it was very important for others to package it up without asking Canonical for
every single license, copyright related license question.
So we renamed everything from Canonical and Ubuntu to Lemiri so that it's generic, others
can make use of it and they can package it for their distributions.
So convergence, what do we mean by convergence, goddamn.
Screen real estate, first of all, let's go back to the basics.
The screen real estate, how many things can I actually put on the phone or on a tablet
or on a desktop?
What's the next property, is it multi-monitor capable, is there a possibility that you can
plug in an external monitor into your phone and have it work easily without much configuration
and can you do so wisely too?
Wired, wisely, both of them can work and which input methods are available to your
device at the moment that you want to use it.
We support various types of input devices from touch, keyboard, everything that you
expect nowadays from a personal computing device which accounts phones into the mix
as well.
And we are pretty much ready to deliver events, input events to applications whenever they
need to be delivered and they deliver everything that the application expects.
If there's a new protocol coming up, we are pretty much future proof due to the MIR team
working on their stuff.
The way the MIR handles the input and passes it on to the compositor is very much making
it possible to increase the abilities of input methods overall and that gives me a hint to
shut up again.
So convergence, what is actually convergence?
In our mind and that is the ability to adapt to different usage scenarios.
It's not which device does it run on.
It doesn't mean what output device, it does not only mean what output and input device
do you plug in.
It also means how is it adapting.
So for example, this phone when you use the wireless display capability, it's still a
phone, it's just got a wireless screen attached to it which displays everything that a normal
monitor would do but it's still a phone, it's not wired.
So how do we determine whether something is in phone mode or in desktop mode or tablet
mode and that's what the shell usually does.
I will get to the components and each of their responsibilities later.
But for now, the basics are convergence.
Attach to a usage scenario that you see fit as the shell or as the user basically because
we cater towards what the user might want at a very specific moment in time.
Both the shell and the applications need to be able to adapt.
Without the applications adapting, you have a great shell and you can't use anything with
it.
So we need the applications to follow the same rules, to follow the same standards and
make it easy with our custom UI toolkit that we have built based on Qt and QML.
It actually existed before Qt controls 1 was a thing.
So Canonical had to get something out of the sleeves real quickly and they made up the
now it is called the new UI toolkit.
Back then it was just Ubuntu toolkit.
And another thing that goes into the whole convergence thing is pausing at the application
as you expect nowadays from a phone where the UI thread of an application is paused.
It doesn't do anything.
How can we provide the same functionality with a typical new slash Linux way of handling
things like we don't have this cycle Android process that spawns other services in the background
and it does everything, quote unquote, hidden away from the user.
We as application developers need to think differently about how to approach a modern
day usage scenario with a smartphone being able to power save as well as being feasible
and doing stuff in the background when it's supposed to do it.
Not run in the background every time, all the time, because that's wasting battery.
But we need to make sure that the application life cycle is something that works on a phone
and it might work differently on a tablet and it might work differently on a desktop.
It definitely does differently on a desktop.
You don't want an application to pause underneath your feet or something, pulling the rug away.
So we do this for preservation of battery life and for that we need different policies
for every usage scenario.
And we do that by using Lamere app launch, which is a little library that handles everything
related to launching the applications.
It puts everything in the C group as you expect nowadays.
Specifically it uses system to user sessions for that.
And it also helps with application confinement and security because, on the point of touch
at least, the main goal is to provide a store that other people can download applications
from without worrying too much whether that data can be accessed or not.
Of course we can trust every application but then we would need to review them.
The typical traditional open source way of, Debian way, whatever you might want to call
it of importing data, software code and auditing it and then releasing it to others.
That's not what we want to do.
We want to give app developer easy access to release their stuff to users that they
care about.
For that we need application confinement and a few security practices that are part of
the whole convergence story and of the application lifecycle model that we have.
The result, or at least the dream for Canonical, was this.
You have a phone, a tablet, a laptop and even a TV which can run the same shell.
That's the last missing property of convergence.
You have one code base running everywhere.
You have one code that is sufficiently adaptive to each situation that it works as you expect.
It looks similar enough.
The input methods of course differ but in reality they provide exactly what the user
wants at a specific moment in time.
Swipe on the phone, it works like a phone.
Use your remote control on the TV.
It works like a TV.
It looks similar.
It feels similar.
Use experience part.
Next one, migration to new technologies.
It took us some time.
It took us some time to move over to system D but the concept very much applied because
AppStart back then already used to start stuff as individual session services.
For Lameerie App Launch it reacts to apps appearing and disappearing for us.
It gives us the events.
Application XYZ is gone.
Remove it from the launcher because it's gone and remove all the resources that you have
allocated to RAM.
Migration to new and new and that's a more interesting one because Dapen is pain.
MIR 2.0 dropped support for the old protocol that everyone complained about.
Current Lameerie on Open Touch does a split like Charlotte Claude Van Dam.
In that sense it runs both MIR Client and Wayland.
Through Wayland it also supports X Wayland.
The Wayland support on MIR on Lameerie is good enough that you can actually spawn a
GIMP application running through X Wayland on a LiPybers device or on a MALON device
depending on which X Wayland version you install and it works.
The problem is we want to go Wayland everywhere.
For Wayland everywhere we need to adapt a few new concepts, a few new things that are
right at this moment in development on the MIR side.
So MIRL, an abstraction layer which allows basic windowing to be done to really receive
data about a window being placed somewhere and stuff like that.
MIR oil takes it another step further which gives us the ability to get those trust prompts
that we use on Open Touch, those dialogues that pop up underneath an application and
overlay themselves on top of an application where you have to say, okay, I give this application
access to my GPS.
I give this application access to my microphone.
It doesn't do it by default.
It doesn't allow it.
You as a user need to allow it.
For that we need a few more components like trust prompt integration into MIR oil.
Screen casting is also going to be tough because screen casting is just different enough, mainline
devices versus hybrid devices that buffer passing might work but then how are we going
to tell which buffer looks like an Android buffer?
I think I need to figure out a few things on my side with regards to Wayland and how
WL buffers are supposed to be passed around.
But if anyone here has a lot of Wayland knowledge and wants to help us out here and wants to
have some screen casting for themselves too, please get in touch with me and we can figure
out something that works for both sides, I guess.
The UI toolkit, Lemire UI toolkit, this is a beautiful thing if you ask me.
I really like this.
The way that our browser, for example, that you can see the Chrome of on the top, that's
the Lemire UI toolkit rendering the tabs and depending on whether you resize the window,
it actually turns into something that you have to swipe up from the bottom edge of your
phone because this responsive design thing is one way to achieve convergence in a sense.
The UI toolkit, it follows our human interface guidelines, allows for convergence use cases
and it is used by the Lemire UI shell throughout the code base.
We have something that can be used by both apps and the shell so that both look the same
compared to others who write one toolkit for the shell and one toolkit for everything else.
In this sense, we have something that works on both sides of the equation.
It's abstracted by Qt and Qt does everything for us, but what it does not do for us is
handle the Wayland connections.
For that, we need MIR and we need Qt MIR as an integration point that takes MIR's window
contents, the buffers, and displays them on the screen or rather the scene graph of Qt.
When you put things on the scene graph, it's like this tree type of structure, you put
things on the screen, they get rendered and then they get displayed on the screen as you
expect using OpenGL and Qt MIR also already does basic window management, but it doesn't
do everything that Lemire needs to do.
It already does multiple monitors and also supports multiple input types, whatever you
expect nowadays from a display that can be driven with input devices.
Lemire itself, the shell, uses Qt MIR for the application window presentation, so everything
the Qt MIR gets from MIR, it gives further down to Lemire.
Lemire displays it.
We can even put some shader effects onto those tiny windows and make it a little colorful,
make them explode as you used to from compass times and have them render quite interesting
stuff just because of the way that Qt does animation in QML, which is quite interesting.
It also does more sophisticated window management, so window snapping, multiple workspaces, the
whole dimension of the
image is what you expect.
Ethercast, that's another one.
This one is not for the mainline folks yet.
I think this is an invitation for mainland folks to help us get it working on the Pine
Phone Pro, for example, which someone in the community has actually started a port on.
They got Ubuntu Touch running on the Pine Phone Pro with Lemire, with everything that
you expect, even the trust prompts, because they required a few patches to our side.
It doesn't know how to take those DRM and GBM allocated buffers and pass it on to an
encoder.
We just need the screencasting and the video encoding to be done quickly, then we can achieve
sort of like 20% CPU usage on one core type of deal for wireless display support.
So 20% of one CPU core being in use, for me that counts as nothing almost.
It's definitely usable, and I regularly do it with my Pixel 3a and it works flawlessly,
right?
And one last notable component, or two of them, is the onscreen keyboard, which also
plays into the whole Lemire story, so to say.
So Malit, we use Malit as the onscreen keyboard framework, and Lemire keyboard is a plug-in
to it, which connects over Wayland or over Mere client to the Shell, and says, hey, I'm
here, take me as your input device.
And Shell says, yes, I like you.
In that sense, the Lemire keyboard, it uses the Lemire UI toolkit as well, as you would
expect, and it also has some nice little features like you swipe up, when you have the onscreen
keyboard sliding up, and you swipe up from the bottom edge, you get to do text selections
very nicely, and you can also do the same with the space bar, with the space key.
That's a totally awesome thing to play around with.
And with that being done, I think.
We have five minutes left in total.
In total?
Yes.
Then we're going to skip the demo because you saw everything already.
Well, that's pretty much it.
If you have any questions, I will play around with the device.
We can interactively together use it, right?
Okay.
There's a question.
So if I want to use my phone as an input device on Gentoo, do I install Malit or something?
As an input device on what?
Gentoo.
Are you planning to bring the Shell over the Lemire experience to Gentoo, for that matter?
I want, for example, I have Gentoo, I have Malit, and I want to use my phone as the touchpad.
Oh, no, no.
That's because it is integrated.
This is the virtual touchpad of the phone, and it's because it's integrated with the
Shell, with the Malit desktop that we are running.
This is onscreen.
This is Lemire, yeah.
This is all integrated into Lemire.
So Lemire knows this is a virtual touchpad.
Let me do all the virtual touchpad stuff, and it does so by...
Is it available as a separate package that I can...
No, no, no, no, no.
It's integrated into the system's desktop.
We're not playing Lego here.
I'm sorry.
I didn't want to sound mean, but it's like those things needed to be integrated because
they wanted to release very soon, very quickly, very on time.
I plan to have a separate library, for example, by using...
It uses U inputs, the typical user space injects events into the Shell.
That's all it does.
U events.
U input, specifically.
Sorry for my intellectual environment.
No.
Is there a plan to have a separate package that I can use in different distribution,
where I use a valor, for example?
This is valent.
This is totally valent, where you use valent.
This is a valent desktop.
This is the desktop, but it also does the virtual screen, virtual input methods for
you.
You could, in theory, create a new Android, selfish, all of them, Mobian application that
just does that and transfers it over the wire to a desktop.
But this is not it.
This is all integrated.
You want something like CnRd.
The CnRd is a tool which allows you to set a separate machine running and then move your
mouse over the screen border.
They want something like CnRd, you can set that up and use the mouse over a new device.
CnRd doesn't work at the moment, but work is underway to make sure that you work.
Oh, multiple workspaces.
I haven't shown that you're that.
Multiple workspaces.
And a workspace.
Hooray.
How do you enable this desktop mode?
Just connected and go?
You just connected and it's done.
Right.
We do detect certain properties of the screen, whether it is a TV screen, projector, monitor,
integrated thing.
We have a whole genome full of different types of monitors that can be connected.
We also do a check by screen size, I think by scaling of the device.
So if you put it on an 11-inch device, depending on the pixel density, it would behave differently.
But yeah.
That's pretty much how it looks like.
This is a terminal that I'm not going to input my password in.
Yeah?
Which device is it running on now?
This is the Fairform 4.
Okay.
All right.
While we ask the last questions, Pablo can already start setting up stuff for the next
so that ends the demo part, I guess.
Yes.
Sorry for that.
But you still have some time for question or answers while Pablo's here.
All right.
Sure.
Can anyone see
them?
Yes.