We try to cover as many, it's unfortunate, there's so many topics to cover when you do
mobile, for Linux mobile phones.
Okay, welcome, looker, we have seen the first fair phone being used as a presenting device
this morning.
So now we are going to learn how to put the kernel on it.
Thank you.
Yeah, so kind of very quickly, who am I?
My name is Zukavayz, I've been my learning phone since like 2017.
I'm a post-marketless core team member and also my day job is Android platform engineer
at Fairphone.
Kind of about the background of how the whole situation, so I mean Qualcomm has a lot of
lot of SOCs like system on the chip.
There's quite a lot of actually already supported, so you see all these wonderful numbers here.
There's the ones launched since 2018, so like in the last four years.
And they are already supported in mainland as in they have a DTSI file and you can build
something on top of this and it's booting.
But of course there's also many, many others that are not supported, especially mid-end
ones like the high-end ones are normally very quickly supported by Linaro.
So like for example the SM8550 is the newest one, it was basically supported on day one
or it's the same with the SM8450, but the other ones are not, but you can of course
do it yourself.
So the device Fairphone 4 used a Snapdragon 750G, so SM7 to the 5.
Yeah, launched like a year and four months ago running the 4.19 kernel, which is already
I mean we had 6.2 nearly.
And yeah, like what I have so far working on the 6.1 or 6.2 kernel is like all the basics
that you can see here.
USB, including nearly the USB roll switching, so you can actually plug in for example a
keyboard into the device and not just use it like as a gadget.
I'm internal storage on the SD card, so the UFS and other things.
Okay with backlight control, which is separate components, touchscreen, GPU, Wi-Fi.
The remote procs, which is like separate cores on the SOC, they are actually all booting,
but at least for the modem one I'm actually not really able to communicate with it.
Mobile data could also in theory work, so the Linux driver initializes it, actually
gets the remote prock up, it already does some initialization things there, but it's
not really testable without actually having modem up.
So it's kind of untested, it's upstream already.
Vibration motor, the flash and torch LED, which is actually was upstream recently, or
is in the process of getting upstreamed.
The camera I2C bus, so I can actually talk with the I2C set and I2C get commands, I can
talk with the camera and get the chip ID, so that works, but yeah not really much more
useful with the camera yet.
And also lots of other plumbing, which includes of course the I2C buses, interconnect, so
like the bus scaling, cache scaling, and a bunch of other stuff that's useful.
So kind of what isn't working yet after this one year in four months that I've been sort
of working on it, I have some parts that are actually sort of working, it's like the speaker,
I do have, I can get sound out of the speaker, it is super quiet for some reason, I don't
know why, and also for some of the audio formats it actually doesn't play at all for some reason,
I know.
One of the problems with the speakers are also not very many phones in mainland actually,
like Qualcomm phones have audio working, so it is still kind of a new area where a lot
of things are kind of unknown.
And Bluetooth I have based on some patch that I found, you can get it on the Bluetooth,
you can make the phone discoverable, so you can see it on other devices, you can actually
connect other devices to it, but when you try to on Bluetooth do the scan on command,
like it just fails.
So which is a bit weird, I don't know why.
Probably need to spend some more time on it.
And also like of course all the other parts that don't work, so the modem, as I said before,
I can talk with the modem via QMI, so the Qualcomm protocol, but when I say please enable
yourself it says nope.
And doesn't say anything else, so it's kind of difficult.
The microphones, which is also kind of a different part of the audio stack.
The camera subsystem, which is used for receiving image data from the sensors, it's not working,
including the time of light sensors, like for autofocus it can be used.
The video encoding, decoding hardware, which is for, so you can play MP4 for example without
actually doing the decoding of the CPU.
And if see the fuel gauge, so for battery percentage and the charging driver, they are
not working.
I was able to port the one from the Fortnite 19 kernel to mainline, like just import it.
It does sort of work the fuel gauge driver, but apparently there's some weird, really
weird things going on in Android where like a user space component writes something to
the kernel driver and without this nothing works basically.
It's super weird.
And also this part of a USB-C, what Alfred already demonstrated before, like it works
in hardware, but it doesn't work with mainline, just with the downstream kernel.
So kind of what is the things that you need to have when you're trying to get a new SoC
app?
It's like one of the first steps is kind of also figuring out how can you make this bootloader
boot what you want to boot.
Because in the Android case, like Google requires some special things going on and also the
way that many SoC manufacturers implement it is kind of sometimes working, it is working
for Android and that's good enough for them.
But for example, the DTP operation which is device tree blob overlay, on some devices
you can just fast boot erase it and then it doesn't try to apply some overlay for the
old kernel on top of the new kernel which doesn't work and doesn't make any sense.
On some devices just crashes and burns and yeah, it is not fun.
So mostly you can do this.
And there's also on new devices with GKI, the generic kernel image from Google, there's
also the vendor boot partition, actually have no idea what this one does and how you need
to wipe it to be able to do something.
The serial console is actually quite useful if you can have access to it in the bootloader
if it doesn't boot.
Like if you cannot even get Linux booting, normally on a serial console it will say what
it's doing and why it's doing the things that you want to do.
So yeah, on the Fairform 4, on the new SoC, I got the first boot actually after some hours
of working on it which contains the early console.
It's just basically already set up area where Linux driver can write to it and you get serial
output and also display via simple frame buffer which is actually now way more easy than getting
USB up or getting actually proper serial console up.
So it's super nice, simple frame buffers where the bootloader already sets up the display,
yeah, the display hardware correctly.
So Linux actually just has to write to some memory area the bytes for the pixels and it
will just magically appear on the screen.
It is very nice, very useful.
And yeah, like the first boot was like 180 lines of the DTSI for the SoC and 40 lines
for the device.
So yeah, total 220.
And like no single driver change was necessary for getting a completely new SoC booting anything
basically.
Yeah, I was basically just following what Iskren wrote on his blog, mainlining.dev.
Super nice.
It really contains useful steps for the very, very first things that you need to do.
Yeah, so if you want to go a bit further, you very quickly start to need the clock driver
which is GCC, global clock controller driver.
There you can basically just take whatever Qualcomm gives you for example, for the 419
kernel, copy it over, modify a few small things, but then it works.
You also, at least for the 419 kernel, also these power domains which is like, it's some
concept in Linux.
It's also called GDSCs.
You need to, they were a bit differently implemented, not in a GCC driver, but you should put them
in GCC driver for mainlining.
Now say more clocks with the RPMH.
There's various other bits you should add to the DTS because otherwise it just won't,
like random things won't work, which are dependencies that are not really expressed in the device
tree, but the drivers still need for example, access to the S-MAM for doing various things.
These data definitions are basically all the same and downstream, so you can also mostly
copy them over.
Don't blindly copy them over because it will be a slightly different, but you can definitely
get good inspiration of what you need to do.
USB is of course kind of the next step because just staring at the tiny text on the screen
is not very good debugging and users also don't have any input.
You can do surprisingly much with simple frame buffer, but at some point you of course want
USB.
At some point also pin control driver, which is for the pin multiplexing.
This is really only starts getting useful once you get to more advanced components,
let's say for I2C and other things, and also regulators are important at some point.
I think that's actually, I don't know if you already need this for USB or not, but these
are kind of the basic components that you need and then you can start building actually
enabling various components that you find like the flash driver, the vibration mode,
and things that talk I2C and things that talk other protocols.
Of course, lots of things that can go wrong.
The IMMU is especially on new Qualcomm chips, it's kind of annoying.
I mean it's less annoying than old ones, but it's still annoying because a lot of things,
like some things that you do, I'm immune directly first, so what's a bit different
between downstream current and also main line is the bootloader already initializes something
in this memory segregation or like SMMU is also called.
Initialize some things for the bootloader to use for example for the internal storage
already initialized it, this normally gets on downstream kernel, it just continues using
those and add some ones on top.
On main line they actually get wiped completely and that need to be reset up by Linux, which
causes some problems if the downstream kernel doesn't express like which IMMU to use, for
example for UFS is a very bad example, it's a very good example where it is bad.
You kind of need to find out there is a patch, you can actually dump the mappings and you
can use this to figure out what it is.
Also the devices really like to reboot when anything is not really right, if you access
some register and some clock isn't on that it requires, it just reboots, it doesn't give
you a kernel panic, it just reboots.
You're writing to wrong register, it reboots, the IMMU is defined wrong, it just reboots.
Everything for IMMU it actually sometimes gives you a message of why or at least that
something isn't correct.
For printing what I've actually used sometimes is just printing the current line where it
isn't a driver, like sprinkling this everywhere, adding a sleep of like half a second and then
seeing like oh this is the last line that I was seeing, so it's probably messing up
there.
Maybe also increasing the sleeps because sometimes the flushing doesn't happen, like
printing it on the screen actually is a bit slow.
Also I feel like once you have more USB up, you can actually also build various drivers
as modules and this way actually it's not built in, where it's built in it loads like
it's like kernel log second 0.5 which is quite early and if it then crashes immediately you
don't really have any time to beat the debug.
But if you build this module you can load it later and actually have something set up
over already.
What is important to do if you work on this?
Actually if you have anything working, if you have something working progress just commit
this into your repository already to have a reference point to go back to because sometimes
one single line change will fix everything or break everything.
The first commit doesn't have to be perfect obviously.
But also don't let this skid branch that you have lying around once you have something
working, don't let it sit around in your local repository on your GitHub fork or in your
GitHub repository wherever and don't upstream it because then it will just drop there and
nobody will know that it's there and they will probably, like this next person has to
do exactly the same thing again even though you have already got it working.
So like already start up streaming your patches early, like if you have simple frame buffer
booting on the device upstream it.
It would be very nice because there's also better overview of which SSEs have already
been worked on and it's very nice.
Of course when you upstream it you also have to do some extra things for example adding
the new compatible strings that are used in the device tree added to the documentation
and do some things there but it's normally, yeah, some extra work but it's really not
too bad.
And also you have patches just because of how Linux development works just takes some
time to get upstream.
So like two months later if you go to, if you re-best a new version your patches are
already there so you can build on top and don't have like 100 patches lying in your
own tree.
Also like git send email is not difficult.
If there's a one for guide git send email.io from the source developers it explains super
nice once you have configured once just works.
Thanks for listening.
In case you have one minute for questions we can make a tool.
When you get GPU working you should also actually get the display hardware working properly.
So this was fortunately done for this.
SSE was done by Conrad who knows a lot there like he got the display hardware completely
up in the GPU also.
This is used for actually because simple frame buffer you cannot turn off the screen you
cannot basically do anything except just write pixels to memory, write data to or write bytes
to memory area and that's it.
Yeah so you actually need to get the display hardware also up but then you also can get
the GPU up.
And yeah this one works really well in mainline like I ran performance benchmark on and it's
actually not too bad it's actually relatively close to the downstream version.
I've contributed to the SDM 625.
Like how to upstream and manage the complexity of panels, generated planets?
I don't know panels.
Yeah the panel drivers are still I think in general a question of like how they should
be handled upstream because in theory I think the panel drivers are not really generic or
mean they are not generic but in theory they are relevant to the display controller and
not actually a panel itself which is two separate parts but like without having actually access
to like all the documentation that I like internal to the company you won't find out
which which driver this actually is and currently let them sit around in your tree.
There I mean most of them you can also just generate from a downstream DTV and it works
so good enough for now.
At some point we probably figured out but the MSM 8 9 16 people also they they have
like already like 20 or 30 panels there.
I think trust is always running so like the bootloader which is like it is a sign binary
and you cannot really replace it without having access to the to the sign in keys.
It is running I think and it also I think this is the thing that kills your that kills
the phone like when you're doing something wrong.
I don't know you can get rid of it you can probably somehow communicate with it.
I know that normally the fingerprint sensor is handled via trust zone as like you actually
talk to trust zone for the fingerprints but I actually don't know how this works.
Thank you very much.