Thank you everyone and thank you for attending this presentation.
The title is Mobian to Stable and Beyond because right now we've been only doing some development
release but first what is Mobian? You could think of it as a Debian derivative or in Debian
language a blend which is targeting mobile devices such as smartphones and tablets. We
provide a separate package repository but it's not a standalone distribution right and we have
some ready to use disk images which are built for several devices and more on that later. But Mobian
is actually a very very small overlay. In our whole package repository we have 44 source packages
compared to 35,000 and more on Debian itself so it's really some tiny bits and actually we have
planned to drop some of those packages and my hope is that basically one year from now we will be
down to something like 15 or maybe 20 packages at most because we have some transitional packages
and actually the most difficult to get rid of will be device support packages where we have downstream
patch kernels and stuff like that. But in the end Mobian isn't supposed to be a long-term project
it's really supposed to be merged into Debian itself and just improve the overall Debian ecosystem
rather than being a standalone project aimed solely at mobile users. The question we have been
seeing a lot lately over the past few months is basically where can I find the latest Mobian
stable image. You can't because it doesn't exist yet. We target Debian testing which is a moving
target you could think of it as a kind of rolling release distribution and the Debian testing
distro is frozen every once in a while it's about every once every two years and then moved on to
Debian stable. The latest stable release from Debian was bullseye which was released a bit less than
two years ago and back then we definitely weren't ready for prime time. For example we had version
0.6.8.2 while we now up to version 0.24 for the compositor and shell sites and there's been a lot
of progress over the past two years. Back when Buzzlye was released we didn't have stuff like
eG25 manager which is basically a piece of software handling the PinePhone and PinePhone Pro modem
configuring it properly to work as we expect. We didn't have MMS we have very few adaptive
applications because libadwator at the time was not even existing we had lib handy but no GTK4
and no libadwator and so in the end we decided against releasing a stable mobian version for
bullseye and the ecosystem was only starting to ramp up there was still lots of issues and bugs
and instabilities and really a low count of actually usable mobile applications. So what does
going stable mean for mobian? If you look back at the bookworm development cycle which is basically
the past two years we've seen some great progress both in the overall mobile ecosystem and in Debian
itself. The ecosystem is really really richer than it was before and it's still growing and more and
more people are creating or modifying applications so they can run just fine on our tiny displays
here. Graphical environments are more usable and way more stable than they used to be. I mean if
you've been using Foch like two years ago it was all tapping buttons and trying to get the things
right. Last year we had the swipes which was a huge usability improvement and overall lots of bugs
were fixed so it can run smoothly on many devices and that's just awesome and we even uploaded a
lot of packages we were hosting downstream to Debian itself and that even includes some
mobian specific package such as the splash screen theme, the installer settings, the repository key
ring also so we have the GPG keys for mobian also in Debian now so if there's another mishap it
happened last year we let the GPG key expire and user was stuck and had to download those manually.
Now they'll be able to just update the keys from upstream Debian and still have access to the
mobian repo. We had also fixed some early mistakes and optimal choices regarding how we named
packages, how we organize those and how we decided to ship all the device support tweaks. For example
we used to have for each device one tweaks package, one support package which was just a meta package
putting in all the dependencies. Right now for Qualcomm devices we have two packages which are
in Debian itself those are Q-Come phone utils which contains all the tweaks which are common
to every Qualcomm supported device and we have Droid juicer as well which I'll tell a bit more
in a minute and in the end now seems a good time to finally go stable. So what will it look like?
We have support for the devices we already support basically so those are the Linux first
phones, PinePhone, PinePhone Pro and the Librem 5. We also have some Qualcomm based devices mostly
SDM 845 thanks to the awesome work the community has done on this kernel and of course we also
ship some x86 images with or without non-free firmware depending on what you want and it runs
just fine for example on the Microsoft surface pro and surface go tablets. This is really awesome.
We also ship two flavors of Mobian one with Fosch and the other one with SXMO. We would have loved
to ship a Plasma Mobile flavor as well but this won't make it. I'm pleased to announce that Plasma
Mobile is finally in Debian itself but we only have the basics which are the calls, contact book,
SMS application and settings application and of course the Plasma Mobile shell but that's not
enough to ship a stable image based on Plasma Mobile so we'll keep that one and start releasing
it for the Trixie development cycle which is the next Debian testing and of course we'll ship an
LTS kernel and we'll commit to keep it up to date with security updates and try to update it as
often as possible for all the supported devices. We also going to ship some kind of semi universal
images. One thing we'd like to achieve with Mobian is that you could just ship one image and flash
it on any supported device and the kernel would support the device. All the small config tweaks
needed for this device would be applied automatically, the firmware could be extracted and so on and we
didn't quite get there yet but we're getting closer. For example on the SDM845 devices those
are Android based devices and they need some proprietary firmware blobs to just work. The
thing is this firmware is shipped by the phone manufacturer, there's no clear license allowing
you to redistribute it so we just can't package those into Debian and call it today. This is why
I came with Droid juicer. The thing is this is a small runtime program, it runs on boot, it mounts
the Android vendor partitions, fetches the firmware from there and copies it into the Linux user space
root file system and then afterwards you rebuild the intramfs, reboot the device and on the next
boot you have your Android device with all the firmware you need running just right now without
the need for downloading firmware from the internet. By doing so we also can have one
image for every single SDM845 devices, one root FS at least because the boot image is using the
device tree for the specific device but you have one root file system and as many boot images as
you have device supported and it just avoids the need for any device specific tweaks and so we
hope that in the future this can be extended to other Qualcomm based devices such as the
Fairphone 4 for example which by the way runs quite nicely on mobile and thanks to the work
Luca has done so far. So that's one of the semi universal images, the other one we're planning
to implement is for all the Pine64 devices because those need very few device specific tweaks, the
two of those the Pinephone and the PineTab already share the same kernel and all we have to do which
is not that easy but all we have to do is basically import the downstream patches for the Pinephone
Pro into this kernel. This can happen quite easily but we still have some things, some details we need
to work out especially considering the audio configuration on those devices due to the need
to have the modem properly talking to the SOC in terms of audio and sample rates, frequencies and
so on. So this might get pushed back a bit but we're working on it and we really hope that it
can be done for Bookworm so that we only have SDM845 images, Pine64 images and one other for the
Libram 5 which needs its own kernel because basically there are some patches that are
incompatible with the Pinephone Pro kernel. They share the same block for the display output and
if it works on one device it doesn't work on the other. Anyway, what we'll do during the freeze
period, so basically Debian is being frozen in preparation for the stable release. We cannot
have new packages in Debian starting the 12th of this month and one month later we cannot have
any update at all unless it's bug fix. But we'll still be able to work on downstream packages to
improve the stability and fix the remaining issues and hopefully, but we make no promise there, we'll
be able to work a bit more upstream by submitting kernel patches, implementing proper to-boot
support for the Libram 5 and Pine tab for example and yeah maybe we could think of other things but
for now we're focusing on trying to improve things during the few months we'll have left before the
stable release. And so what's next? Once we have a mobile stable, well we'll switch obviously to the
Trixie development cycle, tracking the next Debian testing and trying to get even better software
support for mobile devices. And so we're going to try to make it easier to support new devices in
Mobian. This is already, we're paving the way with the SDM845 images and the.64 images and trying to
get to a universal image and so we will hopefully make it easier for people to just support their
own device. We will also support 64-bit RISC-V. We actually have all the bits and pieces in place,
we have a dev board which is acting as a GitLab runner and is able to build packages for this
architecture which is already supported in Debian and so that's one, we'll just flip the switch once
the stable release is there. We'll keep packaging new software and new options for our users,
bit plus my mobile as I mentioned already, Lomi read, the UB ports user interface and finally
try to get this universal alignment thing out of the box and working smoothly. That's basically it
for me. You have a bunch of links there, the slides are uploaded to the website so feel free
to go there and yeah, I'm not sure we have time for any questions. So first thank you very much.
One minute, two minutes for questions.
Well the question was for the semi universal images where we extract firmware from the Android
vendor partition, do we have a solution for getting the updates from the vendor itself? The answer is
no. You just get what you have on the device by the time it's run, you can flash a new Android
ROM on your device and then reinstall Mobian if needed and then it will pick the new firmware but
there's no automated way and I really doubt that Android phone vendors will participate in LVFS
to get updates in a timely manner to users. One last question perhaps. Would it be possible for
Mobian to be completely assimilated in Debian? Almost. The only thing that will be pushing us
further from this goal right now is kernel support. If we manage to get fully supported devices in
the upstream kernel, that means upstreaming a lot of downstream patches and doing so for any new
device which will arise in the next few years, then yes, we'll be able to be completely part of Debian
and have no downstream repository at all but for now we're being held back by the kernel situation
basically. Okay, thank you very much. We don't have more time. Thank you.