Okay, so welcome Oliver, as I said, installing stuff and all the reviewers know.
First impressions count, so whether you have a nice installer or not will make or break
your review of the Linux problem.
So welcome Oliver.
Thank you.
Yeah, so this is called on Dev2.
I'm Oliver Smith and as you can see from the number there's probably also a first version,
right?
So I'm going to tell the story of that a bit.
It started with the PinePhone PostMarketer as community edition where we figured, well,
it would be nice if when you bought the phone and you had PostMarketer preinstalled that
you would be able to encrypt it actually.
So it's not just installed but you can encrypt it like a proper phone.
Yeah.
And that's how the idea for the on-device installer was born.
It looks like this.
Yeah, basically a simple UI, you press your continue button at the welcome page, then
you put in a password or pin for the user and you can select whether you want full disk
encryption or not.
And that's that.
After we released that, an additional feature came, which is that you can select whether
you want to install to the EMMC from the SD card.
So if you already have a PinePhone where something else is installed or PostMarketer as is broken
or whatever, then you can just take an SD card, put the on-device installer on it, and
then you will see this prompt here and it asks you, do you want to install to the SD
card itself, which works after some complicated stuff.
And you can also install to the EMMC and override stuff there.
That's what it can do basically.
And this is our cross-distro project.
So not only PostMarketer as is using this, but also Mobian.
Looks like this.
Mobian already did a talk.
And yeah, they boosted the fund a bit, but it's basically the same.
And they also added that you can choose the file system, which is quite nice.
So I thought to myself, well, it's good that we have this and it works for what it does.
And it was good as an initial version, but what would be the perfect version of this,
right?
And a lot of people tried this out and they figured, well, it would be nice if they had
more options like being able to select a file system or the host name or what have you,
like 100 options like you have in a desktop Linux installer.
And other people were like, well, it's too much options already.
What is this SSH user, which we also removed.
There was a separate user which you could set up.
And so it's a bit conflicting and it was hard to figure out what would be the perfect version.
And besides that, it would also be necessary to choose the language and locale.
And it would be nice if it was adaptive.
So it doesn't look like a letterbox like this when you run it on a laptop, which is the
case of the first one.
Yeah, and also it would be nice if there was the same keyboard because the keyboard was
entirely different and also there was another keyboard in the unlock application and then
another one when you finally have it installed.
So you had three keyboards, which is not very consistent.
So my plan was to add a simple and advanced mode so you could deal with that some people
want more options, some people want less options.
So the casual users can just go to the simple installation and have the least questions
asked that you need to get it running.
And the advanced mode would be for the nodes where you can pick everything and have it
encrypted or not and choose separate passwords if you want and so on.
Yeah, so I went ahead.
This is the decision tree which you would have for the simple and advanced mode.
This is the simple path.
So it goes through Wacom, then you choose your language and locale.
Then it asks you simple or advanced.
Then you say simple and then you choose the installation storage if it's possible with
your device.
And then you would set up one combined password for full disk encryption and for the user.
And it wouldn't even ask you if you want to encrypt it because it's just assumed, okay,
that's the right thing to do for normal people who don't care.
And then it's ready to install.
And then we have the advanced path, which is more complicated.
You get asked for the storage device, then you can pick the file system, the host name,
the user name and maybe lots of more options we can add later.
And you set the user password, then it asks you do you want full disk encryption or not.
And then it asks you do you want to use the same password or not.
In the current installer, it didn't work like this.
You had to type in the same password again if you wanted the same password and that's
not very optimal and a tiny phone screen, you know.
So yeah, after that, you're ready to install.
So as you can see, this is a nightmare of choices.
And yeah, it would need a lot of testing.
You would need to test all the code paths every time and to make this feasible, it needs
to be automated.
And this was not possible with the current code stack.
So I looked elsewhere.
So first here's a slide.
We need short test cycles, CI for all paths, and it should be easy to extend that it's
not much effort to add a new option if it's where it makes sense, right?
Of course, the idea is not to add endless options that don't make sense at all, but
some of them are really useful for users.
So I looked around and figured what could I use for the stack and I found this nice
application.
This is called Unlocker by Johannes Marbach.
And it's a replacement for OSK-SDL, which is the unlocking application you use to type
in your password after you have installed it.
And yeah, the nice thing about it is it can use the keyboard layout from Fosch.
So that's already pretty consistent then.
And it's very small.
It's based on LVGA.
Yeah, it has a dark mode.
And you can, it's actually adaptive like this.
So lots of great potential here.
So I based on Dev2 on this.
And behold, on the next slide, you will see what it looks like.
Looks like this.
Yeah, it's still like a similar format.
You will see some description and then you, in this case, you select the language and
then continue.
And then you, like here are a few example screens which it has.
Here you can pick whether you want a simple installation or advanced installation and
where you want to install it on your eMMC or SD.
And here is, here you would set a combined password.
I know the visibility icon is a bit blown up.
This needs to be fixed, but that's the current state.
Yeah, and here it asks you if you want to use the same password or not.
So basically what I showed in the decision tree earlier.
Meanwhile, while it's displaying all these dialogues, you will see on the serial output
that there's a text interface.
And this is useful because, well, it's kind of nice that you can also type in the answers
on your keyboard, but it has some practical use.
It can be used for accessibility when we hook it up with some text-to-speech and speech-to-text
stuff.
And then you could actually talk your way through the installation.
And it's of course very useful for testing because then we can, yeah, just run through
the whole thing in an expect script.
And that's, so there's one line which would interact with this dialog and there's a function
button and it waits for a page with the title Advanced Options.
Then it looks for a button called Simple Installation and it has to be the first one, all based on
the text output above.
And it presses it.
And if the dialog doesn't show up, then it runs into a timeout and the test fails.
And so as you can see, we can add new tests and extend the test really easily.
That was the goal, that it's super easy to test the whole thing.
What comes next?
Yeah, some, oh yeah, the code.
So this is what the code looks like for this Advanced Options page.
The idea was to make it very small and I believe I've accomplished that.
So you set the title, the description.
It can be translated.
That's why there's this T around it and you set the buttons.
And that's how you would add a new page like this.
And you don't need to add some XML file with the layout or what have you.
Yeah, so that's quite short.
And this is the button handling.
It's also not complicated.
You don't need to read it now, but basically that's my point, that it's easy to extend.
And then we have the current state.
So it's still work in progress.
What's done is it runs entirely in the integer MFS, which was not the case before.
So this is also nice because it saves like 100 megabyte or so of overhead.
There are these abstractions for pages, for installation steps, which also need to be
extended.
I just showed you the decision tree, but that's only the front end.
The back end, of course, needs to handle all these decisions also and needs to react based
on what you chose there.
Test cases are there already for installing from SD to SD, from SD to eMMC.
And these are just examples.
We could also add NVMe, of course, and what other installation mediums you have.
But I think it's useful for the user to be able to see, okay, this is the SD card and
not this is some dev MMC BLK0 or what have you for the normal users so they know where
they are going to install it.
So I just called it SD and set a path in a config.
And yeah, the tests run with LO setup or QMU.
You can use LO setup to run it on your own laptop.
And this gives you the fastest test iteration cycle.
You can also run it in QMU.
So you make sure that you have all the files in the integer MFS actually and that it works
after rebooting that you can properly boot into the onOS.
And so this is the more complete test.
And with LO setup, I actually rebooted my own PC once.
So you need to look out for that if you run it next to your regular operating system.
To do what's needed to replace the first on the WES installer is some more testing, some
fixed me's and the usual stuff properly integrated into postmark address at least.
So yeah, I would be happy if Mobian also wants to use this and other distributions are.
And we have so many distributions out there.
Yeah, but postmark address is probably the first test case because this was developed
in tandem with it.
And for the next level, this is the really exciting stuff.
So when once it works and replaces the current one, we could actually support more devices,
Android devices, Chrome OS devices, because for them you can just install it on the whole
storage device.
You have to keep in mind that there are already partitions and you need to use them in some
way.
And what's nice is we could download the OS images with Wi-Fi.
So you would only flash this very tiny installer to your SD card, boot it up, and then you
could pick any OS image and download it and you wouldn't need to create a new SD card
every time and it would be much faster than when you have to flash this whole image every
time.
And yeah, even better, we could also construct the OS images on the fly with the package
manager, which is APK in the case of postmark address Alpine.
And then we might be able to get rid of some of the OS images because it takes quite some
resources to generate them every time.
So this would be nice also.
And yeah, that's towards the end of my presentation.
Thanks to all these people who helped out making this possible and thank you for listening,
of course.
Thanks for the talk and thanks for the work you do.
Yes that's the plan to use Unlockr to replace OSK as the other also.
And that's quite far, I believe, there were some bugs with some very few phones.
This is why we didn't roll it out before, but it should be there sometime soon.
Any more questions?
Yeah.
You mentioned the expected use case, if you put it in an SD card, an SD card, but do you
could flash the on-device installer to the place where you would install the operating
system and from there it can expand itself into the installation.
So this works by you have first the boot partition, then you have a lot of empty space where you
will put the installation and then you have the on-device installer and it partitions,
it uses the empty space and creates the load script set up device there and then shafts
the data from the third partition in there and then delete this to third partition and
expands it and that's how it also currently works.
Is that an idea or is that implemented?
That's already implemented in the first version already, and the second version can do that
too.
Yeah.
What is the minimum RAM requirements for the initial OSK?
I didn't look, but I would expect, I mean it's AVGL, it's super tiny, maybe 50 megabytes
or 100, it's tiny really.
You can compile the whole UI thing in like a second or so, so it's really, it's also
fun to develop with this.
Yeah.
I have a question if there's no more because it's this train independent, so what's the
way to handle distro specific things like configuring repository sources or set different
ways to set host names on different distros, things like that?
Good question.
There's a config file and there's actually some distro specific parts inside the main
repository upstream and they are separated in a different directory and there you have
a directory structure for all the operating systems and my idea is that we test them in
CI all the time so we ensure that they don't break so when you make one change that it
still works in all the other distros.
And you have a separate config file and you can run your own code.
There are some hooks for example after you're done with installing and you want to regenerate
the in the drum of S then you can put the commands for that in a shell script and run
that after the installation.
Okay, cool, thank you.
Okay.
No more questions?
Okay, so thank you very much, Halle.
Okay, this is the end of the session.