Okay, the room is full.
It's still one minute to go, but I think we can get started.
Welcome, Evangelos, what's new in the world of Foch.
He is a Mobian member, Pearson employee, so he knows what he's talking about.
So welcome.
Yes.
Welcome to my talk and thank you for the nice words.
We'll see whether I really know what I'm talking about or not.
Maybe you can correct me if I speak over.
I'm kidding.
Since you already did the introductions, there's not much that needs adding right now.
So you, I'm not sure, since I'm interested, how many people here in this room, maybe by
show of hands, are currently running a Linux first phone?
Okay, that's nice.
I mean you're in the right room then.
And out of those people, how many people are running Foch?
Okay, that's like, I guess half of it or something.
That's great.
Okay.
So yeah, what is Foch for those of you who might not know?
It's a graphical shell for Wayland and it's aimed at mobile devices, so you can use it
with touch-based inputs.
The UI is written in GTK and we'll get back to that later on why that is really nice that
it's written in GTK.
And maybe just as a short history, originally Foch started its life on the Librem 5 and
the Pure S distribution developed by Purism, which heavily invested in getting the GNOME-based
mobile software ecosystem starting, I would say.
And oops.
So while it originally was written with the Librem 5 in mind, it quickly spread to other
distributions and now also runs on a lot of different devices as well as if you saw the
other talks.
For example, our most talked by Mobian, you see that there's like Pinephone, PinephonePro,
all the Pocophone and so on.
And maybe one thing that bears noting is all of these projects, they are working really
great together from my perspective as like upstream for some of the projects.
And it's really great to see all this cross-pollination going on between the different projects and
distributions.
So now to what has happened in the last year.
I guess most notably is the swiping gestures that was implemented.
So you can see in the video, for example, how it really tracks your finger movement
and it looks very nice.
And yeah, that is already probably old news to some of the people here in this room, but
I think that was one of the greatest improvements in terms of usability because you at least
if you're anything like me, you would always accidentally open up the app drawer because
when you were aiming for the space key and you just went the one pixel below that.
Yeah, so gone are those days.
Well from that there's been a bunch of quality of life improvements.
You got, for example, you can turn on and off VPN in the quick settings.
The quick settings are actually now also accessible from the lock screen itself.
And there's been all sorts of design overhauls and making sure the buttons and everything
look really nice thanks to the people that work on design and so on.
Another thing that I find really enjoyable to use are the lock screen plugins.
So you can have plugins to put some widgetry onto your lock screen.
So in these examples you see a simple proof of concept calendar widget, like the one on
the left that is probably not that useful unless you just happen to forget the date
and then it's great.
Upcoming events is something that I really enjoy because yeah, you see at a glance what
is going on next.
Emergency information is also something that you can have displayed there.
And also, notably, if you want to show tickets when the train conductor comes by, you can
do that from the comfort of your lock screen.
You can actually turn on or off these plugins in the Foch Mobile settings application, which
has a few different things you can, like plugins you can enable or disable and other settings
like well, you want the keypad on the lock screen to shuffle whenever it's there.
So no spying eyes can learn your pin from watching unless they watch really, really
closely then.
This is some more images from the mobile settings application.
So for one, you might find some device-specific things there.
And in the compositor settings, which is also shown in the video on the right, you can,
for example, enable scaling applications with windows that are overflowing down to have
them fit on your small mobile screen.
Then we also have a nice thing that came about while at DevConf in Kosovo where it was really
nice weather.
And the main developer implemented automatic high contrast switching between the dark and
light variants based on what the ambient light sensor would show you.
And if you want to try that out currently, you would need to use these G settings.
You may need to adjust the threshold for your case and to make sure that it works for you.
And, yeah, depending on how sunny it exactly is.
Apart from that, I am, yeah, there were a few design overhauls on the calls side.
And also maybe notably to people who have large call history, it starts up a lot faster
than it used to.
And also the scrolling performance in the history has much improved.
It will get even better with GTK4, which is on the roadmap, but with GTK3 resulting to
some hack limiting the amount of widgets displayed in the list box makes a lot of difference,
especially on weaker hardware like the PinePhone itself.
And you can also, I don't know if you are aware, but you can long press the entries
in the call history and from there you can start sending, for example, a new SMS or if
it's an unknown number added to the contacts and so on.
Apart from that, oh, that image should have, yeah, okay, not been there, but, yeah, it's
also, it can also be used to make voiceover IP calls using the session initiation protocol.
That's been implemented some time ago and it should work for you.
So if you have a, I don't know, jump chat or SIP gate or something account, you can
use that for phone calls, sorry, voiceover IP calls.
And during last year supporting encrypted media streams is also something that has landed.
Actually the call display will not tell you right now that it's an encrypted call, but
you can trust me on that.
On the chatty side, like the SMS application, or SMS and more I should rather say, there
was a lot of work on MMS especially thanks to having MMSD.
There was a lot of work on group messaging flows and there's also work still ongoing
on Matrix, but that is something that I'm personally very excited about.
Then maybe in the wider ecosystem, one of the things in GNOME that I really enjoyed
is that we now have dark style preferences with latest Libadvaita and also in Lipendi.
If you want to know more, you can, I guess you can't click on the links, but if you go
to the slides, there's some blog posts that I linked right here.
Maybe just a few examples of some of the applications that have been made adaptive since I think
pretty much all of the GNOME cause applications are now adaptive.
Yeah, contacts, GNOME software, and there's lots of things to look forward to.
So that's Matrix and chatty is one of them.
And yeah, fixing paper cuts because I think we're in a position with Fosh right now where
it's as it was evident by all the people raising their hands earlier that is in good shape.
There's still things that could be better, but it's definitely usable as a daily driver-ish.
Okay.
And yeah, if you want to reach out, look at the slides and thank you.
Three minutes for questions, plenty of time.
Yes.
Okay, is there a mechanism available to display GTK port compliance on the notification?
I don't think there is.
If you look at the, or maybe I'm wrong, but if you look at the notifications, specification,
I'm not sure that you can put like real widgets on with all the bells and whistles.
You can tell that there's, or as an application, you can say, hey, here's an action.
So the notification will give you some button to click on, which will then, I don't know,
do something, reply to a message or something.
But I don't think custom widgetry would work at all because you'd also need, how would
that work?
Like if it's a QT app and yeah.
Probably embedding that in the way that surface is complicated, but I mean, it's, I mean,
it's, it's already built on GTK, so maybe.
I mean, probably since it's free software, there's always ways you could do things, but
I personally, I'm not entirely sure how, how exactly you would implement something like
this.
Yes.
Okay.
I have a question.
In the convergence mode, you have the application list there and it would be great if you can
press some button or get to something and say, make this application now running in
full screen on the external device, external screen or low-class.
Maybe there is, there is supercating some combinations.
Yeah.
Have you made some of the keyboard to be able to connect the phone and say this one is.
Okay.
You mean like from the, when launching the application.
From when there is already running applications.
Okay.
Yeah.
I'm not sure how like from the spatial model of you, since you already have these swipes
to the, to the right and left to go between the, the open applications, I'm not sure like
how would you need to.
I see a group press and some menu.
Ah, okay.
Yeah.
That's quite missing form.
Okay.
That's good to know.
Please file a bucket.
Okay.
So basically time is up.
Sorry.
We only have very little time for this.
It's just already, it already went through, baby.
Okay.