So that's much better there.
Yeah.
Personally, I think it's like in a perfect world, everyone would have just used mainline and everyone would be happy and this would be this would be
a dream world. And while I'm a YOLA developer, in my own opinion, what postmark it is, what they do is awesome. And if everything would work this way, we at YOLA probably wouldn't have
would use Sony OSB, but it's not at its place. And so I still advocate to use high-wors, especially if you have an open platform, which also has open communication. This is still why I think
open Sony Open device is still a good target to port to. And a lot of Android applications, or Android even just Android ROMs have the problem. They don't have the blessing of the window. So as long as you do it for yourself, it may be fine. Nothing will happen. But you don't know. Lawyer can write you a fancy letter and tell you why are you doing this and now you're broken, you know. And that's about you. And we at YOLA, we cannot do that. So that's why we choose only Sony Open device.
And then one thing, especially for someone that's inexperienced, going to Sony Open devices and trying to start a device is easier because there's existing structure and guidance there. And open communication is like someone behind some back channel where you have to talk to some specific person. They talk to you.
The communication is not always perfect, but they talk, do talk to you. And that's like, this makes a huge, huge difference. And then also the lifetime is really long. Whereas for other devices, you may be stuck in one kernel. Sony Open device actively upgrades to downstream kernel that they have to their devices. So that's also the reason why we don't use Android. So the Android updates don't really do that much. It's still an important factor for someone to decide.
So it's not mainline, but it's like in between being stuck on a really old downstream kernel where you have a long, more up to date LTS kernel that has like most of the features that you need, but also makes it more attractive for to port Linux to.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think I kind of skipped this already.
So contributing to Sony Open devices. So personally, I started contributing to it because I wanted to have a different device that I wanted to run safe shares on because I like to say fish as a platform, but I wanted to have more devices and Yolo while it's a reasonable choice started with the expert and series.
But I want a better device with a better display and so and better hardware, of course. So I choose that.
And if you have something of experience, you can start to try to run HP on it quite easily. You just have to know how to use Linux a little bit and have a device in the computer.
And that's it really, except maybe some programming skills, but a lot of things you can just learn while you go and you don't really have to be an expert person myself.
I'm not someone that has a university degree or a local education, a formal certification or something. I have nothing. I just learned it while I learned.
And here I am.
I think you don't always have to go this way.
Yeah.
So and then I wanted to highlight how Sony contributes because I think many people wonder, like, how what's the relationship of Sony and Yolo?
Because it kind of looks like there's like some some some deeper level of communication there.
Well, yes, we talk to Sony. We have someone to talk to at Sony, but it's except that we're not really someone that gets special treatment.
We just want a contributor and anyone anyone can to be in contributor to to Sony open devices.
And the chance that then you go goes into Yolo devices is quite high then because of the way the Sony open devices works and the way that you can reuse work.
So we use it through some it runs Sony reference Sony devices, a reference port, which then you can use to put other Sony devices to other devices of the same Android base.
Because nowadays, thanks to Google, a lot of things are more sanitized and you don't really depend on one specific device vendor, which is still not mainline.
But it's getting there. And and I think Google as a company, they listen and they if they could make everyone work with mainline, then they would probably do that as they would do with Chrome OS.
But device vendors are like stubborn.
So things change slowly. Yeah. And usually we are more focusing on refining a specific target device, not adaptation.
That's part of quality of the other adaptation is then better than it was before.
Usually not everything is perfect, but it's it's sometimes sometimes sometimes hard like camera stuff or audio.
The audio guy when he talks, it's in our company, it's sometimes like he's no more some kind of black magic skills that I don't know.
And it's it's it's really something. Yeah. And there and we generally contribute quite frequently back.
So most of the work that we do to Sony open devices goes back to them.
Some stuff is specific, but not really. It's depends on how much effort is.
Yeah. So as I said, originally I didn't really talk about mainline, but I still want to advocate for it since I think it's a good thing.
And if possible, if your device has a mainline port and the main import is in a state where it's OK, then then try to push it.
So I think the really big thing about what hybrids is like this.
It's like, you know, when the devil gives you in the garden of Eden gave them the apple, you know, like the the easiest solution that's like hybrids.
So so that's why I think it's still a good thing. And as I said, we're not in the perfect world, Sally.
And then Sony's house is the quality is good to OK, depending on the area or some areas like camera.
OK. But that's like just about the topic in general. It's not really their fault. And it's and it's open.
So it's just a clear line between the separation of the blobs and even open device, even like mainline devices that have a main line kernel.
They don't want without blobs at all. It has some firmware and just to the way that the firm is on a different level.
That's really a big difference. And because you have no features also probably a little bit more blobs, but it's just that's why it's why it's easier to get there.
And in a lot of ways, like it's really.
Mainline tech sometimes to get there, whereas hybrid is easier to have some kind of functionality.
And yeah, really, I mean, I kind of was nice and in a long one, it's really better, but it's on-stream chrono, gives you gives like a better base.
It's just an along one. It's just. No, it's annoying. And while Qualcomm is better than anyone else, really, it's still not nice.
Sometimes there's funny stuff in the kernel that you don't expect.
And then they rub your time when you just try to update the kernel.
With Sony, probably feels quite often. So, and I kind of skipped the spot already, but I wanted to wanted to give like, like some ideas for target reactions.
So I quite strongly follow the port of a Calib to this SEM 845, which is the I think 2009 2020 high end sock from Qualcomm.
And those are really what was very good today. They're good start to try and to think around and then to go further.
While those are mostly one plus, there's also an SO main nine port to it, I think, but SO in main nine right now, as sort of stated, I could demo it.
If it was, I would have shown something here that was idea, but sadly I couldn't get that far. So yeah.
And then the pine for another pine from pro as a really great devices.
And we also have ports to the pine phone and Python pro and our and our stand.
You can can see them can see them. You don't have a pine from pro here, but we will probably find some people that have it.
And then we can show you. And then this may be some strange, but in some ways, KVM is really good target to try main line on because it's PC hardware, essentially.
And you can develop like the basic middleware components on it and then have like a testing target that you can for people to try out and to just have it running.
It's great. And I also, if time I can show the demo of it, I have one on my notebook and if not, then on my stand or an hour stand there.
So, so as I said, I'm a developer, but I come from the community and I want to give back to the community and I am.
Want to bring some of the processes that we have to the community in the same way or in a little bit same way as as a right here and most of the processes that should probably work for main line ports and safeties too.
Or also outside or safeties as maybe.
But some stuff just doesn't apply.
So, for example, since you're a possible reference device of the same of that of the of the year, for example, like twenty three, then to to Sony open devices.
Most of the work can be used for any other Sony device of that year.
So, for example, I post personally, I put the highland high end Sony devices and I can either test the same comment when I work on the device or just have to change a little bit and then import it from from the yellow repositories.
That's why there's so much shared.
It's like ninety five percent of the port is the same as on the other port.
It's just there's different testing and so in the end there's more work, but it's really shared really much.
So we can see a timer somewhere.
Oh, sorry.
So we have to process.
I really am.
Yeah.
Okay.
I tried to speed up a little bit.
Sorry.
And then the infrastructure can also be used and then also the issue tracking can be done similar to the yellow ports and the change.
So, yeah.
Okay.
I just tried.
So I'm not sure if I can cover all of this, but I will try.
Yeah. So you're not just about to track down or on internal issue tracking and then regenerate to change works from that.
But we can do the same with GitHub and then generate some change looks with DNF and then have a markdown based change lock that is based from that.
So you take down you close an issue on GitHub and then we generate change lock for the app package and then with DNF report if we scrap the difference between the repositories down from that and then have a change lock from that which looks really good.
And yeah.
And I think it really helps to just contribute and test stuff. So that's why a lot of people that are not programmers to still contribute and it really helps much.
So, yeah.
Yeah. Okay. That's my last bit.
Yeah. And then the last thing is right now the community doesn't build the enriched parts on the obvious that adaptation.
But for some work with some scripts that I have you can do that locally using the obvious and then upload the binaries which is a lot cleaner than doing this with hard work done because you just have always a clean environment just takes more resources a little bit.
Yeah.
So how much time there for questions though.
Thank you very much. Yeah.
Yeah. Thank you.
One minute for questions. So any questions. Yeah.
Yeah. You.
Yeah.
So we have. So I assume that's in your lobby generate like the technical change locks where sister all changes in them in there they are generated and then we have like a manual change like we have to learn over you for like the non-technical people and that's what's the idea about it.
So you should still look into it if it's like exactly as you want it and not just take it. Okay.
Yeah.
Hello Ellen. Yeah. Thank you.
We should do two small clarifications. Yeah.
Was regarding the fact that it's easy to port to other devices because all Sony devices is one.
Yeah. Yeah. I should have said. Yeah.
So the reason why I didn't mention it and I thought this was a sort of thing.
We are just some country one contribution anyone can call report box and so that's why anyone can do it. It's open. It's just there on GitHub and you can fork it and then contribute and then make a product question that's really it.
Yeah. Okay.
Time is basically up. So thank you very much. I will be also also on the also through him if you have more questions and then later I will also understand. So in case you have more questions you can just ask and I didn't have to put a link here.
I've got to put a link here. Sorry. But I will post my slides and I will have the reference on the slides and you can just find our project on GitHub and the Sony on device project of course also GitHub and just create a back there and ask really that's really the only thing that you have to do to get help.
Yeah.
Thank you.