Welcome.
So, to break the flow of presentations a bit,
there's now going to be a discussion.
So, not just presentation,
but the discussion.
But I'm still going to give
a short presentation first to create some context.
First, who am I?
I need to speak louder.
Okay. No worries.
So, I'm an embedded software architect.
This discussion is also
mostly focused on the embedded aspects.
I'm working on Linux OS integration as
a consultant for dozens of customers.
In, I'm also a maintainer of the Buildroot project.
Which is a team of four maintainers or five,
depending on how you count.
That's actually the context from which I come.
I mean, from which I give this presentation.
I don't actually care about S-Bombs.
It's just something that needs to be done.
And so, yeah. There we go.
Because maybe not everybody is familiar with it.
I'll give a quick overview of
what an embedded Linux build system is.
So, basically, it's taking a lot of sources.
Some open source sources coming from the Internet.
Some in-house components coming
from various ways that you can get at them.
Sometimes, these in-house components
are going to be binaries as well.
And then the embedded build system takes
all that together with the configuration and
produces a number of artifacts.
One thing to note is that the number of artifacts is really small.
So, we are talking about maybe five files or something like that.
It's not like when you create
an operating system that you have all these files that you need to keep track of.
So, from my point of view,
as a maintainer of such embedded Linux build system,
the problem is actually quite simple.
We know what the inputs are.
We have just a few outputs and we can just say,
okay, these outputs are generated from these inputs.
So, that's actually what we do in Buildroot.
We don't have SPDX at the moment.
We don't have anything complicated.
We just have a list of packages with
their package name and version,
where it comes from, the source URL.
Also, the tarballs themselves and the hashes for checking the tarball,
the patches which are applied to them,
the licenses, and the dependencies,
so the build dependencies.
So, what other packages were used to generate this particular package?
And then the assumption is that all of this together goes into your target image.
So, there's no distinction of what is used for what particular output.
There's also a list of files per package which you can use to reconstruct,
to get more fine-grained.
And then what I think is the actual thing you want to have is the CVE information.
So, the two things which I think are needed are the licenses,
and that's part of this top part,
and the vulnerabilities, the CVE information.
So, there's a separate tool that extracts that,
and it uses CVE IDs to relate
our package name and version to what is in the CVE database.
Now, when you do this, this is of course not reproducible because it
uses CVE information all the certain time and new CVEs are created all the time.
So, it's something that you have to rerun all the time.
So, as I said, it's very simple.
There's a lot of things which are missing and where my question is basically,
is this something relevant to work on?
So, one thing that is missing is external files that you supply yourself.
It's basically all the configuration which I mentioned here, this part.
The assumption is that as a user,
you know what these files are and you can inject them yourself.
Same with the built-root source.
We could make a tarball of the built-root source,
but we didn't really see the point.
Then we come to more important things that's thinner dependencies.
So, S-bombs are used for two purposes basically.
One purpose is for license information and second purpose is for vulnerability tracking.
Now, if you have a vendor dependency in some package,
we just see the top package that vendors it in and not the actual vendor dependency.
So, we don't have the package name and the version of that.
This used to be not much of a problem because not many people were rendering.
But now, you have Go, Rust, MPM stuff,
which brings in all these dependencies and they're invisible to us.
We also have everything in one file,
not spread out over dozens of SPDX files.
It is good, this is bad, I don't know.
We don't have SPDX formats.
We have it only at the package level,
not at the individual source file level.
So, our inputs are basically tarballs, not C files.
As I mentioned before, we don't have mapping of source to target files.
So, that brings us to the discussions points.
For me, the most important thing to discuss is why are we doing this?
So, what are the consumers?
How is this information going to be used?
Because that determines what should be used as input as well.
If you look at, for instance,
SPDX specification, it doesn't really say whether you have to look at
a source file or you can treat the tarball as a source.
It just says, okay, there is a relationship there.
It's not, I'm going to give you the microphone.
I'm going to start standing because I suspect I'll be talking.
And I'll come up here with you.
So, turned around.
There is, sorry, back to the question, you got me confused now.
SPDX is-
Individual source files or tarballs?
Individual source, a tarball is just a file.
Exactly.
And you can use SPDX at any level.
And so, if you just want to look at the package level and say, hey,
it's this tarball file, that's fine.
It works.
You do not need to take it down to the source file.
And it's a minimum set of fields that you just basically, all the concepts
you had up there, you should be able to express right now with what we've got
in SPDX today without any trouble.
And so, you basically would put a package there with the metadata that you want to
keep at the higher level and you'd point maybe to a file that has a hash.
Simple enough.
Yep.
So, I see another remark there.
I have a question, also related to the fact that you both have the vendor information as well.
So, I'm guessing that at some point you would want to either add a kind of
dependency tree which can couple up so you get a full list of all the dependencies.
So, in a way that can be flattened, all the dependencies at the top level so you can
pass them as much as you so could?
So, the remark question is, if I understood correctly, so the,
an S-bomb is basically a hierarchy of dependencies, but you can flatten it to
just have input and output.
What I think for an embedded build system, I think it's enough to
only have this flat one without a hierarchy because the hierarchy is
difficult to determine for the embedded build system.
And I don't think it has useful information.
Unless there is anybody that can say there is actually useful information in the hierarchy.
Yeah.
I'm guessing you don't know.
There were those guy comes just coming in here.
Yeah.
I have some thoughts.
I'm going to try to speak about that a little bit, you know, well, later.
But, yeah, there's a ton of uses for having a structured S-bomb.
And if you saw, for example, the Siemens use case where they
enrich S-bombs, you need to have that structure to enable, to let you know when
the enrichment happens where the extra information is going to be happening.
Also, if you want to, like, compose an S-bomb by taking pieces from another one,
like my friend Ivana here has been doing a really great work on composing S-bombs.
So if you want to compose an S-bomb by taking pieces from one and moving that data to another
one, you need to have that structure.
And there are several use cases that need you where you need the structure.
But then I wonder what the, I mean, if you compose S-bombs, there is supposedly also
a corresponding composition of the binaries themselves that the S-bombs describe, right?
Because in the end, an S-bomb is a description of a binary.
Yeah, but the binaries can be repackaged, for example.
You can have a binary product of a field and then you ship it and so on.
So indeed, if you're going to repackage stuff, then this is relevant.
I'm surprised that there are use cases for repackaging stuff.
There was a question of...
I can give you a real life example.
Patches and handling patches.
So yeah, there's a question from the chat.
What about handling patches?
Good question.
So what we currently have in Buildroot is just patches are one of the sources and they're
described as one of the sources.
Or, well, they're included in the tree as one of the sources.
Is there anything else to say about patches?
There's also a specific relationship for patches.
Yeah, there's a specific relationship for patches because it's a modification rather
than an actual source.
What about naming?
So I think there was one more remark about patches.
Yes, I was the one in the chat.
The thing is, it is not a curl and you have a curl in the view of patches.
It's not the same curl.
There could be other vulnerabilities in your distribution than the original one from GitHub
or another one from B2D.
Yeah, so indeed, it's essential that you track patches rather than, I mean, you definitely
have to record that what you are using is not curl version X, but curl version X plus
patches and then also which those patches are.
Yeah, and that's a new P you were talking about.
Which takes us to the naming problem.
Yeah.
So you've got a naming problem.
You say OpenSSL.
Is it OpenSSL?
It's the OpenSSL.
Or is it OpenSSL wrapper?
Or is it OpenSSL someone's patched or modified or built in a particular way because we've
got so many options.
So the remark was, if you say this is OpenSSL or even OpenSSL version X, that doesn't necessarily
uniquely identify it because it can be patched or it can be built with certain options.
So that information about how it's patched and how it's built has to be recorded as well.
So do you capture that as part of build route now?
Yes.
Well, so implicitly, yes, but not explicitly.
So it's captured because we have the baseline, which is basically identified by CPE ID, which
is the upstream version, let's say, or well, the version as published by the maintainer
of the package.
And then the patches are recorded separately.
The configuration, as I mentioned before, in build route, we don't really record that
so to the user themselves to record it.
So I mean, there's definitely room for improvement there.
Yeah, this is a problem with anything that's building from source in this way is that the
name and version are unique.
This is one we have to attach this?
Right, yeah, exactly.
This is recently attached.
Yeah, you have to check the hash and that's why you need to build information because
just because it says open SSL 1.2 doesn't mean that the place or security vulnerability
was actually even compiled into the code, right?
Yeah, so the remark was that the package and version information when you're talking about
the package and version information is not enough are not unique.
It might not even be the same between two people that built the same thing because of
configuration.
And the solution for that is hashing the outputs.
Yeah, but then the thing is simply hashing the outputs.
Okay, then you have an identifier of something, but okay, you have you actually have the output.
You could hash that, but it doesn't give you any information.
You need to actually the build information itself.
Where also even there the usefulness is a bit limited because in the end it goes to
the CVE database and in CVE database you don't have this information anyway.
You don't have it in a, well, you may sometimes have it in an informal way in the description,
but you definitely don't have it in a formal way saying if configured X then so unless
there is also some changes there, I don't think there's much use to.
I mean it's important to record it for manual analysis, but since there is on the other
side no formal recording of it, I'm not sure if it makes sense to record it formally.
So what we do for the CVEs is we don't really put in the, we put the CVE in and then just
once which ones we've patched.
So like that way if you go look it up, you know, I don't need to worry about this one,
but if there's any new ones.
Yeah, that's basically what is done in built root as well, but not in an SPDX format, just.
The CVE ID is a field external reference you can associate with the package.
Yeah, so the remark is in SPDX.
In SPDX there's the external references and you can associate a CPE with a specific package.
You can also associate a Perl with that same package and if you wanted to put both of them
there you could.
It's flexible there and because of the time scales of vulnerabilities and so forth, what
you want to record at a point in time whether something's patched or not or other things
like that, this is all hopefully able to be done.
The question is, you know, are people having tools there semantically accessing it right
now?
Just one of the things about the consumer's tools is actually we are seeing tools emerge.
In fact, I know of two off the top that are basically consuming S-bombs and matching them
to vulnerabilities.
So that takes care of the monitoring over time because there's two different time cycles.
There's what's known at build and then there's what's known in the field over time.
And so the two projects I'm aware of are Daggerboard and the other one is the one that's sitting
in the SPDX repo that looks up vulnerabilities.
So you basically feed it in S-bomb in SPDX and it will go and query the databases for
vulnerabilities.
To all S-V.
Yeah, SPDX to all S-V, yeah.
And so there are tools out there that are emerging and I think we'll be seeing more
and more in the years.
Maybe as a reaction to that, so my intuitive reaction is yeah, but we also have a tool
that generates this information already, I mean, as part of build routes, you can just
run that tool again five years later and you get that information.
But there's a KVET where I think it's actually useful to have the built information formally
recorded and that's basically the same thing as what archaeologists do.
You don't know what techniques are going to emerge later and that can be useful then.
So if you build something now, you should record all the information now that can be
recorded.
A little add to that?
The other little add to that is that use case is also very important in the high assurance
world where you are being asked to attest exactly which vulnerabilities you know about,
but that's an audit case or a high assurance case and so some places they will want to
have that.
Okay, I would like to move on to a different subject which I mentioned here.
That is vendor dependencies because I think that's a, I mean, from the point of an embedded
build system, that's an important thing to solve.
We actually have multiple vendor dependencies.
I'll first give an intro and then multiple vendor dependencies.
So we have some vendor dependencies which are directly included in a source code.
For instance, Tomlip is a good example.
Tomlip is a library that is meant to be Viner tin and so, yeah, people just copy it into
their source codes.
So that's really difficult to trace.
Then there is Git sub-modules.
You clone a Git tree.
That is the information you have in the, as a build system, that's the information you
have in your build metadata.
But then if there are sub-modules referenced from there, that information is not part of
the metadata of the build system.
And then cargo will go in PM modules, obviously.
And then there are some cases where the build system itself vendors things in.
For instance, in OpenEmbedded you have the kernel meta which is kind of rendered in and
which is not, I mean, I don't know if it's taking into account for the SPDX, but you
need to take special action there.
That's the important thing.
It's not using the normal parts of taking sources.
So, yeah, my question to the audience is how can we deal with these vendor dependencies?
You had a remark.
Question?
An additional question.
Okay, sorry.
I'm going to give you a...
This is actually just a problem beyond S-bomb generation because if you're trying to do
air gap builds, these are huge problems in general.
But that we've encountered.
So ideally we could download all of these sources and archive them without, and then
go tell the tool to go pull them from the archive, which is often difficult, if not
impossible.
So yeah, it'd be nice if the tool, like, cargo and go, I think cargo is not too bad, but
go and NPM are pretty bad, last we checked, for being able to do that kind of thing.
And that would make this a lot simpler too.
Yeah, so the thing that I want to add to that is that...
So getting the sources is not the difficult part.
So if it's just for licensing, that's doable.
But for supply chain, you want to know provenance, and that's the hard part.
There is...
Unless the...
I think for all these things, unless the source, the upstream itself gives some provenance
information, preferably in a formal format, then there is no...
It's really hard for us as a build system to go and look for it.
For cargo and go, it's actually doable to do it on our side, because you have a log
file which gives the exact information, not in an easily consumable format, but the information
is there.
For NPM, of course it's NPM.
And kit-zip modules also, I mean, the information is there.
It's...
But you don't have version numbers, you know?
You have Git hashes which are not something that you will be able to check against the
CVE database.
And to some extent, that's also the case for cargo and go versions, because often they're
also specified by Git hash.
And then they're directly included in sources, as usual, hopeless.
Any other?
Well, it's just some perspective.
So one thing to keep in mind about those is, those dependencies that get rendered in, and
you need to capture those in the S-bomb, you can see them in two ways.
One is from the dependency list angle, and in that case, just having the version and
then name and ideally the hashes of those dependencies is enough.
And the other angle is if you're trying to actually inventory all of the files that get
rendered in.
So, it depends on the use case of the S-bomb.
You may want to capture one or the other or both.
So just for dependency's sake, it may be depending on the build system, of course, it may be
the case that you only need the list of dependencies without the actual file information.
Yeah, the thing is, the file information is easy to get.
The list of dependencies is difficult.
I think picking on what Adolfo just said is, a lot of build's dependency just say latest
or not explicit on the view that people say, I want to keep up to date patch-wise, because
we're told we've got to keep everything patched.
But for making it dependable, it's the worst thing because it's going to change.
So yeah, I was trying to just get a debate.
But actually, that's, I think, is a lot of the things.
And people are generally lazy.
I'll just pull in OpenSSL.
I don't care what version.
I'll just pick up the open, because it will be version X today.
It'll be version Y next week.
And I'm not bothered about that.
I don't want to have an admin.
So how do we handle that?
Because it's with the growth of ecosystems that basically is what people find very convenient.
Yeah, so I don't think we have an answer to that.
I think we can get one last question, the question you had.
And then we have to stop, I think.
Yeah.
For a minute.
The question would be, how would you handle vendor dependencies that come as binaries?
Yeah, the question is, how do you handle vendor dependencies that come as binaries?
I guess you record what you know.
That's the perfect answer.
Actually this is probably the answer in general to any question you record what you know.
So actually, you want to record it in as formal way as possible.
Just like for the cargo go dependencies, actually our source store will have the log file which
has the exact information of the dependencies.
It's just not something that you want to go and crawl through afterwards to reconstruct
it.
Would it be doable to have two phases?
First, download the sources.
Then you are in a container.
You cut internet.
Well, you stop the interfaces and you build.
So that's more a remark to the offline build thing.
So to solve the offline build problem, what you can do is cut the build in two phases.
The first phase where you just do downloads.
And then you have a download territory which you expose to the second phase where you do
the actual processing.
And the problem, but there are two problems with that which I don't think are solved in
either Yokto or Biltroot.
The first one is that you actually to do the downloads you need some tools which you have
to build.
You need to do the cargo downloads.
You have to build cargo first.
But that means that you don't completely separate your build.
You can't completely separate your build and your download step because you need to build
something to download something.
And the second issue, I forgot what the second issue was.
But we need the tools to support.
People don't realize.
You need your tools for that.
So you can maybe do something like a download step, a build step, a download step, a build
step, but it's getting complicated.
We're out of time.
Yeah, we're out of time.
Thank you.