Yeah, hello everyone.
My name is Shaheem and I am Gaurav with me.
We both are working for a Phasology community and we are from Siemens.
So maybe let me start.
So Phasology is open source license compliance project.
Initially it was published by HP in 2008 and in 2015 it has become Linux Foundation Collaboration
Project and Phasology is a Linux application.
It works on Linux distributions and different tasks done for OSS license compliance by Phasology
are scanning for licenses, copyrights, authorships, emails and ECC statements.
Apart from this we have key words and IPRS statements as well.
And we also generate documentation like Readme OSS text documentation and unified report
as well.
And then we have export and import of SPDX files.
So maybe we can discuss about SPDX files later in the slides.
So Phasology is about finding the licenses as I said already.
So we scan for the source code.
So the source code might have the license text, reference to the license text or written
text explaining some licensing and then we might also have the license relevant statements.
So this all will be identified by Phasology.
And later we have uploaded a component called Thrift which is Apache source code and Phasology
have found Apache license.
Apart from Apache license we have many more licenses.
It is because it is very natural that OSS project reuses the available OSS from other
projects.
For example if you see Phasology have found 25 other relevant licenses apart from Apache
2.0.
So what is the uniqueness about Phasology is we have conclusions.
So if you take licensing it can be simple but it might be challenging as well because
you might see some unknown written statements about licenses.
Some licenses might be unclear and there might be some incomplete license statements as well.
So actually to do this I think one required a good domain knowledge.
So yeah, Esbom and Phasology.
So we are producers of Esbom as well as the consumers.
So Phasology produces Esbom in SPDX version 2.3 format which includes the file level information,
license findings and its conclusions and copyrights as well as the custom license text.
So as a consumer Phasology import all this information and add it to a component as well.
So more information about the Esbom will be discussed later in the slides.
So yeah, maybe Gaurav will take over and explain about the releases and more SPDX features
of Phasology.
Thank you.
Thanks.
So yeah, with Phasology we recently released few versions and in all of them we majorly
try to sync our license set with the SPDX license set so we are up to date.
And at the same time we are continuously working to improve our REST API so we can provide
more automation flexibility to anyone who is interested to use it.
And like recently we had some GDPR updates thanks to our hands like how the user data
will be managed in the server and things like that.
We recently updated to Bootstrap UI.
We are planning to move to React.
But yeah, it's in the works.
With 4.1 we recently integrated scan code so you can upload your source code to Phasology
itself and let Phasology scan using its own scanners or if you prefer you can also use
scan code and import the license findings in Phasology itself.
We also worked a little on our copyright false positive reduction using spaCy and with the
latest release so we would like to say we are reuse.software-standard-compliant in our
source code and we also try to display the information like whatever reuse linter provides.
So you can check if any project supports reuse standard, they do it like that.
So Phasology can you can very easily know how much scan you have to do.
So we are coming to the recent updates with SPDX within Phasology.
So since it's a pretty old project and we had some difficulty to comply to the SPDX
standards, so we decided to take on the challenge in two steps.
So first step is done what we are presenting and the second is actually a work in progress.
So what we initially started with the pain point was the license name which gets end
up in the report.
So Phasology initially used short names which are supposed to be unique and they are actually
used for identification internally in Phasology.
So we added a new field called SPDX ID so where you can have different variants of the
same license, so for example in a license there is a copyright by X but for a different
one the same license with a copyright Y. So the license text changes but you can still
use the same SPDX ID for both of them and that will be end up in the report whatever
you generate.
In case the SPDX ID is missing or is not in the SPDX license list so we also perform a
check on that.
So it will be converted as a license ref and we have introduced this license ref for Solg
prefix for that.
In the upcoming updates we will further enhance this and provide users way to write actual
SPDX license expressions including the and or and with exceptions.
So with the reports with various DocFest with SPDX we came to understand that many of our
reports were flawed.
So we tried to fix them as well as at the same time update it to the latest spec 2.3.
So what was wrong?
So the extracted licensing info was missing.
So as I said you can have your own custom license text in for Solg so if any of the
file has a finding of that license text or a conclusion on it.
So the license text itself was missing from the report so we have fixed that and also
the package verification code used by SPDX.
The algorithm internally was a little wrong so a minor fix.
And then at the same time we compared the spec and the fields which for Solg can store.
So we figured out like we can have the version information as well in the report the release
date along with external ref to like PURLs, Maven, Nougat and such stuff.
And at the same time for Solg also allows you to manage your acknowledgments and obligations.
So we use the attribution text field for providing acknowledgments to specific files and the
same attribution text field for the entire package if you have any obligation related
to a license.
And also the calculation of conjunctive licenses and disjunctive license set was wrong.
So yeah there for Solg has a special license called dual license.
So yeah we have fixed how we are going to calculate that now.
So not every license in the report is now a disjunctive license set.
And yeah also at the same time added the missing license name and text also for the listed
licenses.
So yeah with that I guess pretty much all our SPDX reports should now be valid.
So yeah thank you and please consider starting us on GitHub if you do use them and if you
have any questions.
Yes please.
Which format do you use for SPDX?
So the question is which format we use for SPDX.
So for Solg currently supports the IDF and the tag value format.
Yeah.
I have a question about the SPDX IDE because this is something that we need to use it all
the SPDX IDE that would end up in the SPDX file.
And then the license text with the name of the copyright order where does it end up in
the original SS or also in the SPDX.
Okay.
So yeah the question is like with the SPDX IDE if there is a custom license text how
it ends up in the report.
So you have with SPDX IDF format.
So it's a self-contained report so it will contain your SPDX ID the license name as well
as your custom license text along with all the other various formats which for Solg supports
read me or assess your unified report they will work the same.
It's just that instead of using the license name which was coming from the short name
field we are going to use the SPDX ID field now.
Yeah but how do you include the text the license in the SPDX file?
Okay.
Otherwise you get only.
So if you see here SPDX has this field called license text.
So you can include information like name of the license, license ID, its text if you have
any external ref and such stuff.
So it's there for IDF.
For tag value I'm not very sure we need to check because for custom text they do support
it for tag value format as well but yeah for standard they do not.
Any more questions?
Thank you very much.
I still say any support is back in the day.
You are kind of correct.
Thank you.
Give me your colleague.
The next question is here song, song?
Take off.