Okay, thanks. So, hi everyone. So, we're about to present you the Ermin project. So, for
those who were here on Friday, I can't talk close to the microphone.
It's only for the video. Okay, sorry. So, yeah, it's the same project that we mentioned on
Friday and hopefully the presentation will be easier to understand. Also, because I'm
with Nico Atoza. Okay. So, I'm with Nico Atoza from Orange
Oula in terms of the general idea of the project. Thank you.
Okay, speaking now. So, what's Ermin, a man apart from a really nice animal, which does
take an age in French. So, it's quite a young project. It's been existing for a year now,
initiated by InnoCube and joined by five other large French companies.
We're trying to do things properly. We haven't joined an organization yet, Foundation, but
that's planned. We have three committees. That's important.
A legal committee, because you'll see later it's all around legal respect, made by jurists,
mostly for jurists. And then, well, we do use a FERO or DBL and so on and so forth.
Can you move to the next? Right. So, we're building something new.
And well, we think so. And we do rely on existing well-established
touring. All of those have been hearing about it all
day. Let's move to the next one. Probably know these ones.
Right. So, the nice part. What it's all about. So, the idea is to really implement your open
source policy. So, we take on one hand all the license texts
from the open source licenses. We break them down into obligations. So, do you have to
disclose a source code, mention the authors and so on and so forth?
On the other hand, we take S-BOMS from the project and we enrich it with legal and technical
context. In the middle, that's where the magic happens. We kind of apply your open source
policy. And out of this, we get on one hand, we get
a validation or not. Is it okay to use that license in that context?
And on the other hand, you get a nice list of obligations you really have to follow,
because you have plenty of obligations and plenty of context. Sometimes you have to follow
them. Sometimes it depends on the context. That's the big picture.
And that's next to Kenny. So, before talking about S-BOMS itself,
you have to have a kind of preparatory case. So, that's license analysis.
It's because the tool was mainly designed for IP lawyers, but we are not familiar with
the open source licenses. So, what we wanted to do is to be able for
them to save time while still being confident in the decisions that were made.
So also, it was important. It's a shared tool. But of course, every company has its own open
source policy, so it had to be flexible enough. So, the first aspect is kind of a pedagogical
framework that will allow lawyers to systematically and consistently analyse open source licenses.
And that will also mean that if it's analysed systematically, we can handle the decision
programmatically to a certain extent. And as I was saying, I mean, the idea is also
to share interpretations, because if you have a broader consensus about interpretations,
then that will increase legal predictability and then to reduce legal risks.
So when we do license analysis, it's basically breakdown in three parts.
The first part is just the global characteristics of the licenses, like about the copyright
level, the types of rights granted, like if you have patent grants, stuff like that.
I mean, technical things like the choice of law of venue, etc.
And the more important is your policy status. I mean, if you always allow it, if you never
allow it, or if you allow it depending on context. But then if you allow it depending
on context, well, you'll have to specify which context it's allowed in.
And if your context is based on simple enough facts, you will be able to automate that.
So for instance, you can have two sub-category of context. You will have a technical context.
I mean, typically, how if it has been modified or not, if it's the type of linking it has
with your code base. But also you can associate it to a category of your products, which means
that a product for which the IP will be treated differently.
I mean, typically, in many cases, you won't accept to have a GPL v2. But if you do embedded
Linux, of course you will accept it. So that will not depend on the technical nature of
the third party components or it's linking to your code base. It really, really depends
on the business expectations that you are doing on the final projects.
And so we can automate that. And the third party, it's the breaking down of each license
in obligation. And each regulation will be triggered at two levels. The first one is
if it has been modified or not. Because in many cases, I mean, you have many obligations
that you don't care about just because you're just redistributing unmodified third party
components. And the second one is the type of expectations, which means do you distribute
it? I mean, a source has been a binary. Or do you provide network interaction? Et cetera.
And also, I mean, when you break down different licenses, you will realize that very often
you have very similar obligations. I mean, they're not phrased in the same way. But you
can decide and that the choice of the lawyer that actually is equivalent in the way they
have to be respected. And so you can relate that to a generic obligation. And then you
will only care about generic obligation. And you will only care about a specific obligation
when they are not related to a generic obligation. And that's about it. And so now that you have
your policy ready, you can be ready to handle S-BOMs. And I will pass you the microphone.
Thank you. OK. So that was the right hand part, the licensing obligation. Now we're
looking at the left hand part. How do you handle the S-BOM? So today, we mostly work
with the evaluated report from Oort, O-R-T, you've heard about this morning and all the
time. We're working on working with SPDX as well. There's a lot of work to be done in
this area. And we'll have to go to and support Cyclone DX in the future as well. Right. So
when you take this S-BOM, you have plenty of information, but you don't have all the
information we need on the context. Two types of information we want to add. We want to
add the technical details. So sometimes you can get it inside the SPDX report. But I guess
there's more automation we can do in this field. But we definitely need to add manually
some extra information like the technical linking, how your component is linked to your
application. The type of exploitation is what do you actually do with your components? Are
you going to distribute it on the Internet? Are you going to distribute that to your end
user? And so on and so forth. Is that a SaaS? You need to also specify if you have modified
the source codes. That makes a big difference on how you're going to trigger the license,
what you're going to have to do. And we also added recently some funding information. Where
does the money come from for a given component? Given project. So the scope comes really handy
to automate all the kind of things. Is that development dependency, build dependency, and
so on and so forth. Plenty of things we can do to automate further. But yeah. Next, please.
Right. So there's quite a lot of work to validate the S-BOMs. And this is what you see. It's
really from a legal jurist point of view. Maybe more than a technical one. So when you
get your S-BOM in, well, obviously you need a valid SPDX expression. If you don't have
the SPDX expression, you don't know what you're talking about. So you need to know what license
you have. Well, number two is a very specific case where when you want to have a choice
to the user, you say it's either a GPL or MIT, quite often the developers tend to write
this one and this one. But what they really mean is this one or this one. So we added
a specific step to fix this particular problem. Type of exploitation we mentioned earlier.
You have also to choose when you have this choice, MIT or GPL, at some point you have
to decide which one you're going to select. Right. And all those licenses have to be reviewed
by legal persons. They have to be what came and explained earlier. If that has not been
done, then you have to go back to your jurist and say please analyze this license. And there's
plenty of things that we did to automate this because it can be a lot of work. We're not
going into details now. But in particular, we're working on exporting the curation methods
to ORTs so you don't have to redo this in the future. Right. Return.
Okay. So actually the interest of the tool is to combine the two aspects. And when you
combine the two aspects, you end up with a list of obligations that you actually have
to follow for your release. And so the idea is that it will really get rid of everything
that is not actually needed. And also we have introduced this idea of a core set of obligations
is that you don't necessarily, I mean, it's not always efficient to stick to the bare
minimum of obligations. Typically you have licenses like BSD0 or unlicensed. They don't
ask you to put license in the documentation. But it's more efficient to have the same process
for every license and also for many reasons to do so. Also it allows you to classify your
obligations as part of something normal. You know that you won't have any extra efforts
or any special attention to put into your release because it's in your core set of
general obligations. And so that gives you free time to actually concentrate on what
is specific and more important. And also another thing that you get, it gives you a global
visibility. And the different sort of components you have in your project. So it's rather
easy for instance if you have log4j you can search for log4j and it will give you the
different products and release which are involved. And also more importantly for us, you can
know which of the third party components you are most relying on. And also it gives you
a direct link to funding them. But it's because it's quite important to actually care about
funding the third party components you rely on. And that's about it.
Thank you. So where are we now? The project is ongoing obviously. We don't really have
a 1.0 version yet. It's on the way. It's not really used in production yet. Maybe you do
actually in a cube. Yeah, but we are not the typical users.
We shall have one soon. Source code is available on GitLab.com. And we do, so we are talking
about this breaking down of the licenses into obligations. That's a lot of work. And some
of it is already available on GitLab as well. So you can have a look at this. And yeah,
if you want to come, we speak back English but we are friendly. If you want to add something.
Maybe because we have some time I can... Yeah, yeah. I think. Just to say on this particular
side of the legal obligations, the idea is to also share with the project a set of licensees,
sets of interpretations that can be shared by everyone. Yes.
How are you going to deal with the back of the Syco DX only has one license field? And
does not differentiate between conclusions and what's detected?
Yeah. So just to repeat, how are we going to... Yeah, yeah. I'm doing that. How do we
handle the fact that Syco DX only has one license field? I have no idea. Do you?
We have just started implementing it. Because historically we have always been working with
SPDX and that's quite natural. But we realized that some tools...
Are you just going to assume it's included when you see something there? Yeah. We'll have to see how it goes.
We have first started to submit some PS to their specifications because we had additional needs,
like support for scopes and stuff like that. So we know that they come from security. They don't
come from license. So it's really two different roles. I think that they'll have to evolve at
some stage. But they seem very open to suggestions. But we're still implementing it. Yes. Thomas?
How would you say Herbine is different than Ford? Ford also has a policy engine and
reports and all that stuff. So as you know it, I mean, basically it started as a front end for
OAuth. Because we wanted to have a graphical interface. So technically it's a Django app.
And we have an API based on Django REST. So we want to stay as close as OAuth,
including to the concept, as possible. But it works a bit differently. And that's why, I mean,
when we make curations, we wanted to make them exportable as OAuth formats. And we also plan to
be able to export your license policy and the OAuth format to be as compatible as possible.
But the main difference is that it has a central database. I mean, just like when you used to use
as OAuth 360, it brings the same functionality. So that's about that. And we really want to stay
as close to OAuth. And that's why we contribute to OAuth when we can. Did I answer your question?
Can I just ask? Sorry. Thank you. Yeah, there really is a lot of work around
working on the licenses and sharing interpretations. So this is part, if you download Herbine and you
execute it, it comes with a set of decisions and interpretations that you can use that you should
actually read and make your own. But I guess that's on top of all. Sorry.
Yeah. Actually, maybe I think it is. But for instance, I mean, we mainly rely on
the model of OAuth, which is kind of semi-official. I'm not sure it's really publicly
documented. The evaluated model. Okay. Yeah, I mean, the code is public. But that's really,
I mean, the kind of information we like, it's like we have scopes. And we have it in also
sub-projects. Because when you scan, for instance, you can have your composer.json and your package.
It's easy to say, okay, this is my dependency for my backend. These are the
execution dependencies. And it comes naturally. I think it could be implemented in a SPU. But I
don't think it's present in a, okay. So because initially, I mean, we wanted to stick as much as
possible. So we say, okay, we will interface with OAuth through SPU. But it was not really convenient.
Sorry.
Sorry. Could you speak up, please?
we need to deliver information to your customers.
So currently, we are focused on legal things,
and mostly related to IP.
We tend to also include export control,
because that's quite easy.
Regarding security, it's a whole different subject.
And actually, in the first prototype,
we had a link with a vulnerable coder.
So it can be done, but it's not that trivial.
And currently, all of the partners
are treating the security aspect with their own tools.
So it's not a priority for us.
But yeah, I mean, we would be happy to be able to handle it.
So did I answer your question?
OK, thanks.
Well, the points we take, I mean, at the orange at least,
is that Hermine is one part of the whole thing,
and we're going to work on interfacing it
with some other tools like dependency track
and that kind of things.
The point is being to have one source, one database,
of all the components that we use within the group.
And so you can use it from different perspectives.
OK.
So the question was, how do we handle incompatible open source
licenses?
For the moment, we don't.
That was discussed on Friday.
And it's not that trivial, because you first
have to understand the relationship between the two
components.
Because currently, what we handle
is the relationship between a third party component
and your code base.
But you can have incompatibility between two
different third party components.
So you have to qualify the technical relationship
between those two.
And that's a bit tricky.
And I think Friday we realized many people
want to work on the question.
I mean, we really want to be part of this discussion.
Yes, but?
You could use Ords as the results for class compatibility.
So you can actually do different things already.
OK.
You can export from Hermine into Ords
or class compatibility checks from Orzal.
So German open source foundation,
they published a license compatibility matrix, which
has been included in Ords and then you can decide to do it.
Is it perfect?
No, but it is possible.
Yes, I think that Orzal has lawyers inside.
They are working on the legal side officially.
At least in Germany.
Well, we do have a few lawyers on the order.
So.
Yeah.
And by the way, I mean, there's no competition.
And we had a very interesting discussion
with Orzal and we really plan to cooperate with them.
And that's our to-do list in the beginning.
It's just that we lack time.
But yeah, I mean, we really want,
I mean, we really will work with them in the future on that.
And anyone next who is interested.
So you have another question.
Yes, please.
Just to remember, guys, that we need
to integrate everything with the system.
So you are not alone.
You are not to us.
We are trying to do the work in the future.
I was discussing last Friday.
We had to work in a common way to do
the things that are so obvious.
Sorry, I mean, you're talking about SW360?
Well, I'm doing things for Orzal.
OK.
I'm a content worker at SW360.
Yeah, I mean, just for your information,
we contributed documentation back in the day.
And we wanted to go the SW360 way.
But that was before the project was reborn.
Because there was this, so we needed it.
I can talk to you about that a lot.
But we really wanted to go the SW360 way.
And we couldn't.
So once again, we are all for collaboration.
Yeah, we can talk about that later.
Oh, yeah, Bradley.
Do you have any plans to assist your users in meeting
their legal obligations?
Or are you just trying to identify
what the legal obligations are and not actually
assist in meeting them?
I know.
I mean, we do.
I mean, sorry.
Could be the question.
I'm sorry.
The question was, do we assist the clients
to meet the obligation or just indent the agent?
Well, ideally, both.
Because the idea is also that for each general obligation
that you have, so then they can identify a generic process
to do it and to do it the right way.
I mean, that means that that will be really
compliant with each license that requires it.
For instance, providing the corresponding source code
and stuff like that.
So you're working on a system to prepare
the corresponding source for these?
Oh, no, no.
Sorry.
We don't do executions of the obligation.
I misunderstood your question.
But we are really happy to be able to branch out.
But I'm not sure if it can be done automatically.
I know that in some built system, it can be done.
But the problem is so that it will really
depend on each built system.
And for instance, just for having a notice file,
there was a very interesting talk about build as well.
And I really believe in that.
But the problem, for instance, if you take the Node.js
ecosystem, you have many different built systems.
And some of them have this kind of automatic function
to generate notice attribution.
Just the only problem is that they're wrong.
And so we're uncomfortable relating something
that we know.
I mean, we can't pretend, oh, it's wrong.
We didn't know.
I mean, that's the problem that we have checked.
And so for one's response to source code,
I think we had very interesting talks about embedded system.
And I think that they are trust-stable.
So we prefer to refer to that.
Because I mean, they are doing it.
And the process could be just point them to that.
I don't know if they understand.
Yeah.
Sorry.
We do have a REST API.
So the idea is to provide one piece of the whole chain
and probably it's not.
OK.
Do we have a question?
Thank you.
That's all right.