So this session is a panel discussion by four or three people.
And the basic idea that we're going to be discussing is the
whole idea always bonds, right?
Their usefulness, caveats of using them, and all these
wonderful things.
The rest of the day, everybody was talking about these
bonds as like something that has to be there, and we all
know what information has to be there.
But maybe this is not so obvious to anyone, and the
whole idea is to discuss the idea of these bonds.
So we have, for the moment, three panelists.
And the format will be that they will be doing a very
short introduction of the problem statement, if you
want, right.
And then after these three short introductions, we'll go
into more discussions, and we obviously will value audience
participation.
So first up.
Right.
Oh, right.
OK, afternoon.
My name's Anthony Harrison.
I used to work for a very large system integrator, so the
work on functional safety was very close at heart.
And certainly they got things like the Siemens team as well,
very similar to the sort of things I used to have been
involved in for many years.
I retired a few weeks, a few months ago.
But before I left, I was trying to introduce S-bombs
into my organization.
And it was following very much on from the log4j, need,
where was the components, which systems were affected,
which customers needed to be informed, and where was our
liability, very much from a risk perspective.
So since I've retired, I've been writing Python tools.
So if you want to talk about me about some of the Python
tools I've been doing, because it's been quite interesting,
have a chat with me afterwards.
But to sort of set the scene, I think we've got four types
of users.
And it picks up on what Adolfo was saying about who's a
supplier, is a supplier a developer, is it, I've put the
word supplier in there, but basically someone who
packages things together.
It might be an embedded solution.
It might be a red hat.
It might be someone else.
And then you've got your integrators, which is like
your Siemens, people who are selling solutions to an end
user who's going to use it.
And I believe that if you are a producer of S-bombs, you
also should be a consumer of S-bombs, first and foremost,
because there should be value to you in what you are
producing, and you need to know where your
vulnerabilities are, whether you're compliant with your
licenses, as we've had lots of discussion about, but also
where are things changing?
Particularly, do you know those changes?
Are those changing happening under your control or not?
And this comes into the ecosystems, things happening
outside, you may even be repositories, et cetera.
So the first thing is, I think everybody who's a
consumer, everyone who's a generator, should also be
consuming.
So if you've seen some of the questions I've asking this
morning was when the Octo guys were saying they're
generating an S-bdx, S-bomb, are they actually using it?
I think the answer is most definitely yes, you should be.
And then what are the sort of things you should be using it
for?
We've heard a lot about vulnerability management.
On the basis, that's heavily dependent on the quality of
US-bombs.
Have you got your components uniquely identified in a way
that it can be found consistently?
Secondly, looking at license management, again, are we
consistent?
But thirdly, looking at the change management, are
versions of packages changing?
Are licenses changing?
I was turning to Kate on an open source project I'm
involved in, we generate an S-bomb every week, and we do a
build, and we are seeing components changing versions,
and the metadata is changing with those versions.
Sometimes it's getting worse.
So why have we lost the name of the supplier or the
developer?
And fourthly, I think you should be using it for
solution integrity.
Have you built what you said you've gone to design?
So we're picking up on the design S-bomb that Nico was
talking about from the safety.
I think that would be really good to actually use the S-bombs
as part of a solution integrity.
Have you built what you said you were going to build?
We saw a lot of that things with the checksums from the
Octo guys.
Have we got end of life components?
Are we planning for removing those end of life
components, obsolete components?
And are we seeing the impact of those changes on the
solution comes back onto the engineering lifecycle?
So I think all of it is supporting risk.
So ultimately, this is all about risk management.
And hopefully, S-bomb and all these are helping you make
effective decisions.
Now I'll shut up now.
But the thing just to try and just shape things for
discussion.
All right.
Thanks.
My name's Paul Noveris.
I'm a solutions engineer for a company called Anchor.
We produce a couple of open source projects that A, can
produce S-bombs in some cases, do vulnerability checks
against them so you can look up SIFT and GRIPE.
I'm not going to talk specifically about any
particular project.
I'm going to talk about the S-bombs.
I'm not going to talk specifically about any
particular projects here.
So just to hit on the topic of the panel, I'm going to just
jump into a couple of things.
Oh, well, what I do there, I'm out in the field.
So I am a solutions architect.
I'm working directly with the end users a lot of the times.
So most of my contact is with people who are on the
beginning of the learning curve.
They may not even know what an S-bomb is the first time I
talked to them, but they've been given
marching orders.
So it spans a pretty wide range.
So as far as content, the biggest thing for me is that
the S-bomb, and this seems to be somewhat of a
controversial statement sometimes, but the S-bomb
needs to be seen as a objective document that only
has factual information in it.
And does not have judgments in it.
Those things are important, but should be separated out a
lot of the times.
A lot of people probably haven't been in here all day,
but there have been off and on comments about should we
include CVEs in an S-bomb.
My opinion is probably not because those are going to
change more than the software that the S-bomb describes.
Obviously, if you rebuild the piece of software, then you
would want to build a new S-bomb.
But the S-bomb should be static as long as the software
it's describing is static.
So in the case of a Docker image, we know when that
changes because the image digest would change.
We could trigger a new build.
But we shouldn't necessarily be rebuilding those S-bombs
continually if there's nothing new there.
Now, that ignores things like maybe our scanner has gotten
better and can detect more things, obviously.
That might be an exception to that kind of rule.
The other thing, just as far as content goes, the first
thing we mentioned today, the specs, whether it's SPDX,
Cyclone DX, are extremely loose.
You can have a valid S-bomb that doesn't actually have
enough information to be useful for your
particular use case.
And what that minimum amount of useful information is might be
different depending on the use case.
So there's just something to keep in mind.
The other thing that's come up again and again today, the
quality of the S-bomb is going to be really dependent on
the tooling.
There's no way to do these things without
automation at scale.
It's just too difficult to keep up with.
The tooling is improving, but still a
long way to go, I think.
So usefulness, the main thing here for me is the S-bomb is
useful because it's going to make all the other aspects of
supply chain security better.
So one, what's in the software?
That's the S-bomb.
It's kind of foundational to all the other aspects.
Two would be things like, is the software safe to use?
Does it have vulnerabilities?
What are those vulnerabilities?
What is my license?
Am I at risk for some kind of compliance issue there?
Those kind of safety issues, whether you, I don't want to
use that term after seeing the
operational safety discussion.
The other thing, provenance, where is this coming from?
If you know what's in that software, having that
assurance of where it comes from and what's in there
together is much more powerful.
And then things like reproducibility.
It's really esoteric, very difficult to actually achieve
in practice.
But if you have an S-bomb, a high quality S-bomb, it can be
effectively a recipe towards that.
And that can also help you prove some of the other things
that you've seen or we've been talking about.
A lot of this is difficult, though.
We've seen a lot of things about opaque artifacts and
things, the difficulty of actually scanning at build time,
which may produce a higher quality S-bomb, but at a lot
of costs, performance and other things.
So that kind of leads us into the caveats.
The main thing here is to keep in mind that our imagined
state of how we want things to be and the actual reality are
basically not the same at all.
We'll try to move towards that.
We're on a journey up the mountain,
whatever you want to say.
We're probably, like if you're climbing Mount Everest, we
probably haven't even gotten to base camp yet.
So there's a long way to go.
But the other thing, in that realm, just declaring we have
a policy to produce or store or evaluate S-bombs doesn't
actually solve the problems you're trying to solve.
There's a lot more work that has to be done.
And the last thing on caveats, things like log for shell, I
think pushed S-bombs into a lot of people's awareness,
because S-bombs were a very effective way of finding where
log for shell was affecting software.
It may have given kind of a false sense of security, just
because log for J in particular sticks out like a sore thumb.
It's very easy to find.
Things like the open SSL vulnerability just a couple of
months ago, I think, may have been a reality check there.
There are a lot of cases where you might have something like
open SSL in software that you're consuming without
even knowing it.
It's a lot easier to hide.
So just kind of a reality check, bring some people back
to Earth a little bit.
And then the last thing is just, in addition to producing
S-bombs, one caveat is you have to think about managing
them after you produce them, storing them, being able to
search them, purge the ones you don't need anymore.
That's been a topic of a couple of times.
We don't want to keep more information than we really
need, so how do we know when it's safe or reasonable to get
rid of some of this data?
Much less, how are we going to search through it when we need
to find it?
I think that covers it for now.
I'll go ahead and pick them up over time anyway.
Thank you.
Like you, I've attended more panels than I've been on, and
I don't like a panel that is a series of talks.
And I did hear Alexo say that I needed to make a very brief
introduction, so I promise I'm timing here.
I'll be under 2 and 1,500 minutes.
My favorite childhood, I'm Bradley Kuhn.
I work for an organization, a charity called the Software
Freedom Conservancy.
I've been, my primary job has been related to copy left
license compliance since 1997.
And so I've seen a lot with regard to that issue, which
does interact quite frequently with the issue that you are
here to discuss today of software bills and materials.
My favorite childhood story, by the way, is the story of the
emperor has no clothes.
And I found throughout my career in open source and free
software that I'm often the only one willing to say that
our emperors have no clothes.
I think S-Bombs is a case where that needs to be said,
at least to a certain extent.
The most useful application of S-Bombs is in cases where you
are in an organization that produces proprietary and open
source software together in products.
If you are an organization that is 100% open source and free
software and choose a copy left license, your usefulness of
S-Bombs is extremely limited, almost to the point that you
may not even want to invest in getting involved in this kind
of thing.
Now I'm a realist and realize that almost all of you
probably work for organizations, including the
trade associations among you, that produce lots of
proprietary software.
As such, you're going to have to worry about all these
issues we've been hearing about today.
Many of the tools today look very interesting to me to
solve those kinds of problems.
But I want to leave you with one thought, if I can.
That is, imagine if there was no proprietary software in your
organization, that you didn't sell it, you didn't use it, and
you didn't want to make it.
And instead, you chose to look at the requirements of the
copy left licenses, like the GPL, which require you to
produce the complete corresponding source code as a
reproducible build every time you produce a binary.
And you have to make that available to every customer
you have.
S-bombs are most often needed when you don't necessarily
have all the source code to hand, or don't know if it's
going to be to hand when you get something
from another vendor.
So my argument is that the level of effort that's being
put into S-bombs is primarily to enable the continued
production of proprietary software.
Being a FOSDEM and being a free software activist my
whole career, that's generally not something that I'm that
excited about, which is why I'm not
excited about S-bombs.
OK, so we heard of any statements about uses, about
general use and caveats of using them, and why they're
not needed.
In an ideal world, they're not needed.
OK, let's go back to that.
Broadly, even if in an ideal world where an organization is
producing free and open source software and following license
obligations, they provide all the source for every release
they're doing.
There might still be the use case that I want to find out
which of my releases, slash products, or whatever you want
to call them, contain a version of a library.
Right.
So if you have a lot of source code, there's this great tool
called grep.
And what you can do is you can search the entire source code
and look if a version of something is in there.
If you have all the source code for everything, and you
never separate the source from the binary, why does grep
not work?
You tell me.
Because it's easier to search a table of contents than the
complete book.
That's why we have table of contents and indexes.
Since things have become electronic, I generally just
search the PDF of the text in grep anymore.
I don't use table of contents.
Really?
OK.
OK, so we have a source file.
I used to write C. I used to be full of hash.
If defs.
So how do I, if I search the source code, I will find a
line of code.
But it's not telling me whether that line of code was
actually compiled into the binary and now actually on my
architecture and target hardware.
So how do we get around that?
So we've talked about having a trail of evidence from the
source code to a binary so we can then match the two
together.
If we have different compile options, I would expect we'll
get different binaries, I hope.
So therefore, how do we accommodate that?
Just to keep the argument going.
I'd love to.
And so in the world I'm imagining, which
does not exist, I agree with you.
This is why you have to do this work.
Because the world that I've been working towards my whole
career doesn't exist.
But if it did, and all software was under the ephiro GPL,
you would be required every time you build a binary to
make sure you had a reproducible build that can
produce that binary.
So when you found a vulnerability in that binary,
you would have stored the complete corresponding source
release right next to all the binaries.
You take the binary that's sitting out in the field, you
compare the checksum to the binary in your repository of
binaries and source code, and voila, there's your source
code release that you made at the time you
build it years ago.
Simple enough.
I mean, I get it, right?
Yes, theoretically, we should be able to reproduce
everything 100%.
But in practice, we don't do things like inspect every jar
of food that's coming off the assembly line.
We only inspect some of them just for
scalability purposes.
So the S-bomb still has a value there in providing a
shortcut so that you don't have to do a bunch of work
over and over and over again on demand every time.
I get it, though.
You're right.
In an ideal universe, that would be true.
We have unlimited time, unlimited compute resources to
do all these reproducible builds.
In practice, though, even if there aren't constraints on
time and compute resource, reproducible builds are
extremely limited in, you know, I mean, it takes a lot of
replacement for reproducible builds.
No, no, no, no.
But they can approximate a lot of what you would get out of
it, not everything.
No, not everything.
But you can approximate some things, right?
So I don't, I mean, I agree with you in principle that
reproducible builds would prove a lot of things,
everything, right?
That would absolutely solve a lot of problems.
But I don't know if everybody is really willing to do, to
live in that world.
My view is be the change you want to be in the world.
That's why I support what the bill is instead of investing
in S-bomb.
No.
I think part of our disagreement here of
different views is the slide that Kate showed in the
beginning, that we're not talking about an S-bomb.
There are different types of S-bombs, right?
And there are S-bombs that apply to the source, and there
are S-bombs showing what the build is or what the deploy
thing is, and stuff like that, right?
Now, to Bradley's point, once you have everything
documented and provided, people can recreate this
information, right?
So the grip example that Bradley said, this is looking
at the source, right?
But if the obligations are, we don't only give the source,
but also the build instructions and all the
scripts that the license obligations require, right?
So people can go and recreate it and then try to find out
this formation, right?
But so the information will be there, right?
The question is how easy we want you to have, right?
Sorry, you wanted to.
Yeah.
You?
I want to take questions.
All right.
Yeah.
Let's try.
Maybe one more.
So I think I completely agree with you that it is better to
take such decisions on the sources.
But what is missing to do this is that the current
vulnerability databases that we have, only reference
vulnerabilities in giving it names, naming components.
So there is a link missing about the vulnerability is
present in this file, in this function, with this method
signature, and so forth.
And so I do not know what you want to search for.
If you only search for CPP, blah, blah, blah, you will not
be able to catch all instances of the vulnerable code,
because maybe a product has been trapped.
We named the code has been founded, and so forth.
So that is, I think, lacking.
OK.
So the comment was that, for example, vulnerability
information does not usually refer to specific source files
and lines on the source file.
But it refers to product names or library names or whatever.
So in order to find something, you have to look for these,
right, and not for the fine grain that we're talking about
in a grip part.
Right.
Yeah.
Thomas.
So I know we talked a lot about S-Robot security and licensing.
But funny enough, how Oort started
had nothing to do with our licensing history at all.
We basically wanted the CTO to have a method.
What software are we using in general?
What are open source proprietary?
So we, as a whole organization, can see,
even all of our sources can see the other edge of what
are we doing and where can we go more
efficient and where should we invest in the leverage
that we should be done.
And by doing them all as goals and having all the stuff,
we actually still want to reduce it.
And then we actually directed these in your organization.
We're like, OK, yeah, you guys are using Ruby.
You guys are using Java.
Actually, we are all standardized in this.
Actually, the company actually saved a lot of money.
But this is organized.
So again, this is often forgotten
that S-Bombs can be a great way to basically
build your building software more efficient.
And that alone for that, I would build S-Bombs, even
if by COVID's complete deal of source.
All right.
So repeating for the mic, sorry.
The comment was that S-Bombs, while we're
talking about uses in compliance and security,
can also be used in a lot of other ways
and can be very useful in this strategy.
For example, having a software catalog of components
being used by different parts of the company.
Sorry, Anton.
Couldn't I give you a second, right?
No.
I know.
So I totally agree, Thomas.
I think certainly the larger organizations,
I think we probably got that discussion a bit
with Siemens this morning.
No criticism.
Big organizations have very difficult to share things.
And so if you had S-Bombs of your build
and then started having a way of identifying common building
blocks, I will hesitate to say the word products,
or different instances of the same product,
then yes, there must be some business opportunities
to, A, save money, or B, be more efficient.
And I don't know whether anyone is starting to see that
or starting to say that.
I don't know whether you started seeing that, Thomas,
with your and your own industry.
So just to be clear, I now work on Alpin, Finos,
to see how we can build S-Bombs for them.
All of their code is fully open.
If you had an S-Bomb, then you can also
see where are people contributing.
Because we can resolve every project to sources.
And both what they hold, so you have to actually figure out,
OK, these are where people are contributing.
These are people using these libraries.
So we can do Finos projects on a basis that include,
we have here people, here people, we need more job guys.
Here and here are already people who
are using this particular library.
So these people and this Finos project
can probably help those projects, that Finos project,
solve things.
And so it doesn't matter.
The size of the mission doesn't matter.
It's really about building software efficiently.
Yeah.
And it's all right?
Sorry.
OK, so I think what Thomas is saying
is, even if things are fully open,
then it's going to help as well.
I would also agree that whether proprietary software still
exists.
I used to work in the defense sector.
That's never going to go open source.
It uses open source, but it's not
going to use fully open source for obvious reasons.
But we've got to keep those separate.
And actually, businesses need to see those separate anyway.
And S-Bombs is potentially a good way of sharing them.
And also handling some of the things like export control
that I think one of the projects said this morning
was actually handling export control things, which is also
an interesting thing that, obviously, some
of the licenses, the open source licenses,
don't have that constraint.
But businesses do.
And we have to recognize that.
No, I just was going to add just to that.
I think that's the other thing we saw earlier this morning
with the S-W360, right?
Identifying the components that are reused over and over again
kind of goes right in with that, right?
Saying, OK, this component, it might only
have two people working on it, but it
is used in 19 different products that our company produces.
That may, from a management perspective,
when we go to devote resources, whether it's
additional headcount, whatever it is, right?
We know that's a project that is key to everything else
we're doing, right?
So yeah, I think that does help.
Again, it's something you probably
could reverse engineer by looking at who's
pulling from a Git repository or whatever.
But it would be very difficult to look at.
You'd have to time things.
And yeah, it would be hard.
And to be clear, I agree completely.
Many of the tools we saw today, and generally speaking,
S-BOMs are a wonderful tool to aid
in the production of proprietary software and mixed proprietary
open-source software.
And I think all of you who are in that business,
you should probably be working and doing more with S-BOMs
because you're going to need it.
I agree.
But I just am not in that business.
I don't want a world with proprietary software.
I want a world with free software.
And in the free software world, the better place to,
you have to pick where resources go,
the better place to focus resources
is in reproducible builds, not S-BOMs.
If the amount of funding and effort
going into S-BOM technology right now
was going into reproducible builds technology,
I think we would get better gains.
So it's a question of where limited resources are being
deployed more than it is whether or not S-BOMs are useful.
I agree completely.
They are.
Are they more useful than things we could be doing elsewhere
with those resources?
Yeah, go on.
Again, many of our main works of commercial companies
like coming in from the start.
But on the other side, we are maintainers of open source
projects.
So we do open source projects.
And I personally, I do not care about detail licenses
so much.
My software is licensed by the MIT.
I want everybody to use the software that's at maximum.
So from my perspective, I would like to have S-BOMs
and my open source projects make it more easy for other people
to consume them.
So this is ideal software because I like it
and because I like other people using it.
So this is for our own opinion.
And having the good overview about the topic and point
that you use is also a good way to tell other people what
kind of open source components are
in view under the global license.
So I'm sorry, but I'm just bringing up the idea
that I need to use the source code for everything
and tell everybody that you want to know something
and then you need to go to all the source code.
I want to provide good information for other people
who would like to use my open source.
OK, so the point here was that even when producing open source
license software, you find S-BOM useful for telling people
what your software uses or for documenting your software,
essentially.
OK?
Please.
There's an expression of that because if you
have this one automatically in a component,
in an open source component, and I have the whole process
automated inside a company, I have mostly almost no lawyer
in my back because they know exactly what is coming there.
They know where it's coming from.
And we have the data.
And usually, they don't understand.
OK, it's passing by this one.
And this one, you know, we don't need to care about this thing.
So we do have this information already here,
completely set up in the system and say, OK, this is the note.
We know.
So we can approve the new level company.
Without this information, it's always the same time.
We just can't.
We need to go to discussions.
We need to see if the company is losing money and time.
OK.
How do I summarize that?
S-BOMs are also useful for getting legal approval
for using software or something like that.
Yeah.
Thank you, Harry.
Sorry.
And this is probably going to be an open question now
to the audience of those who are generating S-BOMs now.
Open source project I'm involved in is Python-based.
And it supports 3.7 to 3.11.
We generate an S-BOM every week in both Cyclone DX and SPDX
for each version of Python.
And each version of Python generates a different S-BOM
because you've got different dependencies that
are version specific.
So I have, depending on the version of Python,
I may have, I think there's about 25 direct dependencies.
But then when you get the implicit ones,
it gets about another 30.
Some of them have got 50-odd dependencies.
Some have got 60.
So I agree with your comment about publicizing it.
But are people picking up the right version
so they are aware of what your software is using
because your software use will change?
I think you forgot the platform, so you need to do a Windows.
Oh, yeah, yes.
OK, so.
And you change your pictures and get armed and the system's
like, OK.
Brilliant.
Glad you picked that up.
So therefore, so are we capturing
that information in the standards?
Consistently.
Yes.
I'm not.
And the standard is one thing, actually collecting it
and storing it in the actual S-bomb that you're producing.
Right, just to repeat that.
The standard allows for that, but doesn't guarantee
that when you produce the S-bomb that that information will
get, A, collected or B, recorded, which is a huge problem
with usually it's a tooling problem, usually.
And we've seen tooling improve a lot.
But again, it's the journey from where we would like to be,
ideally, from where we are now.
It just takes time and effort, obviously.
But that's the number one problem I see in the field,
is that the tooling is not producing either complete
results or consistent with other tools.
I mean, we saw a ton of examples of that,
where tools are producing different results yet.
May I ask that?
Do you know why they're going to survive,
especially with open source science?
It's the level of education that is why the tooling developers
are guarding this topic is widely varied.
So I've been producing S-bombs and all this stuff
for more than seven years.
I've spoken to more lawyers and package managers
to develop it than I care about.
Everybody thinks that package managers can
make that easy.
It is not.
Right, yes.
So to summarize that point, he's been producing S-bombs
for seven years.
And it's not just a matter of querying a package manager
and being done.
We see that all the time.
I work in containerized software mostly,
so a lot of the S-bombs I see produced
are actually produced after the build,
because somebody pulls a base image.
There's no S-bomb for that base image to consume today.
Hopefully, in the future, there will be.
But those things that are in those base images, a lot of times
are opaque.
It may be open source software, but it's
a Rust binary that doesn't have audit information compiled in.
And there have been improvements in that.
Go puts audit information into the binaries.
Rust can do it, but doesn't do it by default yet.
So there's still, yes, a ton of that.
And so the rest of his point was the developer education,
it's one thing to be aware of S-bombs as a concept.
It's another thing to be aware of, the limitations, what
has to be accounted for when you're building them,
when you're producing software in general.
There's just a lot of plates spinning all at the same time.
Maybe to add to that, and we have a little talk on Friday,
but please do not reinvent the wheel.
If you need as much room, ask the community
to have all the questions you have out there.
So building it all and wasting a lot of time in everything.
It's just a good sport.
Another thing that you have from the workshop on Friday,
teaching developers is OK, but it's not the right path.
Because developers are creatures of habits,
and they will not follow you or not listen you.
Even when the deadlines are very near.
So the last comment was that developers,
it's difficult to get developers to change their behavior,
they don't listen.
Which I find too in my work, which is primarily
copy left license compliance, that to your point
I wanted to add, one of the reasons
it's probably very difficult for you,
it's not the only reason, but one of the reasons
it's difficult to build S-bombs for containers
is because nearly all containers in the world
are violating the GPL.
And so you don't have the source code
to even go and start building your S-bomb off the source
code.
You're stuck with binaries that are GPL violating.
But there is absolutely no funding available
to handle that problem in the container world
and the GPL compliant side.
So I guess you'll handle the binary side,
because you have all your S-bomb funding to fund it that way.
OK, yeah, sorry.
I'm trying to understand your point.
And the fact that you implied that if all software was open,
we wouldn't have any need to S-bombs besides perhaps
the things that they mentioned.
Even though every talk today was stuff that wouldn't matter
if all software was open.
But I'm trying to understand what your point is.
Are you implying that instead of actually being here
at Postem, pushing open source software
so that all software at some day being open source,
are you implying that we're wasting time producing stuff
that actually supports the current standard?
Completely yours.
Yeah, yeah.
That's a question for me, and I'll summarize it.
So the question was, in this imaginary world
that I proposed where all software is open source
and free software, is what I'm saying
that the effort being put into S-bombs
is actually enabling the production
of proprietary software?
And I think the answer is yes.
I think S-bombs are a system to make it easier
to ingest open source software and bring it
into proprietary software.
I came to as many of the talks as I could today
when I didn't have other obligations.
And many of the talks today were talking
about ingestion of open source for that purpose.
When you hear people talking about, oh, we
can be able to blacklist GPL stuff.
Well, the reason they want to blacklist copy left stuff
is they want to make proprietary software.
Now, it's a question of values.
The commenter over there that I think never got summarized
was pointing out that in his values,
he feels he really wants to see his software put
into proprietary software and to encourage it and make it easy.
I don't obviously agree with those values.
If you agree with those values, I agree completely.
S-bombs are a great solution to be
able to encourage the adoption of non-copy lefted software.
This is a very stark issue.
I want to give an example.
There was a talk earlier.
You can go on the internet and figure out which one it was.
But their system, when it decided,
when putting licenses in buckets,
when it saw that it was a copy left license,
they had a Python function that I found in their source
grid that says, oh, if it's a copy left or it's a license,
this Python function should return the string is-danger.
So the concept that even those writing S-bomb tools
believe that copy left is a dangerous thing
is kind of giving you a sense of the values that
are circulating around the S-bomb community, which
is unfortunate, because I think the GPL is a wonderful license,
not a dangerous one.
But I realize others in the room disagree.
Yeah?
So my question was, when we cannot see the other side
of the coin, so wouldn't that, I mean,
I'm not trying to reconcile free software and commercial
software by any means, but wouldn't that
ex-reference currency flow by the S-bomb be also
helpful for your use case in identifying
when that piece of software is being used?
The answer is no.
And I don't want to get too much into it,
but I'm going to talk about it later, because I don't want
to take too much of the time.
All right.
Kate.
Sorry.
I want open source data for use in safety critical applications.
Open source is bugs.
How can I track the bugs and fix them
so it doesn't kill people unless I know what's there?
If I'm just in the source code, all true,
I'm not going to be able to find and fix.
It's at scale.
We need to abstract to go to scale.
How do we change, how do we change what you're proposing
from that problem?
So the question is that we want to do functional safety
with open source, right?
And in order to do it on scale, we
have to abstract things outside on a higher level
than simple source code.
And talk, for example, in packages, and how, again,
the table of contents of things rather than the actual source
heights.
So I want to respond.
Off the mic, it was said there's a concern
that software is going to kill people with the implication
that without us bombs, we won't be
able to prevent the killing of people with software.
Which I agree, there is software that's killed people.
I was very taken of the Therac25 case,
which if you're in computer science, you probably studied,
which was a proprietary software system that
murdered a number of people due to a software bug.
So I agree completely that we have a long, long history
of software bugs injuring people.
My argument is that the best thing to have
when you have a binary, that you worry has a bug
and has a vulnerability, the best thing to have
is to have a completely reproducible build
for that binary.
Such that you can go and make that binary again
tens of years later, hundreds of years later,
and see again, have all the scripts used
to control compilation installation
at your fingertips for every binary produced in the world.
I agree with you that it takes a lot of resources to do that.
I would like to get to that world where that's the case,
where every person who relies on a piece of binary software
has the immediate access to the complete corresponding source
code.
There are some tools in that case
that I think should exist that don't.
I don't see anybody in this community working on them.
For example, our mind was working years ago
on this very interesting tool that
was doing orchestration through build processes, where
it was tracking exact hashes of source code that
was going into a binary.
Those kinds of things are very excellent tools
that we do need and should be created,
and they would be a great enabler to the types of things
that I'm talking about.
But I don't see S-bombs bringing us that, at least not
at the moment.
What's that name?
That's all for private tools?
That's all?
Yocto is doing it, Zephyr is doing it, hashes of the sources,
and what's those intermediates, and how does it go?
OK.
So Kate just told us the problem solved,
so we don't have to do anything more.
That's great.
Use Yocto and the problem solved, it sounds like.
OK, so the comment was that build tools, no, build platforms
like Yocto and Zephyr already record
all hashes of sources going into binaries for their platforms.
Great.
Any other questions?
Come on, people, don't be shy.
Yeah?
Yeah, I have a quick question.
So for the escorts, is the idea, and this might be a very basic
question, is the idea that we produce an escort that
represents the suspect or as large whatever combination
of tags, and that includes both build dependencies, transitive
attacks, how it depends, task dependencies, always the idea
that use a multiple of these for other facts and for us
for the happier, so that you can then operate the idea.
I have a form of vulnerability, for licensing issue
in a particular thinking way.
Let's say if it's an open SSL vulnerability,
my build tool, I probably don't have as much,
but if it's in production, I'm not going to have much.
Yocto, yeah, you'll summarize it.
Yeah, I'll summarize it.
Yeah, so the question is whether or not
the SBOM is intended to capture in addition
to the code and the dependencies.
Is it also capturing the build environment, et cetera, things
like that, right?
And the answer there is maybe.
And that's kind of one of the reasons,
like I don't know if you were here all day,
but one of the first things that we covered
was different types of SBOMs, right?
So there are SBOMs specifically for code repositories, right?
There are SBOMs specifically that
are generated at build time, right?
So yes, maybe there can be an SBOM
for the exact combination of conditions,
or there can be a more generalized SBOM, right?
And there's use cases for both of those.
How much are you able to get all of these?
Maybe, right?
Again, it depends on what you're consuming from other people,
right?
If you're consuming a Docker image, right,
it may be too late to.
You may be able to reproduce it in a, well,
let's not get into that.
I'll say one thing more about reproducible builds.
Even in the universe where we have all the data,
actually reproducing a build is extremely difficult,
and maybe even impossible in some cases, right?
Because there's just too many variables.
So I am not one to shy away from saying we should have an ideal
and work towards it, right?
I mean, absolutely.
But the level of effort to achieve one goal
is not necessarily the same amount of effort
to achieve another goal.
So.
Yeah, I guess my question was, let's
say I have something that generates that.
I'm supposed to run it multiple times while I'm
doing pipeline as opposed to running once.
And I have the answer to that.
Yeah.
It depends.
The answer is it depends.
The answer is always it depends.
But I'm just looking at the highest one, is the design one.
Now, one of the things I've heard a lot of people,
and we've talked about lists of ingredients several times
today, people nervous about putting what's in their product
because potentially people are saying, well, if you tell me
I'm using package X, Y, and Z, then a competitor
can also put X, Y, and Z together.
So are people concerned about that?
Because that's one of the things that people are saying
is delaying the adoption and the publication of that.
Or is it saying that certain S-bombs can
have that level information but with a very restricted audience
as a sink from the maybe the later down ones, which
are probably more public because they potentially
have different business needs?
That's out for that.
I'm not saying I've got a view.
Let's see, what do people think about that?
Because I'm seeing some organizations saying,
I don't want to publish my architecture,
since it's an architecture, because that potentially
is making it a community, potentially vulnerable.
My business model being vulnerable.
And go back to the market I used to work in,
my architecture was protected under certain business needs.
And I couldn't share that.
I still can't share it.
I just want to add one thing there.
And Siemens had their talk earlier today
about having different S-bombs for different use cases.
And one of them was specifically around that.
We have a specific S-bomb for regulatory consumption.
That only includes the information
that the regulator needs.
And I don't know if that's a, I actually
wanted to talk to you guys about that.
Is that produced from the other S-bombs?
We'll get into that later.
But they have the other S-bombs they only
use for internal purposes.
So even in the case of software that
is not going to be distributed at all,
there's still a very strong use case for S-bombs.
That software that stays inside of Siemens
maybe doesn't even go into a product
and is only used for, let's say, internal accounting.
I don't know.
Whatever.
How can you get your data?
Right.
So there's still a use case there
where there's not a concern about necessarily poisoning
the software or whatever.
So yeah.
I just wanted to tie back to that,
because I wanted to, A, remind myself to talk to you about it.
But I thought it tied into what he was asking too.
There's a true reality within big organizations
is because at some point someone will ask it where or when
or why.
This is always about the project that you're working.
And sometimes there's someone that
is in a completely different area,
in a completely different country.
But for some reason, how is using the project
to do these questions?
And then what happens is that there's
a lot of people who augment itself
trying to find information.
If that's a thing that already happens on S-bomb since there,
you have all the information of the project details.
And then this question could be totally solved at the moment.
You're saying for just internal management audits
of resource planning, something like that, right?
Who was working on this project?
Yeah.
So all of that, yeah.
That information can be captured in an S-bomb as well.
Right.
I agree with that.
Yeah, I wanted to go back to you brought up this list of ingredients
question again, which I think is a really interesting analogy
to this whole situation.
Certainly, I've eaten processed foods in my life,
and I don't cook everything from scratch.
So having a list of ingredients is certainly much better
than not having one if those are your only two choices,
if you're given that false dichotomy.
However, I'm much more interested in getting recipes,
full recipes, with all the instructions
than I am getting lists of ingredients for something.
And similarly, true, I've used proprietary software in my life.
I avoid it because I don't just want a list of ingredients.
I want the whole recipe.
OK, so staying with a list of ingredients and food labels
analogy, whenever we see a list of ingredients,
it's usually a couple of things.
Not couple, OK.
Let's say a dozen things.
And then may also contain other things.
And it's also, yeah, oh, we can look at the chocolates.
And various other additives, or whatever, stuff like that.
So even in this case, we do not get a complete and exhaustive list
of everything, or not an accurate one.
Are we trying too much?
Right.
Trying to go to the S-Borm and find everything there.
So just looking at this, these are two pieces of chocolate.
Other brands are available.
Other brands, yeah.
So OK, one says this 42.
It's all in German.
What language it's in?
German, probably.
So one says 42%.
One says 44%.
But at the end, product is chocolate.
Are you able to tell that difference, a 2% difference?
OK.
Because there's a set of, OK, probably by taste, maybe,
if you're really good.
But OK, is your software the same?
Because the difference between that 2%
might be different compile option.
Take it an analogy.
OK.
So the question is, if in our food we are so lax,
why do we try to do it in our software so exact
and we're spending all this money that Bradley is talking
about?
Yeah.
I have an opinion on this.
So I'm in a big company that can use a lot of software products.
And while we care that bills of materials exist in many cases,
but we do not care at all what's the content.
So those 2% difference is what we're talking about.
Well, when people come to me and ask,
well, can we get that product from open source point of view,
I ask, well, do they have an S-bomb?
And if they have an S-bomb, it's a sign that they care about
and S-bomb is important, that they
are capable of creating S-bomb and that they produce
an instrument of product.
And in many cases, fine for me.
Go ahead.
Yeah.
I don't care what's in there.
OK.
So you want to?
Yeah, I'll summarize it.
Yeah, so the comment was that he doesn't
care what is in the software necessarily,
but he does care that there is an S-bomb, essentially.
And I agree with that.
As a consumer, a lot of times I don't.
I'm not going to read the ingredients.
But knowing that the ingredients are available,
and I don't know if this is a perfect analogy.
The ingredients list comes up all the time.
There's more to it than that.
But knowing that someone has the ability
to audit that information means that I don't necessarily
have to be the one that does it.
Just like when you go shopping, you
can benefit from other people bargaining,
even though you're not bargaining yourself,
just because that does drive prices down
in the general case.
That activity on the margin is extremely important.
So yes, I care a lot that even if I'm not
doing the inspecting of the food to make sure it's not
spoiled or whatever, that someone is,
just knowing that is good.
Do you know how food inspection has been done?
All right.
OK, so I want to follow up to what you said and ask you.
If your choices were, because you're
saying you're not going to look at it, which means probably
the recipe is not available.
You're not going to go try to cook version of yourself
to see if the recipe actually works.
You're going to be relying on the fact, hey,
there's a recipe out there.
And they say that's the recipe for this.
And probably somebody looked at it.
So here's a question for you.
If you had a choice between just getting the ingredients list
and actually getting the recipe, which
would you rather have out there, assuming you're not
going to really look at either of them?
OK, just what would I?
Well, it depends on what we mean by the recipe, right?
I mean, is it just the list of what
to combine in the performance?
Every step, every little time you step in.
I mean, some of it, there are elements of that
that could be related to food safety, right?
I didn't refrigerate it or whatever.
And yeah, I'd.
I give you the recipe for a salad.
The salami side of the sheet, right?
You want an Islamic, Old-day, Rizzo-backed,
packed with actual pork?
Is that what you're asking for?
I'm a vegetarian, so I'll give you the recipe.
Yeah, but I mean, it's an interesting thing is, you know.
Where are the, where are the, where are the, where are the,
sorry.
OK, OK, it's just an interesting thing
is people have allergies for food.
And taking this scenario along is quite things.
So you know, product may contain nuts.
People are allergic to certain types of nuts.
So if you received an S-bomb, do you, and do you know,
would you validate that that S-bomb is suitable for you
to use and not having an adverse effect on you?
Which might be a GPL license or something.
Maybe an adverse, there might be an adverse reaction.
Just to take it along.
Where's the, where, there seems to be quite a good analogy
here in terms of just receiving it,
you have to actually look at it.
Otherwise, the consequences of it, you know,
basically you suffer those consequences.
So just a sympathetic story.
I understand the argument of this S-bomb is basically
a synthesis of information that if you have all the source
code of all your dependencies, you could extract essentially
from there.
And I understand that in the use case of security,
it's much easier to just look for a version and a component
name in a database of S-bombs than directly to the source code
in their own forms or sources.
But if the stakes are high enough, in some cases,
you also want to do the graph.
So I don't know how big companies handle the Loughborough J
or the, how big is the Loughborough J?
What I'm going to assume is that fairly small company
with not huge budget and not a lot of, you know,
computing resources, if the S-bombs at the time,
it's a big diff, just look at that.
But I'm pretty sure that big companies and high budget
and computing resources also did the graph in the source code
because they couldn't afford assuming that all the S-bombs
were right.
So what I'm saying is that the conflicts we've been discussing,
if you're, you know, if you also get all the S-bombs
for your components, like you have a plan B in case
your S-bombs are wrong, I also encourage you to distribute
the source code and all the source code to your users,
but that's the kind of problem.
Yeah, no, to summarize that point, he's saying that if you
have an S-bomb in a zero-day response situation, let's say,
right, you can find Loughborough J very quickly,
but you're still going to want to go back and comb through
everything to be extra certain, right?
I think you want to have that option.
Yeah, yeah, well, you obviously, yeah, yes, I agree completely.
You want that option.
I think part of the reason that that's necessary today
is that disconnect between what the scanners are capable
of detecting and recording, how hard it is to have a truly
bit-for-bit reproducible build, right, if we get to that
universe where the builds are reproducible.
I mean, they are a reproducible build project, by the way.
Right, you don't have to do it all the time, but if you know
and you have a high confidence level that these builds are
reproducible, you don't necessarily have to reproduce
every one of them all the time, right?
Actually, this whole thing is closed circle with the whole
food part.
So, because in Brazilian I used to see, I saw a little
documentary about a network of supermarkets in the Netherlands
that actually produces other juice and use it.
Okay, blockchain is not the metal part, but from the
original in Brazil, the way they pick up the fruit to go in
traceability and do using blockchain for each part,
then the everything until you reach the supermarket,
and they can show the documents with all the traces and steps
with everything.
Basically, they have found a way to find a vulnerability in
the middle of processing with some food that has gotten
lost.
Yeah, that's a provenance issue, right?
Yeah, I can show this bottle of orange juice came from this
batch of oranges, those oranges came on this ship from this
orchard, and we're picked at this time.
Yeah, that is, so that is a kind of an intersection of signing
images or signing software with the S-bomb showing what's in
that software, right?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
To really stretch the analogy, yeah, but that's, I think that's,
yeah, you need both of those, right?
Ultimately, you probably want both of those.
Yeah, yeah.
There is a, for those interested in reproducible builds,
there is a working group on the open SSF.
Oh, yeah, probably.
There is an open working group on the open SSF.
A bunch of people are thinking on how you can get a reproducible
S-bomb, and some of it deals with, I mean, not necessarily
capturing all of the ingredients into the S-bomb, but I think
it's born, I'm not really that involved, but I, from what I
read, they're trying to think if I take an S-bomb and try to
reproduce a build from only the ingredients listed in the S-bomb,
can I manage to do it?
And they're tying it to other trust issues, but it's an
interesting project, if anyone is interested.
I think we probably end up, I think, you know, to have all
the ingredients and the providence and things like that
is going to provide a huge amount of information to be managed.
And then how do you then manage it, and how do you find it when
you need to find it?
Because it's bad enough in, bad enough finding source codes
sometimes, but then having to find other artifacts and
relations, that becomes quite hard.
So I'll probably put it out there.
For those of you who have got S-bombs and consuming them, how
are you managing them?
Because I believe that there's lots of things we're talking
about producing them, but actually putting the
relationship and S-bombs must be related to other artifacts,
I'm sure, building materials like hardware, documentation that
we talked about earlier about safety.
How are people managing those discrete artifacts together as
a unified, consistent solution?
Okay, a more general question.
Is anyone consuming a box, or are we all talking about
producing them?
Nobody cares.
Sorry, yeah.
Please.
So we're going to introduce S-bombs for folks, and we're
producing a lot of information, even the very build, and we're
producing a lot of specific stuff that we think.
But also you can read about the S-bombs that represent the
software that ends up being fully released in Microsoft.
And so the first thing we hear is we have released some
looks from the state that's happening in the X-box.
And then we have our mechanisms tracking our releases on
the phones that use that same identifier.
And so we want to look at these S-bombs.
We're only really looking at what's going on in the X-box
and what's actually been released, which starts now.
And from that, we have very solid component mechanisms
that are going to be released in the X-box.
And then we have the S-bombs that are going to be released
in the X-box.
And then we have very solid component mechanisms that
you always have an understanding of where things are going.
So your analytics approach makes it the destination of the
software, which consumers are going to be required.
And that can help you build a risk.
Risk is fairly contextual.
And we're producing and consuming S-bombs from risk
perspective, whether it's legal, license compliant, and
security.
And a lot of these cases are turning into denying.
And most of the shows in these cameras, we provide them
a lot of sources, and they can find hundreds of CEs.
They're really finding lots of things.
But a lot of it is not very useful, not actionable for
developers, especially when it's stuff that goes and don't
need to worry about fixing.
So it just gives us a really good data set to search and
use in an operational sense.
But it requires humans.
So we just set up some opportunities at the
independent YA about having better data sources in the
past that can automatically respond to threats and things
like that.
We're blessed with some very nice proprietary business
databases that are important.
And only support things like the quality of CEs and CEs and
CEs, CEs, CEs, you have to change stuff like that and go
ahead and just kind of read away from you.
But this kind of...
Can you summarize all that?
I'll have to summarize all that.
Yeah.
Well, okay.
They produce.
I actually want to go back to Zach's comment because I have
a question now because Zach was pointing out with
someone else earlier that having the S-bomb and the source
code is really the ideal situation.
And everybody has been saying S-bombs will help us with
bugs and identify vulnerabilities,
which possibly is true.
So if you have a log for J or any of these situations where
you've identified in your S-bomb, you have a version,
you have that version and you have that package,
but of course you don't have the source code.
So how does that help you solve the vulnerability if you
have the S-bomb?
It seems to me the only thing you can do is take the binary
out of deployment if you don't have the source code.
So I'm curious if I'm missing something that the S-bombs do
that allow you to solve the vulnerability with no source
code present.
Yeah, I'll take that.
That does happen sometimes where there's a project that has
been...
There are binaries for an internal project, let's say,
and nobody knows where the code is, right?
That has happened.
We've seen people build S-bombs and, yeah,
that's essentially the case where you can get an assessment
and say this is vulnerable to whatever.
That may...
Removing the binary as an option, there are maybe other
mitigations that could be put in place, but it is an
awareness thing, right?
I mean, that's kind of the main thing of S-bombs in general,
is a shortcut to omniscient awareness of every, you know,
mastery over the contents of this thing, right?
I think we're probably drifting a bit into slightly wider
things.
And S-bombs is not your single point of decision-making for
the things like vulnerability.
You need to look at how your product is being used,
has it been deployed, what's the environment,
who's using it.
If it's in a test environment, that's probably a slightly
different environment to an operational deployment in an
L.T. environment.
So you need to look at that, you know, look at the context.
And maybe S-bombs need to capture more of a context.
And obviously, if you're creating a product,
defining what a product is, it needs to also have that
context around it, which then gives you then maybe other
protections, physical protections as well,
that are not captured in the S-bomb that may help you make
those decisions.
I have a totally different question about the usefulness
of S-bombs.
I don't have any comments on co-pilot.
Okay.
So the question there is, with the likes of things like
co-pilot, and I presume our little friend,
Chat GPT, what does that really make to the world of S-bombs?
I would probably say, let's widen that a little bit more to
basically explainable software.
Can you explain what your software is doing?
And I'm sure our safety people would be, you know,
one of the things when I've been involved in safety,
you've got to explain your architecture and explain why
your architecture is safe and is fit for purpose.
So have you got explainable software?
And maybe an S-bomb will help that argument.
It won't be sufficient, but it might help explain why
your software, why you think your software is suitable
because of your selection of your components,
you've got components of known pedigree, et cetera,
may help your argument.
But actually things like, yes, automated code generation,
which we all have if you have compilers,
because that's automatic code generation,
and we ultimately trust them.
So how do we put those different measures together
and collect that and recognize that?
Because obviously we've also got things like with, you know,
AI, machine learning things, as well, capturing the data,
how good is the training data, how good is the algorithm
within that, and can you understand why it made
that particular decision?
And I don't know whether you're going anywhere near that
with your safety.
So I think, yes, explainable software is possibly a
completely new topic.
It works for why you don't want to discuss that.
Yeah, yeah.
In another capacity, I've written multiple blog posts
about the GitHub copilot situation, including essay
that won a prize of some sort.
So I'd encourage you to read those because that's sort of
other issues about that, because there's a lot of issues there.
I think one of the fundamental issues that you're pointing out
is more general, and it's not specific to copilot.
It's that machine learning, generally speaking, as a
discipline, if you can call it that, is one of the most
unreproducible processes that we've ever invented
in computer science.
And so the reason you can't get an S-bomb out the other side
of a code generation system that uses machine learning is
because you can't reproduce anything in the machine
learning process.
Once you train that model, you don't really know why it's
doing, because at that point it's just a table of floating
point numbers.
And so that's something that we, I think, maybe we could all
work together on to be angry about machine learning systems
and machine learning researchers not caring about reproducibility
as an issue.
But the fact that, okay, yeah, good.
So one of the things we're doing in the next webinar
is that we're extending it through the handle data sets
along with computer parameters as well as AIM.
Right.
We've been working with AI researchers, AI experts,
and so forth in order to be able to capture the key information
so we can at least start to summarize these factors into
the index software.
Okay.
So the comment was that in SPDX version 3, we're going to have
AI and data profiles, which tries to capture this information
there.
Why do you think that AI cannot be done in a reproducible manner?
Now that's not done now, right?
But if you can record everything again, have recipes for
everything, do you think that the AI fundamentally cannot be
done in a...
No, no, no.
I think the decisions have been made for the history of machine
learning going back basically 25 years that have led us to this
point.
And there's a lot of, we have to reverse engineer the entirety
of the machine learning research history to get to reproducibility
for machine learning, unfortunately, because it wasn't taken
seriously as an issue early on, in part because of the amount
of processing power required to reproduce, right?
Because if you want to retrain something, the amount of compute
time you need to retrain is not available to most people.
Okay.
Question.
So, I think it's a great correct way to process that.
There may be correct or incorrect, but there are no correct
or incorrect than the NARPH impact that is the IPR set up file
or else.
The comment was, sorry.
I wanted to just kind of add to what he's saying.
But I'll summarize it.
Yes.
So, he's saying that he was surprised by the number of
people, I think it was just one person that said they're
actually consuming S-bombs today.
Yeah.
And that he is in the project he maintains.
I think that you're not, you're just ahead of the curve,
probably.
Most people, their adoption today, if you talk to people who
are doing anything with S-bombs today, their adoption curve
looks like produce S-bomb, then maybe consume S-bomb, and then
maybe in the future I will incorporate the S-bombs that I'm
consuming into the product that I'm building or whatever,
right?
Whereas in the future, you know, let's say a year from now,
that may be a little bit reverse where people start consuming
S-bombs before they create their own S-bombs.
But today there's not enough people, there are no suppliers
producing S-bombs to be consumed, right?
That's the chicken and egg problem there.
I mean, that's what I'm seeing at least.
Does everybody know what you do when you have an egg?
So, Felipe, I should have raised my hand halfway to that
question because I've consumed S-bombs two to three times in
my life in the cases where under the copy left licenses,
like the GPL, we asked for the complete corresponding source
code, and in response to that request, they instead produced
an S-bomb, which is in fact not the complete corresponding
source code.
So I consumed it long enough to tell them this is not source
code, and they insisted, by the way, that a major compliance
industrial complex vendor had told them that that's what they
were supposed to give us if we ever asked for the source code.
Yeah.
Yeah, I just want to respond to that.
Just real quick.
That's, okay, I agree that's unacceptable, but that's not an
S-bomb.
That's not a problem with S-bombs inherently.
That's not a problem with lawyers giving the wrong
information or people misunderstanding what the lawyer
told them.
Or, or, or maliciousness, yeah, it absolutely could be
maliciousness.
Delay, stone wall, right, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
I was mainly...
Yeah, no, no, no, I just wanted to make a...
Yeah, yeah, yeah, I didn't want...
It just wasn't explicitly stated, so I just wanted to kind
of identify the issue.
For the record, I think no one here...
Yeah.
It seems that those bombs are replaced by...
We have to finish up pretty soon.
Yeah.
Just one comment on the using your phones.
I don't know if you can use that, but it's a good
discovery and we can shoot it, so it's not a problem.
It's a way of indicating the risk of balancing between
the developers, all the manufacturers, and the
people.
That's great.
Repeat that.
Okay, so I think what you're saying is, and you're
orange, I think?
Yeah, so you are producing and consuming internally
generated S-bombs.
So our last question is, what have you discovered?
I'm just talking.
Right, so as you are consuming...
Are you consuming the S-bombs?
What are you doing to help make decisions on your
design?
Are you saying, oh, there's a license missing, or oh,
I shouldn't be using that version.
We have a license missing and we find plenty of
we have licenses and some surprises over time.
Some surprising licenses and a little note
that much of a source of those kind of licenses.
And has that resulted in a change to your design,
or have you just...
Well, now and then we have to change libraries
that you use or they have, for commercial license.
Okay.
Oh, yeah.
Okay, well, that's good.
I think...
They have to publish all schools, but actually...
Yeah.
So that's probably quite an interesting...
You know, licensing is probably quite an interesting
use case for people to understand.
I think we've had quite a lot about licensing today,
which is really good.
I think there are plenty more.
I think we can all...
You know, I think that's what I think there's plenty
more to develop over the next month's years as we mature.
And I think actually, I think S-BOM...
If people start producing S-BOMs,
you're going to reveal a lot more than you...
You know, there's a lot of unknowns, I believe, in software.
And I think, are people starting to ask questions
of their suppliers?
And, you know, I'm probably looking at the large
organizations in this room.
Have you put things on your contracts that are now
asking your people to provide S-BOMs with your delivery,
as well as a delivery note and a release note?
Are people starting to do that and ask them, you know,
and probably to keep Bradley happy?
And are they also basically providing their compliance
against licenses?
Because if people start providing that as a starting
point, that's going to help your risk assessment when
you take S-BOMs off into a solution and then start
adding value to it.
That should be basically a real game changer for
businesses as well.
So maybe speaking for big companies, at the moment,
as we already have, it's an act of, you cannot force
our vendors to create a customer so that consumers,
we can politely ask them at the moment.
Maybe next year we can...
Yeah, yeah.
...
Yeah, he's saying that he's unable to force any vendor
or supplier in general to supply an S-BOM, which I
think is a big problem in general, right?
I mean, A, your vendor may be 10,000 times bigger than
you...well, not in your case, maybe not.
But for a lot of smaller operators, right, they don't
have the leverage over the vendor, right?
Or in the case of your consuming open source software,
like, they have no obligation to you at all, right?
They...I mean, we've seen...like, I totally agree.
Like, open source maintainers are already put upon enough,
right?
There's nobody that should put a gun to their head and
say, you have to produce an S-BOM for me to consume.
That's where the tooling has to get better, right?
Companies like GitHub could even, you know, advance
this a lot by making it much easier for project
maintainers to have those produced on a regular basis,
right?
Yeah, in my work in license compliance and
enforcement, the number of bad actors in your vendor
space is much higher than you probably realize.
And it's often not the vendor being bigger than you.
It's actually these small vendors who are...there's
only a couple, there's kind of a cartel, particularly,
I'm thinking of chip set, you know, chip set for
embedded devices vendors.
There is a major chip set that I'm sure there's
probably at least 30 devices in this room that use
that chip set.
The vendor requires you to agree before they will
ship you even a demo board.
You promise I will never ask for the complete
corresponding source code under the GPL and that's
the only way I'm going to send you a demo board.
If you become a customer, you're never allowed to
ask me for the source code.
Now, this is a GPL violation, but it's very hard to
catch because everybody who signs this agreement
says, I don't ever want to, like, tell anybody I
signed that agreement because they'll never sell me a
board again.
And so this optimism that we're going to get vendors
to give us S-bombs, where vendors are getting people
to sign those kinds of agreements, the idea that
you're going to get them in an agreement to agree to
give you an S-bomb, I think is probably a pipe dream
in the current industrial environment around embedded
chip set vendors at least.
I don't know about other industries, but the embedded
chip set vendors, I think that's the case.
It's not bad.
You don't have any embedded products.
We tell hardware companies that we would use the
chip set if the drivers are off-streaming.
Right.
Yeah.
Because this network is easier for us.
It's not easy.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Well, thank you for doing that.
Yeah.
So we're out of time.
Many thanks to the wonderful panel and all the audience.
Thank you, Alexios, for organizing.
Yeah, yeah.
Sure, definitely.
Come on.
That's good.
So we have one last session, which is an open Q&A on
everything S-bomb for whoever is interested and still alive.
Thank you.