All right, so first of all, thank you for staying this late on Sunday and for attending
the Eson Roma bit as part of the organizers.
I'm really happy to see this.
And so we have been going through all of those cool use cases and complex, like really complete
and complex tools to generate desktops and analyzing how companies speak about how they're
doing it and like going deep into the research of how Eson's talking about both.
I was thinking that I wanted to do like my talk as kind of pivot as we are sitting towards
the more discussion part of the bedroom.
And so as you have been hearing from folks right now, a lot of us working on Eson's are
starting to get concerned about what's actually in those documents.
And I think when Thomas opened the bedroom today, the first thing he said was, well,
those dependencies that you're getting, they may not be correct, right?
So I thought that it would be, as we move to the latest part of the conference, it would
be cool if we could get a few talking points just to see the conversation that's about
to happen.
So my name is Aloha Garcia, and I am, well, part of the SPDX community.
I am a contributor to SPDX and some of the tools.
I'm a trained adventurer for open source tools that generate and consume desktops and that
help visualize them.
I am also part of the Kubernetes project.
I am part of Kubernetes SIG release, and I work there mostly on the supply chain security
of the project.
And yeah, like riding my bike, I'm based in Mexico City, and I am a staff engineer with
Changer, which is a company devoted to supply chain security.
So as you heard from probably every speaker today, the goal of having a company getting
a document which you can actually use for something.
And there are many concerns about ESBOMs flying around in the world today because there are
particular use cases, and some people will argue that ESBOMs may not be necessarily incomplete
if they're not suitable for one case or the other.
And this is true, but instead of trying to picture ourselves generating a next one from
the position of a large company or whatever, I felt that it was more appropriate to discuss
today that how I am assuming a lot of people here are maintainers of open source projects
and sometimes very small open source projects, like one maintainer small.
And I think it's important to start considering that when those large companies are going
to use your project, your library, important in that module that you're writing, the ESBOM
that you give them can really make a difference in several areas.
Like first, you can make their life easier because you're having them more complete information
which they can act on.
And the other one is we as open source community become better citizens of the supply chain,
like generating the information that pertains to us is much more responsible thing to do.
So what happens when you open an ESBOM?
Well today you can get all sorts of surprises.
Sometimes there's nothing in there.
You open the ESBOM and it's empty.
Sometimes you don't have absolutely any information that lets you determine what the ESBOM is
describing.
So it's simply just pointing to the same black box that you can look from the outside.
Or the other is what happens if, are you sure that the ESBOM is really describing what you're
expecting to and you're not getting combed by someone?
So that information needs to be in the ESBOM in order to ensure that it's actually describing
that piece of software that you're distributing.
So I'm going to give you a few examples.
I'm not trying to name names and that's why I chose projects that I'm involved with, both
good and bad.
So this is the first one.
This is our company has a Linux distribution which is already shipped shipping with ESBOMs
built in.
And we generate those ESBOMs at build time for all of the packages.
And you can see the structure here of one of the ESBOMs.
This is like a visualization of the ESBOM using the Kubernetes bomb tool which lets
you ingest SPDX documents and see how they're structured inside.
And as you can see, we try to in the Linux district add a lot of detail to the ESBOM
as much as we can to just guide whoever's using those ESBOMs to do smart decisions with
the information they have in them.
So if you look at some of, this is a fragment of the ESBOM and I mean some information is
there.
Some information is, for example, the licenses, the license concluded fields.
They are marked as no assertion but you can omit those, for example, if you want.
But we have the license from the project, from the actual operating system package.
We have some identifiers, things like that.
So it's pretty complete.
It's obviously not perfect but we try and we try to add as much information as we can.
But then let me show you another ESBOM from another popular open source project.
This is part of the Kubernetes ESBOM.
So this is part of the ESBOM like the structure, a little fragment of the structure of the
ESBOM that we generate with when we put out a new Kubernetes release.
And this is describing, for example, the tables which we put out with every release.
One of the tables of the LQA API server, the list of files.
So we also try to add information.
We put out two ESBOMs with Kubernetes, one with the artifacts, one with the source code
which are linked one to each other.
And so we also think that those are fairly complete ESBOMs.
But now I opened an ESBOM in a popular open source project and tried to generate the structure
like this.
I'm not going to say which project it is.
It's just one I'm involved with and we should be doing a better job there.
And you can guess many reasons of why this is showing serial things but we can go over
this.
So as you can see, you can really enrich an ESBOM with a lot of information and some of
it can be more important than other things.
But I've been thinking, well, what's the most important details that you can add to the
ESBOM?
So the first one is, and by the way, most of this you already heard the truth of the
day if you've been sitting in most of the conferences.
So we're going to go one by one.
So the first one is syntactic correctness.
You would expect that most tools generating SPDX or Cyclone DX ESBOMs do the basic job
of just making a compliant document.
Well, the reality is that they're not so.
If you, I pictured this guy from Apollo 13 that tries to fit the square peg in the round
hole or the other way around.
Because if you cannot ingest an ESBOM, so what's the point?
And even if you have tried to somehow hack the document or ingest it somehow, the reality
is that most tools that consume ESBOMs today do not have a clear strategy of deprecating
the documents.
And then most importantly, not clear and also not predictable.
So if a tool tries to somehow ignore errors or whatever, the behavior may not be consistent.
So ensure that any ESBOM that you're producing or requesting at least complies with syntactic
rules of the standard you're using.
The second one, dependency data.
And this is a little bit related to the first one.
I've seen ESBOMs.
So since I work with a lot of open source tools and my job also has to do with ESBOMs,
I've seen a lot of tools producing ESBOMs.
And so for example, one variant of the bad ESBOM is, well, they will just list like a
table and that's your ESBOM, nothing else.
Or the obvious case of this ESBOM contains one thing, an RPM.
No dependency, no nothing.
So we often use the analogy of the ESBOM being the nutritional label of software.
But without the dependency list, well, it's really worthless.
You can still use your ESBOM as the old checksum.txt if you wanted, but ESBOM's going to provide
a lot more value than that.
Then the second one, licensing information.
We heard a ton of the talks today about licensing and why it may be important.
So the truth is if you are publishing software, you're the most qualified person to do the
assessment of what the license your software should be using.
And this applies both to the dependencies that you're pulling in.
And if you are redistributing an information, ensure that the information about the licensing
is going down the stream.
Because the tools that we've been seeing today try to do a good job on helping people understand
their licensing situation.
So I picture checking the passport as an example of the license.
The next one.
And semantic structure in the ESBOM.
This one also came during the discussion today.
So there are folks that think that ESBOM can be just the list of dependencies.
And it may be true.
But then you start losing context on where those things fit.
For example, if you have just a list of dependencies, and especially if they're not related to
an artifact at the top of the ESBOM, if you picture.
So the ESBOM can be this beautiful graph of one node that spreads out to lots of different
relationships in nodes.
So sometimes you'll see ESBOMs that only have the list of dependencies.
And they don't talk about where those dependencies fit if they're describing a concerning image,
a binary, nothing.
So if you try to do something more sophisticated with that data, you simply can't.
If you remember the ESBOM that I showed in the beginning that we built with the Linux
distribution, this is how we structure the container images built from our Linux distribution.
So you have the container, the layers, and the packages, like the OS packages, and then
all of the files in its proper place.
And this information is actually coming from smaller ESBOMs that get compiled when we build
the Linux distribution.
So each of the APKs of the distro have their own ESBOM describing that package.
And then when we build an image, we take all of those ESBOMs and give you one single ESBOM
with all of that information composed where it's supposed to be.
And without structure, you simply cannot do this.
And this is one image, but then if you go and make it more complex, you can start thinking
about multi-arch images.
And those need to have this information for each of the images, so the relationships start
to become more and more complex.
And the way I try to picture is this.
So they give you a box of Legos without any instructions or anything.
You can use your imagination.
Basically you're going to build something really beautiful, most likely not.
Especially not the thing picture in the box, right?
And so these are some of the reasons that I was thinking.
If you have structure, then it's a guarantee at least that the tool at least is looking
at how the thing is composed and where the information is flowing from and lets you do
more complex use cases for the documents.
Now the next one.
This also has come like two, three times today, the software identifiers.
ESBOMs need to be defining and naming the piece of software as close as possible.
And software identifiers are one of the schemes that you need in the document in order to
ensure that the piece of software that the ESBOM is describing is clearly identified.
And all of them have their problems, especially CPE for example, it's really complex to get
it right.
And the idea is there's going to be a tool down the stream that it's going to benefit
from that information.
So if you can add it, you're making sure that the ESBOM can work well with those tools.
And this is kind of the idea of that.
So how many packages in the world named log, right?
So, okay, log, but what's log?
There are thousands in every language like operating system packages, libraries named
log.
And if you have like a properly specified PURL, CPE, both that clearly define the piece
of software that the ESBOM is talking about, then it can be better referenced and used
by tools on the stream.
Now the supplier data, this is like a contentious one.
And the reason why I added the supplier data is because as software authors, sometimes
we don't think that it's like an important field.
We simply, I mean, in most large open source projects, we just list like copyright the
project authors, right?
Like the editorial.
But the reality is that if you jump into any of the ESBOM meetings that go on regularly,
you're gonna hear all of the compliance folks like I need a name to sue or I don't know.
It's a different mentality than ours, but people need it.
And in fact, it's one of the requirements from NTIA as the minimum relevance of ESBOM.
And this is a weird field because if you deal in kind of more into security of the documents
that should be generated during the supply chain and the software lifecycle, this information
is kind of, I don't know, not really very useful because it can be forged and you cannot
trust it.
And so just having a name and an email, well, like it serves compliance folks, but to us
it's kind of, well, worthless really for security purposes, right?
But then you start thinking about, well, what's a supplier?
Is it the author, the company direct holder?
Is it the tool that compiled the thing that people who was distributing it?
And so, well, at least ensure that you're providing some kind of information.
And the idea is, know who's selling you your things, right?
Which you buy candy from that guy, probably not.
Yeah, exactly.
Come, give them, get them from us.
Supplier data.
Oh, okay.
I messed up this slide.
So this one was supposed to be integrity data, integrity data to prevent this kind of thing.
So when you, as you heard today also, ESBOM should be properly hashed, like hashing as
much as you can inside of a document when possible, when it makes sense, and especially
when it can be verified.
So the idea is, is this piece of software that I'm naming in the ESBOM the real deal?
Has it been corrupted or not?
But more importantly, having hashes lets you deal the problem of the latest, right?
So sometimes you will not have a version, but you can still reference that software
artifact inside of the ESBOM and other documents like VEX, for example, via the hashes.
So you can think about the versioning system and the software identifiers as links to external
systems outside of the ESBOM, like vulnerability databases, like for example, package repositories.
But internally, everything should be addressed via the hash if possible.
So if I'm telling you this is the vulnerability document for a piece of software, it should
match with the hashes somehow.
In the ADAs, well, you can, once you start content addressing the piece of software in
the ESBOM, you cannot go wrong.
And that's basically what I have.
And so I just wanted to let this open, you know, keep the conversations that are about
to happen about this kind of thing inside of the documents.
And if there are any questions or whatever, happy to take them.
If not, you can reach me as Poerco in most systems and Twitter, whatever.
So thank you.
Question?
Oh.
I was going to ask about the supply and data and how much is that seen as the individual
entity?
Well, I would like to hear the opinions of the supplier that are from other.
So what's basically, what's the role of the supplier data?
So what's the use of that field?
Yeah.
What should be filled in?
Is it an entity?
Yeah.
So should they feel like a person or an entity or a tool?
Yep.
So I have a question about the last ingredient definition, so the integrity.
In your definition, does that also include sizing of the actual asset?
Not really.
Ripping?
No, no.
Yeah.
I was going to go to that question before, but if anybody has insights about how supplier
data is used in the organizations, that was the time to discuss it.
All right.
Yeah.
No, so the way I've seen it required is...
What was the question?
No, no.
This is...
Yeah.
Exactly.
The first one.
So the first one is how is the supplier used?
And the way I've seen it is mostly from procurement people, like asking for that information,
and lawyers.
So that's the model, the two that I've seen asking for the information more.
I'm coming from the security side of HESMOM more, so the compliance is not my strong side,
but that's why I'm suggesting it.
And...
Yeah.
As one data point, the way that we are using supplier data is actually recording who supplied
the software.
So not who wrote it, not who created it or something like that.
If we got it from an upstream distribution repo, we put the upstream distribution repo
in product.
That's, again, recorded that we know, that's the only thing that I know.
And to the other question is, so does the integrity points consider also signing of
the HESMOM?
And yes, but not in this case.
So integrity, like signing of the HESMOM is mostly done outside of the HESMOM.
And that touches on trusting the HESMOM, which is a whole other kind of worms.
But I mean, it is, but not in the contents of the documents.
How can I make sure an HESMOM adheres to these principles?
Is there something like benchmarks or I give it a score of 8.0 from 10?
That's a good HESMOM.
Well, there are tools then.
Yeah, yeah, I repeat the question.
So how can I know...
Sorry, didn't get out of the lot of sleep.
How can I make sure that the HESMOM really complies to these things here?
So there are a couple of tools that do a validation of the HESMOM, like scoring, try to do scoring.
So eBay has a tool called HESMOM Scorecard.
Then there's the NTIA compliance checker from SPDX.
And I'm not sure.
And there's...
I don't know.
Are the ender folks here still?
Not very much.
Okay, so I seem to remember that they were handling some of that as well.
But there are a couple of tools out there.
It's more like a remark, but some...
It's a surprise we didn't mention Open Chain that much.
Open Chain is...
The goal is to trust from the suppliers, so you can trust the HESMOMs from the suppliers.
So, yeah.
What Nico said is that Open Chain has touches on the idea of trusting the HESMOM on the
supplier and those sorts.
I've had an observation.
This is having looked at Python and the metadata that goes with Python packaging is really
inconsistent.
So, how do you spell Apache 2?
How many different ways of putting Apache 2 license is amazing.
And actually between releases, information disappears.
So, this is really a message for the ones in the ecosystems, put as much data in the
ecosystem metadata that you can, because this is going to support...
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, the comment is...
Because we were looking at a difference and we've got a new release of a package, but
where's the supplier gone?
Right, exactly.
And actually, the question is, do we just use that module now?
Because we don't know where it's come from.
The comment is that in Python, sometimes between releases, information changes or disappears
or whatever.
So, this is actually one of the things that some of us would like to see happening, like
people working on packaging systems, on language ecosystems, to start, if not adding S-bomb
generation straight away in their tooling, at least expose the information so that we,
S-bomb tool makers, can go in and extract them from more trustable sources.
And...
Wait, about two minutes.
Okay.
In regards to hashing, how are you dealing with custom patches when you apply to your
live software?
Can you repeat it?
In regards to hashing, how are you dealing with custom patches when you apply?
So, if you need to patch software you're using, but you can't apply the patch upstream.
In the case of the...
Yeah, just in the case of the distro or...
You can adjust to it in general as well.
Well, yeah, the question is, how do you deal with patch software, right?
When you apply a patch?
If I apply a patch, then it's not upstream.
But I mean, you still have that hash, right?
Or is the question about naming?
What's the best practice, I suppose?
Yeah, so if you're describing a patch artifact, I mean the hash, simply hash the thing and
you can use that down the stream.
The problem comes when you're trying to define, well, I'm using curl, but I applied a few
custom patches myself.
How do you name that?
And that becomes a more complex question.
So internally, as I was saying with the integrity thing, is you can still reference everything
with the hashes, right?
I'm talking about binary, this hash, all down the stream.
But when you want to express it externally, well, I guess that falls into the naming problem
and you have to think about where that thing is going to be used.
So if that is going to be a package, part of a distribution that you're doing, you may
define your own set of package URLs, for example, or if it's not going to be, you can make up
the license, but it falls more into the use case of what you're trying to do with distributing
that budget software.
So that's it.
All right.
Thank you.
Okay, bye.