So we start with a pretty tight schedule.
So thank you everyone for being here and being on time.
So with respect to your time, we're not completely sure we've got the AV all set up for the remote
stream but for those here in the room we'll start it off and post slides.
A bit of housekeeping I guess.
We've got like to say a very full schedule between today and tomorrow.
Today just today.
I'm still going tomorrow to the public.
Tomorrow's a flight but anyhow.
So Alexis you want to walk us quickly through it and then tell us the rest of the housekeeping
stuff and then I'll talk with an overview of the SBOM stuff quickly.
Right.
So first of all for us, for the strange people who do not know us, this is Kate the Magnificent,
Adolfo the Great is somewhere trying to find AV solutions and I'm Alexis.
Right.
In the program that you have seen we did not do a nice job like other dev rooms and did
we not leave any time between the end of one talk and the start of the other.
Or if you're speaking imagine that you've got five minutes stripped off because we're
going to finish early and switch laptops and bring the next period around.
So as you've seen we have lots of talks all about SBOMs.
Right.
Okay.
Okay good.
I can't speak even.
This is.
Okay.
So we have lots of things about SBOMs.
We try to group the presentations according to a couple of themes and so we'll be starting
with more tools that are working on SBOMs.
Then we're going to be discussing what information goes into SBOMs and then we're going to have
more general discussions about SBOMs.
There are two, we had interesting changes in the schedule according to travel plans
for different people.
So we have two discussions or panels or whatever you want to call them.
One is on discussion on SBOM content where we expect people to contribute.
And the other end is the larger panel discussion about, why should it be content there?
Useful and caveat of SBOMs in general.
And then we also have another time slot for everyone to ask questions about SBOMs because
this is something completely new.
And that's about it.
And I give it to Kate to explain what SBOMs is.
The other thing too is as we are moving through the day, if more people are coming in, you
may be getting asked to move that way so that as people come in they can get seated.
And so you'll see myself, one of us, basically we start to see pressure.
Too many people standing in the back of the walls go at some point in time quietly during
the meetings.
So I think that's it.
Plus the room has a corridor at the end after the...
At the back, yeah.
So you don't need to cross all the...
Okay, so quick show of hands.
How many people have started working with SBOMs already?
Okay.
Pretty good.
So why don't you not up?
So I'm going to just sort of say, the common understanding that's emerged of what an SBOM
is, is the relationships between components used in building software.
And these are like libraries, module, open source, or proprietary, widely available or
restricted.
All of these are valid use cases today.
And we have to...
Because we have to work full ecosystem and improve transparency, we need to be inclusive
of all of them.
This is a definition that's sort of been worked up in the industry through various meetings
and there's been European participation as well as North American and Japanese.
So we're trying to get this.
There was a document published last year, actually it was the year before, saying what
the minimum elements are.
And the minimum elements are a supplier component name, version of the component, some other
unique identifier, dependency relationships, authors of the data, and timestamp.
That is pretty much all that is asked for for the minimum.
Now anyone who's working with this stuff, it's not sufficient.
So there are a couple of formats that are already recognized as supporting this minimum.
SPDX and Cyclone DX are on that list as well as SWID.
And so we have a definition set of the fields from that things and we're trying to line
up with that in the various formats, okay?
And then possibly do a lot more.
Most of us here are in the SPDX community and it is able to extend beyond that minimum
and we are an international standard and have gone through the effort of becoming an international
standard.
So you'll be hearing probably a little bit more SPDX than the other one but there are
other people working on Cyclone DX who will be here today too.
The context though is an S-bomb by that minimum definition can apply pretty much anywhere
in the software-to-
Like cycle.
And we were finding a lot of people talking past each other.
And so one of the things that's been working on in a group for the last six months is coming
up with a common set of definitions about the types of S-bombs.
And they sort of relate a little bit to where the things are in the design phase but not
completely.
But the common ones that we see out there in the industry right now are the source ones
and the build.
And the build is where we're getting a lot of information for the security folks.
The analyze is when you have a tool that basically gives you a binary and tries to figure out
what's in it.
The deploy is you've got things that you're putting on a system with configuration information
and you want to know that.
And then runtime is what might be running on your system.
You can generate S-bombs for all these sets that fit the minimum definition.
And so one of the things I'm going to be asking the speakers to do is as they are talking
through their slides and everything else if they could say what type of S-bombs they're
talking about so that people can get it clear in their head how these tools work with different
types of data.
And with that I will turn it over to our first speaker.