So, this is a presentation we're starting now, actually a new set of presentations in
the dev room, not about complete less bombs, but about information that gets inside those
bombs.
And you'll be hearing more about it.
So this is a presentation about a system to capture detailed information about building,
and the work, I mean, almost all of the work happened by Fotis, and so I was just, yeah,
you know, explaining what has to be done, design the problem.
So we're going through a very typical agenda, you know, what we're trying to solve, how
we solve it, how we solve it, and what was not solved and what we're going to do.
Fotis happened as a GSOC project, Google summary of projects last year, of the Geforce organization,
which is an umbrella organization for open source in Greece, and we have representatives
there.
Right, I'm not going to be reading the whole slide, you can read it and you can see it
But there are umbrella organizations that they're looking over open source development
in Greece, and they are, have been participated to GSOC for many years now.
And one of the projects was wonderful that Fotis did.
So let's start with the basics.
What are we trying to solve?
Right.
There are different names for what we're trying to solve.
Some people call it origin, some call it providence or pedigree or things.
Maybe if I have a binary file, and I'm talking when I'm saying binary, I mean an executable
or a library, not an image, right, or a PDF, but an object file, right, how was this created?
Right.
What are the sources that were used in order to create this binary?
What was the process that was used in order to create that?
Yeah.
So essentially these two things, right.
The goal is to have extra information and meta information about all this stuff.
And so in the end you know exactly what information is inside the binary, right, or was used to
create it.
Right.
So think of it very simplistically.
You know, if I have a command that builds a binary like a compiler that gets a source
file and generates an executable, I want to record, okay, there was this process called
cc and it read the wonderful file in c and it produces an executable.
Right.
That's what we want to solve.
And then it gets tricky because as you can imagine, you know, okay, we're not obviously
looking at all the things that are specified in the command line.
Right.
So when you do cc the hello world dot c, maybe it includes a file, right.
You see language has include.
So and this might be significant.
It will definitely be significant.
Right.
So it might include slash your slash include slash stdio dot h.
So I need to record that this file was also used in order to produce this binary.
Right.
And in the same way cc is just a program.
I cannot just record the name because it does not mean anything.
This is definitely a file and maybe it uses other linked libraries in order to do that.
And when you produce the final executable, it definitely, it might include system libraries.
And you want to record all this.
Right.
So we're not talking about, you know, passing the command line and seeing the three files
mentioned there.
We want to record everything happening in there.
And obviously the command may not be explicit.
It might just be make.
Right.
And you want to record everything happening with this build command.
Is the problem clear?
Has anyone else?
How's this problem?
So the project, the whole project was okay.
Let's build something like that.
And how do you create a project?
You say what I want to achieve.
And this is a factual specification.
Right.
So we want a minimal interface.
I don't want to tell developers how you have to change the compiler in order to do that.
And I mean, the first idea would be to change the compiler.
But yeah.
Let's try to make it minimal.
So ideally no changes to the command at all.
Right.
And I want to record the files being created or written.
The files being read.
All the processes being run.
So for each of the files, I want to know the name.
I want to know the full path because there might be difference.
And then because I care about the, actually the content, I want the hash because the same
file can be in different places with the same hash.
So I have to know what it is.
And you know, extra nice information, the size of the file, the model of the file, and
stuff like that.
I don't care.
For every process that runs, I want to know, okay, what was the process?
What were the arguments?
What was the environment?
Because as you probably know, every process reads maybe different according to the environment
that it finds.
Yeah.
Okay.
So the read times would be useful and stuff like that.
Right.
So this is the information that this is the functional specification.
This is our wonderful problem.
Right.
And then for this, sat down and worked.
No, no, wait.
You'll take the mic.
Well, he's not an engineer yet.
He will be.
Can you hear me now?
Well, to tackle this problem, we created the command line tool named build recorder.
You can see right here, build underscore recorder, which records information about the build
on Linux.
You said this is rather simple.
All you have to do is prefix your build command, whatever that is, make GCC, Java compiler
with the name of the executable.
Build recorder runs transparently in the background while your build is running.
You don't need to change anything in terms of your configuration, your source files,
or even your build system.
You can literally pick any project you like at this point in time, run with build recorder
and it's to run.
If it doesn't, please file a bug report.
Now, as you can see, build recorder.
Do you believe an asterisk exception may apply?
Yes.
Build recorder stores all of that information in an output file by default name the build
does recorder dot out.
But as you can see, you can use the does so option to actually supply an alternative file
name.
But what does it actually record?
Well, pretty much everything we talked about in the functional specification.
For its file, we have a list of attributes, its name, its size, its section of its contents,
as well as its absolute path.
Similarly, for its process, we store its command line with all its arguments, a start and end
timestamp, as well as the environment.
We also store a list of relationships, namely a process creates a process that is by forking
or cloning or any of the revients, as well as a process opens a file for reading, a process
opens a file for writing, or some processes are associated with executables.
For example, if we were to run make, the system would probably run the file at slash user
slash bin slash make.
We want to record that as well.
Now, all of this information is stored in the output file in RDF turtle format.
That is being processed and filed.
And all of the attributes, as well as the relationships, been the predicates.
This is an example.
For example, we have a process ID one, which is the initial compilation process.
Imagine this is C, that's all for C. It starts at the current timestamp.
We have another process, which is a preprocessor, the C preprocessor.
It starts on another timestamp.
We specify that the initial compiler actually created the preprocessor unit.
And then we have the fact that we have a file, F1, foo dot C, which should be specified that
PID2 reads F1.
The preprocessor opens the file foo dot C, which has size 100 and the random hash of
zeros.
We have another F2, which is a temporary that the compiler might use, which as we can see,
the process number two actually writes on this.
We have another process, the classical CC, which merges those files together, the object
file.
Yeah, that's a general idea, I guess.
Well, how is it implemented?
How does it support all of those languages?
The basic idea is that we basically want to record all of the files and processes that
a process uses.
And now if we think about it, all processing files are actually handled using system calls.
So if we were to look at the system calls the process makes, we could see all of the
files and processes that it uses.
For example, if we look at the open family of system calls, open create and its variants,
we can easily extract the name as well as the access mode.
On the same note, for process all we have to do is trace, fork, clone and its variants
as well as the execution system calls to actually see the process ID and the executable files.
Now from the information that we extracted from these two, we can actually get even more
information like the command line, the environment, a link to a file, which from there we can
get the size that has in the absolute path.
All of this happens on Linux, so we basically just need a way to trace system calls.
Under Linux this is a fairly straightforward problem.
We use P-trace, which directly copy and paste from the command line.
It is primarily used to implement breakpoint debugging and system call tracing.
Now that's it.
It's a very simple program.
For the duration of our project.
So Fotis ran through the slides that did implement it, so we have lots of time now.
It's not perfect, it has issues.
Let's start discussing, you've got the major idea of how it works.
What are the issues?
The main two big buckets of issues are the real complexity and performance.
So real complexity.
Remember that we said it's a compiler that just reads a file and creates an executable.
That was this wonderful diagram first.
It's real life, it's not that simple.
So on the right hand side you see a more typical idea, again, compiler.
So when you have a compiler it actually calls three different processes.
You call the first one, the first pass that reads the C file and creates an assembly file.
And then you call the assembler that reads the assembly and creates an object file.
And then you have the linker loader that reads the object file and creates an executable.
So this is a very abstracted and ideal world situation.
Real world is nothing like that.
Real world may be like that if you have done your compiler courses and you have seen the
different passes of compiler and stuff like that.
And then you go to the real world where the hello world, which is just print hello world.c
in current Linux, is this one.
So I'm not going to be explaining every file in that one.
But this is just the three lines of main hello world, print hello world.
And if you compile it with GCC, it's better.
So you see there are, what can I say, lots of include files being included.
This is the first step of compiler, the compiler first step.
So you think that it will only read hello world.c, but you have a hash include in order
to include the printf definition.
And this include, unfortunately, includes std def and libc header start.h and lots of
other different files.
And all these are files that have been read by the first process.
And then it creates something else, which I'm not sure where it is somewhere.
So it creates the temporary files.
It creates the assembly there, if you can see.
And then it creates the object files.
And in order to create the final executable, lots of libraries have to be included.
And this is, the library's been included in the executable.
And then we have the other set of things that in order to run cc1, which is an executable,
so a file in the file system, right, you have to load dynamically a number of other libraries
that this executable depends on.
So you have to record all these as well, because again, you have to have an accurate record
of everything being used, right.
So yeah, even the hello world example is complex, right.
And you create and record lots of files and processes for that one, which means, oh, and
a lot of them are going to be reused again and again and again, right.
So when you had, for example, to compile two different files, right, they will both include,
for example, std id.h, right.
And ideally, you don't want to redo, you don't want to have another record, another box here
for the second instance of the same file.
On the other hand, it might not be the second instance of the same file, because something
might have changed, right, while you're running, somebody else is calling a new compiler and
it messes up all your binaries, right.
And it's different binaries in the first run and the second run and all this stuff.
So this brings us to having to do it efficiently.
So you're doing performance.
Well, performance isn't great at the current moment.
I mean, we have to stop and restart the process multiple times using pit race.
Like you stop the process, you read an entire file from disk, you has it.
And then you restart the process.
This relatively expensive, as you can imagine.
The current profiling shows, like, when I built one on my system, normally it took nine
minutes.
With build recorder, it took 36 minutes.
So yeah, it depends on your hardware, your hard disk, pretty much.
But the good news are that there's a lot of room for improvements, because first of all,
we haven't optimized anything.
We're using plain arrays.
We will be switching them with lookup tables.
So we expect massive performance gain from this.
In fact, when I tried the Hasmap implementation, we dropped this to 22 minutes.
So that's optimistic.
And another thing to mention is that pit race actually makes a multi-threaded process run
as a single thread, which is an issue.
So if you run, for example, make that's J8, you won't actually get the performance benefits
of multiple threads.
We have plans to change that as well.
Lots of changes need to be made.
In fact, we proposed it as another project for GSoC for this summer.
And yeah, that's it pretty much.
We hope to see an improvement.
We can't really tell how what at the end the overhead shall be, like how much we can improve
build recorder, but we will get there.
Now, regarding future work, pretty much we improve performance.
We plan to handle more programming systems.
I mean, you can use it with any programming language you want.
But if I was to, for example, compile a project in Java using a build system like Maven, Maven
has web dependencies.
It downloads packages from repositories.
So ideally, we would like to also record those repositories, those URLs.
This is another proposed project for the next GSoC.
And next we have porting it to non-Linux systems like other Unixes, NetBSD, FreeBSD, the list
goes on.
The one thing that wasn't mentioned is that build recorder at the current time only works
with Linux kernels of version 5.3 plus.
Reason being that we're using some system calls that make it run on every architecture.
So you can build it on a Raspberry Pi or any architecture of your like, any architecture
that Linux supports.
In expense of not having support for prior versions.
That was us.
Thank you.
This is the URL.
Yeah, the URL is there.
Right.
Yes.
But we also have a QR code if you find it.
Do not trust QR codes.
You don't know.
You're going to be re-crowned.
Right.
Yeah.
This is not the same URL.
So we're plenty enough time.
Questions?
We'll get it.
I have a question.
How do you want when the file is going that it can crash?
Because the process might be too right for the file.
Right.
So the question was how do you know when to hash the file?
Because when you open it for writing, you have to know when the modification ends.
And then you should hash the result.
Is that correct?
And the answer is?
Well, we hash the file when we find the closed system call.
You wait for all modifications to happen.
And then upon the closed system call, the process is stopped.
So all the stuff is in there, the virtual memory.
And the list goes on.
So you hash the file at that time.
We also hash the file when we open the file to see if it was seen before.
So we can have a nice graph.
In fact, the graph is just a dependency graph like a semantic web, as one makes sense.
Sorry.
I have a hand.
So how do you consume all those information?
I mean this graph.
Nice.
So the question was how do we consume this?
We produce all this information.
And how is this consumed?
And the answer is this is a build recorder.
It just records.
Here's the information.
We do not consume it at all.
It might be used to create, to enter it into an S-form or something like that.
That's completely out of this.
This is just recording all this information.
It's out of the scope of this project.
Let's see.
Sorry.
Have you tried converting the data to SVDX?
We tried converting the data to SVDX.
Similar question to that one.
No, we just record build.
This is a build recorder.
Right.
Another tool might read this wonderful output and create whatever they want.
It's way on the back.
The question is have we explored EBPF, EBPVF, whatever.
You know what I'm talking about yet.
The answer is no.
Not yet.
I should list of pieces open on GitHub.
Come and play.
Sorry.
You just mentioned Maven as an example that still can't be recorded.
Could you just summarize why?
Doesn't Maven also write the web?
Oh yeah.
Sure.
The question is what's the problem with Maven that we said that it's going to be handled
in the future?
On this level, Maven works the same.
We can't record the information.
But will we just be recording?
Hey, a jar file was just being used.
We would like ideally to record because Maven already downloaded it.
But we're just tracing the file system calls.
So ideally we'd like also to record the information.
Hey, we're downloading from this location this jar file.
We put it there and then we use it.
On the level that we're using it, we can record it right now.
Sorry.
Go ahead.
I missed you.
Sorry.
Do you have a way to distinguish between a file which is written completely or a file
which is modified?
The question is do we distinguish between modifications to a file or completely new
created file unwritten?
And the answer is?
Well, if we did that, the performance would be even worse.
You can actually do it.
You can actually add another handler that checks for write system calls and has the
file every time, but imagine if you have to has the file every time someone calls write.
I don't want to.
Sorry.
There's not a question just saying that yesterday the Dell maintainers in the Go dev room showed
how they replaced
C trace with EBPF and their debugger and performances were pretty improved.
The comment was that there was a yesterday talk in the Go dev room that they showed using
EBPF instead of P trace for similar work and performance was great.
Something to explore.
Yes.
Go ahead.
The question is, can we use the code that we're using?
The question is, how does this compare to scan code trace code that suppose doing the
same thing?
We have not measured for that.
I didn't even know that.
Sorry.
If it runs for the trace.
Oh, if it runs for the trace.
It's the same as trace.
We don't.
Any other questions?
Could you just see inside like if you were building a Docker container, would it be able
to see what's going on inside here or would you just run it in your Docker file?
Wow.
The question was, what does it happen when you run it while building a container?
You mean?
So again, remember, it just records all the system codes right into the disk.
So when you run it while you do Docker build, it will record all the files being used in
order.
So if you do copy things, it will record everything being copied into the layer.
Right.
Stuff like that.
Go ahead.
To be honest, the command doesn't have to be a build command.
You can literally plug in anything in there.
LS or whatever.
I mean, we are not supporting it.
We can promise that we will be supporting it in the future, but you can do that.
So anything you can imagine, it will run.
It will probably record that Docker was called.
Docker will still run all those dependencies.
It will still try to compile.
It will still link against all those libraries with.
Anyways.
Any thoughts about going off Linux to Windows?
We added an open source conference.
Repeat the question.
Yes.
They asked if we're planning to implement something like this on Windows.
Well, no.
First of all, it's hard.
The idea would be great if I have developers who can do that and know the corresponding
things magic to do in Windows.
PR is welcome.
It's an entirely different process.
You don't have to all the system groups.
We can work with that.
It should see the interactions.
There must be something in Windows, but I don't know.
Are we done?
Okay.
Thank you all.