All right, so good morning.
Guten Morgen, Wilkam, Bündjur, Huilmore.
Yeah, I can speak too many languages.
For the people that know who I am, my name is Thomas Thiembergen.
I'm the head of the Open Source Program Office at EPAM.
I'm involved in several, well, you can call it Open Source Governance,
and S-BOM-related projects, including I run the security profile over the defects team.
So if people have questions about security information in SPX3,
I'm happy to answer those as well.
I decided to just not make pretty slides, but to just open a browser,
so to be more like a demo and to make it a little bit more interactive.
Since I'm the first talker, I have to keep you all awake,
and I'm usually a very high-energy person.
Apparently last night I was compared to Oblix,
and I fell into a fat of open source juice,
and therefore I'm all hyped up on open source stuff.
So yeah, so I normally can talk very fast,
so I will try to be a little bit slower.
So I'm here a little bit to talk about Wort.
Wort is a project, or OSS review toolkit.
It should be standing a little bit left, so that you and the camera is framing both you and the slides.
Better?
Perfect, like first talk.
So it should work. Hopefully my internet is all working.
So yeah, if you are on GitHub, you can find Wort here.
The full name is OSS review toolkit, or open source software review toolkit.
It's a very complex name. It's actually for those people that are German.
Wort in German means place, and I used to work for a location company,
and all of our open source project had a location pun in them.
So we were really trying to figure out all of the names,
and how can we make a location name, and this is where we landed on.
So I'm actually going to do somewhat a live demo,
but my internet is not working 100%, so we're just going to do it like this,
where I just have luckily pages open, and I'll show you through.
So if you want to get started with Wort, the easiest way is actually to use the GitHub action.
And you can just literally, as the code shows here, you just add a few lines,
and basically it's very standard for people that are familiar with GitHub actions.
In the middle there's a checkout.
The line on top is a little bit different, and I'll get to it in a minute,
and then you run Wort itself.
This line is a little bit different, and it has to do with how Wort generates S-bombs.
So for to create good S-bombs, you can make S-bombs that basically only operate on kind of like the declared license,
the basic package data, but if you want to have a proper, what you want to do,
I originally worked in automotive industry.
We want to know everything down to source level.
And why is that? It's actually very simple.
In the automotive business, basically products on the market, the minimum lifespan is 15 years,
and it can go up to 25 years or longer, because the vehicle on the road is minimum 10 years on the road,
plus European legislation contract laws are now about 5 years, 15 years.
So all the solutions that we built for S-bombs, my successor of my successor of my successor, still needs to be able.
So this is why we started building the way how Wort is designed, that we were like,
hmm, we need a format that we can take the scan results that we have and all that we can just do, store them long term,
in a public format that even if the tool in the V-ride doesn't exist anymore in 10 years, it's an international standard,
so they can just write a new parser, read in this, and then of course I stumbled upon,
and then I happened to make Kate at FOSDEM in the bus.
And so we got talking, and I was like, hey, that's interesting, this S-bomb thing,
so this is like years ago, like what, 2015-ish, I think, 16-ish, a long, long time ago.
So then I was like, hang on, I can solve two of my problems, I can basically have an output format that is recognized,
so I have a long term archive format, and I also have a format that I need it to exchange.
So there are two forms of, why is that?
In automotive, there is a long supply chain.
So what we have commonly, we call this hamburgers, where you get something from a supplier,
you do your thing, then it goes to another supplier, and then my company will be again in there.
So we were just looking at what is the solution that we can, in the supply chain, basically exchange information.
It still is, unfortunately, or a model procedure, so still a lot of paper-based processes,
and we were like, no, no, we need to go digital.
So what you now see, luckily, is that some of the large German ones, which again, I'm based in Berlin, Germany,
they're already switching to basically say S-bombs, and then, no, no, no, yeah, you can still do paper,
but we actually prefer you to give us an S-bomb, because then they can ingest it much more easier.
So yeah, we basically do SPDX, and actually we also support something that is for exchange, and also for archiving.
So yeah, now, it is like that my talk was about how you generate it, so it's actually very simple.
So I took you to the MIME-type projects, which is kind of our default project.
It's a small node project, and if I want to do an S-bomb for it, it's actually very simple.
For people that are familiar with GitHub actions, you just run the action.
There's as simple as it is.
And you can also do this in GitLab.
I don't know for people familiar with GitLab, but basically it's all the same.
You just run a GitLab pipeline.
It says org-scan, and you basically get a nice log.
You click on the Browse button there, and you get basically nice results,
and it's kind of...we generate all of this.
So we actually go further on S-bombs, because just generating an S-bomb is not good enough.
So that the file is generated, that's nice, but you actually want a quality S-bomb.
And it's actually quite challenging to produce a good S-bomb.
What do you think?
People know. Show me your hands.
What do you think, or just speak up loud, what do you think is the problem with generating an S-bomb?
The input data.
The input data. What input data?
Well, you don't know.
You don't know the input data.
So when we do an analysis of your software project...
I'm also originally an engineer. I still do coding.
We're happy when things build.
So all the build tools are basically optimized to build code.
To keep track of what actually went into your code, yeah, that's kind of an additional feature.
It's not a requirement that the build tool does that.
So to figure out what actually goes into your software project,
I bet whatever tool is your poison, whether it's a Maven or Gradle or MPM,
I'm pretty certain your tool can produce a list of the packages that are included.
I hate to tell you that, but most of the time that list is incomplete.
For instance, if I look at MPM, MPM has six methods to give you a list of what is included.
All of them are incorrect.
And it's not to blame anything on MPM.
No, no, when I build things, MPM is a very... JavaScript is a very rapidly developing ecosystem.
So they build functions really, really rapidly. It's amazing.
I work in MPM and know it a lot.
So they add a feature for a particular use case.
And looking at S-bomb, it was simply not a use case that was supported.
So they have different views. There's one quick view that just shows you quickly the dependencies.
There's another view that shows you basically, hey, this was coming somewhere, but if you look, for instance, at a complete S-bomb,
you probably have seen if you're a node developer that there are node packages that you see C++ below.
So node is just used as a wrapper for some other CCC++ program, for instance, to compile your glyphs, your fonts.
What you will look in when you generate an S-bomb, it might see the wrapper, but it will not see the C++ thing below it
and what's in the compiled thing there, because the MPM tarball just contains the compiled C++ code for every platform.
So you won't find this out.
So the way how we went about this is, okay, what we do, we need to resolve everything back to source code.
And that's actually really, really complicated, because if you want to look at Maven,
that whole ecosystem is basically the GIF developer compiled code, not the source code.
Yeah, you can find a metadata. You can kind of figure out what went into this Java project.
But actually, here's a fun fact.
Most of the time, the package metadata from this Maven project is actually incorrect.
For example, not the Bash, for instance, on Amazon, but if you know the Amazon Java SDK,
and you look at the metadata, it points to the right code repository.
Great, Amazon, great work.
But Maven doesn't have a solution to tell you when you have a code repository,
which folder in that code repository actually contains the source code for the package.
And if you know the AWS SDK for Java, it's one code repository with close to 500 packages.
So I have here a jar from the Java SDK. Where is the source code for that jar?
Oh, yeah, it's in this code repository with another 400 plus of its friends.
And for me to know the exact licensing or security vulnerabilities, I need to know exactly which source code.
So then you need to do all kinds of tricks.
So this is where we built our tooling to basically figure this out.
I just want to give you a slight one of the output formats.
So this is where we basically created a simple single file.
We call this the web app. It's a single file. It's not a server.
So when we started building this, we're like, no, no, we want to be compatible with as many different systems and many stuff.
We want to have a docker container that you can just run in your CI CD pipeline,
and it produces just plain files because every developer knows how to handle single files.
You can take this file and you can just send it to your lawyer,
and the lawyer can open the file and they can also view it.
We were all optimized for a CI pipeline.
The second thing that we were looking at it is when we look at things, we want to be when we throw a violation.
So here you have a package in top. You see a license package that's a copy left in source.
So you can write policy rules in order, very powerful policy rules, whatever you want to do.
But when you draw a policy violation, and this was on our complaint that we had a lot of tools,
when you write in your open source policy, like I don't allow this license,
you should tell your users how they can fix it themselves.
Why? Well, in my company, I have 55,000 software engineers.
If all of them, if they don't know it, contact my team, yeah, I'll be very busy.
So the way how we set things up is like, no, no, no, no, we want things to be open source.
We want to be based on open standards, SPDX, Python DX, so all S-bomb standards.
We want to be able to write a policy where we can write whatever we want in our actual legal policy,
actually translated, or it has something called policy as code.
You can really take whatever your policy is and you can encode that.
So we want to really be able to do. And we want everything to be plain file,
so it's easily integratable, whatever CI system.
Why is that? Well, I run an Ospo, an open source program office.
Are people familiar, hands up, who's familiar with the term open source program office?
Some people. So an open source program office is the industry term for like your knowledge center
with an organization regarding open source.
So I run an Ospo, what that basically means is that all open source questions,
everything comes to my team and we try to help our engineers with contributing back
with compliance questions or help with community topics.
We really like there to basically help our organization become better at open source.
So that means I get lots and lots of questions regarding open source.
So I want something that really scales because I have thousands of engineers.
Having this how to fix new text and having a very powerful policy,
I can exactly decide, okay, these are the things we really want to fix
and these are the things we don't want to fix and we want to provide exactly the guidance.
So the funny thing, you might see this here.
This is actually all YAML file and Git based.
So we use actually the same developer workflow with pull crests to basically fix up our licensing.
Why do we do this?
Actually because that's what the developers are already known for.
The developers already know how to do all of this stuff.
So we enable the developers to fix things themselves.
The other thing is we can now use inner source to fix license compliance problems
and security problems together.
And why do we want to do this?
Well, the more things we can actually fix issues instead of what a lot of tools do,
what they call notify more, they throw you an issue up and then you have to fix it.
It's better basically if we work together to actually fix all of these issues
than if we did the inner source.
This was actually the first time we did this.
It was very, hang on.
So other teams are going to fix my license compliance and security teams?
Yes, because in our organization, guess what?
A lot of the same open source is shared between a lot of different teams.
So instead of having every team do all of this compliance and security work by themselves,
for the things that are shared, we do collectively.
And the nice thing is you can do this in your organization,
but we also not only open source the tooling, we also open source the data
and the policies from the org side.
So you can also do this with the whole community.
So we're working and we had a workshop on Friday to discuss how can we do this even further,
how can we collectively work to create better S-BOMs.
That's pretty interesting.
A little sneak peek.
Lots of code, beautiful code, right, in the morning?
This is the other thing that I'm working on already.
This is what it is.
It's the security profile.
So the latest things that we're now working on is like, okay, we want to combine,
update everything and include vulnerabilities as well.
And then you come into a lot of other challenges to create an S-BOM.
So technically, actually, to be clear, security info should ideally not be in your S-BOM.
It should be as a standalone artifact.
It's in S-BOM format, but standalone.
So because your S-BOM should be fixed for your software release and your security information is probably updated.
But then, actually, we ran into a lot of challenges with including security information.
Because guess what?
A lot of security information is either locked up in a priority database
and actually is a lot of times not really accurate.
And that's what we figured out when we were starting to move into security data.
A lot of the data, when you actually look at the data and you look, and I've been working with Philippe from next B,
and looking at this data, you'll figure out that the ranges of software for a lot of CVEs are actually incorrect.
And we were like, no, no, we want to build open source tooling that reduces the burden on our software developers.
Well, I need accurate data.
So it's actually funny now that we started creation mechanisms, as we called it, to fix up license data.
And now we have to build creation mechanisms for security data as well so we can actually fix up the security data
so that at the end we can produce high quality S-BOM.
So we know exactly like these packages were in there under these licenses.
And at the time of release, we know this security vulnerabilities.
And now the next thing is, how many people are familiar with VEX?
Few.
VEX is an upcoming standard.
If you have a security vulnerability, you can basically say, like,
oh, yeah, I know this security vulnerability was found by my scanner.
It's reported.
But I compiled this package with these, say, parameters.
So this vulnerability is actually not applicable to my software.
So it's a way to, in a machine-readable way, to say, like,
yes, the scanner will pack a security vulnerability for OpenSSL.
But the way I use OpenSSL, I don't use the particular code where the security vulnerability was found for.
So that's the next challenge we're working on, like, how can we do that in an automated way?
And that's it.
I think let's go to questions.
Do people have any questions?
You might want to speak up to the microphone.
Oh, we did? Okay.
So basically most of the time when you compile stuff, you do, like, three shakings,
and so you import a library, but you don't import all the functions inside the library.
So if a vulnerability is found in the library but not one in the function you import,
is there, like, some kind of way to detect that?
So the question is, like, is there a way to detect if you compile software whether something is included or not?
Correct it?
You want to?
So I think the question was, if there is a component, but you're not using the whole component,
you're using just a part of it, and there is a vulnerability,
but the vulnerability is for something that you do not use,
for example, a library, a function that is never called in your code, right?
Is there a way to detect that? That's all great.
Honest answer, no.
I don't know about that. I disagree.
There is a difference, okay.
So you can do it, but when I look at things at scale.
So you can do it for individual cases.
You can do this where you know the compiler and other stuff.
What I'm looking at is, like, if you have a larger configuration, like, we use tens of different compilers with tens of things.
It doesn't scale.
So the way how we did it around it, we in order to have a mechanism where you can basically indicate either via SPDX what you're using,
or you can add a creation afterwards where you say, like, yes, I'm using this package, but I'm only using this folder,
and then order for automatically subtract the things that are not applicable.
Okay.
One more question. Quick one.
Let's see here if you want to come up.
Yeah. Do you set up already?
The As
Well, we actually have all source things in there as well, but it's.
But mostly we do build. So basically we look at your source code. We pull it out.
Basically, like in this source code, the idea why we started there is because everything started source code.
Okay. The next speaker. Right.