I want to go very quickly because the rounds are very short.
I'm sorry I'm rushing through because I don't want to keep you from the very
juicy part.
So we are presenting a complete, as complete can be, compliance toolchain for
Yacht projects.
So this in the context has been produced for a project we are part of called Eclipse
Onero or Onero in short.
It's an Eclipse foundation project.
It's Yacht based and it provides a scenario platform project.
It's very complex, the numbers are quite impressive, cannot run through but they
are quite learned and everything is based on CI.
So everything is CI.
We also needed to have a completely CI also compliance process.
So we needed to build with the existing parts and building parts that did not exist by
providing a dedicated toolchain.
This toolchain for compliance has been made not just by us but by the noise path park.
People are in the room as well and they have done much of the heavy lifting of programming
and Alberto of course gets the credit for the software.
It's also an Eclipse foundation project and it's alright.
There is a repo and you can look at everything.
It's based on already existing, the known subjects of compliance, for soldiers to
encode but we have to create a dedicated new custom set of tools also being distributed
as open source.
Of course we use SPDX all across the toolchain for many things and this is important.
This is not just for this project.
This is meant to be a toolchain for all Yacht based projects, not just for this.
Through this combination of tools we have been able to complete a very lengthy process
of compliance, reaching 100% of coverage of all the components.
I don't want to skip thanks to the Debian providing a lot of the information we have
really used.
Here you can see very quickly the dashboard so you can track the evolution and the status
of compliance.
You can also go and have many more details of the single packages.
That's just for knowing what components and what license is there but we cannot stop there.
We want to go farther and we have what we call the second phase of the compliance toolchain
and we decided to go for a graph database for many technical reasons because there are
a lot of interaction and we ought to traverse the database very easily.
We need to do the missing part which is software composition analysis, dependency analysis
and incompatibility checks.
Everything must be done automatically as much as possible.
This must be entirely into the CI pipeline which it does.
In order to do this we need several things.
This is a really important map.
All licenses data from the source to the binary and at file level mapping.
While file level mapping we mean every single file including patches.
Everything that goes through needs to be checked, checked and tracked through in order to make
sure that everything that goes inside is tracked.
This information comes from many sources.
We had a node team that has done a lot of work and finally we need to find a way to
automatically as much as possible see if the inbound and outbound licenses are compatible
with each other through automated tools.
This is in a very short time the general description here in the example of the relationship between
components in the database.
There is the next bit which is perhaps more interesting and I give the floor to Alberto.
Thank you Carlo.
The question is why do we need this?
Yocto workflow for those of you who are already familiar with that is quite simplified here.
We have recipes.
Recipes can map to a single upstream source component but possibly also to different upstream
components maybe the main application then some plugins.
You can have here many different upstream sources combined together fetched and together
combined into a single work here in the AMP
stage task of the build process.
Then the other task, configure, patch, whatever basically build you got binaries and binaries
are combined together to form the final image.
The problem is that when it comes to absent sources we have upstream components that have
multiple licenses inside it.
Maybe we have different components with different sets of licenses but the thing is we have
only a small subset of the binaries that we could generate for all this stuff.
The binaries you don't know what the actual license is especially when here you have kind
of a mess.
The thing is that you risk that some dirty stuff ends up in your image.
I don't know if you have a package with a blacklisted license or a compatible combination
of licenses you may have in your final image something that is not compliant and this is
something we need to avoid.
The thing that we have to do is to follow a process.
To find out the relationship with third party upstream code, the inbound code, then we need
to find under which license the inbound upstream software is therefore the inbound license.
If there is a possible combination of that because not all combinations are allowed and
depending on the context they may be allowed or not like other talks pointed out this morning.
We need to match this combination with the abounded license compatible with the inbound
licenses.
This is for each artifact.
We cannot do that especially in the embedded field at package level because the package
may contain a lot of stuff and we need to know about the files not the generic about
the package.
Here we have an example.
I hope it's readable.
This is GPGME component that GPG made easy.
It's very small component.
In our project we found it out that we generate only three binaries out of it.
If you look at the license and the recipe you find GPL I guess three or LGPL2 or something
like that.
This is nothing, sorry not or but and.
The thing is that this binary is that LGPL is that something else we don't know from
what we have from source license information.
We collect in this graph database multiple sources of information.
On yellow dots are the information coming from our OD team working on phasology.
File levels, source license information.
The purple dots are comes from the Octo metadata and also the information about which files
have been generated by to generate.
They have been used to generate this binary comes from the Octo from the CreateSPDX class
presented before.
Basically we now have MIT, MIT, GPL2, GPL3, sorry GPL2 or later or LGPL3 or later and
then we have GPL3 or later.
What's the license of this file?
Usually the OD team comes to us and we discuss to find out which is the license of the binary
file.
But this is not scalable.
This is error prone.
We cannot do that for every single binary file, for every release, for every snapshot
of the project.
This is another example.
This is another binary you can generate from the same component.
Here we have MIT, MIT, MIT, LGPL2, 0.1 or later.
This is another story.
Maybe it's easier here.
We can have also more complicated, I won't go into the details here.
How can we handle that in an automated way?
The idea is to have a battle between license cards.
You put together every time two cards and you need a set of rules to decide who wins,
which card wins and then you iterate and you look over all the possible combinations of
license until only one will survive, hopefully.
To do that, we are trying to define the language to define those rules.
We need to define the two license cards, the two license cards that are fighting against
each other.
We need to find the battlefield context, static linking, dynamic linking, whatever.
The authority who said that, because the answer by the lawyers always depends.
We need to say who said that.
In this case, FSF.
We trust it, especially when it comes to GPL, compatibility matrix.
Here we are the result of the battle.
We have a winner or we have invalid.
This kind of combination is not possible because GPL2 is not inbound compatible with Apache
2.0, while GPL2 or later may be inbound compatible with Apache 2.0 if you make it become GPL3
because GPL3 is allowed to be inbound compatible with Apache 2.0.
This is kind of an example.
I don't have time to go into details.
The rules in action are like here.
When you have a disjunctive license expression, you need to calculate the Cartesian product.
You need to have, in this case, MIT, GPL2 and GPL3 fighting against each other.
Again, MIT, LGPL3 and GPL3 fight against each other.
You find a list of the decision and we know that GPL3 or later is the license that prevails
here at the end.
Sorry.
The thing is that how I said, already said, we consume data from different sources, from
physiology, from Yocto.
For now, we have proof of concept.
The aim is to upstream everything into the Create Aspidics class in the Yocto project.
I don't think we have time for questions, but here and in the slide, you find all the
information to conduct this.
Thank you.