It's four o'clock, so let's look at our preview.
Sorry, now next talk.
I have been doing some matting in Go, but building a database I honestly have strong
respect for.
So next up is Etienne, who is going to tell us everything about crazy good journeys in
Go.
Thank you.
Yeah, welcome to our mad journey of building a database in Go.
And yeah, it's pretty mad to build a database at all.
It may be even worse or even a matter to build a database in Go when most are built in...
Okay.
Closer?
Cool.
Let me start over in case you didn't hear it.
Hi, my name is Etienne.
Welcome to our mad journey of building a vector database in Go.
So building a database at all could already be pretty mad at doing it in Go when most
are built in C or C++.
Could be even even matter or even more exciting.
And we definitely encountered a couple of unique problems that led us to create creative
solutions and there's lots of shouts out in there and also a couple of wish lists that
we just released Go window 20 and of course the occasional madness.
So let's get one question out of the way right away.
Why does the world even need yet another database?
There's so many out there already but probably you've seen this thing called chat GPT because
that was pretty much everywhere and it's kind of hard to hide from it.
And chat GPT is a large language model and it's really good at putting text together
that sounds really sophisticated and sounds nice and sometimes is completely wrong.
And so in this case we're asking is it math to write a database and go I might disagree
with that.
But either way basically we're now in a situation where on the one hand we have these machine
learning models that can do all the cool stuff and do this sort of interactively and on the
fly and on the other side we have traditional databases and those traditional databases
they have the facts because that's kind of what databases are for.
So wouldn't it be cool if we could somehow combine those two.
So for example on the query side if I ask Wikipedia why can airplanes fly then the kind
of passage that I want that has the answer in it is titled the physics of flight.
But that is difficult for a traditional search engine because if you look at keyword overlap
there's almost none in there.
But a vector search engine can use machine learning models basically that can tell you
these two things are the same and searching through that at scale is a big problem.
Then there's that sort of chat GPT side where you don't just want to search through it but
maybe you also want to say like take those results summarize them and also translate
them to German.
So basically not just return exactly what's in the database but do something with it and
basically generate more data from it.
And that is exactly where VVA come in.
So VVA does a vector search engine which basically helps us solve this kind of searching by meaning
instead of keywords without sort of losing what we've done in 20 plus years of search
engine research.
And now most recently you can also interact with these models such as chat GPT GPT 3 and
of course also the open source versions of it.
So VVA is written in go.
Is that a good idea?
Is that a bad idea or have we just gone playing that?
So we're not alone.
That's good.
So you probably probably recognize these things.
They're all bigger brands at the moment than VVA but VVA is growing fast.
And some of those vendors have really great blog posts where you see some of the like
optimization topics and some of the crazy stuff that they have to do.
So if you've contributed to one of those some of the things I'm going to say might sound
familiar.
If not then buckle up.
It's going to get mad.
So first stop on our mad journey memory allocation then that also brings us to our friend the
garbage collector.
So for any high performance go application sooner or later you're going to talk about
memory allocations.
And I definitely consider a database a high performance application at least I consider
VVA a high performance application.
And if you think of what databases do like in essence basically you have something on
disk and you want to serve it to the user.
That's like one of the most important user journeys in a database.
And here this is represented by just a number.
So it went for UN32.
So that's just four bytes on disk and basically you can see these four bytes.
If you parse them into go they would have the value of 16 in that UN32.
And this is essentially something very much simplified that the database needs to do and
it needs to do it over and over again.
So the standard library gives us the encoding binary package and there we have this binary
dot read method with which I think looks really cool.
To me it looks like idiomatic go because it has the IODA reader interface like everyone's
favorite interface and you can put all of that stuff in there.
And if you run this code and there's no error then basically you get exactly what you want.
You can turn those sort of four bytes that were somewhere on disk, turn them into our
in memory representation of that UN32.
So is this a good idea to do that exactly like well if you do it once or maybe twice
could be a good idea.
If you do it a billion times this is what happens.
So for those of you who are new to CPU profiles in Go this is pretty bad.
So first of all you see it in the center parsing those one billion numbers took 26 seconds
and 26 seconds is not the kind of time that we ever have in the database.
But worse than that if you look at that profile we have stuff like runtime, MLGc, runtime,
memmove, runtime, and advise.
So all these things they're related to memory allocations or to garbage collection.
What they're not related to is parsing data which is what we wanted to do right.
So how much time of that 20 seconds that we spend what we wanted to do.
Don't know doesn't even show up in the profile.
So and to understand why that is the case we need to quickly talk about the stack and
the heap.
So you can think of the stack as basically your function stack so you call one function
that calls another function and then at some point basically you go back through the stack
and this is very short-lived and this is cheap and fast to allocate and why is it cheap?
Because you know exactly the runtime of your variables or the life cycle of your variables
so you don't even need to involve the garbage collector.
So no garbage collector cheap and fast.
Then on the other side you have the heap and the heap is basically this sort of long-lived
kind of memory and that's expensive and slow to allocate and why?
And also to deallocate.
Why because it involves the garbage collector.
So if the stack is so much cheaper then we can just always allocate on the stack right.
So warning this is not real go.
Please do not do this.
This is sort of a fictional example of allocating a buffer of size 8 and then we're going to
say like yeah please put this on the stack and that is not how it works.
And for most of you you probably say like this is pretty good that it's not that it
works that way because why would you want to deal with that?
But for me just trying to build a database and go sometimes like this something like
this may be good or maybe not.
So how does it work?
Go does something that's called escape analysis.
So if you compile your code with gcflax-m then go annotates your code basically and
tells you sort of what's happening there.
So here you can see in the second line that this num variable that we used was moved to
the heap and then in the next point you see the bytes.reader which represents our iodo.reader
escaped to the heap.
So two times we see that something happened to the or went to the heap.
We don't exactly know what happened yet but at least there's proof that we have this kind
of allocation problem.
So what can we do?
Well we can simplify it a bit.
Turns out that the binary or encoding binary package also has another method that looks
like this which is just called view in 32 on the little nd package and it kind of does
the same thing.
You just put in the buffer on the one side so no reader this time you just put in the
raw buffer basically with the position offset and on the other side you get the number out.
And the crazy thing is this one line needs no memory allocations.
So if we do that again our one billion numbers that took 26 seconds before now take 600 milliseconds.
Now we're starting to get into a range where like this is acceptable for a data basis.
And more importantly what we see on that profile the profile is so much simpler right now.
There's basically just this one function there and that is that is yeah it's what we wanted
to do.
So admittedly we're not doing much other than parsing the data at the moment but at least
we got sort of rid of all the noise and you can see the speed up.
Okay so quickly to recap if we say a database is nothing but reading data and sort of parsing
it to serve it to the user then we do that over and over again and we need to take care
of memory allocations.
And the fix in this case was super simple we changed two lines of code and reduced it
from 26 seconds to 600 milliseconds.
But why we had to do that wasn't very intuitive like that it wasn't very obvious.
In fact I haven't even told you yet why this binary dot little nd dot read why that escaped
to the heap.
And in this case it's because we passed in pointer and we passed in an interface and
that's kind of a hint basically that something might escape to the heap.
So what I would wish is yes this is not a topic that you need every day you write go
but maybe if you do need this would be cool if there was better education.
Okay so second step delayed decoding.
So this is kind of the idea that we wouldn't want to do the same work twice and we're sticking
with our example of serving data from disk but now while the number example was a bit
too too simple so let's make it make it slightly more complex.
We have this nested array here basically a sort of slice off slice of view in 64 and
that's representative now for a more complex object on your database.
Of course in reality you'd have like string props and other kind of things but just sort
of to show that there's more going on than a single number.
And let's say we have 80 million of them so 10 million of the outer slice and then eight
elements in each inner slice and our task is just to sum those up.
So these are 80 million numbers and we want to know what is the sum of them.
So that is actually kind of a realistic database task for an OLAP kind of database.
We need to somehow represent that data on disk and we're looking at two ways to do this.
The first one is JSON representation and then the second one would be sort of binary encoding
and then there'll be more.
So JSON is basically just here for completeness.
We can basically rule it out immediately.
When you're building a database you're probably not using JSON to store stuff on disk unless
it's sort of a JSON database.
Why because it's space inefficient so if you want to represent those numbers on disk like
space and JSON basically uses strings for it and then you have all these control characters
like your curly braces and your quotes and your columns and everything that takes up
space.
So in our fictional example that would take up 1.6 gigabyte and you'll see soon that we
can do that more efficient.
But also it's slow and part of why it's slow is again because we have these memory allocations
but also the whole parsing just takes time.
So in our example this took 14 seconds to sum up those 80 million numbers and yeah as
I said before you just don't have double digit seconds in a database.
So we can do something that's a bit smarter which is called length encoding.
So we're encoding this basically as binary and we're spending one in this case one byte
so that's basically a U and eight and we're using that as a length indicator.
So basically that tells us that when we're reading this from disk that just tells us
what's coming up.
So in this case it says we have eight elements coming up and then we know that our elements
in this example is U and 32 so that's four bytes each.
So basically the next 32 bytes that we're reading are going to be our eight in arrays
and then we just continue.
Then we basically read the next length indicator and this way we can encode the stuff in one
continuous thing.
Then of course we have to decode it somehow and we can do that because we've learned from
our previous example right so we're not going to use binary.littleendian.read but we're
doing this in an allocation free way.
You can see it in the length line basically.
And yeah our goal is to take that data and put it into our nested sort of go slice of
slice of U in 64 and the code here basically you see we're reading the length and then
we're increasing our offsets and we know where to read from and then we're basically repeating
this for the inner slice which is just hinted at here by the decode inner function.
So what happens when we do this?
First of all the good news 660 megabytes that's way less than our 1.6 gigabyte before so basically
just by using a more space efficient way to represent data we've done exactly that.
We've reduced our size.
Also it's much much faster so we were at 14 seconds before and now it's down to 260 milliseconds
but this is our mad journey of building a database so we're not done here yet because
there's some hidden madness.
And the hidden madness is that we actually spend 250 milliseconds decoding while we spend
10 milliseconds summing up those 80 million numbers.
So again we're kind of in that situation where we're doing something that we never really
set out to do like we wanted to do something else but we're spending our time on yeah doing
something that we didn't want to do.
So where does that come from?
And the first problem is basically that what we did what we set out to do was fought from
the get go because we said we want to decode so we're basically thinking in the same way
that we're thinking as we were with Jason.
We said that we want to decode this entire thing into this go data structure but that
means that you see we need to allocate this massive slice again and that also means that
we need to in each inner slice we also need to allocate again so we're basically allocating
and allocating over and over again where our task is not to allocate our task was to sum
up numbers.
So we can actually just simplify this a bit and we can basically just not decode it like
while we're looping over that data anyway instead of storing it in an array we can just
do with it what we plan to do and in this case this would be summing up the data.
So basically getting rid of that decoding step helps us to make this way faster.
So now we're at 46 milliseconds of course our footprint of the data on disk hasn't changed
because it's the same data that we're reading which is reading it in a slightly more efficient
way but yeah we don't have to allocate slices and also because we don't have these nested
slices we don't have slices that basically have pointers to other slices so we have better
memory locality and now we're at 46 milliseconds and that is cool so 46 milliseconds is basically
the time frame that can be acceptable for a database.
So quickly in recap we immediately ruled out JSON because it just wasn't space efficient
and we knew that we needed something more space efficient and also way faster binary
encoding already made it much faster which is great but if we decode it upfront then
yeah we still lost a lot of time and it can be worth it in these kind of high performance
situations if you either sort of delay the decoding as late as possible until you really
need it or just don't do it at all or do it in sort of small parts where we need it.
No wish list here but an honorary mention so Go 1.20 they've actually removed it from
the from the release notes because it's so experimental but Go 1.20 has support for memory
arenas the idea for memory arenas is basically that you can bypass the garbage collector
and sort of manually free that data so if you have something that you know has the same
sort of life cycle then you can say okay put it in the arena and basically in the end free
the entire arena which would sort of bypass the garbage collector so that could also be
a solution in this case if that ever makes it like right now it's super experimental
and it basically tells you we might just remove it so don't use it.
Point stop is something that when I first heard it almost sounded like too good to be
true so something called SIMD.
I'll get to what that is in a second but first question to the audience who here remembers
this thing raise your hands okay cool so you're just as old as I am so this is the Intel
Pentium 2 processor and this came out in late 90s I think 1997 and was sold for a couple
of years and back then I did not build databases definitely not in Go because that also didn't
exist yet but what I would do was sort of try to play 3D video games and I would urge
my parents to get one of those new computers with an Intel Pentium 2 processor and one
of the arguments that I could have used in that discussion was hey it comes with MMX
technology and of course I had no idea what that is and it probably took me 10 or so more
years to find out what MMX is but it's the first in a long list of SIMD instructions
I haven't explained what SIMD is yet but I will in a second.
Some of those especially the one in the top line they're not really used anymore these
days but the bottom line like AVX2 and AVX512 you may have heard them in fact for many open
source projects sometimes you sort of slap that label and read me like yeah yeah has
AVX2 optimizations and that kind of signals you yeah we care about speed because it's
like low level optimized and VVA does the exact same thing by the way.
So to understand how we could make use of that I quickly need to talk about vector embeddings
because I said before that VVA doesn't search through data by keywords but rather through
its meaning and it uses vector embeddings as a tool for that so this is basically just
a long list of numbers in this case floats and then a machine learning model comes in
and basically it says do something with my input and then you get this vector out and
if you do this on all the objects then you can compare your vectors so you basically
can do a vector similarity comparison and that tells you if something is close to one
another or not so for example the query and the object that we have before.
So without any SIMD we can use something called the dot product the dot product is a simple
calculation where basically you use you multiply each element of the first vector with the
same corresponding element of the second vector and then you just sum up all of those elements
and we can think of this like multiplication and summing as two instructions so if we look
out first shout out here to the compiler explorer which is a super cool tool to see like what
your go code compiles to we can see that this indeed turns into two instructions so this
is a bit of a lie because there's more stuff going on because it's in a loop etc but let's
just pretend that indeed we have these two instructions to multiply it and to add it.
So how could we possibly optimize this even further if we're already at such a low level
well we can because this is our mad journey so all we have to do is introduce some madness
and what we're doing now is a practice that's called unrolling so the idea here is that
instead of looping over one element at a time we're now looping over eight elements at a
time but we've gained nothing like this is we're still doing the same kind of work like
we're doing 16 instructions now in a single loop and we're just doing fewer iterations
so by this point nothing gained but why would we do that well here comes the part where
I thought it was too good to be true what if we could do those 16 operations for the
cost of just two instructions sounds crazy right well no because Cindy I'm finally revealing
what the acronym stands for it stands for single instructions multiple data and that
is exactly what we're doing here so we want to do the same thing over and over again which
is multiplication and then additions and this is exactly what these SIMD instructions provide
so in this case we can multiply eight floats with other eight floats and then we can add
them up so all this perfect here maybe not because there's a catch of course it's our
mad journey how do you tell go to use these AVX two instructions you don't you write assembly
code because go has no way to do that directly the good part is that assembly code integrates
really nicely into go and in the in the standard library it's used over and over again so it's
kind of a standard practice and there is tooling here so shout out to avo really cool too that
helps you basically you're still writing assembly with with avo but you're writing it in go
and then it generates the assembly so you still need to know what you're doing but it's
like it protects you a bit so it definitely helped us a lot so SIMD recap using avx instructions
or other SIMD instructions you can basically trick your CPU into doing more work for free
but you need to sort of also trick go to use assembly and with this tooling such as avo
it can be better but it would be even nicer if the language had some sort of support for
it and you made my saying now okay this is this mad guy on stage that wants to build
a database but no one else does needs that but we have this issue here that was opened
recently and unfortunately also most recently because no consensus could be reached but
it comes up back and back basically that go users are saying like hey we want something
in the language such as intrinsic so intrinsics are basically the idea of having high level
language instructions to do these these sort of avx or SIMD instructions and C or C++ has
that for example one way to do that and maybe you're wondering like okay if you have such
a performance hot path like why don't you just write that in C and you see go or write
it in Rust or something like that sounds good in theory but the problem is that the call
overhead to call C or C++ is so high that you actually have to outsource quite a bit
of your code for that to to pay off again so if you do that you basically end up writing
more and more and more in that language and then you're not writing go anymore so fortunately
that's not or it can be in some ways but it's not always a great idea so demo time this
was going to be a live demo and maybe it still is because I prepared this running nicely
in a docker container and then my docker network just broke everything and it didn't work but
I just rebuild it without docker and I think it might work if not I have screenshots basically
that do a backup so example query here I'm a big wine nerd so what I did is I put wine
reviews into vv8 and I want to search them now and one way to do it to show you basically
that the keyword that you don't need a keyword match but can search by meaning is for example
if I go for an affordable Italian wine let's see if the internet connection works it does
so what we got back is basically this this a wine review that I wrote about a Barolo
that I recently drank it and you can see it doesn't say Italy anywhere it doesn't say
affordable what it says like without breaking the bank so this is a vector search that basically
happened in the in the background we can take this one step further by using the generative
side so this is basically the chat GPT part we can now ask for database based on the review
which is what I wrote when is this wine going to be ready to drink so let's see you saw
before that was the failed career when the internet didn't work now now it's actually
working so that's nice and here in this case you can see that so this is using open AI
but you can plug in other tools can plug in open source versions of it this is using open
AI because that's nice to be hosted at a service I don't have to run the machine learning model
on my laptop then you can see it tells you the wine is not ready to drink yet we will
need at least five more years which is sort of a good summary of this and then you can
see another one is ready to drink right now it's in the perfect drinking window so for
the final demo let's combine those two let's do a semantic search to identify something
and then do an AI generation basically so in this case we're saying find me an aged
classic Riesling best best wine in the world Riesling and based on the review would you
consider this wine to be a fruit bomb so let's have sort of an opinion from the machine learning
model in it and here we got one of my favorite wines and the model says no I would not consider
this a fruit bomb while it does have some fruity notes it is balanced by the minerality
and acidity which keeps it from being overly sweet or fruity which is if you read the text
like this is nowhere in there so this is kind of cool that the model was able to do this
okay so let's go back now is the demo time by the way have a GitHub repo with like this
example so you can run it yourself and yeah try it out yourself so this was our mad journey
and are we mad at go are we mad to do this well I would pretty much say no because yes
there were a couple of parts we have to give get really creative and have to do some some
yeah rather unique stuff but that was also basically like the highlight reload building
database and all the other parts like it didn't even show the parts that went great like concurrency
handling and the powerful standard library and of course all of you basically representing
the gopher community which is super helpful and yeah this was my way to basically give
back to all of you so if you ever want to build a database or run into other kind of
high performance problems then maybe some of those