Okay, thank you everyone. Our next speaker has some interesting news in for your CI. There are
better solutions than the YAML you used to and he's gonna, so Mark is gonna talk to us about
building a CI pipeline with Dagger in Go. Thank you, thank you. Can you hear me? Okay, so very
important information before we get started. I have some Dagger stickers here if you want to pick
them up. I know maybe I can just leave them after the talk or you can come to me and pick them up.
I'll leave the stickers over here and people can grab them. Important thing, stickers are for your
laptop not for the room. Every sticker you put inside a room involves them we have to pay for,
so keep them for yourself. Yeah, well that's why we are going to conferences for, right? So thank
you again for joining me today. My name is Mark and for the better part of the decade I've been
focusing on or helping the jury teams focus, build, helping them focus on their business
applications, building their best business applications instead of worrying about things
like CI and how they are being deployed. And I have this fake title at Cisco called technical
lead, but I decided that I would come clean here today. That I'm really nothing more than just the
YAML engineer. That feels good. Anyone else want to number themselves? I didn't have their YAML
engineers here. All right. So let's talk about CI CD a bit and CI or CI systems improved a lot in
the last couple years. We have new and more involved CI solutions today, but we still have
some challenges that we face every day, like the one I've been ordering hinting at YAML. Obviously
YAML is one of the biggest problems with CI systems today. And admittedly sometimes like using YAML
to build the declarative pipeline can be fine, but man, you miss a space. The whole thing just
broke. The whole thing just broke. And you might not even know where to start debugging it. So
YAML makes it often really hard for people to even just touch CI. And the other thing is CI
like tends to break for no obvious reasons. Like the pipeline that worked yesterday may not work
today and you don't really know why. And obviously as developers, when something breaks in production,
we can just tell the ops people to worry about it. But with CI, that's not really the case. Like
we have to interact with CI and if something goes wrong, we might have to be the ones who fix it.
And with the currently available CI solutions today, you can't really like everything that's
running in the cloud or in the remote system, you can't really have or you don't really have tools
that you can use to debug effectively, you have to start guessing and start changing some YAML config
and you have to push that to a repository and then wait for the CI to get triggered and you have to
go through this whole and long feedback loop to be able to debug what's going wrong and to be able
to fix that. And that's a pain. Like it takes a lot of time. It's really a huge waste of time.
And it's really painful to do that. Now, sometimes it's not the CI that's wrong. Sometimes it's you,
like pushing something that you shouldn't be pushing to the repository like tests are not
passing or the linters are not passing or something else goes wrong. And again, you may have the tools
locally in your machine, but you may not have the same versions. You may not have the same setup
as in the CI and it may just break in the CI even though you ran the test locally and all everything
was green. It may still fail in the CI and you still have to go through the same long feedback
loop again and again, trying to fix that instead of being able to run the whole thing locally and
being confident that it will just work in the CI as well. And probably there are other challenges
with CI, but these are the ones that wasted hours from my life in the last couple of years. So,
how can Dagger provide an answer to these problems? So, first of all, Dagger is a programmable and
deportable CI solution, which means you can run your CI pipelines basically anywhere. We will get
to how it does that. But the important thing is that you can run your CI pipelines anywhere using
the same environment, which means if it runs on your machine, then you can be confident that it
will run the same way in your own CI system. Now, that's a great thing for a number of reasons
because when you start building a pipeline, for example, using any of the CI systems today,
you still have to go through that feedback loop, like adding some config and then pushing it to
the get to the flow and trying to figure out if it works or not and then changing until it works.
If you have the ability to run this whole thing locally, it's much shorter feedback loop so you
can build your own CI pipelines much more quickly than using some remote system. The other thing is
that if something goes wrong, you have the whole thing running locally. So, again, shorter feedback
loop, you have more tools to debug, so it's much easier to figure out what goes wrong, even if
it's either the CI pipeline or your code. The other thing about Dagger is that you can actually
write your pipelines in your own preferred language. Now, not any language, obviously,
some of the languages that the Dagger supports, but that's already much better than the YAML.
Like, you can write your pipelines in Go or Python or TypeScript, thinkQ, evenQ,
but that's already much better than YAML. You can write your own pipelines in code and you don't
have to invent or use some weird syntax, for example, to represent dependencies between steps
or between different pipelines. You can just do that in plain code. So, that's great. And all those
some of the portability in writing pipelines in your own language points to the fact that you can
avoid pandor locking entirely. Like, you would still have, like, a CI solution, like,
Jenkins or GitHub actions or whatever, and you would still run Dagger on those systems, but you
would have to write, like, a very thin integration layer just to run the Dagger pipelines, and you
can you would be much more confident that the pipelines would run the same way on the CI system
as on your computer, and, yeah, you can avoid vendor locking entirely. Like, you can move to
another CI system if you want to, and you may say that doesn't happen often, but when it does, man,
it's really painful. Like, converting from one YAML to another or one YAML to, I don't know,
Groovy or Jenkins file or something, that's that hurts. And lastly,
costly caching. So, every CI system or most CI systems have their own caching solutions where
you can, like, cache the dependencies of your language or dependency manager, but that requires,
like, configuration. You have to make sure that you configure it right. Otherwise, well, it could
either, like, grow the caching less and you will be paying a lot of money for that, or it would just
be non-functional at all and it wouldn't cache anything properly. Now, with Dagger, everything
is cached by default. Like, every step is cached. You can think about it like a Docker file. Every
instruction or the result of it is basically cached in a separate layer in the Docker file,
and if nothing changed between the steps, then when you run it again, it will basically run the
same way and it will come from the cache. That's really how Dagger works. Obviously,
you have some control over what you want to cache and how you want to do it, but by default,
Dagger got that covered for you. Now, how does all this work behind the scenes? If I had to describe
it in one word, it's obviously containers. Now, we can do it ourselves today, right? Like, we could
just run everything in a container and it would be reasonable to say that it will run on the CEI the
same way. What Dagger adds to the mix here is that you can actually build pipelines with code,
and that would be translated into build pipelines. So, you would use the Dagger SDK, the language
SDK that Dagger provides. Again, today, I believe it's for Go, TypeScript, Python, maybe Q as well.
But the underlying API is actually the GraphQL. So, if you have a language client for GraphQL,
you can actually build your SDK if you want to, or you can just write GraphQL queries and send
those directly to the Dagger engine. But basically, you write your own pipelines using this SDK
in your own language, and then the SDK will basically send GraphQL queries to the Dagger
engine. Now, when you run the whole thing locally first, and the Dagger SDK will actually launch
the Dagger engine for you, all it needs is really a Docker compatible container runtime. So, if you
have Docker on your computer or in your CEI, then you can run your Dagger pipeline. So,
that's once more the portability of this whole thing. If you have Docker on your machine,
and Docker basically runs anywhere these days, then you can run Dagger pipeline there.
So, locally, when you launch this for the first time, the Dagger SDK will launch the Dagger
engine for you, and you send these GraphQL queries, and you'll see a couple examples how that looks
like in the SDK. And the Dagger engine basically builds a DAG-directed acyclic graph of all those
steps, and then sends it through, well, it says in OCR runtime, I believe currently Docker is the only
supported runtime. But sends through an OCR runtime and runs the whole thing in containers for you.
And then, obviously, when a pipeline is finished, you get back the results, and you can use the
results in another pipeline if you want to. For example, the result of your build pipeline would
be used in your deploy pipeline, and you could deploy your project or whatever you have.
So, that's how Dagger works under the hood. And let's take a look at an actual example.
Let's see. So, the example will be in Go, because this is the Go, the room.
Can you see it from the back?
Okay, cool. So, the first thing you need to use the Dagger SDK in Go is importing this module
from Dagger. It's the Dagger SDK for Go that you can use to interface with the Dagger engine.
And once you have that, you can basically start writing your own program. Now, in this case,
I'm using Mage. I'm not sure if you're familiar with that, but it's basically like a make file
like solution for Go. You can write these functions, and Mage will basically compile a
binary from that and execute it like it would work with make. Now, you can absolutely import
this Dagger package in your own application if you want to. In case of applications,
it's probably not a huge deal if you have an additional dependency in your Go modules. If
you're writing to a library, though, you might want to create a separate module, for example,
called CI, and import Dagger SDK in that separate module so you don't import Dagger as a development
dependency in your library's Go that modify. I know it still won't be built or still won't be in the
final binary if you import a library, but some people get to know it if they see dependencies
that is actually not necessary for the library. So make the life easier for your peers. And if
you develop a library and use Dagger, just create a separate module and put all the Dagger-related
code there. The first thing you need to do when you want to write PyPlay with Dagger is call this
Dagger connect function, which will basically connect to your Docker runtime and it will launch
the Dagger engine for you and start the so-called session. Now, within that session, you can start
building your actual pipelines using these containers. Now, it's pretty similar to how a
Docker file would look like, for good reason. But what you can do here is basically use some of the
same instructions as you would do in a Docker file. You can obviously go from a base image,
which will be going in a Go project, for example. You can mount your source code. That's how you
would have access to the source code within the container. And then you can run a bunch of commands
like test or you can do the same with the linker, for example. And the other two here,
these are the mounted caches. You can do that with the buildkit, actually. So that's, I believe,
that's a buildkit functionality. So you can mount a cache directory to the container that will not
actually be part of the container, but it will be a mounted cache directory from your host.
Now, let's see if I can run this.
So I'm using the mage minor here. I'm telling it to change to the CI directory because it's
a separate module. And then I'm telling it to use the current. Can you hear me? Okay.
Don't know what happened there. And then I'm basically just telling it to run the test
function here, again, similarly how a make file would look like. Now let's see what happens.
Kind of hope that I don't have to download all those content images.
Let's see. Let's get some logs here.
Okay.
I swear this worked like a couple of hours ago.
Oh, you know what? I think I don't have Docker running. Yeah. That's a problem.
Yeah, maybe, yeah. So I don't have the Dagger engine running. Let's see.
This should start a new container. I mean, this should start a new container.
What's going on?
All right. This is not great.
Can we operate to the Democrats, please? Thank you.
Okay. You all just have to believe me. This actually works.
Okay. So here are the logs from the previous run. So this actually worked before.
Okay. Yeah, it says let's see. Okay. Let's
try that.
Okay.
Let's see. Do we have internet connection here?
Yeah, we do have internet connection.
Okay. Well, we'll have to work with the logs from here.
Okay. So, well, basically what happens here is when it works is it just runs the whole
thing within this go along image, mounts the source code, and then runs the go that test
comment and just gives back the results. Obviously this is the build log. Like this
is the debug log, but normally it will just output the output of the go test command
or the go XCI command. Let's see. Still not working. Let's try from
the hot spot. Maybe that works better.
Anyway. Well, if someone wants to get back their money, sorry folks, this is a free conference.
Anyway, yeah, you will just have to believe me that this works, but I will try to make
this work after the presentation. Now, if you take a look at the code here, this is still not very
like user friendly. If you don't know how Dagger works or if you don't know what happens here,
then it's not really useful to you. You will have to go to the documentation and understand
how this whole thing works, when it works. So, but the good thing is that this is like,
this is code. This is not an arbitrary YAML interface you have to use. So, we can actually
make this a bit better if you want to. And what I did in the last couple of weeks is that I built
higher level library over the Dagger SDK. So, instead of writing all that container
mount nonsense stuff, you can just use this go link package. It's actually called
VOCI. You can find it here if you want to give it a try. And instead of, you still have to connect
to Dagger, obviously, but instead of running that whole or writing that whole container code,
you can just use this much more friendly interface to run your tests or run the goal in CI-Link,
for example. And it's much easier for developers to interact with this, like, if they want to
change the cover mode, for example, it's pretty obvious how you would want to do that. In this
case, compared to how you would want to do that, it would be the lower level Dagger SDK stuff.
Let's give this another try.
Okay. Now from the... Oh, still one. Let's go to the...
Well, it doesn't work. Anyway, if you want to give this a try at home, you're absolutely
welcome to do that. The documentation is getting better by the day. It has a bunch of different
examples. You will find these examples on my GitHub as well. I promise it works.
They've actually just released a brand-new Quick Start guide. So, so far, the documentation...
They had documentation for the different SDKs in different places. Now they have a Quick Start guide
that is basically the same for all of the languages. So, regardless which one you want to choose,
or if you want to try all three supported SDKs, you can do that with the Quick Start guide. And
you can actually go ahead and run the code from there. And finally, they have a playground
that works with their low-level GraphQL API. So, if you want to give that a try,
it's fairly similar to the SDK, actually. If you want to give that a try,
then you can absolutely do that and see how Dagger works without actually installing it
on your computer. So, that's all I have for today. If you have questions, feel free.
There is a sticker, and thank you very much for your attention.
If there are any questions, raise your hand. I'll try to give you a microphone.
I have one over here that's closer. Hi. Can you...
Other than Docker? I'm sorry, can you repeat that?
Can you use it with something other than Docker underneath, like Nspawn?
You can use it with Docker compatible runtime, so I think you can use it with Podman at the moment.
I think, technically, you'll see it on runtime. But I don't know if that's currently available
as an option. But we have someone from the Dagger team here who can actually answer that question.
Hi. So, how does the portability work when parts of your deployment depend on
publishing a Docker image to a repo that is external or AWS or Terraform or things that
require secrets? How does that fit in running it locally?
So, that's a great question, actually. So, the code itself should be completely portable,
so the pipeline itself can run anywhere. What you would need to do in that case is you need
some sort of either a central secret store that you can connect to from your own computer,
or you need to be able to load some sort of secrets or credentials from your environment
variables, for example. You can absolutely do that with the Dagger pipeline. So, from that perspective,
hello? And from locally, you can push to another registry or push to a development environment,
for example. So, you can parameterize pipelines based on where you run them.
You would still run the same code, but you could deploy to a different environment
from locally.
We have one more question there.
Oh, okay.
Thank you. One last applause, please.