I'm going to talk about the most painful thing I ever did in Go, which is debugging concurrent
programs.
I'll give it a pass for Andrew.
Hi.
Can you hear me well?
Nice.
I'm very pleased all of you here at FOSDIM in person finally since all this COVID.
And today I will talk about debugging concurrent programs in Golang and a little bit about
myself.
My name is Andrei.
I'm a software engineer originally from Ukraine, currently, unfortunately, living in Austria.
I am a big fan of sports, gymnastics, crossfit, and different debuggers, et cetera.
The interest in parallel programming has grown dramatically in recent years.
And the added complexity of expressing concurrency has made debugging parallel programs even
harder than debugging sequential programs.
And usually, sorry, every day at work, I feel like I have these eight stages of debugging
myself.
So that can't happen.
That does not happen on my machine.
That should not happen.
Why does it happen?
Oh, I see now.
I feel I know what's the problem.
Then how did it ever work?
So last couple days, I saw PR like, oh, it's not working since two years, some code.
And like, who wrote this?
And like, oh, wait, it was me.
So the classical approach for debugging sequential programs involves very easy straightforward
way.
So we rapidly stop on and set break points with we just go step by step.
And like, sometimes we print something, sometimes we continue, rerun, et cetera.
So and this style we just usually we call is a tick-click debugging.
But the problem, unfortunately, parallel or concurrent programs do not always have reproducible
behavior, even when they run with the same inputs on the same machine with the same results.
So an output results usually can be radically different.
And it's hard to predict.
This difference, a cure, for example, when you run some program, and as you can see,
it's very dummy one.
But output is different each time when I run it on my machine.
Sometimes it's the same, but sometimes not.
Yeah, I spent lots of time to read some books and articles and videos on YouTube.
I just always trying to find like a question, like an answer to my question.
OK, there is any like, OK, we have books how to write code.
We have books how to write tests.
OK, how to debug code.
There is no books.
Even there is no books to how debug concurrent programs.
And so to start explaining my journey, how I usually do it, let's a little bit remind
you what is gorytine.
So gorytine is just like an abstraction.
Yeah, it's just by the way, it's struct which handle gorytine under the hood inside of Go.
And usually gorytines are multiplexed on different or multiply OS threads.
So if one should block and like we're waiting for some I or call, others can continue to
run.
And there are also lots of design which hides many complexities of thread creation and management.
So Golang do it on our own.
So it's nice.
And to create a gorytine, it's very easy, just prefix your function with Go keyword.
And that's new gorytine, nothing complicated.
By the way, who knows why they name it gorytines?
Maybe somebody have ideas.
Yeah, go ahead.
Why not just call it gorytine?
So in each language, we can just replace first letter and gorytine.
Yes and no.
So like they call it at least from what I read, they call it because like threads, coroutines,
processes and so on.
It's not an accurate explanation what gorytine does.
So gorytine has its own simple model and how it's executed, et cetera, et cetera.
And that's why they know it.
Cool.
So next question.
Before I will share my experience, how do you think how can I debug my concurrent program?
So nice.
Nice.
Can you repeat what the answer was for the stream?
Thank you.
Can you repeat the question, you mean?
If you have an answer from the room, can you quickly repeat it so it's recorded on the
stream?
Okay.
Yeah, will do.
So let's repeat.
How can I debug my concurrent program?
So the gentleman suggested using print.
Nice.
Yes.
It's also of depth, by the way.
Okay.
Any other ideas?
Yes.
Yeah.
It's a good idea.
Nice.
So just to repeat for people who are watching, their ideas was using debugger.
Delft, using trace or trace, using tests, et cetera.
So my first assumption was, okay, playground.
Let's play a little bit.
And like a few years ago, like when I started like writing this talk, to be honest, there
was like a limit.
So playground worked only with Go, Max, Prods, 1.
So it always like reproduced my program.
But right now it's more or less simulate local developments.
Okay.
I have more like bright ideas.
So maybe we can just color logs.
I don't know.
Visualize Go routines.
Why not?
So here's a funny package, which just what it does.
It's just like print different Go routines with different colors like this.
So yeah.
I mean, if you do something very quick, you can just figure out which Go routine, which
color, et cetera.
Yeah.
Return to seriously.
There is interesting article.
It's quite old, but one of my friends from Ukraine, he like wrote this article also a
few years ago.
He decided to visualize how all this scheduling or routines works with these fancy pictures.
Also very good article to read.
Highly recommend.
Another idea is try to print how Go schedule events.
So there is the environment variable, which can print you some extra information and yeah.
And of course, using the buggers today, I will focus a little bit on Delft and a little
bit on GDB.
So next question.
Can I set break point inside Go routine?
Any ideas?
Yes, no.
Yes.
So the answer is yes.
Yeah.
Typically you can set break point inside Go routine.
You can jump into this Go routine, see what's inside and yeah, it's very handy, especially
if you develop like server and other stuff.
Okay.
What about channels?
So if I decide like send a message to the buffer channel of size four, yeah, it's very
nice that you can set break point.
You can pre-channel and Delft has very fancy like metadata, which shows you even like current
channel state.
So you see, I send like one, it's a first item and some information also useful.
Then if I add another one, so like next, you see now I have two elements in channel and
the small problem.
Usually like if I want to send the message to channel from Delft CLI, unfortunately,
it's not supported.
Here's the issue I created.
Yeah.
And there's a comment that yeah, we can fix it, but yeah, I hope we will fix it some time.
So you can't set, so technically it's possible, but it's not, I mean, so it can be same semantic.
You can set and Delft will handle it.
Okay.
Now let's focus a little bit on how we can debug routines.
So yeah, if you're inside a guartine and you will print a state of guartine, there's a
key word guartine.
It prints current guartine where you put your breakpoint, but if you have lots of guartines,
there's like interesting feature.
I really use a lot.
So but let's step back a little bit.
There's another idea and like implementation.
You can use this profile labels.
So it's inside P prof model.
So you can run P prof do and inside through context, run your code and it will like mark
your guartine with label.
And usually you use these labels for profiling.
So you can open P prof profiles and see like some different metrics.
But you can do it also with Delft, which is super cool.
So you can, if you label your guartines with labels like this, or if you use like middleware,
you can also do it.
I mean, if you use web server, you can use this middleware.
I post link on next slide and it will automatically like add labels to all your handlers, which
is nice.
You can see like which handler you are currently because if you print guartines, you will see
like even in Delft, you will see lots of unreadable information.
But if you just need to focus, I don't know, on login, guartines or like guartines, which
is doing something with your database, you can label it in the same manner as you do
with P prof.
And then, yeah, also you can do it directly, by the way.
This library, which I mentioned, it's very small one.
It's also support like set labels, just a wrapper.
So very handy one.
And then if you run guartines, a keyword inside Delft debugger, minus L, it will print guartines.
It's just very simple hello world, which has like this main guartine and few other guartines
without any labels, etc.
But then I created another like project inspired by one article.
And yeah, so here you can print all guartines, which relate it to your like label page.
And yeah, also you can go to docs and find different like group by, I don't know, filters.
So it's very handy.
And how you can find your guartine, then you can switch to this guartine.
If you don't know, also you can print or list source code.
You can set new break point.
It's very nice.
And yeah, also you can use this demo project.
It's not mine, but it's more written for Golan.
But if to run it, you just need to this small tweak.
You need pass some build flags and tags debugger, otherwise this library will not work.
And then you can you can repeat everything I did.
I highly recommend to play with that.
And when you need it, you will be already like with everything you need.
Regarding GDB, yeah, I play a little bit with them.
Inside not supported what I need for Golan.
Yeah, it has this like info guartines keyword.
As far as I remember, you can't like filter guartines and it's not readable.
So like, yeah, especially this part.
Yeah.
And then I decided to not waste my time, to be honest, because it's yeah, you can just
use Delft and for such problem rather than playing with GDB.
Cool.
So next, not only with debugger, you can find your problems.
One important problem in Golan world is deadlocks.
And with deadlocks, usually program gets stuck on the channel send operation, which waiting
forever, for example, to read the value.
And nice that Golan support detection of these situations compared to other languages.
For example, Python doesn't support this deadlock detection, which is hard to debug such problems.
And yeah.
If you need like real world examples, you can see this very interesting library, go
deadlock.
Which using this library, also found lots of deadlocks on Cockroach DB.
And there are lots of interesting examples how mutexes can be handled properly, how to
write it properly, and etc.
It's like this library is an entire separate like discussion.
According to our case, yeah, I wrote like I put two slides is very simple example.
So yeah, sometimes you you have this conflicting access and you have this data races.
And I saw it a few times in some open source projects.
But usually people do not do it.
So I highly recommend run UCI by applying with this dash race, especially tests.
It helps you like always run with this flag and it will print you like users data races
or not.
This dash race not always can find all data races.
Some common yes, but sometimes no.
But highly recommend to add it to your project.
So never skip.
So now I have like seven.
I have it.
I have a seven rules for you.
So how to unblock yourself when you get stuck on something and you don't know how to debug
it.
So first never assume a particular order of execution.
So when you're writing concurrent programs, try to always think about not running it in
particular order.
Especially it works with some benchmarks and tests.
So try to not put this like I also saw it lots of times when people run tests, when
you run go tests by default, if you know, they run it in parallel.
But usually people say like, no, run it like sequentially.
And that's not a good idea.
Another advice, it's more about designing than writing code.
Try to implement any concurrency logic at highest level as possible.
Try to not pass lots of channels, lots of like go routines, etc.
Try to like keep logic separately and this concurrency separately.
Don't forget, as I said, go race not always helps because it's not the text when program
like whole freeze.
It's only when a subset of go routines gets stuck.
As gentlemen suggested, you can use Cs trace and different tools for tracing, which can
help you to see like, are we waiting for some resource like reading file access net?
It's more low level, but it's very useful.
Yeah, I show it on another talk, but you probably know about it.
You can use conditional breakpoints, which helps you to cover cases, especially when
it's concurrent program so you can catch only your case, not like click next on every
go routine.
As I said, you can use shadow and tracer.
You can use go deadlock.
And yeah, last but not least, use debugger.
Don't forget about it.
It's also very handy.
Like every release, every version, I see how the buggers are adding new stuff, which is
nice.
Cool.
So I have like few references because to cover everything is hard in 25 minutes.
I will post slides so you can accurately read everything.
And I will maybe to like picture it.
And thank you.
Thank you.
Any questions?
Are there any questions?
Yeah, before you're thinking, if you want to donate to Ukraine, just let me know.
You my friends right now are fighting so we can help directly if you're afraid.
Thank you.
Oh, I have a question.
Have we tried using tools such as Rr or Hermit, which try to execute the program in a deterministic
fashion?
You mean backwards?
Yes, they can do a recording of the institution and then replay it.
But the point is that the recording is deterministic.
Yeah, I use it for sequential debugging, never for concurrent debugging.
I mean, maybe it's possible.
But in my case, it's I covered what I just showed.
Of course, there are other cases.
I will try.
If you are leaving the room, try to stay quiet for a second.
Do not talk.
Chairs are OK.
So we can still hear any questions.
Well, no more questions.
That means your talk was very clear.
Thank you.
And a round of applause.
Thanks.