Okay, welcome back.
So while you all have been walking in, I've been quickly reading this book, Fish and Go,
it reads very quickly, and now Bartek has made sure that my code is ten times quicker,
so tell us everything about it.
Thank you.
Thank you very much, everybody.
You're welcome.
I hope your travels went well.
Mine were top-party, you know, Play, Cancel, Change your pre-route, so I had lots of adventures,
but generally I'm super happy I made it, and we are at the FOSDEM.
So in this talk, I would like to invite you to learn more about efficiency of our Go programs,
and there was already two talks that I had been on who mentioned, you know, optimizations
in its name and, like, generally how to make software more efficient.
I wonder where this, I don't know, it's not hype, but it's already three talks about one
topic.
Why it's so popular?
Is it because everybody saved me money?
That might be a reason, but I'm super happy we are really uncovering this for Go, because
Go alone might be fast, but that doesn't mean that we cannot, you know, doesn't need to
care about, you know, making it better, and use resources when we execute it, right?
So let's learn about that, and it turns out that, you know, you can save literally millions
of dollars if you, you know, optimize some code, sometimes in production long-term, so
it really matters, right?
But before we start, short introduction, my name is Bartolome Podka, I'm an engineer at
Google, normally I work at Google Cloud, Google Managed Promoteer Service, but generally I'm
open source passionists, I love Go, I love distributed systems, observability topics,
I maintain TANOS, which is like open source, scalable Prometheus system, I maintain Prometheus
as well, and generally, yeah, lots of things in open source, I mentor a lot, and I suggest
you to check, you know, also try to mentor others, it's super important to bring new
generation of people up to the speed in the open source, and yeah, I'm active in the CNCF.
And recently, as you see, I published a book, and I think, you know, it's kind of unique,
everybody's doing TikToks now, and YouTube, and I was like, yeah, let's be old school,
because you need to be unique sometimes in the world, and I really enjoyed that, I learned
a lot during that, and I would love you to learn as well, so I'm kind of summarizing
some concepts from my book here in the stock, so let's go.
And I would like to start with this story, and, you know, apparently, some of the talks,
one of the best talks have to start with the story, but this is something that kind of
maybe triggered me to write a book, right?
So imagine that, I mean, yeah, that was kind of five years ago, we just started the project
called TANOS open source, really doesn't matter what it does right now, but, you know, what
happens is that it has microservices, it has, you know, I think six different microservices
written in Go like you put in Kubernetes or any other cloud, and it's just a distributed
database, and one part of this database is compact or it's like a component, again, doesn't
matter much what it does, what it matters is that it touches object storage, and it
processes, you know, sometimes gigabytes or terabytes daily of metrics, right, of some
data, so what happened is that the very, very beginning of implementation, as you can imagine,
you know, we implemented MVP, it kind of functionally worked, but of course, you know, the implementation
was kind of naive, definitely not optimized, we didn't even run any benchmark, right, at
all, other than just running on production and just, yeah, kind of works, so, and you're
laughing, but this is usually, you know, what development in a high-level ST looks like,
and it was working very well until, of course, more people put load into this, and, you know,
we have some issues, like OOMS, you know, one user pointed us to some graphs of, you
know, incredibly, you know, high spike of memory usage on the heap, on the Golang heap,
right, and you can see it's a drop, which means, you know, there was a restart or someone
killed this, and, yeah, and the numbers are not small, like 15 gigs, I mean, for large
data set, maybe it's fine, but it was kind of problematic, right, so it was really interesting
to see what different feedback and what different suggestions community were giving us, and
I mean, community, everybody, like users, other developers, maybe product managers,
we don't know sometimes who their role are, but, you know, probably depending on their
background, the answers, the proposals were totally different, right, so I would like
you to kind of, you know, check, and like check if you had the same situations in your
experience, because, you know, this is kind of like very ongoing problem, and I would
like to, yeah, showcase this, so, you know, first suggestion was that can you give me
a configuration that doesn't OOM, and it's like, what, do you expect me, like, in the
like very new project to have like flags, not OOM or like useless memory?
This is not as simple as that, yet many, many users are asking us this question of a person's
project, probably you heard this question, okay, what configuration I should use so it
uses less memory, right, or like it just, it's more optimized, how can I optimize using
configuration?
It's just, you know, it's not as simple as that, I guess, you know, maybe in Java, in
JVM, you have lots of performance flags, you sometimes tune things and it's better, but,
you know, it's not so simple, it's a goal, like, kind of low level, you, I mean, yeah,
you need to do more than that, right?
Another, you know, interesting approach, but very, very good in some way, is that just,
okay, I will just put this process into bigger machine and it's done, and that's totally
valid, you know, solution, maybe short term, maybe sometimes it's enough, but, you know,
in our case, it was not sustainable, because, of course, you couldn't grow vertically more
and more, and also, even if you would maybe find a big enough machine that was working
for your dataset, then, you know, obviously you were overpaying a lot if the code is naive
and maybe wasting a lot of memory, right?
Then finally, you know, the most fun approach, okay, let's split this one microservice into,
you know, like a scheduler and then, you know, work errors and then we'll just replicate
in my super nice computer, you know, communities cluster and, you know, it will just horizontally
scale so I can use many, many hundreds of small machines, so it will work.
Yes, but, you know, you are putting on small kind of microservice so much complexity that
it will be, like, more expensive generally, right?
Because of the network cost, like, distributed systems, you know, injects, you know, things
that you have to replicate data finally.
So if you overpaint more and more and more, and you are kind of distributing this non-optimized
code to different places, that's not always a solution.
Sometimes the code cannot be optimized more and we can, you know, we should probably horizontally
scale but not in the very beginning of the project, right?
Yet that was the first suggestion from the community, right?
Of course you can just switch from that to something else, right?
That's also a solution.
And then if you have this approach and probably you would just jump through project, this
is not super efficient but maybe, you know, some parts of the project are better or some
worse.
That's an option.
Some suggestion, some suggested, of course, paying for vendor, right?
They would solve the absorbance for me for real money.
So, but, yeah, that's not always a good solution.
That's just giving up.
And also, you know, migration of data, huge cost of learning new tools and so on.
And you know, all of this work, we're in the code, we have this.
And it's like, you know, it's bumping and super easy ways that you could be avoided,
right?
And, yeah, I understand.
So you know, of course, that was malloc.
So in Bughal we don't have malloc and so on.
But you know, memory overhead, memory leaks like that are very common in GOR.
Just imagine how many GOR routines sometimes you put, you created, you forgot to close
some kind of abstraction and the GOR routine is leaking and so you are leaking memory like
this malloc, right?
And you know, what actually, you know, was the solution was some contributor finally
came up, investigated, thought about this efficiency problem on the code level, algorithm
and code level, right?
And rewrote or like rewrote small part of the compactor to stream data, right?
So instead of building maybe the kind of resulted object that the compactor is doing in memory,
it was as soon as possible streaming that to FireSystem.
Easy.
Generally easy, easy, easy change.
Yet there was lots of discussions, lots of stress, lots of weird ideas and I would just
find it like over time amusing that this story was repeating in many, many cases, right?
So and you know, that's not only, you know, of course, experience so many kind of nice
examples where only small character change, two character change there and you know, so
much kind of like improvement over like large system.
So sometimes, sometimes there are like very easy ways that we can just pick it up and
just do it, right?
But we need to know how, right?
So kind of two learnings from the story.
One is that software efficiency and code level and algorithms for changing code, you know,
matters and learning how to do it can be useful.
And second learning is that there is common pitfall, I think, generally in the years because
in the past we have premature optimizations.
Everybody was playing with the code and trying to over optimize things.
I think now we are lazy and we are more like into DevOps, into changing, you know, configuration,
into horizontally scaling because we have this power, we have cloud.
And this is usually, you know, more chosen solution than actually checking the code,
right?
I call it closed box thinking and I think this is a thread a little bit in our system.
So we should acknowledge that there are different levels.
We can sometimes scale.
We can sometimes put more bigger machine.
We can sometimes write to Rust if that makes sense.
But you know, that's not the first solution that should come to your mind, right?
Okay.
Before we go forward, I have five books to share and I will share the link to quiz at
the end.
And it was super simple, but pay attention, right?
Because maybe there will be some questions around and you need to answer, send me an
email and I will just, you know, just choose five people, lucky people to have my book.
So yeah, pay attention.
All right.
Five steps.
Five steps, yeah, for efficiency progress.
One thing I want to mention, I don't know if you have been in the previous talk or like
more previous, he kind of explained a lot of optimization ideas.
Like I think, like Mache before, like he mentioned string optimization with internings.
Has just mentioned, I think, something around, you know, pre-allocations and many kind of
like, I think, padding, struct padding and generally, you know, all those kind of ideas.
This is fine.
But it's optimizing stuff.
It's not like looking for dictionary of things I did in the past.
It's kind of more fuzzy, more involved.
So what I would like you to focus, it's not a particular way of how we optimize an example
I will show, because it's super simple and trivial, but how we get there, right?
How we found what to optimize, how we found if we should even optimize, okay?
So focus on that.
So first step, first suggestion I would have, and this is from book, I kind of found, yeah,
I don't know, I define this name TFBO, which is essentially a flow for development, efficient
aware development that worked for me.
And generally I see other professionals doing that a lot as well.
So test fix benchmark optimize.
So essentially what it is, it's like a TDD with something else.
And TDD you are probably familiar with, test driven development.
You test first, as you can see, and only then you kind of like implement or fix it until
the test is passing, right?
I would like to kind of do the same for optimizations as well.
So we have benchmark driven optimizations, because as you can see, we benchmark first,
then we optimize, and then we profile, right?
And I will tell you later why, but all of this is a close loop, right?
So after optimizations we have to test as well.
All right, so it feels complex, but we'll make one loop, actually maybe two, doing the
stock on a simple code.
So let's do it.
So let's introduce a simple function, super simple, super stupid.
We are creating a million elements, I mean, a slice with million elements, and each of
those elements are just a string, a constant string for them.
Super simple.
It's the first, you know, kind of first iteration of this program we want to write.
So what we do regarding TFBO, okay, so we test, right?
I mean, now we have a code, for example, and we want to maybe improve it.
We test of development, so let's assume I already had the test, right?
But the test could look like this.
And then, you know, I'm ensuring, okay, it's passing, so nothing functionally I have to
fix.
So what next?
So next is this measurement.
It's a benchmark.
And, again, it has already mentioned how to make benchmarks, but I have some additions,
to that, that you might find helpful.
Something I want to mention is that, you know, we were talking about microbenchmarks, because
the same level of testing behavior, like, for example, like, for this small function,
we have this create, you know, unit test is totally enough, right?
This is on micro level, we are making just unit test, it's fine.
But sometimes if you have a bigger system, you need to have, you know, to do something
on macro level, like integration test, end-to-end test, whatever bigger, right?
And the same happens in the benchmarks, right?
This is microbenchmark.
This is a kind of unit benchmark.
There are also microbenchmarks I covered in my book.
And then you need to have more sophisticated kind of setup with low testing, with maybe
some automation, with some observability, like, you know, Prometheus, maybe, which measures
over time some resources.
But here we can, we have a simple unit create function, we can just make it simple with
microbenchmarks.
And, you know, it has already mentioned, but, you know, there is a special signature in
a test file you have to put.
And then there are optional helpers, for example, that I like, actually, to put almost everywhere.
Report allocs, which is by default making sure that this function will measure allocations
as well.
And the reset timer, which is super cool because it resets the measurement.
So anything before you allocate, you spend time on, it will be discarded from benchmark
result.
So benchmark will only focus on what will happen within this loop iteration, right?
And then this for loop, you cannot change it.
Don't try to change it.
Always copy.
This is a boilerplate that has to be there, right?
Because it allows Go to make repeatability, check the repeatability of your test by running
it, you know, hundreds of times.
Okay, so how we execute it already, again, as mentioned, but this is, you know, how I
do it, like, focus to one test.
But this is not enough, in my opinion, right?
By default, it runs only one test, one second.
I recommend to actually make sure you explicitly state some parameters, right?
And I have one liner, one liner in bash, for example, that I often use.
So what it is, essentially, I'm kind of creating some variables so I can reference this result
later on in the short-term future.
V1, for example.
So this will create a v1.txt file in my locally.
It will run this benchmark.
It will actually run it, you know, sometime, I specify, again, which is super amazing,
because it was like, okay, so I have this v1 file, what I was doing with it, and then
you check in your bash key story, okay, oh, that was one second, and then that was something
else, right?
So it's kind of useful.
And then this is crucial.
This is something I don't know why I didn't learn in the beginning.
Maybe you learned the count, dash count, right?
So what it is is that it runs the same test a couple of times, six times, actually.
And so one second, six times.
And this is super important, because then you can use further tools, you will see, to check,
you know, how reliable are your results.
You will essentially calculate the variance between the timings, for example.
So if the variance is too big, then your environment is not stable, right?
And then I pin to one CPU.
This is super important to generally pinning, not to one, right?
Just pick something that works for you for concurrency, pick something that runs on production,
maybe, or similar.
But always between tests don't change that, right?
So that's super important.
And also I recommend to change less than numbers of CPU, because your operating system has
to run on something, right?
So those things matter.
Also don't run this on laptop without power connected, because you will be CPU throttled.
There are lots of kind of small things that you think, oh, it doesn't matter.
No, it matters, because then you cannot rely on your results, right?
So try to make this serious a little bit, and at least, you know, don't benchmark on
your lap, you know, in the bed, you know, because they will be overheating.
So yeah, small things, but it matters, right?
I was doing that all the time, by the way, yeah.
All right.
So results, you know, result looks like this.
You can see many of them.
But this is not how I use it, or how we're supposed to use it, apparently.
There is an amazing tool called Benchstat, and it just prints in a more human-readable
way.
And you can see it also aggregates and has some averages over those runs, and tells you
within this percentage, for example, that the time latency, there is a variance of 1%,
which is tolerable, for example, right?
And you can kind of, like, customize what exact how it calculates this variance and
so on.
So we can trust it.
Like, it's even 1% of, I guess, free, you could trust it, depend on what you do, but
generally it's not too bad.
Allocations, fortunately, are super stable, right?
So, okay.
So we benchmarked, we measured, okay, we know our function has these numbers.
Like, I mean, what's next, right?
Everybody was like, yeah, let's make it faster, let's make it faster.
But wait, wait, wait, wait, why?
Why should we make it faster?
Maybe, okay, maybe that's a lot, 100 megabytes of every, you know, create invocation, but
maybe that's fine, right?
So this is where I think we are missing a lot of experience, usually.
I mean, you have to set some expectations, right?
Like, to what point you are optimizing?
And you know, usually we don't have any expectations.
Like, okay, yeah, I mean, even from product management, here we have maybe functionals,
you know, requirements, but never really concrete performance requirements.
So we don't know what to do.
And honestly, if you don't just ignore those requirements, okay, I don't have, I just want
to make it faster, then this premature optimization is always, right?
Because it's always premature because it's a random, random goal you don't really understand,
right?
So maybe, maybe just make it fast, right?
That's also like very fuzzy, obviously, that's not very helpful.
So what is helpful?
What I will look, and I know it's super hard.
I know it's kind of uncomfortable, but I suggest doing some kind of efficiency requirements
spec, super simple, as simple as possible.
I call it rare.
So, rare efficiency requirements.
And what it means, essentially, try to find out some kind of function, right?
Some kind of, you know, complexity, but not asymptotic complexity, just more concrete
estimation of the complexity based on inputs, right?
And for simple functions, like for example, our function, we can estimate, you know, what
in our minds we think should happen, roughly, right?
So for runtime, we know in one million time we do something.
We don't know how many in our seconds, let's pick 30.
This is actually pretty big for one iteration of just append, but just really pick some
numbers.
Sometimes it's good, it's just, you know, you can iterate over this number, but if you
don't know where you go, then, you know, how you can make any decisions.
In allocations, it's a little bit bitter, a little bit easier, because we expect a slice
of six, of one million elements of strings, and as we learned from Matri talk, every string
has these two parts.
One part has 16 bits, which has length and capacity, or maybe capacity not, but then,
yeah, length, capacity, and pointer, and then there's other parts which lies in the heap.
But for this, you know, 16 bytes, we can assume that will be 16, right?
So it's every element is 16 bytes, so now we just multiply.
That's our function, that's what we all expect, right?
And with this, we can, you know, kind of expect that every invocation of create should, you
know, kind of allocate 15 megabytes.
But what we see, we allocate 80 megabytes, right?
So already we see that, oh, there might be like easy ways to do it, or something I don't
understand about this program.
And this is what leads us to better, to spotting maybe easy wins, and spotting, you know, if
we need to do anything, right?
In terms of time, latency, it's already kind of like more than we kind of expected, right?
But this is more of a guessing, I just guessed it's 30 seconds, right?
Okay, so what we do?
Now we know we are, you know, not fast enough, not allocating, we are overallocated, right?
So then we profile, then we check, okay, we have a problem.
Now let's find what's going on.
And this is where on micro level we can, you know, use profiling very easily by just adding
those two flags.
It will gather memory profiles and CPU profiles in a file, like v1.mempprof.
On macro level, there are other ways of gathering profiles, but you can use the same format,
the same tools, there are even continuous profiling tools in all the cells, like Parcadev,
I really recommend them, and it's super easy then to gather those profiles over time.
So this, what we want to really learn is that what causes this problem?
And this is like a CPU profile, and we could spot, and the wider means it spends more CPU
profiles, the depth doesn't matter, it's just how many functions we have, right?
So you can see that create, of course, is one of the biggest contributors, but the growth
lies, right?
Like why we spend so many cycles growing slides?
Ideally, I know how many elements I have, kind of why it doesn't grow me once, right?
And then we can check, and by the way, you can use this go tool, pprof, dash, itp locally,
I kind of use it a lot on this file to kind of expose this kind of interactive UI, you
can do the same for memory, but honestly, this is not useful because Append is a standard
library function, and they are not very well exposed, right?
So they're hidden.
So this is not very helpful, actually CPU profile was more helpful, because it pointed
us to the growth lies, and if you just Google for that, you will notice this comes from
Append, and then you can go to documentation of Append and learn what it actually does.
And as you probably are familiar, because this is like, should be a trivial case, I
mean, Append resizes the slides, or resizes the underlying RI whenever, you know, it's
full, right?
And resizing, it's not super simple, it has to kind of create a new, bigger RI, and copy
things over, and, you know, garbage collection will kill the old one, but not fast enough
because of the garbage collection.
So we kind of aggregate that as another allocation, right?
So this is what happens, and kind of the fix is to just pre-allocate, right?
So to tell, you know, when you create the slides, okay, how much capacity you want to
prepare for that, and thanks for that.
So what we do now, okay, we did optimize in our TFBO, now we test before with the measuring,
because if you are not testing if this, you know, this code is correct, then, you know,
you might be, you know, yeah, we'll be happy that things are faster, but functionally broken.
So always test, don't be, you know, lazy.
Run those unit tests, easy.
And then, you know, once they are passing, you can comfortably measure.
Again, I just changed V2, just to specify another variable, right, on our file system,
and then I can do bunch.v1.txt and then V2.txt.
Again, I can put like 100 of those variables.
It will compare all of them, but here we compare two, and not only we have absolute values
of those measurements, but also a diff, right?
So you can see we improved a lot, and if we check absolute value in regards to our efficiency
requirements, you see that we met our threshold, roughly, but like we estimated it, so it's
totally good, you know, 15 megabytes, we have 15 megabytes, and then it's faster than our
goal.
So now we are good to go and release it, right?
So that's kind of the whole loop, and you kind of do it until you're happy with your
results.
So yeah, this is it, and learnings, again, five learnings.
Follow TFBO, test, fix, benchmark, optimize, use benchmarks, they are built into Golang,
they are super amazing, go test, slash, bench.
Set the clear goals, goals are super important here, right?
And then profile, and you can, I mean, Golang uses Pprof, which you can Google as well,
it's like amazing kind of protocol, kind of set of tools integrated with other clouds
and so on, and use it every day whenever I have to optimize something.
And then finally, the key is to try to understand what happens, what I expected, and what's
wrong.
Reading documentation, reading code, this is what you have to do sometimes.
And at General Tip, whenever you want to optimize something super, super carefully in some bottleneck
part of your code, I mean, avoid standard library functions, because they are really
built into generic functionality.
It will test, I mean, it will do a lot of things with different edge cases that you
might not have.
So a lot of times I just implemented my own parsing integer function, it was much faster.
So this is like General Tip that always works, but again, do it only when you need it, because
you might have a box in the disk out, right?
So that's it.
Thank you.
You have a link here, bwplot.dev.