Next up, we have two speakers for the prize of one.
They are going to talk about everything to do with an open, more open source version
of Tailscale.
So let's give an applause to Christopher and Joanne.
Hello.
This is cool.
This is Christopher and I'm going to, together with Joanne, talk a bit about how we use integration
testing to kind of re-implement the control panel or the control server of Tailscale.
So first a little bit about us.
Juan Fontelonso is the creator of HetScale.
He works for the European Space Agency on cloud and DevOps and infrastructure.
He claims to have been my first manager, but I think that's incorrect.
And he has the attention span of a goldfish.
Which makes the whole collaboration very fun.
And I'm here with Christopher.
He's a top contributor of HetScale and one of the other maintainers alongside me.
He's part of the technical staff at Tailscale and part of his time paid by Tailscale is
to work improving HetScale.
I was his manager, at least from a hierarchical point of view.
And one of the challenges we have is that he always finds these kind of super niche
languages like Ocamel or things like that where he tries to re-implement HetScale in.
But first of all, how many people here know Tailscale?
And HetScale?
Good.
That's pretty good.
So for the people who don't know, we'll do like a quick tweak what is Tailscale.
So Tailscale tries to solve this problem where you basically sit and you want to connect
your organization or home or something like this.
And you have an old school or legacy VPN concentrator where you connect into your kind of perimeter.
You have access to absolutely everything.
There's a single point of failure and a massive bottleneck.
And it tries to do this by creating like a mesh VPN that uses direct connections wire
guard and kind of facilitates this for you using techniques like natural versatile and
has a very, very powerful client that will make sure that you always reach like what
you're trying to get to.
And it offers a lot of different kind of granular access and you get a lot more power compared
to your old school bottleneck single point of failure VPN.
And in Tailscale, the clients are open source, at least for the open platforms.
And what they have is a closed SaaS.
But still they are quite open when it comes to explaining how the whole thing works.
And in March 2020, they published a blog post basically explaining how the whole thing worked,
how they use these natural versatile techniques to so you don't have to open the ports in
the router.
And there was a phrase in this blog post that gathered my attention for a little bit and
it was basically talking about a coordination server that the clients talk to a coordination
server core of this service service offering, which is essentially a shared rob box for
this wire guard public case.
So I was puzzled by that and basically took that open source clients and started reverse
engineering, basically a lot of print apps to see what kind of payload were they sending,
what kind of endpoints or protocol they were doing.
And yeah, this was around April 2020 in June.
I mean, there was a lot of free time at that time and in June I did the initial release.
I talked to my friend Christopher about tail scale and he was very happy distributing wire
guard keys with Ansible, which yeah, so I kept doing my own thing for a while.
Head scale gain a little bit of traction and around mid 2021 he joined because he was quite
curious about the whole thing.
But he was afraid about breaking stuff and that's why kind of we are here.
Although he was not afraid of making a logon that I think is super nice.
So what I've learned during this reverse engineering exercise is that the test kit clients talk
to what is basically a web service.
This web service receives metadata from the clients like the endpoints or the wire guard
public keys that they use and assigns them IP addresses like you would have in a classic
traditional VPN service.
Once everybody knows about everything, you can establish this mesh network across the
clients because the data doesn't go through the web service.
So we arrived to the initial stage of head scale.
The illusion that everything works and kind of worked until you stop doing.
So we had this web service, we implemented the web service, series of endpoints that
we found in the reverse engineering exercise and we were assigning IP address when that
node arrives and what happens when a second node arrives.
Hey, we want to tell that I'm here and I want to find my friends and I want to communicate
with them.
So in order to handle that and to handle the metadata that you need to establish the connections,
we developed a little bit of a state machine to handle a new node has arrived.
There has been a change in the map of the network and we need to distribute the updated
metadata that we have.
However, at that time I was kind of learning go and we follow a little bit of a weird approach
in handling concurrency which was basically adding more mutex every time we needed it.
And this is a problem because at the end we ended up with a great mutex for this state
machine and this is a very big problem because a Python track is tomorrow so the grid logs
are over there.
So what ended up happening inside this state machine or what didn't end up happening was
that basically some of the failure modes we saw was that a new node tried to register
and then we burned a couple of CPU cycles trying to calculate some stuff and then we
did nothing.
So no updates were sent out or anything.
Sometimes we would have a new node joining and we would compute everything, send some
network traffic.
We just omitted the new information.
That was kind of crucial for everyone to know.
So it ended up not working.
And sometimes a new node joined, nothing really happened but then eventually something happens
and it sent out an update to everyone and that was useful.
And sometimes on the individual update channels for each node some of these aforementioned
mutexes kind of deadlocked up the whole thread or the go routine and then we just never sent
updates to particular nodes and sometimes we just deadlocked the whole server and you
kind of had to kick it to make it come back to life.
But still there was kind of this notion that it did work pretty well eventually most of
the time and it gave this kind of like dissolution of working.
Because what you often saw was that you had like three nodes and only two of them actually
talked together and as long as those had received the updates they needed, the user was happy
and you're just like, it works so I'm going to press the star side on GitHub and share
it with my friends.
So but we figured that eventually this would like caught up with us and we're trying to
get to this stage where we, you know, it works most of the time.
So what we did have was a fair amount of unit tests but the problem with unit tests is that
we're trying to reverse engineering something, that we're also learning how it works and
what we spent a lot of time on was misunderstanding how it was supposed to work, writing unit tests
that would pass but they were wrong so you kind of have like a passing test and it's
an entirely wrong implementation.
And 90% of what we were actually trying to do was integrate with a third party software
and this is where we get to actual integration tests.
So what I started doing was I found this Docker test framework which basically allows you
to programmatically create Docker containers.
So we started making tests that spun up a headscape container, it created a bunch of
tail scale instances also running in Docker and associated them with a couple of users
and tried to emulate the entire environment so you can test everyone to everyone.
We had them join the head scale server and since it takes a little bit of time for everyone
to catch up with each other and send the updates and stuff, so we put a sleep of two minutes
in front of the test which is a terrible idea but you know, you learn.
And then after that sleep runs out, presumably everyone is now up to date and can talk to
each other so we had a test, the most basic test is, is my network working, can everyone
ping everyone?
So we tried to do that.
And of course that didn't work because of all of the errors we actually had in the code.
And I ran some initial, like, tried to make some statistics on my laptop and out of like
100 test runs we had 70 failures, that's pretty bad.
But at this point we're starting to approach like we have an actual goal that we can measure
so we can improve on this.
And quite rapidly we figured out that these two big blocks of problems that we have is
associated with two things.
So one of them is the being able to reliably send updates to all of our clients, which
is the kind of deadlock problem that the update channels were just locking up and didn't really
work.
So we made a massive, massive rewrite PR that redid the whole logic and made sure that we
always were able to send an update to the client as long as it was connected.
And then the other problem was the state machine that was very broken.
And then we kind of figured out that we can make a global state and we tried to simplify
it initially and optimize later.
So basically a global state, how can we determine if everyone is up to date and make sure that
we know when you last received this successful update and if not we have to reissue ones
to make sure that you know everything.
However, changing the Rambo culture takes a little bit of time.
We kept merging stuff without proper integration testing, but as Christopher said, we didn't
have the incentive, we didn't have the pressure because the thing really worked.
It's not the same when you are in your home lab and you join a node than when you are
joining 100 nodes within one second.
So if you are slowly joining machines to your tail net, things were working.
However, the project was gaining popularity and we were increasing more and more in contributions,
in external PRs.
This was around August 2021 or September, something like that.
But it was great.
We were getting to a point where we could improve head scale with confidence.
We had a...
We could improve head scale with confidence in three aspects.
From a technical point of view, given that the project started as reverse engineering
effort, we had a lot of stuff that was not that great.
We could improve or maintain the compatibility with this third party external clients that
we are using and we could improve from a community point of view.
I'm going to talk a little bit about this now.
For starters, we could improve from a technical point of view.
We could do massive refactoring within the project or implementation of the second version
of the protocol without breaking the existing users.
The only thing that breaks is probably the mental health of the reviewer that has to
deal with 3000 lines of code.
But that's a different thing.
Then as I said, we have this minor small detail that we completely depend on a third party
client.
Because we are using exactly the same official clients as a stale scale.
However, we have a very good working relationship with them and every time that they change
something we get a heads up.
However, we keep everything, our integration tests, quite a bit commitment for support
of these clients.
We target the head of the repository, we target the unstable releases and we target nine
minor releases of the client to make sure that nothing breaks from their side or from
their own hours.
Because I mean, it can happen.
And then I think integration testing also helped the community because we as maintainers
can trust in a better way those random PRs from random unknown people that appear in
GitHub.
Which is something that is not given.
And in theory, or that's what one would think is that by having integration tests, contributors,
also external people that we don't know, should also feel more confident when submitting
a PR.
But that's a theory.
So it does still come with some challenges.
So one of the things that we see occasionally is that a PR comes in and it doesn't have
a test and then we ask nicely if they can add test and the contributor disappears.
So some of the times we're trying to improve on this thing and kind of like always get
them in.
So what we try to do is if they truly disappear, we try to pick it up if it's a feature that
we really want and we are bound to do so.
Sometimes we try to reach out and kind of sit and help them write a test and kind of
onboard them in this kind of things.
One of the tests actually for our, there is a SSH feature and the test for that, I knew
the developer and he was also in Norway.
So once I was dropping by Oslo, we sat down for an afternoon and we worked on them together
and paired on them.
That's not available for everyone, sadly.
But we always try to kind of like get this test message out there in a way.
But there is a couple of other challenges as well and that is that adding the test raises
some sort of learning curve.
So you need to know Go test, you need to understand our test framework, you need to have Docker
and all of these kind of things versus not writing tests that are a lot less code.
And it's hard to convince people how awesome tests actually really are, that they're not
really a chore and that you really, really thank yourself later for doing them.
So some of the things we're trying to do to even make this barrier lower, since we're
so heavily dependent on this for compatibility and everything, is that we're making like
our own test framework V2 because we depended on a lot of repeated and copied code and there
was a really high bar for adding new tests and it was really hard to update and change
and it did depend on time.sleep which was, yeah, haunted me so many times and it couldn't
really be run in parallel for many of the previous reasons and the documentation wasn't
really good, like I knew how to use it, one knew how to use it and then that was about
it.
So a couple of other people figured it out.
So what we're trying to do is we're abstracting things a bit away.
So we have this concept called control server which is what essentially head scale is and
the tail scale product, the software as a service and it's implemented as head scaling
container and it exposes convenient functions that now have Godox support and all of these
things to make it easier for developers to actually use it and then we have the tail
scale client which is implemented as tail scaling container and it has the same type
of convenience functions and what this allows us to do is previously the two files on the
right here, sorry, on the left is two different versions of the setup code for the test because
when you needed something that was slightly special, you had to copy the whole thing and
then make a new file to be able to write a test case like you see on the other side here
but now after abstracting that away, making it a lot more configurable, we allow people
to write more or less regular test cases but you just set up what we call a scenario which
is a head scale with a given amount of tail scale nodes and then you let them ping each
other or something like this.
So what do we test right now?
We kept all of the original tests.
So basically we make all nodes join the network and we make them ping each other to verify
that we have a fully functioning network both by IP and magic DNS.
Magic DNS is tail scale DNS system.
We test tail drop which is a file sharing feature a bit like Apple's AirDrop and we
send the files from every node to every node to make sure that they work.
We test all our registration flows because we've broken them a couple of times so it
was better to do it that way which is pre-authored keys and web plus a command line flow and
even open ID we currently have tests for.
We try to isolate all of our network from the internet and test with our own embedded
relay server because tail scale depends on relay servers that we also embed in our binary
and we have a preliminary test for the SSH features that we support which is like authenticated
by head scale so you can SSH into your machine and we test SSH all to all and we try to
do negative tests and also we test our CLI because if you may change something you don't
want to sit and type in every single command in a structured way manually because that's
just painful.
So in the future we want to also kind of improve this granular access control that tail scale
offer.
Currently this is a very good example of where we have added a lot of unit tests and they
all pass but they're all wrong.
So they're mostly wrong so we have to kind of redo most of this into integration test
first and then kind of backfill the unit test once we know how the implementation is actually
supposed to work.
And one of the things we've been dabbling with especially for this ACL feature is to
use that control server abstraction we have before and use the tail scale product to test
our tests because if they pass on the public server we know they're correct and then we
can use them to verify our thing and then maybe run tail scale in the VM instead of
Docker to test it properly but that's more of a benefit for tail scale than it is for
us.
So if you're just here waiting for the next talk a little bit of a TLDR is that I mean
we cannot understate how important having this integration testing when we depend on
an external party having for the development of hell scale.
I reckon also the head like a name is also excellent.
Pointing tail scale would have been worse.
We have I mean with integration testing we are able to maintain this compatibility with
a client and we are able to take contributions from third party developers otherwise it's
a little bit more difficult to develop this trust across the internet right.
And even though the tests are not perfect and we still have to migrate unit tests towards
integration tests I think this is one of the keys for the success of the project.
So some extra things.
Tail scale is hosting a happy hour at a brew dog by the station.
This QR code takes you to a sign up form.
I'll quickly switch back to this slide at the end but I have like a question slide as
well so you know we go through this.
Basically this is how to reach us.
Get up we have a discord community and we're very happy to talk to anyone who wants to
talk to us here at Fostem so please feel free to reach out and I'll leave it at this one
if anyone has any questions we have we have some minutes I think.
Thank you.
While I have your attention we have a go for that lost air wallets.
Look to the left look to the right front and back if you see a wall that is not yours please
come bring to the front it will help this person a lot.
Thank you.
Let's switch things.
After you look for the wallet and you have a question raise your hand and I'll try to
come with these microphone.
How is the front thank you.
How come the tail scale guys are not mad at you and not only are not mad at you but they
heard you afterwards.
I mean part of it is working.
No.
I think part of it is that they are quite chill.
I mean they could have they are quite chill.
They could have taken this way worse than they have and I don't think we are competition
we are focused on self hosters on home labs perhaps a little bit of a small company.
I'm going to usually happens is that people that use head scale at home then they go to
their companies and they talk about their scale and when you're in a company you actually
prefer to pay for the service.
So it is like a way.
Thank you very much.
Last round of applause if you have any questions you can catch them in the hallway track.