Thank you.
We have to stay on our schedule.
So our next speaker, Rona, she stood here three years ago but
before the pandemic was a thing and she gave us a challenge to
solve the Go diversity problem within a year. Rona, is it
solved?
Well done. Well done.
No? No?
So actually, Martia stole this from me because three years ago
I did challenge this forum to solve the problem of lack of
diversity within the Go community within a year.
And then the pandemic hit and it seems that these issues kind of
took a long time to solve the problem.
And so the issues kind of took a side, were pushed aside
unfortunately. But we can start again.
So I'm here to talk to you today about a lighter topic, is Go
object oriented? Now, it appears to be something that people have
many opinions about. And I hope that you do too because that
will be fun. So I am Rona. I'm a Google developer expert for
Go. I create workshops. That's kind of like my thing when I
want to teach something. I make a workshop about it. And in
2022 I kind of realized that after a few years of seeing
developers struggling with different paradigms around the
Go typing system, specifically with interfaces, I figured why
not create a workshop about it and I submitted it to Go for
Europe. It was the name of the Go workshop was object oriented
design with Go. And then the comments started coming.
So something between object oriented is dead. Please let
it R and P.
I'm going to give a comment to why. Somebody posted a comment
on my tweet and then blocked me. Because apparently that's how
the Internet works. So, yeah, and somebody blamed me for
introducing spring into Go. Now, I have been a developer for
20 years, but I have not done any spring in my life. And that
is why I'm here. I was fairly surprised. So I'm not here to
promote my workshop, even though I'm giving it again this year
in Berlin. And, you know, in June, because that would be
bad. So what is object oriented programming? So it's the idea
of building software into things or objects or concerns or
instances and adding some functionality to them, usually
called messages or methods or member functions so that we can
work with software in a more intuitive way, the way that we
understand how we interact with the real world. That's it.
Now, where there are things, it can get incredibly messy.
That's the business model behind Marie Kondo. Yeah. I felt
this sigh. You don't have 14 items maximum in your house.
You're not alone. And we have this lovely quote from Joe
Armstrong. The problem with object oriented languages is
that they've got all of this implicit environment that they
carry with them. You wanted a banana, but what you got was a
gorilla holding a banana and the entire jungle. And that
feels like it. It does. It really does.
So go really went a different way. It tried to sort of stay
away from this. But we'll see what remains and what actually
remained from this and what actually we were able to let go
of in a second. So we're going to hold a trial where we're
going to check you're going to be the jury. You're going to
decide if go is object oriented. I'm going to try and convince
you. I'm going to show you the arguments for both sides. And
I'm going to have to convince you that it is object oriented
or I am responsible for defamation. I am taking the
ghost good name and dragging it through the mud, tarnishing
it, hurting its reputation. You're the jury. You will decide.
So disclaimer, this is not a real trial. But and I'm the
judge and the rules are what I say they are, which is to say
that these proceedings are going to be ridiculous. But yeah,
we're just going to have to do it. So what have we come to
expect from an object oriented language? Most of you know this
by heart, really. We have classes because classes and only
classes can have methods classes can also have this constructors
constructors are created allowed to create objects safely.
And we also expect inheritance. Objection. So in go. We don't
have classes. And therefore we don't have constructors, but we
pretend to have them. So here's where we pretend to have
something. Now this one is quite fun. So this is a package that
I created. And you can see here that inside type robot, the
go doc aggregated nicely a function called new. Now you
can see that it doesn't actually have a receiver. It's not a
method. It's not anything. And it's just the package level
function that the go doc understood to be a constructor
and then added it where it should be nicely nested inside a
robot type. Which is really interesting because what that
means was that the go team essentially decided at some
point that safe construction of objects is a tooling problem,
not a language problem. It's interesting. We work
constructors. Okay. All types can have methods. So you've
probably seen this or code similar to this some point in
your life. So I created a new type my thing out of an
integer. So we have a new type with an underlying type int. I
added a method foo to it using the receiver. Remember that we
said earlier that we have objects interacting through
messages. It's called a receiver because it receives.
It's that easy. Yeah. Come on. All together. Nobody agrees.
What's going on? Yeah. Okay. Pathetic. But yeah. I said I
was going to judge. All right. So and then we have so now
we created a variable T of type my thing. We assigned it
one and then we're able to call a method on T foo. Voila.
We have a primitive type and it has a method because in go
all types are created equal. Thank you.
Only real life. Okay. So let's move on to inheritance. So we
get in go we get composition. We don't get inheritance.
That's not something that's available to us. So this little
snippet here is supposed to show the difference. I created
a type a it's an empty struct. I added a method foo to it.
It has a method bar foo calls bar. That's nice. Returns bar.
We have type B that embeds a it can embed as many as many as
many as many as many types as it wants. It embeds a that means
that now it has foo and bar and then it decided to override
bar. Fine. Variable B of B lowercase B of type uppercase B
to be confusing not to be confused. Okay. Get it.
And we can call B dot bar and we expect B dot bar to be
invoked directly and then we call B dot foo. Now with
inheritance we would expect B dot foo which returns a dot bar
which is overridden to be called. So we would expect to get B
in both cases. But that's not what's going to happen because
we do not have this type of polymorphism. That is true.
Who was it who said it earlier? Raise your hands.
Round of applause to the gentleman.
Okay. Moving on. So let's talk about single and multiple inheritance
because this really bugs me. So I started my career with seven years
of C++ and yes it sounds biblical because it is.
Thank you. Yeah. So I started with seven years of C++.
C++ actually has a really nifty feature you can inherit a lot.
You have multiple inheritance. It's not limited. Java, Ruby,
they allow you to inherit exactly once. That to me does not
feel like a feature. That feels like a limitation. I don't
understand it. Let's say that you have a truck and you want to
describe a container of goods and a vehicle. You cannot
inherit from both. What do you do? Well, in Go we have composition
but in many, many languages that offer inheritance you only get
single inheritance. Now I will say this. If you feel, and I know
that a lot of people do, if you feel that inheritance is that
important, it just doesn't make sense that it will be so limited
a feature that you will not be able to use properly or like
or fully. And I do believe also that that is the cause of all
the messy code that we see because my, the classes that I
used to define were very small, were one function, two functions.
I didn't have to make odd choices of what is going to go
into a class or what wouldn't. So it was really easy to be
very expressive. So that's what I personally, my personal
opinion, is about single and multiple inheritance. I don't
feel in most common languages since it's usually single
inheritance, I don't feel that it makes it a, it makes it
something that is going to determine whether a language is
or isn't object oriented because if it is, then as far as I'm
concerned, single, any language that has single inheritance
cannot be object oriented. So, go is not object oriented, the
usual argument summary, and I'm going to like, you have to
understand that I'm aggregating here everything that was sent
to me over the internet, which is a great source of information
and also a great source of information. So, go is simple,
object oriented programming isn't, therefore go is not object
oriented. Go doesn't have classes, so go cannot be object
oriented. It doesn't have inheritance, so it's not object
oriented. And lastly, and this one is a great argument, we're
going to dive into that one, methods are not really messages,
so go is not object oriented. Now, this one is fun. So this
comes from the Alan Kay school. So all the fans of Alan Kay
have jumped in to let me know everything about the history of
object oriented. So here's what I've got. One person said
technically they aren't methods, so he's referring to
receiver to method receivers, they aren't methods on type T,
they are functions where the first argument is type is the
type. The promotion to them as methods is syntactic sugar.
It's why you can call, now look at this, this is amazing,
V dot foo with bar or T, call the type, invoke a method on
the type and provide V as a parameter. And it's true, show
you what it looks like. So same code as before, we have a
empty struct, we have method foo on that we added to A,
quiet in the court. We have method foo that we added to
type A, which is nice, and we can invoke it using two ways.
One is clearly less common than the other, so this is the
common way, or we can invoke it on the type and pass in
lower case A as a parameter. You have the screen?
That's why, by the way, a pointer receiver can be nil.
So I have this game, I play this game all the time with
people who are new to go and ask them what's going to happen.
So I create, we are able to create methods with pointer
receivers. So I add foo and make the receiver a pointer.
I create variable A, which is a pointer to upper case A,
which is a pointer to the pointer. It's zero value is nil.
And I invoke A.foo. And then I ask people what will happen.
Now, we're not going to be able to do this quiz here, because
we are late on time and we have to make up some time.
So, hi from foo is actually returned by foo, which means
we were able to invoke a method on a nil pointer.
It's possible because there is no receiver, there's no actual
receiver. Most of the time when we call a method in other
languages, what happens is that we are, we have to go and
go through some reference that's somewhere in the address
space of the variable itself. This tells us that it's not
where the method is at all. It's not where it's defined.
It's not where the run time looks for it. It's just not.
So my coorganizer, my women who go coorganize it, Jessica
Green saw this and said, so there is no spoon, which I
thought was amazing, because this is kind of a design thing,
right? So everything is in our minds. Really everything is in
our minds. We sort of, you know, we have these philosophical
ideas and then we put them into code. If there is anybody who
actually thinks that the gopher that you saw on the screen in
the maze, there is an actual gopher out there doing this, let
me know. I want to hang out. So where do receivers come from?
So listen to this, because this is very interesting.
According to the Go team, the Inspiration2 method receivers
came from Oberon 2, which is the object oriented version of
Oberon. Okay. And they're called receivers because they
receive messages, except there is no receiver. So everybody's
right. Another thing that the same person brought up, which
is really cool, he said, well, I forgot to say who Alan Kay
was. What's wrong with me? Alan Kay is the creator of small
talk and also is considered to be the person who coined the
term object oriented. So he's supposedly supposed to know
stuff about it. You know. So that's why people quote him and
that's fine. It's totally fine. And he has a lot of opinions,
which is also great. We encourage opinions. So what a
person said to me, so in small talk, you don't need to
explicitly declare that an object can have a specific
message. You send it a message and then it decides whether to
handle it. So duck typing. Now, this is really interesting.
Can we do this and go? Can we check if a certain value, if
this can handle a certain message or has in layman's
terms, has certain methods? Well, the answer is yes,
through the magic of interface conversion. So again, we type
a, we added function foo, it doesn't do much. We don't
actually care what it does. And we created interface i,
uppercase i. And this interface has one function, defines
one function, foo, that returns a string. And a,
coincidentally, or pointed to a, coincidentally, also has
foo, which is a string. Now, this is where go completely
differently than other languages. In go, interfaces are
implicit. In most languages, if you have, let's say, class
a and you wanted to implement interface i, you have to, at
the time of creating that class, you have to say something
like class a implements i. That means that you have to be,
that you cannot have a type that is not aware, has no
idea that, and implements, that a certain interface exists
and will implement it. Not unless, not unless, that's
why a lot of people move to scripting languages, because
that allows them to pick some code from the internet and
use it. You know, just use it. Regardless of what's going
on. And go allows you to actually download some random
code from the internet and plug it in using your own
interfaces. It's very strange. It's very unique. So, with
that in mind, if you have implicit interfaces, it makes
sense to be able to try and be able to ask whether a type
implements an interface. Because maybe it does. In other
languages, it just doesn't make sense because the answer
will be no. Right? Right. Okay. So, therefore, we use
interface conversion. Now, this is the syntax. What you
need to understand from this expression is that if
everything was fine, then Val will have a type, will have
B, which is, which it points to A. And with the
interface of I, inside the interface of I, Val will have
all of that and will be able to invoke foo, which is
this one. Which is exactly what's going to happen. And
this is how stringers work. Now, we said that small talk,
we said that small talk was created by Alan Kay and he
coined object oriented. Well, actually created small talk
with the explicit, explicitly with his ideas of what
object oriented is supposed to be. And it's important
because according to Robert Grissmer, who is one of the
creators of the Go programming language, this is what
small talk was actually the inspiration for this kind of
interface conversion so that at run time we can actually
check if a type has certain methods. And Russ Cox
compared it to duck typing. And by the way, this is a
really, really nice read. So, if you just Google Russ
Cox duck typing, you will find it. It is a really nice
read. He explains how the run time does it and also how
the caching works because obviously you cannot compute
well at compile time. You cannot compute every type
against all the interfaces in the world. It's really,
really nice. And finally, we have a surprise witness.
Martje is going to be the proxy of said surprise witness.
Do you have your?
I am here. So, before I introduce our witness, I am
going to ask the witness, do you remember giving an
interview in 2010 to Danica Lev? I don't recall.
Well, it's on the internet, so it must be true. It's
true. I submit into evidence a web page, exhibit 90210.
So, please read a portion of the text from the web
page in your own voice.
Okay. Go is an object oriented even though it doesn't
have the notion of a class. The type system is more
general. Any type, even basic types such as integers and
strings can have methods.
Thank you very much. So, what makes you such an expert
to be able to say such claims?
I co-created the language.
You created the language. What is your name?
Rob Pike.
Thank you, Rob. New glasses?
Yeah, new dress. Really made it.
Thank you very much. Thank you, Martje.
So, yes, Rob Pike actually said that in 2010. I don't
know if he actually changed his mind since. But the
truth is that I feel that at this point it is clearly a
matter of opinion. So, I would like to know yours since
you are the jury.
Voting is now open. So, the verdict. It's verdict time.
I hope it's now open. Yeah, it is.
The Go team is not permitted to answer.
I believe one of my members asked the Go team last year
if Go is object oriented.
That's a dare.
I am going to give you 35 more seconds because we have to
wrap it up.
Am I correct? You already see 105 judgments. 108.
Oh, no.
I'm not sure if I'm going to get a bunch of bots.
All right. So, I have to close this.
Unfortunately, let's find out what you said.
That's interesting.
Are you showing the Q&A?
Yeah, I don't know what happened.
Let's do this.
That's what I did. Wow.
Okay. So, I am going to cancel these proceedings
because clearly you're out of your minds.
As the judge, I condemn myself to providing you with
stickers. Lots and lots and lots of stickers.
Iris Rona, thank you very much. I have to get off.
Thank you.
If you have a sticker, you also have to give her one if she
convinced you.
Again, housekeeping announcement.
If you submitted lightning talk, check your mail matrix,
Discord, WhatsApp, whatever you sent to me.
I'll try to contact you if you got accepted, if you aren't
sure, our mested on account has...