Hello, everybody. I will talk about GoEvil, which is a personal project which allows you
to do one-liners in Go. So you just type your Go code and call it with GoEvil, and you can
simply write a yellow word from the command line. So this is like magic. I will show you
a bit under the hood how it works. The whole project is about 300 lines of code, not more.
So here is another example. You can call GoEvil and tell it to take the code from the SD-IN.
But here is how it works under the hood. From your Go code, from the command line, GoEvil
generates a full Go program. So the dash E allows you to print that Go program that has
been generated. It is sometimes useful when you want to debug the syntax that you make.
And then the Go imports equal allow to stop using Go imports, because here you see that
in that code there is no import of the FMT package, but it is introduced by the Go imports,
which is called by GoEvil. So I'm announcing today that GoEvil has been
released just a few hours ago. And the new feature of GoEvil 1 is that Go modules are
supported. And with Go module, you get locked version for your dependency code from GoEvil.
So this allows you to submit, to share your well-lined notes with other people, because
the previous code that I showed was depending on the dependency to be installed in Go Pass.
And so that's it. Try it, use it, report bugs. And I'm available for questions. Later.
Thank you. It's weirdly enough, not the first open source project to be released when people
are in the dev room. If this is your slides, you can come up now.
Hello, everyone. My name is Keegan. I'm a staff software engineer at Element. And I've
been debugging why Go servers are slow. So hands up, who's made a CRUD application before?
Create, read, update, delete. That's basically everyone in this room, which is what I thought.
Who's tried to speed up their server before? So, you know, this is a slow request, 3.6
seconds, fewer people, but still a fair number of people. Who's used Pprof before? So, you
know, flame graphs. Okay. It's great. Who's used runtime trace before? Not that many people.
Okay. Who struggled to figure out what was going on when you're using this? Right. Okay.
Great. This talk is for you. So the first thing you need to do really is use spans to
make these traces readable. Very easy. If you've ever used the AEGR spans before, they're
basically the same sort of thing. So you can create a new task and then you get a new context,
you pass the context through to new functions, you can create regions from those, and you
end up getting something that looks a bit like the stuff on the bottom there. You can
also add log lines for some contextual information. That will appear on the UI, which we'll get
to in a moment. And the crash course in using runtime trace is you make a trace in the same
way that you make a CPU profile with Pprof, except you hit a different end point, but
you also tell it how long you want to trace for, and then you use GoTool trace to open
that trace. You don't use the GoTool Pprof, confusingly. And you'll get something like
the bottom over here, which is quite a lot of scary words and links, and you have no
idea which thing to click. The only thing you care about is the user defined tasks.
If you click on that, you'll see something a bit like this. The only thing you care about
is this GoRouting view, and if you click on that, you can profile basically everything.
So for example, here's a bit of requests, which is slow because of garbage collection,
and if you click on any one of those Gs at the bottom, which are highlighted with the
red circle, you'll see stack traces that mention GC. Also the blue bar in the middle there
says GC. So, no, spoiler. Other thing, if you have slow SQL queries, you can find that
as well, because if you click on any of these things, you'll see stack traces, and those
stack traces refer to any point where the Go run time kind of yields away for network
I.O. or syscalls or things like that. So you can clearly see, oh, it's doing something
with SQL, and it's just doing the same thing for SQL for, you know, not particularly long
here, but 20 mils, but still, it takes a long time. You can do the same thing for profiling
functions, the functions are being slow, so you may, this is calling the same function
over and over and over again, which you probably shouldn't be doing in this particular scenario,
but again, it depends on your actual code as to whether or not this is the right thing
for it to do. Sometimes that is normal behavior. In this case, it's definitely not normal behavior.
So the TLDR is you should probably use run time trace next time, and not CPU profiles.
So for me, I've sped up requests that were taking 3.6 seconds to 96 milliseconds for
the same request, and there are bottlenecks from various different things, so from garbage
collection to poor database queries and poor computational complexity on certain algorithms,
and some of these things will only be visible if you use run time trace. So you know, flame
graphs don't help you for debugging slow SQL queries, but run time trace will do. Thank
you very much.
Thank you. If this GitHub repo is yours, come to the stage. And you got 10 seconds to switch
over. And it works, which is a miracle for Linux.
Hi. I actually didn't create a slide, and this will be the fastest lightning talk in
my life. Basically, I just wanted to talk about the JSON package and the issue what
we faced with, and lots of people faced with it. Basically, it's the... Have you ever used
struct with omit-empty? Then basically, this is where the issue come in, and there is an
open issue here which trying to fix this, but it's basically a bad end, and it's a pretty
big issue because it's created in 2015, and there is nearly 200 comments under that, and
basically I just wanted to make an attention on this ticket because if someone fixes this
ticket, that means that basically you can do something like what I show you in this
code.
Sorry, it's really hard with poor hand. Yeah, probably you use this package, the encoding
JSON, yeah? I have a struct here, which is...
I'll become your mic stance.
Thank you.
I used two hands.
So, this is basically... I introduced a new struct which is basically a new string or
something like that, and here I added omit-empty. In this case, I implemented the E0 method
here, which says if it's not valid, then it's basically a zero, so I wanted to remove it
from the JSON, but if I run the actual code, please run it.
Live demos in a lightning talk, you're brave.
Yes, live coding. You see that it's basically here inside the JSON, however, I wanted to
do basically an empty JSON, and there is another implementation with exactly the same code,
but I just created a pumpkin seed JSON, which is exactly the copy of the built-in JSON.
The only difference here, that the issue what I mentioned is basically suggesting an implementation
that the omit-empty section of the built-in JSON should check for the E0 method, whether
it is existing in the struct or not, and if I run this one, it's basically doing what
it should do. Basically, that's it. This is something that I think should be implemented
in Go, and this ticket with this number is basically showing actual implementations for
that. Right now, most of them are not declined but not processed, so I think if anyone has
a good idea how to implement it in Go, then basically it would be nice to put into this
ticket. There are also... This is the actual change request, indigo language, what the
guy made, and I just copied his code. Yeah. One disclaimer, the pumpkin seed JSON package
is you shouldn't use in production. And that's it. Thank you. If this is your slide, come
to the stage. All right. Hello. My name is Nachil. I created Mox. I started using it two
weeks ago, released it earlier this week. It's a meal server. Is anyone here running
their own meal server for the main? One, two persons? Wow. Okay. Three. Room for improvement.
So let's go right ahead. This is a tag line. It's a modern, full-featured, open-source,
secure meal server for low-maintenance, self-hosted email. Let's break it down. It's modern because
it supports all the latest meal standards, and there have been added quite a few over
the years. It is full-featured in the sense that it aims to do everything at once, meaning
all the relevant email standards. You just need this one thing. You don't need a whole
bunch of components to make a working system. It's MIT licensed. It is secure, meaning it
supports all the latest security things about email, like TLS, et cetera, and, of course,
a bit of secure coding. Low maintenance. You actually started using it because many people
are moving all their email to the cloud, some big providers, because it's too hard, apparently,
to run a meal server. So it's for your self-hosted email. Email is one of the oldest decentralized
messaging protocols, but we're making it more centralized by moving everything to the few
big providers. Mox is an attempt to make it so easy that you will all start using it.
So a bunch of features, a list of acronyms. IMAP, so you can access your meal. SMP, so
you can send mail. Nowadays, if you want to send mail, you need to configure SPF, DKIM,
DMARC. Does anyone know what that means? Yeah. See nods. That's good. Automatic TLS. So you
don't have to worry about any significant stuff. So it's like a caddy for email. TLS
reporting, MTA, STS. That's one of the latest additions to secure email. There's a reputation-based
junk filter in there. So if you receive messages from people and you don't like those messages
and you mark them as junk, then next time those people send mail, it's rejected. So
new senders don't have any reputation. You can look at the content. So there's a content-based
abuse in spam filters. So in there, internationalized email. So you can have Smiles in your domain
names. That's what you'll want. And auto-configuration. So you get your Thunderbird and setup is just
instant. No need to worry about all the port numbers, et cetera. It just works. So getting
started. Of course, now you're all convinced you want to use this. Luckily, there's a quick
start. You just set up a Linux machine probably, get your email address for your domain, and
you get a configuration file that has it all configured. You just can start it right after.
Not only does it make the configuration file, also print some commands and all the DNS records
that you need to create. So you don't have to think. You can just copy, paste, and be
happy. Then the code. 40K lines of implementation, 10K lines of tests, quite some test coverage.
There's integration tests, fuzzing tests. It's all pure Go. No C Go. It's just Go install,
cross compile, all the good stuff that you get from Go. The implementation is heavily
cross-referenced with the RFCs. So both ways. You can go from code to the RFC and back from
the RFC to the places in the code where it's used. So this is supposed to help with maintenance.
So it's implementing all these protocols, and it gets a bit overwhelming to understand
all of that. So if you would code it once, you cannot go back to the specification and
back to the implementation. So how you have to fix bugs, et cetera. Let's move on. Wow.
So what's next? I just released it. I'm looking for feedback. Please use it and tell me if
it works for you or why it does not work for you. So I aim to make it very simple. So if
you find something that's not simple, let me know. And of course, if you find bugs, let
me know. And this is where you can find it. All right.
Thank you. If this is your slide deck, you can come to the stage. If this is nobody's
slide deck, I'll just skip it. You did the talk.
Something with Postgres. If this is your 404 page which you sent to me, please also come
to talk to me. So yeah, also the speaker is not found. That's the thing with last minute
talks. Then I had one backup speaker. You can come to the stage. And the gophers are
also falling down. They are tired. I understand. Me too. Me too. Can I connect? Yes. I have
to use the C. Let me just close this down for you. That's how you clicker if you want
to use it. Should I continue? Okay. So thank you. First of all. So I want to tell a goal
of story that we and why we use Go to have to implement this idea of Flute pull requests
at Reviewpad. Before starting with that, I need to talk a little bit about pull requests.
So bear with me. For that, I brought Robin and Kat with me. So Robin wants to contribute
to a project that Kat is a maintainer. And what Rob does is what everyone does or at
least they try to. They open a branch. They create what they have to do. And then at the
end it comes a time where it needs to merge into main. And then when Kat comes in and
says, wait a minute, we need to review those changes. So this kind of methodology is important
for critical contributions from interested parties. And it's well known as open source
projects, especially with the name of pull requests. We also use it inside our own companies.
But it's well known at the open source community. And it's quite popular. As you can see, in
the line, we got a lot of pull request new merge. And the process goes like you do what
everyone wants to do. Then the CI triggers, you get the review, you get some feedback,
and then you have to apply the feedback. And we enter a loop here until someone decides
that it's good to go and we get our approval. Then it goes to merge and everyone is happy.
And the problem here is that Robin goes through this process every, every, every time, regardless
of the type of change it is. And we are uninvolved with the fact that Robin and Kat have been
contributing and working with each other for some time. So this idea that all pull requests
are the same can be actually improved. For instance, Robin is just trying to do some
configuration change. Why do we need a pull request? Maybe we can just go directly to
main without the review. And then there's a scenario where Robin just go and duplicates
an API with some documentation or some warnings. Let's imagine why can it go to main and then
we can do a review afterwards. And then when it comes critical changes, then when we want
to stop the process and say, okay, this is critical, we need to have very good review
here. And maybe instead of just asking one guy, we can ask two people for them to get
their own approval. So this idea of pull request is that all that I just said could be defining,
could be defining, predefining rules. And we can apply those rules into our own process
and minimize the time. That's where we came with this, with the review pad, which is done
on Go and it's full open source. And that's, that's where we can define all these ideas
of what are the rules for our team. So here's some, some, some, some, how, how we could
work with, with, with this terminology behind this is Go of course. Then it can, for instance,
if my, my changes are all on a MacKlown files, I want to merge my pull request right away.
So no, no review. If for instance, my author actually is considered one, a new joiner,
a new joiner could be someone who has at least 10 that didn't, didn't do 10 PRs like Spotify
does. I want to assign a reviewer from, from my, from my tech leads. And then for instance,
for instance, if I want to get some compliance, make sure that my pull request has a link
and issue, I want, I can confirm that and make sure that the, the user gets notified
as soon as possible in order to, to iterate on that. And then we can do some, some, some
more incredible things. I want you to look at, at the line at the top where we have an
annotation saying that is critical, saying that changed every time someone changed that
function, that function is critical. If the function is critical, if my code has touches
a function that has this annotation, then I want to trigger my, my pull request review
that he's, he's for critical changes. Like I want to assign a label or I want to someone
from the tech list to review it. And I want to notify John, which, which is the tech architecture.
Okay. We had a talk this morning about reducing cognitive load from Frederick and I want to
show how we could do that with his terminology. So here's how we could, we could look into
line of sign and make sure that if someone uses a lot of, of, of, of, of tabs, so it
means that we have a lot of loops between each other or if and else, we can actually
send a warning to the user. For instance, our error validation, making sure that they,
they don't use string contains for errors or equals, but they just, they use error is.
And last one, the mysterious Boolean, making sure that no, no more than one Boolean is
used as an, in the fun function signature. Yeah. And that's pretty, pretty much it how
we could use to make our lives easier on, on, on pull requests. Thank you all.
Thank you. The last lightning talk of the day is from me again. What do you want to
talk about today? Well, two subjects. What is Neemin Gohno? I want to talk to you first
of all, a big thank you again to everyone. First of all, to all speakers who came here
today to give a amazing talk, who's standing with a lot of stress to say things. I also
want to thank Eva again for helping me out. I also want to thank the two FOSDEM engineers
in the back who made our audio video work all day. I want to thank the people from FOSDEM
who brought me food today. I also want to thank everyone I have FOSDEM. And I also want
to thank all the volunteers. I think they are left right now who helped us with, oh,
no, still one left. Still one left. Good. Still writing. Who helped us with DORUS,
helped us with video, even what they couldn't solve today. Thank you very much. Thank you
all for coming, by the way. Thank you for staying so late. Thank you. And now my second
subject, which is that Goh is a garbage-placket language. And you know you can trigger the
garbage collection by doing runtime.gc. So when the time is 19 o'clock, I want you all
to do runtime.gc and grab some ways to see around it and put it in any of our bins. But
I think Eva wants to say something. Yes. You thanked everyone that has been here to help
you. But without you, this wasn't possible. So a big thank you to Marja. And thank you
for coming. Thank you.