We still have one minute before we can start.
Ready to go?
Thank you.
Our next talk is by Sha Shin and he's going to talk about a thing I use every day in
Go but it's kind of weird because it's only existing in this language as far as I know.
But it's how Kubernetes is built which is the reconciliation pattern.
Go ahead.
Thank you.
Thank you all.
Thanks for coming.
Welcome to Fostream.
Today I'm going to talk about control theory, reconciliation pattern and how do we use
that in cluster API.
So a little bit about me.
I work at Canonical, particularly the MicroCADES team.
Previously I used to work at VMware.
There I got to know about cluster API by which and I try to contribute to cluster API upstream
too.
And I'm very much interested in distributed system and cloud native technology.
So ping me with your favorite tech.
So the agenda is like this.
So we start with the first basic principles like what is control theory and PID controllers
then we go up the stack.
So L0, L2 just simulates that we're going up the stack.
One more layer of abstraction.
Then we'll see about reconciliation pattern and how they are using Kubernetes.
We then see how we extend those reconciliation patterns.
And finally we'll take a look into those patterns in cluster API and a short demo to come into
play with it.
So a quick one on one of control theory.
I'm talking to you.
You folks are taking a feedback and that's like 90% of control theory right there.
So control theory is like a branch of mathematics, engineering.
So there's a lot of folks were in trying to find a common theme for like dynamic systems
and they were all like wait, we are all talking about the same things.
Let's just unify it.
So that's how control theory was.
It's just a study of how dynamic systems work, particularly the main fundamental crux of
it is to bring a desired state, final state into a desired state.
So this is kind of what control theory is all about.
Let's take a very simple example to know more about it.
And open loop controllers, what is it?
A simple example will be you have some wet clothes, you want to dry them.
You put them in a dryer, you set the timer on.
Now, the clothes are in no way dependent on if they will be dried or not.
The only function that is variable is like the timer.
It times the duration that it needs to shut down the dryer too.
It doesn't matter if the clothes are dry or wet.
So it's not a good approach to take this.
Before I introduce closed loop controllers, there are a few terms that we need to see.
One is the entity that we want to control.
Set point is our desired state.
Process variable will be observed state.
Error is the difference of how overshot or undershot we are from the set point and the
process variable.
Controller is a simple finite state machine which drives essentially your process variable
to the set point.
Very favorite example of mine is a thermostat.
So we are in a room, we have an air conditioner.
We have set the thermostat to maintain the temperature at T1.
Currently the temperature is T0.
So the thermostat says no, no, no, the temperature I want is T1.
So it produces some processes to the AC and it does like an adiabatic process or something
to achieve that state.
So in that case, our thermostat will be the controller.
T0 will be our process variable.
T1 is the set point and the error is the difference between the temperature that we want and the
room is our system in that case.
But it's not always this ideal.
This change takes time.
It's not like instantly you do, instantly the thermostat says okay, make the temperature
T1 and the AC does that.
It takes a gradual amount of time to do that.
And so we need a non-ideal situation.
What would be an ideal controller look like?
So it needs to do these three things essentially.
It needs to see okay, how far am I under shooting or under shooting from the set variable?
It needs to do the compensation for large changes and try to adjust based on it.
And also it needs to make prediction of how to minimize this error based on previous experiences
it has.
A very good example of this will be cruise control in your card system.
When you're going, you turn on the cruise control and it identifies okay, now I'm going
straight and there's a turn coming up.
I need to apply this amount of turn essentially to make it to avoid an accident or something.
So PID controller, essentially what these three accumulate to.
The P is the positional.
It's essentially the amount of, for example, in the case of cruise control, it's essentially
the amount of turn that the card needs to take to make that curve.
It is the linear component.
The P is the proportional or the linear component.
In the graph you see that it is defined by, if the set point is like a straight line and
P we just fluctuate all around.
It's the magnitude of the point from the set point to the process variable.
The I is the integral component.
It is the compensator.
So it adjusts based on what the current state is and how I need to set to the desired state.
But also it needs to compensate fast.
So you're going on a straight road.
You need to quickly make the curve.
So the card cannot go like, okay, I'll make the turn right away when the turn comes up.
It needs to gradually make the change.
And so for that it uses the integral component just signifies that gradual curve that it
needs to take.
And it is defined by the area under the curve in the magnitude versus time graph.
P is actually really interesting.
It's the predictor.
It's how previous experiences that it has.
It applies the previous experience that it has and tries to control the state it is trying
to achieve.
In our tools control example it will be as simple as it sees the curve.
It slowly gradually starts to make that adjustment based on the previous experiences that it
has that I should not just overshoot when the curve comes but start gradually differentiating
it.
Most of the controllers that we have fall under PID.
The D is not much used but it's a really interesting one if you look at it.
This funny looking diagram is just a block diagram of how the PID controller tries to
manage the process and it has a sensor in it.
It just takes the state of it.
In this example R is the set point, the signal that we are sending into the controller.
The Y becomes the Y function.
That becomes the process variable.
E is obviously the error and U becomes the signal that is sent to the process here.
This fancy looking thing is just a state of the process that we are in.
UT is the signal that we are sending into it which was in our previous slide the set
point.
The controller is the signal that was sent to the process.
IT is the measured output as you can see from there.
The error is the difference between RT and YT.
RT was our set variable from this previous example.
This simple differential equation just tries to find the particular state of the controller
that it is in and how is it trying to achieve that state.
The coefficients cannot come in K2.
Totally depend on the system that we are in.
So reconciliation patterns in Kubernetes.
How do Kubernetes incorporate these patterns that we see and use it to make controllers
and reconcileers?
On a very high level this is what a simple reconciliation looks like.
It is a forever loop which has a desired and a current state which are set points and process
variables and actuator that makes it change.
It tries to take the current state into a desired state.
This is available from the controller.
You can check it out.
It has a very good specification on how to make a controller.
Let's take a very simple example to see how it actually works in a one-node cluster.
So we have a one-node cluster.
We have deployment that is deployed which has a replica set which provisions two pods
on a single node cluster.
The node talks to the API server.
The API server talks to HCD and it has a bunch of controllers that it needs to run the state.
So everything is fun.
Now pod decides to bail out.
It's gone just like that.
And so there is now the state is not maintained.
The desired state is lost.
So what the cubelet does, it talks to the API server.
The API server just talks to the HCD.
It says, okay, I needed two pods but there is no pod here.
So the API server talks to the controllers.
It's the scheduler, the deployments and the scheduler and replica set controllers should
use a new pod to that node.
It is mentioned in the HCD server.
And finally a pod to its provision on node zero.
So this is a very simple example of how controllers works in Kubernetes.
Now how do we extend the reconciliation pattern?
How we use it to make CRDs?
So first of all, how many of you folks have used Kubernetes cluster API, CRDs, all these
fancy words?
Quite a lot.
So most of these frameworks, cube builder, operator SDK, these have this basic structure
to make a controller.
You create a spec which is set point in this case.
We have a status which will be the process variable in this case which is the desired
state that we want, which is the observed state that we want at any point of time.
And we have a schema that defines this object foo in this case.
And it has all these spec and status, this domain, and meta objects like the name type
and all that stuff, information in that side.
And we need to fulfill the reconcile interface.
So we create a foo reconcile object.
And we essentially provide it with all this business logic that we need to reach that
desired state from the current state at any given point of time.
The way we do that is we define a CRD.
Our CRD has a spec which is the desired state.
And the controller continuously looks at the CRD to check, OK, this is a desired spec,
but we don't have a desired spec right now.
So it needs to change and it calls the reconciler and it does, it executes the business logic
that we want it to do.
And so that is how we use the reconciliation pattern that we've seen earlier and extend
this for other custom-made objects that we have.
Now how do we use these patterns that we saw and incorporate them into cluster API?
First of all, cluster API is a community project which tries to declaratively use cluster
APIs to create and figure and manage the life cycle of other clusters that you have.
So in a very crude example, the user applies a spec to the cluster.
There's a management cluster which is kind of a cluster of clusters.
It manages all these other clusters that we have.
So a spec defines what those other clusters need to be doing.
And the management cluster basically has these four kinds of things.
It has cluster API CRDs, infrastructure provider CRDs, control plane and bootstrap provider
CRDs.
So all these need to be present in the management cluster.
And based on these, these specs that it has in CRDs, it will try to maintain the state
of all these other clusters that we have.
So what do these different CRDs do?
These different objects, what is their purpose?
The cluster API is basically all these copy objects, like machines, set clusters, all
these stuff that the upstream cluster API provides us.
The bootstrap provider does the job of turning your VM or any default server into a Kubernetes
node.
It applies logic to that and converts it to the particular Kubernetes node that we want
for EC2, for OpenStack, whatever your cloud provider is.
The control plane provider, it provides you with the objects that the control plane of
the, like the simple control plane cluster API in Kubernetes, it provides you with all
those reconciliation loops and controllers that the control plane needs to mark those
states.
And the infrastructure provider is basically how particular infrastructure, like EC2, OpenStack,
whatever infrastructure you have, and how they will be incorporated into bootstrap or
control plane providers.
So this is kind of like how these different CRDs go into, CRDs interact with each other.
So cluster, our cluster is from cluster API, but we need to provide an infrastructure cluster
which comes from infrastructure provider to that and then it will manage.
So all of these are very much dependent on which cloud you're using.
We'll see an example of this in a few minutes.
So a control plane is directly from a control plane provider, machine, machine deployment,
machine set, it's all cluster API stuff, but we need to provide it bootstrap and infrastructure
and similarly bootstrap config and infrastructure machine for it to work, machine health check
comes directly from cluster API.
Its job essentially is to keep checking the state of the machines and if it's working
fine or not.
A bit about microcades because we're going to use microcades, control plane and bootstrap
provider.
So what happens, so microcades is lightweight communities we have been working on.
It is one touch community, highly available, it has all the sync configs you don't need
to do much and it has a very good add-on ecosystem that you can call your own tools.
You don't need to rely on us to do all this stuff, you can bring your own custom tools
that you need for your clusters.
So for the demo, it's a small demo, we need three essential things.
So the cluster API comes from the upstream tab but we need to provide these other three
things.
And then for this, for bootstrap provider, we'll use our microcades bootstrap provider
for control plane syncing and from infrastructure we will use OpenStack providers that we have.
Demo, let's go.
Let's see if it works.
So, like I said, these clusters, these are from upstream cluster API.
We just take these CRDs but then we need to apply what control plane reference we'll be
using, what infrastructure we'll be using and it's all custom based on what you want
to do.
Similarly to that, we have OpenStack cluster that is specific for OpenStack cluster.
We have different projects for that, AWS, Azure, EC2.
Then you see microcades control plane, it's specific to microcades, it defines all these
specs that a particular instance of microcades will have.
And this is a thing to see a bit.
So we define a particular version that this particular control plane will have.
OpenStack machine template that we saw before that is needed for that.
Machine deployments and machine deployments will also have a version that is essential
for our demo.
And then there are all these stuff that comes from template, whatever template you apply,
it comes from that.
So it's quite default by default.
Without trying to actually go into entirety, I have screenshots of it because the entire
demo took an hour to show.
So if I apply this cluster, I'll get this.
So I don't know if you can see, but I'll have six machines in an OpenStack cluster which
will have a version of 1.24 each.
As the time progresses, it provides a provider ID.
And at a certain point of time, they're all in ready state and good to go with all of
them with 1.24 community version.
I think to note that is both of them are controlled by different providers.
So the machine deployments are controlled by the bootstrap provider and the control plane
take care of all these control plane nodes.
So we'll see what happens when we try to update this cluster, what reconciliation is happening
when we try to do that.
So if I go there, I'll change it to six.
And then again to six.
As soon as I apply this manifest back, I have changed the desired state for me to have version
1.26 on both of the control plane and the machine nodes.
So as and when I apply that, both the controllers, the bootstrap and the control plane controllers,
we'll see, okay, 1.24 is now not what we want.
We want 1.26.
So it will start provisioning these machines at 1.26 version.
It goes to the entire place of, so these are rollout updates.
So what happens is a new node is provisioned, a old node is depleted.
And this happens until all the nodes are in the desired state.
There's also in place updates, which is a very cool idea.
So rather than depleting the nodes, it just does that in a upgrade in place without having
to drain nodes each time it comes and go.
And it is a very good use case for when you have a stateful application like a database
or something.
So it does that.
It does the deletion.
It does all that stuff until entire cluster will be 1.26, which was the desired state.
So all of this we see, we go from basic first principle is like what was control theory,
how it gives us controller.
Then we apply, then we see how we applied it to our communities ecosystem.
And then how we extended that, extended those patterns for cluster API.
And finally how we can have a feature from that first principle.
These are some of the talks that I took inspiration from.
I definitely recommend control theory in Friedman given by Valerie.
It has lots and lots to say about this.
Control theory and all these stuff.
Control theory is dope.
It's a very good article that you should definitely check it out.
It also talks about reactive patterns, which is cool stuff.
Lots more using AI and stuff.
So it is cool.
And these are all references that I use from others as well.
So yeah, thank you.
Thank you for coming.
I hope you did something for me.
Thank you.
I'll take questions if you have.
Are there any questions about Kubernetes?
I'm just going to try to get the microphone to you.
Not any questions about Kubernetes about the talk.
Thank you.
Can you pause the microphone alone?
Hey, Guruji, thank you for your talk.
In the theory, you have the desired state and the current state of the system.
And then when you're talking about the thermostat, this is the desired temperature and this is
the current temperature.
How do you accommodate for when can the system predict when this is not going to happen?
It's like, oh, I've been pumping the heater for 48 hours and I see that the temperature
is not raising, not a single degree.
How do you cater for that?
So first of all, it means that the system is a fault.
If it does not reach the desired state.
But it will take it as an experience.
So if I go to here, the predictor component is what predicts it.
It will see okay.
The derivative is the predictor component.
At some point of time previously, this did not work.
This change was not working.
So it will take that into account.
And the next time it does that, it will take it as a experience.
So if it was not working and how did we try to make it work, it will try to take that
experience and incorporate into the next time it tries to do that.
Thank you.
Any other questions?
I guess I'll take it as a note.
Thank you very much again.
We have a small five minute break so you can stand up, stretch a bit.