Okay, thank you.
So our next speaker is Jesus.
We've been talking a few times in the Go Dev Room about everything that has to do deeply
within the language and today he's going to talk to us about what's going on with functions.
Round of applause.
Hello, everybody.
My name is Jesus.
I'm software engineer at Marimos.
I'm going to talk about squeezing and Go functions.
So what is optimization?
I think it's important to know that optimization is not being faster or consuming less memory.
It depends on your needs.
So it's better fresh, squeezed juice.
Probably everybody will say yes, but it depends if you are looking for convenience or for
something that lasts forever.
So in that case, it's not the best option.
Optimization is about what you need and trying to address that.
It's important to optimize at the right level.
You can buy the best car.
You can get an F1 car and it's not going to be fast if this is the road.
So try to optimize always at the upper level because these kind of optimizations that were
the ones that we are going to see in the stock are micro optimizations that probably are
not the first place that you should be starting.
Optimize what you need and when you need it.
It's not about taking a Go function and try to optimize forever and try to make that run
superficially and scratch every single nanosecond because probably the bottleneck is no longer
there.
You have to search for the bottleneck.
You have to optimize where the bottleneck is and then look again if the bottleneck is
still there because if it's no longer there, you are over-optimizing that function without
much gain.
So just take that into consideration.
Optimizing is an iterative cycle and you need to keep moving and keep searching for the
bottleneck.
Do not guess, please.
I know everybody has things and all that stuff but guessing about performance is an awful
thing because there's so many things that come into play that is just impossible.
There's the operating system, the compiler, the optimizations of the compiler, if you
are in the cloud, maybe a noisy neighbor.
All that stuff comes into play with performance.
You are not good at guessing almost for sure in performance.
So just measure everything.
The important thing here is try to measure everything and work with that data.
Actually it's what probably the talk that is after the next one is about.
I will suggest to go there also because it probably is a very interesting talk.
So let's talk about benchmarks.
The way that you measure performance in micro-optimizations or micro-benchmarks is through Go benchmarks.
Go benchmark is a tool that comes with Go and is similar to the testing framework that
comes in Go but very focused on benchmarking.
In this case we can see here an example to have two benchmarks, one for MD5-SUM and one
for SHA-256-SUM.
That's it.
It's just a function that starts with benchmarking and receives a testing.b argument and that's
this four, half this four loop inside.
And that is going to do all the job to give you the numbers.
And I show you now the numbers.
If I run this with GoBench, we go test dash bench dot.
The dot is a regular expression that means everything.
So you can use like the Go test run regular expression for only executing certain benchmarks.
And here you can see that MD5-SUM is around twice time faster per operation than SHA.
So well, just a number.
It's that important.
It depends.
If you need more security, probably MD5 is not the best option.
So it depends on your needs.
Another interesting thing is the allocations.
One thing that you maybe have heard is about counting allocations.
Counting allocations, why is that important?
Is because every time we allocate something, when we talk allocation, we are talking about
allocation in the heap.
If every time we allocate something in the heap, allocating that is going to introduce
an overhead.
And not only that, it's going to add more pressure to the garbage collector.
That's why it's important to count the allocations when you are talking about performance.
If you are not worried about performance at that point, don't count the allocation.
It's not that important.
And you are not going to gain a massive amount of performance from there if you are not in
that point there.
Okay, let's see an example here in MD5 and SHA sums.
We have zero allocations.
So well, this data is not very useful for us now.
So let's use another thing.
Let's open a file.
Let's open a file thousands of times and see how it goes.
Now I see that every single operation of opening a file, just opening the file, is going to
generate three allocations, and it's going to consume 120 bytes per operation.
Interesting.
So now you are measuring things.
You are measuring how much time it takes, how much time is gone in processing something,
is gone in allocating things, how much memory is gone there.
So let's talk about profiling.
Because once you, well, actually, normally you do the profiling first to find your bottleneck,
and then you do the benchmark to tune that bottleneck.
But I'm playing with the fact that I already have the benchmark, and I'm going to do the
profiling on top of the benchmark.
So I'm going to execute the gobench.
I'm going to pass the mem profile.
I'm going to generate the mem profile.
And I'm going to use the piproftool.
The piproftool is going to allow me to analyze that profile.
In this case, I'm just asking for a text output.
And that text output is going to show me the top consumers of memory in this case.
And I can see there that 84% of the memory is gone in OS new file.
Okay.
Let's see what happened.
It's that file, but I need more information.
Well, it's that function, sorry.
I need more information.
Actually, I kind of like this output.
But if you don't like this output, you can, for example, use SVG.
And you are going to get something like this that is very visual.
And actually, it's kind of obvious that where is the bottleneck there.
And in this case, again, it's OS new file.
If I go to the piproftool again, and instead of that, I use the list of a function, I'm
seeing here where is the memory going by line.
And here, I can see that in the line 127 of the file, fileunix.go, I'm consuming the
memory.
Actually, there you see 74 megabytes.
That is because it's counting all the allocation and aggregating all the allocations.
It's not, every operation here is consuming only 120 bytes.
Okay.
The same with CPU profile.
In this case, this is generating most of the CPU consumption is in Cisco, Cisco6.
I can see in SVG, this time it's more scattered.
So the CPU is consuming in way more places.
But still, the Cisco, Cisco6 is the biggest one.
So I'm going to list that, and I see some assembly code.
Only you are not going to optimize more this function.
So probably this is not the place that you should be looking for optimizations.
Anyway, this is an example of getting to the root cause during the profiling.
Okay.
This talk is going to be more by examples.
I'm going to try to show you some examples of optimizations.
It's just to show you the process more than the specific optimization.
I expect you learned something in between, but it's more about the process.
Okay.
One of the things that you can do is reducing the CPU usage.
This is a kind of silly example.
You have a fine function that have a needle and a high stack, and just go through the
high stack and search for that needle and give you the result.
This is looping over the whole string, sorry, the whole slice.
I'm going to do a benchmark.
The first thing, I'm going to do the benchmark.
I'm going to generate a lot of strings.
And I'm going to do a benchmark looking for something around in the middle.
It's not exactly in the middle, but it's around there.
And the benchmark is saying that it's taking nearly 300 nanoseconds.
If I just early return, that is just a kind of silly optimization.
It's not super smart or something like that.
I'm going to save basically almost the half of the performance.
This is because the benchmark is doing something really silly, and it can vary depending on
the data that it inputs.
That is an optimization of just doing less.
That is one of the best ways of optimizing things.
Well, reducing allocations.
One of the classic examples of reducing allocations is when you are dealing with slices.
When you have a slice, for example, this is a common way of constructing a slice.
I create a slice, I loop over this, generate a loop, and start appending things to that
slice.
Okay, fine.
I'm going to do a benchmark for checking that.
And it's taking 39 allocations and around 41 megabytes per operation.
Okay, sounds like a lot.
Okay, let's do it.
Let's do this.
Let's build the slice, but we are going to give an initial size of a million.
And the time, I'm just setting that.
The final result is exactly the same, but now we have one allocation and we have consumed
only one megabyte.
And actually, if you see there, it's around 800 microseconds.
And here you have around, well, let me check, 10, oh, yeah, around 10 milliseconds.
So it's a lot of time, actually, a lot of CPU time, too.
But you can squeeze it more.
If you know that at compile time, if you know exactly the size that you want to have at
compile time, you can build an array.
It's faster than any slice, actually.
So if I build an array, I'm now doing zero allocations, zero heap allocations.
It's going to go in the stack or in binary somehow or whatever, but it's not consuming
my heap allocations.
And this time is 300 microseconds, approximately.
So an interesting thing if you know that information at compile time.
OK.
Another thing is packing.
If you are concerned about memory, you can build this stack and say, OK, I have a Boolean,
I have a float, I have an N32.
And the Go compiler is going to align my stack to make it more efficient and work better
with the CPU and all that stuff.
And in this case, it's just adding seven bytes between the boot and the float and four bytes
after the integer to get everything aligned.
OK.
I built down a slice and initialized that's a slice.
And I'm allocating one time because that's what the slice is doing.
And I'm consuming around 24 megabytes per operation.
If I just reorganize the struct, in this case, I put the float at the beginning, then the
N32 and then the Boolean, the compiler is only going to add three bytes.
So the whole structure is going to be smaller in memory.
And in this case, now, it's 16 megabytes per operation.
So this kind of optimization is not going to save your day if you are just creating
some structs, but if you are creating millions of instances of an struct, it can be a significant
amount of memory.
Functioning lining.
Functioning lining is something that the Go compiler does for us.
It's just taking a function and replacing any call to that function with the code that
is generated by the function.
I want to show you a very damaged sample.
I'm not inlining this function explicitly, and I'm using the inline version that is going
to be inlined by the compiler because it's simple enough.
And then I'm going to execute that.
I'm saving a whole nanosecond there.
So yeah, it's not a great optimization, to be honest.
Probably you don't care about that nanosecond.
But we are going to see why that is important later, not because of nanosecond.
I'm going to talk now about escape analysis.
Escape analysis is another thing that the compiler does for us and basically analyzes
our variables and decides when a variable escapes from the context of the stack.
It's something that is no longer able to get the information from the stack or store the
information from the stack and be accessible where it needs to be accessible so it needs
to escape to the heap.
So it would generate that allocations.
And we have seen that allocations have certain implications.
So let's see an example here.
This is an inlined, an not inlined function that returns a pointer.
That is going to generate an allocation.
This is something that returns by value.
A value is going to copy the value to the stack of the caller so it's not going to generate
allocations.
So we can see that in the benchmark that is saying the first version have one allocation
and it's allocating eight bytes and the second one have zero allocations.
And actually you can see there is one allocation and it's taking ten times more to do that.
Ten times more is in this case is around 12 nanoseconds.
That is not a lot but everything adds up at the end, especially when you are calling millions
of times the things.
Okay.
And one interesting thing is escape analysis plus inlining.
Why?
Well, imagine this situation.
You have a struct, a function that generates or instantiates that struct and the constructor
of that extract.
Okay, the constructor returns me a pointer and do all the stuff that it needs.
Okay, great.
It is generating three allocations and it's consuming 56 bytes per operation.
Okay.
What happens if I just move the logic of that initialization process into a different function?
If we do that, suddenly the new document is simple enough to be inlined.
And because it's inlined, it's no longer escaped.
So it's no longer needed that allocation.
Something that simple allows you to just reduce the number of allocation of certain types
when you have a constructor.
What I would suggest is just keep your constructor as simple as possible and if you have to do
certain complex logic, do it in an initialization function.
Well, if that doesn't hurt the readability.
Okay, let's see here.
We have less allocations.
We have now two allocations and 32 bytes per operation and the time consumed is just taking
50 nanoseconds every time you instantiate that.
So this is a good chunk.
Okay.
Well, this is optimization sometimes is a matter of tradeoffs.
Sometimes you just can't do less.
Like less allocations, less you work, less garbage collector pressure.
All that stuff is things that can be done.
But sometimes it's not about doing less.
It's about consuming different kind of resources.
I care less about memory and I care more about CPU or all the way around.
So concurrency is one of the cases where you need to decide what you want to consume because
coroutines are really cheap but are not free at all.
So let's see an example with IO.
This is two functions that I created.
One is fake IO that is going to generate some kind of IO, IO simulation by time asleep.
And then you have the fake IO parallel that receive the number of coroutines.
It's doing basically the same but distributing all that 100 cycles between different coroutines.
Then I built a benchmark to do that using three different approaches.
One is serial one, no concurrency.
The other one is concurrency using the number of CPUs in my machine.
And the other one is using the number of tasks that I have.
And because this is the result, I'm going to see that if I create one coroutine project,
the number of bytes per operation and the number of allocations is going to spike.
But the time that is going to be consumed is going to be way lower.
So I'm able to execute 100 times this function using this one coroutine per job approach
and only 12 using one CPU per job.
Because this is audio.
So let's see what happens if I do that with CPU.
Using the CPU, this is to simulate some CPU load and using MD5-SUM.
And it's more or less the same approach as we saw in the fake IELP.
The benchmark is exactly the same approach.
We are using the number of jobs and the number of CPUs and using no coroutines.
And here is interesting because if you use the number of CPUs and this is a CPU workload,
that is what is going to do the best efficiency.
You can see here that executing one coroutine per job is going to be even slower than executing
that in serial.
And actually you have the worst of both worlds.
You have plenty of allocations, plenty of memory consumption, plenty of time consumption,
and you are not gaining anything.
In the case of CPU, you are consuming more memory, you are consuming more memory, and
you are getting better CPU performance because you are basically spreading the job all over
your physical CPUs.
And the serial one is just doing everything and it's using only one core of your CPU.
So whenever you want to optimize using concurrency, you have to take into consideration what the
kind of workload that you are using is the CPU workload, is it your workload, do you
care about memory, do you care about CPU, what do you care about?
So well, that's the whole idea.
I just want to explain that all this is about measuring everything, doing all these benchmarks,
doing all these kind of experiments to see if you are getting improvement on the performance
and iterate over that.
Just the main idea, I showed some examples of how you can improve things and some of
them can be applied in general basics like using the...
Try to keep constructors small or using the constructors for slices when you know the
size and things like that.
Some references.
Efficient Go is a really book that is really, really interesting if you are really interested
into efficiency.
Dr. Tolomei Prok wrote that book and actually is going to give a talk after the next one.
So I'm not sure it's going to be super interesting.
High-Performance Workshop from Dave Cheney.
There's a lot of documentation about that workshop that Dave Cheney did and it's really
interesting also.
The GoPerf book is a good lecture also.
And Ultimate Go course from Aragon Labs is also an interesting course because it's giving
you a lot of foundation and the course takes a lot of...
Cares a lot about hardware sympathy and all that stuff.
Well some creative common...
All the images are creative common so I put the reference here because it's creative common.
And thank you.
That's it.
Thank you.