you
Good morning everyone
Finally I can hear you again after two years online where I just had to stare at a boring matrix chat
I am honestly so glad to be here and welcome everyone back in our physical bedroom
Just like every year we're starting with an update with the state of Go
We're gonna talk about what's new in Go, how quickly touch on some topics, how interesting things about Go come in later talks
So what I'm gonna look into today is change to the language, as well as the standard library, tooling of course
I got two interesting design drafts for new releases in Go and of course an update on our Go community
What is new in Go since Go 180? Well of course Go 119 was released in August of last year
Go 1.20 was released a few days ago
It's just the first time that they released a Go version before I do this talk
What are the big new changes? There are four new changes to the language
It's the most we ever had, however one is not really a change so it's more like 2.5 changes
But actually more like 2.25
Okay let's just keep it there, two real changes to the language edition
The first one is that there is a new syntax for converting a slice to an array
Those of you who are new to Go might be confused because what's the difference between a slice and an array? I call them both arrays
Well technically in Go an array has a fixed length and a slice doesn't
That's too easy to say it's not correct
But you can convert between those two and you could have done so since Go 117 using this ugly syntax
Which has to do with pointers and how it works underneath
I would have never come up with this myself
When in Go 1.20 it's more logical now
You can just make an array with a fixed length of 3 and put your slice in it, this now works
The next change has to do with generics which were introduced just last year
It has to do with a comparable constraint which we could give to variables
You could say a variable has to be comparable
Why would you use this? For example when you have to loop over a map it has to have a comparable key
So you could write something like this to make a sum of some numbers
And you can use it wherever you want, you make a map from strings and ints and it will count as
Okay, strings will work because they are comparable, how do I know that?
Simple, you can compare them with equal size
But what about the empty interface? Is that comparable?
Well that depends what the interface is
Before this was not valid, you couldn't do this
When in Go 1.20 you can because now you have two types of comparables
You have strictly comparables like ints, thin strings, bytes, the usual
But also non-strictly comparables like the empty interface
Do be careful because this might panic at runtime
It's allowed but it can panic
The next change is the comparison of struct values
It now checks one property at a time and it will exit at the first mismatch
Wait a minute, this was always this way
Yes, it was always implemented this way but it was never specified in the language specification
But this isn't really a change in the language
The next change has to do with three new unsafe functions
But this is the unsafe package, you should just avoid doing this
Next up, what is new with the Go tooling?
Well, I say this every year and before me, Frances said it every year
Is that there are new warnings in GoVets
Why should you care? Okay, there is a new squiggly line in your editor
You might not care about those squiggly lines in your editor
You should, but you can't
Okay, but it also runs when you run tests with Go test
So you see I might suddenly turn red if you update your Go version
Because there are new warnings, that's why these are important
The first new warning this year is in Go 119
That it will now error when you pass a pointer to an error
And the error.s function
Which is such a common mistake that Kitop co-pilot wrote this code for me
It's not bad, it doesn't work
The next warning has to do with incorrect date formats
I'd say I want to format the date of today in an ISO-like notation
Well, I would write some code like this
But wait a minute, let's think twice about my code here
How do I format dates in Go?
Well, you always have to think about Monday, January 2nd of 2006
This is February 1st
Many of you probably haven't noticed
Again, this is a common mistake
Because people are confused with the one and the two
GoVets will now warn you against the above format
Because it probably is used nowhere
There are also some welcome changes to GoDoc
You can now list, link, and headers inside your doc comments
Which will be rendered into HTML
Here's an example below where I put a header in
I link to the RC I'm implementing
And I'm also listing which guys of coffee my machine supports
There is also in 119 a new Unix build constraint
If you want to build a file that only will be built on a Unix system
You can do that using Go column builds
In the past you could do it by listing all different Unix systems
There are a lot of them
That's a lot of code, right?
Well, in 119 you can just do Go column build Unix
Wait a minute, isn't this a common thing to do?
Because the file system in Unix is almost the same everywhere
So I asked chatgpt, like every developer does these days
I asked, give me a Unix build constraint
And it gave me this thing
Go build, not Windows
Okay, you all know what's going to happen, right?
Okay, you say, it's an AI, I trust the AI
Let's think thrice about this
Don't go out to be smart
And read the actual compiler code
Like every one of you does all day
And immediately I found this thing
Oh, JavaScript is a thing
WebAssembly, one important fact
I didn't even talk about if plan 9 is Unix or not
No, I just want JavaScript
That's not Unix and it's also not Windows
So just don't trust your AI, please
1.20 adds also coverage on building binaries
Why should you care about this?
Well, many integration and end-to-end tests
You run them by making a special binary, running it, and getting your test results
If you also want coverage results, this wasn't possible before
If you now build it with dash cover and add a code cover dir environment variable
Then run the script, okay, you get your output
And you also get which lines all your code touch
So you can put it in your site, your favorite coverage tool
There are also a few small changes on which I want to touch upon
Cgo will now be disabled if a C2 chain is not found
Many container people will now be happy
Go generate and go test
I also have a skip flag which you can put in the regex for which file to skip
Okay, let's take a look at the standard library
Go has many things in the standard library
And of course we have changes in those every year
The first one is in 1.20 and I find super useful
You can now wrap multiple errors
You can do so using errors.fmt.errorf
You can now put multiple percent, sine w in there
You can just wrap multiple errors
Your functions that you will run on them like errors.is or errors.s
Just loop over all those errors
It does that by using the underlying new unwrap interface
Which just gives you the slice of original errors back
There is also the new errors.join function
Which you can just throw all your errors into
Why would you use this?
You always written a code like this
You just loop over a list
And you want to check for some errors
Okay, you could just return a slice of error
But then you have to check for the length, if it's not nil, etc
Okay, you just want a single error out there
You can use errors.join and you get a list of all your errors
Which are joined together
You can just treat it like a normal error in your code
And even use errors.is and errors.as
So you could just say, oh, was there any NP string in this list?
There are also a few changes to the strings and byte package
Which is that it now has a new cut function
It just works as a React trim with trim prefix, cut prefix and cut suffix
Except it will now return a boolean if a cutout happened
There is also a clone function which returns the same instance copied in memory
Also, a few small changes to the time package
We now have a compare function
Which is a combination of before and after
It does both
It will return you an integer from either minus one plus one or zero
Depending on which before, after, or the same at the given time
There are also three new layout constraints which you can use
And those actually came from you
Those came from the Go user survey that they are commonly used
So they added them
There is date time, which gives you an ISO-like notation
There is also date only and time only
Which gives you only the date and only the time
There is also a change in the TLS package like every addition
This time it's a change in how it treats memory
It now shares a copy of your certificate in memory
Why is this useful for you?
Well, let's say you have an application that does many concurrent connections
Like Kubernetes
Well, ultimately now it stores a copy of the certificate for every connection in memory
It now is sharing those amongst multiple connections
So you are saving memory
If you somehow have an invalid certificate
You also get a specific error that says the certificate is not valid
Instead of a general error
And yes, we also have breaking changes in addition in the standard library
The first one happened in 119 in the HTTP package
The HTTP client will now no longer give an error back
If your server sends a 300 response without the location header set
If you rely on your code to check if the location is set or not
By using this error, yes, your code will break now
Also a change in the random package
It is now pre-seeded when you use the global random functions
You no longer have to call the.seed function with some random number you get from somewhere
It now does that for you
Of course it deprecates the.seed function
If you still need your own seed for predictable random numbers
You can do so by using the run.new function
If this somehow breaks your code, it could
You can disable it using this new go debug variable
In tar and zip there are also some changes which are welcome
Which is that it will now error if your archive has an absolute path
An invalid character in a file name
Or a reserved name on the Windows platform
It will now return an error in secure path
This to protect your server from being hacked
If you somehow don't want this you can also turn it off in go debug
There is one new package in the standard library
Which is the elliptic curve default command key change
Yay, very excited
This was possible
Google can do this using the lower elliptic one
But you had to implement more yourself
So it's probably more secure than you would it
Okay, the core runtime
We also have a few changes in there
Well, go 119 has a revised memory model
And I have no idea how they did that
I don't know
So if you want something, actually know what he's talking about
Rescox wrote an amazing blog post about it
But what does this means for us average go developers
And not compiler developers?
Well, first of all go now has a soft memory limit
You can now tell go how much memory you want it to maximum use
To a soft limit
Okay, you can for example set it to be 1 gigabyte
Okay, what will happen?
The more go towards the 1 gigabyte limits
It will try to trigger the garbage collector more to get more memory freeds
Yes, you can see the results if it's too low
Well, what will happen is if it's too much
It will try to limit it to 50% of the CPU execution time
Which your process is using to be garbage collection
There is however a warning if you set it to tens of milli
Tens of megabytes it might just not work
Because your operating system says that's absolutely not enough
This also results in a new atomic package
Which provides low level atomic memory access
So you can now access these variables in multiple go routines
It works only for primitives like integers, boolean and unsafe pointers
It does this by exposing the function store and load
Also add for integers and compare and compare and swap
Okay, but if you use this you need to know exactly what you're doing
You need to know how automics work
As always
And it's still not really recommended
They recommend that you still share memory by communicating
For example with channels and not communicate by sharing memory
So please only use this as if this is your only option
Go 1.20 has a few small changes in the runtime
The garbage collector got better yet again
Say this every year for five years
It got better and it is now a lazeratic
There is also a new mode which you can compile a binary scene
Which is Pgo which you can give it a profile of your program that has been running
Which we will now will try to optimize the binary towards your CPU profile
From a previous run by for example inlining frequently called functions
The go team claims that is up to 4% faster
I had some colleagues who were looking into this
But not in time to get actual benchmarks
At last I want to give you a small update on go ports
So what is happening on the ports in go?
Well go 1.19 added a new processor architecture on the next one
Which is long arc
It's a chinese build architecture
It's not yet in white use however
Go 1.20 will be the last one to support Windows 7 and 8
It will also be the last one to support Mac OS 10.13 and 10.14 but who cares
Go 1.20 also adds experimental support for RISC-V for the free BSD platform
Yay!
Okay that is the current version of go
But of course let's take a look at the future
And always we try to look in the future it won't always work
I have two interesting design drafts which I found
The first one is one for structured logging
Something you all do but doesn't work in a standard library
There is a proposal to make an S-lock package in lock in a standard library
They want this to produce machine readable logging
And it hopes to replace the many many many many many many structured logging libraries
Like logris, zet, zet, log, logger, clock, hclog, clock and however you pronounce all those
It tries to propose something like this
Something like every library probably already did is
You set up for something, you set up where you want to send it to
You put in messages, you put in variables and it logs those out
In something that is machine readable
This is the text output which is just key value pairs
So your computers can all read it and can index it and make it searchable
How does it want to do this?
It wants to give you a logger interface
Again these are all interfaces you can just implement them in your own library
It wants to give you fellow functions like info, error, warning, log attributes
It then makes those into records
This is just a struct containing all this data
And you give this record to a handler
And this handler will turn it into something that is machine readable
If you want JSON you just give it to a JSON handler
If you want some proprietary format you just make your own
So it tries to give you an implementation and interfaces in the standard library
For different log levels like debug, info, warning, error
Passing in data to be printed out and outputting it to text and JSON and maybe more formats
Again this is a design proposal
It's not yet implemented anyway
If you have strong opinions about logging
You can read the full proposal of this link
I will publish the site of false them later today
And you can go there, read everything about it
And leave some comments in their issue tracker
The next big thing they want to tackle is Go version compatibility
Why do they want to do that?
Well we've been doing this talk ever since 2015
A lot has changed, bigger room, different speakers
And especially different slide templates
But there is one thing that always stays the same
It's this slide
Breaking changes
Wait a minute Marcia, isn't there the Go 1.0 compatibility promise?
And yes
Well Go's emphasis on backwards compatibility is why we all use Go
Because we don't have to rewrite our whole application every two years
However there are times which is not possible
For example with external security dependencies or just bugs that we have to fix
Okay let's take a look at this in practice
Let's look at the big Go project
Kubernetes again
And Go break Kubernetes, well more than you think
Just in the last versions
Go 1.15 broke Kubernetes in some way
By deprecating the X.509 command name
1.17, a bug fix in that parse IP, broke it again
In 1.18, again X.509 broke Kubernetes again
Because Go changed something, they deprecated something
And in 1.19, a bug fix in loop path also broke Kubernetes
Oops
Of course it's impossible not to break Kubernetes somehow
But still let's try to avoid this in our language
So we have a solution and it's a solution already we have today
It's that Go debug flag I've been showing on my slides
Okay what is this proposal? It is to commit to adding one of these Go debug flags
To every breaking change in the following releases
And also to guarantee that they'll stay there for a few years or maybe forever
They also want to add metrics to it so you can look at your program
See how many of those are there that you have to fix
And also to put it in code so you can use Go call and debug
To override it inside the code yourself
Again this is not yet fully implemented
There is design proposal, you can read everything on the link there
And leave any comments
But wait a minute Marcia, don't we already have this
I have to specify that Go version in my modules file, right?
Yeah but what does it actually do?
Oh I know, this says the minimum Go version to build it
No, it will try, any version will just try to build it
It's just a suggestion, it might fail
Oh I know, it says the Go version in which it uses
Also, no sorry, it uses the installed version on your laptop, nothing else
Oh then I know, it says the semantic rule set for the version
And yes that is correct, but only the semantic rule set
So that's slice to array conversion, yes that is set by the flag
The octal numbers which got added two years ago, yes that is also checked by the flag
But that's all
Ok they want to change this
And this is the Go toolchain proposal
They want to add a Go toolchain environment variable
Which you could use to set a specific toolchain
Ok I want to use the 1.20 toolchain for this application
This will allow Go get to get a new Go toolchain
Just like you would get your Go modules
Ok, but it also needs to change the Go command a lot
Because it has to get your toolchain from somewhere
And then first download it, check it and run it
That changes our tooling a lot
And also there is a cool toolchain local
If you still need a local for some reason
Again this is just a design proposal
I might be saying that this is implemented next year
If you have comments about it, there is a link here below
There is also a proposal to add this to the Go mod file
So it's right under the Go version
You say ok, my application uses the 1.19 syntax
But it has to use a 1.20 RC for toolchain
So if you build this module, it will go download this version of Go
And build it using that
Ok, that's a technical thing
Let's talk about my favorite subject, the Go community
This is a map of all Go meetups in the world
We are pretty much covered everywhere
Where big populations are, but still not enough
What are the numbers?
Well the professional Go developer network on meetup
Counts 127,000 members
That's 8,000 more than last year
There is sad news, for the first time
There is now only 190 meetups
That's 6 less than last year
Which also results in one country being less represented
Probably due to the pandemic
There are also the women who go in GoBrick chapters
Which is still stable at 41 chapters
And Berlin is still the most active one
But now let's talk about my favorite community
The Franceland community
Our death room is 9 years old today
So we've been doing this since 2014
Ok, small room, anyone can see themselves
Ok, we got upgraded in 2015, 2016
Ok, bigger one, we stayed in the same size for 3 years
Which was crowded enough, and today even it's full house
2019 we got the biggest upgrade ever
We got a giant room
And in 2020 we got the biggest room they could find for us
But I regret doing that because a month later we were all in lockdown
That cost our 2021 edition to be fully online for the first time
We all did our best, we turned our living rooms into giant television studios
Trying to bring you some talks about Go
We learned a lot of lessons
And in 2022 we brought you Govers Around the World
Which we had great fun in producing
But hey, welcome back
This is something you'll never ever see again today
There was just one guy still sitting there
And he'll be here at 9 pm
Ok, let's talk about Go conferences
You're all in the mood, right?
So there is a Go Dev and what falls down, you are here
Please stay, there are better talks than mine
If you quickly catch a plane, right now you can still make
Govercon Israel, February 7th
Govercon 42 will still be held online in April
If you want to go to New York you can do so at April 28
Govercon Japan will be held online
Govercon Europe will be in Berlin in June
Govercon US will be in San Diego in September
And Go up in Florence, Italy will be held in November
Which I have not officially confirmed yet
So we got an amazing schedule today
I already want to talk all speakers for signing up
To be in our dev room today
I hope you're welcome again next year
But before I leave you all I want to give a few housekeeping announcements
First of all, out of tradition we have lightning talks at the end of the day
We reserve the last half hour of the day to do five minute talks
Those timings strict I will pull you off stage
We have a CFP for those, it's open till 17.00 or 5 pm for you Americans
And you can submit a tile till that hour at govers.left.light
I'll write it on the right board later
You just have to fill out three easy questions
And if you fill those out I can welcome you on stage at the last half hour
So you have time to submit a talk, quickly think of something submitted, we need you
If you want to talk to us about social media
You can do so by using hashtag goal line
And hashtag false them 23 or false them 2023 or false them
Nobody agrees on that hashtag
But we stand to say with false them 23
We're also on the Fediverse this year because Boo isn't
You can follow us, mention us, like us at godevroom at false.social
We have a social media responsible person this year
If we will be happy to reply to all your angry toots
So this is a state of goal I first of all want to thank
The false them organization for welcoming us back in the U of B
I want to thank all the volunteers who are helping
Who make this room possible as well as the AV team from false them
Who makes my camera work
And everyone else working at false them
And at last I want to thank all speakers for coming here today
And of course you all for coming to the godev room again
Thank you