It's getting late already in Brussels.
The sun is shutting down.
But we still managed to find a second TinyGo talk somehow.
Then you'll ask everything about visual programming in Go, which I think means that I no longer
have to write codes.
So, front of the bus.
Okay.
Can you hear me?
First of all, thank March and the rest of the organization for this beautiful Go Dev
room today.
Also the first one.
And I'm Daniel Esteban, also known as Connejo.
And I'm going to talk about a visually programming Go.
Probably you use your eyes to program right now.
But I'm talking about a visual programming language, which is like you use graphically
element instead of text or code.
Usually there are two main branches of visual programming language.
One is flow based and the other is block based.
And today we are going to focus on this block based way of programming Go.
Why?
Because I like to make crazy things with Go.
Especially TinyGo and I wanted to know if it's possible to make some code graphically
and then translate it to Go.
Because well, more seriously, because I think Go is programming is an essential skill for
the future.
It's a great way to introduce non-programmers to programming, especially children.
It's great for simple tasks like home information or if IFTTT.
Also no code, low code movement are getting popular.
And Go has a standard nice library, some nice package.
It's easy to read and has multiple targets.
You can run Go on Mac, Windows, but also on a lot of microcontroller.
How are we going to be showing program Go?
Well, there is blocky, blockly.
Also known as make code or scratch or block, all of them use the same engine.
And we are going to see this in a few moments.
Blockly is a JavaScript library.
It's 100% clear and not server side dependencies.
It's compatible with all your browser.
And it's highly extensible and extensible.
Blockly, unfortunately, does not show for Go officially.
So I hear to fix that.
Unfortunately, I have a playground specifically made, but I left the last update at my home.
It's not on the Internet, so I cannot run on my laptop right now.
But I will show you some screen shot and we are going to see some demo.
As you can see on the left side, the blockly editor is run on your web browser.
Once we have it generate the Go code and then we send it to a server so it can compile,
it can format the code.
And then we can get the ones file that it runs on the web and browser again so we can
see the output or we just get the file for our device.
We are using for the server to compile, we are using TinyGo, which is a Go compiler for
microcontroller, but you can use a regular Go.
Let's see a sample.
This is for example we can make and we are going to see a different feature of Blockly.
The first one is, of course, a hell over.
So Blockly we have these different blocks already made and we just drag and drop them.
We can edit them.
We can add we want for example to print hello war and we just go for a text.
We drop here.
Hello foster.
We are going to make this five times.
We just drop and drop the different elements.
The code it will generate is pretty simple and it's just Go code.
So this was our first example.
You will need to trust me like this is working but like I said, the last version of the playground
is not I couldn't bring it here.
Our next example is like especially focused to children or non-programming people.
I present you the Lobo tartle.
Tartles are educational robots used in computer science.
Because it's really easy to see, to program the robot and you can see like you tell them
move forward one meter, turn right or to left, move forward again, go back and then you see
the little robot moving and it's very easy for children to understand the principle of
programming.
So they became popular with the local language and tartographic.
So we make our own version.
It's the gopherino.
It's this little one.
Okay.
This is a different robot, the chassis.
The brain is a BBC micro bit which can go inside and then the eyes are ultrasonic distance
sensor.
We are going to avoid obstacle.
For example, like you can see, we set a variable called distance is number variable and then
while forever we just get the we read the distance from the sensor and if the distance
is less than a value, we just move to the we spin to arrive.
If not, we are going forward and then repeat it indefinitely.
Or go code, the generated go code will take and I mean, blockly will make the right imports,
it will declare some variable needed for it and it generate valid.
This block will generate a valid code.
So we just run.
I will skip the flash bar because again, it's just waiting waste time and I think we are
pretty tired for a long day but we just can't see.
Maybe.
Yes.
And when it's fine and obstacle, it just spin.
Bye bye, Ego Farino.
The next example is what I call the string tank problem.
I have a string tank at home.
Oh, shoot.
string need to live in a very specific temperature and it turns out like water heater are very
cheap but water cooler are not.
You can just blow air with a fan to the fish tank and it will lower the temperature.
So I couldn't bring the fish tank here but I have hopefully still hot coffee and hopefully
still cold water.
The circuit is very simple.
It's an Arduino nano RP 2040.
It has waterproof temperature sensor here and instead of blowing a fan, I will just
put some RGB LEDs.
So you can see them on the back.
The code is quite similar as before.
We just have a variable called temperature.
We just initialize the device.
We read the temperature and if the temperature is higher than 30 degrees, we just blink red.
If it's under 20 degrees Celsius, it will be blue and if the temperature is okay, it
will be green.
So the temperature is okay, we're going to put the sensor in the coffee.
It turned red.
And now in the water, it will get hopefully blue.
So we can make this a small thing because with very, very few blocks, we just save us
a lot of money instead of buying a water cooler.
The code.
The code again is very simple, but it makes a regular code.
Also the next example is more focused on no code, low code and wet assembly.
Wet assembly is getting supported by more and more entities, more and more in service
like Fastly, Cloud Fair, Capsuleware, X team.
You can have serverless function run right now.
X team tried to make what Lua was a couple of years ago.
You can have your program and you can include some extension from the user or the community
built in wet assembly.
So I just create a once worker, it's a visit counter.
In orange you can see the special block to work with Cloud Fair.
We just create a data store with an encounter or the connection.
We get it's time we visit the main route on the web server.
It gets the value of that data store, it's increment by one and then put it back.
Just a simple visit counter.
The code generates here is again like HTTP handle function.
You can probably write if you have done some web server code.
This is a bit early code I will explain later.
But the rest is just convert from string to integer, just add one and then put back again.
And then we search the code.
Wait.
The URL will be here.
This is right now one and two.
If we keep reloading the page it will continue and if we go to the backend on Cloud Fair,
we can see the value is there.
So again with very few blocks we can allow non-programmer people of our team to write
an extension for our main program or whatever tool they are using.
And now what makes blocks the blocks?
You need to define the blocks.
It's a JSON structure which you have what type of block, the message to solve, if it
has some input, the output, the next statement, you can add a tool tip, some comment or documentation.
Then you just define what the block does and what the go code that it should write finally.
There is even a block generator.
You can add different properties to your block.
And now the feature of the block is they are type checking, there is a little bit of type
checking.
You cannot assign a text to a text variable or something like that.
Some blocks you can define what type is returning.
You also have conditional, of course.
You can edit the own block on live to add more else if or else condition.
You have some lists also.
You have inline documentation.
Just wait a little bit and just the tool tip appear of what this block does.
It can be translated, of course, in any language which makes it really, really easy for people
to start.
You can have different colors and different styles for each type of blocks.
You can also have some image on any part of the block which helps a lot, again, the user
to know that, okay, this block is an LED or a temporary sensor or something like that.
The limitation is currently not everything is yet supported.
You need to create a block for it.
It's probably worse for vision impaired people or screen reader user because I guess just
a text file or a code file is easier for them.
So static typing is complicated because there are a lot of different types.
Blockly was made with JavaScript, Python, Dart in mind, like dynamic type kind of language.
You have to make a lot of decisions in behalf of the user.
For example, on our example of our web service, we just assume the response writer will be
called D and the request is REQ.
So you have to have that in mind when you make other blocks.
Agri code is sometimes needed because, for example, since I'm just focusing on TinyGo,
I expect all number variables to be integer 32 because it's what is common in TinyGo.
So when you have to type in to 32 or something like that, it gets ugly.
And there's not much documentation right now about how to debug it or how to develop on
Blockly.
So it's kind of hard right now.
Here are the links for the different projects.
That's it.
Thank you.
I'll give you some time.