Okay. This speaker claims that in 20 minutes Robert is going to build an event-driven application.
Well, to be kind, I gave him 25 minutes. So start your countdown clocks.
Hello. My name is Robert. And yes, I would like to show you today that we can build event-driven
application in Go and it can be as simple as building simple HTTP server.
And I actually decided to put the bar a bit higher. I think that I can do it within 15 minutes.
All right. At the beginning, a couple of words about myself.
So during the day I work in a company named SlashID. So I work there as a principal engineer
and we are creating some identity and onboarding solution that is a bit more frictionless
than a solution available now on the market. And during the night I'm blogging at 3.techblog
where we are writing some blog posts that are covering how to create Go applications
that are kind of business applications but are also maintainable in the long term.
I know maybe some of you had a chance to read at least one article there. There are some people.
Nice. Nice. I will have something special for you later.
You can find me on Twitter, GitHub, Mastodon. There's also my email if you would like to write to me
and ask about something. But what's the most important for today? I'm also a owner of Watermill Library.
And how everything started with Watermill? Because I think that this is a pretty important context.
So a couple of years ago I worked in a company where we are creating products that were not doing something
super unusual. But the idea was that each user was able to add some content and he should be able to...
We were storing it to MySQL. Plus we wanted to have some more advanced search.
Plus have the ability to create a fit for other users with some machine learning models that were doing personalization.
And usually if you are building such kind of system in a synchronous way, there's one problem.
So this part may be sometimes slow because I know Elasticsearch is under high load
or I know Magic Machine Learning model said that this day it will not work.
Not nice, but it happens in water unfortunately. And...
Or even worse for example, some part is not working. And it's not best user experience if it's working slowly
or it's... So for example, you can imagine that you're adding some tweet and you're waiting for 10 seconds
because Elasticsearch need to index something or Machine Learning model is working slowly.
Or even you are not able to add this content. And it doesn't make sense because everything what is done
on this other part of the diagram could be done asynchronously.
Because it's not a problem if for example the search...
Some content that was added cannot be searched for example for one minute after it's out that if something is done.
It's much better than not allowing people to add anything.
So by the book, the default solution for such problems is using some kind of PubSub and doing it asynchronously.
So in this case we decided to SCAFCA because it's scalable, it's nice.
But as usually with some concepts that you're reading in the books or listening on the conferences,
it's not that simple in practice. And it was also the case here.
The first problem was that the big part of the team wasn't actually working in asynchronous architectures earlier.
That kind of makes sense because if you're starting to learn to code, you're not starting with building some even driven application.
You're rather creating some REST API or website.
So it makes sense that it was a big entry point for people that didn't use that.
And it was not the only problem because even in the architecture,
you have a lot of concepts that you need to know like customer groups, partitioning,
etc. ordering, at least once delivery, acknowledge negative, acknowledge poison queue.
And with all of that, you need to be sure that you didn't miss an event.
And it's pretty important in some domains. In some cases, okay, it's fine. You're missing some event and okay.
But for example, I used to work in the financial domain and losing one event may, for example, mean that somebody will be not paid out.
It's not nice. In general, I believe that as engineers we should be responsible because, you know,
sometimes the code that we are building is a pretty big impact to the real life.
And after thinking for a while, I actually started to wonder, is it maybe something that I can do to making,
to building some kind of applications and go simpler?
And here we are. This is how water mill was created. So, so far we have more than 5000 stars in the GitHub.
It was, we have more than 50 contributors across multiple water mill repositories.
We are supporting 12 different PubSub implementations, like Kafka, like Google PubSub, like NITS, JetStream, RabbitMQ.
But we have also some more strange implementations, like MySQL, for example, if you don't have the infrastructure for some real PubSub.
Or for example, I would like to avoid face-comet problem.
If you are doing some more fun projects, you can have just Go-Channel implementation or
a
project that makes your life simpler, like standard library for HTTP.
So, for example, if you are implementing an HTTP server, you don't care about TLS, seven layers of network,
clicking star, connection pooling, all this stuff. You are just implementing the logic in most cases.
Sometimes, of course, you may have some specific scenarios that you care about that.
But in most cases, you should just implement your handlers and don't care about everything around.
And as some of you have shown, I wrote the article that I think that frameworks are probably not working best in Go.
And watermills, for example, that's the case why watermills are actually a library.
And it has pretty good two upsides.
So the first one is that if you already have some system and you would like to migrate to watermill, it's kind of simple.
Because watermill doesn't add anything super custom and it can be integrated with any existing system.
And vice versa.
If, for example, for some reason you decide that you don't like watermill, you can migrate from watermill to some different library.
So this is the good thing.
And I think what's pretty important, so how everything is done, because, okay, in theory, it may sound nice,
it's helping, but how watermill is built.
And in the heart of watermill, I would say that you can see in multiple places something that is named Unix philosophy.
And it's kind of old philosophy because it's from 1978.
And it's saying as to write programs that do one thing and do it well, write programs to work together,
and write programs to handle, in our case, message.
Because that is a universal interface.
So that's my question now.
Do you know who's that?
So it's Ken Thompson.
So he's author of this philosophy.
And also interesting, he is one of the authors of Go programming language.
Actually, it makes sense because if you look on the Go, for example, to IO reader or our writer,
this is pretty nicely visible there.
And I know that for a lot of people didn't know about Unix philosophy.
And sometimes when I have too much time to think, I have some impression that sometimes we forgot about some good old ideas
that we are trying to bring when they will, even if some problems were already solved.
And it may be something like in the Dark Ages that it was some old nice ideas, but it was a bit forgotten.
And okay, maybe I'm thinking too much.
Let's go back to the watermill.
So there are a couple important times in watermill.
So the first one is message.
So if we compare it to HTTP server, it's something similar to HTTP request.
So in message with a UID that is pretty useful for debugging, we have metadata.
So metadata is something like headers request plus payload.
So this is the place where you are storing your event, for example.
The two next important parts of watermill are publisher and subscriber.
So publisher, you can publish those messages.
And with subscriber, you're right, you can subscribe for those messages from the provided topic and receive that by the child.
Usually I'm not using these interfaces because it's used somewhere internally in watermill.
But for example, if we would like to add a new implementation of PubSub, this is something that we're implementing.
And each PubSub implementation is implementing this interface.
That's why I actually pretty like this interface, because it's making some constraint on the implementers that, okay, they need to implement that in that way.
But it's also good because it's making each of them pretty compatible with themselves.
And then last but not least, type is handler function.
A handler function is something like HTTP handler that we are implementing in the HTTP server,
with the small difference that instead of receiving HTTP request, you are receiving message, and optionally you can receive the message.
So the idea is that you can react on some message, do something, and send me some other messages so you can do some kind of training later.
I will show shortly an example.
And everything is magically connected.
Sorry, it may be even small, but you need to trust me that in the middle there is a router here.
And this is connecting everything.
So message is going from some publisher.
It doesn't need to be watermill.
It's going to the queue from by subscriber, the router.
The router is passing it through middleware.
Middleware is working in watermill like in HTTP.
So another thing that is pretty similar.
And it's processed by handlers.
And later, if we want, we can publish some other messages.
Not super complex.
So do you know the first rule of live coding?
Don't do live coding.
So do live coding.
Both can go wrong.
All right.
So I need to change sharing settings.
So one second.
It's probably not this one.
This is why you are not doing live coding.
Yes.
Okay.
So something does work.
That's good.
I don't know if you really want it.
Perfect.
This is something that I wanted to have.
So I prepared a simple application here.
And what does this application does?
So if you are not from Brussels, so this may be something familiar to you.
So it allows you to book a room in hotel.
You can provide room ID, pass guest counts, and let's see if it works.
Okay.
It seems that it's not working sometimes.
Sometimes it's working.
Sometimes it's not working.
Sometimes it's working slowly.
Slowly, slowly, slowly.
Sometimes it's even not working slowly.
So it's even worse.
So let's check the source code of that application.
So, okay.
So here we are running HTTP.
So boring.
Signals handling.
Boring.
But this is probably not boring.
This is usually when the most interesting part of the application leaves.
Let's check our handler.
Okay.
So we are on Marsha Link, stuff, to book room request.
We have some advanced algorithm of calculation of room price.
And we are taking payment.
What can go wrong here?
And, okay.
As we can see, our payment provider is not super stable.
But, okay.
I don't know.
Let's imagine that it's our boss colleague and we cannot change that politics.
It happens.
It's okay.
What we can do.
In the interior we can do like that.
Go, fun.
Okay.
Done.
It works now.
But it's one problem with that.
So if our server ruled I, there is a chance that we will not take payment.
And it doesn't like that as the best idea.
What would be my idea?
Instead of doing it synchronously within this HTTP handler, I would like to emit some event,
listen to that event, and take payment asynchronously.
So let's do that.
Let's do that with full terminal, of course.
So at the beginning we need to get rid of that.
And we need to have our publisher here.
Message publisher.
So this is the interface that you should remember.
All right.
And I also can prepare some code snippets to not lose time on some boring stuff like
room booked.
Boom.
We have our event.
So room booked.
All right.
Get count and price, room price.
Now we need to marshal that because we are sending bytes between our processes through
our path map.
So JSON.
Because JSON is kind of common and it's pretty easy to debug.
So let's marshal that.
Playload error.
Room booked.
Don't do such error handling at home, please.
And now let's publish them.
So H, publisher, publish topic.
Let's use bookings.
And we need our message.
So remember we need to have free ID.
So it doesn't matter actually what format of ID it can be.
I know it can be even empty for some presentations, but good luck with debugging.
And room booked payloads.
All right.
And it returns error.
So we need to handle that in not a nice way, but it's live coding, so it's fine.
All right.
So we have the first part.
So for room booked event, we're publishing that to the topic bookings.
And okay.
So we just need to inject now the publisher.
So check where it's created.
Okay.
We no longer need payments.
I heard that Kafka is nice and scalable for this Kafka.
I have also snippet for that.
It's nothing magical here.
It's just what this and the water mill documentation.
And let's use this publisher.
We don't need subscriber yet, but probably we'll need it later.
All right.
By the way, I'm running some nice Docker compose under the hood that is recompiling
the project each time when I'm putting changes there.
At the end of the presentation, I will give you materials with all the source code and
with the description of how it's done that it's automatically reloading after each change.
All right.
So we have our publisher.
We are publishing our event.
So let's check if it works.
Hopefully it will work.
Okay.
So as you can see that our API is pretty stable and let's check if our event is really published.
So we'll use meal tool.
So meal is part of water mill, as you can guess, and we'll consume from bookings from
Kafka and meal is allowing you to consume messages from multiple pub supplies that are
supported in water mill.
I know that there is two for that in Kafka, but you know, it's not mine.
And yeah, with meal you can use multiple boxes.
Okay.
As you can see, now we have event here.
So it seems to work.
Okay.
So Dan, thank you.
Not really.
We are not taking payments.
So probably if our company will go bankrupt pretty quickly.
So we need to start to take payments.
So for that we already have our subscriber.
That's good.
So let's uncomment that.
Okay.
We need to have water mill router, some router config, water mill logger, good error handling.
And now we need to add a handler.
So we'll just add handler.
So we'll need to provide handler name.
So it will be payments.
It doesn't matter really what is the handler name, but again, pretty useful for debugging.
So we're subscribing to the topic that we published this message.
So this is bookings.
Bookings.
We need to use subscriber and we need to publish to topic.
So we'll publish event when we succeed to take payment.
So payments, publisher and handler function.
So hopefully you remember handler function signature.
So yeah, we are receiving message and we are returning message.
But we'll do it in a bit more fancy way.
Payments handler because we can inject some dependencies earlier.
I need to fix that and that.
All right.
So we have our payments handler.
So we'll receive message and we'll take payment and emit some event.
So we need to have our payment provider and what?
We need to have room booked.
We need to un-martial that.
So message payload to room booked.
And compared to standard library HTTP handler, you can return errors from a water mu handler.
So I don't need to panic.
And all right.
So we should have the payload that we published here.
So that's good.
So we can now use that to take payment for room booked price.
Great.
And as I said, so I would like to also emit some events.
It may be useful.
I mean, even if we took the payment, we can have some BI or we can do something else.
I mean, I don't know, we can send beer to this person after he booked room.
Because why not?
And okay.
So we need the second event.
Payment taken.
Film fields, room booked, as well as price.
And we need to marshal it again to JSON.
Error.
Cool.
Okay.
And the last thing that we need to do is return new message.
Message as new.
Message new.
UID new string.
And payment taken payload.
I hope that I'm not writing too fast or too slow.
All right.
So in the error, there is a chance that it may work.
So what we are doing.
So we are receiving our room booked events.
We are marshalling that.
We are taking payment.
When we succeed, we are emitting another event.
Sounds like a ton.
So the only thing that we need to do is to reuse that handler.
So we have that one.
And handler.
Cool.
Let's check if it compiles.
It even compiles.
So let's check if it's working.
So let's book a couple rooms.
And the idea is that by default, Watermute handler will try if the payment provider
failed.
So in there we should see some information that payment was taken.
And we don't see that.
I know why we don't see that because we didn't start at router.
Run.
Context.
It's a bit naive implementation because it's not really graceful shutdown.
But what in the documentation, as I remember, we have examples with real graceful shutdown.
Okay.
And let's see.
So we have some random error.
And you can see payment taken.
Hooray.
Our company is saved.
All right.
So this is working.
But there's one problem with that.
We figure out that, okay, Kafka is a bit hard to run.
And we're on GCP.
So maybe we can use Google Cloud PubSub.
So I think that I can change Kafka implementation to Google Cloud PubSub in one minute.
I'm realizing the bar today.
Hi.
But I think that I can do that.
Let's see.
Let's start the timer.
One, two, three.
Go.
Whoa.
Okay.
Let's check.
I think I did that.
So let's book.
And okay.
Payment taken.
We can double check.
So let's use Neo.
And let's consume some bookings.
Yes, it works.
All right.
So it will be that from live coding.
One last thing that I would like to show you.
Because you may notice that, okay, it's a lot of boring JSON there, et cetera, et cetera.
You may notice that I don't like boring stuff.
Because probably there are more interesting things to do than marshalling to JSON.
That's because of that we created a component that is named CQRS component.
And the idea is that instead of doing this JSON marshall and all that stuff, you can
provide configuration to which format you would like to marshall everything.
And under the hood it would be done.
So you can use, of course, JSON.
You can use protobuf, Avro, even something custom if you really want one.
The idea is that you're only implementing this interface, so providing the name of the
handler.
You are providing the event that you are expecting to receive.
So in that case it will be room booked.
And you may notice that it was pretty generic.
So we have an interface here.
But we are working on the newer version.
And you are just receiving this event.
Zero, un marshalling, or whatever.
And the same is going when you are publishing an event.
So you are just providing the struct and what you are under the hood is doing all the marshalling
stuff.
Okay.
So I think that will be all for live coding.
It looks that I was lucky this time that everything worked.
And yeah, of course, it's still not production-grade implementation.
I mean, it's even hard to create a production-grade implementation of HTTP server.
So it's more kind of inspiration to look deeper and see that, okay, it's not that
scary.
But you need to take into consideration that there are things like Kafka and Google Cloud
PubSub internals, Lucky
documentation.
So yeah, I heard that we have pretty good documentation.
So at the end of the presentation, it will be in the link.
What else?
We have also a lot of examples in watermills.
So I will encourage you to...
It's black.
Oh.
Live coding.
Okay.
It's not live coding.
So see, not only live coding is risky.
So yeah, we have a lot of examples that probably you cannot see because it's on the block.
You need to believe me that this is on the watermill repository.
At this point, I wanted to say a big thank you to all watermill contributors because
without you, it wouldn't be like it's now.
And slow announcement that we actually released watermill 1.2 after having too many release
candidates.
So yeah, finally it's released and you are all invited to a library party.
And we will say what are the new features and it will be on March 1st.
On the last link, it will be also linked for that.
And I think that will be all.
So this is the...
Again, it's not working.
Oh.
Yeah.
So this is the link that I promised to give you.
The bonus that I have, I have super fancy holographic sticker notes.
I'm sure that you don't have sticker notes, laptop stickers.
So I'm sure that you don't have holographic ones.
So if you don't have, I have a lot of them.
And yeah, I think that would be all.
So thank you very much for your attention.
Thank you.