Welcome, Max.
Can you hear me okay?
Awesome.
Hugo has warned me if I step here that it will no longer pick me up on the camera.
I like to walk, so I'm going to do a little bit just to get out of my system if that's
okay.
I want to talk to you today about malware on the PyPy on the Python package index.
More importantly than that, I'm going to run some malware on my own machine to show you
what happens.
If I do this, you don't have to, and you'll know what the dangers are, so you don't have
to worry.
I'm going to go here so people, if there's a live stream and I'm popular enough for anyone
to look at it, they'll see me.
Hello, everybody.
I think we might be going to a normal mic stream here.
How do I make it off?
I don't know.
I'm just going to hide it.
I'll put it there.
It's all good.
Right.
My name's Max, and I'm a developer advocate at Vonage, this company here, up there on the
side.
Hearing something?
Okay.
What I want to do first of all is just explain, because these guys have paid for me to come
here.
They've paid for my flight.
I've come from the UK, so I'm going to do the bit where I tell you what they do.
What we do is we make communications APIs.
Things like SMS, voice calls, video chats, two-factor authentication, as a service, on
demand.
That's what we do, basically.
What I actually do is I manage the Python tooling for that.
In my role, I've done quite a lot of work to actually understand how I can not get myself
screwed over with malware, which is where this kind of talk comes from.
Unfortunately, my research of malware started to annoy some people.
This is a colleague I actually work with who no longer trusts anything I send him, because
he knows I've been researching malware and he gets annoyed now.
He's like, hey, don't send me that weird stuff.
Unfortunately, he's like, come on, man.
Don't do this to me.
He said this is not going to be a slide in your talk, and I was like, yes, it is.
This is going to be a slide in my talk.
That's what's going to happen.
He didn't like it, because I'm going into the Vonage Python SDK, but I made a version
called not the Vonage Python SDK that I uploaded to PyPy.
I'm going to show you what happens if you install it.
Please do not install it unless you want to have a bad time.
It is live, and you could literally do it right now.
Please don't, again, but you could.
Maybe you should.
It's up to you.
That's where we are with this.
Before we get there, that's the foreshadowing bit where I say, look, this is Chekhov's malware.
We set it up at the start.
We hit it at the end.
That's what we do.
I've just also hit that.
That's a literal punch.
Okay, so first question for you.
Does anybody remember this website, this old font?
Remember that?
Quick question, yes?
Anyone remember that?
Who thought that said Google.com?
It didn't.
It didn't say Google.com.
You're wrong.
You're crazy.
It says gobble.com.
Actually, this was a real website that in the mid-2000s you might accidentally visit
when you were typing in Google.com into your browser.
If you did, I can see some nodding here.
I can see some people might know about this website.
But what would happen is it would do a drive-by download of malware onto your machine, and
it would basically screw over your machine.
This was one of the really prominent examples in the early 2000s of typo squatting, where
just making one typo would absolutely destroy you.
What's really nice is I managed to get some archive footage of a machine being infected
with the gobble.com malware.
I'll show it to you now.
Here's the machine, and here it is after malware has actually infected it.
I'm just going to drink some water because I'm on the line.
What we're going to talk about today, hopefully we're not going to run on because I see panic
looks over there from Hugo.
Thank you very much.
In this talk, we're going to talk about malware, as you might expect at this point, given the
very obvious foreshadowing.
We're also going to talk about how it gets onto your machine from PyPy.
We're going to talk about how it gets made to look legitimate.
We're going to talk about how it works, and we're going to talk about how we can protect
ourselves from malware, as you can see now, because I'm reading my presenter view, not
the actual view, and that's the issue.
Does that sound good to everybody who's here?
Open question.
I'm seeing more of that, more energy.
I love it.
I feel like there's been some really very smart people giving talks, and I'm not that, so
I'm just hyping you up.
That's my job.
I'm like that guy in the back who's like, come on, guys, let's get going.
That's me.
Okay.
Quick disclaimer.
First of all, I'm a freaking idiot, as you've now learned.
More importantly, malware evolves and it changes.
A lot of stuff happens here.
A lot of stuff goes on.
What I'm going to show you today is currently what I'm seeing.
I'm reading a lot of research blogs and stuff from really smart people.
But this is the kind of way that I'm... The malware I'll show you works in the way that
it's currently working, but that will not be the same in a year's time, or a two year's
time.
This stuff is going to evolve, and it's going to change as bad actors get better at dealing
with malware or hiding their malware.
Also, I am not a security professional.
I'm just a guy.
I just woke up here.
They just let me.
I haven't even registered for this thing.
I just showed up and was like, yeah, sure, we got a slot.
Essentially, what I'm saying is the stuff that I found through my own research, but
please don't yourself try and necessarily take what I say as gospel because I'm learning
and sharing what I know.
Is that cool?
Is that cool with you?
Yeah.
I love it.
Okay.
I'd like to show you an image I generated with Dolly because it's cute as heck.
That's the only reason I included it.
It's just really cute.
Look at that little face.
Look at those eyes.
You get a 50% hit rate on eyes, which is why he's only showed one on there.
But let's see.
The cost of malware.
This is important because this is big business.
Malware is big business.
The question, first of all... These stats I'm about to show you, they came from a research
study that was done by the Poneman Research Institute last year.
They studied 550 organizations.
I've got to walk.
I'm going to walk.
I studied 550 organizations that have been infected with malware and how they dealt with
that.
They basically shared their findings.
The question here, first of all, this is a genuine question.
Shout out.
What do you think the average cost of a data breach was for those organizations?
Anybody shout at me.
100,000.
Keep going.
300k.
500k.
Keep going.
A million.
A million sold to the gentleman in the red shirt.
4.35 million was the average cost of a data breach on PyPy.
Sorry, that was not true.
It's just a free breach in those organizations.
I just did a spin and distracted myself.
It's the blood flow.
Another question here.
This is slightly more relevant to our talk today.
What percentage of breaches were caused by compromised credentials?
I don't mean phishing scams.
I mean some malware scraping your credentials and actually then using those credentials
to infect a network.
What percentage?
70.
A little lower.
Three.
Slightly higher.
You know what?
We can play this all day.
I'll show you.
It's 19%.
About one in five breaches were caused by this exact thing.
I love your enthusiasm as well.
Dig it.
I'm back here.
If anybody is watching this can see me.
The question I'd like us to think about is what does this mean?
Thanks.
That was my water break.
I'll tell you what I think it means.
Developers are now a target for this type of malware.
Developers are a real target.
There are two reasons a malware actor might want to target a developer.
Hello new people.
Welcome.
There are two reasons.
The first one is because developers are installing something.
They're going to have stuff on their machine to exploit.
But also because those developers might make software for end users and we might be able
to screw them as well.
That's awesome.
For the malware.
It's not good for us.
I'm just enthusiastic.
I don't love crime.
First of all, let's talk about remote code execution.
This is the gold standard.
If an actor gets into your machine, they execute code on there.
What can they do?
We've talked about credential stealing.
Also ransomware.
Also things like crypto mining and crypto diversion.
I saw a piece of malware that would siphon off payments that would go to your Bitcoin
or Ethereum wallet and put it to a different wallet address and put it to the attacker's
wallet.
There are some quite interesting use cases for this.
Again, I don't love crime.
What's important is you can be a target as a developer but also your end users can be
targeted.
If you make software that's important that someone is using, you might download a dependency
that behaves as expected except for the fact that it includes vulnerabilities.
That means your users could be vulnerable.
Alternatively, it could use outdated versions of dependencies itself or outdated version
of the package.
That means essentially your users will be vulnerable as well because it hasn't, for
example, received updates or if there's a CVE that's come out saying, look, here's a
threat advisory.
We need to patch this.
You won't get that patch.
These kinds of things can be done to actually get your end users as well.
Does that make sense?
Good.
Because this is the most dramatic slide I put in, or one of them, which is this.
Python developers beware.
I'd like to set the scene for you here.
It's Stormy Night.
It's a castle in Romania.
A man in ragged clothes is running away from the castle.
Bats chasing after him.
He hears the howling of wolves in the distance and then lightning flashes.
He says, stay away.
He screams at you with wild eyes.
Stay away.
Stay away from the Python package index.
I didn't rehearse that.
I'm kind of proud, actually.
That went pretty well.
Okay.
Three bomb.
So, right.
PyPy is what we're talking about today.
Because whilst it's awesome, and I don't really think you should stay away, it's an awesome
way to get our dependencies right.
I couldn't live without this thing.
Well, I could literally live, but I couldn't do my work without this thing.
So I want to talk to you about why maybe it's not the safest place in the world in certain
contexts.
So the first thing is that if we talk about typersquatting, if you mistype something,
you misremember something, you put it in wrong, this is the case, for example, with goggle.com,
where a user would type it in wrong and would get screwed over.
They would get that malware on their machine.
But the same exists with PyPy.
Because if you type in pip install and then a package, if you type that wrong, it doesn't
check.
It doesn't say, oh, did you mean requests?
It says, okay, yeah, I'll install asdfj.
You know, that's fine, too.
As long as that package exists, you will get it.
And that can be concerning.
So quick question here.
What percentage of PyPy packages are estimated to actually potentially be using a typersquatting
technique?
Five.
That's a good number.
Any other guesses?
40, 20.
42.
Very specific.
I love it.
41.9.
About 3%.
So a lot closer this time.
You redeemed yourself or respect it.
So yeah, basically a little smaller.
But still, there's millions of packages on there.
So this is a big ass number.
This is a big old number.
So the next question, this is maybe relevant to us now, is what percentage of PyPy downloads
are estimated to be of typersquatting packages?
So in percent, how many times does someone download something where they maybe didn't
mean to?
10%.
Two.
One percent.
Two percent.
Four percent.
Sold.
So 0.5 is about the right answer.
So again, we're getting to people who I just saw, yes.
And I respect that as well.
I love the enthusiasm that we're generating here because that's really the content.
You guys are the product, right?
So yeah.
But 0.5 is not much, but it's 1 in 200.
And if you think about how many millions of things are downloaded from PyPy every day,
that's a big deal.
That's a really big number.
Easy photo, good, because I need to move on.
Let's talk about types of squats.
In fact, this is a type of squat of typersquat, which is a pun, and I'm so proud of it.
I didn't sleep all night.
Types of squats that you can get.
So misspelling, pretty obvious.
You mean to type something, you hit the wrong button, something goes wrong.
For example, these are all real typersquats from the request module.
We all know the request module, I hope, I assume.
You send HCP requests?
Awesome.
Well, you might send requests or requests or equests, any of those.
And those are real actual pieces of malware that were found on PyPy.
So if you had mistyped, they would be on your machine.
Which isn't ideal for you.
There's another type, which is confusion typersquats, where the user misremembers the name of a
package, and there may be some separated confusion or ordering confusion.
For example, easy install, maybe there's an underscore, maybe there's a hyphen, maybe there's
nothing, maybe it's install easy, who knows, right?
So in this case, you might end up with some malware, but there's also version and confusion,
where basically you think, oh, this is a certain version, or maybe like, you know, beautiful
Super 4, BS 4.
That's the kind of thing where, what, it's BS 4?
I never scraped before.
Sure.
Okay.
So there are some examples where you wouldn't actually want, you know, you'd want to basically
consider these different versions.
So for example, this is a real piece of malware that I saw on PyPy, request 3.
You might think, oh, a beta version of version 3 of request, yeah, okay, I'll get that, I'll
get that, that's good, that's good stuff.
Do not do that.
Get the request module.
Okay.
Right.
Let's play a little game, because apparently all we do now is audience participation.
So, which of these is the malware?
Choose now.
Top one or bottom one?
Hands up for top one.
Hands up for the bottom one.
Heck yeah.
Damn right.
Okay.
Another one here.
Libkill or Pykill, which is the malware?
This is a Python package.
Which is the Python package?
Top one?
Bottom one.
Top one.
Aye.
Really split on that one.
So I think the confusion there is because the actual package that Pykill calls, that's
the system package, but actually the actual Python package is called Pykill, and that's
why if you would guess wrong, it's really sensible that you might guess Libkill, but
it's actually malware.
So once you've got some malware, how does it look legit?
So one way is that you can have dependencies where basically you have a package itself
that is innocent, doesn't do anything bad, but it includes a package as a dependency
that is malicious.
And in this situation, you might have the original package behaving as normal, but actually
that's just to avoid suspicion, but the actual second package is the malware.
And we'll see an example of that very soon, and we'll see a live example depending on
how good the Wi-Fi is in here.
So there's also malicious commits over time.
And this is another real attack vector.
This is not so based on type of squatting.
This is based on other elements of trust and abuse.
So first of all, the project might be safe.
Nothing wrong with it.
But then builds up a user base.
It's a useful package.
People start to use it.
And eventually maybe malware gets added.
And this was the case with a package called FastAPI Toolkit.
So if we've heard of FastAPI, there was a toolkit package which was adding some useful
stuff.
And the toolkit package eventually in version 0.27 actually added some malware, which has
now been rolled back.
But as I'll show you later, that doesn't mean you don't get that malware.
I had an ooh, yeah.
Ooh, ooh, it got me to, it shot me to my core.
It shot me to the very depths of my soul.
I've gone very Manchester all of a sudden.
Right.
The other way this thing can work, come in, come in, join us, join us.
Move that way.
It's the shift left principle.
Okay, so the other way this can work is that a repo might get a new maintainer.
So somebody who's starting to contribute to the repo in a useful way.
And they say, hey, can I just get some admin access?
I want to maintain this repo.
I want to take something over.
Okay, awesome.
Sure.
Oh, oh no, this person added malware.
What a surprise.
What a coincidence.
And this is a genuine and real thing that does happen.
Now I want to drink some more water.
So I'm going to show you a pretty slide with a cute snake on it.
It's now jacking.
Look at the cute snake.
I'm going to get hypnotized by it while I drink this water.
Sick.
Thank you.
Right.
Have we heard of star jacking?
Is that something that we're familiar with?
Is it a term?
Shaken heads.
Okay, perfect.
Ten minutes left.
Really?
Oh no.
Okay, we're going to be hauling.
Okay, right.
Star jacking.
What is it?
I'll tell you what it is.
On PyPy, they don't verify the URL that you give as the project URL.
And that means you can exploit that.
So quick one here.
I'll tell you the answer.
We don't have time.
First tool belt or tool belt request.
One of these is an actual tooling package for request.
It's the top one.
The bottom one is malware.
How do I know?
Because I made it.
And it's on PyPy.
That's how I know.
But we can see here if we look at the page on PyPy, look at these stars.
Look at them.
I've got 900 stars.
I only did it yesterday.
I'm that popular.
And you can see this is a real thing.
So if you go and check out a package, you can get screwed this way.
So think about it when you look at this, right?
It's a real problem.
Okay.
Right.
We are pushing for time.
So I'll say a typical chain of events that happens.
A user installs a dodgy package that's been type-exported or in other ways confused.
It depends on a malicious one.
That package runs.
It decodes some basic code which downloads some true malware from a remote server.
The upshot of it is very sad snake.
Hello.
So let's show an example.
That's what we're here for.
We want to see my machine get screwed.
That's why we're here.
That's why we're all on this talk.
That's why we're in the full room.
Yeah.
Come on, boys.
So right.
I said I work for this company, right?
And I maintain this particular SDK.
You can look at it if you want.
I just put the QR code in again because they pay for my flight.
That's why I did that.
You can scan it if you want.
But the reason my colleague didn't trust me earlier is because I made a version of this
called not the Vonage Python SDK.
I didn't want to make it too obviously type-awable because I actually don't want someone downloading
this.
But this is a real package.
I uploaded.
You can see it looks similar.
It has the same number of stars as the actual package.
So again, it looks pretty legit.
But I want to show you what happens if you download that.
So that's the plan.
So just to summarize, we got these two.
We got these two packages here that I've uploaded to PyPy.
As of yesterday, I had to make a fake account because they deleted my first set.
That's not a joke.
I had a lot.
I didn't get to go to this conference because I was redoing my malware.
So anyway, the point is here, we've got these two packages.
And what I want to do is show you what happens when you run them.
Can you?
Nope.
I've got a...
Oh, dear.
We're going to have a problem.
I'm going to drag you over there.
It does.
Great.
There's a thing already.
So we can see here, this is going to be very difficult to manage.
Essentially, this is my Python SDK.
And we can see here in the setup Py, it's normal.
Except for the fact here, it includes tool belt requests, which is a new dependency that
wasn't there before.
And we can see in the client class here, I've got request util.
This is a random function I've imported.
It doesn't do anything.
But what's important there is I've imported tool belt requests.
Can we all see that?
Is that big enough at the back?
Great stuff.
Okay.
Awesome.
So I can actually go and where's my mouse?
I'll show you.
I've got this one on here.
This is going to be quite a lot of dragging and clicking.
This is my malware package.
This is tool belt requests.
And we can see here that this setup Py looks normal.
Request util looks fine.
Nothing happens in here.
If we go to init Py, again, looks normal.
Where's the malware?
Well, let's scroll over a little bit, shall we?
And I say this.
This is a legitimate technique that is used by bad actors.
This is real.
So if we scroll over, what do we see?
Oh, look, a base 64 encoded payload.
What could this be?
Who knows?
Right.
So this is what we end up with, right?
And what happens is this command will decode that and then it will run it.
And so because of the first package what we had was this import statement here, it will
run as soon as we import the first package.
And the reason for that is that actually in the init Py file we've got this import of
everything for clients.
So basically when we import a package, we believe it's called Vonage, which inherently
the module, the package itself is called Vonage still.
So a user may not know that they've downloaded the wrong package at this point.
You will download and install and then use and activate that malware.
So what's left to do?
Check off malware.
Let's get some malware going.
Right.
And we've got this up here.
So I've used a blank one because I'm hoping we can download it live.
So let's do that.
Can I try this while not looking?
Not the Vonage Python SDK.
Okay.
Wi-Fi is working nice.
So this is a blank VM that I've got here.
We can now see if I do a pip list.
We can see that I've got tool belt requests in here, which is my malware.
And we can see here that I've got not the Vonage Python SDK.
Okay.
So now if I open up a Python shell, cool.
And if I actually import that, what's going to happen?
Import Vonage.
What are we going to do?
Oh, wait a minute.
It's done it on my off.
This demo would have been so cool if I just mirrored my screens.
Where's my mouse?
I'll show you what it did.
Can I do that?
No, I can't.
I need to do it this way.
I'll show you right now.
All righty.
So that's what I want to show you for now with that.
But because we don't have much time, I'm going to actually tell you now I've spent most of
my time telling you what screws you up.
I'm now going to tell you how you can protect yourself a little bit.
So thank you, Mr. Ashley, for your once again, your dedicated service.
It actually won't play because the Wi-Fi is not fast enough.
But you can imagine it in your head if you want.
So right.
Now we're back here.
Let's talk about protecting ourselves.
Right.
Again, adorable snake.
That's my water break.
Snake for the break.
Okay.
So as maintainers, if you maintain a package and you don't want your users to get the wrong
thing like me, what can you do?
Well, your dependencies might become compromised, right?
So you need to think about how you can look for those compromises and deal with those.
So this is the case where maybe a patchy, like fast API toolkit becomes malicious over
time or there's some vulnerability that's discovered.
In that case, automated scanning tools can help you, right?
Five minutes left.
Okay.
No worries.
We got this.
We're a team.
I appreciate you gave me a little more.
I like that.
Okay.
So right.
So first of all, there are things to use.
We use this.
We give these guys an awful lot of money.
So if you want to do the same, please feel free.
I don't know.
I'm sponsored by them.
There's also dependables.
There's other services that will scan your repos and check and see if there's any malware
or any CVs that might provide vulnerabilities.
Also as maintainers, another cute snake, you might want to consider defensively type of
squatting which is where you preemptively type of squat your own stuff like I did there
with not the Vonage Python SDK.
You might do that yourself with your own package.
You might give something similar typos or confusions.
You might want to make those yourself.
Oh, now it plays.
How do I actually turn it off?
I actually don't know what that's up.
Wow.
Okay.
I did not think it would go like this.
This is my second proper talk.
Right.
When you preemptively type of squatting, that means you can save the packages that you're
dealing with.
Right.
So there was a person, William Bernstein, who decided to take some of this into his
own hands and he type of squatted 1,000 packages.
In two years, they got over 500,000 downloads which shows how useful that technique was
to stop those $500,000 potentially going to malware.
Right.
As package users, we've got other things we can do.
The obvious one here, if you type something in, you're at risk.
You might want to look at how you do that.
What is obviously maybe a good practice is store from a file so you can check what you've
written.
Vet your dependencies if you can.
And, again, you might want to use those automated scanning tools.
Now if you're using a mirror, you might want to check the latest safe version.
This is really important because if you're using a mirror, what can actually happen?
I'll give you the fast API example again.
Basically, a mirror site.
For example, if you're in an enterprise and you download all your stuff that's cached
at a mirror site, you can end up in a situation where, for example, 0.27 is malware, 0.26
is not.
When that was discovered, the whole on PyPy went back to 0.26, but in the mirrors, they
often configured so they only take the latest version.
In that case, you'd not get that safe version.
It would keep the malware on your mirror.
Just consider that as well if that is how you install stuff.
Because I've got two minutes left, I'm going to sum up really quickly.
First of all, type of squatting on PyPy is a real attack vector.
So benign packages that become malicious, as we just said.
So what you should do is vet your dependencies really carefully.
And if you can, use automated vulnerability scanning tools.
If you really have to, you might want to consider defensive type of squatting because that's
a way to protect your users.
But also be careful when you're using mirrors.
So the final thing I just want to say, first of all, is never get security up.
It will never let you down, run around, or even.
And I quote, desert you.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
So, just quickly, if you want to see the slides or any resources, they are there.
And this is just the summary because the other one wasn't super useful.
If you want to tweet me and ask me questions, feel free.
I'm an idiot.
Tweet me, it's fine.
Okay.
That's me.
If there is anything else, any questions, shout them out to me and I'll attempt to answer
them.
Thank you, Max.
Now I really want to install your SDK.
I haven't seen that video enough.