And it is time for our next talk. I would like you to welcome a venduler.
Hello, I'm Wendy. I'm a software engineer. I work at third head for six years now and
and I'm part of the system in starting.
And today, welcome on my talk about the communication
with D-Bus from Python applications.
So first of all, I would like to clarify
that I'm in no way an expert on D-Bus.
I'm just a very lazy programmer who wrote library
to make her job easier.
So what is D-Bus?
It's a shortcut for the disk to bus,
and basically it's a system for the inter-process
communication.
It consists of two parts, the protocol and the bus daemon,
and on a typical Linux distribution,
you can usually find the two bus daemon,
the session bus and the system bus.
So for example, this is a screenshot from my laptop.
This is the visual representation of the system buses
and services that you can find.
And for the demonstration purposes,
I've created the example chat service,
and you can see on the right side
that this service provides for objects,
and this object implements some interfaces.
So how do we talk to this thing from Python?
We will use the D-Bus library for that.
It's a library that I wrote some years ago,
and basically it's an abstraction level
above Python bindings for the GV library.
Okay, so let's jump in.
Let's start with the client part.
So we know that there is a D-Bus service
that we want to talk to,
and how do we do it from the Python application?
First of all, we need to establish the connection
to the message bus.
In this case, we know it's the session bus,
so we will use the session message bus.
And the other thing that we have to create
is the proxy of the remote object we want to talk to.
For that, we need to know two things.
The first one is the name of the D-Bus service.
The second one is the object path of the remote object.
After that, we can use the proxy
like any other Python object.
So we can get and set properties.
We can call methods.
And another thing we can do is to watch D-Bus signals.
D-Bus signals is something you can connect to.
You will create a callback,
connect this callback to the signal,
and every time this service emits the signal,
your callback will be called and run and processed.
So this is how we do it.
This service, or this run proxy,
has one signal called message received signal,
and you can connect the callback
to the message that you receive.
And that's it.
This requires one more step,
and that's to run an event loop.
Basically, it's a little complicated to explain.
It's just a black box that runs forever
and handles any asynchronous events that can come up,
like emitting of a signal.
So the things run forever unless you stop the loop
or kill the application.
Yeah, so let's actually do some demonstration
because I think the demonstrations are doomed to fail,
but let's try.
So here I need to start my server.
Let's not dive into that yet.
It's just I needed to have a training.
And we can actually check the defeat,
and on the session bus, you can look for my example chat.
And you can see what you saw on the slides.
Sorry, it's so little.
And there's my Room 3, and there are some interfaces,
and this is the interface I'm interested in.
So let's do some stuff with it.
The first one, we will ask for the name of the room,
and that's it.
So here I can just write the first one,
and it just prints three because we asked
the Room 3 for the name.
The second thing that we can do is to send a message
to the room.
So this is the number two.
Yeah, this doesn't print anything,
but as you can see here, the server received a message
for this room, and it printed.
So if I call it server times, it prints this stuff.
And if I change it to something else, I can actually talk
to another object and send another message
and stuff like that, and it just will send
a different message to a different room.
Yeah, it's a very primitive chat.
Don't try to find something clever about it.
And the last thing I want to show you
is the signal processing.
So this is how it looks like.
The callback will just print the receipt message
with some additional stuff, and this is where I connect
the callback to the signal, and then I will just
start the event loop.
So for that, I actually have to...
Yeah.
So this thing is listening, it's waiting in the event loop,
and it's waiting for any events.
So if I, again, send some messages to the...
Oh, and something, yeah, because I changed it.
That's why you shouldn't change your code.
It should work now, yes.
Okay, so because it's listening on the Room 3,
so if I send a message to the Room 3,
it's well printed here, and this service behind it,
it's still running, it receives the messages.
So, okay.
That was the client side of the things.
Let's be the service.
How do we do this?
First of all, we need to register the DBUS name
of the service.
That's basically, you announce the name of your process,
so the other applications can find you,
and reach you, and talk to you.
So the other thing that you have to do
is to publish some objects,
so other applications can actually use some API
that you provide, and do some stuff with your service.
And the last thing, again, is to start the event loop,
and the event loop handles the incoming DBUS calls,
calls the relevant handlers and callbacks,
and sends the return values to the callers.
So, the last part that is missing
is how do we create this DBUS object?
Every DBUS object needs to provide something
called the XML specification.
This is,
it's a declaration of our interfaces, methods,
properties, and signals that this DBUS object implements,
and that you can call.
And when I saw this for the first time,
I thought, oh my god, my colleagues will do
some metipos in the things.
And we will have so many bugs.
So the first mission I had was actually
to get rid of this, and make it generated
automatically from the code,
because I knew that we are going to do a lot of changes
all of the time, because it was a huge project.
And in no way, we would keep this same as the code.
So let's look how it can be done with DBUS.
Or you can, all you have to do
is to just use the DBUS interface decorator,
and provide the name of your interface.
And this decorator just looks at the class members
of the decorated class.
And for every member, it will generate this piece
of the specification, and it will create
this whole specification.
Sometimes it collects more interfaces,
it's more complicated.
But at the end, you don't have to do or write any XML,
but you can have access to it,
and use it to publish your object.
So we will start with this decorator,
and then you can just define a DBUS method.
This is definition, and at the same time,
the implementation of the method.
So you can see it prints the message.
One thing that you have to do is to provide type hints
for the arguments and the return values,
because DBUS needs to know about the data types
of these of the arguments.
And another thing, yeah, everything is comma-cased.
I'm sorry about that.
It's a standard for DBUS, and it didn't make a lot of sense
to try some mapping from the traditional Python
to this comma-cased thing.
So it's easier to just try the comma-cased.
So this is the method, and this is how to define
a DBUS property, it's just a Python property
with a type hint again.
And last but not least, DBUS signal,
you need to use a special decorator for that.
And if this signal emits some additional arguments,
you need to specify them as arguments of the method,
kind of, yeah.
This method is never called, it's just used
for the definition of the signal.
So that's it.
Let's have a look at the implementation
of how it looks like when you put it all together.
So this is the classroom.
There is the decorator, and as you can see,
there is just all the definitions and implementation
that this class needs, and the XML is just generated
by the decorator.
You don't need to care about anything.
The chat also has a DBUS interface,
but it doesn't contain anything.
Here we can see later how the XML looks like,
and you create a connection to the message bus,
you register the name of the service,
you publish some objects, and you start the event loop,
and that's all.
In this case, it's good to disconnect from the bus.
There's an open-floor request to use the session bus
as a context manager because it's nicer,
but it's not matched yet.
Because it will unregister everything that you did here,
so that's a good thing to do.
So, and here we can see that when the server was started,
it printed the interfaces that were generated,
so the first one is empty, there's nothing there,
but with the room, it contains everything
that was inside of that class.
So yeah, this was completely generated.
You don't have to care about it.
You don't have to figure out what type S is.
In this case, it's simple, but sometimes
it gets a little more not so pretty.
So yeah, you don't have to care about it,
which is, I think, great.
Features.
So, this bus has a lot of features
because the project I was working on was big,
so we wanted to do as many simplifications as we could.
So one thing that we did, okay,
I want to mention one thing.
I decided I will focus on the end result of these features
because it's a little difficult to explain the definitions
and like all the steps you need to do before that,
so I will just show you what you will end up with
in your code.
So the first thing I want to mention is the management
of the bus names and pass, because you could see
that there are a lot of strings you need to handle.
And it's very easy to make typos in this again.
So, I can, okay, yeah.
So it's very easy to make typos in that as well.
So basically, this bus provides a system
that allows you to define namespaces and objects
that are published in these namespaces.
And at the end, you will have these very simple objects
called chat and trims3, and you can just use these objects
to create proxies or ask for the interface name
or ask for the service name or get the object pass,
and you don't have to care about the strings behind it
because they are created from what you defined earlier.
Yeah, I can get to that later if you have time.
So another thing that the bus provides
is management of a group of publishable objects.
So let's say that the chat is not static,
it doesn't have only three rooms,
but you can ask the chat to create a new room,
and you want to get the bus pass of that room
so you can connect to it.
So yeah, you can implement it manually on your own
and make sure that every room has a unique pass,
and if someone wants to do something with that room,
you can just figure out again what was the room,
or you can just use the room container.
It's very easy, you just provide the namespace
that the container can use, and you will specify
the message bus that can be used to publish these objects.
And the whole purpose of this container
is just to give it a Python object and get a debus pass,
and it works the same way backwards.
So if you receive an object pass, you can get room.
So with this mapping, you can deal with this mapping
very early, and in your code, you only have the objects.
You don't have to care about the debus implementation
behind it, so yeah, it's a little difficult to explain,
but it can simplify your life load.
Yeah, another thing I want to talk about
is how to handle debus errors.
So this bus raises a default exception by default,
but sometimes you want to handle a specific debus error,
or maybe you want to raise a specific debus error
from your service.
It's very easy thing to do.
There's a special decorator for that
that you can use for your exceptions,
and in the decorator, you specify the debus name
of this error, and that's all you have to do
to be able to use this exception in your code.
So once you decorate it, you can raise it in a service,
and you can accept it in the client,
and you don't have to care about the magic between that.
Yeah, that's also a cool thing to do.
Debus structures, so this is very, yeah,
this is a funny thing.
Debus doesn't have native support for structures,
so what everyone does is they send dictionaries
that map attribute names, attribute values,
and since these values can be of different types,
you have to wrap them inside variants.
Variant is a special data type
that basically couples the data and the type together,
so when you send it from your service,
the client is able to interpret the data,
even though it didn't know the type of this data before.
So this is pretty horrible thing to work with,
especially when you need to receive the structure,
change something, and send it somewhere else,
because creating these variants is not easy,
variants are not changeable,
so you have to always create new ones,
and yeah, it's not pretty.
So with this bus, you can actually describe the structure
using data classes, and these classes
just have some properties,
and there's a lot of automation
that allows you to basically give it the dictionary,
it will transform the dictionary into a Python object,
then you can just play with the Python object,
and when you need the structure again,
you will just go to structure
to get the structure that you can send on the bus.
Yeah, so that's another thing you can do.
Lastly, this is a new feature
that I was working on with some people last year.
Yeah, I would like to think this way.
I would like to use this to thank everyone
who was involved in this,
because it was bigger issue than I expected,
and basically, you can send Unix file descriptors
through the bus.
It works only on Unix systems, obviously,
and it's optional feature is disabled by default
because there's some overhead,
and I didn't want it to slow down everyone's services.
So all you have to do is when you create a proxy,
you will specify a little different client library
or the server library that will be used
to process the incoming calls or the requests,
and it basically means that if,
yeah, it's a little complicated
because the bus has a special support
for your next file descriptors,
but it's very messy when you have to deal with it specifically,
and with this extension,
you don't have to care about it, basically.
If you want to send a file descriptor,
you will just send a file descriptor
and receive a file descriptor on the other side.
Yeah, so these features can be very hard to understand
and I get it.
So I want to mention that this is optional.
It's not something that you have to use
if you want to use a dustbuzz,
and I would suggest if you don't have the need to use them,
don't use them, keep it simple,
do whatever is the easiest,
because there can be a lot of,
yeah, additional code that can be hard to understand.
Another thing I want to mention is that
I acknowledge that every project is a little different
and has very different needs,
and sometimes you can make a lot of assumptions
about your service.
Like, you might not need half of the debug support
that there is, so you can simplify some stuff a lot,
and it's great, but that's often not generic enough
to be implemented in a library like dustbuzz.
So what you can do actually is to take any piece
of dustbuzz, re-implement it to fit it to your needs,
and propagate it in the right places
so dustbuzz will use it instead of the original
implementation.
I want to mention this because we were in this position
at the beginning of our project,
and we had a lot of troubles with the library
that we used back then,
and basically we had to patch the whole library
because we were not able to get there
the stuff that we needed,
and it wasn't easy to just change it,
so we have to patch it.
So this is the link to the library.
There's open discussion session, there's issue tracker,
so if you have any suggestions, questions,
you can find me there, reach me there.
I don't hesitate to ask.
There's also, there are some examples.
You should be able to find the examples
that are similar to the one that I showed you.
I think I will use there also the demo stuff
because it's easier to understand.
Yeah, and there's also recommendation that might help you
because maybe this talk didn't help you so much.
So that's all from me.
Thank you so much for coming.
Yeah, does anyone has any questions?
Yeah.
Thank you.
I think we have time for questions.
Yes.
Yeah.
Hi, I just wanted to ask, where do you find people
who are using this?
Is it in chat message applications
or what are the applications of this for most people?
What are the applications who are providing
the debuffs API that you can, okay.
So like on the ONNX system, it's basically
like there are printers or you can control the media player
or you can set up your firewall or on the session bus.
I think this chat actually has their own debuffs API.
So it's more like the applications that are running
on your rest stop often provide this debuffs API
so you can write some scripts to tweak them
and to control them.
So yeah, that's it.
I'm sure.
Yeah.
Okay.
Does bus support properties and annotations?
Properties, yes.
Annotations do mean like properties changed annotations
or stuff like that.
Like it's changed signal and deprecated
and stuff like that.
Oh, I'm not sure about it.
I think it's not like needed.
It's just like a recommendation for the documentation
but it's not something that.
Otherwise the client can't see that the server
may support an API call but it's a debt marked
as deprecated.
Okay.
Yeah, I think it doesn't like support customer annotations
but that's definitely something I can look at if it's like.
I just wanted to give an add them and that's fine.
Yeah, yeah.
So I don't think that this is supported
but it's definitely supportable.
So yeah.
Hi, why would someone want to use debuffs,
I mean, Daspos for versus like some other debuffs library
that's out there for Python?
Yeah, okay.
So this library was actually inspired by Py debuffs
which is also very popular.
It just, we hit some issues and it's complicated
like you need to think a lot for us.
So at some point I just got so frustrated
I decided to rewrite it and create Daspos.
But yeah, there are a lot of like interesting libraries
and sometimes they are a little simpler
and it might be enough.
So like you don't have to use this one.
It's just, this is much easier if you,
if you have a lot of debuffs API
because like with our project
there are several debuffs services
and it has a lot of objects, a lot of interfaces
and it will be very difficult to deal with it
in a, with a library that operates on lower level.
So we needed a lot of abstraction
to make sure that the code is okay.
We have time for one last question.
Who was first?
Maybe two questions.
Hello, thank you for the library.
I've been trying it and it's great.
I wanted to ask a question regarding the van loop.
Lately I've been doing some work with debuffs
and I find it very painful that most libraries
rely on the G-LIP main loop
rather than the default event loop coming from Async.io.
I saw that in the code base.
You, there is an abstract event loop
that could become something else.
But do you have any plans about that?
Yeah, so right now I don't know about the demand
for additional support for other event loops
and like the cons.
But the code is implemented in a way
that it should be possible to do it.
So if there is like enough people
who would be interested in this,
that's definitely something I would like to look at.
It's just, yeah, it's no demand right now.
Thanks a lot, thank you again.
Thank you.
And to our audience for people interested in
the next desktop here.