So, hello, everyone. My name is Anastasia, and I can say a few words about myself before
we start today's talk. I came here from Berlin. I live in Germany, Berlin, for already seven
years, but I'm from Ukraine originally, and I play a role as an associate director of
engineering at Soundwide in Berlin. Also, I'm one of the organizers of Bye Berlin Meetup,
and I have 11 years of experience in software development and seven of them in Python. You can
see how happy I am with Python, and I can share, and I will share, my long road to programming,
actually, with documentation, and you will learn from me what I learned through all the years of
software development. And let's start today's talk with a question. Do you document your code?
So, raise a hand if you do. Write documentation. Wow, a lot. Nice. Okay. That's very nice. So,
some years ago, around ten years ago, when I just started, I remember myself, I started
programming language. I took a programming book, then I just went by the book. I wrote a
hello world program. It was very nice. It looked so perfect. I did a first pull request into our
code, and I thought it was very perfect. It looked so great. It was approved, but it didn't feel right.
I didn't even know what to check, but I just didn't feel right, and I was not sure, would this code
still be live or there in some years, or maybe in six months, or somebody will just change that code,
and then it would be not good anymore. And when I even passed the code review, I merged the code.
I was still not sure what to check in the code and when to consider that the code is good enough.
And, of course, I didn't know about documentation. I was not told that I should write documentation
in my code. And today, we're going to look into the ten years after I started. So, after all of
this time, I realized that experience comes together with the confidence of you more.
You are more confident in the code that you're writing because you're writing a lot, and then
you learn from other people, you go to the conferences, you listen to all the talks,
all the experiences, you talk to other developers in the community. If you're an open source developer
and there is no documentation, it's a bit tricky. So, what if me ten years ago could possibly travel
into the future and listen to this talk and know what to do from the very start? I would be maybe
happier in my life. I would not do so many mistakes as I did through all the years. And that's why
we're here. I'm going to show you things that I learned over the years. And we are going to
have a bit of magic today happening following the ten years into the future. So, let the future
begin now. Let's start with the story of one little set code which was lost in its lifetime,
and no one wanted to play with this code. This is the code that I'm talking about.
And the code was just sitting there very sad, very little, wondering.
Wondering why am I so sad, why no one is talking to me? And had no clue how to deal with other
services or other developers and had so many questions in its lifetime. And the only sad cat
was sitting and supporting that set code. So, the set code was actually wondering what is wrong with
it and how to change to find new friends. Let's take a look into the code. So, the first function,
it's pretty clear. It's just the hello world, the basic stuff. But if you look to the second one,
this is the sad part. So, there is a function with some of the arguments and some of the results
returning something, but not very clear, not very clear the outcome of the function, what does it
do, what is the purpose, also names of the parameters, where they lost at some point.
So, you remember the story, there was a set code, very sad code, and just a cat
sitting next to the sad code. And the code went to sleep. And something truly magical happened.
It met someone. It met its future self. Just right ten years after. And the future self said,
I will give you four pieces of advice which will help you to improve your communication skills,
and in the end, I will give you a riddle to solve. So, follow my advice to reclaim the ancient
knowledge of programming superpowers and you will shine for many, many years. So, let's start.
Then listen carefully. Yes, the sad code said, please continue. So, here is my first advice to
you. This is the way how to use the goal oriented approach to show the world how to solve a problem
if there are any in the future. This approach is about writing how to guides. So, those are
basically the directions to the reader and you can read a bit more in the links which I listed
over there. This is the most used guide, the most searched and the most read in basically everything
written about the code. It includes like a recipe or the direction for solving a very specific
problem. So, if you are trying to create something of the how to guide about something very specific,
not very about everything, like how to create a web server, something that would not be how to guide,
but something how to create for a very specific reason. That would be how to guide. And those are
actually very specific guidelines that we are usually looking for because we have all of the
specific issues and then we are searching for a specific piece of information for a specific
problem as a solution. So, with the first piece of advice, the sad code was thinking, okay, I can
improve by just writing a simple setup, how to set up myself to be open for others. So,
that's a very specific what to install, where to install and added some read me file to the
guideline of the code. And then after following that advice, the sad code noticed that they got
a friend. Can you imagine? A friend, a real friend. How do I know that? Well, just look at that. There
is a star shining. Well, that was just the star, the first one. So, the second advice showed the
sad code how to use learning oriented approach to show the world what actually is done by this code.
So, those are the tutorials. Those are a bit different from the how to guides in the way that
this is more like learning by doing so you're not reading all the documentation, you're just
doing an exercise like a teacher showing in the school what to do to learn a specific subject.
So, if we're talking about the code, then just follow the advice also would be learning by doing,
writing some specific tutorials would be to achieve some goal, but it doesn't have to be
a very specific problem to be solved. So, if we're following the advice, the sad code was thinking,
okay, maybe I can add a bit more. Let me write some tutorial about basic set up, how to write
it, how to build it. And then something happened again. There was another friend. Look at that.
The second star is shining. Already good. Good path. The third advice showed the sad code how to use
understanding oriented approach to explain more what the code is doing. So, those are the
explanations, different discussions on very specific topics which are broadening the main subject.
So, if we already have the basic documentation, we have the how to guide, we have different
learning by doing exercises. Those are explanations are very, very specific. So, if you compare to a
recipe book, this is not a recipe book. This is more of a reference of the different ingredients,
how to get the ingredient, for example, or which ingredients are particular for a very specific
dish. This is everything that could tell the sad little code how to deal with different packages
or different services, how to integrate with others. And, of course, the sad code
did implement something like this. So, they wrote a bit of more explanation on why do we
need documentation in general. And, again, it was very helpful, very happy. So, the sad code
was thinking, okay, and more friends are coming. That's great. Let's go to the last advice. So,
the last but not least piece of advice was about information oriented approach, about references.
In software development, reference guides are usually describing the functions, the input
output arguments, the results of the functions, key classes, different APIs. So, everything that
is about the code, about different attributes, it doesn't have to be every single function,
but it should be all of the main key classes, key functions that are used. So, then, afterwards,
you can recap and then look just the ten years after you can look at what was done before.
And, just like that, the code, the sad code followed the fourth piece of advice and decided to
write the code reference, edit that, and also applaud that to somewhere for others to see.
And, after those four wonderful advices from the future self, something really magic happened.
And the code woke up not very sad anymore, not mad, and it felt very comfortable to go out and
then talk to others, connect to other developers. And then, after some time, the sad code remembered
that there was a riddle. The future self said, that would be a riddle, and then you will gain
the superpowers, right? So, here it is. I'm someone who can teach you a lesson, but not a teacher.
I'm someone who can guide you to a goal, but not a tour guide. I'm someone who can tell you
everything about technical specs of your functions, but not an encyclopedia. I'm someone who can
explain you a particular topic to help you to understand, but not Google. Can you guess what that is?
Okay. So, the code was very happy because they knew the answer already and asked the future self,
so, well, look, was it all about you? All about you, my future, so you are documentation, so you
are really my future. And the future self said, yes, those four advices were all about me and
your future. I'm your future. Fantastic documentation with the tutorials, how-to guides,
explanation, and the references. And, in other words, we all need to understand that documentation
is not a single piece. It's more than that. It consists of four different types of documentation,
and it's very important that we add all of them, and we at least have some sections of those
to focus for our future selves not to be in trouble.
So, just to recap the future of that little code is now, it's about code references,
tutorials, explanations, how-to guides, and that would make your code happy, and the cat, of course.
And it would get many friends, especially in open source, it's very important to add
documentation and to explain what is code actually doing and all the functions. And that would be a
really bright future. So, I have another question for all of you. Would you document your code
after all of you heard in the future? So, if this example didn't convince you, I have a few more
pieces of advice from myself from my own experience. Why do we need to document code? Because people
forget things. Even if you wrote a code, you will forget about it in a week, in a month, in a day,
or maybe something happens and then, well, you return back to the code and then you don't
remember why was it. People leave the code alone. And this is also important. If you are working for
open source, you can give it to somebody else. You leave it alone. Then you come back, you need to
review. And then, oh, my God, I didn't remember that function. Then new people come to contribute.
This is also very important. They need to know how to contribute, what to contribute, what is
important for this. So, how to start? First, you need to choose main source tool for documentation.
And then, of course, you need to make sure that it's up to date. So, the continuous documentation,
it's a culture. It's not the thing that you can force people into. You need to make it as a culture
for yourself and also for other people. So, I would recommend you to read a few things.
This was the original document where it's actually written about those four pieces of documentation.
I recommend you to go through it, read more about different types of documentation, then also
work with documentation about the legacy code. And the real Python has a very nice tutorial about
documentation with MK docs and also GitHub pages. So, how to start? You need to start as simple as
possible. This is the best solution. Just start some basics. Then you can go to version control
documentation. And that would be like a next level. So, you have Python code. You need to document
something. First, what do you do? I would say you start documenting. So, for that, you need to add
some doc strings to your code. Then you will take them and make a reference guide which is nice to
have. It's out of the box. It can be auto generated if you host it somewhere so beautiful and easy.
For that, you can use Sphinx, MK docs to prepare the documentation, also put some files.
Of course, you can try to host it somewhere like read the docs which is free for open source
projects or GitHub pages. There are other tools, but those are the ones I used. And, of course,
add more documentation. So, if you want to see those pieces of documentation that I showed,
here is the link where they are. And also, you can see in here, so this is how the read the docs
would look if you would use it for a simpler project. And this is how the Sphinx of the
documentation that I showed you with the set code would look like. And then, just to remind you that
you cannot force people to read documentation. You can force them only to write documentation. So,
if you want to make sure that your documentation is up to date, you need to make it as a culture
for yourself to also start somewhere to start writing documentation, and then it will somehow
become a habit. So, thank you so much. This is all you can all join the PyBerlin meetup in Berlin.
You're all welcome to come. We have meetings every month. And also, some of the more articles
about documentation you can read over there.
Thank you, Anastasia. We have five minutes for questions. If we have questions,
please raise your hand. I will pass the microphone so we can record the questions. Can you maybe
pass it over? Thanks for the talk. Did you experience an increase in your documentation
quality when using such tools? I mean, so, the overall problem is you actually need to write
documentation and you need like an incentive for it, right? Did you experience that using the
tools that you presented helps? Well, it did help. So, we forced a certain documentation level. You
can also see the tools that I used on the CI on the project that I shared. They just did help to
force people to write it. But actually, as soon as we made this as a must to have for every code
review, then it helped. So, for every code review, every developer was looking, okay, you didn't
write this documentation. This is important. And then they would ask, can you please write some
few lines about this. This is important to remember. Then it did work.
Thank you for the talk. I wanted to ask about your opinion on using ChetGPT to maybe ease the
work of documentation, save your time if you've got any opinion on it. Because from my experimenting,
it can document code quite decently. So, maybe it could even be used for the tutorial-based
approach that you mentioned. Oh, actually, I didn't try it. So, I can try and let you know next time.
Thanks. Any other questions?
Hello. Thank you for your talk. Do you use restructure text, markdown? Do you think
Python coder should use one or the other? RST or MD? Which do you like?
Well, it doesn't matter if you don't write documentation. So, it's important to actually
write. And it's actually up to developers. Sometimes they like one, sometimes they like the other.
And I don't mind both. I just want to make sure that there is up-to-date documentation.
Do you have tools to help you to make documentation up-to-date?
Oh, that's a tricky question. Well, this is more like a human factor, how to make documentation
up-to-date. You can test examples. You can even try the examples if they work. So, you can automate
that. You can check how many lines of the documentation are in every pull request. So,
this is automated. But it doesn't automate the things which are outside of the code. You cannot
really test those unless there is a piece of code. You can go through it. You can try running it. So,
unfortunately, the things outside of the very specific code, and this is basically not.
Thank you.
Okay, we have two more minutes for questions.
I see a question in the back. Perfect. I needed to do some sport today.
Okay.
A, thank you for your talk. Is writing documentation something that you do
alone or something that you collaborate with someone else? And if so, are there non-technical
people that collaborate with you in the moment of writing? Or how can you be sure to address also
people with different levels of technical knowledge? Thank you.
Thank you for the question. Actually, those are different types of documentation. So, there is a
technical documentation which could be written by a technical writer. But documentation that my team
is writing, for example, should be written by a developer who is writing the code. So,
you're a developer, you wrote a piece of code, a function, something you have to document it.
And this is actually written in our ways of working for the team. So, that is part of the
done of the features. So, as soon as this is done, it has to be documented.
Unless it's documented, we don't close the ticket. So, it has to happen. And this is for everyone in
the team. So, there's no specific person on the developer who did the feature. Then they do it.
Do we have any other question?
Okay. Regarding chat GPT, I played a bit with it. I have the feeling it's a great tool for
beginners to learn. But if chat GPT can document it, then why should you? Shouldn't you put what
chat GPT cannot guess from the code, all the business logic, the reasons you did it?
Just a small thinking. Thanks a lot. Thanks again.
Thank you.