Hello, so yeah, I'm talking about PyScript.
So I'm trying to get a catchy title, so it's kind of like a clickbait, so we PyScript,
we place Django, so maybe a lot of people will be like really, you know, sparking their
interest because I mentioned Django, which is a very popular framework for web.
But today I'm not going to talk too much about Django, but I'm mainly going to talk about
PyScript and I would have some crazy demo at the end, which is like very interesting
demo, so you may not want to miss it, but the most important thing is that this is the
link to the slides.
I should have used some QR code, but kind of lazy, so this is just a link that you could
find the slide deck.
It is also uploaded to the Fostem website, you can find it to follow along, if you can't
see it very well or anything happened, then you can look at the slides, and all the links
are there as well.
So I hope that since you're here, you have heard of PyScript, but how much do you know
about PyScript, except that it's something to do with Python?
So, yeah, silence.
So, yeah.
So I think most people that I met, I've talked about PyScript and they said they have heard
about PyScript, they may have read a block or two about PyScript, it's something that's
relatively new, so that's why I think it's important to kind of, you know, to put information
together so people have something to look at when they want to know more about PyScript.
So by the way, I'm Czech, why am I talking about PyScript?
Why it sounds like I know a lot about PyScript, because I work in Alekonda, so PyScript is
developed by a team in Alekonda, so I work with them a lot, so I have, you know, kind
of very close to the source, so I kind of have some information about what's the newest
thing about PyScript, and I love open source projects, I have been involved in open source
projects in the past, I just want to put more pictures there, so that's why I put it here.
And I organize a lot of events, so let's jump into it.
What is PyScript?
PyScript is actually a framework, some people think that PyScript is a new language, but
it's not, it's actually Python, but you can write Python in your HTML file, that's what
it is.
And also, like, it's a framework, why, because later you'll see why, like, we say PyScript
is a framework, because of how you can change the backend and other stuff.
So it lets you run Python application in the browser, basically it just means that you
can, well, you can run, you know, you can write Python script, just like you write JavaScript
in the HTML file, and then the browser would understand what you wanted to do, and then
we'd do something.
So but it's not trying to repay JavaScript, you can actually use it with JavaScript, for
example, I'm using it with the D3 library, which is crazy.
Who knows about D3?
Yes, okay, good.
Okay, I'm not speaking to other people, but yeah, it's good.
So I will show some demo later, so basically you can actually pass the objects back and
forth.
So you can change your Python object into JavaScript object, and then your JavaScript
library like D3 will understand it, or the other way around, so it is something that
is quite new.
So also, so all these things that I talk about, that you can, like, change the Python object
into JavaScript object, all this stuff, won't be happening if we don't have the PyEoDy project,
which they, by the way, for those of you who haven't heard, it started as a monselas project
called Iody.
They tried to have a lot of things that is run, you know, as a WESM, WebAssembly, so
the browser can run it.
And then there's a, so within that, all those projects, there's a Python, you know, project
that is actually like converting Python into WebAssembly, so that's the PyEoDy project.
So that's actually allow you to run the Python, so without it, like, actually, PyScript won't
work.
So, well, PyScript will still work, you can change the backend, but like, it started with
PyEoDy, sorry, I'm like kind of, I'm trying to be correct in what I'm saying.
But the main thing is that you need to kind of compile Python into a WebAssembly.
So PyEoDy is like the, kind of one of the most popular one, that is like having the
whole, more or less the whole thing that your standard Python offer is actually compiled
into WebAssembly, so you can run Python on the browser.
But there's also other things that we are trying, the team is trying now, for example,
they are trying to compile microPython, which is a lighter version of Python, into WebAssembly,
so it more or less works the same, but you have some kind of Python functionality that
is not available on microPython, so you can actually choose which one you want to use.
And also because one thing about the PyEoDy project that is, that is why it is the first
one that PyScript adopts and why it's the first one that is like, why it is so popular,
because the project itself also provides a lot of Python packages, for example, those
that we use a lot, for example, NumPy, like scientists and data scientists use a lot,
it's like, for example, NumPy, SciPy, SciQL, and all those actually are quite difficult
to run on a browser because they are not pure Python.
So for pure Python, if you have a Python interpreter that actually is compiled into Wasm, of course
you can do it because they are just Python, but something like NumPy, SciPy, SciQL, and
they are not pure Python, then it's a bit tricky, but PyEoDy project also provides that,
so now we can also run those very complicated Python packages on the browser, which is cool.
So I will show you a little bit of the PyScript basic, and then I'll show you the demo, and
then like, all the questions will come at the end.
Is it too small?
I don't know how to zoom in though.
That's why the link is important at the beginning.
So I can explain, but the content of this code is not the most important thing, it's
just like how a typical PyScript will look like.
So I'm just talking about this section here.
So for the first two lines here, you don't need to see it, but I'm telling you what it
is, it's just like when you have a JavaScript code, you would actually have a, probably
you have a CSS, which is like the style of how your website will look like, the style
sheet, and then you have a JavaScript that you kind of pull it in, and then you can run
all these like JavaScript functions that you have.
So this is actually something like a path to a PyScript.js that's hosted on the PyScript.net.
So this is actually what allows you to write Python on the websites, on your HTML file.
You may ask, why is it.js?
This is just how wasm works, so we have to follow the standard.
So yeah, that's.js, but that's not important, you're not writing JavaScript, so don't worry
about it.
Next is there is a section that you can actually write Python code.
So here is just some NumPy code that is plotting some NumPy random numbers.
So here, like if it's, sorry, I'm not expecting the room to be this big.
So if you can see it, so the first line is basically a HTML tag, and it's PyScript, and
then it also have a little bit of settings like output equals to plot and stuff like
that.
And it is just a Python script.
It's just like import NumPy, import Map.lib and all that stuff.
And then it's Python code.
It's just like you can copy and paste your Python code there.
It's more or less the same thing.
And the other thing that you may have when you are using PyScript is a PyConfic file.
So this PyConfic file is actually, there's multiple formats that is supported.
In this example, in JSON format, it's just a JSON file with packages is NumPy, and then
Map.lib, because we are using it in the Python code.
That's why we have to put it there to say that we are using those packages, kind of
like your pip install.
It's like putting it in the environment within your browser.
So that's what it does.
So this is the code.
That's typically how it looks like.
One catch is that it's using the latest version in the first two lines there.
So if you don't want to break your code, you can pin a version.
Now you can also pin a specific version with the releases and then the version number.
Now we are named.
We are attacking it as like the year, month, days, year, month probably, and then the versions.
So if, for example, you don't want it to, because now PyScript is still changing a lot.
So if you don't want your code to be not working next month, so you may want to pin the version
until you want to update it manually when you look at the code again and update it.
You can do it, so don't worry about it.
I know people will have questions about it.
Or you may think that, oh, like, you're a web developer and you don't like the CDN calling
in from another website that you have no control of.
If that website got attacked or something and it won't work, it may be very dangerous.
You can host it yourself.
You can download that two things, the style sheet and the JavaScript code yourself.
And the other things will fit as well.
There are also a few other things.
But they are all downloadable.
You can download it and host it yourself if you want to.
So it's getting more complicated because now the PyScript is getting more developed and
now there are more things you can config about how PyScript works.
The PyConfig tag is where you can change all those.
So, first of all, the tag itself, so within inside, there's multiple formats you can use.
There's the Tomo format, which is the default.
So if you don't tell this tag what format you're writing, so it will just assume you're
using a Tomo format.
So in this demo here, it says packages and paths.
So it's just like what package you are putting in.
Just like the pigment store thing, there's an environment within the browser that's running
all the PyScript code.
So you have to first say what packages you are using to allow it to be usable.
The JSON format, again, it's just different formats, more or less the same thing.
Or you can actually have another source.
You can write your file in another, for example, either JSON file or Tomo file.
You can also put it in because you don't want everything to be in your HTML file, so you
can actually put in other sources as well.
And also, the PyConfig tag is not just used for putting all your packages and other stuff.
There's also other things that you could set in a PyConfig tag.
So you can also host the will of the package.
It doesn't need to be using the one that's provided by Py
Script, but you can do it as well.
You can change the runtime setting, like I said before, because Py
isn't necessarily there of a lot of fun.
Take no time to load, but it provides all the basic Python
code that you could write in the HTML file.
So you can quickly teach someone Python
without installing Python and just like
running it on the HTML file.
You can also add some metadata, for example,
you want to add the author who writes this script
and the license, you can also do that, no problem.
So another thing that you may put in your HTML file
while you are using PyScript is the PyRepo.
It's something that's just like Jupyter Notebook.
If you have Jupyter Notebook, you know,
it's like very nice repo that you can put in the
Python code, shift enter, and then you execute
and give you the result.
You can also embed that in your HTML page
when you are using PyScript.
So you just need to do the same thing,
you know, having those two lines of the style sheet
and the PyScript.js.
And then you can just put the PyRepo tag
and then you will have a Jupyter-like repo
that you could use in your site.
So why is it so useful, right?
Like, it's a new thing, it's exciting,
but can I really use it?
Or is it just a fun thing to do
while doing it on the front end, right?
Like now you can have like application, like Django,
like I said, it's a kind of people love Django,
like I, you know, why do we want PyScript?
Because sometimes like things just need to be run
on the front end, sometimes like we can't really rely
on an application like Django or other Python application
to handle all this Python code.
For example, if you don't want to use up all your resources,
right, like if you have a back end and then the back end
is actually hosted by you or the cloud service
that you pay for, if there's a lot of user
and like if every single user had a very like heavy use
of your resources, then the bills can be expensive
and then you may not want that, you want to maybe,
you know, give back the law into the users
who is using it, right?
So you could push things into the front end.
And all, if I've heard like maintainers said that like,
they want people to try out their code, you know,
you can build a sandbox that let people to run it,
like for example, a lot of the data science stuff,
you know, for example, the NumPy, SciPy,
they will have, before they will have the binder thing
that actually load in, you know, another application,
you know, that have the back end
and then they could run some code there to do it
as an example.
But for these services, they are provided for free usually,
they are quite slow or you know, they have limits.
So if you want to provide a sandbox for users,
if it can run on their machine, you don't have to worry
about people abusing it as well.
Like for example, some people, if you,
whoever run whatever on your sandbox,
they could do crypto mining and then it's not a good thing.
So if it's on the front end,
it's using the user's resources, not your resources,
which if they want to mine Bitcoin,
it's fine, it's on their machine or on your machine,
you don't have to pay the bill.
Also, sometimes we have applications that, for example,
is some research data, some medical data, very sensitive.
So you can't really, you know, it's like the rules that you,
the data can't leave the machine.
So you can send it to a backend somewhere to do it.
Then, you know, maybe you can provide the, you know,
provide the code that, you know,
someone can use it to run on the browser.
So it's run on their machine.
So instead of, you know, you have,
you have built application and they have to send the data
over to your, whatever the backend is,
and then to run the application.
So it's also easier to set up as well.
Otherwise you may have to provide a separate,
secure environment with the whole kind of set up
of the backend and the front end together and stuff.
You know, if you just have the front end, it's much easier.
You don't have to worry about it.
So with Highscript, with H. Django,
I know that you already know the answer is no,
but actually it's very fun if you use them together.
I will show you a few things that I like,
that is done by either me or some of my friends.
That's actually quite cool things that we have used,
like both Django and Highscript.
So for example, this is what I have done with,
can I just pass it in here?
Okay.
So this is something that I've done.
It's like using Highscript with Django.
That I've, so this is what I,
I will show you what it is first and then I will explain.
So here, this is the thing I do.
I think this one, this one I can zoom in cool.
So this is a recommender system, right?
So I have all these movie that I download
from the movie dataset on Cardo.
And then is there a bunch of ratings.
So this recommender, if you put in a movie that you like,
if you try to find all the potential movie
that you like after, for example,
I always like putting Iron Man because I know it works.
And then give me five recommendations.
If I like Iron Man, what else would you recommend me?
And then if I click recommend,
and I've got five of them, right?
So most of them sci-fi movie, which is quite cool.
There's also the Dark Knight, which is,
I think it's the movie about a Batman,
which is also, I like it.
So yeah, that's nice.
So, but this thing, right?
This thing, usually you think of, oh,
it's like a machine learning thing, right?
It's a recommender system.
You know, can I run it on the front end?
Yes, you can.
As long as you have your model already trained,
then for example, in my example here,
actually you have a link to see the,
how it's set up.
If you click on this link,
it will show you how I set it up.
So you can play around yourself as well.
So what I did is just like,
of course I download the data as a given,
you have to have the data to make it work, right?
And then after that, you just run some of this script.
You can actually do it in a more beautiful way.
I'm just using some command line to run all this script
to load in the data to train your model and stuff.
You can do it with other ways.
For example, you have a user, a main user interface, right?
They upload a new data and other stuff.
Then it will automatically retrain the model
when there's new data.
You can set that up as well,
but it's just a demo, so this is like this.
But after that, there will be a model that's already trained.
It will deploy to the front end.
And then in the front end, that's how this come in.
That's how it works.
So this is just a trained model.
It's very lightweight.
And then you don't have to host all the data.
It could be done somewhere else.
But for the user, they have a trained model
and then they just need to put in the input
and then it will give you some results.
So if a machine learning model deploy on the front end.
Another thing that my friend has done, which is quite cool,
is front end as a back end.
So it's running Django on the browser.
So.
Yes.
No, this is, oh, this is so small.
But yeah, someone has done it.
This is not my doing,
so I don't have responsibility.
But have a look.
So this is actually like,
basically you have two browser, like HTML page.
One page is the server.
One page is the front end.
So this is what it is.
So you have a back end and a front end.
On the same page, yay.
So yeah, you can do that.
So I was like, oh, this is a bit fun, but is it useful?
But my friend here Hugo told me
that you can actually use it to test things
because you now can run an application on the browser.
So everybody have a browser.
So you can run an application on it, which is pretty cool.
So yeah, check that out.
Other things that I used PySquared for is not with Django.
It's with other things.
For example, use it together with D3.
I have this example here.
I already preload them because I'm not going to like,
for you, it actually take quite a while to load.
So that's why I preload them.
But yeah, because I'm using the whole kind of package.
Here I'm using NetworkX.
I have put in a network graph.
I have all these network analysis, which is super cool.
But I don't like the NetworkX visualization
because it's kind of basic.
So that's why I use D3 for the visualization.
I can do this.
Very good animation.
I can click on things and things change.
Now I see all the neighbors are colored coded.
So yeah, you can combine the cool stuff
that JavaScript provides, for example, D3,
and the cool stuff that Python provides,
which is all this data science stuff, which is cool.
Also, there are other plots as well.
Before, you can't have these interactive things
that you could, you know, interactive graph done easily
on your website.
So yeah, and also, map as well.
This is not, again, not my demo,
but you can now have this map thingy.
You can use volume, which is, again, Python library.
Now you can use it on the browser.
Super cool.
Yeah, and also, I have actually started building
a PyScript tutorial.
Again, this is work in progress because things keep changing.
I can't keep it up, but if you're interested,
if you want to try it, that may be a place
you want to have a look at.
So yeah, all of these slides, again, this is on the slide.
So yeah, so download my slides if you need to.
No.
So I think I don't have too much time left.
I would like to answer your questions,
but there are these common questions
that I would also ask and answer myself.
So for example, people ask me,
can you put in a Python script?
Yes, you can.
You can use the FASH now.
Look at the documentation if you want to.
What Python version you're using,
it depends on the runtime, which is, again,
PyConfig settings that you could, you know,
you can look at it and see which one you want to use,
you know, PyEldy version, which version you want to use,
you can choose it yourself.
And, you know, why we can't do it like JavaScript,
having script, tech equals to Python.
Because this is so new, all the browsers,
they don't support it yet, so we have to make a custom tech,
which is PyScript.
Okay, why don't you just use PyEldy?
I think PyScript is just easier to use.
PyEldy is very nice, but, you know,
sometimes get quite complicated for beginners, especially.
Also, you can change the runtime with PyScript,
so it's not just PyEldy, you can, again, you know,
there's, my colleagues now working on a compiled version
of micro-Python, it would be much faster,
much more lightweight, so try that.
A bunch more other things, so can you pin a version
of the packages that you use?
If you want, well, if you want,
then you better host the will yourself,
then you know which version you're using,
and it's there, frozen, unchanged forever.
So also, some, do you know Brighten?
Maybe some of you have heard about Brighten.
So Brighten is a project that tries to translate Python
into JavaScript and then run it in the browser.
The difference is that PyScript actually
is not using JavaScript, it's actually using Wasm.
So Python is compiled to Wasm,
so more packages is available.
So yeah, also you can, again, change the runtime,
the backend, which one you want to use.
Bware, as someone mentioned, Bware in my previous talk,
so yes, I would love to see more support for Bware,
but I can't say for the company, so I'm not saying that.
Yeah, so that's the end of my talk.
I know I have a few minutes left for Q&A,
so, or if you didn't get the sticker at the beginning,
come to talk to me, I'll give you a sticker.
Thank you.
We have a few minutes for questions,
and before the questions, I want to thank everyone
for joining the Python Dev Room,
and I want to thank also Eric Gazzoni,
my friend who organized all of the planning of the day
and everything upstream,
and he made a great worry for all the selection
of the speakers, the planning, everything.
He couldn't make it here today,
but I really want to thank him as well.
Thanks everybody.
And thanks to Arnaud also for joining me today
to help the Dev Room.
Yes, yes.
Hi, thank you for a wonderful talk.
High script is very exciting.
I know people are using WebAssembly
to run untrusted code in the browser.
You can use it like a sandbox, so it's very exciting.
But my question is, so you were importing packages.
Is that easy to do?
Do the packages have to be on the machine already?
Yes, so if you have internet connection,
so the package, if you just simply put in like,
you know, in the PyCon state,
you put in package equals to something,
so those will be actually approved
from whatever PyOutice provided.
So it needs to be loaded from online,
so you'll see if you have a web page,
it will take quite a while to load.
But you also have an alternative
that you can download the will of the package
as long as that will is purely written in Python.
So something like NumPy, SciPy, those,
because they have extension,
they're not purely written in Python,
those you don't have an option.
You have to use the WonderPy that I provided.
But otherwise, if it's in other library,
for example, Fuzzy Wussy, you know,
it's purely written in Python.
You can download the will and it can run locally.
Yeah.
Yeah, my question's about matplotlib is okay,
but how is this base map or carto-py?
Can it be used also?
Matplotlib, sorry.
Matplotlib is for graphics,
but if you have cart, maps, base map,
can such a tool also be used, sent in the browser?
Yeah, most of the library that if it's available in Python,
it will also be available, so.
It must be pure Python or it's.
Oh, matplotlib, I'm not sure matplotlib is pure Python.
I don't know matplotlib enough, John, so the question.
I try.
Yeah, but yeah, so you have to check.
Like the library that you want to import,
is it purely in Python or not?
So yeah.
I'm a bit confused because what we loaded in the browser
is a JavaScript module,
so is there some WebAssembly somewhere?
Yeah, so you see the script that was import is.js, right?
But actually, that's a WebAssembly.
It's just that the standard, the WebAssembly standard
is like when my team provided,
like when they released the thing,
which is in WebAssembly, but it's the extension.js.
It's a bit confusing, but actually it's in WebAssembly.
It's not in JavaScript.
It's just how the WebAssembly kind of standard work.
You have a JS file somehow after you have, you know,
done the release, the build and the source.
It become.js.
We have time for one more question.
Should I have one?
Yep, better.
Thanks for your talk.
Does PyScript use any Web workers?
And if so, how do, can you control them?
There's the web, sorry.
Does PyScript use any Web workers?
Like does your code run parallel?
It's purely in the browser.
So if you host everything locally,
actually it's just on the browser.
So there's no Web worker that communicate
with other applications.
Yeah.
Yes, yes.
One tiny question.
Yeah.
How does it all came in with different browsers
for Firefox, Chrome?
Because I guess it depends on your browser supporting that.
Yeah.
Now, definitely work on Chrome.
Firefox maybe, others, I can't guarantee.
Right.
Yeah, yeah.
But it's very young, the project.
So later it will be more support.