Please give a big welcome to Walter, who is coming from the Netherlands for an introduction
to micropiton.
Well, hello everyone.
Take your seats, you people.
I cringe at every extra person who walks in because it's an extra 100 watts of heating.
It's already quite hot here.
Okay, can start I think.
Okay, that's me and that's a Python subject for today.
I welcome questions.
If anyone wants something while I'm talking, please raise your hand and you'll get a microphone.
And if that takes too much time, I just skip subjects.
Interaction is always nice.
Okay, I'm Walter van Ooye.
I did informatics, the technical version, when it didn't just exist.
I worked in industry for quite a long time.
I still have a web shop and sell things like these stuff.
I worked at Hochshoe Utrecht for a year at Avant to teach technical informatics, of course,
and now I'm employed by a company who does robotics in industry.
But this is about micropiton.
First context, I guess you all know what a microprocessor is.
Way back when they first made a single processor on one chip, it was a very feeble small thing.
And since then we have progressed a lot.
Now we can pack a lot of power in one chip.
But that's still a processor.
It cannot do anything on itself.
It needs external stuff like memory, IO, hard disk to store things permanently, probably
less of cooling like we all do here.
That's one way to use what we can put in a chip.
The other route is don't make necessarily the processor much powerful, but put more
things on a single chip.
More RAM, flash ROM to store code, peripherals to do things in the outside world, and then
you have a microcontroller.
Everything in one chip.
And that's a nice thing not to run your windows on, but to think of things in the real world,
with motors, lets, relays, all kinds of stuff.
That is, if you can still buy them.
Maybe that will be solved in the near future when ASML produces more chip machines.
Compilers and interpreters.
You know, an interpreter looks at source code for line by line, sees what's there, does
it, and then it looks at the next line and does it again.
That's not very quick, but there is no extra steps involved, so when you change your source
code, it immediately has effect.
And when you interact, you interact in its way with that interpreter.
Compiler takes source code, turns later to native machine code, and that is the thing
that runs.
When you interact, when you interact with the program, you interact with the running
native code.
All clear?
I used to be a lecturer, so everyone clear?
And then, of course, no one raised a finger, it's not clear to me.
Things cannot be that simple, so there's combos of compile interpreter.
That's actually how Python generally works.
You have a source code, you have a compiler that translates that source code to an intermediate
representation, and then you have an interpreter that interprets that intermediate code.
Now, you have either the best of both worlds or the worst, I don't know.
This takes some time, but less than real compilation, and this is slower than real running native
code, but it's still somewhat faster than directly interpreting the source code.
Real clear?
Okay.
Python typically runs interpreted, which has benefits and disadvantages, but we'll combine
that.
What's Python's place in the larger world of things?
There are programming language, I think you can recognize the symbols, that make it easy
to change your code, to run it quickly, to think of it, to try things.
It's the one end of the spectrum.
There's the other side of the spectrum, when you write high performance codes, like operating
systems, graphical tools, games and things like that, those language are much less forgiving
in what you do.
It takes a lot of time to compile it correctly, but then they filter out a lot more errors
than those type of languages do, especially the torus for that.
And somewhere in between are the compromises, that's generally used for not too high performance,
but really some easily performance user interaction thing websites, simple graphical applications.
That's the whole scheme of things.
And traditionally, micro-controllers, these kind of things, were programmed with these
kind of languages, because they simply didn't have the resources, speed of the processor,
size of the RAM, size of the flash, to run with these kind of languages.
What really distinguishes the language is whether you are runtime-typed, in Python,
when you have a variable, the runtime system has no ID, whether it's a string or an integer
or a list or whatever, it will find out at runtime.
Very typed languages that's fixed, less flexible for you, easier on the processor.
It compiles to, well, the left side compiles to intermediate languages, some of them are
even really source-interpreted, right side languages are compiled to mostly machine language.
And memory management, an important one.
In Python, you rarely wonder about where your memory is, what memory is used.
The runtime system solves it.
In C and C++, you have to worry a lot about which memory you claimed, what you released,
don't release it too early, or you'll get a nice crash or something else.
And in between, well, you take some care of it, maybe give some hints to the runtime system,
but in general you don't bother too much with it.
So left side, easier programming, right side, quick running.
That's how traditional C Python works, you have your source, you translate it to an intermediate
language representation, that is runs.
And that's all done by your Python system you install.
That's both compiler and interpreter.
Wow, this looks more complex.
This micro Python, you still have a Python system, but now it no longer runs on your
quick fast desktop, it runs on a small microcontroller.
Both the compiler and interpreter run on the microcontroller.
And when your Python application runs, you interact with that microcontroller.
You still have your laptop, because you do the editing.
I don't have an editor running on this thing, so that's the old desktop.
I use Toni, it's a simple Python application, but it's quite useful for interacting with
micro Python.
So I interact with Toni, I edit my code there, it's sent or stored or kept on the microcontroller
itself.
There it is compiled and runs, and then it runs here and hopefully does nice things with
the outside world.
Still clear?
Nothing new, nice.
On the microcontroller, let's say standard, read, evaluate, print loop, so you can do
things like you did on the prompt on the Python on your normal computer.
And evaluate what you did, print it, and it can do more interesting things like linking
lets or reading files that are stored on the chip.
I think we should just show, because it's too...
Okay, here I have a R
We've seen extra drive here, that's the drive we created, and I can copy...
Here's the front end image.
I copy the micro Python image to that drive.
It copies it.
When it's done, it reboots.
Now the extra drive is gone, and I can see...
There's an extra communication port here, that's what the chip made.
I always rename my communication ports to 42, because...
Okay, just repreter to be sure.
Now let's start.
Okay, now here I have a prompt that is running on that small tipi, and just like a good Python
it can print hello.
Doesn't seem like much, but that's happening here.
It's not my laptop that's doing it.
And if you're a bit lazy and you don't want to fiddle with files, you can also...
Oops, boot again.
Here in Toni you can select under options, interpreter, I want to install micro Python,
and for the Raspberry Pi Pico it just knows where to find it.
Ah, internet is working.
It just grabbed the latest version, installed it.
Close.
And I have it running.
Yep, trans.
Nice.
Okay, now I must do something.
Let's take some code.
I can put code simply in the editor and say run this.
No.
Are you able to make it larger, please?
I think that's the wrong direction.
Large enough for you?
And it didn't show that let was not on, but now it's on, so it works.
Now, well, I can maybe I can convince you if I put a zero here and then run it again.
Ah, let's off.
You can all see that?
Well, just on is not that interesting.
Let's blink.
Make it simple, define the pin.
I import the libraries that are standard for this chip, and it allows me to access a pin.
Pin 25 happens to be the onboard LED.
I say it's an output pin, then I make it high, sleep a little time, make it low, sleep a
little time, and repeat it forever.
Okay, that should blinky.
Ah, it blinks.
Oh, nice.
Print the plot for any demo, otherwise your hands will get sore.
Okay, but now when I stop it, it stops and this thing doesn't do anything.
It should stop, it doesn't.
Well, there's always the reboot for that.
It's supposed to be interruptible by that stop button, but since a week it doesn't do
anything, I don't know why.
If I want to do the chip, do something on itself, I have to store this file on the chip.
So I make the blink.py on the chip.
Now it's here, and I can run it from there.
It still blinks, and that's not very interesting.
Now if I stop it and put it on a power bank, it doesn't do anything.
It's a pity.
When it starts, it looks for a main.py and excuse that file.
So if I wanted to start, I have to make a file, import blink, save that as main.py.
Ah, it's amazing.
This irritating, there is a small file system here.
I can make a new file directly delete, but I cannot rename a file.
So let's do the performance way of doing that.
Save as main, not me.
Now I can delete that one.
Nice.
It deleted the correct one.
And that's import blink.
So now if I put it on a power bank, it starts blinking of its own.
But now at least that's what happened yesterday.
When I start to hold it again, now it doesn't want to.
I cannot get into it anymore.
It's breached.
But okay, I can still reload.
But now if I reload the micro-py interpreter again, it keeps the file system.
So it keeps the main.py.
So it doesn't work.
So some clever guy made flash nuke.
And when I put that there, it reboots with that code.
Now it's nothing.
And if I now reboot it, I can put the normal code on it again.
Where it is.
Force the vehicle images.
Okay, put it one over there.
It just USB transfers quite quick.
And now I have a normal behaving.
Yeah, okay, that behaves again.
Nice.
We named CioPort.
You've seen blinky.
You've seen the startup.
Demo of the startup.
Okay.
I was going to demonstrate blinking a LED on a breadboard.
But it's too feeble to bring here.
So let's blink more LEDs.
Or it's better.
Okay.
Now you know why I put all the things on the table.
So I have the correct order of driving everything.
What's on here?
There's a bit.
I can blink a single LED.
Now I use a library I wrote.
And it's loading all those library files.
It takes some time.
And after that, yeah, it really blinks.
I'll come back to that later.
And this one, if I'm a bit insistent, it will probably stop.
Yeah, there it is again.
We can also have more LEDs.
I've made a system that's whatever target ship I use, it has eight pins that are connected
here.
So we can swap it for another board.
The whole different processor still has the same eight pins.
That's the edge library.
And edge.port is those eight pins gathered together in one port.
And I give it to the kit demo.
And then it should first load everything.
And then it's kit.
Okay.
Kit on eight LEDs.
But that's not enough.
You take an I2C extender chip and that chip.
Does it work?
Yes, it works.
And it has more output pins.
Load, load, load, load.
And then have a kit with 16 ports.
And if that's too slow, I think it's boringly slow.
Maybe 10 milliseconds is nice.
Load, load, load, load, load.
Yeah, that's a bit quicker.
Okay.
Back to the sheets.
One more LEDs.
We have some more LEDs.
Okay.
You saw that it spent some time at beginning by loading a few libraries.
It shows because I coded it that way because I want to know how long it takes to load the
libraries and how much RAM it uses.
In general, you can have three ways of putting library code on micro Python.
You can have the source files, the simple.py files.
And then when you load them, they are first compiled and then loaded.
You can also pre-compile those files on your laptop and then load the compiled version.
That's the.mpy files.
You can also take the files and build them into the image you load anyway.
You show me copying that image onto the chip.
You can put your files in there.
And that has effect for how much time it takes.
When I demoted, it was irritatingly long.
My files took about 12 seconds to get loaded from the flash compiled and ready for run.
When I pre-compiled, it's a little bit faster.
And when I freeze it, I build an image of micro Python with those files included.
It gets really fast.
And then it also uses less RAM.
RAM, memory on those chips is always a very scary source.
This chip has about, I think, 130K left after loading this library.
Looks like a lot.
You can eat it quickly, especially if you make screen buffers for LCDs and things like
that.
A 240 by 320 LCD with full color, that's two bytes per color.
I think that's more than is left there.
You couldn't still use it.
So it's very important to conserve that.
When I develop things, I simply take a very fast target.
The TNG is maybe 10 times faster than a pipe pico.
And it has, I think, one megabyte memory.
So that's ample.
But there's always a bot.
But it comes later.
Okay.
Embedding your code into a micro pipe image is not that complex.
I had it running on my Linux machine in maybe an hour.
Then I tried the same recipe on Windows and it fails.
So when it happens, what do you do?
You make a docker container.
So I made a docker container on the Linux machine that does exactly the same thing,
worked.
Then I run it on Windows.
Works too.
It's fine.
And I can show if I take this.
Maybe here.
There it is.
If I import my library, it's...
Okay.
You can do it.
There's a license statement.
A lot of text.
Okay.
Here I have that license statement in the source.
Let's add this is.
Fostem.
Foste?
Whatever.
Okay.
Start a docker container.
It works.
Otherwise it doesn't do it.
It takes some 40 to 400 seconds.
I cannot predict how long.
Of course it's docker.
So all the preparations, loading the Linux image, loading all the development tools,
that's cached.
But then after it, it takes the my library code and then it compiles the micro Python
with that library code edit and that takes some time.
Wait.
Okay.
It's running now.
Didn't take that long.
So what do I do now?
I reboot my chip again.
And now take the new code.
It's the new code.
Copy that to the boot.
Okay.
Let's see what we have here.
Now you no longer see the library files there because they are not present on the internal
file system.
They're built into the micro Python interpreter that I can still...
It's a bit faster now than it used to be.
And now print.
And now license text is expanded so I really have put the changed version of the library
in there.
Okay.
Let's go on.
I showed freezing code.
I still want more LEDs.
Not enough.
Why is more LEDs?
I think this is enough.
Like that.
Okay.
That needs more power.
I cannot power it off the USB port of my laptop so I need external power for that.
All right.
Now I take...
Oh.
It's a microphone.
Okay let's see what's on this chip.
Now I loaded the code from the chip.
I prepared on the chip there.
Don't need to load it from my PC there.
And it runs over there.
And it still loads the library.
So enough LEDs for you.
Okay.
Put it over there.
With so many LEDs you can do nicer things and just put them in the long line.
You can put them in a square and make displays with it.
So take that one off.
Does it stop?
Yeah, it stops.
And let's run that one.
And we are at Fosdam so it prints an F on it.
The code takes a long line of 64 LEDs and then it folds.
It offers 88888 LEDs to make a square.
That's what I call a canvas and I can write text on that.
Sorry?
Timed you mean?
I'm not going to do them all but let's say gf.wait a little bit.
What did I do wrong?
Ah, a slap won't work.
And then because we can't get enough of it.
While true.
Sorry conventions will take one.
Yeah, I need a flush and I need to wait after that.
I need this flush over here.
Oh, they should work.
I didn't prepare this one so let's see.
Something like that.
Ah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Okay, demo.
What am I missing?
Yeah.
I sleep here.
Clear right flush sleep.
Oh, you guys are wonderful.
This gets even more hold now.
But I guess two letters is not enough.
Where are more stuff here?
Ah, here are my flexis.
They also sell these things on flexible PCBs.
It's nice.
And then I put this one again.
Like this one.
And now it's garbage.
Anyone has any idea why it's garbage?
Yeah, the first one they go tuck, tuck, tuck, tuck.
And this one goes tuck, tuck, tuck.
Instead going the same direction it's zieksacht.
Okay.
So we must fold it in the zieksacht version.
Yeah.
If you know a better term for it, feel free.
Ah, hit the bug.
Fortunately, I know where to correct this.
Okay, to shosh, it's in canvas, and I made an error there in the zieksachting.
Rotate it.
Yeah, somewhere like here.
It's a forward one here.
It's of course an off by one error.
I have to subtract one more here because size is one beyond.
So plus one, yeah.
Okay, save it.
And run it again.
And just a hint, this won't work.
Why doesn't this work?
I made a stupid mistake.
And it's not in the code.
What?
No, that was a different chip.
But you're hot.
It's hot anyway here.
What did I just edit?
I edited the source code on my laptop.
That's the upper screen here.
This one is a source code on my laptop.
This one is the code on the chip.
I made a mistake resilient times.
So do the same thing, but now on the code here.
That one.
Now you see it's a bit slower because it must first retrieve that code from the chip to
the laptop.
Then I can edit it.
It's the same code, but still I have to edit it.
Well, which one will work?
Ah, that's quick.
Okay, thanks.
I'm not 25, okay, near.
I'm doing something stupid here.
Control-Z is your friend.
And now I've changed it on the...
Okay, there.
And I must still...
It's saving.
And now I run that one again.
It should...
Compile.
There's not the baked in version, this is from source version.
And now it works.
Well...
Okay.
I prepared all kinds of versions.
They do all kinds of things with the ordering of the LEDs on the screens.
Not again.
Okay.
Sorry?
Actually, this is not an accident.
Okay.
So what I do is the XY inverted, and that should be in here somewhere.
Where is the XY inverted?
You asked me to enlarge your letters, so I'm scrolling slowly.
It's called swapped.
What's this one?
Okay.
But do reflect on what I was about to do, that is to edit it in the code stored on the
chip.
That's not a problem.
But then I decouple the chip and start working on the chip, and I just lost my code, or I
don't know where it is on one of the 20 chips I have.
And now it's FO again, so that works.
But that's not a problem.
I frequently don't know where I have put my last version of the code, and Tony doesn't
support GitHub via the microcontroller.
That in fact would be very nice.
Okay.
Never enough.
Let's take more.
Okay.
Now it doesn't know it has more lets, so let's tell it.
Where's the code?
Stop it first.
Stop it.
Then that one.
Sorry?
Oh, that takes a lot of time.
You might do that for consistency, but downloading the live takes one minute.
So not for sure.
That's true.
But then you lose a bit of the essence of using Python.
The essence is you can quickly make a modification.
If I can afford one or two minutes, I might as well use a really compiled language and
spend that much time.
So yeah, you couldn't do it.
Okay.
So I could add one more display, but that's more of the same.
Let's not do that.
Go back to these things.
Yeah.
You saw that again loading the library from source is slow.
You can also use a faster chip.
If I take my fast chip, this one, and take that connection from it and use that one.
Tony stop again and recognize new chip, please.
Yes, it does.
This one even has a separate flash card, so I can store more files on it than if I want.
I can blink on it.
This loads the library quite a bit faster.
It doesn't have an onboard LID, so I blink a whole LCD screen.
It works too.
But sadly, I cannot use this target with the new pixels because it doesn't have the new
pixel library built into the Python version for this chip.
Sometimes you're just screwed.
But I can't, oh, it doesn't want that.
Sometimes when the communication goes wrong, Tony is very confused about what's happening.
You just have to restart the chip or maybe restart Tony or whatever you want.
I can do this one.
Now that will leave that.
I'll go to the sheets again.
I've compared a few target chips that you could use for this kind of work.
The TNC is what I just showed, very fast one, but then it costs 36, so this might be real.
36, maybe I've photographed you all.
It's quite expensive.
If you want to have lots of fun with things that are expendable, the ESP32 and the PyPico
are very good contenders, less than 10 euros and readily available everywhere.
For ESP32s, there are a lot of funny versions of it.
There's a watch with ESP32 in it, I don't know, my computer number.
In a previous situation, I did a demo with it, but it uses Wi-Fi and it has the habit
of working perfectly before you all walk in over tens of meters.
And then when you're all present with all your phones, the reach is reduced to five
centimeters.
That's Greek, havakom, demos.
These are other things.
Adorable camera has a built-in ESP32, can run micro-Python, and then you can transmit
the images over Wi-Fi, at least if you're not all present.
You all know these ones.
The BBC One bits, they can run micro-Python, sort of.
They cannot store files on the flash system, and they can run about 50 lines or so of Python.
So it's nice for a kindergarten Python course, but not for your work.
And this one, I sure hope I get it to work sometime.
It's a Kendrite.
It's down here.
It's quite powerful and also has neural network hardware on it.
But it uses some Chinese version of micro-Python, and Tony doesn't recognize it, so maybe it
works but I don't know how.
10 minutes left.
Thank you.
If you have questions, those are more important than the rest of my sheets, so interrupt me.
A few of those more interesting tips we saw are, in fact, not a pure micro-controller
or pure micro-processor, they are hybrids.
They have a micro-controller core, but an external ROM added, and in some cases even
external RAM.
That is overall a cheaper configuration because optimal, let's say, process parameter for
making micro-tips, flash and RAM, are quite different.
So you can make a cheaper, more effective, make a RAM chip, but you have only RAM cells
on it.
So for instance, the ESP32 doesn't have that much RAM on board, but it can use an external
coupled RAM chip as a buffer for it.
It caches the things, and then you suddenly have a few megabytes of RAM, which is more
actually, but it's a bit slower.
Not that much, but a bit slower.
Excuse me, can you make the slides fullscreen, please?
I will, if I get my cursor back.
Where's my cursor?
Yeah.
Oh, they'll publish the slides, so don't worry.
So then it's nice appearing, and you have the hybrid version in between.
When you work with this thing, RAM is very scarce.
So the more RAM you have, the better, especially if you're working with screen buffers or images
or things from a camera.
The thing is, when files are loaded by Michael Python, it first loads the source, then from
that builds intermediate representation.
That intermediate representation is smaller than the source, but the peak memory usage
is still the full source.
So I cannot load my library as one file on, let's say, an ESP32, because it doesn't have
enough RAM to load that peak amount.
It can load it in compiled form, but not a source form.
So what I do, I split it in a lot of small files, and one trick I often use is I have
a main file which imports all sub-files, and for, let's say, basic classes you must do
that, but for utility things like a driver for an LCD, I use a trampoline function.
It pretends to be the class, but it's a function, and when it's called, it loads the real sub-module,
so it's loaded only when it's needed, and then it calls that with all the arguments.
And such a trampoline takes maybe 50 bytes, while this full file could take a few kilobytes,
so that saves a lot of RAM and loading time.
All right, Stuart, can you get a version of Michael Python which only takes pre-compile
to save space on small machines?
Yeah, you sure can.
So when you really develop something, I think you should take a larger machine, and when
it's in production, take a smaller machine, use a pre-compiled version, yes, of course.
Can I get a question?
Oh, sorry, he asked whether using pre-compiled version saves RAM.
Yes, it does.
Whether you could have a smaller Michael Python program with complete Michael ports to save
space in the Michael Python program?
Yeah, but you still want to tweak with your own main code if you're developing.
If you have a finished product, then all things are different, but I think the main power
of Michael Python is that you can thinker with it at a late stadium.
If you have a finished product, indeed you can freeze it, but if you want that, how did
you develop it?
Presumably on a different processor with more RAM.
Let's think of it.
Limitations.
Yeah?
So we can use pre-compiled large libraries and put them on the chip, and then we can
thinker with our own code, but have the pre-compiled libraries, and is that something to do?
Yeah, indeed.
But there are a lot of pre-comp...
Oh, is it a good idea to have pre-compiled libraries incorporated in the Python interpreter
and then thinker with your own code?
Yeah, I think that's a good approach.
Indeed those libraries are stable, because if you must change in those libraries, you
don't have the source code, at least not on your target chip, and you're stuck in a much
slower development cycle.
So it's...
Well, if things are indeed stable, freeze them in the Michael Python interpreter.
If not, take a large chip and develop on that.
Five minutes left.
Well, you can really develop limitations.
Time-wise, if you're in the, let's say, clock cycles, time domain, if it must be that fast,
then even C or C++ won't do it.
You need hardware or Raspberry Pico Pios.
If you're in the tens or hundreds of cycles, you can use compiled language.
If you're in the thousands of cycles, you can use an interpretive language like Python.
To be concrete, driving those new pixels that requires microseconds timing, you cannot do
that in Python code.
In the Michael Python interpreter, they do it in C code, and that's built in.
Driving a server motor, a hobby server back and forth, that's milliseconds timing.
You can easily do it in Python, in Python source code.
There's a list of deviations from C Python.
You can read it.
They didn't bother me much, except that it doesn't support type hints.
I like type hints from my testing, so I must do the testing on my laptop.
You can test a lot of basic things, not on the small machine between your desktop.
When it's compiled, is it the same byte code as C Python?
When it's compiled, Michael Python intermediate code is different from C Python.
It has its own pre-compiler, which you can download and you can pre-compile it, but it's
different from the standard C Python.
Does Michael Python have the garbage collector?
You can bet it has, yes.
When you want to do really time-critical things, call the garbage collector and do it after
that.
You can be reasonably sure that it's called.
But if you want to do really time-critical, life-critical things, don't use Python.
Sorry.
Okay, I'll skip this one.
What is it good for?
Maybe not for volume production.
For that, you use compiled language.
But for anything that requires tinkering, exploration, lab setups, experiments, education,
it's really nice, too.
What is problems?
I'm always confused by my latest version of the source code is.
I changed what something on that ship, maybe it's on my PC or on GitHub, I don't know.
Where you use B port cannot supply a large current.
If you want things like these pixels to have a separate power supply, the terminology of
Tony with upload and download is reversed from what I think is normal, but have to use
it.
It's not a problem.
If you want to have your code saved from prying eyes, I think forget it.
The intermediate code can be back compiled so anyone can see into your code.
You have large invested interest in your code, maybe Python is not the way.
Then probably you want to make a large amount of products, so it's not the way anyway.
Okay, I did cover some things.
Take away.
Well, start tinkering.
That was a good idea.
Get the same hardware as you would use for an Arduino, get some micro piping cable board,
load it on it, it's five minutes work and start doing things.
Okay, well, if I did that demo, then those pixels would show questions.
But I think we're at times up anyway.
One minute.
One last question.
Yeah, where does it come from?
Micro python is a book of three he asked, well, I did codes come the pin and the machine.
Micro python is a common part and then a specific spot for specific chips and accessing a GPO
pin of a chip is very different from chips.
But it's a it's a that's a very shallow part.
Once you have that you can build a lot of things on top of that.
So the micro python distribution that I used here to compile, I must specify for which
target chip I compile and then it grabs the correct code.
Okay.
Thank you.
Thanks.
I like to order.
Will you be available outside for questions?
So water will be around for questions.
If you have questions on hesitate.
I hope for the smart watches we still have hope.