I'm going to turn it over to you.
Hello, everybody.
Welcome to the Python, the room of Fuzzdam. I'm really happy to
welcome all of you here and to welcome Mark for his talk and
introduction to async programming. Thanks for everyone
for coming. Also, so early for this talk that I'm really
looking forward to see with you.
Thank you for the introduction. It's really nice to see so many
people here on a Sunday morning at 9 o'clock. I'm really happy
about this. I wouldn't have expected so many people. I hope
this is going to be interesting for you. There is a lot of text
on these slides. I uploaded the slides to the website so you
don't have to write down everything and read everything.
There's a lot to talk about in async. So what I wanted to do is
give a short introduction to async and frame everything into
writing a telegram bot. Because that was the motivation behind
the talk and how I came to doing this. So a few words about
myself. I'm Mark. I'm from Düsseldorf in Germany. I've
been with Python for a very long time, since 1994. I'm a core
developer. I've done lots of work in the various organizations
around Python. So with your Python chair, for example, I was
on the board of the PSF. I'm a PSF fellow. And I've done lots
of work in that area. In my day job, I am a consulting CTO or
do senior architectures. Also do coaching a bit. So if you have
a need in that area, just ping me. So the motivation for the
talk is writing a telegram and a spam bot. Now, why do we have
to do that? We have a user group in Germany, the Python meeting
Düsseldorf, and we're using a telegram group to communicate.
And early last year, we started seeing lots of signups to that
group. Because it's a public group, anyone can just sign up
to that group. We started seeing lots of signups from strange
people. And the people then usually started to, you know,
send spam, send crypto, links, you know, link spam. Many of
those people were actually not people but bots, and they
scraped the contact info and started sending DMs to the
various members. So it was, you know, getting to a point where
it was not possible for us as admins to handle this anymore
because most of these people or bots, they were actually
signing up during the night so there was no one there to
handle these. And so the idea was to write a bot which
basically tries to, you know, check whether people are human,
check whether the signups are actually from people who know
Python. And that's what I did last year. So the idea was to
have a scalable bot because it needs to run 24-7. It also needs
to be very stable because, you know, at night no one is there
to basically restart it. We needed something that is low
resource because we wanted to have it on one of the VMs that
we have to run. And so we decided to look out for, you
know, a library that we could use. And there is a very nice
library called pyrogram which you can use for creating these
bots. It's LJPL3. It's fairly new. It's well documented and
it's actually maintained. So basically all the checks are
there. And we started to use that and we had great success
with it. It is an async library. So what is this
asynchronous programming? I'm going to go through the three
different models that you have for execution in Python. And
let's start with the synchronous execution. So what is synchronous
execution? Basically you write your program from top to
bottom. The Python interpreter then takes all the different
steps that you have in your program and runs them one by
one, one after the other. So there's no parallel processing
going on. Everything happens one after the other thing. If you
have to wait for I.O., for example, then the cord just sits
there. It doesn't do anything. And of course waiting is not
really very efficient. So what can you do about that if you
want to scale up? One way to scale up in Python is to use
threads. And probably many of you know about the gil. I'm
going to talk about that in a bit. But let's just mention
what threaded programming is. Threaded programming is where
the operating system basically assigns slices to your
application. And then each slice can run for a certain amount
of time. And then the operating system switches to the next
slice and the next thread. So everything is controlled by the
OS. This is a very nice and very elegant way to scale up. You
can use all the cores that you have in your CPU. You can, you
know, in the past you usually had multiple processes in the
servers and you could use those multiple processes as well.
There's one catch, though, with thread programming. Because
it's controlled by the OS and not by the application, so not
by Python, it is possible for two threads to try to access
the same object, let's say, or same memory area in your
application and do things on those memory areas. For
example, you know, take a list, append to it, delete from it,
and so on. And if two threads start doing that at the same
time, you can have clashes. And in order to prevent that,
because you don't want to have data loss, for example, you
have to put locks around these things to make everything
work. So there is a bit of extra work to be done there. You
have to consider how things work in the thread environment
and you have to put locks around areas that can be shared
between the different threads that you have. It is an
efficient use of resources. So this is actually something
that people try to get working. With Python, it's a bit
harder. And because it's a bit harder, some years ago,
async support was added to Python. So what is asynchronous?
Asynchronous is basically focusing on a single thread, on
a single core. It looks very much like a synchronous
program, except that whenever you do I.O., the application,
Python in that case, can then say, okay, I'm going to run
this function until I hit a spot where I have I.O., for
example, or I have to wait for something. And then I give
back control to something called an event loop. And that
event loop is then going to take, going to go through the
list of everything that is scheduled to be executed and
then just run the next thing that's on that list. And so
whenever you wait for I.O., you can tell the program, okay,
that's the thing that's going to be done with this part of
the application. And now I'm going to switch to a different
part and run that part. So that's a way to work around the
threading issues I just talked about. It's also a way to, you
know, write code that scales up very neatly, very fast. It's
a bit limited in terms of focusing on just one core. So
you, for example, you cannot use multiple cores that way, or
you can use multiple cores that way. And if you want to use
multiple cores, you can push work that is being done in the
application that's not running Python on these other cores.
That's certainly possible. But if you want to scale up, use
all the cores, then you basically have to use multiple
of these applications, run them in different processes, and
then use up all the cores that you have. There's one catch
with this. I mean, there's no free lunch, right? So all the
cores that you have to collaborate. Because it's
application-driven, all the parts that you have need to have
certain places where they say, okay, I'm going to give up
control back to the event loop at this point because I'm
waiting for something. Because Python cannot know that you're
trying to wait for something. And so you have to tell Python
that this is a good place to give up control. Now, why do
you want to do this? Because it's a good place to go. And this
slide is about the global interpreter lock. How many of
you know the global interpreter lock? Just a few. That's
interesting. So what Python does is it keeps a one big lock
around the Python virtual machine that executes the
Python bytecode. And it does this because it wants to
support multiple processes, sorry, multiple threads. But
it's not the same thing. So when Python was added, threading
was actually very new. Python is, you know, it's more than
30 years old now. So there's been a lot of development going
on since Python started. Because Guido wanted to start
supporting threading right from the beginning, he added this
global interpreter lock to make sure that the logic that's
inside Python is only used by one thread at any point in
the world. So what happens is the Python starts running
code, Python code in one thread, then reaches a certain
point, and then gives up control back to the OS and says, okay,
you can switch to a different thread now. But it does this
under the control of this global interpreter lock. So it makes
sure that no other thread is running Python at the moment.
So the other thread will have been waiting for the Python
thread to lock to get the lock. And then we'll start executing.
And this goes on, you know, for all the threads that you have
in your application. So in a multithreaded program that's
running Python, you can just have one thread execute Python
code at any point in time. And this is something that, of
course, is very scalable. It's also not a very big issue, as
some, you know, may tell you. Because if you're clever and you
put all the logic that you need to run on multiple cores or
multiple threads into parts of the program that don't need
Python, for example, if you're running machine learning and you
want to train a model, then you can just easily push off
something. And you can just run a code that doesn't need
Python. And that can very well run next to Python in another
thread. So that's certainly possible. But, of course, you
know, sometimes you don't have a chance to do that. And then you
need to look for other things. And this is where async becomes
very nice. So let's have a look at how threaded code executes
in Python. The image on the right there basically explains
how you can do that. So you have three threads. The orange
is Python running. Then the yellow is basically the thread,
the Python interpreter in those threads waiting for the Gil.
And then you have some waiting for IO that happens in between.
So if you look closely, you will see that it's not a very
efficient use here. Because there's lots of waiting, lots
of blue waiting for IO. Let's have a closer look at this.
So this again is the picture that I had on the other slide.
And I moved out all the waiting and all the execution. And if
you move all the execution together, you will see that only
one thread is running at any point in time. So the other
threads are basically just sitting there doing nothing.
Now, how can you work around this? You can use async
programming for this. And async programming has the need
feature that you can actually saturate a single core very
efficiently without doing too much work. So again, you have
the execution here. You don't have three threads. This is
just one thread that you have or one core. But you have three
tasks running in that one thread. And the different tasks,
they share the execution. And again, you have the orange
here executing Python. You have some waiting for IO in here
or could also be waiting for calculations to happen. And if
you move everything together, you will see that it's really
the thread, the core is saturated. So everything is
working out nicely. And it's very efficient. So how does
this work? How many of you know coroutines? Okay, about
like one-third. So a coroutine basically is very much like a
normal function except that it's possible to have certain
spots in the coroutine, in the function, where it says, okay,
at this point, you can give up control back to the caller of
that function. And this is essentially how async
programming works. You have something called an event loop.
The event loop calls these coroutines. The coroutine
executes until it hits one of these spots where you can give
up control. The function, the coroutine gives back control to
the event loop at that point. And then the event loop can
execute something else in your application. And then at a
later point, it comes back to that coroutine and continues
executing where it left off. In order to make that easy to
define and easy to use in Python, we have new keywords.
We have async dev, which is a way to define these
coroutines. And we have these await statements in Python,
which are basically places where the coroutine says, okay,
you can give up control and you can pass back control to the
event loop because I'm waiting for, let's say, I owe or for
longer running calculation that you want to do. And everything
around this, all the support for this is bundled in this
package called async I owe, which is part of the standard
library. So let's have a look at how this works in Python to
compare synchronous code and async code. So on the left, you
have a very simple function. You have a time sleep in there,
which is like a simulation for the I owe. So something, the
application needs to wait for something. And then you call
that function. And if you run this, the simple example, you
see that, you know, it starts executing, it starts working,
then it sleeps for two seconds, and then it's done, and then
it's the end of that function. Now, in the async case, it
works a bit differently. So what you do is you put the async
in front of the function, so you have to turn it into a
coroutine. And then inside that function, we use the await
statement to say, okay, at this point, I can give up control
back to the event loop. And so what happens here is that you
have a special function called async I owe sleep, which is a
way to, you know, wait for a certain amount of time in async.
But when waiting for these two seconds, you can actually
go back and you can execute something else. It's not
possible to use await and then time.sleep for this, because
time.sleep is actually a blocking function, right? It
doesn't give back control. So you have to make sure that
whatever you use with await is actually a coroutine so that
it can pass back control to your coroutine that's calling
this coroutine. And this is what I meant with everything has
to collaborate. If you have places in your application that
are not compatible with async, you have to be careful and you
have to use certain work arounds to make it happen. So the
next thing is that, you know, now you have a coroutine,
calling the coroutine will do nothing. Basically, all that
happens is you get back a coroutine object. So it doesn't
run. So in order to run it, you have to actually start the
coroutine inside the event loop. And this is what async I O
dot run does at the very bottom. And this, if you look at
it, it takes, it defines two tasks. So basically two
instances of that coroutine. Puts them into this tuple. The
tuple is passed to this async I O gather, which is a special
function I'm going to come to in one of the next slides. It
basically just takes the coroutines, creates tasks
objects, and then executes them until all of them are done.
And then passes back control. So this is how you would run
an async application. I ran through these so I can basically
just skip these. So what are the things in the async I O
package module? A very important function is this async
I O run. This is basically the function that needs to be
called in order to set up the event loop, to run everything in
that event loop. You typically just have one of these calls in
your application. Basically just starting the event loop and
then running anything that's being scheduled. Then you have
this gather function. Gather is, like I already mentioned,
it's a function where you can pass in coroutines or tasks.
And then it runs all of these tasks until completion and then
it returns. You also have a couple of functions down here
for waiting for certain things. So sometimes in an application
you need to synchronize between various different parts. So
there are some handy functions for this as well. Now what is
this task object I keep mentioning? Task objects are
basically just coroutine calls that are being scheduled. And
it's a way for the event loop to manage everything that happens
in the event loop. So whenever something is scheduled to be
run, you create a task object. And this is done behind the
scenes for you. You don't have to create these objects
yourself. In fact, you should not create these objects
yourself. You should always use one of the functions for this,
like this create task that you have down here. And then these
task objects go into the event loop, are run, and everything
happens for you. There are also some query functions down here
if you're interested in what's currently scheduled on the
event loop. You can have a look at the documentation for those.
So how does this event loop work? It's basically just a way
just to do the same kind of management as the OS is doing
for threads, except that it's done in Python. And the
asyncio package manages one of these event loops. Now event
loops can actually be defined by multiple different libraries.
But what's important is that there should only be one event
loop per thread. So you can have multiple threads, of course,
also run. Then again, you hit the same kind of roadblock as
you've seen with the gil. But there might be ways in your
application to make use of that. So that would be possible as
well. Typically what you have in the async program is you just
have a single thread. And so you just call this run function
once. Now, I mentioned blocking code. So blocking code basically
is code that doesn't collaborate with this async logic. And you
have that quite often in Python. For example, let's say you're
using one of the database modules, not one of the async
modules, but the regular ones. Those will all be synchronous.
So you call, let's say, an execute to run some SQL. And
that will actually wait until the database comes back with
the results. So in order to run this kind of code in an async
application, you have to use special functions. There's a
very nice function called asyncio2thread, which was
added in Python 3.9, which makes this easy. So what these
functions do is they spin up a thread in your async
application, run the code inside that thread, and then pass back
control via the threading logic to your event loop. So you can
still run synchronous code because the synchronous code is
most likely going to give up the gil. For example, if you have
a good database module, then when you execute something,
typically what these database modules do is they give back
control to other threads running Python code because they're
just running C code at that time. So this is a way to make
everything work together. And of course, there's lots more.
I'm not going to talk about these things because I don't
have enough time for that. In fact, I'm already almost out
of time, so I have to speed up a bit. Let's just do a very
quick view, overview of what's in the async ecosystem. So of
course, we have the async IO standard library package. We
have event loops inside the async IO package. If you want
fast loops, then you can use UV loop, which is the faster
implementation, speeds up your async by almost four times.
You can also have a look at other stacks that implement
event loops, like trio, for example, or you can use the
package any IO, which abstracts these things. So you can use
async IO loops underneath in your application when using any
IO and in abstracts away other details. Now, there's a rather
large system of modules and packages around the async world
in Python. Many of these are grouped under the AIO libs. So
if you go to GitHub to that URL, then you will find lots of
examples there. There are database packages there. There
are things for doing HTTP DNS and so on. Something to watch
out is the database modules typically don't support
transactions, which can be a bummer sometimes. At the
higher level, you have, of course, web frameworks again,
because, you know, everyone loves web frameworks. And of
course, you have API frameworks. The most popular one right
now is fast API for doing the rest APIs, and then
strawberries is coming very strongly as a GraphQL server.
Both operate async. Even Django does or starts is starting
to do async right now. It's not fully there yet. If you're
using Flask for synchronous code, then you might want to
look at a quart, which is like an async implementation using
a similar API. And the most famous one probably in the
async space is tornado, which some of you may know. It's
very fast. Right. So let's go back to the bot. If you want
to see the bot code, it's on GitHub. Just search for
eugenics telegram and then you'll find it. How does it
work? Very easy. You just subclass the client of that
package. You do some configuration. You do some
observability. So logging for things. I'm lazy. So I just
put all the admin messages into another telegram chat that I
can manage so I can see what's happening without having to go
to the server. Because we actually want to catch all the
messages of these people signing up to the telegram
group, and not just people who want to run bot commands,
slash something. We have to use the catch all in here. And
that's also why we need something that's very scalable
because literally the bot sees all the messages that go into
that group and it has to handle all these messages. And then
what you do is basically you just do these awaits whenever
you have to do I.O. And if you look at it, it looks very
much like synchronous code, right? Except that you have
these awaits in front of certain things. Wherever something
happens where you need to do some I.O., you put the await
in front of it. And then everything else looks very
natural. Looks like a very much like a synchronous program.
So what are the results of doing this? Writing this bot,
it's actually helped us a lot. We've had over almost 800
spam signups since April 2022 when we started to use it. And
this has, I mean, this is one part, this is just the admin
part that saved us a lot of work. But of course, you know,
every single signup would have caused spam messages. And so
that was very successful. So the time spent on actually
writing things was well invested and basically mission
accomplished. So what's the main takeaway of the talk?
I think it's great. And give it a try if you can. Thank you
for your attention. Thank you for your attention.
Thank you, Mark. Thanks, everyone, for attending this
talk. Don't hesitate to reach to Mark and Ray if you have
any questions or want to discuss this further. Thanks a
lot. Thank you. Thank you very much for coming. Let me just
show you a picture. Excellent.