Let's welcome Pedro Halanda for his talk on DuckDB and Magnificent Snake Duck.
Yeah, you guys can be surprised at all.
Anything you can find as a rubber duck these days, you know.
All right, so I'm Pedro Halanda.
I am one of the main contributors of the DuckDB projects, which is an open source database
system.
I'm the COO of DuckDB Labs.
And today I'm going to be talking a little bit about how DuckDB can bring analytical
SQL power directly into your Python shell.
So to give you a little bit of an idea of how these talks look like, I'm going to start
with what is DuckDB?
So I'm here talking about one more database system.
I'm going to motivate you guys that we actually needed to do one more database system.
The other ones didn't solve the problems we had.
And then I'm going to go over the main characteristics of DuckDB.
So what actually makes it special?
Then I'm going to go over DuckDB Python line, so how DuckDB integrates in the Python ecosystem.
I'm going to do a little demo.
The basic idea is that we're going to use the infamous New York City taxi data sets.
And we're going to try to do some estimation of fair costs.
And we're going to use DuckDB pandas and PySpark just to see a couple of the differences.
Of the things I'm going to be talking over.
And then some summary of the talk.
So what is DuckDB?
Well, DuckDB was actually born at CWI, which is the Research Center of Mathematics and
Computer Science in the Netherlands.
And what we actually had there is that a lot of the projects, the PhDs in the projects,
the master projects, they are very data sciencey.
So usually you have a data science problem and you want to throw a database management
system at a data science problem because you're handling data.
So initially we're like, okay, we can probably use a database server, use a database connection,
and then just transfer the data from the relational database to your Python terminal, for example,
right?
Like where your analytical tools are.
And it turns out that's quite a bad idea because you are transferring a lot of data.
So that's pretty costly.
And then we're like, okay, this is really not solving our problem.
Can we draw inspiration from somewhere else?
And then of course there are SQLites, the most famous database out there, at least the
most used one.
And it has a quite a nice property, which is being an embedded database system.
Being an embedded database system, it means it can run inside your Python process.
So you can eliminate this data transfer cost.
SQLite comes with one design decision that is a transactional database.
So it's actually super optimized for small updates, but it's not really optimized for
analytics.
So we kind of wanted to use SQLites in terms of being easy to use and eliminating this
data transfer cost, but focusing on analytical queries.
And that's kind of how the code was born, and that's also why we frame it as a SQLite
for analytics.
It also has a very simple installation.
So if you think about Python, it's just a big solve and you're good.
Since it's embedded, there's no server management.
So let's say you just want to, I don't know, query a per K file, two lines of code you
can already query it.
There's no starting of server.
There's no schema creation.
The schema is inferred from the object.
So it's very easy, very fast.
And we also really focus on this fast transfer between analytical languages.
And there are tools like in Python and R to DuckDB.
DuckDB is currently in pre-release.
I think the last version we released was 0.6, 0.7 is coming up soon.
In the web page, there's a little bit more details about all the things that are in each
release.
All right.
So I'm going to go over some of the main characteristics of DuckDB, particularly the color data storage,
a little bit about compression.
I'm going to talk about vectorized execution.
So these are all like core database stuff.
Actually talking about vectorized execution engine, it's going to be difficult because
Professor Bong is here and he actually created that.
So I'll try to do it correctly.
A little bit about intimate corruptimization, parallelism and beyond memory execution.
So color data storage.
Well, there's basically two ways that you can do it.
One is a row store, a scan store.
As an example, row store, we have SQLites.
And the whole thing about the whole idea is that you're storing your data consecutively
in memory per row.
So that basically means that if you want to fetch a row, that's very cheap because it's
contiguous in memory.
However, you always have to fetch all the columns.
So analytical queries usually you have very wide tables, but you just want to really get
a couple of these columns.
So what if you only want to use a field?
So in this example, what if you just are interested in the price of a product, but not the stores
they sold, right?
In a column store, you actually have your layouts that the data of the column is consecutively
in memory.
So if you want to access just a couple columns, you can actually have immense savings on disk
I.O. and memory bandwidth.
So that's why this type of format is really optimized for analytics.
So to give you a more concrete example, let's say that we have a one terabyte table with
100 columns.
For simplicity, let's say all the columns have the same size.
And we just require five columns of the table in our analytical queries.
So in a row store like SQLites, reading this whole table, if you have a disk with around
100 megabytes per second, it will take you three hours.
If you were using a column store model, which is what Pandas and Ducktivitas, for example,
reading these five columns from disk takes you eight minutes.
So there's a huge improvement by just setting up the correct storage formats for your workload.
Compression, well, I'm not going to go into a lot of detail about the compression algorithms
that we implement in Ducktivi.
But what I can tell you is because of having a column store, you're going to have your
data from your column continuously in memory, which gives you a very good advantage to compress
units, because usually the data from the same column is somewhat similar.
So you can apply cool things like RLE, FSSC, and CHIMP for floating point numbers, FSSC
for strings.
So you can start applying all these algorithms and really decrease the size of your data.
So in this table here, we actually have, I think this is from one year ago, one year
and a half, 0.2.8 from Ducktivi.
We had no compression at that point.
And then a year and a half later, we actually managed to implement all these things which
got us five times better compression line 19, for example, 3.18 better compression in
the taxi data set that I'm going to be using later.
And why is compression so important?
Well, if we go back again to the same example where we're reading our five columns and it
was causing us to read them from disk eight minutes because of the storage formats, if
we compress these columns, we suddenly don't have to read 50 gigabytes anymore, right?
You read less.
And then of course, you apply the best case from what I showed you from the last table,
five times.
The RLE increases the cost to one minute and 40 seconds.
So execution.
Well, there's three ways of doing query execution.
There's actually one more, but it's not in the slides.
But SQLite uses a top-order time processing, which means that you process one row at a
time.
Pandas uses column-at-a-time processing, which means that you process one column at a time.
Inductive B uses kind of like a mix of the both, which is a technique developed by Peter,
the vectorized processing where you process batches of a column at a time.
So basically, the top-order time model from SQLite, it was optimized for a time where
computers didn't have a lot of memory.
There was low memory to be used because you only need to really keep one row in memory
throughout your whole query plan.
So the memory was expensive.
That's what you could do.
But this comes with a high CPU overhead per tuple because you constantly resetting your
cache.
You don't have any cache-conscious algorithm running that piece of data up to the production
of the query results.
If you go to the column at a time, which is what Pandas uses, this already brings better
CPU utilization.
It allows for SIMD.
But it comes with the cost of materializing large intermediates in memory.
It basically means that you need the whole column in memory at that point to process
for that operator.
And of course, the intermediates can be gigabytes each.
So that's pretty problematic when the data sizes are large.
And that's why you see, for example, that Pandas, if your data doesn't fit in memory,
what does it happen?
It crashes.
And then if you go to the vectorized query processing, it's actually optimized for CPU
cache locality.
You can see the instructions, pipelining.
And the whole idea is that your intermediates are actually going to fit here in a L1 cache.
So basically, you're going to be paying this latency of 100 milliseconds to be accessing
your data throughout your query plan instead of paying the latency of a memory, which is
also the case of a column database, which is 100 milliseconds.
It seems like a small difference.
But when you're constantly executing this, this really becomes a bottleneck.
And so end-to-end query optimization is, of course, something that we have in DuckDB.
So we have stuff like expression rewriting, join ordering, sub-query flattening, filtering
and projection pushdown, which is a bit more simple, but it's extremely important and brings
a huge difference in the cost of a query.
So here's an example of a projection pushdown.
Let's say you have a table with five columns, A, B, C, D, E. And you want to run a query.
That's pretty small.
The query is like it selects minimum from column A, where there's a filtering column
A saying the column A is bigger than zero, and you group by B. So the whole point of
the query is that you're only using two columns off the table.
So what the DuckDB optimizer will do is like, OK, in the scanner, I know I don't need all
the columns.
I just need NMB.
And you just don't have to read the other ones.
If you do the same one in pandas, for example, you can apply your filter, and then you have
the filter to group by the aggregator.
But at the time you're doing this filter, you're still filtering all the other columns
you're not going to be using your query.
Of course, you can manually make this optimization.
But it's pretty nice that the database system can do that for you.
Of course, DuckDB also has automatic parallelism and beyond memory execution.
So DuckDB has parallel versions of most of its operators.
I think all of our scanners, including with insertion, all your preservation of parallelized
now, aggregations, joins, pandas, for example, only supports single-threaded execution.
We all have pretty good laptops these days, right?
So it's a shame if you cannot really take advantage of parallelism.
And DuckDB, again, supports the execution of data that does not fit in memory.
It's kind of the never-give-up, never-surrender approach.
It's like, we're going to execute this query.
We try to always have graceful degradation also, that it just doesn't suddenly crash
the performance.
And the whole goal is really to never crash and always execute the query.
All right.
So a little bit about DuckDB in the Python lens.
Basically we have an API.
It's a DB API, it's a.org compliant.
So very similar to what SQLite has, for example, where you can create a connection and you
can start executing queries.
But we also wanted to have something similar to the DataFrame API that still could, people
that come from pandas, for example, could still have something familiar to work on.
So here in this example, you can also create a connection.
You can create this relation, which kind of looks like a DataFrame.
It's just pointing to a table.
You can do a show to inspect what the table is inside, and you can apply, for example,
these chaining operators, right?
Like a filter, a projection.
So in the end, this is all lazily executed.
And this also allows you to take advantage of the optimizer of DuckDB, even if you do
the chaining operations.
Of course, I talked to you about memory transfer.
So we were very careful as well into being very integrated with these very common libraries
in Python.
So with pandas and PyArrow, for example, what we actually do is that in the end, for pandas,
the columns are usually not PyArrows, which turns out they are C, vectors, which turns
out it's also kind of what we use.
So with a little bit of makeup in the metadata, we can just directly read them.
And they're all in the same process, right?
So we have access to that piece of memory, which in the end means that you can actually
access the data from pandas in DuckDB without paying any transfer costs, at least constant
transfer costs just for doing the metadata makeup, let's say.
And there's the same thing with PyArrow.
We also have what we call zero copy.
So we can read error objects and output error objects without any extra cost.
With NumPy, we also support SQL, and in IBIS, we're actually the default backend from them,
I think, since six months ago.
A little bit of usage.
So as you can see, this is our PyPy download count.
The Python library is actually our most downloaded API.
We have APIs for all sorts of languages.
And you can see that in the last month, we had like $900,000.
So there are a lot of people that are trying out and using DuckDB in their Python scripts.
So now is the demo time.
We got this.
All right.
This looks like you can see.
So this is just installing DuckDB, PySpark, and getting our yellow trip data set.
I executed this already.
Just importing the stuff we're going to be using.
And here is just getting a connection from DuckDB, creating a relation that's just, okay,
we're going to, as a parquet file, DuckDB can read parquet files, and then you can just
print to inspect what's out there.
So if we run this, we can see, okay, these are the columns we have.
We have vendor ID, we have pickup dates, time, passenger counts, you have the types of the
columns.
You can also have a little result preview to have an idea of what it looks like.
So I think this data set has about like 20 columns maybe.
And there's just information about the taxi rides in New York in 2016.
And then you can also, for example, run a simple query here.
I'm just doing like accounts to know how many tuples are there.
And we have about 10 million tuples on this data set.
All right.
So this function here is just to do a little bit of benchmarking coming from academia.
We do have to do something that's kind of fair, I guess.
So I run just five times and take the median time of everything.
And then this is actually where our demo starts.
So we start off with a data frame.
So Pandas can also read parquet files.
And the whole thing about DuckDB, again, is that it's not here as a replacement for Pandas.
This is not what I'm trying to sell, but it's something that can work together with Pandas.
So the cool thing is that we can, again, read and output data frames without any extra cost.
So let's say that in the query here, we're just getting the passenger counts.
Then the average trip amounts of trips that had a short distance, right?
And the group by passengers, by the number of passengers.
So what we want to know is for short trips, does the amount of tip matters by the number
of passengers in that rides?
And what you can see here is that you can, again, read from the data frame.
That's what we're doing.
And we just have to use the data frame name in our SQL query.
And if you call.df from the query results, you also output your data frame.
And it's pretty cool because the data frames have these plot bars, they have plotting capabilities
that DuckDB doesn't have, and you can get easily a very nice chart.
So you see here, apparently, there's some dirty data because people are getting tips
when they don't have anyone in their rides.
Not sure what that is.
But apparently, if you have more people 7 to 9, maybe the more expensive cars, you get
a higher tip.
And you can do the same thing in Pandas, of course, right?
So in Pandas you don't have SQL, you're going to have to use their own language to do the
group by, the average, and you can directly use the plots.
And the whole point here is to show the different execution time.
Like now we're waiting.
Okay, so it took a second.
And DuckDB took 0.2, so this is like a 5x, right?
0.25, so like 4x.
And you also have to consider that we're using not a very beefy machine, right?
This is a Colab machine.
If you had more cores, this difference would also be bigger.
And then I added Spark for fun.
So actually, Spark can also read data frames, but it crashes out of memory in my Colab machine,
so I had to give up on that and read directly from Parquet files.
But it does output it as a data frame.
I think we're going to have to wait a little bit.
But as me, it's best.
So of course Spark is not designed for small data sets, but turns out there are a lot of
use cases where you use small data sets.
It's still going.
It's warming up a little bit.
It's good for the winter.
It produces some energy, I think.
All right.
Okay.
So it took two seconds, 2.2 seconds.
The extra execution, and that's already like what?
More than two times what Pandas was.
So yeah.
Anyway, for the demo, of course, I showed you something that's fairly simple.
Can you do actually very complicated things?
Maybe not very complicated, but more complicated.
So here I'm not really going to go over the query, but the whole idea is that we can just
like for example use DuckDB to run a linear regression, right?
So can we predict, can we estimate the fare with the trip distance?
And turns out you can just calculate the alpha and beta with not such a crazy query, right?
And then you can again export it to Pandas, and you have a very nice figure there.
So you can really combine these two to get the best out of both.
All right.
That was a demo.
Summary.
Oh, that's my last slide.
Very good.
So yeah, DuckDB is an embedded database system.
Again it's completely open source.
It is under the MIT license.
Since it came from academia, this is something that we're always worried about.
It's to also give it back to everyone because it was initially funded by taxpayers money
so everyone can use it.
100% of what we do is actually open source.
There's nothing that's closed source.
It's designed for analytical queries.
So data analysis, data science has binding for many languages.
So of course I'm at the Python dev room.
I'm talking about Python.
But we have R, Java.
Turns out that Java is one of our most downloaded APIs.
So I guess that's an interesting sign.
JavaScript and a bunch of others.
It has very tight integrations with the Python ecosystem.
Again the whole idea is that you eliminate transfer costs, implement the database in
relation to APIs.
The relation to API again is this more data frame like.
It has full SQL support.
So anything you can imagine like window functions or whatnot, you can just express them using
DuckDB.
And that's it.
Thank you very much for paying attention.
Happy to answer questions.
Thank you, we have five minutes for questions.
You mentioned beyond memory execution and that it tries not to degrade as much.
Can you shine a little bit more light on what happens under the hood and how much degradation
happens?
Of course I think there's only the ordering operator that actually does that.
We have Lawrence that's doing his PTC.
So there's a lot of operators that need to do research to be developed.
That's more of a goal than something that actually happens now.
But the whole goal is that you really don't have this sudden spike in the future.
But there's research going on in the future that will be more to be shared for sure.
Thank you very much for the talk and it's very exciting to see such a powerful tool.
I'm working usually with data warehouses and I saw on the website that you do not recommend
using this with data warehouses.
I would like to know why.
So of course there's no one solution for our problems.
There are cases that data warehouses are very good fits.
It turns out that for data science, for example, which is kind of what we preach the most,
they're usually not good because then you fall back to the senior data outside your
database system.
You're not really going to be running your Python codes inside the system.
You can do that for UDS, for example, but they are messy.
They're a bit nasty.
So you want really to have it embedded in your Python process so you completely eliminate
the data transfer costs.
Because usually what you do is like, okay, I have a table, 10 columns, I'm going over
four columns but I'm really hitting, reading like huge chunks of it.
So that's a bottleneck we try to eliminate.
How do you handle updates?
Yeah, although we are in the Lidical database system, we do do updates.
So Mark, I don't know where he is, but he's there.
He developed a MVCC algorithm for OLAF.
So we have same asset transaction capabilities that you would expect from a transactional
database.
Of course, if you have a transaction workloads, you should still go for Postgres or SQLIs
or a database that handles this type of transactions.
But Mark has developed like a full-on algorithm to handle updates completely.
Yeah?
How do you compare to Vertica?
Good question, I think in terms of analytical queries, TPCA is probably similar performance.
But then again, the whole point is that if you go again for the Python process, the data
transfer costs will take most of the time there.
And then it's really catered for this type of scenario, the embedded scenario.
We have one minute left for one more question.
Yeah, I actually have a repo somewhere for a bunch of examples as well.
I'm very happy to share it.
I don't know where I'll post it.
Ah, there's only the first one thing, I guess.
All right.
All right, thank you a lot, Pedro.
Thanks a lot.
Thank you very much.
Any other questions or comments?