I'm here to talk to you about graphics programming in Python on an embedded microcontroller,
which is hilarious because I'm none of these things, I'm not a Python programmer, I'm
not an embedded programmer, so we'll see how this goes.
It's for that reason I just, you know, I can't emphasise enough this part of the talk description,
this is not an instructional talk, this is just what I did.
So there's some background, EMF camp is this weekend camping festival for hackers and makers,
and it's in a similar vein to the Chaos Communication camp and the Dutch Hacker Festival, you know,
there's robots and lasers and geodesic domes and things, it's great fun if you get the
opportunity to go, I highly recommend it.
And it's a bit of a tradition of these style of events to give the attendees electronic
event badges, and the aim of these is to give attendees opportunity to play with some hardware
that they might not have come across before.
These are the two most recent badges from EMF camp, the one on the left here.
If I told you they had, they put a SIM card on it and a GSM modem and then they set up
an on-site cell phone network, you'll understand why it's made to look like a Nokia N-Gage,
but it's got all of the usual peripherals and sensors and things on there as well like
accelerometers and humidity and temperature and things, and because it runs micro Python
it allows people to easily get started with experimenting with that kind of hardware.
The one on the right there is the newest one, these photographs aren't to scale by the way,
let me just hold them up for comparison, the newest one is much smaller.
The reasons for that, you might guess, is because of the silicon shortage that's been
caused by fire, flood and plague, as you might expect, but it's still a lovely device.
The one on the left here you can see, you might recognise this as a version of the settlers
of Kirtan, I spent a lot of time trying to isolate small parts of the screen to redraw
because the update speed on that screen was so slow, it was almost unusable for anything
in real time, so when I got my hands on the new one this year I obviously wanted to see
what this one could do.
And so the first thing I wanted to do was to just try and blitter full screen pixels
to the device using the display driver directly, in this talk about 70 milliseconds, which
is already orders of magnitude faster than the old badge.
If I draw to an off screen buffer instead, that's way faster, but if you're doing that
then you have to get into the business of implementing your own drawing functions for
primitives and I didn't really want to do that.
That is ominous foreshadowing by the way.
But I did discover that micro Python has this frame buffer module which provides you with
an off screen frame buffer and also some drawing functions, which is great.
So 41 milliseconds, that was a fair compromise, that's a good start.
Now I've got a baseline for how fast I can draw to the screen.
So obviously what this is about is drawing 3D things to the screen of this device, and
so this is just here to, in case you don't know, this is basically, I guess this is 3D
rasterisation 101, this is like the minimum we have to do in order to get 3D points onto
the screen.
We start with our vertex coordinates and then that's multiplied by the model matrix to get
into world space and then you multiply that by the view matrix to get the view space and
then by the projection matrix to get the clip space and then the clip space allows you to
see which vertices will be clipped by the edges of the screen or not.
So then once we know we've got the list of vertices we want to render, then we can do
the perspective division to bring that into normalised device coordinate space or NDC space.
The perspective division is just the part that makes the further away points closer
together, so it gives you that illusion of 3D.
And then we've got to convert the normalised device coordinates which are between minus
one and one to screen space which is like our pixel coordinates.
And so when I was doing this, to render these eight points on the screen from a cube, it
wasn't too bad, 53 seconds and then if you join those up to create your cube wireframe
it's not that much slower, there's 12 triangles there obviously.
The next step is to then start filling in these triangles, you want to draw solid shapes
after all.
Annoyingly there's no method or no function for doing that in the frame buff module for
micro Python.
There is in the display driver but as I mentioned, using the display driver directly is much
slower because we're making many more calls to the hardware and we're setting pins high
and low and stuff for every time we want to draw something.
We just want to do that once when we blip the whole thing to the screen.
And yeah, so frame buff doesn't provide a polygon or polygon fill method and so I do
have to get into the business of writing these sort of functions myself after all.
So yeah, the display driver itself does have these methods, so obviously that's the first
place I looked for implementation clues, they have a polygon and a fill polygon method.
Only obviously there are problems with it and it's a little bit rubbish.
Here's the figure on the left there is just using the outline polygon method and then
the second one here is where I've tried to draw a filled polygon over the top of the
wire frame polygon and you can see it just doesn't quite match up.
And so reading the code, there is, it seems to be implementing quite a well known or well
documented fill polygon method and there's a link to the website where this algorithm
is described.
And that also supplies a reference implementation so I was able to copy the reference implementation
to see if the display driver's implementation was different.
And it isn't, it's exactly the same, it looks like the display driver has inherited the
same problems that were in the reference implementation.
You'll notice that it's not only incorrect on this side but the left edge here is completely
different to this edge here, so it's over drawing on this side and not drawing enough
on that side.
A lot of the problems with it were sort of like rounding errors and like floating point
to integer truncation and that sort of thing which I managed to mostly fix except for this
really annoying pixel down here that I just couldn't get.
And when I submitted, because I wanted to submit like this enhancement to the frame
with module upstream to the project and so we spent a few days scratching our heads over
this to try and figure out what we could do.
Initially we proposed just drawing the outline again on top of the fill polygon just to sweep
it under the rug but eventually we managed to figure out a much better way of doing it.
We just tried to detect when these stray pixels were going to happen and then fill them in
explicitly instead of letting the algorithm do it.
Oh yeah, it's pretty obvious that the algorithm I think was developed by a physicist or a
mathematician because in the article that describes the algorithm it says, and I'm quoting
here, the detecting points on the polygon edge will deliver unpredictable results but
that is quote, not generally a problem because quote, the edge of the polygon is infinitely
thin.
My polygons have an edge of one pixel so this is obviously why we had to fix the problems
with it.
Anyway, now we can draw arbitrary polygons to the screen.
Let's see what that looks like.
This is the cube here again which is basically the hello world of 3D graphics programming.
And it seemed to work pretty well, 66 milliseconds there but you can see on the left hand screen
shot there, that's not the inside, it looks like you're looking at the inside of the cube
but it's just because we are drawing the back face of the back of the cube on top of the
front face of the front of the cube.
As part of this 3D rasterization process you've now got to do back face culling which is more
maths added on to that pipeline.
You've got to calculate the normal vector of the face which is the direction the face
is facing and then compute the dot product of that with the direction you're looking
so that you can know if the triangle is facing you or not and then just don't bother drawing
the ones that aren't facing you.
But yeah, it's just more maths so it adds more time.
And yeah, I get the occasional really long frame and that coincides with a garbage collection.
I guess we'll talk a bit more about that in a bit.
So there's some really low hanging fruit things we can do to improve the performance initially
which basically amounts to being smarter about the algorithms we use.
We pre-calculate the normals instead of calculating them every frame which for a static model
like this makes total sense.
And yeah, avoid doing the perspective division if we can help it because it's like part of
the matrix multiplication process and usually it's a no-op unless you're multiplying it
by the perspective matrix and only then is it doing something.
So we can just avoid doing those divisions at all on every vertex, in every face, in
every frame.
That's quite a lot of time saved.
But it does mean I can add more things to it and make it do extra work like you add
a rudimentary lighting model and make the cube nice looking by adding shading and whatnot.
What I'm trying to do basically is to keep the rendering time below 100 milliseconds
as well because that seems like a good target to have.
If I can do that, then I get a reasonable performance of 10 frames per second.
So this is, although this works well, that's within that target, it's close to that target.
So I want to try something a bit more complex.
So I download a model of the industry standard T-pop and try and render that.
This is about 240 faces, 240 triangles, and this obviously completely destroyed my 100
millisecond time limit.
So I've got to think of more ways to make this faster.
And the obvious way is to rewrite all of the hottest math functions in C as a micro Python
native module.
The two ones that are called the most often are the vector matrix multiplying method and
the dot product method.
And you can see that more than cuts the time in half.
And with the success of that, it's pretty clear I should rewrite all of the maths in
C. Because if I've got the bonnet up, I might as well.
But that brings the time right down to a glorious, glorious, glorious six frames per second.
But yeah, as a general strategy, if you find yourself calling a method, you know, 1200
times a frame, it's probably a good target to be pushed down into the native layer.
So yeah, a note on writing native code for micro Python.
There's really two ways of doing it.
There's the what is called the external C modules, which is basically C code that you
write that is a module exposed to the Python runtime.
Those are compiled directly into the firmware, which is a bit suboptimal because it would
be nice if I didn't require other people who have these devices to reflash the firmware
every time I change this program.
So the other way of doing it is to write what they call a native module, which allows your
application to supply native code as an MPY file, and then that can be dynamically loaded
by your application at runtime, which is a much nicer way of doing it.
Obviously that's what I wanted to do.
But I did come across problems.
When I tried to build the native code, because I used a floating point division in there
for the perspective division step of the pipeline, I got this problem, which is a linker error
from the Espressiv's tool chain for the ESP32.
I'd love to know why this happens.
And if anyone from Espressiv is here, I'd love to know if it's fixed in the newer version
as well.
But it seems like it can't link this software implementation of floating point division.
So obviously what I did was I downloaded the source for the tool chain and found the assembly
implementation of this method to add into my project, which also didn't work.
The micro Python build system wasn't prepared to accept that, but that was an easy fix.
And that was actually the first change I got accepted into micro Python.
They were very good.
They're very good at, in my experience, they're very good at accepting patches.
And then once I got that building, it just caused my application to crash.
I'm not sure why this happens, but there seems to be like a reference to the native stuff
that gets collected erroneously by the garbage collection.
And I spent a lot of time trying to reduce my object allocations in the frames, but all
that did was just push out the crash to further in the future.
So I had to settle for compiling my maths functions directly into the firmware.
There are some other things I did to try and make it faster.
The big one is trying to reduce object associations.
This is super costly in Python.
And wherever you can, preallocate lists and arrays and things and then just reuse them.
I initially wanted to have a lot of my classes to be totally immutable, as a good programmer
that I am.
But they just totally wasn't feasible.
So I just, you know, you just have to mutate when you do calculations on your vertices,
just mutate one of the operands and send it back that way.
You can also, the other thing I found that saved some time was reducing the amount of
times that we cross from Python into native code and back again.
I found I was doing lots of the same operation to vertices and matrices.
So if I could just send them all as one batch in a single function call into the native
side, then that made it perform a lot quicker.
I think there's a lot of function and stack manipulation overhead there that you save.
So pass arrays and not lists into the native functions as well.
Especially for this kind of stuff where we know the data that we're passing are floats
or whatever.
You know ahead of time what type is in your array, which means you can make some assumptions
that micro Python can't make.
And when you manipulate the data objects in the native side, you can skip a bunch of type
save stuff.
You can just write directly to the data structure, which is useful.
And also, this won't surprise me as well.
Well, I don't know if it's surprising.
Maybe it's obvious to people who are veteran Pythonistas, but I didn't expect the libc
q sort function to be so much faster than the sort function in Python, but I was, if
you look at this picture here, you can see that some parts of the teapot are drawn on
top of, that should be occluded, drawn on top of the body of the teapot.
So what I had to do was z sort the faces so that we draw the faces from back to front.
And that's what I was doing, using the list sort method for here.
But just like implementing this face sorting as a native function as well, as it says there,
it's 100 times faster.
And the other thing that made a measurable difference as well was locally caching object
references in your functions as well.
So instead of, if you're using an object value more than once, instead of doing self foo,
self foo, self foo, just create a local reference, a local variable in the function and use that
instead.
So there's some dereferencing overhead there that is quite significant that we're saving.
And so after applying all of this sort of stuff, this is the final result, or the result
so far.
I'm pretty happy with it.
Getting the teapot model down to under 100 milliseconds per frame was really pleasing.
And yeah, I'm pretty happy with the performance.
So what can this be used for?
Honestly, this was just a fun way to spend a few weekends after the festival had happened.
But it seems to be performing enough where you could do some kind of small 3D game like
a lunar lander or something like that, or make yourself a Jurassic Park style 3D user
interface for your home automation.
But really, the chief lesson for me, I think, was the best way to get involved with a project
like MicroPython was to just start using it.
And eventually, you come across some kind of limitation that probably your best place
to overcome, because you're the one who's trying to solve the problem.
You've got the vested interest in it.
You have all of the information is currently paged into your brain.
And then the MicroPython people were extremely helpful in helping me whip my contributions
into shape.
So yeah, thanks to them for helping me get involved in MicroPython.
And thanks to you for listening.
I can try and answer questions, but I'm not super expert on anything I've been talking
about.
Hi, and thanks for your talk.
I had a question about the ESP2 that you were implementing on this.
Did you ever look at using the dual core setup to try to accelerate any of the maths?
That is a good question.
And someone has mentioned this to me before, but when I was writing this, I was actually
unaware that it had more than one core.
So I haven't yet, but it's a great idea.
Thanks very much for your talk.
If you're interested in MicroPython in the building A, there is a stand about MicroPython
and also a stand by pint64 who makes smartwatch that can run MicroPython and stuff.