Okay.
So hello.
Let me introduce us.
Like you may have heard, we are from Red Hat, from Berno actually, and we are going to talk
about the NFI, the new generation, as we have in the title.
To introduce us and the talk, we have it split into three sections.
The first one is covered by me.
It will be a technical overview.
Then there is community history and action items by Nicola, and finally a live demo from
Jan.
First, I would like to explain what are we actually talking about.
I imagine you most of you already know this, but DNF is a package manager, and probably
the easiest way to explain this to someone is to compare it to like an app store or a
command line app store.
So it installs, upgrades, removes packages, and dependencies, metadata, and stuff like
that.
There are many examples, and we are actually working on DNF and microDNF.
To put this into some more context, we have this diagram that's actually describing Fedora,
but I think many distributions have something similar set up like this.
You can see that it's possible to interact with the package manager in many ways or in
many levels, but here we are talking about the high level manager, and that is DNF or
libDNF.
If we focus on that section, we could see a diagram of components that for the current
version looks something like this.
There are some problems with this.
At first glance, I think it already looks more complicated than it needs to be, but
mainly you can see that the libDNF, the library is split into two sections, and DNF is actually
just using the Hawkeye section, but not the libHif one, while microDNF is using both.
This would be fine if there was some extra functionality in microDNF, but it is actually
the other way around.
MicroDNF does less than DNF, and this is because we have duplicate code there.
That's of course not good, so we should fix that.
The other big issue is with the extensions or plugins.
All of our plugins are for DNF, and they are in Python, but as you can see from the diagram,
it's not possible to use the same extensions in microDNF.
There's simply no way how to get to them, and also the other way around, if you have
some extension for libHif, it doesn't get used in DNF.
This is again not good, because we already have some extensions that we want in both,
and we have to duplicate them, again, that's just a bad situation.
To resolve that, we are introducing or creating DNF5.
I should mention that when I say DNF5 here, I mean this whole part of the stack, so the
library, the plugins, the actual command line DNF tool, but the new diagram looks like this.
It is much simpler.
We have merged the insides of the library into one piece, and we have also merged DNF
and microDNF into just one tool, which is here called DNF5.
There's also a new DNF daemon.
We still have two nodes here for plugins or extensions, but it is much more clearly separated.
For the library, we have more like passive extensions that get used automatically.
Every time you use the library, they get loaded and run, and for DNF5, there are more like
active plugins, so this is typically like a new command that you can add, and the user
actually has to type it and run it.
Other big two features are that we actually are breaking API, and it's not backwards compatible.
These are not exactly features, and you might ask, why are we doing this?
Let me try to explain that or justify it.
First for the library, we completely restructured the API and tried to make it better and most
importantly unified and safer, because before, like I mentioned, it was merged together a
bunch of things, and it wasn't that great, so hopefully this time we try to learn from
our mistakes and make it better.
Another change we are also doing is inside of the library.
For example, we are now loading and downloading the repositories at the same time.
This is because typically downloading the repositories is network intensive, but loading
them on the other hand requires CPU, so they kind of nicely match together and can be done
at the same time.
Another change is, no, we don't download file list metadata by default.
If you're not familiar, the file list contains a list of every file in all of the RPMs, so
it is quite a big file, and we think it's possible to get by without it, as other distributions
do, so we don't download it by default, but of course it's still possible if the user
wants to download it or even configure it, so it's downloaded every time.
We are trying to make it, of course, in general faster, and I think we will see this in the
demo later.
We have bindings for the new library.
We mainly focus on Python, because that's most of our users, but thanks to Svek, it
should be possible to generate also for other languages like Per or Ruby, and it will need
some work to do that, but hopefully it wouldn't be that too bad.
Now I'm moving to the actual command line package manager, dnf, dnf5.
Probably the biggest change or one of the biggest changes is that we dropped Python
as a dependency, and this is actually what allowed us to merge microdnf and dnf together,
because before we needed microdnf for like a container on minimal environments where
you need smaller footprints, but since now we don't need Python and everything is in
C++, we have best of both worlds.
Not everything has changed.
We keep most of the commands are actually the same, except for a couple differences
that needed like speaking or fixing, but on the other hand, the outputs of the commands
did change.
In fact, we do run still the same CI test that we ran for dnf4 as well as for dnf5,
and usually you have to change the checking of the outputs to make it work.
Most all of the tests work, but we are still developing it and working on that.
Then there is the daemon, and just really quickly it will be or it already is accessible
by debuffs, and since it uses the whole library or the same library, it will have the same
functions, so you can use it to work with groups or modules and stuff like that.
Last thing from me, I want to mention a couple additional improvements.
I'm not going to like too many details, but we have configurable aliases, fully integrated
modularity, just single configuration for all the users of the library.
We managed to separate system state from history database and module state, and for example,
we have built in autocomplete.
That is a good thing.
If you have questions about this or anything else, you can of course ask us after the presentation.
That was everything from me, and let me now hand it over to Nicola and the community part.
Thank you.
After the technical review, let's focus more on who is actually contributing to the nf5
and how we are changing our idea of looking at the community, not just our idea of the
code base, how we plan to change our approach with the community.
Of course, the nf5 is an upstream project, so it all starts from upstream.
It was, I would say, quite a bit chaotic in the past because components were a bit separated,
issues were not enabled for dnf, for example, for quite a while.
Now they are, but it wasn't super clear the path we were taking with the community.
Many issues stayed open for a while.
Pull requests are reviewed.
We didn't do great, but we plan to change it.
Let me give you an overview of what was the past of dnf contributions.
Then we will look at what we expect in the future, and then the action items that the
team has to make everything more transparent and all the workflow much clearer.
First of all, the past of the projects.
I'm saying projects because here I graphed the weekly contributions by author of dnf,
libdnf, and dnf5.
What I want to pull out from this graph is that, well, first of all, now the effort of
the team is all focused on dnf5, as you see, it's just all the contributions are on the
green part.
One other interesting thing is that, yes, dnf5 efforts are higher, are more, compared
to dnf or libdnf alone, but actually the effort, if you sum the highest points of dnf and libdnf,
the efforts of dnf5 is less, and that's because you have to maintain unified code base, and
that's much, much more easier to do.
Just one thing.
Also, I want to show you during the history of the project how many people actually contributed.
These are on the Y, the number of people that did some number of contribution on the X.
So there is some exceptional guy, around 200.
There is some others.
There is just one guy, 150, 125, and I like everyone is doing a very small number.
So that's fact, and that's how upstream works.
You have exceptional core team members that they will do all the job, and they are carrying,
they're pulling the efforts, but it's actually good to maybe improve the community a bit
more and, well, to give you maybe some more perspective, you can even see, like, this
is every bar is a contribution.
So it's a different person.
And yet again, there are just a few people that did a huge amount, a huge number of contributions,
and many, many people that did just a few, like one, which of course are important.
But what it means to us when we, what it means for us having someone from outside contributing.
So I had this idea of kind of splitting the contribution into groups, and here is my analysis.
So there are, of course, the authors of the project.
They are responsible of, let's say, the 10% of the total number of commits or contributions,
right?
One, two, max five maybe in the project.
Those are, like, the key components.
They are there from the beginning.
I'm talking generally, but this applies for our components.
Then there are the paid programmers, co-authors, exceptional contributors that are doing a
hundred of commits, a hundred of commits.
Well, it's quite a number, right?
And then, of course, there are the one-liners, the people that come, and they're like, hey,
there's a typo here, super important as well.
But they are just, they come and go, they, you will never see them again.
And well, they might be not even interested.
Sometimes they just come and they are just doing one small fix and going away.
And then there are who I call the people in the middle.
So actually the people that can effectively contribute by following the project and by
coming in more than once to just point out, hey, I am doing this request, maybe I'm opening
an issue, and then the contributor gets interested in working into the project and does active
commit, let's say, so brings in some code or maybe deletes some code.
The deleting code is very important.
So let's look at how we perceive contributions from inside a team.
So for DNF, talking still about weekly contributors.
We had a total of 225 contributors for authors, so four people that did more than 10% of the
whole work, and 19 people, very good people that did 100 commits.
And those people, they are regular.
They're since forever.
You kind of know that they are there helping you out.
But let's focus on the others.
So how many commits are in total and how many have been without those people?
And the number is actually roughly 10,000 total commits.
Oh, sorry, I'm talking about contributions.
So it's a little binned, so it's smaller numbers.
But still, like the statistic applies.
Roughly 4,000 commits without the authors and roughly 1,000.
So 1,000 commits are done just by those people that stay in the middle, more or less.
And so what is your effort to be, let's say, active member of the community?
So I said, OK, I want to do the 1% of this.
That's pretty easy.
You do roughly 1, sorry, 11 commits, 11 issues, 11 whatever, 11 comments.
And you are actually 1%.
If you know 100 people, you definitely remember if one person is missing or not or like, hey,
you change your haircut to pink.
And you remember because the 1% is quite a lot.
So it's very easy.
And I'm talking about 11 contributions in whole the history of DNF.
And DNF is being active for like 10 years.
So it's like one contribution per year.
It's quite easy, right?
And now it's the time to jump into DNF5 because if you look to DNF5, same applies.
It's basically just team effort.
So five authors roughly.
This number will decrease with time.
And six very good contributors.
And then those are the number of contributions.
And again, if you do one or two contributors, we value that kind of contribution, whatever
it is, quite a lot.
I mean, it's significant.
This is what I'm trying to bring up.
So what kind of contributions are we talking about?
We have a transparent workflow.
We have open issues now.
We triage all the issues weekly.
This is something that, again, we were not doing for DNF for some time.
We have public milestones in GitHub so you can understand what our action plans are.
And also we have discussions open that we use for announcement, that we use for gathering
opinions.
DNF5 naming is discussed on GitHub.
So you can go there and give your opinion.
And questions, of course, if you have a question now, you can ask it.
If you have a question later, there will be the link to GitHub to just go there and ask
something.
And of course we have Bugzilla for Fedora tracking and, I mean, downstream requests
or specific Fedora things.
But like the upstream is where we start.
And the upstream is where we are trying to improve to the community.
A bit more to that.
We have now a better documentation.
The documentation is actually generated from the code base.
It is tested.
So everything, every snippet that's there gets compiled in C++, it gets interpreted
in Python.
And so it's much more, let's say, reliable documentation.
So we expect to have, I'm not saying what we expect to have, you know what?
Because you'll never know.
But then we have now tutorials.
We have code templates.
We have a lot more material that a newcomer could work on and start to contribute to DNF
using that material.
Right?
And then we are planning to also add contributing guides that now are missing.
But we are planning to improve the contribution workflow on GitHub yet again and also to open
first time issues which are missing.
But we are targeting that.
So just to conclude my part, who's the community?
Actually the community for us is the people who create issues.
I mean, not create problems, create GitHub issues, right?
People who add or remove code.
And people to take part in the discussions.
Even now.
Even just by coming to us and say, hey, DNF5, you know what, I tried it.
It worked.
Or it broke my system.
It happened.
So I mean, it can happen.
It's not perfect.
Or the people who raise questions.
Like now or again, they are reaching back to us to the mailing list.
The more questions we have, the more reliable we can provide a code that actually works
for the most user cases.
And just using DNF5, you're part of the community.
And most importantly, and I really feel this quite a lot because when I started working
on DNF, I actually needed help from the team.
And I believe that many people didn't quite dive into the contribution system because
they didn't have help.
So we're actually in the need of people that help and ask for help.
And that will bring to all the other points.
So well, I hope now it's much more clear how we intend to work in the future.
And now let's see how DNF5 works in practice with the demo.
So here we go.
Jan will talk to you about the demo.
So hopefully it will work.
So let's try some hands-on ECGs.
And what do we have here?
So we have two separate individual containers, both running federal Linux.
And they have the same configuration.
And on the left side, I will show you the examples using the original DNF command.
And on the right side, I will show you the same examples running the DNF5 command.
So let's start with something simple.
Just install a package.
So we will try to install this package.
Hopefully the Wi-Fi will work.
And I will try the same on the right side.
Okay.
So what's going on?
We need to download the metadata about the packages.
So basically what are the packages?
What are their dependencies?
The requirements?
So the definition of repositories is configured in the system.
And now we need to just pull all the data, the metadata from repositories.
And now we can see the first difference between the DNF and DNF5.
What I was already talking about.
And it's the size of the metadata.
Because in DNF, everything is hard coded.
And always all metadata was downloaded.
So there is like 64 megabytes for the federal 37 repository.
And if we look into DNF5, there is just 21 megabytes.
And it's because of the file lists are not there by default.
Because usually we don't need them.
Okay.
And we can see some differences in the outputs.
Like for the DNF5, we have some more information there.
Like what packages are being replaced.
Yes.
But it's basically it looks very similar.
But the output should be a little bit more convenient for the user.
So let's try to install the packages.
And yeah, that's it.
Basically.
Another example, Alish was talking about the auto completion.
So this was also improved.
We can see that for DNF, there was also some auto completion.
If we try, for example, the mark command, I will type the M and now the double tap.
And we can see the DNF offers the commands for us.
Okay.
That's fine.
But the mark command has also the subcommand.
So if I type the double tap again, oh, it shows me like the installed packages on the
systems.
So these are the arguments I should use.
But if we see the help, like we need to use one of those three subcommands and these are
not suggested by the DNF.
So this was improved for DNF5.
You can look at this.
If we put the M and double tap, we can already see that there is some difference.
There is also some brief description of the subcommands that are offered for us.
And if we now put the double tap again, we can see also the subcommands there.
And of course, there is also the auto completion of the option.
So we can use the double dash and put the double tap again and we can see all the parameters
that are relevant to this command.
And it's quite, it could be quite convenient.
So now let's try some performance comparison.
So for example, the repo query command was quite improved.
So it's basically the command for querying the packages based on some keywords, on filtering
it and so on.
But for this example, we will use just the empty repo query, which basically lists all
the available packages in repositories.
So let's try that.
I'm running also for DNF5.
And we can see that the DNF5 was a little bit faster, but let's measure it exactly.
So let's use the time command.
And the same for DNF5.
And we can see there for DNF, it was like almost three seconds and for DNF5 it was one
second.
So it's a little bit faster there.
And we can also try some more advanced repo query.
So we can list all the packages that depend on the corollibrary.
And we will see that there will be, oh, there should be quite a big difference.
All right.
So what depends on...
Right.
So running it, I will try to run it parallel.
And we will see.
Okay.
So here is about six seconds for DNF5.
It's quite fast.
And for DNF it will be like three times longer, I think.
Okay.
20 seconds.
So that's it from the CLI demo.
And we can move to API.
And you could ask why I should use the API.
Well, of course, it depends on the use cases.
But usually if your project has, like, support one of our scripting languages, we have the
bindings for, like, the Python, it could be much more convenient to use directly the API.
And also it's more powerful than the CLI interface.
But yeah, some common use cases are simpler to write through the command line.
And so sometimes in the end the client chooses both approaches, right?
Okay.
So let's see some simple API example.
Let's say we have some our favorite package.
And we want to know what are the latest available version of this package in different federal
releases.
Could be useful.
So let's see step by step what we need to do.
So if we have installed the double packages and the API bindings following our tutorials
on the GitHub pages, the importing of the Python module is super simple.
Then we need to set up the session for the DNS and running some initialization method.
Then we need to override the release version variable, which is basically used in the repository
URL.
So we always look only for the packages of the respective federal release.
Then we need to prepare or load the repositories from the configuration and prepare, like,
the objects for the Python.
And then we need to prepare the query, what we will actually be querying.
So this is also quite simple.
There's a package query object and we will just filter all the packages containing the
kernel name.
And we want to have the latest version always.
That's simple.
And if we found any of those packages containing kernel, we just print the name of the package
otherwise not available.
Okay.
Let's try it running this simple script.
And for Fedora 35 there is this kernel version.
For Fedora 36 there will be some probably newer one.
Oh, it's taking long.
And also should output for Fedora 37 something a little bit newer.
Okay.
Now we can try to edit our script and show you if we have already some DNF5 package available.
But yeah, we need to add here a row height version, a development version of the Fedora.
Doesn't work.
I don't know how to...
Does anyone know how to exit V?
No, I couldn't resist.
I need to escape.
Different laptop.
And the thing is that it's actually a different laptop because the HDMI wasn't working.
So I don't know.
Because escape is not working.
Thank you.
If anyone has any questions, we'll try to move on and maybe...
Yeah, we can move on.
Okay.
So you will never know if DNF5 is actually in some Fedora.
Well, guess what?
We will say it anyways, but there was the clue.
It's always exiting.
Oh, maybe.
Maybe I got it.
I got it.
So in Fedora 35 there is no DNF5.
In Fedora 36 there is a DNF5.
In Fedora 37, no DNF5.
Oh, maybe for row heights.
It's taking some time.
I don't know.
Maybe just...
Oh, it's there.
Okay.
We can move to some more challenging example.
What if we want to add some...
Our awesome new command to DNF5?
So then the user will install it and just type DNF5, our command, and it will do the
magic.
It's quite simple.
We can show it to write some simple DNF5 plugin in like five minutes.
So what do we need?
Okay.
We need Devlin bindings packages.
That's no problem.
We can install it for the tutorials.
We need some template sources.
Okay.
You can steal our DNF5 plugin sources and use them.
And you need some build tools and build script, and then you can also steal the CMake script
we have for the DNF5 plugin.
No problem.
Everything is in our DNF5 repository.
Now how to write it?
You can follow our structure of the DNF5 plugins.
It's basically always some definition file, like the header was there, the actual implementation,
the CPP file, and then there is the adapter for the plugin API.
But it's like the boilerplate code.
We just need to change few lines and it will work.
So let's look at this C++ example.
There is the implementation of really simple example command.
And it's following the command interface from the DNF5.
So there is some methods for the setup of the command we need to follow.
In this step, we need to tell the DNF5 we have some new command.
So we basically register our new command into the DNF5.
This is super simple and it could be copied from other plugins.
Then there is setting the argument parser, basically parsing the arguments.
What are the arguments for our new command?
Listing all the positional arguments and what we have.
But in this simple example, we don't have any, so we just set some simple description.
In the configure section, we can modify the DNF5 session, change some configuration or
request some optional metadata to be downloaded.
Here we just gonna be quiet.
And there is the actual implementation of the command in the run method where we just
output something on the terminal.
And here I will show briefly the adapter code.
So this is the boilerplate one.
You just copy it and change a couple of things.
This is like the plugin name, the version, like name your outer and name of the plugin.
Then there is a long block of some boilerplate code that is same for all the plugins.
Each plugin consists of one or more commands, so we just put our new command into the list.
And finally, we need to return the instance of our new plugin class and that's it.
So let's try to build it and run it.
At first I will show you that there is no example command for the DNF5 right now, so
I'm not cheating.
And here are the sources.
There is the CPP file I was showing.
Then there is the header file which is basically just the definition and the adapter code in
the example plugin CPP.
And then there is the build script for the CMake which is stolen from the DNF5 sources.
So we just need to create build folder and then we will do everything to make it, there
is again some weird keyboard.
I need, this is not English keyboard.
I was using the check keyboard.
You should know the check keyboard.
I need like the M%.
English.
This one.
Where is it?
There we have it.
How did it happen?
What happened?
I don't know.
Show me again.
What?
The shift and.
This is the Italian keyboard, so don't look at this.
Just go by memory.
Oh, it is the printed in Italian.
So make it, make install.
So basically just build the sources and the installation is just the copying of the library
into the correct place where the DNF looks for it.
So building is done and we can try running the DNF5 example.
And yes, we did it.
I don't see.
Okay.
So when will the DNF5 release, you discovered already.
DNF5 is actually already in Fedora row height, so 38.
And there is a plan to, well, in a moment.
So first of all, if you're running stable Fedora 36 or 37, you can use a hopper to try
it.
And it will be parallel installation with DNF.
And also here are all the sources that we have for whatever.
You can find everything in the GitHub repo.
That's the only link you need.
There's everything there.
We have all the links copied in the talk information.
If you run Fedora row height or if you're in a container of row height and you want
to try it, it's there.
So just DNF install, DNF5 and you're good.
And something more about it, when it will actually land in Fedora.
So there is a plan to do a major upgrade of microDNF that will actually simply to DNF5
so it will be replaced in Fedora 38.
And in Fedora 39, there's the plan to replace DNF with DNF5.
So it's coming and we hope to be ready for that.
That's it.
Thank you.
And if you have questions, we have time.
Any questions?
Thank you so much for this presentation.
My question is related to community.
You demonstrated there is quite a few people that are not making more than like odd one,
two, three, four commits.
Can you tell me what is your plan to help people contribute more?
How are you going to improve the contributor experience?
So thank you for the question.
So the idea is to once again make it simpler and be more proactive to help people.
So again, in the past, we weren't very responsive and people got pissed because their code was
just ignored and their questions were not as important as maintaining DNF or there was
a perception from the outside.
And now we try to again, every week we go through all the discussions, all the new issues,
all the new PRs from community in all our components and we set an action plan for that.
So we set the milestones in every one of them.
We want to make this landing for the 38, we want to make this landing for the 39.
So you know what is our priority.
And we take seriously in serious considerations PRs.
So if you just drop some code, it's very easy for us to review it and be proactive to that.
And once again, it's done weekly and it's on our priority.
Our workflow has changed.
Hope it answered.
Thank you.
Just technical curiosity, is the new DNF5 daemon intended to replace the package kit
daemon?
Is the DNF5 daemon intended to replace the package kit daemon?
So it can, we did start with that in mind because package kit was officially deprecated
before.
So that was one of the goals.
But lately I've seen that package kit is maintained and there is even issue on our page that someone
wants to create backend for the DNF5 for the new IPI for package kit.
So I'm not sure how it will turn up, but we will see.
It was the plan originally.
It could, sorry if you want to, yeah.
The thing is package kit works, right?
So it's not that easy to, I'm hearing, okay.
Well, I would say that for now gets the job done.
But still, there's an alternative.
Actually the first enablement of DNF daemon on the system, there will be for other components
that are less critical to probably to adapt to the new DNF or actually the new API.
We're looking at cockpit, for example, that could use the daemon or anaconda maybe could
use it.
So it's not just package kit for which the daemon would be relevant.
Let's say that.
Just finally, we would like to do that because, like to replace it because it could provide,
for example, like I mentioned, the module support or group support to even to Chrome
software which is currently not possible and that would be nice.
So any other questions?
Hello.
I do also have a community participation question.
Are you talking or have you considered reaching out to other RPM based distributions beyond
Fedra and the CentOS, like Open Man Revover or SUSE perhaps?
Thank you.
I'm not in contact because no one here is project manager or team lead.
Let's say that.
I would let another team member of us answer into that.
But yes, of course, the RPM distributions are taken into account and all the relatives
to Fedra, they're of course taken into account.
The thing is, for now, let's say it's a quite younger project, NFI.
It's just two years since it has started developing.
So I would say that this is the reason why we're just talking about Fedora, Fedora, Fedora,
Fedora because this is our upstream where we do the testing, our CI runs on Fedora.
And well, I think that we definitely would be porting or like we would be very happy
to see the NF5 land in other RPM distributions.
I think that's it.
No more question.
Okay.
Thank you again.
Thank you.
Thank you, everyone.