I've been involved with, oh, I'm Stuart Allen here.
You can reach me that email address.
I've been involved with open source since the early 90s.
I dabbled with Linux kernel development, but mostly my projects have been standalone applications
and libraries.
I've been the technical founder of several companies over the last 30 years, and I've
managed to thread open source work through those companies and got them to release pretty
significant packages as open source internal works that have data processing libraries
and things like that.
And over the last 10 years, I've become increasingly enamored with the idea of not having to install
software anymore, at least not on the desktop.
So I'm going to walk you through a little bit of backstory for that.
I don't like slides.
So most of this will actually be a live demo of different applications, walking you through
the functionality.
But I will walk through just a little bit of the technology and the backstory for that
first before sort of hopping into this.
So it'll be a bit of a high wire act.
Let's see here.
Bullet points.
Excellent.
So this is just the rough order of things that I'm going to talk about.
I'm not good at following directions, even when I've written them, maybe especially when
I've written them.
So I might wander a little bit, keep me on topic.
If I do ramble a little bit or if I talk too quickly, definitely let me know.
I'm prone to do that, which is why I didn't have any espresso today.
I'm at least not told this is over.
Okay.
So on to a little bit of backstory.
All right.
Since we are talking about maker tools, I want to just have a slide about making, but
not dwell on it too long.
While I was organizing these slides, it always turns into something other than what you start
out.
I had an idea when I went to this, and then what came out of it was kind of different,
but the exception of the demo parts.
It occurred to me that the proliferation of really powerful and accessible tools has turned
really everybody into makers, and this is historically anomalous, like we've had tools
in the past, but the kind of tools we have now are really incredibly powerful.
My starting point as a maker was in the 70s.
My older brother purchased a TRS-80 Model 3 and abandoned it, so it became mine.
From that point, I basically learned basic by typing in programs at a bike magazine,
and so I was a touch typist by the time I was 10 because I was like this, trying to
get programs in faster.
That terminal window was for me a portal into an entirely new universe, and I can't really
overstate how profound that was for me at the time as I learned to code, exploring the
whole new world that you could just sort of create on the fly in front of you.
You had to use your imagination a little more than you do today with 3D and all the great
stuff we have and VR.
Imagination can be a powerful thing.
I've been giving away software since about the time that I learned to code.
Back then, we called it Shareware.
We used bulletin boards to get our creations out of their nest at an incredibly slow rate,
but they would make it around the world based on the letters and even checks that I got
from around the world at the time.
Unfortunately, I was like 12 when I did this, and I made up a company, and I put it on the
software title screen.
People sent me checks written out to that company.
They didn't exist, and I couldn't cash them.
Lesson learned.
Let's see.
Back to the point.
The difference in time now in history is that we are all makers to some extent from, I would
say, the ridiculous to the profound, as I have here at a bullet point, and I would have
said that before, chat GPT and mid-journey and all the other stuff that's out there today,
but that just serves to underscore the point.
We can all be creators in a way that has really not been possible before.
I guess that's sort of a debate.
Let's see.
Did I miss a slide?
No, I didn't.
This is the first time I'm using this, and the first time I'm presenting in like five
years.
There with me as I sort of find my footing.
I don't actually read the bullet points.
The things that I say are just inspirational things.
The things that I say are just related to that.
Why are browsers called browsers?
We haven't called PCs word processors since the 80s, and it has to do with where they
came from.
I'm sure that there are a lot of people here who could better tell the story and the history
of browsers, how they came to be, and the motivations of the people behind them, but
I think it's safe to say that the early creators were focused on document hyperlinking, sharing
of knowledge, not progressive web apps, and the browser sandbox, which is where we are
today, many decades later.
The reason it took us as long to get here is because we did start off from a document-centric
view of the web, and outside of mostly closed self-referential sites like Wikipedia, I don't
think that hyperlinking really is what it was envisioned to be, right?
Link rot is sort of the order of the day.
What has been far more successful is the evolution of the browser as an application platform.
Okay, so this brings us to sort of the inherent and natural tensions of today.
I've grown skeptical of the way that we distribute software, the software itself, pretty weary
of uninstalling, reinstalling, cleaning up and organizing.
Do you really know what's in the software that you're installing on your machine, what
it contains, and to what extent should you have to worry at all about this, right?
Conntainerization on the server side has not really delivered us from complexity, which
is totally a topic for another day, but since we are talking about containerization, it's
related decades on, there's still really no cross-platform application development environment
that works really at cross platforms.
Like I spent way too much time in the Java world, mostly enterprise, but even their take
on AWT and all the other things that came after that were pretty horrendous.
The toolkits that you can use now and try to get cross platforms, it really don't work.
The fact that mobile tablets touch new interfaces further complicate the ability to create applications
that run in multiple different formats.
The cloud has created more tensions around data privacy and questions of individual agency.
So hopefully, let's see if I actually address this in the next slide.
This brings us to progressive web apps.
I don't know if you know, are you familiar with this term?
You know, HTML5 and CSS, progressive web apps are basically web pages that can be self-standing
at the end of the day.
If you add a manifest and some service workers, they'll cast their own data, they can be installed
and run offline.
And so this is why, my background has been in high performance computing, embedded systems,
but I've ended up on the other end of the spectrum building web-based applications.
And so there are a lot of people who will question the performance of JavaScript, JavaScript
in general, and the browser.
I hope to address all of that.
My coding arc, as I said, started with BASIC.
It went through C, Tickle TK, Perl, other scripting languages, embedded systems, Java
for a couple of decades, a detour through Verilog, doing FPGAs and some of these real-time
systems for quantum computers, actually, before landing on JavaScript, oddly, while doing
a prototype in sort of like the late, or around 2010.
So over the years I've spent way too much time struggling with cross-platform and UI
issues, and I think that open source progressive web apps are really a solution for a lot of
these problems.
So let's see, they are deemed trusted because they're running in the browser sandbox, and
I lost my place on my, because I wrote way too many notes for this slide, and so give
me a second while I find where I was.
I'm going to skip this, and I'm going to spend more time on the demo.
You don't want to hear me talk about this much more.
I will say that Android and Chromium are friendlier platforms than iOS.
Apple is not really keen on progressive web apps because they compete with the app store
if you think about it.
If you have really good progressive web apps that you can install off a web page and run
them offline and have access to all the modern web standards like WebUSB and WebSerial and
all these other things, you don't really need the app store and app frameworks as much.
And so they've done a pretty good job of trying to hobble WebKit and enforce its use on iOS.
You used to be able to run Chromium on iOS without WebKit, and you had all these things,
and they're like, no, for security reasons, we can't do that.
Well, not really the case, but it does serve the purpose of enforcing the app store hegemony.
All right, so all the apps I'm presenting today are single page progressive web apps,
installable, runnable offline, fully open source, MIT license, been around for quite
a while in some cases.
I'm not sure if I'm going to spend a ton of time on this.
Just this is the pros and cons sort of as I see it.
For me, faster development time is the thing that I care the most about.
It is basically a page load away from testing new code, which is a subsecond process for
the most part, as you'll see.
I spent a year one day trying to add a small feature to an open source popular Python package,
and the dev test restart process took three minutes, and I was like, this is insane.
I basically modify code, I hit reload, and I'm testing it immediately.
Developer tools, especially Chromium, are shockingly good.
I'm just going to leave it at that for right now.
All right, so this is setting up or teeing up the first application that I'm going to
show you.
So I promise I'm almost to the demo.
A lot of my early making was in CNC, solid modeling, electronics, robotics, and things
like that, autonomous vehicles.
Sorry.
Then around 2012, I started getting heavily involved in 3D printing.
You'll see a couple of my early projects here.
Slicers of the day were painfully slow.
They produced output that was suboptimal for the things that I was trying to make.
The strength that I wanted, and I was working on engineer materials, scaled sort of like
Lego-like things like this, and I was like, I've been coding for a long time, how hard
could it be to write a better slicer?
I sort of like the genesis of a lot of things like, this doesn't annoy me, how hard could
it be to make a better one?
And so I started to build a prototype, and in a couple weeks I had basically a slicer
that did everything that I needed to do, which was good for me, and that was ten years ago,
so you know you're never done with these things.
But just to give you an example, a single cube or block out of this with the slicers
of the time would take 20 minutes to make one of those cubes, and I was doing scaled
up large scale models.
My slicer would produce the same part, the output, it would produce the same part in
11 minutes, and the part used less material and was more mechanically, was stronger, would
bear more load, and did a lot of things that I wanted.
So it was already success, sort of like two weeks in, again, ten years ago.
Slicers have come a long way since then, and I'm not sure how much I want to get into that.
But again, let's see, I'm going to skip the next slide.
Wait, this, then this.
I have the dual screens set up, it's hard to know what's going on here because this
is not totally in sync with that.
Lots of timeline of some of the tools I've been building since then.
Kermodo, which is a multi-modal application that runs in the browser, does FDM slicing
for 3D printing, does CAM, does laser, does MSLA, which is for resin printing, does drag
knives as part of the laser.
So basically it's an all-in-one maker tool for most of the things that you would have
commonly used in your maker space.
Because I was doing a lot of large scale printing, I ended up designing and building my own printer
from my printer farm, which is also open source, open design.
I ended up writing my own Gcode Center for that and a whole bunch of other things.
And then around 2015, when Onshape came along, so my CAD program of preference was SOLIDWORKS
for 15 years.
And those guys left and started Onshape, and just a little bit back story there, SOLIDWORKS
promised since the very first day they came out that they would eventually have a Mac
version of their software, and they didn't deliver on that after 15 years.
So the guys left, created Onshape, and now it runs on a Mac in a browser and is better.
So they opened an app store, and I was like, this is perfect.
I could integrate Kermodo into Onshape accessor APIs and have a connection between CAD and
CAM in one thing.
And I did that, got accessor APIs, and integrated it in 24 hours.
And the next day they called me and they're like, hey, that was awesome.
We'd never seen anybody integrate in less than 30 days.
Do you think you want to do a CAM package?
And I was like, huh, 3D printing CAM, additive, subtractive.
It's interesting.
I did it for a long time.
How hard could that be?
So I ended up adding CAM in 2016.
Again, had a prototype working in about two weeks, and here we are six years later, and
we're really just getting into the interesting stuff on that package.
So this is the interface for different modes of Kermodo.
This is the GitHub repository, and I'm going to jump into a demo of this.
Application is called Kermodo.
Most people call it Kiri or K-M when you're typing it out.
The back story on that is that when I was building this, I was building two applications
at the same time.
One was the slicer, and the other one was actually a modeling program.
I wanted to do CAD modeling in the browser, and again, none of the other tools really
existed at that time.
This was 2012-ish, and I started to build a block modeler that was sort of a combination
of Minecraft and blocks that you could skin things and connect them, and you could create
blocks to create blocks.
So I called it Metamodo, but this ended up taking all of my time, and I never got a chance
to really finish that.
I abandoned it.
But now I have the tools to actually maybe go back and finish that if I have time, which
is doubtful, it seems like.
Okay.
This is a really short and quick slide.
All the different modes have the same workflow.
Whether you're an FEMCAM laser or an MSLA, you're arranging it on a workspace.
You're doing a slicing pass, and the slicing pass is the crude pass that basically just
says I'm deconstructing geometry, I'm creating the rough paths that I'm going to be following,
but I'm not doing things like path routing and other complex stuff.
That's the prepare step, which basically takes the raw slices and then does path routing.
And path routing in the 3D world for 3D printing and CNC and laser are all different, which
is why it's abstracted out.
And each of them has their own different views, and you can do different things and different
views based on that.
And then the last pass is basically exporting into your device target.
I'm going to export G code or an SVG or, in the case of MSLA printers, massively large
binaries for no reason.
Yeah.
All right.
Let's see if there's something missed here, didn't miss here.
The code structure, again, this is all running in the browser, 100 percent JavaScript unless
I say otherwise, and I will denote when that happens.
There is a little bit of WebAssembly in there, and I plan to add more WebAssembly in the
future to accelerate things.
The major libraries I'm using are 3JS for the 3D, Clipper for polygon offsetting, and
very recently I added Manifold for a 3D Boolean engine.
It's not, it's used in one small place, but in the future I probably want to use it in
other places.
It's actually an incredible library.
Storage on the right, these different blue boxes are different workers, different thread
contexts, so you've got the UI context.
And then all the work is done in workers to keep the UI responsive while all the heavy
lifting is happening.
There's no lateral communication between the workers.
It's all hierarchical, top down.
There's a reason for that.
I don't know if I have enough time to actually really talk about it today, but denoted in
each of the boxes are the languages that are being used, languages and or libraries.
All right.
And I'll just hope to remember to show you all that stuff in the demo.
So I'm going to hop into the demo now, start with KIROMoto, show you different parts of
that integration with Onshape, and now I have to switch up the UI interface or rather the
this thing here.
I have to go to mirror display so you guys can see what's happening.
Great.
Now I have to go find my browser.
Let's just do it here.
All right.
This is not good.
That's better.
I am running this live on the network here, which I found to be spotty sometimes during
the day today.
Sometimes it's great, sometimes it gets a little bit of trouble.
So right off the space you can launch these applications directly.
Because it's running in the browser, actually hold on a second, and you get my, because
I no longer have speaker notes, I'm going to use my phone.
That way hopefully I won't forget major important things to discuss.
All right.
You can launch these things directly from here.
This allows you to launch any of the major modes or just hop right into the application
by clicking on it there.
And there you go.
The whole thing is loaded.
The footprint of this is under four megabytes compressed and usually loads in under a second
with a cold cache, maybe about two and a half seconds to load the entire application with
all the different modes and everything else that's in it.
So it's quite small in terms of footprint for the code.
Other slicers, if you go to download and install them, are going to be in the two to 500 megabyte
range for the similar code size, for similar functionality.
And I'm going to bring up on the right-hand side really quickly just to show you what's
going on under the hood.
On the right-hand side, I don't know if you ever brought these up, you can look at the
different threads or thread contexts that are down here.
In the interface, you can turn on and off threading, which will start and stop the workers
on the right-hand side, which sort of eludes to the previous slide that I showed you.
So these are the distributed workers that will be doing all the heavy lifting sort of
behind the scenes.
And you can turn it on or off because some browsers, like Safari, don't allow you to
do nested workers.
They have to only work in a flat space.
It's just one of the most of the web standards they refuse to support properly.
And so it'll still work that way, it's just going to be slower.
All right.
Typical slicer interfaces.
The original interface for Curimoto was very much like the slicers that you see today,
Cura and Prusa and all that kind of stuff with essentially a tree of 1,000 parameters.
This interface is slightly more opinionated and cut down.
And so you'll see that you've got a lot fewer parameters for your model.
But that's not really a problem.
I would say that most parameters and most slicers are designed to help you deal with
crappy 3D printers.
And it makes sense because most 3D printers are crap, to be honest.
And they don't have good software, or they don't have good hardware, or they don't have
both.
So there's a lot of stuff that you can fix in software with a crappy 3D printer, even
if your firmware is junk.
And a lot of printers actually are capable of running better firmware than they are delivered
to you with.
And it's just beyond most users to change out the firmware for a custom one and tune
it the way it needs to be tuned.
And so a lot of that stuff gets pushed into the slicer.
And so the slicers will give you 1,000 parameters, 1,000 parameters, 900 of those work against
each other.
And so slicer profiles become a religion, where it's all about, oh, mine works perfectly.
Tweak a few things, something breaks, and so you're like, you can't correlate why this
thing is breaking this other thing.
Because this whole product is just me.
I'm forced to be basically really brutal about what is in and what is out.
And I'm doing heuristics for 99% of the stuff that's out there.
Like it's going to work for most cases.
And under the hood, in the engine, are all the parameters that would be in other slicers.
I'm just not exposing them to you.
Because I don't really believe that's helpful.
And again, if you run into a corner case where you just can't do the thing you want to do
with your favorite parameter, just go use the other slicer.
Or commit some code.
Because this is open source, it's all on GitHub and has been there for a long time.
Let's see.
There is, before I actually get into really demoing this, I want to show another thing.
Because this is running in the browser, this is used pretty widely in not just in 3D printing,
but CAM and everything else in a lot of classrooms.
Because it is one of the only pieces of software that runs on Chromebooks.
It doesn't have to be installed.
You can basically run it in classroom, Google Classroom, and other places.
You can configure everything on the URL.
So you can create profiles and put a bookmark somewhere.
And somebody can click on it.
It'll open up the profile.
And it'll be preloaded with everything that the student needs for that class.
So you can use the device profiles, even loading up objects into your workspace.
So it's pretty easy to do that kind of stuff.
And the fact that you can basically export your workspace, open a private browsing tab,
import it.
You can use this as a way of getting your data around from browser to browser.
Or again, for testing and debugging.
People send me workspaces all the time.
I open a private browsing tab, I import it, I replicate whatever their problem is immediately,
and then be able to fix it right away.
So from this interface, usually it comes up like this.
You can click on the Docs grid space.
It'll take you to this page here, where it shows you everything about the different ways
you can do shared profiles, which are just alluded to, Gcode macros, and different ways
to embed or otherwise use the API for this.
So to show you a quick, let's just open up something which is sort of like your basic
3D printing thing here, the Benchi.
If anybody's done any 3D printing here, in the slice mode, you go in here and you're
going to have the ability to look at different slices, ranges of slices, like this.
And the reason that there are two different modes, most slicers will basically take you
right to the path-routed version of a sliced object.
The reason I put you in here first is because you might want to modify parameters for ranges.
So in this case, I could just say I'm going to turn off the infill for that bottom part,
and then I have a range here that shows me that I've done that here and I've overridden
the fill amount.
And if I re-slice that and go look at this at the bottom up, you'll see that there's
no infill down here, and then all of a sudden it switches to the normal view there.
And then you can go and look at the preview, and this will show you the path routing.
Path routing in view involves also determining the speed at which those layers or portions
of layers are going to be printed.
And you can turn things on and off like booths.
So you can look at the booths.
Yeah, I realize that aspect ratio is a little funky maybe here.
Typical stuff that you would see in a slicer.
Nothing really amazing there.
What is a little bit more interesting about Kiyomoto, and this isn't really specific to
3D printing, and I'll get to this more later, is you can go in and change the version on
the fly because I'm hosting the last ten versions of the software, I'm working on the
beta channel, I'm pushing out software two to five times a week depending on how active
development is going with major releases about every four to six weeks.
And so if there's a bug in the current release, you can go just switch to the previous one.
Your workspace will be preserved and it will bring you back into the same workspace that
you were in before with all of your data and all of your everything.
All of the stuff is persisted live in the browser, so again everything is just like
reload the page and you're back where you were before, screwed something up, reload
the page.
All right.
So there are three ways to import, export files really quickly.
You can just drag and drop stuff into the browser.
There are different formats you can support, so like in this case I can just drag in this
file here, which is something that some users really love to use as a benchmark because
it's got about a million polygons and it slices pretty fast.
There are some users of the program who really helped me with performance because they care
a lot about it and have benchmarked Curie against Cura and Prusa and a bunch of other
kind of stuff like that.
Again, million polygons, slicing this thing at the end of the day is about as fast as
Cura was, at least last year, that was the last time we looked at this, fairly well optimized.
And again, this is pure JavaScript, there's no WebAssembly or anything else happening
here under the covers.
What else I'm going to show you here?
I'm not sure how important that is.
But anyway, the version switching is nice and then they're pluggable language.
If anybody wants to contribute languages, it's pretty easy to plug in a new language
into the interface and again you just reload the page and you've got another language with
the same interface that you had before.
And here we can go through, look through this, there we go, look through anything else.
So typical stuff there.
Interesting thing to note about this is that once you've sliced this thing, we're now looking
at about 25 or 30 million polygons in WebGL and it's still fairly responsive.
I mean, it's not as fast as I'd like it to be.
So future work is actually writing custom shaders, which I think would help with this.
This is not a case where you can basically de-res or hide stuff on the fly because if
somebody goes in to look at the interior of this object, you can't just hide and then
show that thing.
There's always a possibility that interior features are going to be shown through the
shell so you can't hide them.
Everything that's in this, every path that's in this thing has to be shown at all times.
And so this is an area where I would, if they're graphics experts, this is not my field, would
love to have some feedback on this at some point.
And then you can just export the code.
The nice thing about this is that Kiyomoto also has a G code.
And again, I'm not sticking to my own script here.
There's the things I want to talk about, but you can export the G code and then once you've
done that, download the G code.
You can also send directly to printers.
I have a spooling agent that allows you to send directly from Kiyomoto in the browser
to OctoPrint.
So if you use OctoPrint as a back end, there's a way to send directly from the browser to
your printer.
And that's fairly well documented and I have other ways of doing that for some of my own
printers.
Download G code.
Kiyomoto also has a G code render built in.
So if you get some random G code and you want to bring that in, you can actually bring in
the, bring the G code back in.
Oops.
Let's find the downloads and bring that back in.
And we'll re-render the G code.
This works in all modes.
So Kiyomoto will render G code from CNC, laser, FDM.
And so I'll get into it in the CNC section.
I'll show you that as well.
And then there's exporting and sharing of workspaces.
So for example, I go into a private browsing session.
And the internet's great.
Let's try it again.
Great.
Private browsing.
I can import something like a CNC job.
And it will switch modes, bring it in, tell me, give me a screenshot of when the workspace
was created and then bring everything in with it.
So this is an example of the fourth axis lathe work that's happening right now in the cam
mode.
This isn't fully baked yet, but it's the next thing that's coming out with the next release,
which is fourth axis CNC was the thing I added in the last release.
And this just sort of gives you the ability to do some fun stuff like this.
But that's just showing you importing, exporting, and sharing of workspaces.
Cam mode.
Let's just hop in a cam mode real fast.
CNC mode.
So you'll notice when you change modes, your device list changes and the platform changes.
It's adapting on the fly to whatever the new mode is that we're working on.
I got this new CNC mill, make it our carvera, and it got rid of all my other mills because
it does everything that I need.
And so that actually leads to another project that I've been working on.
I'm going to bring in a workspace for that.
This workspace that somebody sent me, they're like, hey, I have a problem with some anomalous
cuts happening here.
So in CNC mode, you get a new bar at the bottom.
These are reorderable operations because CNC is a set of operations.
Each operation may or may not use a different end mill.
And then you can hover over each one and change the settings for those, and you can enable
and disable them like that.
And I'm just going to go into slice through this and give you an idea what the slice view
looks like.
I can turn on and off the different operations to look at what they're doing, or I can go
through them like this.
But this doesn't involve the routing.
This is just, again, the pure slices.
We go to preview this, and it's going to show us the path routing.
That's a little aggressive on the hover.
But once you've done this, we can go to animation mode.
And now this is the first time we're doing something actually pretty interesting, where
on the back end, there is a shared array buffer, which is a relatively new technology in the
web standards.
The shared array is like a shared memory, but having shared memory in JavaScript is
cool.
This is a new thing.
The workers have access to one shared pool memory.
They're all rendering into it simultaneously.
And the front end 3JS engine is rendering the same buffer that's being rendered into
by the workers on the back end.
So I can go through, and I can run this animation, and I can speed this animation up.
And so all of this is actually happening in real time by the workers on the back end.
And I got this workspace that says, I have this anomalous cut right here.
What's that all about?
Well, I'm not going to walk you through the great details, but they had one thing incorrectly
set in one of the settings.
I figured that out, sent it back to them with the correct settings, and it wasn't a bug
this time.
Oops.
It looks like, no, that's fortunate.
My hand touched my phone.
All the notes disappeared.
It looked like I deleted them magically, but it didn't.
It just created a new note that was empty.
OK, so here, this is a fixed workspace.
Let's see.
Can really also do other sort of import export.
It can import SPGs and extrude them.
It can import images and turn them into height maps.
So one of the common things people do with CNC is they'll do reliefs.
And so I can bring in a relief, like an image of a flower, and add some parameters to that.
And actually, I want my stock to be offset.
And then I want to resize this thing because it's kind of too large.
So this is sort of a common use case.
People want to do reliefs.
These are a pretty common thing.
This came from this image right here, which I grabbed off the internet this morning.
But just to show you that it will import things like that, and it will also import SPGs.
So if you have an SVG, this is more common with lettering.
If you want to do, like, lasering or CNC of lettering or things like that, you want to
bring in an SVG that you created in another 2D program.
And I can do that.
And it'll bring it in.
That's too large.
I can delete pieces out of it and scale it because that's, again, too large.
So then just to leave and add some new operations there, this is actually a good segue into
the laser mode.
This is actually really too large now again.
Let me scale that guy down.
And in laser mode, you're creating, let's see.
I don't want to use this.
I'm going to use a different cube.
I'll just show you this.
So by default, in the laser mode, when you slice, it basically looks at all the different
Z changes.
And it will, if you say nothing for zero for the height, it'll basically find all the transition
points and it will create a slice at that point.
The assumption there is that you're going to slice the thing into a stackable layer
and you're going to basically do stacked, registered slices with a laser cutter.
You can do something a little more complex.
You can choose the slice height.
But lettering, the things I showed you before, you're basically going to bring in a 2D thing
usually and then slice that and set like an offset.
Offset is a curve for the laser.
And that'll tell you how far the line's going to be set off from the part so that when you
take into account the width of the laser, you get the size of the part that you want.
It has some other interesting features like a drag knife.
You can turn on drag knives.
Drag knives will do the radial cuts so that you can basically, if you're cutting vinyl,
for example, it's very similar to laser cutting, but you're dragging a rolling surface.
And so 15 minutes.
Thank you.
I'm rambling.
Drag knife support.
I'm going to quickly just go through the last mode or two here and then show you a couple
other things.
Resin printing, also known as usually MSLA, which is masked SLA as opposed to actually
resin printing using a real laser which is tracing something.
Chitty Box owns that market.
I bought a couple of resin printers and I used them before I figured this out, that
all of the file formats for resin printers are pretty much proprietary.
They all contain the same information, which is basically a stack of images.
But because Chitty Box sells the hardware, they force everybody to sign NDAs and make
everybody to have a different file format.
So what's out there today is all reverse engineered.
I haven't put a lot of effort into MSLA since then, but it's really, really brutally simple.
It doesn't even have the problem of path routing because you're really just doing layers.
So you're slicing into layers, you're generating a bunch of bitmaps, you're encoding them into
a file and then you're throwing that at your resin printer.
I will say the one thing that really doesn't make sense about this is that resin printers
take so long to cure each layer that a microcontroller could render and master each next layer and
it really should just be a stack of SVGs instead of 100 megabyte.
This would be like a 100 megabyte file going to a resin printer.
Should be 5K.
Makes no sense.
And I'm done ranting on that for today.
So the next way that you can access Kirito is through the engine.
There is an engine API and an engine example.
This is the pure API not associated with any UI or anything like that.
You can run it standalone, you can run it in a browser.
Here I'm actually going to just slice an object and generate out code in the browser.
This is just using the engine directly.
There's one more API which is actually used by, so the engine API and the frame API are
used by a couple of different projects, even a commercial product.
This is an API driving a frame.
You can embed Kirito in a frame in your site and drive it through an API.
This is automatically the API interaction.
You can skin it.
You can remove any UI elements you're not happy with.
You can use the 3D part of it.
So you can basically create your own engine for this, your own wrapper for this and put
it anywhere you want.
So that's just another sort of interesting way to access the interface.
I'm going to show you the integration into Onshape.
If you've never used it before, browser-based CAD, love it.
Can't say enough nice things about it.
It's not open source though, obviously.
Go in, open a model.
In this case, I actually did a YouTube video demoing this, creating a CNC job to mill a
guitar neck.
So you go into Onshape.
This is the model in Onshape.
Kirito's a tab over here.
You basically just say add Kirito.
It shows up here.
It's in the App Store.
And then inside of Onshape, because you can see I'm iframed right here, I bring in the
guitar neck and it imports into my workspace.
And I can start to go into CAD mode and start adding operations to mill this thing.
Export the gcode, all in the same interface.
If I update the model over here, I can come over here and refresh the model in place.
So if I have things that are referenced in the model and I'm doing some milling stuff
and I change the model, I can basically just re-update it in this tab.
So that's really the beauty of having this integration done in the browser through their
APIs.
It's the only case where this isn't a fully standalone application.
I have to have APIs on the server that talk to their APIs using OAuth and a bunch of
other stuff.
So I'll leave it at that since we're running out of time.
The last two things that I want to show you are, if I go back to grid space, MeshTool.
In the slicer world, you get a lot of crap models from Thingiverse and other places like
that, non-manifold objects.
And I kept adding more and more features into KIROMoto to manage those problems and try
to heal those objects and clean them up.
And eventually I'm like, I don't want to crowd the interface in KIROMoto with a bunch
of stuff that really I used to use Blender for.
And so I created my own tool for that.
This was beginning of last year, I think.
You can come in here and you can bring in any...
So one of the things people do commonly with, oh, I didn't even show you the belt printing.
So I will say that one of the things that KIROMoto did before most other slicers was
add belt printing.
So if you're not familiar with belt printers, one of the reasons I'm going to show you that
is that belt printers are, you would think, very similar to Bottoms Up 3D printing.
They're not.
They're completely different.
They're similar in some ways, but basically if you think about it, every layer has a first
layer problem.
At 45 degrees, every layer has a first layer problem.
And you have to deal with the fact that your bed is not rigid.
It doesn't like a lot of materials.
And you have a really hard time enclosing that thing.
Having said that, if you can get your print job to work in a belt printer, it's phenomenal
for lots of things.
Why do you like to print swords?
Problem with swords is they don't lay flat on the belt.
So one of the things you can do in this tool is you can go in and split a sword.
And there I have half a sword.
Now the problem with that is that it is not manifold.
It is open.
So in here I can go to repair, patch.
I now have a sword, which I can flip over, put on a belt printer, and print it, which
is something that people do pretty commonly.
I'm not going to spend a lot more time in this tool other than it's something that
I would love to improve over time and add a lot more features into over time.
I think it's a tool that we should have running in the browser.
There are some other things that are similar out there.
But again, there's no cloud involvement for any of these programs.
They're all completely standalone and run in the browser.
And the very last thing, which I will show because we're totally out of time now, is
card control, which is a sender.
I can't actually show you this because I am not connected via serial to a CNC mill.
But this runs in the browser, uses web serial to talk to your device directly, locally.
It's abstracted so that you can talk over USB serial or you can talk over the network
to the device.
But what's really cool about this is that if you get a mill and you go to your first
time setup and you plug it into your laptop, you can click the serial button right here.
It will find your mill.
You will connect to it and start controlling it immediately, run the browser without having
to install any software.
What led me here was when I got the mill and tried to install their software, it didn't
work on any of my computers.
It didn't work on Windows, it didn't work on Android, it didn't work on Mac.
Now they fixed most of these problems.
But again, it was like, this software is not complex.
I've written senders before.
How hard could it be?
So the cool thing about this software is actually that it shows you, it uses 3JS, will render
and show live in 3D what the mill is doing.
So it's tracking in real time the G code against what's happening on the mill.
All right.
Go to GoodSpace, you'll find links to the forums, dot, discord, all that kind of crap.
And now I can take questions.
If anyone has questions, send over the microphone.
Yes, on that side.
The room is full of makers.
Yes, yes.
Hey, thanks for the talk.
What are the techniques you're using for the workpiece simulation that you've demoed in
the CNC workspace?
The question is what?
It looked like maybe you're using just a height map?
For that, yes.
Modeling this.
Correct.
In the three axis CNC mode, it's rendering a height map because you can't do undercuts
or side cuts or anything like that.
In four axis mode, it doesn't use a height map.
That's way harder to deal with.
That's actually the only place I'm using manifold currently.
And so it actually does 3D subtraction in real time of the tool geometry against the
geometry.
It's far more computationally intensive.
But yeah, and I didn't have time to show that.
Is manifold like robust mesh billions?
It is.
So it's a relatively new project.
It's really exciting.
Written in C++, compiled into Wasm, and then loaded in as a library to run in each of the
workers.
Again, it's WebAssembly.
So it's pretty fast, but it is a proper, like, manifold library for doing Booleans.
And I did contribute to that project because their initial API was too slow for what I
was doing.
They weren't producing arrays properly.
I rewrote their JavaScript API for import export of those and made it, like, 200 times
faster.
So that got accepted recently.
Another question?
Hi, thanks for the talk.
I found it really interesting.
I was wondering, I might have missed it, but I don't think you mentioned where you used
WebAssembly in the product.
And I was looking at the WebAssembly, Wasm.
Yes.
And I was curious, because looking at the slicer algorithms for FDM, they must be pretty
computationally intensive.
So how do you get that to work fast enough in the browser to be usable?
So none of the slicing that you saw, none of the CAM stuff, none of that used WebAssembly.
Nothing that you saw today used WebAssembly.
That's all pure JavaScript, which I know is probably upsetting for people.
Fun minutes.
Yeah, I'm surprised it's fast enough.
It's impressive.
So part of it is I did spend decades doing high performance computing, and I'm a bit
of a performance nut.
So why would I use JavaScript?
I did my prototype in JavaScript, and I'm like, this is just too easy.
Like I said, it was more than ten years ago, and I was like, it worked.
And my intention was to rewrite it in a real language, because I spent most of my life
writing in real languages.
And now I spend all of my time writing in JavaScript with a little bit of WebAssembly
and some other things like that.
And totally hooked on it.
You can totally do some pretty amazing things in JavaScript if you decide you want to.
Cool.
Thank you.
Jenerob.
.