Hello, everyone. Hello, hello, hello. It looks like it is time for me to begin. So if you
are here for this topic, you know, you're in the right place. That's awesome. Who am
I? I am Matt Yakovitz. I am the head of open source strategy at SCARF or the HOSS for short.
You may have heard me or seen talks from me before. Multiple ways to connect with me.
I will podcast different things that I do. If you don't know what SCARF does, what we
do is we help projects and maintainers grow their open source adoption, help track it,
help analyze it, help you understand who is downloading and using your open source software.
We also do a hacking open source business podcast. And so that is up to 14 episodes,
I think, are recorded now. So if you're interested in understanding from others on what is working
in the open source business space, okay, seems like I need to hold it a little closer, then
that would be a good place to check out. We're also launching a new website that has all
of the information from these slides as well as a whole bunch of other details on how to
measure your open source businesses. And we have it under open source metrics.org. If you're
interested, there's links to the podcast and various things on running an open source business
and measuring it. So how many people here know open source is different? Right? Unlike
other businesses, obviously you are competing with free, which changes the mindset quite
a bit. Let me give you an example. It's a very easy example and people will pick it
apart, but let me just, you know, get through it real quick. If you're selling a car nowadays,
if you're a car manufacturer, you have the ability to set your price for the car. People
can walk away from the car. If they don't buy a car or a vehicle, then they would have
to choose some other alternative modes of transportation. If you use a car that's in
the open source space, you can still set the price for the car, but you don't actually
have to pay for it. So someone can come get the car for free, drive it around and do whatever
they want with it. So consumers can choose to buy your car or someone else. And that
boggles the mind of many traditional business folks because it's giving something away for
free. And one of the key things that people misunderstand about open source is it's great
if it's free and people can use it, but in order for people not to choose the free version
and pay for something that's in the commercial space, it has to give you more value than
what you're going to get in that free space. You have to figure out some way to connect
with those folks and you have to make sure that they are finding value in what you have.
Now some of you, and I'm interested to know, how many people are more in the tech space
in here? Can you raise your right hands? Okay, how many people on the business space raise
your left foot? Okay, so few. Well, so many in the tech space consider this type of a
talk when we talk about revenue and money evil. So I'm going to go ahead and put on
my other hat, which is my super evil villain hat, you know, for this talk. And that doesn't
necessarily mean that this is wrong or that it is super evil or villainous, but it's hard
for tech folks, especially founders, to talk about revenue and money. This is outside of
the wheelhouse, right? From a technical standpoint, when we talk about growing, you know, your
business, that's not something that is naturally inherent. So people seek out different advisors,
they look for who's done it before, what sort of things have worked, and then they try to
repeat that process. So I want to start by giving some baselines. There's a lot of common
open source business models out there. There's several, but I'm going to talk about the three
primary ones. And that's open core, a SaaS model, or as a service model, it could be
infrastructure, platform as a service, just consider all those the same, or services themselves.
Now from an open core perspective, okay, and excuse all the graphics in this, I'm not a
graphics designer, so, you know, they're a little hokey, but open core. How many people
have heard of open core before? Oh, the vast majority, but not everyone. Okay. So open
core is when you have an open source version of your project that's freely available for
everyone, but then you have an enterprise version. The enterprise version reserves some
set of features, and then if someone wants those features, typically more enterprise
features like maybe higher security integration with partner products, things like that, then
people will then have the ability to purchase that from you, and then they'll pay a regular
ongoing fee. A lot of companies have dual licenses in this case, so their open source
is, you know, let's say GPL, and then there's some enterprise license for their, you know,
enterprise version. Okay. Now this is dwindling a little bit in popularity as the cloud has
taken over much of the tech industry, and that's where a lot of new businesses, especially
in the open source space, are looking, and that's in this SaaS or this cloud model. Okay.
You can download the software, but if you really want to run it, then, you know, you
should use our SaaS thing. We'll make it easier. This provides a higher level of quote-unquote
stickiness. Now, if you are a manager, director, executive at a company that has, you know,
venture funding or that you're, you know, has executives who are, you know, kind of
been in the industry for a while, I guarantee that they have had at least ten conversations
about stickiness in open source in a calendar year, and what stickiness is, is the ability
for someone to start to use your open source software and then continue to use it. So how
do we make it sticky? How do we retain them? In many companies, this is a model that provides
a higher level of stickiness, because once you get into a cloud service, it's often really,
really difficult to migrate away, because you're relying on that cloud service to be
your sys admins, your DBAs, your, you know, DevOps folks. They're handling all those functions,
and so to replace that, you either have to go to another cloud service or you need to
find someone who can do those functions for you, and that's often a really difficult prospect
to do. But there are some issues with this model. This model is disruptible, because
other people can run that exact same as a service. What we've been seeing in the space
of the SAS lately is a lot of open source companies have changed their licenses to prevent
that, and they've gone from open to not open. So you might have heard of SSPL, you might
have heard of the BSL, other things. These licenses are kind of sort of open, but that
means that, you know, as you get into the cloud space, you're restricted from competing
with them, so it's more of a preservation of their revenue stream, if you will.
And then there's the services model, which is really the original kind of OG, the old,
you know, model for open source software, and that model is definitely something that
we have seen be very popular and very successful in a lot of different companies. This is a
viable pathway for a lot of companies to start. It's an easier pathway to revenue, but it
is hard to grow beyond a certain limit. So, you know, you might be able to get a handful
of customers working with you from a support perspective, from a consulting perspective,
but you're really bound on the number of people, because you have to have people to deliver
those services, and if you don't have people to deliver those services, that becomes quite
an issue.
And if you compare the three models, you know, you can compare them. You've got that open
core, which is a proven model, but it is getting disrupted and eroded by the cloud a little
bit. And, you know, there's still some success in that space, because a lot of companies,
especially when you listen to some of the sovereign cloud, the cloud native, they're
looking at enterprise versions or open core versions, they want to run their operators.
They want to build their own private clouds. So, there is still some play in that space.
X as a service or software as a service, you know, that is still a very popular model.
But the question is, if you are releasing features that are only available in a SaaS
version and only a minimal open source version, is SaaS, the SaaS model, is it still open
source? Or is it not? And that's a question that we really haven't answered yet, especially
as companies start to reserve features and software specifically just for their SaaS
customers. And then there's the service model, which is definitely the easiest to get started
if you're a small company. It, you know, has the most likelihood that you'll get some revenue
in the door really quickly without a huge buy in cost.
Now part of this model, okay, if you, whether you choose, whichever model you choose is
how do you get people to move from being open source users to actually paying customers?
Okay. And, you know, this is probably the most stressful thing an open source maintainer,
founder, someone in the open source space has. Because ultimately, you're looking at
this open source adoption and let's say you're tracking 100 million downloads, but nobody
wants to pay for anything. That's actually a use case that happens quite a bit. How do
you, how do you, how do you figure that out? How do you, how do you turn that 100 million
downloads? How do you turn that, you know, 5,000 people who are tweeting about you into
something that is actually commercially viable?
And when we go look at the classic sort of marketing funnel, and anybody here in marketing,
I'm just curious. No one, well, one person, two people want to admit it. Hey, three people.
Okay. Oh, look at that. All right. So you might be familiar with this if you are in
marketing, right? So this is just this very simple marketing funnel where you've got,
you know, people who are hitting your website and they turn into a contact or a lead, if
you will, where they become a known user and then they turn into a marketing qualified
lead after they do a certain number of things. So let's say you're there on your website,
sign up for a webinar, maybe they downloaded your software, maybe they did a few other
things. They get a certain number of points and when they reach the point value, then
all of a sudden it's like, woo hoo, you are now qualified. So then sales can talk to you.
And then you have a, you know, sales accepted lead. So sales goes, ooh, that looks pretty
good. And then you have a sales qualified lead when they start to say, hmm, I think
I could sell something. All right. This is the classic marketing funnel, but it doesn't
work in an open source space. There is a similar way to think about this, okay? Because the
open source model kind of flips this on its head. There is this model where we've got
the interest phase, which is the people who are discovering what your product can do,
how it can behave, what it can do differently. And you want them to actually try your software,
okay? You want them to install your software or use your containers or use your library
in, you know, their product. And only a subset of those who are actually interested, a subset
of those who will visit your project's webpage, visit your webpages, visit your assets, they're
all, only that small subset is going to actually try. And of those who try, only a subset will
continue to use it in production. And then only a subset will become a customer. So that
model is very important because as we look at this phase, you've got to realize that
if you have a million people on your website and you have 100,000 downloads, that's great.
But there might only be 10,000 who use it in production and that might only have like
a thousand people who would be willing to pay for it. Now, some of you who are familiar
with the product space might say, well, we don't follow the funnel, we follow the, you
know, product flywheel, the product growth flywheel. So anybody familiar with the product
growth flywheel? All right, one. Okay. So the idea is, it's funny because they actually
stole a lot of this from the open source movement. When you look at the product flywheel, and
this is all the hotness in all the product companies, right? So when we're talking about
a product led company, a product, you know, product led growth, what they're talking about is people
start off in this center, this core, and it's like, oh, how do we track and engage with
people? How do we delight them? How do we make them really excited about things? Okay.
And then we can take those strangers, turn them into prospects, which then turns them
into customers, which then turns them into fans. And then they will start to become the
people who will preach to the other people to tell other people how awesome our software
is and get them into the community. There's an open source version of this. And again,
excuse my crappy little, you know, diagrams here. If someone wants to contribute these
better versions, that's awesome. But the idea here is it's very similar, similar phases.
But if you look at the differences, the differences are we have a download and try, we have that
build and deploy into production. And then we have, oh, they're running it into prod.
And then it kind of goes into, hey, do I need something more? That's when I'd be willing
to pay. And then you'll evaluate a paid option and become that paying customer. It's a very
similar cycle. Both are the same, but there's a few differences. I like to clarify this
a little bit more in the open source space because it makes sense. Because really what
you're talking about here is someone who's trying your open source software, they're
getting used to it. They're like, wow, this is pretty cool. But if it only did this next
thing, and then you're like, oh, well, I have that. It's in the enterprise version. Right?
If it only did, you know, you know, integration with this other product. And so that's where,
oh, I need something more. And then you get them to evaluate it. And that becomes a way
to build external evangelists. So there's also this idea of evangelism or evangelists.
A way to foster people who are in your community, who become fans of your product, who then
actually go out and contribute to that flywheel. Right? So the goal here is you want someone
who can start off telling people, wow, I was really successful with this application. And
then they'll tell their followers and people who like them and people who are like-minded.
And then those people will watch that content. And then those people will go ahead and try
it. And it's similar when you add dev rel, evangelism, this is all part of that product
flywheel, where you want more people to understand it and then eventually try it. And then eventually
you want those people to create or help foster new people into the community where there
are new evangelists who can go out there and talk about your product.
So let's talk specifically about driving open source adoption. Okay? And there's only three
things you need to do. Yeah, I'm going to sound like one of those shill salesmen on
the late night TV commercials where it's like, you know, these three things, if you buy into
my system, you'll be awesome. This will be the best thing ever for you. And so there's
actually three requirements that we'll dig into a little bit as much as we can in the
time remaining for driving open source adoption and growing your open source adoption. And
those secrets to the success are a kiss-ass product. Okay? It all starts with the product.
If you don't have a product that people want, it doesn't matter what else you do. They're
not going to, you know, listen to you. They're not going to try it out. It needs to be rock
solid. We need people to know who you are. Okay? A lot of open source projects that are
out there have awesome technology behind them, but nobody knows who they are. Has anybody
run into a product like, and said, like, how did I not know about that like three years
ago? Right? That happens. And why is that? Because, however, you know, whoever's running
these projects, they're not really sure how to bring awareness to everyone else. And then
you need to make it easier than all the alternatives out there in the space. Okay? Obvious, right?
All these are obvious. It's not like it's like anything that's just crazy. All these
should be obvious and easy as well. Now, I can't go into a deep dive for all of these,
but briefly I want to touch on each one, and we'll go through each one separately. So how
do you build a kick-ass open source project? Now, I can tell you, like, you know, all the
technical jargon, but I'm going to stick with from a business perspective what this looks
like. First, I want to talk about the biggest mistake we all make when we're building a
project. At a certain point, we have to realize that, you know, when we are building a project,
we're often starting it, building it for what we want. And that works for maybe, like, a
little bit of time. And you might even make a successful company, but you're going to
limit your growth if you are building for people who you think are the exact same people
as you. Right? It's that, oh, I assume everyone is like me. I know people who follow this,
and they're like, well, I assume that everyone is going to install on the command line. I
assume everyone will install from source. And so that's just the way that they think.
That's not necessarily how everyone else in the community thinks. So make sure that you
avoid that. And that's why the first key, in my opinion, is understanding. Right? Understand
the product and its value. Right? What can your product do better than anyone else? Okay?
Are people willing to even pay for that? You should ask yourself that question. Can you
answer that question? What do you do over the alternative? Right? So is there an alternative
to this? Is there some other piece of software, something else that other people are doing?
What do you consider success? Now, this one is really interesting. I've talked to a lot
of founders. I've talked to a lot of CEOs, executives. And, you know, they'll talk to
me about, oh, we want to accelerate our growth, our adoption. And I'll say, well, what's your
goal? And they'll be like, well, we want to, you know, sell the company, or we want 10X
valuation, or we want, like, you know, fill in the blank. It's like, no, no, no. What
do you really want? What do you want in the next year? What do you really, really want?
And a lot of times it's like, oh, well, really what we want is people to sign up for our
new beta. I've actually had that conversation where it's like, we just want like a thousand
people to try it and then give us feedback. Well, it's a very different sort of product
that you're building and sort of, and also marketing activities or community activities
that you're doing. And so that's something to consider. Who's going to use it? Are you
building this for, you know, devs? Are you building this for business folks? Who's the
end user? Who's going to benefit from this the most? And who would pay for that product
if they're in that space? And where are those users most likely to be? You know, are these
users going to be at Fostem? Are they going to be at like, you know, open source summit?
Are they going to be at KubeCon? I mean, like, where will you see these people pop up? And
how do you ensure that you know where they are and what sort of things that they like
and what sort of things that they need? And so you want to understand that really early
on, even if you're not trying to monetize or commercialize the open source yet, you
know, you want to keep that in the back of your mind and start to funnel things in that
right direction. Now, the next key is to listen and ask questions.
Now remember I said a big mistake people make is the founder builds the software specifically
for themselves and they don't necessarily take into account other people in the ecosystem.
And this is where product success is really determined based on your users and your potential
users and listening to their needs. If you're not listening to their needs, you're going
to be missing out on a lot of opportunity for growth. And that's where that mistake
comes in. So avoid that if you can. The other one is you have to set a goal and
focus on it. Be really good at a few things, not really okay at a lot of things because
there's a lot of other software you might be competing with. There's a lot of other
people who are potentially solving the same issues. And it's really easy to get distracted
by shiny object syndrome. Anybody get distracted by shiny object syndrome? I'm like that all
the time. Yeah, I see hands waving all the time. And that is so easy to do. In fact,
I was just talking with Avi our CEO over here and we're talking about tracking webpage stuff
and I'm like oh we can do that in our product. But we're like wait a minute, that's not our
core product. Why would we go down that hole? But people do that a lot and when you do that
it might be cool and you might learn that there's a new subset and there might be a
time for expanding your product but until your core product has that established base
you don't want to do that. So don't deviate too often. Stick to that original purpose.
And if you do that you will eventually find that you become better known in the market.
People are willing to talk about you, use you and then share additional contributions
to maybe make your project a little better. Okay, this one's a big one. All right. Has
to meet or exceed expectations. Now this totally seems obvious, right? But let's assume that
I build a cell phone and my cell phone has the awesomest speakers, the awesomest music
system and it is the best gaming platform ever but it can't take calls. Is it still
a cell phone? If I market it as a cell phone, if I sell it as a cell phone, if I say oh
this is my cell phone, it doesn't matter. It's not. So if I'm trying to build a cell
phone but it is great at just music and gaming but it can't take a call I have not met the
expectations of that. And that's where you need to figure out what are the table stakes
for your project. What are the key ingredients? Whatever those are that's where you have to
focus. And that means do the job that it was originally intended to do and meet some
minimum standards. And there are minimum standards that we all have from an open source perspective.
Okay. What are some of those minimum standards? Hey, you know what? It has to be secure, right?
Like who wants an insecure piece of software nowadays? Well, we have too many of them.
Let's not add any more. But it has to protect from data loss. I don't want leaky data. You
know how much you know how many times my personal data's been leaked? My daughter's going to
inherit free credit monitoring for the rest of her life because I've had so many data
leaks. I mean, I think there's several Matt Yackovits running around right now. Maybe
even at this conference. So, you know, it also has to be as bug free as possible. Now,
while we strive, I'll strive for bug free software. We know it's not a viable thing.
But shipping with known critical bugs is bad. And I know some companies who do it just to
meet deadlines. It's not good. Next up is UI UX. Any UI UX guys? There are people on
here. A few? Okay. Awesome. Oh, yes. Many, many. All right. Well, so it's like this.
If your product is designed like this elevator, that's really confusing. Isn't it? I mean,
UI UX is probably one of the most important things to get right. The user experience can
ruin an awesome technical project. You can have the best technology out there, and if
the user interface sucks, people won't use it. Or they'll use it once, which is even
worse. So a bad user experience can ruin any benefits that you provide. GitHub is littered
with projects like this, by the way. So of the millions and millions of projects that
are out there, many of them fall victim to this, even if they are really solid. And if
you want to grow your community and grow adoption, easy. Remember, easy was my point number three.
You know, you need users who can be advanced if they want to and get into the weeds, but
most of the users won't. And again, that gets back to that assumption that we build things
for ourselves. A lot of CTOs, a lot of cofounders, a lot of people in this space, what they think
is I'm super technical, and they are. They're building a company. Those out there in the
space where founders, you know, at that executive level, maybe they're maintainers or projects,
you are all brilliant. And that means that your brilliance probably exceeds your average
users brilliance. That's okay. But keep that in mind. So make it easy for folks. And my
product key number six is community. Open source projects need community. And we need
to bake that in to the beginning. Okay. And that means including plans for fostering that
strong community up front. Now, I brought this up. I was previewing my slides and someone,
you know, said, wait a minute. What about curl? Does curl really have a strong community
of contributors? Right? And this is what I say is we have to look beyond code. This isn't
just about code. You want people who will use your product. And if you search for curl,
for instance, you know, your favorite search engine, you're going to find thousands of
examples of how to use curl. Right? You will. You can do it right now if you want. Tutorials,
examples, cool things, hacks, whatever. That's community even if it's not code contributions.
And that's what you need to continue that product growth. All right. Moving on. Now
we're talking about how do we super charge the awareness? All righty. So let's talk specifically
about community. Anybody here in the community space? Oh, a few people. Oh, yeah. Okay. Great.
So this is the great hope for adoption in open source companies. In fact, a lot of people
will prioritize a dev rel hire over any of the business hires because they want to start
to connect directly with that community. Okay. And it's this is a balance, but the community
can really help accelerate and drive that awareness if done right. But here's the thing.
Okay. Community is starting to turn into the new marketing. For the last five years, the
last ten years, marketing has often been in control of community. Community has been a
subset of marketing, sometimes a subset of product. But ultimately, this shift in mindset
where the community is so important and it's driving so many conversations, it's supplanting
marketing. And there are reasons that you still need marketing. But in the future, I
think that what we'll see is the community team has marketing as a function, not community
as a function of marketing, which is a different way to think of it. And that's a real mind
shift for a lot of people in the business space. But if we do approach this from a community
first approach, we can accelerate and grow the open source space even faster. And that
gets back to this expectation, right? So when we talk about that expectation, I mentioned
earlier that funnel, the flywheel, you know, when we're talking about, hey, can we have
people in the community who talk about us and then turn into followers of us who then
continue to watch our things and then who continue to try and use our software in different
ways. That's the ultimate outcome that we want. And when we talk about this community
team, there's multiple functions in it. This is a chart that I've used several times before,
but, you know, we're talking about dev rel or evangelism, we're talking about community
management, we're talking about these Ospo roles with contributors. All of these things
are part of a strong community team. All of them need to be satisfied. Now, a lot of us
will focus only on evangelism and then they won't do the other functions. Or they'll focus
only on the contributors and not do the other functions. And so all three of these are needed
for a healthy, healthy ecosystem. Now, what are some popular ways to grow open source
adoption? Okay. These are probably obvious for anybody who's been in the open source
space for a while or been in the community, but they're classic, right? Content, number
one, right? Content. Everybody loves content. The more relevant content that you have, the
more code examples that you can share, the more conference talks that are relevant to
people, the more blogs you write, you know, those will make a difference. Tutorial sample
applications and whatnot. All of these things are things that are important to those in
the community. There's other activities you can do, especially when your product solves
something that's newsworthy. Has anybody heard of the term newsjacking? No? Okay. A couple
people. It's the idea that, you know, if there's something in the news cycle like, you know,
oh, the latest hack and, you know, or whatever, if there's an opportunity for you to maybe
talk to people about how to build better products. If your product or your company does something
differently that solves these other issues, this is a way for you to use the stories that
are already out there to reach additional people. You know, if somebody's hacked or
some cloud provider goes down, well, this is how we would prevent that, you know, or
here's how our software did this differently. Those types of things actually can have a
really far wide reach because those are things that are on top of people's minds. Now, you
also need to generate friends telling friends, right? So that peer to peer connection, if
you will, of people who are willing to share their experiences and share the different,
you know, goodness of your software. And that goes hand in hand with some other things like
good messaging and products and making it easier to start. Now, how do we make this
easier? That's key. The first one is it requires a lot of collaboration. It's a choreographed
dance. Okay? So making this easier is you have to have not only easier products to use,
you not only need a great user experience, you also need to make sure that you have enough
information, enough tutorials, enough example code, enough out there in the community activity
to merge those together because you have to have good product as well as strong community
as long as strong content, good documentation to make this work. And so that easy is important,
but it goes beyond just one team's function. You know, and some of those key things or
some of those things that I see people sometimes stumble with or sometimes fall down on are
things like installation. You know, so how easy it is to install and get started. Same
defaults. How many people have installed software and it's like how did you not set that up?
Like why isn't that defaulted to on? You know, like encryption. Oh, encryption is just left
off by default. Or my favorite is, and I don't even know if maybe there's somebody here who's
run Mongo recently, but they used to not set a default password because they're like, oh,
you don't want to limit people from getting started. Well, how can you not set a default
password? By the way, that's the number one reason MongoDB has like data leaks. You know,
you read these articles and it's like, oh, because these old, you know, these old installations
didn't set a password. I don't consider that a security issue. That's more of a user issue,
but that's a whole other story. How much automation do you put in place to help users? That's
another critical one. Again, UI, UX, and how easy it is to debug problems. You know, if
your problems, if the software crashes or has an issue or doesn't work as expected,
do you have the right debugging in place for people to actually find what's wrong and fix
it? Because if not, that's going to cause a really, really, really hard time in getting
people to operationalize it. So we talked about, you know, kick ass product.
We talked about, you know, the awareness. We talked about, you know, how to make it
easy. Now I got to put on my other hat. I do have another hat. It's my metrics hat.
I got to wear my metrics hat for my metrics section of this. So we're going to talk about
how do we track open source usage and adoption now. Okay. And there's really kind of four
or five major functions that I want to talk through. Awareness, usage, conversion, customers,
and retention. Okay. And this kind of follows that funnel and that flywheel that we talked
about originally. This is one of those things that, you know, each one of these requires
a certain set of things to potentially look at. You don't have to look at all of these,
but these are metrics that you should all consider and then pick and choose which ones
make the most sense for your business. But when we talk about awareness, okay, a lot
of people start with the first one on this list. So how many people track GitHub stars?
Okay. Hey, you know, GitHub stars are a popularity contest, by the way. Did you know that? Like,
it really is. Because it actually doesn't really show much other than people like your
project or maybe they like people on your project. And did you know that for only $5.99
I can get you a thousand stars on GitHub? There are services that do that. And so I
don't know how many of the stars are actually real or not in some cases. It's hard to tell.
But you should be looking at that because if it is going up and to the right and you're
not gaming the system, that is a good indication that people are finding your project. But
keep in mind from a project perspective, there are more users than there are users who will
go to your GitHub page and get into your repository. And that's something to consider. Unless you're
forcing people to go and install, you know, via source or your documentation is on GitHub,
you might have more people who are downloading some other mechanism. Maybe they're getting
from a third party repo. Maybe they're just going to your website and getting it. So they
might never go star or even see your GitHub pages. But looking at not only GitHub pages,
but your traffic to your docs, your website, your different pieces of content and understanding
who is interacting with it, that's another critical piece to this. And that's a classic
marketing thing. A lot of people look at, you know, the website traffic. But you also
want to look at those unique views to each individual page. All of those are critical
to look at. Now, what's interesting when we talk about page views is we've had conversations
with folks who talk about page views and they're like, there are certain pages that don't matter
and then there are certain pages that do. And so understanding and being able to segment
your traffic and look at who is looking at what is a very important thing to understanding
that growth and adoption. So, for instance, if someone looks at your pricing page, that's
probably a good indicator that they might be interested in something commercial. If
someone is looking at your documentation, that's a pretty good indicator that they're
trying to install or debug an issue. If they're looking at tutorials on how to get started,
that's a very good indication that, again, they're trying to use your software. And so
you can track adoption through looking at those types of things. Now, when we talk about
external evangelists and trying to get additional people into the ecosystem to talk about you
or to figure out, like, what you're doing or, you know, maybe, you know, get excited
about your product, looking at the referrals to the website is another really good example.
So I can see your blog or your blog pointed back to my website or your social tweet mentioned
me. These referrals are often more critical than the website traffic on itself. Now, there's
also two concepts that are really squishy. I won't get into a terrible amount of details
if you're really interested. Check out opensourcemetrics.com or.org. But share a voice. Have you heard
a share a voice before? No? Okay. Think of share a voice is how often does the project
or the thing come into people's minds or how often does it show up in search? How much
of the market do you have? So, for instance, if I was to say to you, like, you know, when
I say Linux, what pops into your mind? Like, what distribution pops into your mind? I'm
going to guess most of you are probably going to say one of, like, three or four. But there's
lots of other ones. And so those three or four have a higher share of voice than everyone
else. And so if you can measure how much of your share of voices, then you know how much
of the market you potentially, you know, can reach out. And then when you have something
to say, people are going to potentially listen. And then there's this idea of social reach.
Now, probably everyone here has different social accounts on different platforms. And
it's awesome. And the question is how much of a reach do you have? And this is, you know,
measured by the number of followers, the amount of engagement. And the reason you want a larger
social reach from an awareness standpoint is when you do have an announcement, when
you launch a new product, when you talk about a new release, when you do have something
important to say, this helps amplify that voice. Now, from a usage perspective, usage
is where the adoption really comes into play here. Okay. Usage is how many people are actually
using your software? All right. Now, I know a lot of companies have struggled with usage
on the open source side. There's a lot of times people come back and they ask the question,
well, who's using our open source software? And the answer a lot of times is, I don't
know, you know, certain number of people, this number of people hit the download webpage.
But there's so many different places to get, you know, that information. I can't really
get it. But some people can get raw download numbers. Anybody look at download numbers
for their software? A few? Okay. It's hard to get. It really is. Especially when you're
looking at, you know, I deploy via Docker. Some people are doing source. Some people
have packages. So that is a challenge. But it's important to understand if there are
more people downloading, that's good. But you have to be careful. Because a lot, I'm
going to tell you a secret. There are a lot of bots on the Internet. I don't know if you
knew that. Don't tell anybody. And those bots download stuff. In fact, what we've found
is a lot of times we might have a project. And so one of the things that I mentioned
that SCARF does is it tracks, you know, things like downloads and download metrics. But what
we found was stuff like, oh, this project has, you know, 50,000 downloads a month from
two people. It's like, well, wait a minute. There's only two people actually downloading.
So when you see 50,000 downloads, but you see only like two unique people, you're like,
well, what is that? And then you dig into it and it's some bot that's downloading it
and distributing it some other way. So that's important to realize that that is something
that can happen. You want to look at that. But you want to look at that scrubbed unique
download. So how many people are actually downloading versus how many people are, you
know, just downloading and it could be bots or duplications. A lot of companies download
the same software over and over again. A lot of people in their pipelines will download
the latest version of software, et cetera. New users, new companies coming into the ecosystem.
That's really important for usage. Signups. So if you are a SAS provider, you're offering
a free trial. Maybe you have a webinar, maybe you have a mailing list, maybe you have Slack.
Signups are another thing that you want to track for usage, but that's not necessarily
going to correlate to actual usage of the open source. But again, that's more of a directionally
correct up into the right. You know, so the one that is really on the bottom here, the
last four, this one's sticky. This one's tough for me. Call home metrics. So most of the
people in the open source space hate the concept of anything that's going to call home. It's
not necessarily always welcome, but there's a certain amount that might be needed for
projects. And the question is, where is that line? And when I talk about call home metrics,
is something running? Is it installed? Is it available? How many things are running at
any one time? These are critical questions that a lot of projects struggle with. Just
because even if you have a download doesn't necessarily mean that download actually translated
into an actual user. And so you want to make sure that you can go back and forth between,
yeah, they downloaded, but they stopped using. Because if they downloaded and stopped using
or never actually use it on a regular basis, that's a very different thing than someone
who's just downloaded and you assume that they're using it.
Now before we get into conversions, I want to say that just because you have adoption
of your open source software doesn't necessarily mean that that's going to lead to commercial
success. Okay? How many people, I mean, there might be some people in here, and maybe you're
willing to raise your hand, but I know that several people that I've talked to struggle
with this, where they're like, I have a million downloads a month, but I can't get anybody
to buy anything from me. You know? Oh yeah, there we go. We have one brave soul. That
happens quite a bit. And it gets back to some of those product things, and there's a lot
of reasons or things that you can do to try and change that. But it gets back to this
expectations on the awareness versus what the business expects. And from a metric standpoint,
you've got the two sides, right? So when you talk about the community side, the adoption
of open source side, a lot of times our efforts are around fostering that really strong community.
And then there's this big question mark in the middle, and then on the business side,
then there's, oh, now we want ARR. Now we want to look at expansion numbers and churn
and all this other stuff. So how do you bridge the gap between these two? And this is where
conversion comes into play. And conversion's a bad word for people, right? You know, yeah,
you will be assimilated. You know, we want that from the open source side, right? It
might be a negative connotation, but I think it's funny. But I do have a super evil little
hat. So, but you do want those conversion metrics. You want people to say, okay, what
does it take to go from free to paid? And to measure that, okay, there's different
things to look at, right? That conversion is impacted by a lot of different things,
and each one of these are things you can measure from a product. You know, you want better
features, better security, you know, you want support, things like that. From a policy perspective,
you know, companies often will require support or they might have compliance requirements,
so how do you meet them? And then people, right? So all these things affect your conversion
ratios. But looking at conversion ratios you can actually control, you want to look at
things like page docs or source to download conversion ratios, doc views to those who
have downloaded, to those who eventually signed up, if you can track that, that's great.
I know that in the past I've had to go through and do stuff like that where I've seen, I
mean, actual example where it's like company A, this really large company, four years ago
started looking at our blogs. And then they attended conferences, they did all this other
stuff, and then two years they called us up and had a conversation, and then a year later
they did something else. So there are breadcrumbs when you look that you can actually see what
people are doing and what sort of activities help lead them to be a customer. Now, customers,
when we talk about customer metrics, we're talking about standard business metrics. So
these are the ones that most people who are running an open source company are familiar
with. The critical ones, things like the number of new customers or new logos, ARR, MRR, you
know, stuff like that. So I'm not going to go terribly deep into this because there are
MBA courses that cover a lot of these and I don't want to necessarily go in depth. But
the ones that I look at typically, the big three, number of customers, number of new logos,
and yeah, the ARR, MRR. And then also I look at the user to customer ratio. So if you know
you have a million users and you have only five paying customers, how do you adjust that?
How do you tweak it? How do you make that work better? And then I also look at the number
of customers who are also advocating for us. From a retention and churn perspective, churn
is the idea that people start using and then go away. So you want to look at those, you
want to look at the number of instances that have gone away. You also want to do some competitive
analysis, right? So if you have users and customers who are starting to use other open
source projects or take a look at other things, you might want to be aware of that. So recapping,
not all businesses, open source businesses are the same. Realistically build an awesome
project, focus on the funnel and of course measure it. All of these things will help
lead you to open source success. Again, if you are interested in getting more details
about any of the metrics or learning a little bit about what's been successful for other
folks, check out open source metrics.org. You can contribute to it if you think that
there is something that is missing, something that you think we should work better, definitions,
et cetera. We would love to have your feedback and help there. Details if you want to reach
out to me. Be happy to have conversations with anybody offline. And that is it for me.
Questions? Oh, we got one question. Oh, two. We're running mics to people. We're running
mics to people in the crowd, it looks like. Oh, it's not working. Ah, okay. Well, maybe
you should shout. Maybe now. You mentioned collecting metrics from users, but because
of the GDPR you need informed consent that you're allowed to collect metrics. In your
experience, what's the percentage of users that actually allow to do that? Is it like
1% or 10%? It's generally more than you would think. I mean, it's at least a third, maybe
more. And beyond that, there are metrics that aren't tied to PII that can show those indicators
going up and to the right. Just because you know that you have web page traffic or downloads,
even if you don't know specifically who they are, you can still see those up and to the
right and those are just as important in a lot of cases. And that's why you have to pick
and choose which ones make the most sense. And in a lot of cases, what it is is it's
about building that community and that relationship so they're willing to share details. And how
you do that and how you make sure is you don't do old slimy sales tactics. You don't want
to spam people. You don't want to call them. Look, let people raise their hand when they're
ready and that helps people a lot. And when people go to bat for you and tell other people,
hey, you should sign up for the newsletter. You should sign up for this. And then they
give you that consent. That helps a lot. Thanks. Yeah. Oh, other way. Other way. Yeah. All
right. We had a couple more questions. We've got one in the middle, one in the end, one
down here. Hello. Yes. Okay. So I was one of the folks that raised their hands when
you asked what are we know, open core. So I don't, but then you started explaining and
I say, okay, that's like Freeman. So I just was asking, could you explain the difference
between open core and freemium? Ah, so yeah. So freemium is where, you know, your first
taste is free and then, you know, you can, you can get more later on. Open core has been
a lot around a lot longer than quote unquote freemium. Okay. And typically from a freemium
strategy, you're going to pay more as you go. Um, and so having like a cloud service where
the first, let's say a hundred gigs of data or something that you store is free and then
it goes on, that's more of that freemium strategy. But from an open source perspective, how I
view open core is you've got a complete product that's running. You don't have to pay for
anything. And if you wanted to augment it or change it on your own, you can. I think
freemium typically comes in my mind and more into play on the cloud side where you've got
more of that, you know, kind of like ongoing service where you're paying for something
where you can't necessarily replace it or pull it out. But it's a fine line and it's
really difficult to draw that line and a lot of people might go back and forth. Oh, it
looks like our time is up. I'm happy to answer your question if you want to come down and
we can, we can chat afterwards. That's cool. I appreciate your time. Um, I do. Thank you
very much.