Thank you all for coming and staying so long. I'm positively surprised and impressed. I'm
a bit nervous. I hope I entertain you well and don't make a mess out of this. Who of
you thought that this title was clickbait? That's fair. It's clickbait, a little bit.
But I'm also serious about it. I think it's a serious issue. Quick introduction. I will
not read this to you and you already heard it. I think the key point, I work at Red Hat,
yes. My motivation for this talk is informed by my experience at Red Hat, but really I've
been an open source, free software for a long time and I'm really committed to that. That's
the reason why I work at Red Hat, not vice versa. Also, I have to give this disclaimer.
Nothing I say here is official position of any of my former current or future employers,
although it may be the same things I tell my employer. So take that as you wish.
Let's get on the topic. Why do I say that the cloud is a threat to free and open source
software? Because while free software has democratized the access to code at rest, so
code in a repository, taking that code and actually operationalizing it, running it, has
become a new proprietary differentiator even on top of free software. In my experience,
that is undermining both the usefulness and the sustainability of free software. Let me
explain that a little bit. Why do we do free software? I trust everyone here in this room
knows the definition of free software, so I'm not going to belabor that. I'll use open
source free software for synonymously. We can discuss that over beer later if you want.
The point is that you have the freedom to use software, and it matters. It's important
because before free software, code was a major proprietary differentiator. Proprietary code
was also the major entry hurdle for accessing technology. It incentivized centralization
and walled gardens and thus became an inhibitor or was an inhibitor to innovation. It created
and maintained dependencies and lock-ins. You were dependent on the decisions of someone
else who had authority over the code that you used. Back then, that was the reason why
it was annoying. Maybe it wasn't as big of an issue as it today, but the world has changed
and I'll get to that. Free software, in contrast to proprietary code, levels the playing field
and it democratizes the access to technology. It incentivizes open collaboration and offers
a base for technical sovereignty, sovereignty being the state where you have authority over
your technology. That's my own path to open source. I got to open source because I was
in high school and I needed a compiler. I was using OS 2 at the time. I guess my age
based on that. I was using OS 2 because DOS and Windows were not my thing. The TOBOSy
compiler I had used on DOS didn't work on OS 2 and IBM wanted a lot of money for a compiler.
Luckily, there was this guy DJ Delorey who also happens to work at Reddit nowadays, who
had poured the GCC to OS 2 and that is what saved me. Let me use a compiler on OS 2 and
that's what got me into free software. The key point here was that I was excluded from
access to technology. I was excluded from being able to use something to write my own
code on that platform that I happened to be running. I could have switched platforms but
would have run into similar problems. There was a different, there were other compilers
that were maybe cheaper but the problem became obvious to me because of the pricing that
made it inaccessible for me. That removed the hurdle.
Sovereignty is a big topic right now. For me, it starts with individual sovereignty.
That becomes an issue for any organization. If as a business, you are dependent on other
people's decisions or in Europe that's a big topic nowadays. Even as a state or union
of states, you become dependent on other people's technology decisions, that's creating major
risk. Free software is the antidote for that. It provides you an environment that lets you
control your own technology and it creates an environment where access to technology
is fully democratized. It provides incentives for collaboration. It creates a better innovation
model that's based on collaboration. Now I'm repeating myself. Apologies for that. It
creates this level of sovereignty and control over your code. That's why it matters. That
is something that in the cloud is becoming harder to do. What happened is that software
aids the world. Everything is software defined now. An example I often use is the connected
mousetrap I have in my basement. Mousetrap is a pretty, pretty simple software. It's
a mouse trap. A mouse trap is a pretty old concept doing something very physical. Now
I have a mouse trap that has a microcontroller, talks to my network and tells me through a
cloud backend with a front end on my mobile phone when it did its business so I don't
find it weeks later. That's software defined now. I bought this one because it has software
features. That shows how integrated our lives become. It's a silly example, but it shows
how integrated our lives have become with software. How things are defined by software.
I always go back to Lawrence Lessig's book in late 1990s or early 2000s that he wrote
called Code where he argues that code becomes law because it defines our ability to interact
with the world increasingly. I came across that in the context of the fight against software
patents in Europe in the early 2000s. I think that's become more and more reality. Everything
we do is more defined by code. That is not defined by code at rest anymore. It's not
defined by code in a repository. It's defined by code that's running somewhere. The software,
well, open source is a base for that. The cloud is built on open source. The software
the complexity of modern software, the integration in the world has left and the dependencies
that everything now has on that has led to a model where users, commercial users, private
users, increasingly just build on top of services provided by someone else. It's just a function
of complexity versus utility of something. If I need a database, I can click a button,
I get a database. I don't have to become an expert in deploying databases myself. I don't
need to figure out how to find the right infrastructure for it. I just press a button, it works.
I can focus on the top 10% of my solution stack where I implement my, as a business,
I implement my proprietary differentiation. I will use that. But the price for that is
a dependency on a service that in itself may be based on open source code, but the step
from taking the code that's in a repository to putting together multiple pieces of code
into a running service and running that service, keeping it running, keeping it secure and
integrating with other things increasingly becomes proprietary. It becomes the proprietary
differentiation to the degree that less and less people can actually run services on their
own. Why is that? Because the knowledge of running things in this complex interconnected
world gets harder. It's hard to keep things secure, even configuring them secure, which
you can see in the news, basically daily base, is hard. People fail and all kinds of data
shows up in places it shouldn't be. That becoming a new, that knowledge, so it's not just, it's
not the question whether, and this goes back to the definition of free software, my complaint
is not that I may have to pay for a service. My complaint is that the knowledge on how
to go from code in a repository to a running service, that knowledge in itself has become
a proprietary differentiator that's creating walled gardens and that removes access to
technology. I'm guilty myself in actually falling into that trap. I mean, I don't run
my own mail server anymore, which has been, I don't know how many of you are in that camp,
who runs their own mail server? Yeah, that's sad really. I mean, in this audience, I was
wondering whether I should dare ask this question because I would have felt really silly if
like all of you would have raised their hand and say, I'll run my own mail server, Daniel,
you idiot. But like in reality, why don't I run my own mail servers? Because I can't,
like I don't have the time to do it and keep it secure and keep my family on it and deal
with the support requests of that and provide the same access from every device that I get
if they are just on Google mail, right? But that's a compromise I make for the ease of
use, the utility of it, and in the end it creates a dependency. Now I have the situation,
I'm going a bit off script here, but I just write, like now they are scanning my mail
for certain legal violations, right? And they will forward certain types of violations automatically
to the police and lock you out of your account. I think that wasn't Google. There was a case
recently where a family got into trouble for like a photo they had of their kid, like traditional
family photo that was flagged as inappropriate and they lost access to their mail account.
I don't say which vendor that was, but you can Google that in the US, right? And they
are locked out forever because algorithm decided that that was not acceptable. And it's all
well intended, right? But it shows what it means to not have technology sovereignty,
right? You are now dependent on an algorithm that might be very badly implemented that
then decides whether you lose access to your own data because it recognized a violation
with the best intentions, but sometimes, you know, dangerous consequences. And we'll see
more of that, right? Because there's a whole different thing I'm not talking about today
that's happening with artificial intelligence and further integration of these systems into
cloud services. So my point here at the end comes down to that, like, the question, it's
great that we have free software, right? It's great that we have revolutionized the access
to technology, access to code. We have revolutionized the business where free software has one.
It's a base for all modern software development to some degree, right? There's always something
like proprietary differentiation in code, right? Now, I would imagine it's limited kind
of to the top of the code pyramid, right? When it becomes like the things that one company
writes in-house, right? Their own business differentiations, that's always proprietary,
right? That's where your trade secrets are. And that's okay, right? So it's shaking the
head. Like, it's a separate way. But you will, like, at a point where something becomes so
unique, right, you get into the question with a... No. We can debate it in a question and
answer. I see it. But I think, so ultimately I respect people doing that, right? But then
you get down to something is domain specific. Maybe there's some proprietary stuff in there.
But latest you're like outside of like one specific industry, you get into free software
frameworks that everyone is using. Because all this stuff on the business side that's
common, their free software is a huge advantage. Because it gives you the ability to collaborate
among competitors, to not reinvent things all the time, to get to common standards in
a very practical way, right? Because code is better than a standard. So that works.
But how much use is it really if you cannot run it anymore on your own without a dependency
on someone who is a big centralized provider? And the issue here, you know, that goes into
that is true for individuals, it's true for organizations, it's true for civil society,
that is true for companies that are not as big as some other companies. You always create
these dependencies. Because of the talent gaps and just the knowledge gaps and the risk
included in it. And this has allowed the leading cloud providers to create centralized economies
of scale based around their proprietary operational knowledge. And it's really useful. You click
a button, you get anything you need in infrastructure. This sometimes includes unfair strip mining
of free software projects, right? We've all seen that. They can do that just because of
the scale of operationalization. It has nothing to do with the code. It has led to a situation
where sometimes code itself is actually commoditized, right? Your challenge is not writing the code.
You can't get enough people together to write the code. Really the problem comes running
it and creating the economy of scale and adoption that makes it successful. And that is a dynamic
that basically goes back to the mainframe. We went full circle and now we are running
black box services on someone else's hardware. How do we do that? And then we have a lot
of black box services on someone else's hardware. It's a convenient model but it's really creating
lock-ins. And it's the same kind of lock-in and access hurdle that code used to be when I was in high school.
It was impossible for many people to get to that level of technology even if they knew how to code
in a sustainable way. And now we are getting back there. And there are plenty of examples
how this goes even into how we create free software. This is not just a problem in using or deploying it.
It affects our own creation. If you write modern cloud-native software, you aggregate existing
services and you focus on the last 10% of what you really care about. You don't have to worry about
anything else because you can use that from the cloud provider. If you're doing free software, then you
have to run everything yourself because we haven't expanded free software to solve this problem.
We can take prominent examples. Who here uses GitHub? Does it include GitHub issues and things like that?
Who thinks that GitHub is open source software or free software?
It's great. It's a great service. It's a great tool. Git is free software. GitHub and everything
around the code management itself. When you go into issues, actions, integrations.
It's owned by Microsoft, yes?
I'm not going to go there. I have a similar comment who I work for. I don't want to have prejudice against
Microsoft. Slack is not on Slack. We can go around and around and we will find that even the development
of free software depends more on proprietary services. Software as a service.
This is not necessarily criticism in these companies. I believe that everyone has a choice to
offer their software and their service under the license in terms of services they see appropriate.
But it's a problem for me where I think there should be an alternative. We need to think about how
sustainable this is in the long term. Can we get to a model where free and open source software
development can be integrated with other free and open source software development in a consistent
model end to end? Where it regains its utility all the way to running code. That is the underlying
problem. Having code and then not being able to actually offer the service or run your own mail
server. A big topic that everyone here is probably aware of is the switch towards the
Fediverse right now which is great. Which brings more attention to this issue. People are trying to
run their own instances of a decentralized social network now. They're finding out that's actually
really hard. That's going to get ugly before it gets good if people don't run back to the
centralized wall garden because it's too hard. But that makes a point.
Ultimately right now while the Fediverse I think is far ahead. It's one of the areas where I see
hope because it's fairly easy to run. A lot of people are running and it's this decentralized
system where you have hubs and people are running them for others as non-profits or as things
where you have direct contribution but it's not a walled garden. That's hope. I see hope with
projects like in the home automation space. I personally use Home Assistant but there are other
great projects. But a lot of them go deep into actually giving you something that just runs.
So operationalizing it isn't hard. It's actually often out of the box. You can download an image.
It just works. Sometimes there are even services and the integration into services works out of
the box. You can actually aggregate things. Sometimes it's a bit part of the problem is that
there's no differentiation between integrating into other open source components and services and
some very weird proprietary cloud-based things that maybe upload your security camera images to
places where you don't want them. So there's that. But on the other hand it's progress in the sense
that part of the open source project is to actually solve this problem.
And this is a problem again I think this is a problem for everyone. Even if you're building on
top of the cloud, even if you're a company building on top of the cloud and you have like very
little code that is your own code where you put your business differentiation like your UI to
control the microcontroller code that controls the mousetrap, you still need to figure out how to
operationalize it. That means you need to have that knowledge from somewhere. And that's becoming
increasingly a problem because it's hard to do that securely. So open source has one is only
half right. That's my take away. Open source is a preeminent software development model at this
point but it's not the operations model. And this limits how useful free and open source software
is for users, whether it's individual users, private users, nonprofits or civil society
organizations, companies or even governments that try to have sovereignty in their technology
and data use. You know the GitOps is a nice example here. It's great to have a GitOps model
but if you GitOps your free software, how free is it when the GitOps part is actually proprietary?
So my thesis is that we need to expand the concept of free and open source software from code at
rest, from code in a repository to really include the operationalization of the code. And we need
to create the collaborative decentralized infrastructure model for that where we can use
the same approach of aggregating existing services that are run maybe by other organizations,
by other projects without having to rerun everything on our own. We need to create an exchange
and operationalization knowledge and we need to create a practical capability to build applications
in that way. And I think it's important to really take this also in something I hadn't
thought about before as much. I spent some time at an open forum event on Friday about
where a sovereign cloud, cloud sovereignty in the EU was a big topic. I think as a free
and open source software community we need to also make sure that this point gets pushed
into the cloud sovereignty discussion. Because if you end up with cloud sovereignty many
people talk about how we're going to use open source code but at the end it's going to be
in itself just a black box service. Maybe it's just a data center that happens to be
in the EU but otherwise it's following the same existing proprietary centralized cloud
model that wouldn't be sovereignty, at least not in my definition of sovereignty, which
means you have actual control over your destiny. So what I'd like to see is what we need to
do here, expand the model, create a collaborative model around actually running things, focus
on sovereignty aspects and I think we need to consider technologies without bias. What
I'm really concerned about is for example when I see discussions around web 3. There
are a lot of people who have now a mindset where blockchain, web 3, that's tainted by
either scam affiliation of similar technologies perceived or real or by political affiliations.
I don't know how big that is in Europe, in the US that's like a big topic where you can
talk to someone and they'll say no web 3 that's something that the crypto growth use.
I think we need to be agnostic there, we need to look at technology and that's utility.
I'm skeptical on each individual technology but ultimately it comes down to how can we
solve the problems and there are areas where a distributed ledger is going to be the right
solution. There's going to be areas in my view where for example something like Filecoin
is the right solution because you need to find a way how to monetize offering services
on a peer to peer basis. We need to be careful not to put everything into the same bucket
as maybe other things like some scam coin and snowball model because they are not just
the same technology, they're not the same thing. I want to give a concrete example of
what can be done. This is something we are trying at Red Hat but it's an open source
initiative. It would be silly to talk about it in this context if it wasn't. We call it
operate first and I should explain the term. Red Hat has internally in our Linux group
and I think for most other groups but there it comes from, we have a core principle that's
called upstream first which says that we will never try to differentiate from upstream
code on a technology base. If we implement a feature in our product we try to get it
into the relevant upstream projects before we ship it as a feature to customers. It's
not always true. We ended up maintaining Zen kernel patch for a long time because it was
never accepted upstream but we also regretted that quickly and switched to KVM because
it's painful. This is not altruism per se. The reason why Red Hat doesn't try to differentiate
on the technology level from our upstream open source code is because that would make
our whole development model really painful and almost useless because you lose the main
point why a company should use free software. It's the development model that allows you
to collaborate and achieve better solutions than anything you could come up with in-house.
You lose the corrective. Most modern issues that you have in complex systems in the lower
layers of your software stack you're never going to solve on your own. Any big kernel
issue, any big security issue, it's always a collaborative effort and that's why they
get solved. That's even true for most proprietary software at this point because someone else
finds it. Red Hat has this principle called upstream first which features go upstream
before they go into the product. Exceptions are always there but that's a goal and it's
motivated by core business requirement not by altruism. Now we need the same for creating
services. Red Hat is now as much software as a service company as it's a free ship code
company. All our services are based on free software. Not all the glue code gets developed
in a free software open source development model. Not all the glue code is publicly available
yet. The point there is we have the same problem and this is not only speaking about our use
of services. We can't force and we don't have the capacity to build everything ourselves.
We have to offer services on proprietary cloud for example. There is no way around that.
For the things we create, we were also drawn into just everyone in the culture of DevOps
and cloud native development. We have created things that are proprietary in the productization
step and we have lost the ability to collaborate on that which hampers ourselves. It hampers
our customers that then try to do things on prem or try to create a hybrid environment.
At the end we believe strongly in a hybrid cloud model for whole different discussion
would be its own talk. We created this initiative to change our own dynamic but invite others
to join it. It comes down to approaching the creation of our own services from a model
where we start with making the upstream code operationalable. We make sure that what we
put into the software repo is not just theoretically runnable code. It's actually everything you
need to run it. Open source service first of all means something that the average person
can instantiate as a running service. Second, drive the knowledge on how to operationalize
it into the same community or overlay community. Sometimes you can't because things aggregate
into bigger services and create communities to have an exchange on how to operationalize
the software and make that knowledge available under free software licenses in a free software
exchange model and development model. Then also try to create actual running instances
that our projects can reuse without having to run component services on their own and
invite others to participate in that. We collaborate with some universities. This is not new.
Matt Miller from Fedora Project is sitting in the first row reminding me that Fedora
has done things like that all the time. Linux distributions of course have run what nowadays
would be called a cloud service like build systems and so on in a collaborative fashion.
This is not net new. The problem is we have to expand that into everything, into databases
that we need to run, we need to make reusable, into any kind of software that we ship we
have to include to operationalization. So that's the pitch. And we have 10 minutes for
questions, discussions and answers. 15, I did some quick talking there. Do we have questions
online? Maybe we can start with these then. Yes, no. Nothing online. So questions? Yeah,
I will take the first one then. I'm not going to heckle you. Closer? Okay. There we go.
So a lot of the public discussion I've seen about cloud services and open source has come
from a different direction. It's like companies who have open source software and their business
model will support around it and then some other much larger company suddenly runs their
software better than they do and they say hey, that's not fair. That's not why we open sourced
it. We wanted something else out of that. And there's been a kind of a fight over licensing
and some new licenses basically meant to restrict that kind of running things. And there's
been debate about whether those fit under open source. I think you're talking about something
entirely different. And is there a licensing approach we can take to drive software towards
this operate first model? So I'm not convinced that code licensing itself will solve the
issue of strip mining code. Like the problem when a larger company takes your code and runs
a service and monetize or doesn't have to actually be a service. They could just ship the
code into it better. There's always a risk like that. It's a dynamic that always existed in a
Linux distribution. We ship something that undermines the ability to sell the same thing
unless you find a way how to make your selling the same thing either better or an add on.
So in the tradition sense I always like I was a product manager for Rel a long time where
we ship components that other people try to monetize because it's expected from a Linux
distribution to bring certain things out of the box. Now what we always said is look we
have a very generalized solution here. We will help you upsell your specialized support.
So that's solved in that sense. But if you go into the strip mining by for example cloud
providers it takes the same piece of software run it, competes with you and they can operationalize
it much better than you and then win. Also have more reach and have a better customer
model. They have a marketplace where they can promote their solution over years. I don't
know if a code license can solve that because part of the problem there is that they could
also rewrite and when that was done they rewrote the code or forked an earlier version when
you changed the license. So this didn't work. What worked however I think is creating the
awareness, creating specialization and creating a dynamic around the integrations.
So embracing that you're not selling actually the code. Now I still believe that it's probably
better to license the code under a copy left license and license your operationalization
under a copy left license to minimize the abuse versus a license that's too liberal and
allows people to take it proprietary. But the successful countermeasures I've seen were
not based on licensing primarily. They were based on business model and engagement with
the customers. Right. How do you copy left the operas, I can't say that word. Well you
get into like a game we just found out luckily that game rules cannot be copyrighted. Right.
So D and D will live despite Hasbro. But I think the code you implemented in can. Right.
And at the end it comes down to like how much of the hurdle is writing new automation code
and actually that becomes a fairly big hurdle to reinvent automation code. And then copy
left helps. You know it doesn't help you against the reach and economy of scale. There you
need awareness of your benefits, good business model and awareness of the problems of walled
gardens. Right. I mean the Twitter versus Fediverse situation is a great experiment of that.
You know I think we should all try to help make that successful. Right.
How do you feel about decay of self hosted infrastructure for example servers or domains
disappearing and in general being less reliable than for example get up. I couldn't. OK. How
do you feel about decay of self hosted infrastructure for example servers or domains disappearing.
That wouldn't be the case with get up. OK.
How do you feel about the decay of self hosted infrastructure like servers and domains
disappearing and less reliable than example get up. Well yeah that. So that's a huge issue
right. So self hosted infrastructure always decays. Right. And I mean that's true for anyone
who does something you're interested in at the beginning and even if you're still around
you move on to the next interesting topic that is at least true for me. And well you know
I was I was I'm very happy with home assistant. I wouldn't want to run a security scanner
on my home assistant device. Now it's like that's fairly OK because it's so isolated
and doesn't control well it controls the heating so there's a risk there. So yeah that's a
problem. I mean and I think my impression is for example the home assistant community
and again that's just what I'm using. I don't want to like single them out and I haven't
had time because I didn't have time to try others it might be better ones but what I'm
seeing there is that there is out of the community actually people start offering the services
commercially. And nothing I said today is an argument against commercial offerings.
It is an argument against proprietary offerings. It's totally fair to charge for something
right. Developers want to eat. Just admins need to eat. We can sell services. And so
I think professional free software infrastructure is the answer to the decay of self-hosted
systems and you know a reasonable approach and some of us we have to figure out by reasonable
approach decentralization where multiple people can offer things without making you to choose
proprietary lock-in is the answer. That's why I think we need to look at VEP 3 without
making you choose proprietary lock-in services because that is one way that could work. If
I look at Filecoin IPFS as an example that actually is working right now not economically
for the people who are offering it because the hardware is too expensive for the money
you can get with it but if you're using Filecoin based storage that is actually pretty cheap
and the problem is that the specialized compute capacity needed to offer it is too expensive
right now but that's just going to be solved with progress in technology and I'm sure that
we'll see some risk five based specialized Filecoin systems in the near future that makes
this affordable. And then we have a way how you can have at least for storage you can
have distributed in fact a good funding model. Other ways are foundations or other peer payment
models or small companies decentralized small companies.
We have three more questions. There was someone over here there and then there and then over
there. So what do you think is the way or the sort of gold standard or end point for
packaging up operational capability with the code and with the application when shipping
to end users who are not software developers and who don't have servers.
I agree with everything you said before. My thesis so far has been that it's straight peer
to peer you know stuff like BitTorrent or Tor or old school file sharing apps would be an
example where if when you got LimeWire you got the app with the data but you know it could
also maybe be web three something but what do you think that looks like for the two billion
people who don't have servers and are software developers.
So I have an example of right now a piece of software that I think is doing this really
well and it's a sync thing. It's a peer to peer you know file synchronization system
that I use between my mobile phone with Android Linux machine bunch of servers and I now use
it for everything where you use everything we need to full copy everywhere.
At least last time I haven't checked for new features it was a debate. They don't have
like on demand replication I didn't have that last time I looked for it. So I use other things
when I want to have things like the Google Drive type thing right where you have something
in the cloud and you only download it when you look at it. For that it wasn't the right
thing last time but I use it for my you know key pass replication things like that for
backup for all documents I want everywhere and it's super easy it just works right like
that. And so my 11 year old daughter uses it. Now the poor kid also has to run a Linux
laptop because I refuse to do anything else. I can tell you the pressure to go into a proprietary
ecosystem of a specific company that sells laptops and phones primarily I think. That's
what they do and watches. It's a fashion business I hear but like the pressure on kids to be
on that because all the other kids have that is enormous. So you know poor kid is in trouble
but she has a swing thing and some other cool things and Roblox works in wine just like
if you are struggling with this. Hi thank you for your talk. I'm wondering whether this
might also come as a problem because of sometimes a need for centralization. I myself move to
Mastodon but I still push all of my toots to Twitter and I would move to GitHub to GitHub
into a local GitLab but if I want to have users on my code I still need to push all
of my code to GitHub as well. So what's the solution with that? I mean I'm in the same
boat. Of course I have a Mastodon account. I'm not super active on Twitter. I try to
do all my code projects on GitLab which is slightly better. It's a more hybrid model
although it's not perfect but I like them. But yeah I think it's a cultural change in
awareness. People need to understand that you need decentralization and we need to create
code and infrastructure and culture that works in the federation to give users a reach. The
problem is reach. It's really a cultural question at the end. I mean the perfect example is
the switch from IRC to Slack as a dominant interaction for developers in many places.
I mean there are really limitations with IRC that become problematic. Technology wise Slack
isn't fundamentally different. It's nicer UI, some additional features and the persistence
that you had to do extra steps to get with IRC. But it's primarily minor improvements
like threading and the web UI and persistence. And then the critical mass effect and the
reach it created. Really the answer is a cultural change where people appreciate and do the
extra work. And it goes back to the earlier question about what's the gold standard for
creating such an app. It's us here who have to drive that and then make it usable for
all the others. That's not different than what happened with free software in general.
We've been through this cycle and I think it's truly equivalent. I mean using free software
20 years ago was hard. I mean when using software was hard but when I installed my first Slack
where that was painful. And then nothing was available and then you had to recompile it
and it behaved randomly whenever you compiled it. So we have to do that.
This has to be the last question. Hi. Hello? Hello? Okay so I agree with what you just
said about cultural change and to give an example of that, for me Microsoft's acquisition
of GitHub was the last straw and I closed my account. But that means that if I want to
contribute to free software projects it's increasingly hard because I'm expected to have
a GitHub account. And it seems to me that anyone here who agrees with what you've been
saying and yet who still uses GitHub or other proprietary software and particularly proprietary
software that they allow to be at the heart of the development of the free software is
being very hypocritical. And so it's up to us surely to as you say take on that pain
but that includes a lot of people in the room who put their hands up when you asked who
has a GitHub account. So I put it to you. Should we not change? We have to go through that pain.
Thank you. Yeah. I agree we have to change. I'll be honest. My presentation part of the
reason why I was struggling I couldn't read my speaker notes because I created it in what's
the defaulted Reddit which is Google presentation, Google Docs and then downloaded it because
I didn't want to look super silly in front of you. So yes it's a hard right. I honestly
believe in, I don't know, who recognizes this t-shirt? You're not watching enough TV or
the wrong. Watch the Expanse, best show ever. But that's from the TV show. That's a TV show.
They changed it. Next time I'll do a tattoo or something. Anyhow, so I believe in the power
of subversion and not the Git predecessor. I actually do not believe, that was great at the
time. Stick with Git. My point is, so for example, I kept my GitHub account. I do contribute
to projects where I need to because I don't want to put too much of a burden on people I'm
trying to collaborate with that I depend on. It's hard. But I do try to problematize it,
bring it up and I do everything I can on alternative platforms. And I think, you know, I
think that's really like adding that extra step of advocacy and pulling people, trying to pull
people over is the best we can do. I just created my, I just created a Noster key and now I'll do
Noster instead of Twitter because that's a fully decentralized thing. But I'll cross post, but
I'll point out that you find me on Noster and if you want me to reply you have to talk to me
on Noster. Things like that. I don't know if we all do it, I think if everyone who comes to
Fostom starts behaving like that, I think we can change things.