I'm talking about Fedora, which is Fedora for Apple Silicon.
It's funny, I was in the bar the other night talking with David and Neil about doing this
presentation.
And I said, yeah, on that Mac mini, on about one in ten displays, it just doesn't work.
So there is a small chance that I arrive on the day and HDMI output won't work.
So yeah, we hit that issue.
So I was hoping to do the whole demo directly on the Mac mini, but we had to go to plan
B on my Chromebook here.
But I still got short and will still do all the Q&A.
I was hoping to show you a couple of things live.
But yeah, we'll have to show that.
So yeah, I'm Eric Horton.
I work for Red Hat.
I work in the automotive world.
So that's what I kind of work on.
I had a competition, but I have to shelve that, because it required the hardware.
We'll see.
A free time at the end.
I might try and plug in the HDMI one more time.
So why do we care about Fedora and Apple Silicon?
So Apple released new Ambus, Apple Silicon devices.
I think it was late 2020.
And there's actually a shortage of well-abstreamed devices.
What's cool about this one is the firmware is unlocked out of the box.
So it's actually a feature of the Mac devices to run alternative operating systems.
And virtualization is also unlocked on the firmware as well.
That's actually a feature I find quite handy.
I run KVMs a lot on this Mac mini.
Yeah, and it's blazingly fast.
And I swear that will be known for selling marketing their hardware as premium, which
it is.
But it's also great value, great bang for book in terms of performance.
So why do I care?
What did I get involved?
Repeating, like I said earlier, I work in the Red Hat automotive org.
Many automotive boards are Ambus.
So I end up doing quite a bit of work that requires some kind of an AMR environment.
And working on the Mac mini allows me to iterate quickly.
And there's a bonus I learned more about AMR hardware and software implementations and
things like kernel space rust and that kind of thing.
So these were benchmarks.
I did these well over a year ago.
I was working a bit.
I know it might be quite small and difficult to see.
I was working with LibCamera at the time.
And I just used it as a program to profile different pieces of hardware I had around
the house.
So it's basically minutes it takes to build LibCamera, or seconds even.
So on the very left is Raspberry Pi 4.
The green one is interesting.
That was my phone.
It was like a mid-range Motorola.
I like a Fedora-ish P-Rooch, it's called, the piece of software.
So I like a Fedora container running on my phone.
So that's the green one.
The yellow one is also a Fedora container running on my phone.
Yellow is when my phone is rooted so I can get an extra little bit of performance out
of that that was using Shirot rather than PiRooch.
And the yellow is my company-issued laptop, which is like an Intel i7.
And the small blue bar at the end is how long it was taking me to build LibCamera on my
Mac Mini.
And funnily enough, the orange bar, my company-issued laptop is twice the cost of the Mac Mini.
So that's kind of going back to there's great bang for buck with the Apple device.
So it makes the project great.
We've really great upstream folk and we collaborate with these quite frequently.
So we've Hector, Alyssa, Asahilina, Dugal, Sven, Mac, and there's many more as well.
So we've great downstream folk as well.
Neil and David, they are actually here.
They're big in the whole Fedora ecosystem.
They're big contributors.
And Michelle, Lou Fliddy is another guy.
She lives out quite a bit and there's many more.
So this is another thing that I really love about the Asahil community in general.
They have this kind of upstream everything aptitude.
So like absolutely everything we send to the various upstream projects, if at all possible.
And that's one thing.
There's various certifications around ARM devices.
Like I listed just three there I could find.
One is work through a Chromebook and one is the Red Hat Enterprise Linux certification
and the third is system ready.
One thing that's in the spirit of all those certifications is upstream everything.
And yeah, that's one of the kind of core values we have.
And that's actually not as common as you would think with ARM devices.
It's almost an exception when absolutely everything gets upstreamed.
So in Fedora Asahil, this is a preferred workflow.
So most of the time things will hit upstream first.
And then Fedora will package that up and then the Fedora Asahil remix will use those packages.
So that's the common case.
We also use this workflow because sometimes submitting things upstream, it can take a
bit of time.
So that's a lot of our work as well in the Fedora Asahil community.
So sometimes work will be submitted upstream but it might not be accepted yet.
So in Fedora Asahil we'll take those patches and we'll fork whatever packages we need to
make sure you have the best experience possible while things are still being upstreamed.
And eventually that will make its way to Fedora when it gets upstreamed.
And yeah, I'm going to explain that further in the next few slides.
So yeah, absolutely since this is a success when it comes to Fedora Asahil.
So ultimately we'll be planning getting as much as possible into the main Fedora repository.
So every time a forked package is absolutely right, I would regard that as a success.
So what do we fork?
We fork U-boost.
That's kind of one I'm kind of expecting could be forked almost forever because we have some
Apple Silicon specific stuff in there.
Sorry, yeah.
I knocked off my mic.
Two seconds.
Okay.
So we have U-boost.
We have a package we call kernel which is our own kernel.
It's separate to the normal Fedora kernel.
We have another kernel we call kernel edge.
We fork mesa.
We have this kind of firmware package that Hector and I made called M1N1 and there's
a handful of others.
I think we have some flags, build time flags and we don't have a way of changing how it
behaves at runtime yet.
I could be wrong.
It may not remain forked.
The other thing about Fedora as well, we generally try and avoid maintaining firmware and focus
on the operating system side.
So if you notice our Fedora images, they generally don't get packaged with firmware.
We try and avoid getting into maintaining firmware because, yeah, I can scale quite
badly at the lower level pieces of software.
So the Fedora kernel, it has Apple Silicon support.
We continually test and enable more kernel configs as support gets profited upstream.
It's built with 4K page size.
So that's something interesting in Fedora.
In Fedora we try and just build one kernel per CPU architecture.
So at least the way things currently are, we don't build a kernel for 4K, for 16K, 64K
because, yeah, against scale, we just, it's easier to maintain one kernel per CPU architecture.
So something interesting about this kernel is not everything at the moment is upstreamed
with support for 4K page size.
That's something that's continually in progress and the upstream folks are working on.
But hardware is designed to work with 16K page size.
So we'll get there.
Getting everything working with 16K page size upstream is definitely the priority first.
The other thing about 4K page size is you take a performance hit because the hardware
is kind of tuned for 16K page size.
So that's something to bear in mind.
So yeah, the Fedora Asahi SIG then maintains two kernels and this is the first one.
I called it the Fedora Asahi kernel here.
So it uses the Fedora kernel as a base and we didn't add extra yet to be upstreamed
patches from like the Asahi Linux repos.
We enable even more kernel configs.
We build with 16K page size and it uses simple DRM which is software rendered graphics and
that's actually surprisingly fast.
I'm always amazed at how fast simple DRM is on hardware like this.
So if you're interested in Fedora Asahi from a user perspective, I would be recommending
this kernel or the next kernel I'm going to talk about because just the user experience
is a bit better.
More things work basically.
So this is another kernel we maintain.
We create this one not so long ago, just before Christmas.
So this uses the Fedora, the last kernel I talked about basically as a base and we add
even more patches and we enable even more kernel configs.
So it uses accelerated graphics.
What I had intended to do for this talk is that we would have a little computation of
two people playing super dox cache just to show off the accelerated graphics.
Yeah, HDMI issues.
So I found this kernel interesting to work with because it's built with the Rust for
Linux kernel space port and yet the DSI GPU driver is one of the first fully fledged Rust
for Linux drivers and it's pretty neat.
It works well.
And another difference is we build this kernel with Clang LLVM because that's the basically
GCC Rust support is a little bit behind.
So at a minimum you have to build a Rust code with Clang LLVM and I remember playing around
with that package at the time and at that point it was just easy to build the whole
code base with Clang LLVM including all the C code.
But I think it is possible if you kind of want the hybrid build to build the C code
with GCC and the Rust code with Clang LLVM but we switched everything to Clang LLVM at
least temporarily because it's easier.
And we also use a forked mesa package so that works with the Rust GPU driver.
So what's our official release date?
David, he's here somewhere.
I was talking to him before the talk.
He's presenting this stuff at scale in March in about a month's time.
I hope he has better luck with his CMI output and that kind of thing than me.
So yeah, David is handling our release so we think we should have an official release
output for that.
So oh yeah, so most of the people working on this are kind of doing it part time except
for the upstream folk.
They're more or less.
Some of them it's their full time job.
So we're always welcome and open to have new contributors so if you're interested, reach
out to us on Matrix.
Apple is actually pretty impressive.
They seem to be releasing new hardware pretty frequently.
And every time they release new hardware, there's new things to do because every piece
of hardware has its own nuances.
Like this is something we were talking about in the last month or two.
I don't actually have an M2 device so I can't test it personally.
But WebKit is basically broken because there's this thing, it's a new feature of ARM.
It came in ARM version 8.5 and it's called Branch Target Identification.
And basically someone has to write the code in WebKit to say if BTI do this but nobody
has done it yet.
Which was interesting.
I remember yesterday at an M pair talk, somebody asked a question, can new ARM versions break
user space?
And I didn't want to answer because I wasn't speaking but yes, they can sometimes because
this is one of those cases.
And that's kind of it.
I have a couple of links there to our matrix, our wiki, our project tracker, the upstream,
the Linux page and diskit and copper.
You'll find some of our RPMs in there if you're interested.
Yes, so that's kind of it.
I'll take Q&A now if anyone has questions and answers.
And if we don't and we have a little bit of time, I might plug in the HDMI cable one
more time to see if we get very lucky.
So anybody has questions?
We have one here.
Hello.
At the beginning you mentioned that Apple Silicon is well upstreamed on ARM device.
What do you mean by being well upstreamed?
Does it have work put back into it?
Could you repeat the question?
In the first slide you said that Apple Silicon is a well upstreamed ARM device, which is
why you work on it.
What does that mean exactly?
So that's all thanks to the upstreamed fork, the Saahe Linux fork.
So Hector Martin is the leader of that and he really believes in upstreaming.
So he tries his best.
Sometimes certain piece of code, he does get difficulty.
That's normal.
It spends so many subsystems and so many different projects.
So the world is upstreamed, absolutely everything.
Amaro pointed that, oh, there are plenty of ARM SOCs that publish their code.
So they'll put a git hub repo out and they'll publish the code there.
But they'll never, often they don't go to final hurdle and get it into Linus's tree.
So everyone's out of the box with Fedora, Debian, Ubuntu, all the various distributions.
And that's one of the things I love about the Saahe guys because they go that extra
mile to try and upstream everything.
So that's what I meant by that.
Hi, you mentioned that U-Boot, you think that might not be upstreamed.
Would it make sense to have a separate project to create a UEFI layer on top of that to harmonize
Fedora in that way?
Yeah.
I'll be honest, I did not work on U-Boot stuff myself.
I think Hector did most of that.
He calls it EFI like and not exactly EFI.
So that might be the reason why it might remain a fork.
To be honest, I work more with the downstream folks, so you'd probably have to talk to the
upstream of Saahe guys about that.
I think it was Hector working on U-Boot stuff, but I could be wrong.
So yeah.
I'll try and plug in the HDMI.
Hi, thanks for the talk.
I would like to know how it is to use a new programming language which is Rust in the
kernel and in Meza.
Is it going to be supported upstream?
I think it's amazing.
I'm not going to lie to you and say I've written thousands and thousands of lines of
Rust because I haven't.
But building it is easy as long as you're applying LLVM at the moment.
And I believe GCC started to...
They released Rust support recently, so I expect GCC to get there as well eventually.
So building it isn't too bad now.
Using it, it works solidly.
I've never had any crashes or anything.
Hector and all those upstream guys swear by it.
They reckon they got that GPU driver written twice as quickly just by using Rust and by
not having to handle memory management manually always and all these things and to handle
trade races and stuff.
I think another reason they chose Rust is I think when they're Rust engineering the
Apple GPU driver, I think it was written in C++.
So I think it made it a little bit easier for them because Rust has some of the features
of C++.
But they swear by it and they're the guys that actually write the Rust kernel patches,
not me.
Do you see a need or a demand for or use for Apple Silicon to run Linux servers in real
scenarios in companies and this kind of stuff?
Like in Enterprise?
Yes.
Enterprise is tricky because we're very much a community supported effort and we don't
have any...
Apple don't really have an issue with us doing this, but we also don't have an official relationship
with Apple.
So it would be hard to deploy Linux and Apple Silicon in a data center when you don't have
support, official support from the hardware manufacturer.
So at the moment I don't see that happening unless Apple all of a sudden are like, yeah,
yeah, we'll support that configuration like in an Enterprise environment, yeah, could
happen.
Where did the HDMI cable go?
Just gonna plug it in there.
Sorry, guys.
Hi.
Sorry, I was just gonna wonder, you mentioned that for U-Boot you weren't gonna push things
upstream from your fork.
Is that a licensing issue?
Like is it a GPL conflict or something like that?
Or what's the problem?
Could you repeat the question a little bit louder?
I think earlier you said that for U-Boot you'd be maintaining a fork.
Yeah.
Is that a licensing issue?
Is there something you can't commit back to U-Boot that they wouldn't accept?
Yeah, I didn't, again, I didn't write the U-Boot patches.
I'm pretty sure that was Hector.
I think it's because it's written in a non-standard way.
He often calls it UAFI-like and I think there's certain hacks he had to do to get it working.
I'm working on Apple Silicon that the maintainers may not accept.
But I'll repeat, does upstream cut, does the upstream Asahi community, they really care
about upstreaming into the real projects, be it Linux, kernel, Meza, et cetera?
So far all possible.
I'm sure they will, you know.
Sometimes there's just hacks required because it's, yeah, it's built around macOS at the
end of the day.
Some questions?
No.
I'll be around for today.
If any of you see a monitor around the campus or whatever and you want to see it in action,
we can hook it up and try and I'm open to that.
So yeah, it's about, yeah, I've seen this happen before.
90% of monitors work, so if you find a random monitor, yeah, we can do it.
Okay.
So, thank you Eric.
Thanks guys.
Thanks very much.
Julius.