Well, thank you everyone for attending.
It's lovely to see all of you.
My name's Mike.
I go on mine under the handle Nolski, so you'll find me as Nolski in the Matrix chat as well
as in IRC.
I have a bunch of titles because I choose to have titles instead of a social life.
But probably the most important in the context of this talk is the bottom one.
I am a scholar of political economy of science and technology.
I'm a graduate student, and this is kind of the field that I study.
So political economy is kind of a funny word, but essentially what it means is it's the
study of how economic systems and political systems are intrinsically linked.
And so this framing is really what drives the analysis of my talk today.
And so political economy has been around for a very long time.
It's been the primary subject of many very, very famous and loved thinkers throughout
history that I'm not going to name.
But, you know, what are we talking about here today?
Well, first I want to do a quick history of free and open source software, like a very
abridged one to kind of drive home a couple of questions I've been asking myself over
the last few years.
Second, I want to kind of posit a question about are we really building the same software
now that we were when the initial foundations of the ideology around free software began?
And if we aren't, how is this software we're building today different?
Then I want to talk about kind of where we are today as a community, as a society and
ideologically.
And then lastly, I kind of want to, you know, posit some questions that will hopefully generate
a very lively but hopefully respectful discussion that adheres to the code of conduct with this
event.
So let's get started.
Or actually, let's not get started because I talked to my boss and I have to give a couple
disclaimers.
So first, you know, I want to I'm going to be talking about politics here and economics
of free software.
And I want to be clear, you know, this talk, it doesn't seek to analyze or make any stance
on like the morality of who you work for or whether your employer makes you a good person
or a bad person.
It doesn't even seek to analyze whether certain organizations are good or bad.
This talk is to analyze the structures that exist in our technological production and
see whether, you know, we might be interested in changing those structures, not like who
is good and bad.
Furthermore, I got to read this verbatim according to my boss.
The views and opinions expressed in this program are those of the speakers and do not necessarily
reflect the views or positions of any entities that I represent.
So now that that's out of the way, thank you.
Yes.
So hopefully I will have a job when I get back home.
So let's do a quick timeline of free and open source software.
This is very abridged, so I'm leaving out parts for brevity so we can have a discussion
and focus on other things.
But in general, for this talk, I want to bisect the history of FOSS into two periods.
And these dates are very generalized, but the first period I would argue is between
the 70s and the early naughts.
Really during the beginning of this period, computing hardware was just becoming starting
to become standardized.
Previously, if you bought a computing machine, it would come with the software provided by
the manufacturer, and it was custom made for that model, and you couldn't easily transfer
software from one model by one manufacturer into another.
But soon after, hardware architectures became standardized.
And so people could write software that runs on many different kinds of machines.
They could share it with each other.
They could trade it.
And software became what's called a commodity.
And so this generated all sorts of new industries that I'm sure you're all aware of within information
technology and so on.
And as part of this, businesses formed to develop and sell software and services around
that software.
And at the same time, so too did communities of practice, of production, that sort of formed
the early ideas of what we imagine as open source or free software communities.
And so from this situation, arose the beginnings of what I would call one of the foundational
ideological pillars of free and open source software.
In particular, Richard Stallman proposed these four essential rights or freedoms for users
as this core ideological pillar of what free software should allow and be about.
These aren't licensing terms, but rather a stance ideologically.
Specifically, it's for any software user obtains, they should be able to use it for whatever
purpose they want.
They should be able to understand how it works.
They should be able to share it onward to whoever they think might want it.
And they should be able to modify it to suit their own needs and improve it potentially.
And so one thing I'm really interested in considering during this period is the underlying
assumptions and technological context during when these four freedoms were initially positive.
At this time, most software was this very discreet thing that oftentimes came in a box
or on a floppy disk or whatever.
And when you ran it, it was on your own machine, it was limited in its size and complexity,
it was portable and understandable largely, and it was discreet.
So many businesses at the time would license their software in this way that explicitly
forbade these rights.
You can download my copy of Windows, but you have to pay for it and you can't modify it
and you can't do whatever.
And so this causes tension between these communities of developers creating free and open source
software and businesses who were specifically seeking to profit off of their ability to
generate revenue through these proprietary licensing strategies.
You know, Bill Gates had this infamous quote where he referred to free software activists
at the time as communists on a television interview.
And I would argue if you talk to folks from this period, many free software organizations
actually struggled with being labeled as communists or anarchists at the time.
And so this was kind of almost like a meme.
And just as a disclaimer here before I get sued, this poster wasn't made by Microsoft.
So this poster was a meme created by someone else.
So this is not representing Microsoft's views at the time or now.
So Microsoft, please do not sue me for false light.
So anyways, this struggle led to there being many projects and products, both open source
and proprietary, right?
Oftentimes, like competing products, right?
And many businesses offered their own solutions that actively marketed against open source
software alternatives that were trying to accomplish the same goals, fulfill the same
features as their proprietary counterparts, right?
And these businesses, a lot of their ideas at the time is they're relying on their greater
cohesion to try to build a better product and software ecosystem when compared to their
sometimes fragmented open source alternative.
And this is how they seek to try to capture the market for any given use case, right?
So in short, we had this situation where we see directly competing products whose common
differentiator is really their licensing strategy.
This is the thing that made them stand out apart from each other, right?
You got Windows and Linux, you got Firefox and Internet Explorer, you got OpenGL and DirectX,
right?
All these were competing products to see which was better.
And all these cases as a competition between which organization, the community or the firm,
could build what capacities more effectively, right?
And many of our debates and discussion at the time revolved around which method of production
was more efficient at building these capacities.
And I'm sure even if you go around today or you talk to your friends, we still hear these
discussions, right?
When we're talking about trying to encourage people to develop open source, it's more effective.
It's just easier, we can share costs.
And so during this time, licensing was this huge part, if not the most important part,
of when we thought about the battle between free and open source software and proprietary
software ecosystems.
You know, IP rights at the time were really coming to a fore with the advent of a lot
of digital intellectual property.
And when considering this initial ideology focused on user autonomy, freedom, user autonomy
and freedom, this idea of IP ownership in order to facilitate that through licensing
was like the sort of core method that many people thought about how to achieve this sort
of more ideological goal, right?
So now I want to kind of jump ahead to the sort of second phase where we are today, right?
So this relationship between open source and proprietary software, it didn't really stay
this way, right?
Now as we all know, as you come to any one of these conferences, you've probably seen
this statistic already today.
Free and open source software has become this foundational infrastructure upon which like
pretty much all of our digital services are built, right?
And before I go ahead, I just want to drop like a thank you and a note that a lot of
the graphs I'm going to be showing in the next couple of slides come from this amazing
2021 report written by the Digital Commons Policy Council.
So I got a link to that policy council in the slides, which you can download off of
the FOSDEM website.
I encourage you to check it out, but they did a lot of really great work for getting
the data and the empirical sort of findings here.
So anyways, you know, today we see some of the biggest antagonists towards free and open
source software actually directing the most significant amounts of their workforce towards
its support and budget, especially when compared to other firms, right?
Microsoft was like the big bad in open source, right?
And now they're actually one of the largest contributors of it, right?
They're very much bought into open source software production.
You know, not only have major firms changed their tune in relationship to each other,
but now when we look at open source communities in the largest projects and most important
projects on the internet, employees of these firms now generally outnumber independent
contributors.
And, you know, I'm careful to use the term independent here rather than volunteer because
independent contributors are oftentimes contributing in the context of like an organization or
institution, but it's not really one that is focused specifically on maximizing profit
for themselves.
So these types of contributors, I would argue, face like very different incentives in terms
of like what they're trying to build and for what purpose.
Furthermore, you know, as time has gone on, the ratio of firm employees to the independent
contributor has increased steadily, right?
So year over year in most or in pretty much all major projects, the amount of firm employees
when compared to non-firm employees has increased, right?
So this is not just like a finding, but it's a year over year trend that's increasing steadily.
So I would argue one thing to note in this case then is that we can sort of find that
independent contributors oftentimes have less power in these communities simply because
they're being outnumbered by a much more cohesive group of other contributors and they just
have less power to develop, right?
And so while these projects are majorly developed at the explicit discretion of firms, right?
What I think is most important is actually the shift between these two periods is actually
how the form of software itself has shifted when thinking about open source software.
So if you look at this list of projects, so this was I think the top 20 or 25 projects
that the, in terms of like contributors and activity founded by the Digital Commons Policy
Council.
And if you look at this list, nearly all of these projects, they aren't really end user
software anymore, even of the technical sort, right?
Many are for use solely in the development of these sort of large scale products and
platforms that can really only be applicable to users who have significant resources to
run them, right?
So like let's have a look, right?
We got a number of server orchestration software such as like Kubernetes, Moby or Ansible.
We also have machine learning and distributed systems projects such as like Spark, PyTorch
and TensorFlow.
And I'm sure as you attend talks today, even at Fostom, a conference that's quite community
focused, you'll likely find the majority of software programs being discussed are of this
type.
So why has the production of free and open source software shifted so incredibly to this
one very kind of specific niche within software applications?
So I'd like to argue that most of the software we interact with on a day to day basis, and
you know maybe I'm leaning out of the free software developer archetype here when I'm
saying this, but most of the software we interact with aren't really discrete applications
anymore but rather what I would call platforms, right?
And because of this, the relationship of much of our open source software and our proprietary
software has like fundamentally changed, right?
So why are these projects that are, you know, important now so different than the projects
that were important before?
Now I'd like to argue that many of the most powerful technology firms have largely pivoted
away from licensing discrete software products as their core sort of revenue model to the
development and, you know, managing of platforms to generate revenue for them.
So you know, before we go forward, I'm sure you've all heard the term platform before,
but I'd like to try to formally define it in economic terms, right?
And so this sort of, I'm paraphrasing here, but this definition was first posited by
a Nobel Prize winning economist, learner and to roll.
So platforms, when we think about a platform, you oftentimes think about it like a software
system or something like that, right?
But these software systems aren't really commodities in themselves, but rather they're made as
a system to manage access between like networks on two sides of a wall or like commodities
on two sides of a wall.
So to give an example of this, you know, Facebook is a platform which manages access to communities
in media for end users on one side and then, you know, willing eyes, data and ad positioning
for advertisers on the other side.
And Facebook has kind of this monopolized access to both of these networks, right?
Or at least like a very preferential access to both.
You know, Amazon is a platform which facilitates access to distribution networks in a global
marketplace for producers on one side and then a network of goods and services for consumers
on the other side.
Google is a platform which facilitates information and digital services for end users on one
side and again, you know, willing eyes and user networks for those digital service providers
and advertisers on the other.
So the nature of the platform has positioned their creators to exploit what are called
these multi-sided markets with these sort of two networks by acting as a mediator and
a gatekeeper between access across this sort of divide.
So you know, I'd like to posit this question to everyone that we always hear all the time.
It's honestly probably getting a little old in the tooth.
But you know, has open source won?
Like you know, have we done it?
We are foundational to the operation of like the entire world.
You know, open source is really important.
More people than ever are creating it, right?
And so, you know, no, I don't think so.
I mean, there's clearly more open source, right?
There's probably a similar or larger proportion of open source software to proprietary software
that we use on a daily basis, at least within the dependency chain.
However, we still have little to no control over the vast majority of services that impact
most people's lives, particularly digital services, right?
From e-commerce to social media to healthcare provision, all of these, you know, might heavily
rely on free and open source infrastructure to function.
But we still have no actual control.
So when we think about the ideological pillars of our movement in the first place, I don't
see any significant gains in this area.
So you know, to me, when looking at this history, it really seemed that many free and open source
advocacy programs have been out-maneuvered in this way due to the shape of our software
changing.
So, you know, I know that's like a little depressing and everything.
And I'm sure many people have a lot of opinions about maybe the validity of that.
But I kind of want to talk about, well, if this is the case, right, and if this is a
problem that we as a community are facing, then what do we do about it, right?
So first I want to kind of review a couple of key points that I wanted to make.
And then I want to, I know this is like a stage talk, but I want to have a lot of Q&A
afterwards to have a discussion with the audience.
So first and foremost, you know, I want to claim, you know, free and open source software
isn't competing with proprietary software anymore in any significant way.
I know there's, you know, probably examples, but when we look at the largest, most active,
most important free and open source software projects, they are not competing with proprietary
alternatives.
They're helping host them, right?
The second is our labor as free and open source software contributors in general is being
increasingly dictated by firms.
We see this year on year because we're being continually outnumbered by firm contributors.
And we're having less of a say in the communities that we act in.
You know, furthermore, more of us are working directly for firms when contributing and are
therefore, you know, required to represent their interests.
And even when we aren't, certainly the most important projects, our ability to dictate
the direction of these is, you know, we're outnumbered.
On the flip side, we are finding when these firms suffer any loss in their rate of profit,
usually it is us who are among the first to be cut, right?
This precarity and increasing control that firms have over our collective labor powers
means that oftentimes we're losing autonomy as creators over our own labor.
You know, so this original framing of user control over, you know, our software that
we download and run on our machines, you know, I would argue is no longer relevant because
we live in a time where, you know, we majority interact with these really complex, massive
platforms.
Most critical software we interact with is no longer these discrete packages offering
specific functionality to users, but rather, you know, these platforms are gating and mediating
access between markets, commodities, and other networks, right?
Therefore, our original conception of simply increasing the amount of openly licensed software
products is no longer as relevant as the projects we're building are largely infrastructure
to maintain these platforms, right?
So we can no longer avoid this very political question about how we attempt to reorganize
free and open source software labor on behalf of these original ideals of, you know, user
rights.
You know, labor organization has frequently been a topic avoided previously in free and
open source software, and I would argue it was due to this major focus on licensing instead.
You know, we didn't talk about, like, who we're working for or how we're organizing
our work because we wanted to focus on where the ownership was, and if we can create more,
you know, open licensed things, then the ownership goes to everyone, and then the power is distributed,
and I would argue we've seen that we've been kind of outmaneuvered in that sense because
our interaction with owned software has largely changed.
So you know, this all sounds not great, but if this is the case, then how can we adopt
a more sort of labor-oriented approach to the topic of free and open source values and
ideals, right?
How can you as a foster or me, you know, I'm not off the hook here, help bring about this
change?
So, you know, I can't claim to have all the answers here.
You know, I'm just a guy interested in this topic studying this stuff.
Especially now, you know, I understand the topic of political change is a very touchy
one.
However, there are some ideas I've researched that I think would be, you know, at least
worthwhile for us as a community to investigate further.
The first is the idea of understanding that not all free and open source software contributions
are equal.
So when considering the value of free and open source software contributions, you know,
maybe we should prioritize developing alternatives to existing platforms that are controlled
by firms, right?
And so when I say alternative here, I don't just mean an openly licensed clone, but rather
a solution designed specifically with these ideals of user autonomy in mind, right?
It may take an entirely different form to create something that would be comparable.
The second I want to talk about that I think is very important is organizing within the
workplace.
You know, I've met many, many, many burnt out free and open source software maintainers
in my life, and I understand the pain there.
And so, you know, our ability to produce what we want requires that we have greater control
over our own labor.
So while technology roles are oftentimes compensated well, at least within certain geographic
areas, it doesn't eliminate our precarity as workers, right?
And I think in particular, many of us are finding that out now.
So in this case, what do we do about it?
Well, historically, the formulation of labor unions have allowed us as workers to better
bargain with our employees and regain control over our labor power.
And I think when thinking about how we can manage to have the time and capacity to be
able to build what we want, thinking about regaining that control within your own workplace,
particularly through labor unions, is a great first step.
The third thing I want to talk about, which is a little touchy, is explicit political
organizing within the context of our free and open source software community.
I don't think we can just build and license the solutions that we want, but rather we
need to organize ourselves along explicit political lines that go beyond that of licensing.
When you think about free and open source software, I was in Bradley Kuhn's talk today
in the legal dev room where he was kind of talking about his personal history in this
case and he talked about how there were a lot of, I forget the word he used, but like
collaborations between groups that had different interests, right?
And he was questioning, he was like, you know, I don't know if we should have worked with
them or worked with someone else.
And I think it's very hard to determine these sort of partnerships that you enter unless
you have a very clear political line that you as a community are agreeing to work together
on.
And I think defining this is really important, probably just as important as something like
the open source definition.
Lastly, you know, I think finding and developing new workplaces is going to be a really important
fact when thinking about, you know, kind of figuring out how we can organize ourselves
to develop the software that we want, right?
I get that this isn't an option for everyone immediately, but, you know, the role of institutions
such as, you know, NGOs, nonprofits and universities have historically been, you know, key creators
of foundational free and open source software infrastructures.
And furthermore, I think we as a community see our ability to represent ourselves lessening
in general, right?
You look at organizations like the Linux Foundation and they pretty much exclusively represent
the interests of their corporate members, that is literally how they're incorporated,
right?
And they have no public good mandate.
So I would argue that we should organize, agitate and push for these institutions and
our society to support this production to draw power away from firms.
So now this is a bit tongue in cheek, you know, I'm not claiming you should all be communists,
but this is my poorly made rendition of the earlier poster.
I want to wrap up with, you know, free and open source software, you know, I would argue
was largely outmaneuvered due to this lack of cohesion and organization within a specified
political framework.
And so if we do, you know, seek to reorganize ourselves for a new era in free and open source
software, then we should consider how we got here and, you know, see if we can correct
some of those mistakes.
So you know, I want to, this is my second to last slide and I'd like to open it up for
Q&A if that's okay.
But I thought I would leave this here, you know, if you found this stuff interesting,
I like to leave kind of further reading lists.
And so these were some of the primary citations that drove this research for me, but also
I think just were interesting, relevant sort of pieces of written work.
There's a couple of books in here.
I link to them on LibGen if you can't afford them.
You should be able to download the e-book at least.
And yeah, thank you.
I'm Mike, and I'd like to hopefully try and answer any and all questions you might have.
Thank you.
Thank you very much for the talk.
You presented a very interesting table regarding the leading firms for each repository, etc.
So I'm a NixPKG contributor, and it was mentioned that the leading firm was Logic Blocks.
I think it doesn't exist anymore.
So I'm very interested in understanding how you generate such tables, because it's super
interesting.
Also, how do you deal with corporations or firms which are not really firms?
So for example, on the table there was Home Assistant, and the leading firm was Affolter
Engineering, which to the best of my knowledge is 2% which I don't know if you can qualify
this as a firm or not.
What about those repository projects where you have a lot of people which comes from
very different backgrounds?
Yes, that's pretty much it.
So as I understand it, there was a little bit of rattling.
You're kind of asking, so what was the methodology for generating the data that you're showing?
How'd you get it?
So am I able to click on this?
So these tables were generated by the Digital Commons Policy Council as part of a Ford Foundation
Digital Critical Infrastructure Research Grant.
I don't know if I – oh, wow, that is small.
So this is the research grant.
I don't have Wi-Fi.
That was silly of me.
But essentially, the detail in this report, the exact methodology for doing it, it was
a lot of like we had to deduplicate identities.
We compared emails for frequency commits and mangled it all together into a single report.
But they can detail it pretty well.
I did look over it because I was asking myself the same questions and I was pretty satisfied
with it.
It was a while ago, so I probably would do a poor job of repeating it.
I'm over here.
Hi.
Thanks.
I found that really interesting and very provoking.
An outcome I see a conclusion of this, the idea that free software has become platformized
and has become this sort of substrate, is a sort of two-tier society where we in this
room are a sort of intelligentsia and we have access to these free tools and we get access
to the four freedoms.
We can use free software licensed products and we can study them, share them and improve
them.
Then we build services as a software substitute and everybody else is a kind of London proletariat
who doesn't get those freedoms and doesn't get to sort of benefit in the intellectual
fruits of free software.
Is that necessarily connected to the kind of corporate capture of free and open source
software that you were talking about?
What are the organizational roots or the agitations that we can take to actually extend those
freedoms out beyond the experts and to the people who use computers?
Yeah.
A very big question you asked for sure.
If we imagine the free software community, oftentimes we're very technical people.
Like I use Linux desktop and I'm a social scientist so I would consider myself fairly
non-technical here.
But it allows us to have these sort of freedoms by having this technical knowledge.
Many people, I'm sure many of you have interacted with, maybe don't have that technical knowledge
or that capacity or whatever to sort of interact with free software in the same way and use
it, maybe their job requires that they don't or whatever.
And so does this play a part in sort of figuring out how we can advocate for these ideas to
be more equitable across people?
Is that correct?
Cool.
So I would argue that for sure as technologists we face unique labor pressures.
In particular, I was at the EU policy forum thing yesterday and there are a lot of policy
people that go up and they're like, technology, the coders are going to save the planet because
they're genius and they kind of, we get a lot of lip service towards our technical ability.
But on the flip side I would argue that we still face many of the same precarities that
people have, that we've seen workers have throughout history.
And for sure it's a struggle and it's a discussion we need to have as we're organizing ourselves.
But I think first and foremost, if we want to have better free and open source software,
we got to have more control over our own labor power to create it.
We've done a lot of really cool stuff just like as hobbyists and things like that.
Imagine if there was an army of us all working together and dictating like, oh, this is what
we want.
I don't want Facebook.
Who likes Facebook anyways?
I want to build the thing that's actually allowing me to connect with people and the
ways that I dictate is best for me.
It takes a lot of organization and agitation to get there.
And I think even as intellectuals or a person in the professional managerial class, we still
have a lot of incentive to work at that.
I hope that answers it.
It's kind of a vague answer.
Yeah, so when open source was being developed in discrete ways for discrete products, there
was no cost to the developers of the software when someone used that software in whatever
setting.
So you could produce a thousand or a million and the open source project almost didn't
know who was there and who was using it.
And I understand your concept that there's more of a consumption at the platform level
now than discrete software.
But the question is, how do projects evolve in an environment where you have to provide
now there is now a cost to that platform?
So you've got to have infrastructure, you've got to have networking, you've got to have
admins and so forth.
And there's now a per user cost in a lot of ways to how your software is consumed in a
way that before it was zero cost.
And it feels like that change is pretty significant and does almost open the door or close the
door frankly for pure open source projects to almost operate at scale in that environment.
Yeah, great question.
And very, very relevant and not one I think I have the answer to.
But I want to maybe propose a couple of potential answers that I think I can't choose.
We have to choose.
And so when thinking about platforms, there's a lot of different ways.
Currently many platforms are kind of exploitative.
We don't really have a choice in terms of whether or not we use them if we want to have
access to a certain thing like social networks or whatever.
So part of it's like, oh, maybe we just need to collectively own it.
Maybe just nationalize it.
It's one very political way of thinking about solving this problem.
If we nationalize it, then it's democratically controlled theoretically.
This is one way of approaching this problem of user autonomy.
Then if someone wants to change it, then we have democracy to help facilitate that somehow.
Another way of approaching the problem though is do we need platforms at all?
Is this approach of one specific technological solution to solving one specific need within
our society?
Is this the right way of going about it, or was this just the most effective way of running
it?
Can we imagine futures of which our technology is progressing, but it's still discrete enough
that we can maintain control over it?
And then what does that look like, and how do we get there?
I think these are the different arguments and maybe factions that might arise within
the open source community.
I think if we start begin really rethinking what we're doing on a more fundamental level.
Does that sort of?
Yeah.
Thanks.
Hi.
I was wondering what would we see or hear when there's good organization within the
workplace?
And that question is sort of in context of major strikes in the UK at the moment around
a lot of public services, and also in context of a broad post by Carl Mitchell called It's
a Trap, which is basically warning that the union sphere in the US is very heavily legislated,
and there's lots of sort of bad political context when it comes to saying, we should
have a union for this, basically being something that you shouldn't ask for unless you really
know what you're getting into.
So I guess maybe before you hand it off, is your question more on what do we do about
unions kind of being portrayed in a certain way, or is it like as a union applicable?
I've organized well.
Why do you organize?
What does that look like?
Yeah.
Yeah, that's a great question.
I have a lot of friends, and as part of my research, I do lots of research with how unions
currently organize and how they use technology.
So there's not one... Everyone I talk to, whenever I ask them this question, they're
like, well, I can't give you a blueprint, but I can tell you some things that work for
us.
I work with a couple union organizers at Amazon, and they have huge turnover.
So focusing on new employees as a point of organizing and getting people and educating
them is very important for them.
I have another friend that works as a technician in a hospital who has a very small department.
And when they started focusing on unionizing, or at least collectively bargaining amongst
themselves, they started in a very small but critical part of their organization, saying,
we can't do the whole hospital at once.
We'll just get fired, right?
We'll have a bad time, and it'll be very hard, and we don't have the capacity.
But maybe within our department, if we begin forming certain lines about what we want and
what we care about, we can begin starting our organization from there and then moving
outward if we gain momentum.
I think particularly within the technological context and people within tech companies,
this might be an interesting thing to try out.
But that said, we haven't seen, we don't have a lot to learn from in this sense, right?
There aren't a lot of existing tech company unions, but maybe that's a place to start,
maybe looking at some of the smaller ones.
Or if you work at Amazon, check out Amazon Workers United.
If you're at Google, check out Alphabet Workers United.
There are existing unions within these companies, even if they aren't contract unions.
Thanks for your talk.
This is also related to organization.
You mentioned software foundations.
Unfortunately, a lot of them have similar structures in business models.
Because I've been thinking about alternatives to software foundation.
Is it that we need to work on a different membership or a different business model or
governance?
I don't have any thoughts on this.
Yeah.
It's a big question.
And certainly, when I hear a lot of folks talking about, I think it's, I would argue,
and I know I called out many companies here, but I would argue the Linux Foundation is
quite different from most open source software foundations.
Linux Foundation is a membership organization that is formed specifically to represent its
corporate members.
They're looking for a membership to get into the Linux Foundation.
They have a summit and stuff like that.
And they're supposed to advocate on your right, on behalf of your interests, as a tech company
that utilizes open source.
They've grown quite a lot due to their funding.
I would argue that's very different from something like the Python Software Foundation or the
Rust Foundation or even Apache or something like that.
I would argue, I would like to see more collaboration.
I don't think software foundations for every project that exist in their own little ecosystem.
I think that's good, so you can receive funding and stuff like that.
But we should start figuring out ways that, what if there was a Linux Foundation that
wasn't driven principally by members who paid for ownership?
Maybe we could think about things like, oh, I know the top contributors might get membership
if you contribute a certain amount or some other form.
There's a lot of different ways that you could go about it.
But I think figuring out how to bring communities together with similar interests, even if they
aren't the same project or in the same tech stack, is important because then you can begin
organizing along ideological lines rather than just like, how do we make Wayland work
better in Nome or something?
I feel like there are a lot of pieces to dismantling these platforms.
I feel like a few of them are being discussed around here, like the cooperative company
structures and building new open platforms.
But when it comes to unionizing, because there aren't really many tech unions, I've been
thinking a lot about how these would work.
And I wondered what your thoughts were on the idea of using tech unions to try and dismantle
some of the existing platforms, like say, we're not going to work on AWS because we
don't agree with Amazon and what it's doing with its other employees, for example.
What are your thoughts on that way of approaching this kind of thing?
Yeah.
I would say one step at a time.
Before giving the talk, obviously I talked about this subject to a lot of people.
And there's a sense of, like, things are pretty bad now.
How are we supposed to deal with all this stuff?
It feels like everything's collapsing.
We're kind of in survival mode.
I would argue, at least right now, at this moment, the real benefit of unionizing within
technology workplaces is it gives a little bit more time and autonomy and stability back
to technology workers.
And so when I think about the crisis and open source around volunteers who are just overburdened
and stuff, and I think about everyone I know that works in tech that's on call all the
time and software services are crashing and now their coworkers are being laid off or
maybe they are, this is the problem that I think if we can claw back some of our own
time, if we can get a little more autonomy on our own, a little more reasonable working
conditions, like even I get that the pay is good in some conditions, then we can begin
just having the head space to think about these new solutions and have the time to organize
with each other where our boss isn't watching us either.
Right?
Thanks for your talk.
You talked about software, but do you think we can observe the same shift from individual
and independent contributors to software companies and big firms paid contributors in the international
standardization organization like IETF, for example, I think about how the first version
of HTTP protocol was defined and the third version which was mostly the result of a bargain
between Google, Facebook and Microsoft.
Is there any data or work on it?
I'm sure there is.
I don't have any.
I have anecdotal data.
I served on a couple IEEE standards committees and noticed this sort of major differentiating
where you get people who are there on developing a standard specifically for the interest of
their company.
Right?
They are like, my boss is paying me and I'm supposed to help manage this and make it so
our organization can accomplish the goals that we want to do.
I'm not saying it's evil to want to do that or anything like that.
I see a lot of that and I don't see a lot of people who are like, I think the standard
is pretty cool.
I did a thing with something related one time and I want to, it's like showing up at your
town hall meeting.
Who has time for that anymore?
I would argue the same principles are at play here.
More and more organizations are interested in forming standards with each other because
it helps share the cost of development of a lot of their infrastructures.
No one wants to reinvent the entire stack for whatever thing they are building.
By utilizing standards, you can more effectively do that the same way that you could by utilizing
open source software to do that.
I would say principally there are a lot of similarities but I don't have like a, I certainly,
at least at this time, I couldn't empirically prove it.
But a great point for further research on the road here.
Right, is that better?
Fascinating talk.
I just wonder whether we've made life easy for the big corporations.
I think we all enjoy writing software.
We enjoy solving a problem.
It's a bit like an academic, researching something and then you get an entrepreneur
making his fortune.
How can we fight back as developers?
Yeah.
So I guess your question is, if I understand correctly, you're kind of like, we kind of
made it easy for us to get into the situation that we are in now.
Like how do we fight back?
Is that it?
Yeah.
Well, you know, I think, I'm not a huge fan of like kind of the self-flagellation where
it's like, you know, we got corrupted or whatever.
You know, as the last 50 years of history around, you know, the development of digital
technology has a lot of very major incentives.
It was very complex.
It was not necessarily super obvious that we would be where we are today.
You know, I think the most important thing is like, you know, the future is yours if
you fight for it.
Right?
It's not like an easy, you know, the things I suggested, if you want to try to unionize
your workplace, it's not an easy thing to do.
You know, I have many people that have like tried and failed.
I know many people that have succeeded as well.
But, you know, I think like if this is something you want, right, if you think about like the
four freedoms or these ideals of open source as like user autonomy, you're like, you know,
this is the world I want to live in.
And as a technologist, I can create this stuff, then, you know, like anything, it'll take
work to try to do that.
And it's more about recognizing that and then figuring out what to do next.
I think we're at time to one more question.
Thanks for this.
It's really kind of a great thing.
I want to ask not only you, but everyone else here, you know, do you think that we as humans
can step away from that kind of that you always need to have someone like in charge?
So we have that, you know, pyramidal kind of thing and that to like to go more, you
know, a flat.
So that's what I'm saying.
So we are so used to have someone in charge and to someone, as you said, word that I don't
like a lot, I can dictate to someone and dictate what you should do and actually team up.
I'm not sure that we as humans really can do that on some bigger scale.
It's a left.
I'm very left, but I don't go far left.
So I am really left side.
So I'm saying that it's kind of feels like if you play in a small band and you make a
nice songs and, you know, with music.
And as soon as you get my mind there, you sell your soul and you're gone.
So how we can go more flat without losing our soul.
Yeah, I mean, it's tricky, you know, the human nature and eating someone in charge.
This is a little bit of a joke here, but like, you know, I would love to introduce you to
my four year old nephew.
He would he might have you changing your thoughts on that very quickly with respecting authority
and wanting that.
I think there's no easy question about like, but you have to think about our organization
scientifically, right?
I don't think it's like a matter of preference, but we have to think about our relationships
to each other.
We have to test and evaluate various modes of organization and we have to approach it
like any other difficult scientific problem in our lifetime.
And, you know, through that, hopefully we can find a better solution if not the right
one.
Thank you.
My many thanks for the amazing talk.