Hi, how are you doing?
Welcome to FOSDIM.
Congratulations on managing to get inside a room.
This is the largest one I've ever seen.
Usually it's just looking at the doors of ones that are full.
So yeah, my name's Daniel Stone.
I'm here to just give a relatively high-level overview of the graphics stack.
My hope with this, like I said, it's fairly high level, is to give you a decent understanding
of all the different components that go into the modern graphics stack, how they fit together.
So if you're trying to work with it anyway, you won't be trying to debug it because it's
already perfect.
But just being able to give you a good understanding of how everything does fit together.
And now we have graphics output working, so that's a good start for this talk.
Because that wasn't looking likely five minutes ago.
Right.
So the graphics stack looks like this.
Any questions?
That's the simplified version as well.
More sensibly, if we try to build it up incrementally, just try and work through all of the different
pieces and different components in essentially the order of near to far, which is, you know,
in networking you think of upstream and downstream.
Usually in the graphics board, a lot of what we think of is what's close to URI and what's
far from URI.
So in our case, the display is closest to URI's, and this one's incredibly by.
In between, just underneath the display, controlling the display and giving you determining what
should be shown.
We have the window system layer, so that's your way lens.
It can be X11, but we don't talk about that.
And then at the very back end, the sort of upstream side, you've got the clients which
are actually presenting the thing that you want to show.
But then it turns out that your window system also uses the GPU to render, so it's not just
OpenGL games that use accelerated graphics, it's the window system.
So the nice diagram already gets a bit muddied because we're breaking the layers.
And then maybe the window system uses some media output because you want to stream stuff
on Twitch or, you know, to stream a conference talk.
And maybe one of your clients is also a window system because it turns out that even Chrome
is a way lens server these days.
So our lovely little, we have three classes of three main components of our graphics stack.
This illusion's already disappeared.
But, you know, let's pretend that everything is fine and let's just try to build it up.
So for us, DRM and KMS are the acronyms you mostly see.
The direct rendering manager is anything to do with graphics or display inside the kernel.
It's a weird legacy name.
And those are all of the GPU and display drivers.
And KMS is very specifically the part of DRM that actually controls the display.
So when you're talking about HDMI output or something like that, then it's going to be
KMS.
And KMS is that very last step in the pipeline, the one that's closest to your eye.
This job is to turn pixels into light.
Some people will tell you that there's a thing called FB dev as well, but that's not right.
FB dev doesn't exist.
And then, yeah, in the division of responsibility, as we go one step further back from your eye,
the Windows systems job is to fundamentally to take a bunch of images from clients, combine
them into a single image of multiple images if you have multiple displays, get them out
to the eye and bring input events back.
So Wayland is a protocol and nothing else.
There's a very small C layer in Wayland, which is really just IPC.
Apart from that, it's just protocols and conventions.
So you know, Mutter that GNOME uses as a Wayland server, other popular ones would be KWin,
Western WL roots.
That's where all the implementation actually lies.
And yeah, like I say, they just combine window images together, get them out to the output
device, in the reverse direction they're bringing input back.
X11 doesn't exist either.
So we'll move on.
Yeah.
So OpenGL and Vulkan, in a way they fit in.
Their APIs, as we know, for accelerated 3D, so you provide them a mesh and some textures
and some shaders, run this thing, make it fast, great.
But they only handle rendering.
So GL and Vulkan themselves have no concept of I want to be able to display to Wayland.
That comes in with EGL and what we call the Vulkan WSI for Windows System Integration
Layer.
Their job is to bridge the two worlds.
So with OpenGL, you have EGL on the side that's the bridge between GL and, say, Wayland.
With Vulkan, you have Core Vulkan and then the WSI on the side is that that bridge bringing
all the content across to the Windows System.
And then there's GBM as well, which is maybe the most ill-fitting part of what we have.
GBM's kind of a side channel to bridge EGL to KMS.
So right now, I mean, this is all happening through GNOME Shell and Motta.
It's using GL to render my image with the next slide as a bonus preview and this one
that you can see.
Motta, yeah, it uses GL to render and it uses EGL plus GBM to be able to pull images out
to kernel mode setting.
And GBM is a really, really strange and idiosyncratic bridge.
Some people will tell you that GBM stands for the generic buffer manager.
That's definitely not true.
Yeah, we had an idea that GBM would be the thing that let people kind of peek under the
hood of what EGL does as an implementation and be able to generically allocate buffers.
We got as far as making it work for kernel mode setting and then realized how terrible
the whole problem space was.
So we just pretended that it was never an acronym, that it's not generic and moved on
with our labs.
So at the end of all that, before we get into something more meaty, we've got clients rendering
the content, maybe with the GPU, maybe just on the CPU, maybe it's just doing mem copy.
It will pass a handle to that content over to the Wayland compositor with some metadata,
some context.
The compositor is going to pull it all together, choose how it's going to display it, apply
any kind of policy or what have you.
And then it's going to just push that final image out to KMS, which is going to turn it
into electrons.
So we've got a diagram that's back to making sense.
So if we're looking at how KMS is actually put together, every single discrete device
in your system is its own.
I just have an Intel laptop here.
I have one DRM device, which is the entire Intel GPU and display complex.
If you're on ARM systems usually, you're going to have two devices.
The display and GPU are separate IP blocks from separate vendors who aren't really on
speaking terms.
So you'll have one DRM device for your display controller and another DRM device for your
GPU and they're completely separate.
So yeah, four KMS devices.
We've got connectors representing real displays.
So we've got an embedded DisplayPort connector here and various DisplayPort and HDMI connectors
for my external outputs.
CRTCs, that does stand for CRT controller because that's how long ago it was when we
designed all this.
CRTCs are the thing immediately upstream from connectors.
They generate a pixel stream for the displays.
So any kind of scaling, cropping, compositing is done in the CRTC space.
CRTCs are just a combination of planes.
So planes, they take frame buffers, they can scale, they can be positioned within the CRTC,
they can be stacked.
And then the CRTC is the one that combines them.
So in quite a poor diagram, because for a graphics person I can't actually draw very
well, I'm more of a text person, to be honest.
Yeah, it's the frame buffer is just the client content.
The plane is the one that's going to do any format conversion or scaling or what have
you.
And then the CRTC combines them all together, pushes them out to the connector.
Then I think the important thing to bear in mind if you're trying to reason about graphics
pipelines is that timing flows backwards.
Timing never flows forwards because when you've got a physical display, it's going to refresh
at a certain point in time.
Assets VRR, no one asks about VRR.
We don't quite know how that works yet.
But timing flows backwards because this HDMI output is ticking at 60 hertz.
That's happening at a very, very fixed point in time.
And so that's the beginning of our reference.
When we know that we want to present stuff to HDMI, we know exactly when the next refresh
cycle is going to start, the next one after that, so on and so forth.
Timing is always flowing backwards.
This goes right the whole way from the connector back to the CRTC, back to the Windows system
and then back to the clients.
It's always starting from that fixed hardware source.
So yeah, you want to use DRM and KMS.
Good for you.
I'd recommend it.
It's just a set of objects like everything it turns out in computer science.
It's objects with properties and that's it.
You open your KMS device, you enumerate a list of objects, your CRTCs, your connectors,
your planes, you look into their properties.
So this connector type is DisplayPort, this one's HDMI, whatever.
And then any time you want to actually affect something, so display new content, change
resolution, whatever, that's all done through what we call atomic mode setting, which is
about ten years old now.
And it's a very low level property based interface.
I wouldn't really recommend trying to drive it yourself, but it is possible.
So atomic is just a list of properties.
So you've got all of your different objects and their different types.
You know how you want to put them together.
You know that I want this plane to go to this CRTC, to this connector.
And so you take all of those objects, you do a massive property set, and then you do
an atomic check before you commit just to see if the configuration's going to be accepted.
And one of the things about display hardware is that it's weird.
It's really, really weird.
There are infinite constraints on what you can actually do with the display hardware.
So you might have three or four planes that you can use to composite content without using
the GPU.
But you can only use a couple of them at a time, or only one of them can have compressed
content or only two of them can be scaled.
So because we don't have a good generic way of expressing these constraints and of constraint
solving within the kernel, we do the dumbest possible thing.
It's brute force.
We just try every possible configuration that will get us to where we want to and see which
one's going to stick.
Then yeah, once you've gone through all that, you've done your atomic commit, you've got
a frame on screen, it lives there until you change it.
Because DRM is a frame by frame API.
It's not a producer consumer where you connect a camera to an output and magic things occur
and you get a video stream.
That's the domain of higher level frameworks, like say, pipeline and G streamer have that
pipeline concept.
The DRM is quite dumb.
It just does what you tell it to.
And it doesn't do anything else until you tell it to do something else.
So yeah, we've essentially summing up.
We've enumerated all of our devices.
We've used the DRM to do that.
All of the objects.
And again, as with timing, we're working backwards from the starting point of the connector.
We know that HDMI 1 is the thing that we want to light up.
So you always work backwards from that when you're building up your object tree.
And then you are going to need a way to allocate some memory to display.
It's not just a malloc pointer.
So we have gem graphics execution manager.
It doesn't manage execution of any graphics jobs.
It's just a memory allocator.
This was about the point where we stopped actually naming acronyms because we've got
almost all of them wrong.
So gem you see a lot of because that's the base of our kernel allocator for all graphics
and display memory.
And BO is something you see a lot of as well.
I told you it was bad at acronyms.
So gem BO is just like a malloc pointer.
It's un-typed.
It's a raw bucket of bytes.
Can be pixel buffers.
It can be shaders.
It can be geometry meshes.
Whatever you want it to be.
Doesn't have any properties or metadata.
Just a length and some content.
But you can't allocate them generically because hardware is really that weird.
We gave up on that a long time ago.
So you're going to need some kind of hardware specific API to come up with a gem BO.
And you might be quite disappointed about that, which is reasonable.
So we came up with dumb buffers as a specific class of gem BOs designed specifically for
CPU rendering when you're displaying KMS.
So if you have something like Plymouth for your early start splash screen, that's not
going to be using the GPU.
It's just going to be doing CPU rendering, no device dependent code.
And dumb buffers are the path to that there.
I just wanted to get something up on the screen.
I don't care if it's amazingly fast or efficient.
I just need it to work and work everywhere.
So this is actually a generic API inside KMS dumb buffers.
Gives you a gem BO.
You can map it.
You can fill it up with some nice pixels.
And then wrap that in a KMS frame buffer is what annotates the BO with stuff like format,
and width, and height, and stuff that people think might be important.
So like I said, you can use it for splash screens.
Please don't try to use it for other stuff.
It's not a generic memory allocation API either.
It's just the thing that works.
So with all that being said, that's a reasonable end-to-end picture of how to use KMS.
You've allocated all the buffers you need or imported them from other clients.
You've attached those frame buffers to planes.
You've stuck them on a CRTC to get them in a kind of logical space and stacked against
each other.
You've set your CRTC and connector up for the output path.
Commit everything.
Hopefully that works.
Then the kernel tells you that it's complete.
You know when the next frame's going to be, and you just keep on going.
You can't click these links if you're sitting in this room, but they are clickable on the
PDF.
There's a bunch of pretty decent documentation, examples, and formats.
Because I'm not trying to show you the entire thing.
Just give you a good idea and some pointers.
So if you're bored of KMS or you just don't find display that exciting, you might want
to move on to the Windows system world.
There's a super quick run through Wayland.
Again it's the same thing.
It's clients giving you images and you giving clients pointer and keyboard and top screen
events in return.
I think the main thing about Wayland that people take a while to grasp is that it's
descriptive rather than prescriptive.
What I mean by that is in X11 when you have a pop-up, you tell X as a client, put this
window exactly here on the screen, give me all of the input events until I tell you otherwise
because you're dictating specific outcomes.
Wayland is exactly the other direction from that.
The client tells the compositor this is a pop-up.
And the compositor does the right thing for pop-ups, including capturing input and making
it always be on top but still letting your screensaver work, which is nice.
So yeah, it's just about the client annotating everything it has with a bunch of descriptive
information and properties and then relying on the server to actually implement the right
semantics.
So there's a fair bit of trust but it gives us much, much more flexibility because by
the end after how many years of X11 we were kind of painted into a corner really because
clients were just dictating so much.
We tried to make sure that there were no pods in Wayland that required the compositor to
do a huge amount of work because such a critical part of the stack that you can't have it burn
in loads and loads of time.
So yeah, like I said at the start, your compositor could be GNOME, KWIN, could be Western, Sway
or something like that.
They're all designed for different things and different use cases like window managers
in X11 were.
I think Western's the best one because I work on it.
It's basically designed for everything that isn't a desktop, so literally planes, trains
and automobiles, digital signage, that kind of thing.
It's really, really efficient and predictable and reliable.
But I do use a desktop so I have GNOME on this one.
There are absolutely a pile of them to choose from but they all use the same protocol so
they all look alike to the client.
Then yeah, it's just a large collection of essentially all extension interfaces.
So WL buffer is much like a frame buffer to handle to some pixels somewhere.
No other information just width and height.
The WL surface is a window, can be a pop-up, can be an application window, can be a subsurface.
Takes the buffer, it just crops it and optionally takes input back.
XDG surface is the main one you'd interact with really because that's what adds all the
desktop-like things of being able to resize and move windows and all that kind of thing.
And WLC is where the input comes from because we're still bad at naming, it turns out.
That one was my fault actually.
We did design Wayland fundamentally to be really, really easy to extend so there are
quite a pile of extensions that you need to sort through and deal with.
The nice thing is with it having been designed with KMS in mind, it's a pretty similar, you
know, you've got your compositor doing the final output at the end and that's composed
of a bunch of windows and surfaces which have got buffers attached to them.
And the compositor is the ultimate source of the timing and it flows that timing back
to the clients as feedback.
And it's sort of, you know, if you take that, it looks exactly the same as the KMS diagram
we had earlier which is not really any coincidence and, you know, using that is exactly the same
flow as KMS.
This slide was almost copy and paste.
And again, I'm not trying to give you a complete guide to how to write every Wayland client
in the world.
Please do use the toolkit.
They will make your lives much easier.
So GTK, Qt, STL, IMG UI, whatever.
Use the compositor toolkit as well if you like.
You know, LibWest in particular and WL Roots are toolkits you can use to build compositors
on top of good code bases.
And, yeah, there's some links in here as well to Wayland info is a good tool to inspect
and so is WL Hacks is a debugging tool.
Western Debug is another debugging tool and then, yeah, there's some sample clients as
well.
The simple SHM and simple EGL are our kind of references of, you know, how do I actually
start using this and start approaching it?
So now we've got all that out of the way.
I'm not going to try and explain GL to you because we'd be here forever.
But, yeah, like I said, it's GL as a model for Accelerated3D is clients providing the
vertex data, so your kind of wireframe geometry, your input textures, but your images, and
your shader programs as well to run to generate the final output.
No shaders can deform the geometry so you can do cool stuff.
You can also do things like lighting per pixel and do that in a nice reflective way that's
all computational.
I guess the main thing to recognize about GPU is they're enormously parallel, so, you
know, thousands of threads, really.
There's not much in the way of synchronization or shared memory.
They really, GPUs can't do branching like CPUs.
They want to have everything set up for them a long time in advance and just do straight-line
things from there.
So it's a long, deep pipeline, essentially, and you want to make that roughly as static
as you can.
And yeah, the cost of being enormously fast and really, really powerful, it turns out,
is that they're really power-hungry.
So that's why we have composition in a display hardware as well, because it turns out that
just spinning up your GPU once per frame to produce the final display output can...
I worked on a device where the video runtime went from five hours if we didn't use the
GPU to four hours if we did.
You know, it's a really measurable cost to get a GPU involved, so you only want to do
it if you've got the right reasons for it or if you actually need it.
And then, yeah, it's, like I said, it's just a pure 3D-only API when you talk about GL
and GLES, because it came out of SGI where you told it to draw and it was drawing because
there's only one screen and obviously it's going to come out at the right place in the
screen as a simpler time.
So then SGI realised that they needed some more nuance.
They brought in GLX, which was the first go at integrating OpenGL with the Windows system.
So originally it had the X server actually processing all the commands, and that was
terrible, so we came up with the DRI for direct rendering infrastructure, not let the clients
actually directly access the GPU.
But it sort of relied on central memory allocation, so we came up with DRI2 where the main innovation
was that clients would manage their own memory in cooperation with the kernel and also execute
all of their own commands.
That was so good that any time you see DRI, it just means accelerated rendering, so roughly
describing the last 20 years.
Any time you see DRI2, it doesn't mean actual DRI2 in X11, it just means this kind of looks
like a modern Windows system by which I mean about the last 15 years.
So that can be confusing because those two terms are massively ambiguous, but if you
ever see DRI2, it probably means that you're somewhere good.
Then yeah, EGL is just an abstraction of GLX, so rather than just plugging GL into X11,
it lets you do Wayland, Android, whatever, and all it really does is give you Windows
that you can share with the Windows system, gives you some vague notion of timing, but
it doesn't have any kind of events, so the only way you can get a consistent frame timing
is if you block a lot in EGL, and it just tries to hide everything and make it implicit,
which again is where GBM comes in because that's what lets us steal buffers away from
EGL, push them into KMS for display, handle our own timing and do it properly this time.
Yeah, EGL has that shape, and then not coincidentally, Vulkan has a fairly similar shape.
You know, Vulkan is the rendering API, and that's it.
Vulkan WSIs, the EGL equivalent which provides that Windows system integration of creating
Windows, posting content to them, and so on.
The main difference with Vulkan is that it's really, really explicit and clear about what
it's doing.
The downside is that because it's so explicit and clear, you end up typing a hell of a lot
of code, so it's more effort to use, but there's no magic hidden under Vulkan.
You know exactly what's going on for better or worse.
It's really good on the desktop, but on mobile, SOCs, the hardware isn't necessarily entirely
there yet.
But if you're doing high performance things or you just like seeing what's going on under
the hood, I'd recommend Vulkan.
And yeah, I think about the last bit that we'd end up having time for is I keep on going
on about how we, just saying that EGL will get things from GL to Wayland.
One way we do that is DMA Buff.
It's a kernel concept about sharing memory regions between different subsystems, different
processes, different contexts, whatever.
So we've already got in the graphics side of things, we've got the gem buffer objects,
but they're local to one particular device and to one particular user context.
So when you want to export a buffer to your Wayland server or share it between V4L for
your video capture and your GPU to do some analysis on it, that's
DMA Buff, which just gives you a file descriptor you can use as a handle to that memory area
and import it into different contexts or subsystems or places.
And that's completely consistent throughout the stack, like all of Wayland, EGL, KMS,
Vulkan, everything I've discussed has DMA Buff integration because that's our lowest
common denominator.
So yeah, we put it all together.
I mean, because they're all built on the same building blocks.
It's largely how you think it is.
Well, hopefully, if I've done a decent job of this talk.
The client's connecting to the compositor.
It's creating a window declaring some very simple annotations about that.
It wants to use the GPU, so it creates an EGL context pointing to the Wayland server.
I'd like to render over here.
The Wayland server has some DMA Buff protocols, which tells it what it can and can't accept.
The client uses GLES to render into that.
That's wrapped in a DMA Buff and passed over to the compositor.
The compositor is deciding how to place and configure everything.
It's importing that DMA Buff that it's got from the client to generate one final image.
It's then waiting until the next deadline, that sort of 60 hertz cadence that we have.
It's waiting until the next good deadline to present that out going into KMS.
That might be KMS doing its own composition directly in the display hardware or through
the GPU itself.
It's tough because the display hardware can do that final image composition of taking
your four or five images, mashing them all together and coming up with one.
It is, like I said, a really measurable win on things like power and memory bandwidth,
memory usage as well.
It's kind of complicated in that it's hard to know, be predictable about when you can
and can't use it.
It's a bit fiddly.
One of the reasons I recommend using compositor frameworks like LibWestern, which do do all
of this heavy lifting for you, I've spent ten years of my life trying to solve this
problem and wouldn't recommend anyone else does it.
Not even really that interesting.
Internally, Western has, like I said, that kind of brute force loop of just trying every
possible configuration that could work, seeing what happens and throwing it at KMS to check
if that will work.
Currently, that's the most advanced one, but yeah, others are catching up.
I think really to sum up what I was trying to say about GPUs and efficiency is one of
the things that gets collaborative a lot is that no one realises that every problem on
mobile comes down to memory bandwidth.
You can solve every problem by just copying buffers around more.
When you've got 4K buffers and you've got a low-end device, it turns out that this is
always where your performance problem is.
It's down in things like copies and naive memory usage.
That's just one thing to really be aware of, is try and go for a zero copy pipeline because
when you have 4K and 144 hertz, you really don't have much time and you don't want to
spend it all just waiting for slow memory.
With that, I think we're pretty much coming up on time.
Yeah, that's the quick whirlwind tour of how all that fits together.
Anyone has any questions or wants to talk about how Wayland's amazing?
Please feel free.
If you have any questions, please raise your hand.
When we launch a game in full screen, for example, does it go straight from GPU to screen
or does it go all the way through KMS and that?
It will go through the Windows system.
The question being, if you have a full screen game, will it go straight from the GPU to
the display or will the Windows system still be involved?
It will still be there, but ideally doing nothing.
It will just take the client buffer, give it directly to KMS and ask KMS to display
it in the happy case.
It's always involved as the mediator, so when a notification pops up, it already has control
so it can show it.
Hello.
Is it working?
Yeah.
So, forget the super newbie question.
When you say the frame buffer is tied to a plane, a plane is not a desktop, a plane is
just a window.
I'm sorry?
When you tie a frame buffer to a plane, the plane goes in the compositor.
So the plane is a window, it's not the entire desktop.
Yeah, exactly.
So, the CRTC is your final output as one flat image and planes are windows within that CRTC.
Thank you.
More questions?
All right.
Hello.
Is it working?
You mentioned that kernel mode setting is used turning the pixels into...
Sorry, could you please...
Sorry.
Yeah.
You mentioned that KMS, kernel mode setting is used to turn the data into pixels from
the screen.
Is this where graphics card drivers are involved, another vendor specific software, or is that
earlier or later in the pipeline?
Sorry, which parameters?
So, basic, where are...
Where did graphics card drivers come in?
Because I know there are some, like, vendor specific hardware requires its own drivers
somewhere in kernel space, I believe.
So, where does this fit in the pipeline?
So, all of the properties and parameters are defined in kernel space.
We try to standardize them as much as possible.
So, in the generic world, we do stick pretty religiously to a standard set of parameters
that have common behavior across everyone.
If you go to things like Android, where you have hardware composer and vendor based tells,
it's completely different.
And they're all...
That's more of a negotiation between kernel and user space, which are both vendor specific.
That answers your question.
Do you know if there's any toolkit libraries for writing compositors that are not desktop
specific?
Any compositor libraries that are...
Libraries for writing compositors that are not desktop specific.
Because LibWestin is good for writing desktops type things, but for embedded, highly embedded
use cases, I haven't found any things that make it easy to write a compositor like that.
Yeah.
So, LibWestin's the one for...
Yeah, those kind of embedded or single purpose, I guess, use cases.
Mutter, which is the basis of GNOME Shell, can be used by anyone else, but it's really
GPU reliance.
And WL roots is, I guess, kind of in the middle.
It's not as friendly in desktop as GNOME, but it's not as insanely efficient as Western.
And that's the halfway house, I guess.
Is there any tool you would recommend for profiling?
Sorry, could you please speak up?
Is there any tool that you would recommend for profiling?
The graphics stack?
Is there a tool for profiling?
Profiling.
Are there any tools for profiling?
The graphics stack?
So, kind of.
So Mesa has integration with a tool called Profeto, which is basis of Android GPU inspector.
There's some support in there for Western specifically to interpose its timeline on top
of Profeto, but it's pretty patchy, to be honest.
Like, where we've been working on that basically to try and make it easier so we can stop getting
paid for debugging and profiling stuff, to be honest.
But, yeah, it's a slow process.
Profeto is the best one there.
I have a question.
So why can't we do screen recording or screen sharing in a Wayland?
You can.
Screen sharing in Wayland is done through the XDG screencast portal.
And we did that because once, if you try to put it in Wayland itself as like a core protocol
for clients to use, it was really going against the grain because everything was designed
with this idea of the timing coming from the display and flowing back to the clients.
And then once you put it in the other way that the client's receiving content, it really
just is a terrible fit with pretty much every interface we had.
So it's easier for us to, and also working for sandboxing and containers to go with the
XDG portal solution.
And yeah, it works everywhere basically.
Okay.
I think, yeah.
Thank you, Daniel.
Thanks very much.
Thank you.
Anything.