My name is Bruce Mamjan.
I live in Philadelphia.
Glad to be here.
I've been attending FOSDIM since 2003.
This is my first time in a huge room, so I guess I'm going up in the world.
This presentation is actually part of a 20-year journey for me using home automation.
Not a whole lot of 20-year home automation folks out there, but I'm one of them.
What this talk is going to be is walking you through that journey and giving you a lot
of practical experience of what I've learned.
Hopefully leaving here, you'll have a better idea of not only what home automation things
you can do, but also what home automation things are worth doing.
That's a distinction.
What you can do and what you should do are not always the same.
I will give you some examples of that.
If you're interested in my slides, they are right here on this website, in addition to
this QR code right here.
I am a Postgres core team member, so that's where you actually will also find 58 other
Postgres talks and a lot of other Postgres things, but this has nothing to do with Postgres,
so feel relaxed.
I expect this to be an interesting talk.
We'll take questions as I go about specific topics, and then I'll leave time at the end
for general topics, if that's okay.
I'll just walk through.
I'll ask for specific questions on a specific thing, and then at the end we'll have time.
What are we going to talk about?
First we'll talk about what is computerized automation?
I know that might sound kind of trivial to you, but I'm going to explain what automation
is and then what computerized automation is slightly different.
We're then going to evaluate some technologies I'm actually using because I've been using
automation for so long.
My automation goes back to the 1980s.
Yes, amazingly.
They had automation back then.
Why are we not all flying around in cars?
Right?
I have robot helpers.
I don't know, but again, this technology has been around for a long time, and I will talk
a little bit about some of the evolving technologies.
We even had some new technology in the past six months.
It's a very hot field now when I was doing it, not so much.
We'll talk about a sample deployment, basically how I kind of went at the problem.
Again, I'm going to be using old technology, but it's going to be the same process that
you're going to go through.
You have to sometimes avoid being overwhelmed by having too many options, and I'll try and
explain how to sort of hone in on that.
I'll also explain what happens if you overdo automation because nobody really talks about
that.
Everything sounds wonderful, but not always true.
I'm going to talk about some of the programming issues I have, and then toward the end, we're
going to talk about what is success?
What does home automation success look like?
Again, just because you can do something and it works doesn't mean it's actually benefiting
your life.
That's what I'm going to try and cover.
Finally, I'll talk about a couple applications that I've been challenged with, and then obviously
some solutions to that.
All right.
Let's talk about automation.
What is non-programmatic automation?
This is the concept of you've automated something, but it doesn't necessarily have computer control.
It's not something that you can programmatically adjust and basically control.
Things like, I don't know how many of you are old enough to remember that years ago
you used to have timers that you'd plug into lamps and you'd have a dial.
Yeah, okay.
Yeah, you still have them.
That's good.
Although, there's older people who are raising their hand.
There's just one younger person there, but they'd have a dial and you'd turn it and you'd
set the time.
Then every time you lost power, you had to go back and set the dial to the right time.
That is not programmatic automation.
How many people have heard of something called the clapper?
Oh my goodness.
Yeah.
If you want a howl, take a look at an old commercial video.
It basically was a lamp that you would clap your hands and it would turn on and then you'd
clap your hands and it would turn off.
Hence the name clapper.
Okay.
Darn dust sensors.
You see those, of course, everywhere where when it gets dark, the lights go on.
When it gets light, the lights go on.
It's not programmatic, but it works really well.
Of course, motion sensors.
Those have gotten much more sophisticated over time, but again, years ago they had even
the idea of motion sensors.
Somebody would get close to the garage or walking to an entryway and the light would
go on.
Very convenient.
Not programmatic, but very convenient.
Then we're going to talk about programmatic automation.
This has really exploded in the past, I don't know, five years I'd say.
For example, the concept of voice automation, voice control is something that obviously
really didn't exist effectively 20 years ago.
Now it's hugely popular.
The interesting thing about programmatic automation is that it allows you to take, you see the
non-programmatic automation, the automation was kind of built into the device.
You had the clapper or you had a motion sensor or you had a dawn dust sensor.
You couldn't really change it.
It was wired into how the device behaved.
You couldn't combine that with some other device or combine it with some other inputs
and make something different happen.
Not that it wasn't useful, but programmatic allows you to combine behavior.
It also allows you to do distance things.
Again, one of the examples would be somebody comes into the garage, the garage door is
open and some other action happens somewhere else in the house.
Not usually something that would happen in a non-programmatic way, but it's easy to do
if you're on a network of some type.
Activity detection, being able to write scripts and basically programs that control with the
automation incredibly powerful.
Then finally, and I'll talk about this a little later, the idea of even bringing in external
data and having the external data affect your home automation.
For example, how cold is it outside?
You may not have a home automation thermometer outside of your house, but you may be able
to go to the weather service and find out how cold it is and change your automation
based on that.
Again, this is where I think it gets really interesting and you're going to see a lot
of examples of that.
Any questions so far?
All right.
Now, evaluating your technology.
Now I'm going way, way back in history here, but basically what is a network?
What is the ability to communicate distances?
Well, one of the early networks I didn't even list here is the telegraph.
Now I was a history major, so I studied the impact of the telegraph on society and it
was pretty dramatic, right?
Something could happen in New York City and within several minutes, people in Europe or
people on the west coast would know about it right away.
That's pretty impressive.
The telephone, of course, is a network.
You used to dial a number.
It used to make sparks in the phone.
That doesn't happen anymore, but you dial a number and somewhere some distant person
answers.
Courtless telephones, I was around long enough to remember when those came out.
All of a sudden you didn't have to have the receiver connected with a wire anymore.
It's a sort of network, right?
Then we had Ethernet, which obviously has been around since, as I remember, somewhere
in the 90s.
Before that it was like token ring and a whole bunch of weird stuff on coax.
Although you can still do Ethernet on coax, but you get the idea.
Wireless networks, I remember when those came out, so all of a sudden now I didn't have
to be tethered with a wire Ethernet.
I could do it wirelessly.
This fourth one here, electrical network.
I'm going to show you how that's actually a network.
You might not have thought of that, but it is and I'll show you why.
And then finally we're going to talk about some new wireless networks that are available.
Looking historically, kind of a very 10,000 foot view of what's going on, the technology
you're going to see me using from the 80s is something called X10.
I'll show you how it works.
I'll show you some wiring diagrams.
I was kind of impressed over here.
I got a nice little electrical sticker here.
I was like, oh, it's an electrical panel.
Very exciting.
We're going to show you a little bit of that.
There is something called universal power bus, which I don't think it's even around
anymore, but it was an early way of doing the same thing.
And then we have things like Z-Wave and Zigbee.
They are somewhat confusing because they both begin with Z, but Zigbee is the one you normally
see.
It is an international standard.
Z-Wave is a proprietary interface that you don't see around a whole lot anymore.
There used to be something called Insteon, which I think is still around, but again,
you don't see it pretty much anymore.
I wanted to talk a little bit about a brand new standard that just came out in the fall
of last year, so maybe four or six months ago, called Matter.
How many people have heard of Matter?
Wow.
Okay.
That's great.
Matter is basically not...I want to qualify what that is.
It's not really a network.
It's really a protocol for devices using different networks to communicate.
Up until now, for example, if you had a Zigbee, Philips Hue light bulb, let's say, you had
to communicate with it using a Philips app or a Philips hub.
The idea of Matter is that it's going to allow for home automation using different protocols.
Could be Zigbee.
I believe it's for its X10.
It could be something like Thread, which is kind of a lousy name, frankly, because it's
confusing so many things with Threads.
It's a new protocol for low-powered devices, which you have a lot of those things now.
If you want to get a lowdown on that, I've got a great article here.
I also have some websites down here.
Anything in blue is basically something you can click on if you download the PDF.
You can just click on the blue and it pulls up the site for you.
Again, a lot of opportunities.
It's sort of thinking back.
When X10 came out in the 80s, there was a sense that home automation is now here.
We're going to be able to do all this stuff.
35 years went by and really nothing happened.
I was the only guy, the person doing it.
Eventually now you hear a lot more about it and there's a lot more excitement about it,
partially because the technology has advanced, partially because there's more options, partially
because more people are doing things electronically or they're used to that interface and people
are getting used to it.
There's still some limitations and I'll talk about that.
Not only do I do home automation, but I think I've inspired my family.
My son does home automation.
He's a big home kit person, a home kit being the Apple home automation thingy.
I have a brother who does it.
Most of his stuff is Zigbee.
I have a nephew who does it who also uses a lot of Zigbee stuff.
I have some interesting stories about that.
Some good, some bad or problems that they had.
I'll talk about that when I kind of get a little farther ahead.
Choosing the network.
Let's suppose you're going to use some network technology or you're going to use some kind
of home automation.
One of the first things you have to figure out is what do I want to measure and what
do I want to control?
Because effectively all of the home automation is really like an input output kind of a case.
When this happens, this other thing's supposed to happen.
Or when I see this activity, I want some other activity to happen.
You have to identify if you're going to choose a particular technology, is it a multi protocol
technology?
Does it something like matter that can operate with multiple things or is it more like a
Phillips hub that only really controls like Phillips devices?
You kind of see the difference.
There's hubs that do only one protocol.
There's some hubs that do multiple protocols.
If you pick a technology and that technology doesn't have a sensor you need or doesn't
have a controller you need, what are you going to do?
For example, I needed 220 volt control of my pull pump.
Some of these protocols don't have 220 options.
220 volt options.
I'm sorry, I'm living in the United States.
Remember, everything's 110.
You have 220.
Everything here.
Everything's fantastic in Europe.
We got both.
In my case, that was somewhat of a challenge.
What about a thermostat?
If you need to control a thermostat or HVAC system, does that have an interface?
What if you want to open the garage?
I'm going to show you later how I figured out how to figure out if the garage opens
or shuts.
I can figure out.
But what about how to open it yourself?
What's the control?
Is your protocol support controlling garage doors?
Chimes, that's one that's actually pretty limited.
A lot of the interfaces don't have chimes.
You may not think that's important.
I use it a lot.
Wireless remotes.
The ability to have a wireless control for your device.
What about a phone?
Does it have a phone app or a phone interface?
Of course, most of them have electrical plug controls.
That's pretty clear.
Again, you have to, and then there's different open source products.
I'm actually using this thing called HeyU.
Mr. House is very popular for home automation.
There's a whole lot of open source home automation stuff.
It's pretty cool.
But my point is that you can't just jump in and say, I like the name Zigbee or I like
the name Matter or I like the Hue light bulbs from Philips.
You got to make sure that you're going to be able to bridge your sensors and your activity
together under a unified system.
Does that make sense to people?
Does that kind of make sense?
I guess I noticed it because I would say, oh, I really want to do X.
Oh, I don't have a way of doing that.
Or I really want to know X or I don't have a way of finding that out.
That was kind of cool.
Now, signal reliability.
You see that a lot, some with different, like Zigbee I know has a limitation of distance
because it's a wireless protocol.
So again, it might use Wi-Fi.
Do you have Wi-Fi in all parts of your home?
They're all reachable.
Is it reliable?
If you're using something like X10, do you have a way of doing that?
I'll show you how that actually works.
What about, this kind of seems kind of unusual.
Simplicity of device replacement.
Why did I bring that one up?
I had a friend, I knew a friend who when he bought a new house, he put automated outlets
in all, all of his outlets were automated.
So instead of the normal plug, like the normal outlet, every outlet was home automation
enabled.
And you're thinking, wow, guy's a genius.
This is great.
He's going to be able to control.
This is probably 10 years ago.
And he said, you know, it was kind of neat, but the reliability of the devices wasn't
very good.
And it feels like every one month, let's say one Saturday a month, I am replacing an outlet
in my house.
And I'm like, oh, that does not sound like fun because again, outlets, normal outlets
will last for 30 or 40 years, right, is a home automation outlet going to last 30 or
40 years?
And even if it does, are you still going to be using that protocol 30 or 40 years from
now?
Right?
I mean, think about how much it's changed even in the past five years.
It's hard to imagine, right?
What opportunities or what interface you're going to need 10 years from now.
You really want to replace all the outlets in your house with a new, with either replaces
they break or replace them.
My brother had the Zigbee thing and he, the electricity bounced on his house and all of
a sudden all his devices went offline.
And we're at a dinner, I think we had, me and my cousins and my brother were having
a dinner and he's talking about this thing and it just happened.
And he hasn't been home yet because he went to work and happened while he was at work.
So his wife calls, now the lights work, I can't turn on anything.
He says, well unplug this, unplug that, plug that back in, doesn't fix it.
And he's asking me, could a power spike when they take the electricity off and on, could
it have wiped out like a third of his devices?
Because a third of his device would just like go on.
And I said, it's possible, but it's more likely it's like a hub or something.
And it turned out he gave me the report later.
He said I went home and I played with it for like four or five hours and I got it working
again.
So A, he had to be home to do it.
His wife was not able to do it because she didn't understand the network and how it was
set up.
But even then I think what he ended up having to do was to hard reset one of the hubs and
that brought all the devices back on.
Power cycling, it didn't work.
It seems like some part of the CMOS got whatever.
The firmware got weird.
But again, is that something you want to deal with in your house?
And is that something your family wants to deal with in your house?
So I'm just saying, I'm not saying it's right or wrong, but it's a reality is what I'm saying.
Cost can be an issue.
I know the Insteon stuff was fairly expensive.
I have heard complaints about the cost of some of the Philips products, although the
quality is very high.
People have talked about that.
So again, a lot of things go into that choice, longevity, ability to upgrade, that kind of
thing.
Very interesting.
I don't have any answers, but very interesting.
Any questions so far?
Okay.
All right, let me just dive in because this is a software conference.
I want to give you some geeky stuff here.
And this kind of freaked me out that this actually works.
But it works every day without fail to the point where my family has no idea it could
never not work.
So about 20 years ago, I had just moved into a big house.
And we're kind of living in a house for six months.
Electrician was there.
He was working on something.
I don't know why he was there.
He was a really nice guy.
And I said, you know, I said, can you look at something?
My wife, there's a light at the bottom of the stairs.
And my wife would like a switch at the top of the stairs.
She can turn the light on.
You're going down the stairs at night.
You want to be able to turn the light on as you're walking down the stairs.
It makes perfect sense.
So I asked the guy, I said, can you put a switch here?
He's like, well, he said, I can.
But the problem is the light's downstairs.
The switch is on the wall downstairs.
So I'd have to open the wall and then the ceiling to get the wire up to the wall on
the second floor to put the switch in.
I'm like, well, I don't think we want it that much.
I don't think it's that important.
He said, have you thought about X10?
I'm like, I said, I've heard of it.
I said, does it really work?
And he said, actually it does.
He said, I put it in my house.
And it actually works really well.
But he said, also, he said, I've talked to my customers about it.
And particularly when I'm doing new construction, I can basically install it while I'm working
on their stuff.
And he said, every person I've talked to, I give them the quota, the price.
It's like $600 to add some home automation to maybe the lights outside or whatever.
But every customer I've talked to has said no.
So he said, I use it.
But everyone I try and recommend it to, they're like, oh, I don't want the headache.
I don't want to pay the $600.
I don't see the value.
These are the kind of things that the feedback that he as an electrician got.
So let me show you how it works.
And we can kind of walk through it and sort of see.
So this is, and I apologize if there's any US specific electrical things in here.
I'm going to do my best.
So this is basically the sine wave for electricity.
I believe this is a US cycle here because I think it's 60 hertz.
And in Europe, it would be 50 hertz, right?
So you just pretend it's not that.
So basically, the electricity goes up and down like this.
This is alternating current.
Pretty straightforward.
This is positive volt.
This is negative volt.
And then the target is 115 roughly in the US.
And it just goes back and forth.
What they figured out in the 80s is that when the electricity crosses the zero voltage point,
they could inject a small signal, like a blip at a certain frequency, and have it travel
along the entire wiring of your house.
So I'm not sure how many of you are aware that, for example, you can run ethernet over
coax now.
It's called Mocha.
And it's basically, if you have coax in your house, you can run ethernet.
So I have a TV in the family room.
I don't have ethernet out there, but I have a coax.
So in the basement, I have a Mocha adapter.
Ethernet plugs in.
Out comes the coax.
The coax goes through the whole house.
Gets picked up in the family room.
I have another Mocha adapter.
In comes coax.
Out comes ethernet.
Goes right into the TV.
So the same way that you can run ethernet over coax, you can run home automation over
an electrical system.
Crazy but true.
So here we have a signal blip right here.
Here's a zero.
So this will be a one.
We're getting back to binary here.
Very exciting.
People are salivating.
So here's a zero.
Here's a one.
Here's a zero.
And if you think of, now we're starting to see where we're going here, you can see this
is 1 1 0 0 1 1 0 1 0 0 1.
So what they effectively did, these people in the 80s weren't idiots.
They basically had a binary code for different house codes.
It goes from A to P. So this is the binary code for A. I know it's not ASCII.
It's just whatever it is.
They did have ASCII back then, but stick with me here.
This is A. This is B. This is C. This is D. And these are the patterns for the different
house codes.
So if you want, so actually here's a sine wave on what device is this?
Anyone?
All right.
People know what that's called.
That's good.
Oscilloscope.
Yes.
I'm not that old.
People remember.
Yes.
This is an oscilloscope right here.
And you can see that's the way it used to look.
And it was, Tektronix was the big manufacturer of these, I remember.
And here is an oscilloscope showing those little blips in the crossing of the zero voltage.
Okay.
So that's literally, and we can thank, I believe I have a website that lists where I got this
from.
And it's kind of cool that you can just kind of link like that.
Okay.
So that's two ones right there.
So the X10 standard basically, actually, forget the 1980s.
1975 was the standard was made in Scotland.
It didn't really become popular, I think, till the 80s.
Uses the 120 hertz carrier.
And again, that's two 60-carat cycles in the US.
I believe they also have them in Europe for European things.
So one bit is transmitted per zero crossing.
120 bits a second.
There you go.
You thought modems were bad.
This one's really bad.
256 maximum devices on your network.
16 house codes.
Each house code has 16 devices.
And again, there's the standard right there.
Okay.
So this is what it would look like, the protocol for that.
This would be the start code.
This is the house code.
And this is the device number.
And then you would say on or off or dim or whatever you want that device to do.
This is how you control it.
Okay.
This is the full protocol.
So here are our house codes.
Here are device numbers up to 16.
And here are commands.
So it looks like there's about 16 commands.
There's brightness, dimness, on or off.
These are the big ones right here.
These four.
These four are the ones you see the most.
Okay.
Crazy but really cool that they got this to work.
Obviously one of the problems is you need like three-quarters of a second to send a
signal.
And those of you who are really smart will realize that's kind of slow.
It's because you always send a signal twice.
Because electrical systems can be noisy and therefore if the same signal appears twice
then you know that that's the valid signal.
Okay.
So it's sent twice.
Poor propagation.
The United States uses split phase systems.
I'll talk about that in a minute.
I don't think Europe has that problem but that there's an issue there.
Line noise can be a problem and other buildings can also probably be a problem.
Okay.
So this is what a house typically looks like.
You've got a 220 coming in but basically it's positive 110 and negative 110 and then you
have two phases.
You have a positive phase and then a negative phase over here.
And that's typically the way that houses or in the United States at least are built.
One of the problems of course is that because you have split phase it's hard to get signal
from one side of the phase to the other so they have something called a signal coupler
which basically transmits that blip between the two.
Okay.
Phase coupling.
Let's just do that.
You can filter stuff so you can filter out line noise if you want.
So let's look at the actual devices.
This is a switch right here.
This is a normal switch.
This is an X10 switch.
Notice there's no up or down because it's just a button because you may have turned
it on remotely.
So we don't have a status to it.
There's no physical status.
You push it.
So on you push it.
It's off.
Okay.
You might be thinking, oh gee, why would I want a button like when I have home automation?
And the funniest story I can tell you is that if home automation had started first and we
never had physical buttons and physical buttons showed up people would think they were genius.
Because physical buttons are really convenient.
Let me tell you how convenient they are.
My nephew lives in New York City, rehabbed the whole house, decided he was going to go
full with home automation, put in physical light switches but decided I'm not going to
use them.
I'm just going to use the Phillips or the Z-Wave Zigbee bulbs.
So if you're going to use the Zigbee bulbs and you control them remotely you effectively
have to always give them power.
So the switch, you've got to leave it on all the time.
If you turn it off it can't turn on anymore and flipping a switch doesn't work.
It doesn't do anything.
So what he decided he was going to do is every time he was going to control it with voice
controls so when he walks in the room he says echo lights on and he leaves.
He says echo lights off and echo lights on and echo lights off.
I was there in the fall and I said how's it going?
He said you know we're getting tired of talking all the time.
He said you know I thought it was really cool but after a while it gets kind of annoying.
So I think he's going to have to rethink that whole home automation lack of switch control
thing.
So there's what physical switch.
What I'm saying is don't dismiss the light switches as completely useless.
There actually is some use to that.
Here's a different type of switch.
It's a flat switch.
More modern basically.
Three way switches you can do those with X10 as well so that's actually a three way switch
right there.
No actually this is a three way.
They're all three way switches actually these three.
You can do this which is kind of cool.
It's basically there's nothing behind this.
This is just stuck on the wall.
So it's basically a wireless remote.
You just hit the button.
You stick it.
This is how I fix the problem coming down the stairs.
I just stuck one of these on the wall and then every two years I replace the little
battery that's in it like this big.
So I go around the whole house just replace all the batteries every two years.
It works really well.
This is the adapter that basically receives the signal from the wireless if you have that.
It's another wireless device that we have little buttons do those whatever you want.
You control it.
This is a four device model.
There's also a 16 device model right here.
So this one right here and this is a lamp and you can see here's a good setup.
Here's the lamp.
Here's the X10 module plugged into the into the outlet.
OK.
And then and then and basically this goes up and goes to this right.
So this is an X10 controller and it does up to 16 devices.
So again you need one two devices four devices 16 devices.
You can pick a different remote that does that for you.
OK.
So I think this is kind of a good example where you'll notice I did not get outlets
that no X10.
I just got plug in things.
Why did I do that.
I don't want to spend one Saturday a month like pulling out my outlets and fixing them.
They've been very reliable but at the same time I may not stay with this technology.
I don't necessarily want to rip everything out.
I don't mind seeing a little white box there.
It's easier for me and if something doesn't work I can just plug another one in and debug
it like real quick.
Right.
Because it may not may not be the bug maybe the box it just makes you really.
OK.
Pool pump.
I talked about this.
Basically I have a pool and I want to turn the pump on.
Basically this is done with the big timer dial.
Remember we talked about the timers with the little dial and you know it goes around every
24 hours.
The problem with that is that I want the pump to run more when it's hot and less when it's
not hot because the hotter it is the longer you have to run the pump.
So by controlling it and this is right here this little X10 switch right here.
Right.
In this little box you can basically figure out what how warm is it outside.
You ask the weather service how warm is it outside and then depending on how warm it
is that's how long the pump runs.
And my pool people will come and they'll say you should sell this.
I'm like well I could but then I have to have a controller and I have to have some way of
programming it to get the weather and it's not what I found it's very hard to to productize
a lot of the home automation stuff in general because everyone's need is different and to
prioritize it it's kind of it's kind of difficult.
This is a command open source program called Hey You which actually controls X10.
I've used this I guess since I've been using X10.
There basically is an interface between the electric plug right there and a serial cable.
A serial that comes out here and goes over to here where my server is right here.
OK so this goes out and then I think currently it goes into a little USB adapter which converts
serial to USB and then the USB goes in and Linux has no trouble communicating serial
to that.
So you can see the sort of network interface between right.
You've gone from Linux to USB to serial and then to power to X10.
Kind of interesting.
OK.
I can monitor what's happening so here is a report of what has happened at the house
all of the activity that's happened so I can basically say OK this is happening this is
happening this is happening and I can look and get a log of that.
This is a shell bash script that I wrote which effectively monitors what happens in X10 and
then it takes different actions depending on what happens.
So if somebody does one thing I say go do this other thing.
Is it too late?
Do this other thing.
Don't do it if it's too late in the day.
People might be asleep.
Are we ready to eat?
There's all these things that happen.
For example when somebody hits a button in the kitchen it sends a message to all of the
terminals and all the laptops in the house saying it's time to eat.
There's a slide show in the kitchen.
Big batter comes up time to eat for 20 seconds.
And there's also an X10 chime.
So there's little X10 modules that make like a little ding dong sound like a doorbell.
And I put them in different parts of the house so when they press it there's this little
ding dong you hear different parts of the house.
And then it's time to eat.
I tried it first just making one really loud sound that didn't work well.
Because when you were in the room it made the loud sound it was very annoying and when
you were far away you didn't hear it.
So to do that I had to kind of spread it out.
So again you're looking at some input and you're looking at some output and that's kind
of the way you have to think of it.
So what inputs do I use?
I use the time of day.
I have dust on sensors to know how light it is outside.
I use wireless remotes.
I use caller ID.
I'll talk about that in a minute.
I even have telephone dialing so I can actually I don't know if you're familiar with modems
but you can still buy modems and you can make them dial the telephone.
So you can have like a instead of dialing it yourself you can tell the computer take
this address book entry and dial it and I'll just pick up the phone and talk to them.
So it kind of makes it convenient for people.
Even things like outside temperature you can get from websites.
And then outputs.
We can do lights.
We can turn on motors like the pool pump.
We can do appliances like the coffee maker.
I'll tell you that when we get there.
I can make sounds.
I can make broadcast messages on the laptops and I can even have a slideshow have a big
screen to say time to eat or somebody's arrived in the garage.
This is maybe overwhelming but it's basically a lot of the first floor of my house.
Here's the server right here.
So remember I show you that little adapter the serial adapter with the X 10 that's right
that's number four.
Here are the yellows are lights that are controlled.
Here is the sunset sensor.
Here is yeah.
So this is where you have a remote.
You can tell people to do stuff.
One of the interesting things you'll notice that the lights at the front of the house
you see all these these lights right here.
They turn on right before dusk right when it's getting dark.
But what I realized is that why would I turn the lights on always at the same intensity
every day.
What I'll do is I'll randomly have different intensity lights every time I turn them on.
So if you look at my house one day maybe the maybe the garage will be brighter and the
front door will be dimmer and the next day the porch will be brighter and the front door
will be brighter and the garage will be dimmer.
So just adds a little bit of variety to how people view your house and kind of looks like
a neat little thing.
I think it's kind of cool.
Let's see here.
Yeah.
So this is basically this is walking you through how you know how the system works.
I think it's I think it's kind of interesting.
Any questions.
Yes sir.
So the question is does the X10 link to your neighbors as well.
So technically X10 will will broadcast up until your transformer.
If you're familiar with the transformer it turns out that my run goes right from my house
to the transformer.
So I don't have other people between me and the transformer so I don't think anyone else
sees it.
However if you're sharing a transformer with other people on the same wire they will absolutely
see it and that's why they have the house codes.
So if you find that somebody's using your house code you may switch to a different house
code and therefore you will not see interference from them.
Great question.
OK.
Yes.
Can you have a filter in your mains.
Absolutely they sell filters that will filter your mains and therefore it doesn't leak out
to the rest of the house.
Yeah.
Great question.
I'm going to keep going here.
So I promise I was going to talk about what success looks like.
Basically adding home automation changes your family's home environment.
Good or bad.
Right.
I recommend you start slow because my brother he had seen me do it and he kind of went all
in.
But the reaction I got from I just talked to my wife last night and she was at a funeral.
My uncle actually had a funeral on Friday that I unfortunately missed but she was talking
to my sister in law and she was complaining about the fact that when she does not know
how to control the lights in the house there are different voice commands and she can't
remember what she what my brother called that device and she it's my brother.
I don't know.
I would have I told maybe we put labels on things so you can remember what we called
them for the voice commands.
But it's not a good situation to be in when your family is feeling like they don't have
control because it's their house too.
And they want to feel like they certainly should feel comfortable in controlling their
environment and if you kind of come in too strong you can bypass them.
So in fact my trick was that I put in home automation just for the outside lights.
OK.
And my wife like two month later she said can you do this one lamp for me.
I said sure.
And I waited like four weeks and I was really excited to do it but I'm like I'm going to
wait a couple of weeks and then I did it because I didn't want to feel like I just was trying
to move it too fast.
So it's been very incremental and that has allowed people to look at it as a positive
versus I think sometimes can look at as a negative.
OK.
Except that some home automation tests are impossible and again you've succeeded when
a family member asks for home automation edition.
That is your gold standard.
Try and keep an eye on that one because if you don't get there I would say you're kind
of full and this is actually a great article.
Smart home gadgets still a hard sell.
Wall Street Journal article right there.
So challenges.
Change is hard.
Reliability.
So sometimes it's hard for family members to understand how it's working.
Device longevity I talked about that.
Maintenance I talked about what happens if something breaks right.
The cost I talked about that and of course security privacy are also important.
And again we have a nice talk about the Nest thermostat bug leaves users in the cold.
Not a good not a good experience there.
So be aware it's it it's scary sometimes.
OK.
So let's just run through this and I'm going to take some questions.
So this is mostly just a Q&A part.
I mean show and tell.
So here are the modems I use where it actually again serial cables going up to USB.
But I have two phone lines and it's just modems they can not only can I dial the number but
I can get caller ID so I can get caller ID and show everyone in the house who's calling
on the phone.
Right.
You don't have to look at the phone you see it on your computer.
Really kind of nice.
This is I can log all the telephone calls coming in.
All right.
I can dial the phone as I said before.
Again I use caller ID to broadcast messages and to make it shine if it's somebody important
like a family member.
OK.
And I end up taking the caller ID I look it up in my telephone directory and then I know
who it is and I can actually give a text message instead of just a number I can customize what
it looks like.
OK.
I can make outgoing calls as I said before.
This is a second floor is the first floor.
Again talking about all the pieces work together.
This coffee maker is kind of fun.
Second floor again some lights some chimes and you know some wireless remotes so you
can kind of see they're kind of spread out in different parts of the house.
Here's the pool pump out here.
OK.
This is what the hell you can fake file looks like you basically define your codes and then
the names that go with each of those codes.
All right.
Here's what extent commands look like.
Here's the standard timer.
Here's a crontab course we're running on Linux so we can crontab schedule a whole bunch of
stuff right.
Works just very seamlessly very easy to control for me anyway.
Dawn dust sensor I talked about that.
Here's a remote that you can use to control this is the coffee maker kind of hilarious.
The way we do it is my wife my my aunt lives with us and she usually gets up early.
So my wife has a remote next to the bed and when she wakes up she presses the remote and
then it makes a chime in my aunt's area and that means my aunt should it turns on the
coffee maker for her.
OK.
So I saw somebody look at their spouse.
So yeah.
So the cool thing is that you have to have an ant to set it up for you.
Right or something or want to make a coffee system if you don't have an ant.
But the cool thing is you you you hit the button when you're about to get out of bed
and by the time you get downstairs your coffee's ready.
OK.
And here's the coffee maker time.
It only turns it off for like 15 minutes so it doesn't stay on for long.
And she also has a little button on her phone.
So if she's driving home as she's heading home she can hit the button and then everyone.
Yeah.
OK.
So this is how it actually works on the phone.
I actually have an it actually does an SSH session and then calls an X 10 command and
then logs out basically.
OK.
Pool pump job scheduler weather for the website wireless remote.
This is kind of an interesting case garage entry detection.
I'm not going to get into this but effectively what I ended up doing was to put an X 10 switch
up at the top and when the door comes up it detects it and and just pushes a little lever
and I have an X 10 control with like wires and it sends a signal to say somebody closed
the contact and I know somebody came in the garage.
OK.
And again that's exactly that's what it looks like right there.
Right.
There's the there's a lever right.
And there's the X 10 so the wires go up here and then plugs in and then it goes right to
the computer and the computer does everything.
OK.
All right.
Let's take some questions.
Yes sir.
Right.
So how would you implement this with modern technology that didn't have as many moving
parts.
So my son I would say has done that.
He's doing Zigbee so everything's controlled with his phone and he's using HomeKit.
So basically he's he's using instead of using switches he's using light bulbs that are Zigbee
enabled and but he's still using some X 10 stuff because he wants a physical switch on
the wall.
So I think the question is are you happy with doing everything on your phone.
That's the question.
Right.
So when I walk into a room do I want to pull my phone out to turn the lights on.
I think he's OK with that and there's a whole bunch of cool stuff you can do like proximity
when he's getting when his car is getting near the house cool stuff can happen.
So there's a lot of potential there.
But because I'm trying to bridging the old and new technology together that's why it
looks so kind of hokey.
One more question.
Let's see if I can get it right here.
Right.
You're basically clearly to a study where he gone largely for extent which is wired
and you are more of a power user slash tinker.
So but the dealing of the kind of like ever Joe user who's got no idea what exactly smart
home does and or what their smart home assistant sends to the big tech.
How would you talk to such people about automation because we've got the game.
Oh you want your light bulb connected to the Wi-Fi.
Cat flap is connected to the Wi-Fi and everything.
And then they end up with a situation they can switch the lights on at home because the
power is.
How would I start if I didn't know nothing.
I would just say get a get a light bulb that has a phone control and they just kind of
get started with it.
But you're going to be on a 10 year journey potentially because it didn't start this
way.
I started just with the out front lights and it grew over time as I found need.
So again my goal is not really to talk about technology but to figure out how to think
about that technology in relation to you your family and your home.
So thank you.