Welcome, everyone. It's probably the first time in the last three years I actually see
this big auditorium full of people willing to hear something I'm going to rumble about.
I actually wrote a bit of script for this, but I'm bad at the memories in those scripts,
so it will be remembering as I go, rather than seeing something that I wrote about.
For the past 10 years, a team I'm a member of, we are working on a bunch of stuff related
to something that many people think is uninspiring, because it's all about the enterprise use
of Linux, which is just a done deal. Every enterprise uses Linux nowadays.
We kind of look into some of the areas and choose what to work on, because there's always
stuff unfinished and needed to be worked on. Suddenly, there's obviously 10, 15 years ago,
some companies from the west coast, they started to look into, hey, this shiny thing called
the internet and this shiny way of having your account somewhere in the social network
drive your login into your machine, and so on. Here we are, 10, 15 years after talking
about doing similar thing for Linux in enterprise environment and at home.
I will start with a bit of introduction. I'm working at Red Hat for almost 12 years now.
I'm focusing on the identity management, so basically really running accounts in the Linux
systems. Centralized identity management is what we do. Mostly working on these days free
IPE, and I started with Samba 20 years ago, SSSD on the client side, MIT Kerberos for
the authentication and so on. There's a lot of things blended together, and it's really
not a single person or a single project. It's an amalgamation of a lot of activities of
a lot of people around the world. This talk is a kind of a split between past
contemporary things and what we see in future, or what we see now will be in future. Hopefully
in February of 39, if we get this through in up streams first and then manage to collect
this all together in the distributions, which will be a point to talk about a bit later.
In the past, we've been always getting all this stuff with a bunch of assumptions. One
of the really unspoken assumptions is that when you log in into your system, be it Linux
system or Windows system or so on, you don't only want to use that particular system. Typically
you want to go beyond that system. You want to go, well in these days you go onto web
typically and use all these web applications. But before that in office environment, you
were reaching for your nice non-working printer, or you were reaching for something to fetch
files from or get your home drive and all the other stuff, or play games together with
your colleagues on the local network and so on. In many of those cases, you needed to
get through the authentication information that you provided or got at the log in time.
You needed to get this state of authentication translated or correlated into the network
onto the network services. A typical approach that we see these days is that you unlock
your let's say, NOM session. Then there is a secrets manager, which gets your secrets
store unlocked using the password that you provided as a part of login. Then the passwords
from this secret store used transparently by the other applications through some common
APIs like browsers have their own stuff, of course they have their own password managers
and those might be even shareable across multiple devices and so on. But it still doesn't solve
the real problem, which is when you log in into the system and you go to specific network
phase and applications, you need to do this transition or transfer the authentication
state between maybe incompatible or not well connected protocols. It is bridging that we
don't really have in place and in many applications we kind of derive it based on certain things.
In reality, it's much easier in the enterprise world because for almost 40 years we've been
dealing with something that is called Kerberos in different ways of it, which is effectively
a decoupling of the initial authentication and then requesting some authentication tokens
on behalf of you after you got this initial authentication done. That's a nice thing.
Over years Kerberos as a mechanism grown these authentication or how it's called awkwardly
in the Kerberos world pre-authentication mechanisms that allow you to use something more than
just passwords. So you can use for example smart cards or you can use one time codes
two factor authentication mechanisms and so on to log in or initially provide the initial
credentials to obtain the so called ticket grant and ticket in the Kerberos thing. The
good part of it is that this is exactly a way to get the transferable authentication
state. Over years we added to Kerberos ability to record how this initial state was acquired.
So an application can use an API to inquire whether this initial token was obtained with
a password or with a smart card or with some other more strong type of authentication.
So it can differentiate how to behave if for example application specific policy says that
you cannot use this application if you were not using smart cards or you were not using
FIDO2 tokens and so on. Then application can inquire this information and say yeah you
are not allowed to use this. You cannot use sudo on these machines because you're merely
used your password. That kind of thing. And this is the thing that I was doing a lot and
the one thing connected with this is that the complexity of a typical Kerberos environment
is huge. But separating the pre-authentication method is a nice part because it allows to
decouple the other part of complexity. All these tokens or separate devices that you
can use to prove who you are and that you possess these credentials from the actual
applications. It's really splitting up in these two parts is what is important here
because we can write applications once and forever at least the verification of the authentication
authorization there and deal with the rest separately. This is for example how it looks
like in a typical Kerberos environment with free APA or with Samba AD or Microsoft Active
Directory. This is detailed description from the Red Hat's Enterprise Linux Identity Management
Guide. Links in the PDF map just as an example of what we are dealing with. And the fun part
is that how many seven years ago I've been talking in the other room in Janssen about
similar things. So how we started with this. How we started with the enterprise graphical
workstations on Linux. That was how many fifteen Fedora releases in the past. Fifteen that
when I wrote that I kind of did not realize that we are thirty seven now and it's like
seven and a half years back. And almost all this stuff already worked by that time. The
smart cards were possible to use in this environment. Of course there were some issues with the
visual representation how you choose these smart cards and so on. But it's kind of funny
that what I will be showing to you today is kind of similar to what we did seven years
ago. We fixed this problem for smart cards eventually together with the GNOME people
by introducing some interfaces between SSD and GNOME components. GDM and the other parts
of the window manager. So that they can pick up this information and show a nicer UI to
choose who you are based on your smart card and so on. But smart cards were the first
thing we did with this passwordless authentication because you don't need passwords anymore on
this system. So what happened in these seven years and that's a nice period because every
seven years something happens with people. They change themselves and environment around
them changes a lot. So what happened? Actually there was change of winds and that's a fundamental
one. If you remember 2015 2016 a typical office environment first there were offices where
people were working every day going into those offices and they had a network actually where
those computers were connected and enrolled into the whatever domain controllers were
in those offices. So it really was an environment that was for the infrastructure for people
right that you come you switch in your laptop connected and it's it knows what to do. It
was so to say infrastructure for people. Nowadays these are all infrastructure in cloud and
it's not for people it's for applications. You deploy applications some way in the cloud
and all that infrastructure that is there is not for your you as an employee you as
a someone who consumes it. You don't consume that infrastructure anymore. In most cases
of course there are exceptions. In most cases you are consuming the applications and applications
consume that infrastructure. So if your laptop is enrolled in something that's most likely
not the same environment as your applications enrolled. The applications are actually consuming
what they consuming stuff like or else they get tokens they get authorized to get tokens
on your behalf from the identity provider service that is some wag stuff that you don't
really know how is built inside in most cases and you don't care. All you care about is
that you can prove to this identity provider your identity and for that you can use a bunch
of stuff. For most of the cases on the social networks or on a myriad of websites and so
on you don't even prove for them that you possess certain credentials. You prove this
for some identity provider that they connected to and that something that I call bring your
own authentication. So you connect your account in something to your social network account
and you prove to the social network that you are who you are and then that social network
IDP issues talking to that site where you want to be. That's essential to bring your
own authentication to that site. The site doesn't really care how you authenticated
to the social network how you prove yourself. And in fact what becomes out of it is all
infrastructure around OAuth and OIDC is a part of it is built around I have a browser
and this browser is everything I need. There are redirects between different components
and websites they talk to each other on your behalf so this is kind of a new mainframe
where everything runs. So you still need a network access for this to work. And here
we get back to the 2016. In 2016 one of the biggest issues we were identified at that
point for enterprise workers was everyone goes into business trip, goes into the hotel
and every single hotel has captive portal on their Wi-Fi. So in order to log into your
machine using your credentials you have to solve a problem of solving captive portal
before you log into the machine. The fun part is that we never solve this problem at all.
Instead of solving this problem we basically say to ourselves let's remove our machines
from the corporate environment, right? Decouple machine from the environment rather than solving
the problem. Maybe this is a good solution but maybe not because right now to solve to
get this authentication again working for us we need to run browser before we log in
again and running browser before you log in in titles running insecure unknown executable
which is JavaScript code with the access to your hardware which is your at least screen
and GPU and so on because that's what the browsers are requiring to do this stuff. So
that's still the problem to solve and of course some of these problems might be solved but
some of these problems might be hey move the way. So almost everyone has a phone. So this
is somewhere I can run a browser instead of my laptop. So maybe I can run the authentication
and authorization process on this separate device instead of running it on my laptop
when I try to log in. It's kind of getting around the problem but maybe all the problems
are like that. Get around them rather than solve them directly. And in some cases this
is not even a problem. For example if you want to log in over SSH and you're already
logged into your workstation then launching a browser on your already logged in workstation
is easy right. You just need to have a URL to get into. So let's try I hope I will show
this. Let's try a demo. So here I'm trying to SSH into some machine and on the whatever
left side from you I have IDP based on the key clock open source project and this user
it doesn't have the security key associated with it. Now I'm associating so basically
I'm taking this kind of token and connecting it with this user. Okay. I have this token
associated somewhere there and now I can log out of my IDP just to make sure that I don't
reuse the same session that I obtained with the password. Right. So now I'm trying to
SSH and I'm presented with a message that says okay authenticate against this browser
somewhere. So I have a browser it's handy. I'm getting I'm using the security key to
actually authenticate instead of the password. I authenticated into the system now the system
says you're after I said do you after I rise this access. Yes I have for I said this access
and logged into the system but a part of this authorization is that I'm getting a Kerberos
ticket. Kerberos ticket issued to me by my infrastructure and now this Kerberos ticket
can be used for well anything. Anything that's allowed there within this Kerberos environment
so I can SSH with this Kerberos ticket further. I can mount NFS or some of something shares
get access to files. I can use this Kerberos ticket to sudo into the system itself. There
is since last year or actually 2000s first there is a palm module as a part of SSD palm
SSS GSS. This module actually checks that you have active Kerberos ticket and its properties
are good enough to access palm services so you can configure for example sudo to say
that if you have Kerberos active Kerberos ticket with obtain it with the IDP authentication
or smart card then you can use sudo rules on this machine. Which rules is separate from
this but you can get access to sudo with it. You don't have password you never had password
in your system. The password maybe existed somewhere in the IDP in this key clock thing
or in GitHub or GitLab or Google for your company or Azure for your company or your
own like key clock stuff. But the rest will work the same regardless how you get there.
So it's a bit complex in terms of how this is implemented and how it goes. But at the
core of it is we split the process into parts. There's initiates in part which in this case
is the running on the server I tried to log in. There is a part that actually verifies
that your IDP authorized access which is running on the Kerberos key distribution center part
so Kerberos server side. And then there is a client which is in our case SSH trying to
connect to the SSH server which initiates process and of course there is a browser that
you run somewhere. You so you're right there. Probably to use a phone to access that URI.
You probably want to have a QR code instead of the URI or in addition to the URI. This
is one easy kind of thing that we need to implement to make it easier. But also it will
become probably a mandatory part if you want to integrate this with the graphical login
into the system because you cannot run browser yet. But surely you can show the nice picture
that you can access from your phone or other device. And you will need something like that
for the pass keys existing only on your phone. The soft FIDO2 tokens that both Apple and
Google are eager to push to us these days. So effectively the same thing works with the
FIDO2. In fact the demo that I showed was FIDO2 token because the IDP side was going
to configure it to use FIDO2 or WebAuth token instead of password or smart card or OTP whatever
is there. So we already can do this. It's already in fact all the tests that I ran it's
Fedora 37. The one that's already released last November last year. So this password
let's login to the Linux console works on Fedora works on well 8791 and a client side
of it works on Ubuntu 2210 because they have this new SSD version that supports this stuff.
Okay so if I want to do this with the other services let's hope I can get another demo.
Now I can switch to the next one. There's it. Just a second.
Okay so this is basically exactly the same demo just using instead of SSH I'm using VLOK.
VLOK is just a normal application that uses PAM, Plugable Authentication Mechanism module
to lock your system. So typically what happens is that you lock your console and then you
have to provide a password. VLOK doesn't know anything about all this stuff but it works
because we use the standard APIs there. And in this case I don't need to provision the
token obviously because it's already provisioned but I can use it to login into the VLOK application.
This goes just transparently maybe awkwardly because of the URLs and not nice UIs and so
on but still it's there. The most important part here is that in order to all this get
work and we have to have a network and service, this IDP thingy, how we can get without it.
Well FIDO2 has this ability to work locally and not really through the web stuff so we
can run this authentication locally. And all these tokens that Yubico and well this is
Tokenill or some others, they use them all in the isolated environment as well. So we
can actually run it so I got one small demo with this to let's hope I get this started
again. This is recorded with my phone camera because I needed to actually show you that
I press something on the screen. So this screen is locked, right? And now I'm trying to login
into that screen and it asks me to insert this PUSKey device so I'm inserting it in
and you can see that it doesn't actually show you the full message that is shown there.
The part of the message says and press enter before it goes further. So when I press enter
it tries to communicate with the device, it blinks to me and then I have to press a test
that I physically present at the device to login it. And after that I'm unlocking the
same way as with Vlog or SSH through the palm I'm unlocking this. This was my presentation
this morning at the security dev room about the same thing. Now if we go logically further,
this is working actually by the way. I cannot show it on this laptop because as soon as
I lock my screen to unlock the video stream through HDMI will get disconnected and we
will have to wait another five minutes to get my screen working back so you wouldn't
see this on the screen. So believe my camera. Now how we can combine this? Okay, login in
locally with the FIDO2 token is effectively gives me a login into the system but the very
first thing the same problem that I discussed in the beginning applies here. How I transfer
this authentication state that I used the passwordless device to login to other applications.
Well in enterprise environment, whatever we call enterprise environment, for me the last
10 years or so enterprise environment is my home environment because I run what I develop
every IPA in my as my home authentication service. I simply need to transition from
these FIDO2 token authentication to Kerberos ticket using it, right? Sounds simple. Yes
it's also a bit of arrows and lines and so on but it's pretty much in line with this
one. It's just the question of who is communicating with whom to prove that the possession of
credentials is the real one. Okay. Unlike the previous one, I cannot show them of this
one because we are at the point where maybe in two weeks we will complete this implementation.
And of course the amount of bugs to find and fix will get this probably delayed until FIDO3
39 or so. But I really hope to get this working by that time which is by the way just how
many? Seven, nine, nine months away. Sounds a nice number. So that's not everything of
course because well it's only an infrastructural part of it. To get it usable and not to the
point that users will trash their laptops because they cannot read the message. Imagine
this is just a simple insert here, passkey device, the what if this was authenticate
against this URL, HTTPS, something that can't even fit into this box. That's the situation
right now. So we need to fix this with in this case it's a GDM of course, this is the
GNOM display manager. For the login we need to fix this. We started talking with the GDM
developers and there's some common understanding what to do. Similar to what we did with the
smart cards. The nice part of it is that it's mostly about a protocol of communicating between
the PAM service in this case and the display manager through the environmental variables
within the process. So SSDS can tell that I'm now using this type of passwordless authentication.
Please switch to this visualization of it. So we kind of can make it this way that it
works for GNOM but it's also usable for others. And here I come to the point of effort across
multiple projects. You can do this with GNOM but then what to do with KDE, what to do with
XFAC and others. There's a need to agree on something. We can agree on APIs, we can agree
on protocol driving semantics behind this but somebody needs to implement all these
pieces in the end. This is a common effort, us as a community. It's not just one company
or one developer crazy enough can drive and write all this code and get it. We as a community
need to work together to get this done. And of course this is just at the top of the iceberg.
There's a bunch of work needs to be done on the distribution level to make it usable for
clean installations for example. If I want to use this type of the key, if I go to keys
for example for the login into machine, I'm sure probably want to use it also to provision
encryption of my disk. And this is already possible with system D supporting configuration
of lock devices with the FIDO2. In all contemporary distributions, system D already compiled with
support for FIDO2. It's a matter of configuring them. It's the matter of configuring other
services to reuse all of this. But I don't think as much as I like Wiki pages that describe
how to do this in multiple articles, I don't think this is what we should be doing. It's
the distribution level job to polish or add this kind of polish. Again as a community
of distribution developers in Fedora, in Debian, in others, in Arc, we need to focus on this
kind of polishing. When all these pieces ready, sure someone will be faster with the releases
and polishing of it. But in the end, we as a community, we as a community of developers,
users, we are users themselves even if we know how this stuff works. It doesn't mean
that we tolerate how badly it's integrated. So that's my message here. We need to work
as a community to bring it all to us to be pleasant to work with. And with this one,
I guess I'm even on time. Thank you.
My question is about the two factor authentication when there is a password and a security key.
Do you know why in all the workflows the password is asked first and then the security key?
Whereas it likes to me that the security key is the strongest part and it should be better
to first press the button of the key and then enter the password. Is there some movement
to change the current way of doing things?
The question is whether using password and second factor and so on can be one of the
ways of doing it and is there an activity to make it better, let's say this way? Yes
and no. It depends on what we define as the first factor and second factor. One of the
driving factors behind passwordless work in the last 10 years or so across the industry
is the tightening of requirements from the government, specifically from US government.
US government issued so-called zero trust memorandum last year for origin governmental
organization to move by end of fiscal year 2024 to move to passwordless authentication.
This means that they have smart cards already. That's solved but they specifically name Web
Wolf and FIDO2 as one of the alternatives to smart cards. In fact, all of these things
they have pin associated with this which can be looked as a first factor. It's not the
first factor as we understand it. It's a first factor to unlock hardware rather than unlocking
some factor in software. This is the thing which drives some of this work, not necessarily
for us but for many others already. I think there is a value in staking factors. The question
is in which environments you want to use them and so on and configure this this way. Certainly
there is already a mechanism to enable it. For example, PAM already is staking. Technically
you can stack multiple PAM authentication modules in the same configuration for V-lock
or GDM or something and say always enter free passwords from different sources. That already
would be multi-factor, multi-password authentication. One of them this and the other one is the
password and the third one is phase of the moon and so on. You can get that stuff already.
It's the question of adopting to a specific environment where this makes sense. I have
not seen multi-password in the traditional kind of environments yet. If we do something like
integration with the identity providers like I show it in the demo, that gives you possibility
to move this check away into let's say, kick log. Kick log actually has ability to ask
a password or TP and the web often at the same time. You can configure that already.
Again the question is in which direction you want to focus this. Maybe not adding into
SSD or some specific PAM module but instead adding into more flexible and more controllable
source. Any other questions? Yes, here. You were talking about how can distributions and
desktop managers contribute to get a unified interface. I recently prompted to a project
called XTG credentials portal which tries to specify a standardized interface for interacting
with web often credentials such that different KDE and gnome and stuff can hook into this.
I was wondering whether you were aware of this project and if that would be a good place
to maybe start trying to collaborate on a unified interface.
The question is am I aware of the projects like XTG credentials that tries to specify
or unify access to the credentials for things like I think it's for the containerized environments,
desktop applications running in flat pack and so on. Yes, I am aware and that's one
partial thing that I mentioned about the parallel effort there. But it's not for the login.
It's for the reuse of the credentials in the browser or relay in party outside of the container
so you can isolate direct access. That's very important but it's a bit different layer.
It's the layer that we will eventually need to reuse if we want to do this transferable
state of authentication between different places without Kerberos. Yes, we will have
to work with them or they will pass or everyone. Yes.
Hello. So I use ED25519 security keys which SSH supports and it's really simple. So I
just generate a key and I can use it and my SSH team supports it. I don't really need
to run any services. I don't need to use Kerberos. How do we get to a world where everything
is that simple? So the question is why do I need all the things if my SSH keys work
fine with the hardware based tokens, X549 and based certificates and so on. The answer
is simple. It's not an answer for all use cases. You cannot authenticate with these
tokens and these keys to, for example, file services. You cannot use them to authenticate
to NFS. You cannot use them to authenticate to SMB or other resources. Needs are different.
Use cases are different. All of this thing does not replace SSH keys and SSH keys do
not replace this one. They exist in parallel to each other because if you start using FIDO2
tokens you wouldn't be using them exactly the same way on SSH level as well because
SSH will need to generate all the keys based on the same use of the same hardware but different
call specific and application specific thing. And this is where the problem really comes
in. You can find use cases where existing functionality is perfectly usable and secure
and attainable but it's not transferable to the other systems and other protocols. That's
the problem we try to solve. So it's more amending rather than displacing.
Hello. Hello. And thanks for the talk. My question is if I'm a very, very bad person
and want to break the system and steal the Kerberos ticket authentication for example,
what's the easiest way I can do it? So the question is how to steal Kerberos ticket in
the Linux environment in the easiest way despite all the protection mechanisms we want to add.
I probably answer what mechanisms we have so that you may reconsider your activities.
So in comparison, Microsoft some time ago added a virtualized slice where they store
all the credentials so you do not have access to that slice. It's running literally not
as a container, it's like a VM separated from the actual system where they handle all the
security credentials and so on. And you cannot easily store that from the memory of the applications
that try to load this stuff. On Linux side at that point we had a project called GSS
proxy. The GSS proxy is a daemon that runs in separate, typically on the root and it
interjects into GSS API hence the GSS proxy, GSS API operations and interposes access to
all Kerberos crypto material. So when you are a service like HTTP or NFS, you want to
have access to the Kerberos key top so that you can authenticate clients coming to you
and get access to it. Or your IMAP or send mail or something. And GSS proxy basically
removes access to the key tops, removes access to the credential cache that you use. They
are in separate process. So now if you are broken into NFS server like Ganesha or even
the kernel, well kernel one is probably easier target, right, if you happen to find a bug
that allows to exploit it. But you're probably not a Linux Torvalds anymore and it's not
1994 where he found NFS problems to hack into and get the data out, out of NFS. So typically
this privilege separation between the processes works fairly well. If you're root, of course,
you get what you get. In that case, there's some number of ways of preventing root running
processes from accessing the capabilities on the kernel level and on typical steel this
is an operation that should probably be multilayered. Like you have to use kernel capabilities,
then you have to use the file system level capabilities, then SLE, so App Armor to prevent
other access things. But basically with the GSS proxy we get isolation on this level and
also we get the content of the credential caches encrypted. So you can store or you
can steal credential cache if you get access to that. But it will be encrypted with temporary
key that exists only until GSS proxy runs. So even if you steal it, you cannot really
use that one. The other part is that there are credential cache collection types that
do not allow direct access to the credential cache. So for example, a keyring, kernel keyring
where you can store and tighten it fairly tight so that application doesn't get these
keys out. The other one is KCM which is also a separate process accessible over the Unix
domain socket. You don't get direct access to the files either. So there are some mechanisms.
They are not so dramatic as in Windows case where they run it in completely different
way. We are isolated on a hardware level. But we get fairly far away. I've seen people
trying to decode the KCM databases but that presumes that they get access to the physical
root partition so they can read the actual files from the KCM back store. But of course
that if you're root, if you're having access to the root partition, your game is lost in
most cases.
Yep.
Alexandra, many thanks for your interesting talk to give the community.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.