Thank you.
Hi.
Hello. I hope you had good beers yesterday.
Thank you for coming that early this morning.
I'm going to talk to you about the work that a few of us
started a while back, which is we're implementing one of the
tools that we're doing today. I'm going to talk to you about
the history of the project, explain what we're trying to do,
why, and maybe do a demo. Let's see what happens.
So, who I am. I'm doing a lot of things. Way too many things
according to my partner. I'm a developer for 15 years,
IBM for 10 years. I'm also my actual job is I'm a director at
the
web. I'm a developer for 15 years. I'm a developer for 15
years. I'm a developer for 15 years. I'm a developer for 15
years. But that work is clearly unrelated to what we're doing
at Mozilla. I don't want to get into troubles. But it's not a
project. But I've been working with the developer for a long
time. I managed some key people in the project. And in Paris,
I'm a developer for 15 years. I also uploaded the initial
version of REST in Debian a long time ago. And if you don't
know about packaging, you can package a software when you are
not an expert in the language it has been written in. I know
that sounds crazy, but I'm not a C++ compiler developer, but
I'm maintaining Clang for 10 years also. And I'm also
working with the developers in the Debian archive for a long
time. And they're for Ubuntu. But, yeah, let's talk about
what happened. If you remember, something weird happened three
years ago now. Most of the planet went on lockdown in our
country. Sorry. In France. I think it was the same in
Belgium and Italy and some country. So, this idea took
everything. So, I don't know what you have done on your side,
but what can I do with that three times that I had? So, some
people make bread. So, I stole a picture from Julien Dangeau.
He made some fancy bread. Who did bread here? Ah, a few.
Cool. Ah, béranger, too. Some of them did some woodworking.
So, I stole a picture from someone who used to work at
Red Hat, but now he's working at Mazias. He did some
woodworking. The picture is ugly. It's not my fault. Some
people did that stuff. Some people did gardening. And
myself, what I've done, it's my son on the top right. He
loves Lego, but he's destroying everything. Everything was
put in the single bracket. And we decided to rebuild the
Lego. So, it kept us busy for like three or four days. And
then, he still has to work, but my partner decided to wear
40 something. And she decided to rewatch Bushy as a vampire
slayer. I have a good memory for TV shows. I was like,
yeah, I don't want to watch it again. So, and then she did
also that. So, you can do the math. It's like 200, 204
hours. And it's basically I use that time to work on rest.
Because she was watching that stuff and I saw her. I
already saw the episode when I was younger. So, yeah, wanted
to go on rest. So, before what I've done 10 years ago is I
worked on that fancy project, which was at the beginning of
Clang when it was just starting to support some basic C++. I
package it into Debian and then I rebuild the Debian archive
instead of CCC. I use Clang and cut me a job at the end. And a
lot of fun. And I'm still doing that stuff even if I should
stop at some point. So, the idea of that project was how
can you replace a compiler by another one? Or like, yeah, I
like to do the same with rest. I'm not a student anymore, so
I don't want to do projects that are useless. So, I want to
work on something interesting. So, I started thinking about
what can I do? So, the first one is do I want to rewrite the
G
code? I don't want to read assembly. But at the end, there
is no assembly in a core. It's just one file that I can
never, I don't care about that one anyway. I'm good. But,
yeah, some people are going to say, why are you doing that?
It's pointless. So, yeah, it makes sense. You can think
about that stuff. But the first one is why not? We all had
crazy ideas in our careers and this one is one of them.
Rest is amazing. So, you can bring some value and you will
hear during that talk me repeating that stuff many times.
I'd like to, I will repeat that stuff a few times, but the
new implementation is fantastic. People doing that work are
amazing. They are giant. And we always hear that, first, is
amazing at security, at Modia. We keep repeating that stuff.
But for the new implementation, it's not an argument. They
had only 17 CVs for the last 20 years. So, it's not about
security, the implementation. And it's not about the license.
I know that some company cares a lot about license. Myself,
as soon as I can upload it into Debian, I'm fine. But some
people love debating how the GPL or MIT are amazing, or
they suck, depending on who you talk to. I am not
interesting to have that debate. I leave that debate to
Reddit or the other one. And last but not least, it is
super interesting. I hope during that presentation I will be
able to convince you to contribute and to write
patches. It's not that hard. I will even do a demo of fixing
a bug live, hopefully. So, I keep talking about that
stuff, but I think you all have a basic understanding, at
least, of what are the coretors. So, we'll start with a
quiz. So, who was born before 2000 in that room? I see a
lot of grey hair. Oh, yeah, a bunch of people. After
90, who was born after 90? That's N. After 80. After 71.
Yeah. So, congrats, you are younger than the initial
implementation of the coretors. So, the first version
was published by Ken Thompson in 70. So, thanks to
Software Itage, the archive done by Inria and a lot of
factors, you can see the sources of the initial
implementation. As you can see, the.s means assembly. I
won't share any assembly code today, don't worry, but you
can look at the source and it's pretty amazing to see that
that code has been written 53 years ago. So, Ken Thompson
and Denise, they worked on that stuff a long time ago.
And what we are doing right now, and you can generalize
that to most of the things in text, is that we are building
stuff on the shoulder of those giants. So, those two
folks invented things that we are still using on a daily
basis, like we all use CP, MV, and all that stuff. Even if
you don't know about it, your system is probably going to
use it behind. I will also mention that it was very
good for Madame Gordon-Belle, who is interviewing Brian
Keringan, talking about the history of the UNIX operating
system. So, those folks worked on new implementation of
those commands in 72. So, mostly C, so you can see that,
for example, CP and the if command were written in C.
The code is surprisingly easy to read. So, this one is a
source from, again, 50 years ago of CH mode. I'm sure that
if you know a bit of C, you can read it. And found that
fascinating to see that the code those folks wrote 50
years ago, I'm showing it at first then in 2023, and it's
still relevant, and people can relate to that code. And you
can ask yourself, is your code you are writing today still
going to be valuable in 50 years? Well, really not. But
those folks, they made it. And it's probably going to stay
for a long time. And this one is the actual implementation
of the CH mode function in the function written in 72. So,
it's not crazy code. It's full of bugs probably. But it
worked, and it is what started UNIX a long time ago. And
what I found surprising, listening to that podcast, is
also how amazing programming language, sorry, corey
fields and those commands are. We take that for granted.
But when you think about it, when you use sort, UNIX, cat
and all that stuff, it allows you to do some crazy things
very quickly. So, let's take a few seconds and think, I
give you a text file, and you want to tell me what is the
most common, the five most common words in the Shakespeare
books, longer than six cars. We can all do that stuff. It's
probably six, seven lines of Python, same in Rust, and
same in some languages. But if you do that in bash, sorry,
in corey field with bash, it is that common. And when you
think about it, it's very impressive that pipe and
redirection are the key things that we are doing and how is
it to program on a daily basis. All your system is running
that kind of stuff on a daily basis, and it makes it
super easy. I'm not saying that it is great, because it's
not full tolerant. If you have the single error in that
command, everything is going to break and you are not
going to get what you want. But still, you can do that kind
of things very quickly and very easily. So, by the way,
the results are those ones. So, in Shakespeare, more than
five letters, it should further accent. I don't know how to
pronounce that one. So, I had to google what it means. It
means that you leave the scene. That is what it means in
English for Shakespeare before and after. And it's pretty
funny to do that stuff. I did it until I checked it out,
and it's quite interesting to see what Shakespeare used in
terms of words. So, now let's talk about today. My
brother and history teacher, I'm not. So, I will talk
about what we have now. So, we have 105 comments in the
implementation. In the blue implementation, we are trying
to reach that level. You are very familiar with many of
those. Some of them you probably never heard of. And
I'd like also to remind that what is in the core details
of the comments can be weird. So, sometimes you don't
have find, you don't have find last stops and all those
comments, but you have some other things. And most of
these comments, they come up with arguments which sometimes
are conflicting with each other. Sometimes are completely
changing the argument of the behavior of the comment
depending on what you enter. So, second quiz. So, who
knows what the comment is? So, L, I, C, P, M, V. Everybody.
Sure. And then this one, probably two. Now we are
starting with the art stuff. Nump format. So, it's a
comment that, yeah, there is one of the maintainer of the
project with myself. Of course, you know. But really,
this is the only one. So, it's the kind of stuff that we
have to deal with because we want to be a drop team
replacement for the new project. But we have those
things. So, we have a lot of different things. One guy. So,
someone else. Convert text files for printing. So, it's
one of those comments and it has a huge number of arguments
which are probably conflicting with each other. So, C
split. Who knows? Daniel knows. Just a few people in
that room. So, it is to split a file into section
determined by the context line. It's cryptic, right? It's
weird. And we have plenty of other factors to do math. We
have pinky. I don't remember what he's doing. T sort is
doing some kind of search. Shred is to delete. Really
remove the data of a file on the hard drive. Sec is more
common, but still I really see that one in scripts.
And so, we have a bunch of implementation of the
curios available on the market. So, the most common that
everybody knows is the new implementation. So, our BSD
which is used on Mac, for example, BSD box is the one
when you want to use on MBD devices or when you want to
recover a system. Toy box is one of the core developers
of BSD box. This I did to rewrite Toy box because it was
sick of license discussion. I learned recently that there
is a V lang implementation. Don't ask me what is V lang. I
don't know. And if you are aware of the implementation,
please let me know. I will tell you why I want to know.
So, let's talk about our implementation. So, it was
started by Jodi. I will butcher his name, but
in 2013, before version 1.0, I sent an email to Jodi
because he has a.b email address saying I'm going to
present the work that you started ten years ago at first
time and he said, oh, cool. Glad to hear that this project
is still alive. Myself, I found it in early 2020, so
I started contributing in April. I remember that
COVID started in Europe in March. It's not a coincidence.
Now, he reads the size of the project. So, we have
13,000 stars and we have 300 and 50 contributors.
The second contributor to that project, you see his
picture with the white background is over there. Well
done. That's for your amazing work. He's the one
who is doing RPR. I'm doing the easy one. He's not a
good developer in general. Now, it's packaged in most
of the distro. Obviously, it's not a coincidence in
Debian and Ubuntu, but Fedora and most of them. It's
used by it is shipping in Appartis, which is a
Linux distro for cars, which between you and me found
it scary that they are using our work in production.
But I'm always the impostuous syndrome in terms of
development. It's used by a social network through
the project. It's not Facebook, the famous social
network. Another one and they are making glasses and
so on. I think you can guess who they are. They are
using that to take pictures in the glasses. This one
is for license reasons. Now, I'm doing some product
placement for one of the M
odzea achievement REST. Why do we want to do it in
REST? You don't have to worry about security issue at
MUSEA on Firefox. In particular, we see security
issue caused by C and C++, not on a daily basis, but
almost. You should not do C and C++ anymore if you
care about security. It's very portable. One of the
things that I learned with that project is we are
supporting a lot of configuration, a lot of
operating system. REST is really amazing for that.
It was one of my big discoveries. It was probably
for some of the REST developers in the room, but for
me, it was a surprise. I really don't like to
invent the wheel. We can leverage a lot of create
which has been developed by very talented people
over the years. LS color, for example, is used by
LSD or XR probably to provide the same color as LS.
We are using that stuff in the REST corey fields.
We are using that work here to do recursive
operation on the directory. We are using that
crate, so we don't have to worry about that one.
We use it for MK-10, for example. If you look at
the sources of the new corey fields, they have to
re-implement everything by themselves. Sometimes they
use that in some libraries, but they have to rewrite
a lot of things. While for us, we can reuse what
we have to do. And last but not least, we have
amazing performances. I will do a demo later of
some of the performances that we have, but
surprisingly, we are in some cases, we are
significantly faster than the glue implementation.
And it's a very popular language. No need to
explain why, but we have a lot of contributors,
and sometimes we are struggling to keep up with
the
things that we are trying to do.
We are trying to make sure that everybody wants
to learn REST, and you should if you don't, but
it's very popular.
So what is the goal of this specific
implementation? When I took over that project
a few years ago, I had exactly the same idea
in mind as Chris Lettner and Apple did back then
with Clang, is to be a drop-in replacement.
Clang is a pure replacement for GCC in general
for most of the options. It has been one of the
success, you just have to override the CXX
variable and you could use Clang directly.
If it was not working, it was a bug for most of
the cases. So it works surprisingly well.
Now Clang is a de facto standard for compiling
most of the very complex applications like
Chrome or Firefox. What can we do to
replicate that? So with the current
use, we focused on that one, to be a drop-in
replacement.
We want that stuff to be a cross-platform.
It has been decided before my time as the
leader of the project, but I love the idea, so we
support this operating system.
We are struggling with a free BSD,
CI, because it sucks on GitHub, but besides
that, it's working pretty well.
Except for Fushia, we have CI for every one
of them, so for every PR, we run a lot of
tests on those.
It's very easy to test. So on my laptop,
running the free test suite takes less than
a minute, and it's covering a lot of part
of the code. I will share some of the
code coverage information.
I don't care about it. Some people do.
For some people, it's strengths. For some
people, it's weaknesses, but it's an MIT
license, so that social network and reuse
still are a code to save money. Anyway,
I'm not interested in having that debate.
In my opinion, and I haven't seen anyone
in the community using that argument, it's
not a fight against the GNU project or the
FSF. The GNU project has been doing a lot
of good things for us in the open source
world for 20 or 30 years.
We are standing on their shoulder. It's not a
fight. I know that some GNU quality
developer of monitoring that project for
a long time has been very friendly and so
on. I met Jim Meyering 10 years or 20
years ago, and I was very impressed by
that person. It's not about fighting.
It's about collaboration.
When I started that project two or three
years ago, my initial goal was I want to
be able to put a Debian on it. My laptop
here is running the GNU coretils now.
For example, so it's not lying or it's
working well now. Then it was to install
the top 1,000 packages in Debian.
If I wanted to do that, it's that Debian
has a lot of script to configure the
package because that post-inst, and they
are usually done in Bash and using the
sort and CP and NV and install.
It's exercising a lot of features of the
GNU coretils.
One of the goals was also to build three
of the big projects I care about, Linux,
LLVM, and Firefox obviously. We don't
use that much scripting, Bash or
Knoritils, but I still found some bugs
building the Linux kernel, some corner
cases. Of course, packages into Debian
and Ubuntu.
I published some blog about it.
They have been shared on a bunch of
places. I had some interesting comments,
some of them not very interesting.
Anyway, so to achieve those goals, we had
to deploy a CI, add code coverage
support, improve the code coverage.
It's one of the things to get familiar
with the project. I wrote a lot of unit
tests, so now the code coverage of our
implementation is 80%. If you don't know
much about code coverage, 80% is usually
what we are trying to achieve. In a
project, it means that the code coverage
is very good. It's very hard to reach 100%,
and sometimes it's a waste of time, but 80
is usually considered as being a very
good code coverage. I think on Firefox,
we are at 65 or 70, something like that.
We plugged a bunch of tools. I'm in love
with static analysis, so of course I had
to do that for that project.
We also documented a lot of those processes.
Everybody loves about docs, so we wrote
plenty of docs. It took about a year to reach that state.
Now is the current stages. What we have,
you have a CI that is running for every PR,
and we run our implementation against
the new test suite. This is the latest graph,
so you can see that we have been working
a lot on improving the compatibility.
We are not there yet. I will fix one of them
with you later during that presentation,
but there is no silver bullet. For many
of those, you have to spend a few hours
to fix one, and you improve one by one.
Before you ask a question, the skip is
mostly that it is SELinux, so CPMV and
some command or CHCon are using SELinux,
and GitHub action uses Ubuntu, and Ubuntu
doesn't have a default, so it's tricky
to test that stuff into the CI.
If you know how to do it, please reach out to us.
I'd like to fix that stuff.
How do we work? As I said many times,
we want that stuff to be a team replacement.
We wrote a menu wrapper to make it super easy.
That command that I share is going to run
the not owner test for the touch command on GNU,
so it's going to use the GNU test
and run it against our implementation.
It's super easy to test.
We wrote some scripts to make our life easier.
We have a Python script which is going to tell
a series to the list. If you do it,
it's several pages because we still have
a lot of tests to fix.
We wrote also a fancy page.
I can show you what this looks like.
Here it is. We have the list of all the tests
for each command, and of course,
the big one is MISC, where we have the MISC.
Sometimes it's just a one-line change in the code.
Sometimes it's a big refactor.
It really depends. It's part of the fun.
You never know what you are going to get.
Let's use an example for MKGIR.
This is the GNU I would put.
You do dash P. Who knows what is dash P in that one?
Okay, cool. It creates a recursive,
and V is verbose. Everybody knows that.
In the GNU implementations, they decided
to do it directly by directory.
You can argue that maybe it's not a good use.
It's not smart. Maybe it is.
Who cares? It's legacy. We have to deal with legacy.
Our implementation was that one.
You can argue that maybe ours was better or worse.
Who cares? We updated that code,
so we match exactly what GNU is doing.
I will share the slide.
After, you can look at the change.
It's pretty easy to understand.
This one is one of my favorites.
In Debian, when you install LibreOffice,
it is using App Armor, and someone decided
that instead of doing a touch,
you do install devnul, which creates an empty file.
This legacy also.
I want to fix legacy everywhere.
Probably not.
That was one of my favorite bugs,
so I started investigating.
Here is some rest cards which reproduce that issue.
If you do a copy of devnul into a text file,
it is failing with source path.
It's not an existing regular file.
I open a bug upstream.
It's quite interesting.
I think people in the Rust community
are very passionate about that kind of thing.
Too long didn't read. It hasn't been fixed.
Here is a workaround.
It's ugly, but if you know a better way to do it,
besides fixing restc and dealing with the fallout of the fix,
this is the best that we have.
We are looking if the input is devnul.
If it is devnul, we are creating an empty file.
This is what it takes to deal with legacy.
Let's do a demo together.
Please bear with me.
Just switch to alacrity.
I never remember the shortcut to increase the font.
The AS1.
Better? Cool.
This is not the new version that I'm running.
You can see I'm running our implementation.
We are working 30 days.
This is 0.0, 17 weeks ago, something like that,
when we could go, so we are using that implementation of it.
When I took the train to come here,
I looked at the test suite, and I was like,
I will try to find a cool bug for the demo.
I found one, and I want to show you what it is.
I don't always remember the command.
Because I'm a font of a crowd, I don't want to look stupid,
so I did a post-bait within French.
Here is building some stuff.
What I'm testing right now is a sort command.
The sort command has some fancy flag.
This is a command from the GNU project,
so I will show you what the test looks like on the GNU site.
Here is the test.
Of course, we have the TPL suite leader on top,
and then there is a list of file with version name.
On the top, we have the input.
Below, we have the expected one.
The command that they are testing is a stable sort
with a sort by version.
Sort, and same for LS.
You can specify what kind of sort you want.
Of course, doing sort of version is super complex,
and we can basically do the test for hours.
I love it.
Here is what they are testing.
Of course, as you can see, it failed on our side.
Why did it fail?
It seems that it is complaining that 5.4.0 is not sorted
the same way as 5.04.
Super interesting, isn't it?
Basically, it means that we are sorting that version differently.
Of course, it's obvious that it is the same version,
and in theory, it should be equal,
but when you are sorting in those cases,
equal doesn't mean anything, so you need to make a decision.
Of course, we decided to do other arrays
because I think the person who did the implementation
didn't realize that you were doing something different.
Let's try to fix that together.
What I like to do, I don't know how other contributors
to the REST project are doing, is that I like to have test cases.
What I'm doing is I'm creating some basic commands
to be able to reproduce that easily
so that I don't have to run the test.
I spare you the details, so here is the test case.
Let me do that right now.
I've got my test file.
What I'm doing is I'm forcing the full pass
to use a new implementation.
I used the two arguments that we mentioned earlier,
and now I have the input and the output.
If I do a div, it should be empty.
It is.
I love when demo works well.
It's just the beginning, so I will probably affect up
at some point.
Now I want to test the new implementation.
How are implementations of REST 1?
Here it is.
Now I have a simple test case that I can work on.
I don't have to run the test with it.
I don't have to do anything else.
It's one of the things that I love with that project.
That's why I'm not doing REST code at Mediite
because I'm not a very good developer,
and Firefox is super complex.
That stuff is pretty easy to do.
You can do that on the train to come here.
For example, working on it, taking this one,
it's probably going to take 20 minutes to fix.
There is a weird thing at the end,
but I'm not going to produce a surprise yet.
Anyway, this is the code that I have.
Let's dive in now into the actual code.
Let's use GDB.
GDB and REST works very well.
If I do a run, yeah, it works.
If I do a breakpoint on main, yeah, it works.
Next, next, next.
Here it is.
You can see the REST code.
You can evaluate the variables.
It's working super well.
I won't open and look for the function.
I already did that for you.
I already know the function where to put the breakpoint.
It's version underscore CMP.
Our code is pretty well written.
I guess you'll understand what version CMP is doing.
It's comparing version.
Now I continue the execution,
and then I'm in the function doing it.
If I look at A, I see that it is that string.
The first one, if I look at B, here it is.
I have the two string.
I will move in quick mode.
There is execution.
We have the version compare.
Here is a function that I care about.
I will scroll.
You see in that function, it's probably what I care about
because if you don't know about it first,
it is going to trim the zero at the beginning.
Obviously, in that case, it is what I'm looking for,
so I want to remove the zero at first.
Let's fix that code now.
I learned from one of my colleagues at Maggia
that nano is the best text editor, so I'm following the example.
Yeah, exactly. It's the best, right?
Here it is. I removed the trim.
Of course, it's going to break something else after.
I'm confident that it works, so let's rebuild that stuff.
Here it is. It's rebuilding.
The file that I touch is used in a U-call,
so it's one of our basic library to do file management and so on.
It's normal that it is rebuilding the various dependencies.
Yeah, not GDB. I want without GDB.
Please. That one. Did it work?
Yeah, it worked. Cool. I fixed the bug.
I'm very proud of myself.
I love how Geeks love versioning comparison.
We all love that stuff.
Now, the funny story is, of course, because it will be too easy.
Now, I'm not going to run the full test suite
even if it takes less than a minute,
but I'm just going to run that test because I know that that one failed.
LS has the same function, but LS has a different expectation
in terms of version sorting.
Of course, that test is going to fail because LS likes to zero before
instead of the other one. Of course, that test failed.
One of the things that we could do is in the version compare,
we could have, do we want zero to be first,
or do we want zero to be after doing a Boolean?
When I service, because I don't like the version comparison function
is on our tree. I think it's done. Someone else did it.
Of course, there is a crate doing it.
I reached out to the developer saying,
can you add an option to change the sort when it is a zero?
The upstream made fun of me, but they have a PR ready,
so they will probably end it.
We are going to remove 100 of line of code and use that crate
because it is what we want to do.
We don't want to maintain a comparison of version because who cares, right?
Let's come back to the presentation.
So, performances. Benchmarking performances is hard.
I know that in the room we have some media experts in performances,
and they are not going to contact me when I say that benching is hard.
But we are using a perfume.
We can see that, for example, the start is almost five times faster
than the good implementation because some people spend a lot of time
improving it in our code but also in the crate.
So, that one is basically taking all Shakespeare books,
the text file, making it random, and sort it.
So, we are significantly faster than the good implementation.
Similarly, if you do a recursive LS or a recursive CP,
we are 1.5 faster than you do.
Then, new is probably because the code generated by USC
is much better than the one we turned by new for a long time.
But I don't want to pretend that we are always doing better.
For example, with the factor function,
we are significantly slower than the good implementation five times.
I don't know who uses the command factor.
I learned about that command when I started contributing,
but still, we want to be a good tracking replacement,
and that one is very slow.
So, I'm going to do another demo.
I'm going to do some product placement for a project called Simplies.
He also has that project, works at M
He's in the room, so if you need anything, don't blame me, blame him.
And I will do a quick demo about how can you do
a proper benchmarking of performances.
I will try to find how to do the primary per kernel change.
That one. I love the SH.
So, I just did a recursive LS with a command called Simplies.
So, basically, it is going to instrument it,
and it's going to upload into the Firefox profiler
the analysis of that program.
So, I will zoom in a second.
So, here it is.
I think Baudrillard did four presentations of the profiler today,
so if you haven't seen any...
I'm going to do a quick demo.
Anyway, so it is one of the magic things of Rust,
is that we can easily do that stuff you saw, how long it took.
I will show you the command again that I run.
It is that one.
So, simply record the binary and the argument.
So, it's very easy.
If I try to do that, we see another language is going to take forever,
but Rust simply makes that so easy.
So, here I have the flame graph, so I can see that for a recursive LS,
most of the time that we are spending is in display grid.
So, most of the time that LS is going to spend is not reading at the file
or reading the metadata.
It's just doing computation about how do you want to show the result
into the terminal.
And one of the amazing things is that it's going to...
I can look at the source directly and see the counters
and I can easily benchmark that stuff.
So, if you are into performances in Rust,
you can use simply and the Firefox profiler to do it.
And again, not here as Maggia, but it's very valuable for any project.
It's not Maggia related and makes that stuff super easy.
So, we have also some fancy documentation.
Tert in the room did most of the work.
So, one of the things that he did that I love is that one of the things
that I really struggled at first when I became a Unix developer
like 20 years ago is that I never knew how to do an example
and find the example.
So, Tert link to TLDR.sh where it's providing example for every command.
So, for example, here it's base 64.
You have example, but I'm going to use a command that I didn't know about, shred.
You have example for shred, so you don't have to Google and Stack Overflow
or how to do that stuff.
You have that out of the box in our documentation.
So, we have development documentation.
I won't go through it for a matter of time.
But one of the things, we are taking the liberty also to extend the new clarity.
So, we don't want to break compatibility, but we are doing some fancy things
like progress bar because who doesn't love progress bar.
So, for example, of course it is that one.
So, we have a fancy progress bar now.
You don't have that upstream.
So, you can thank the guy.
He's over there.
I haven't done anything.
But before the talk, he came to me and said,
I looked at the implementation, at the patch that wasn't merging new
and that patch was very hard to understand.
If you look at the diff on the right side,
even if you don't know about it first, you will understand it
because we are relying on the crate.
I think the upstream developer of the crate called Indicative,
is that first demo, so thank you for your hard work.
So, here is what kind of stuff we can do.
We can do it for MV.
MV is interesting because if you are moving between one file system to the other,
it's not always super fast.
We are also implementing some tools that Moot doesn't have,
so B3-some, for example, because it's like B2-some,
so it's an actual algorithm.
Ncut-w, someone contributed that patch recently.
It's a function, it's one of the options from BSD that Moot doesn't have.
I'm like, yeah, why not?
So, what is next?
We want to implement the missing option for the various binary.
It's not hard.
It's fun.
We try to be nice.
I'm not always nice, but I try to.
We want to have a full compatibility with Moot.
So, the list that I show you, I'd like that to be fully green at some point.
It's going to take years, but it's fun.
Improve the performances on some key programs, like, for example, for Factor.
I don't know if we want to spend too much time,
but there are other things where we could improve the performances.
And if you're interested, that link is the most interesting one to know where to start.
It's well-documented.
If you are a student, we are probably going to apply for the Google Summer of Code.
And if someone is interested in sponsoring that project,
if your company or your foundation is interesting,
I'd like to buy some credits on GitHub Action to build faster,
because we're running the new street test about, and it takes about an hour.
And I think we are using a lot of resources,
so it would be nice to have a faster CI.
And now I'd like to predict the future.
It's easy, right?
So, the Linux kernel, they landed the first support of Rust inside the tree.
So, if you do some stats on the on Linux Git repo,
you see that they are first, so there is only 37 files upstream.
It's mostly glue, so how do you manage memory and compatibility with the system
and support for the build system?
We hope that they are going to learn something in the main line soon,
a feature that is going to happen this year or not.
We don't know, and some people are still challenging Rust in the Linux kernel.
The main argument that I heard is mainly for legacy system.
But my prediction is that next year, we will start to see more and more
of a distro vendor or cloud company to ship with more and more Rust code.
Probably, I'm pretty sure that some Linux distro are going to ship in the cloud
our implementation in the next few years.
So, thanks for your time.
I'd like to remind that it is not a muchier project,
so please don't say muchier works on that.
It will make my life easier, and I think we have a few minutes for questions.
Thank you.
I think you need in the badge.
Oh, it's recorded.
I'll say it.
It's an issue for every Rust project currently.
The fact that cargo is amazing at updating dependency is many of the Rust project
are subject to supply chain attack legacy, and we are no exception.
So, I can do product placement.
If you have a tool called cargo vet, which mitigates that stuff,
but it's too complex to deploy for a hobby like this one.
So, yeah, you can do supply chain attack in our project,
but we don't merge the dependable pull requests immediately.
So, we are trying to mitigate that by taking our time.
Any other questions?
Yeah, over there.
Yeah, please.
The cut size compared to busy box, I don't know.
With GNU, it's similar.
So, you have different way to compile the project.
So, the trick that I'm using in Debian for the package is that I'm building
a single binary and I'm doing sim link.
So, if you do a sim link from Cori Tilt to CP or to NS,
the binary is going to understand that you are calling CP.
So, the size is comparable to the GNU implementation in that case.
But because of the nature of first,
the binaries are bigger than the rest.
Another question?
Yeah, it's a question that comes back often.
Do you compute the code coverage only on the passing tests or all of them?
We run code coverage on everything, including the GNU test suite.
So, it takes a lot of time.
So, the tests that are failing?
Yeah, we test everything.
Did you find any bugs in the original GNU implementation
when doing the re-implementation?
Yeah, we have a contributor who found two or three bugs
in the upstream implementation and they have been fixed up here.
We bought it and fixed up soon.
Have you had any need to use unsafe?
And if yes, can you give a few examples in which kind of areas?
We have some unsafe when we are calling the libc,
some function of the libc, we are calling it directly,
so we have some unsafe.
Do you agree?
Yeah.
Basically, your name is false and no one is equal.
Dert, I'm going to repeat what he said.
He said that it's for the libc.
It's mostly, yeah, native code.
Have you looked at code complexity metrics like
cyclomatic complexity?
Because I guess with the error handling,
the memory management and clean-up in C is often really messy
and that could be a huge boon in maintainability.
Yeah, we have some codes that clearly need refactoring.
So, for example, in LS, we have to work around the limitation of CLAP
and the code complexity here is getting more and more complex.
Yeah.
That project needs some policies of our implementation
and refactoring to decrease it.
But the code is usually pretty easy to understand.
Thanks.
I think we're out of time.
Yeah.
Thank you all.
Don't hesitate to contribute.
I can find my email easily.