So welcome to my talk, clear skies, no clouds inside, running a business on free and open
source software.
A little bit about myself.
My name is Hein-Peter van Brin, but if you talk to me, please call me HP.
My mom does, and it feels much more at home.
I'm a co-founder of two Godot related companies, Prehensile Tales, BV, which is a Godot consultant.
Recently, Ramitaking corporate, which is a company that plans to improve the Godot mobile
experience.
Always be selling, I just heard.
I'm also treasurer of the Godot Foundation, a gigantic nerd.
I started a free and open source hosting site called notabuck.org around the time when,
what was that?
A gatorious shutdown, I think, and my personal blog is at blog.tm.cx.
So what is this presentation about?
First of all, can you run a business entirely on free and open source software?
Should you run a business entirely on a free and open source software?
Are you mad?
And by that I mean me.
Maybe some of you too.
I don't know.
What does it mean to do this and how can you actually do this?
What this presentation isn't about.
It isn't a total lesson on managing a large fleet of servers.
There's other talks about that.
There's other people specializing in running data centers with thousands of servers.
This is not this.
This is for a reasonable amount of people and a reasonable amount of servers.
It's also not a lesson in starting a flame war about configuration management systems.
So please don't at me if I say something you don't like.
I am going to say some things you don't like if you are a sysadmin for a much larger organization.
So first of all, can you do this?
Well, I've polled all the speakers on this stage and 100% of them say yes.
So that's a good start, I think.
So why would you do this?
That's I think a question that a lot of people might ask themselves.
I mean, we're all here at FOSDEM.
We're here so I don't have to talk to you about the benefits of open source software,
why you should use free software, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
That's not what I'm here for.
So first of all, while you can use free tier of cloud services for almost everything, you
can get most of the features.
Once you start to get to a certain size, even if you're only as a small company, you end
up with five, six, seven accounts for individual users.
And it is very difficult for people to figure out what password to use.
So you either end up with people using very insecure passwords, so you end up having to
force a password policy on them, and then they're just going to write it down or whatever.
And someone still has to fix these issues if they happen in your company.
Now you are a certain suddenly help desk for people forgetting their passwords.
At least that's been my experience.
So access control is actually the real big one.
Once you start to mix a bunch of different cloud services on basic tiers or free tiers,
figuring out who has access to what, if everyone has the access that they need, and most importantly,
new people have more access than they need.
It is very difficult to keep track of which document was shared with whom, why was it
shared with that person.
Is it an individual that shared it with another individual?
Is it someone that maybe left the company now but they shared it with their public or
private Google accounts, et cetera.
It's very difficult to keep track of these things.
This could be a problem if you sign non-disclosure agreements with customers, other people that
you work with.
And depending on the business that you actually run, it could be a compliance issue, particularly
now with GDPR, et cetera.
There's a lot of things you have to keep track of.
Of course, I see some of you think, but you can already do this.
In fact, my company already does this.
Yes, it is certainly possible.
But usually, if you want these level of features and these level of integrations, you end up
having to pay actually quite a bit of money for individuals and only to get this fairly
basic level of control over your data.
It also does work if you say, okay, I'm going to pick one SaaS provider.
If you say, okay, I'm going to use only Google products, I'm not going to use anything outside
of Google products.
If Google doesn't have it, I'm not going to use it.
That of course also works.
So is this all about money?
But not really.
I will get to that in a minute.
But the first thing I usually hear from anyone who talks about doing something like this
is either a knee-jerk reaction, as in, but it's actually more expensive to do it yourself.
I don't think that is true.
At least it's not true for me.
So at least it means it's not a truthism that definitely applies to all cases.
Or of course, the other one, it's only free if your time is free.
That is also fair.
But having tried this in a different way, supporting individual people in a bunch of
different time zones in the case of my companies with, oh, I don't have access to this document.
Can you send it to me?
Or I have people working in North America who share a document or fail to do it correctly,
and a person working in Poland needs it the next day.
Due to the time zone difference, they won't get that document until 5 p.m. because nobody
but the person who created it had access to it.
This is also a time sink.
And of course, if the worst came to worst, failing in a compliance case is probably not
going to be free either.
So what is this about, then, if it's not just about money?
First of all, I just like being in control of my data.
I like to know where my data is.
I like to know where it's backed up.
And I like to know that if I need to, I can just stick it on an external USB drive and
take it with me somewhere.
And you just want to hack your data.
I like having unsurprising costs.
I know exactly how much my infrastructure is going to cost this month.
I know how much it's going to cost next month.
If I need to, for a new project, whatever, add five external people to give access to
some shared resources, I know I'm not going to end up paying 150, 200 euros more next
month.
And I do forget to not cancel again because I end up keeping paying it.
It gives me a big peace of mind when it comes to access control, what I just talked about.
I know exactly which one of my users have access to what data.
I know why they have access to it because it's based on group memberships.
And I know, luckily, this has not happened, but I also know if something were to go really
wrong, I can, in fact, make sure that people stop having access to the data that I don't
want them to have access to anymore.
By giving people access to just one user ID and one password and one way of logging in,
I feel like I'm making their day just a little bit better.
And that makes me happy.
Just using free and open source software is nice.
I mean, most of the people here are here for a reason as well, so I'm assuming that most
of you agree with that.
If I run a laptop with just free software because it's important to me, why would I
run my business on anything else?
And it feels very good to be part of a community rather than just a customer.
I do pay for certain software.
Let's get into that later, sorry.
But even there, you end up not really being treated so much as a small customer.
You tend to be treated more like a community member to a certain extent.
Also they appreciate good bucket reports more, which is always nice.
But isn't this like super duper hard?
I don't think so.
It is true that you need some things, need to know some things that you might not need
to know otherwise, particularly not if, say, you go in all in on Google Workspace or you
go in all in on Office 365.
You don't need to know a whole lot about infrastructure at all.
For this you do.
I'm not going to lie about that.
The most important thing is actually DNS, tying all of that together, making sure that
your emails don't end up in people's spam folders, et cetera.
Most of this actually boils down to a basic knowledge of DNS.
You're going to need to know a little bit about how to run a web server, how to administer
a web server and what web servers do, but not as much as you might think.
And of course a basic understanding of the Linux CLI.
Or I guess the FreeBSD CLI, if that's what you decide to do.
But it's a similar thing.
So most people when I talk about this have a perception that building something like
this ends up with a cognitive overhead that looks something like this.
It's an extremely complicated set of tools where every individual thing that fails could
break everything.
But in reality it's really not that bad.
You end up with a bunch of containers running on one or more hosts with a simple set of
configuration files that you stuff into Git and that's basically it.
You don't manage 15 things, you manage six things or seven things.
All right.
So how do you do this kind of thing?
Well, the most important thing really is to keep things simple.
As soon as you start looking online about managing Linux servers, et cetera, you end
up finding a whole pile of wonderful tools.
I'm not trying to tell you that you should not use these tools, by the way.
I'm just telling you that in this case if you're just managing two or three servers,
some of these tools might not be what you need.
And trust upstream.
When you use a cloud provider you're just trusting that your cloud provider does the
right thing at any given time.
If you use a piece of open source software, if you use an open source operating system,
if you use an open source NGINX or other web server, trust that upstream tests the stuff
they do.
You don't need a five street test environment just to install a security update on your
operating system.
So how do you keep things simple?
As I said, there's a lot of really great tools like puppet chef, and probably a bunch that
I forgot.
I think there might even be some in this floor that I forgot to include in this.
My apologies if that's one of your projects.
These tools truly are great.
I have been a sysadmin at a large company and without tools like this I would have absolutely
lost my mind.
However, setting up services using these tools is a lot of translating between documentation
you read about the tool into a configuration file format that isn't the one that is documented
on the side of the thing you're trying to configure.
And there's a lot of testing involved, which is great if you need to repeat this on 100
servers, but if it's one box you need to do and that you maybe need to redo in a year,
it's a lot of cognitive overhead.
And if your business grows to the point where this becomes necessary, then probably the
overhead of converting what you did now into a puppet manifest, Ansible or whatever, is
probably not the thing that's going to prevent you from growing.
In that same vein, as soon as you start to look at how do I run containers, how do I
do that myself?
Again, lots of great resources, lots of super great projects.
But if you search on Google, how do I run a server with containers, one of the first
links you're going to find is you're going to get to set up a Kubernetes, you're going
to create an under cloud and an over cloud and you're going to set up redundant, I don't
know, load balancers.
That was the word I was looking for.
And you're going to set all of this great stuff up and at some point when you have a
thousand servers it's just going to be just as easy as if you had a hundred.
Yeah, and I can understand why if you start reading that you get incredibly overwhelmed
immediately because that is a lot of stuff to learn.
And again, you're not going to need it for what we're talking about here.
Again, I think all of these projects are great.
I have used many of them.
This is just not about that.
Please don't add me.
So what does it mean to use simple software?
So in this case, use what is supplied by the OS that you use.
Every piece of software you install that is not in the repositories of the operating system
you use, that is something that you might regret later because that is something that
is not tested by your upstream.
This is again where we come to the trusting upstream part of things.
So in this case, we're going to get there.
I'm using Fedora for most of this stuff.
Use Potman or Docker, use systemd, not whatever else might, a nice thing you might come up
with.
And in this case, you are not going to need to do anything too creative.
Use Git for your configuration management.
This is probably the most controversial point of this presentation.
Use a recent OS.
You do not need CentOS.
You do not need Alma Linux.
You do not need Red Hat Enterprise Linux.
You need something where if you read a documentation that it is the last thing that people actually
touched.
People are not writing documentation, generally speaking, on how to set up a modern thing
on an ancient enterprise distribution.
Again, these things have their places.
I'm not telling anyone.
I'm not trying to tell anyone that these things are bad.
Again, this is about you managing your time and making sure you don't spend a lot of time
doing this.
And upgrading your server every 12 to 18 months really isn't a big deal.
Again, trust upstream.
The enough system upgrade released for the next one 20 minutes later, you have your operating
system upgraded.
It's not a big deal.
Another thing, use preexisting containers wherever possible.
You can, of course, write your own.
Sometimes you will have to for the demo I'm about to give.
I did have to write one.
And don't forget that upstream tends to prefer using their containers over a different way
of deploying their software.
So generally speaking, if you have an issue and you say, okay, I'm running your latest
container version, you're actually more likely to get help than if you installed in any other
way.
Of course, what do we do about backup and disaster recovery?
Well, if you follow the recipe that I'm going to talk about, then basically you have two
directories to backup on each server.
And if something goes wrong, you have two directories to replace back on the server.
And basically your stuff is back.
I will hear the people managing infrastructures for a large corporation saying, but this will
take hours.
Yes.
It also almost never happens.
And this way you can be sure that your data is not gone if something goes wrong without
breaking the bank.
Basically speaking, I've been doing this for quite a while now.
And I've had one server fail due to a hard disk failure.
Of course, the server was just using a rate one mirror.
So I just called the people who run the data center.
They replaced the disk.
And there was actually not really a problem there.
I would like to now introduce megacorp.icu.
This is a very big company that has graciously let me demo their environment.
Completely non-evil.
They let me show you their environment because prehencetiles, my own company, the CEO, thought
it was irresponsible to have the internal systems recorded on iFree and open source.
And a developers European meeting thing.
I don't know what they're thinking.
Because nine totally real employees that were absolutely not AI generated.
The thing I'm about to show you is a setup that is roughly looks like this.
There are three hosts running on this laptop, hopefully.
Configured as such.
So we have three hosts with an overlay network on WireGuard to make sure that these hosts
can talk to each other over local IP addresses.
Even for that being, when you do something like this, you're probably not going to be
able to afford or want to pay for dedicated workspace where your server is nicely lined
up above each other, connected to each other over local connections.
So you need some way for the servers to feel like a LAN.
By doing a simple WireGuard mesh, any one server can go down and the other two can still
talk to each other, which is a nice feature to have.
So and now a hopefully non colossal mistake.
I'm going to try to actually show you what this looks like by using a system like this.
So first of all, this is the basic basically admin interface you might see if you're using
something like this.
So we have our nine users here in LDAP.
And we have a couple of groups here that you can manage.
So I've made a human resources team for which Chatwick and Maxwell are our members.
I made some shared mailboxes that human resources team can also look at.
And so what this looks like here is for instance, let's see, I have a new container tab.
This one I think.
So to show for a little explanation, I'm using a feature of Firefox here called container
tabs.
Basically in the top right here you will see the name of one of the fake users.
I mean totally real users.
And basically Firefox will keep all the cookies, et cetera, separated so I can show you what
it means to log in from multiple systems.
Just a private tab would only give me two Firefox tab containers because it basically
gives you an unlimited number of private tabs essentially.
So that's what we're doing here.
So the first thing we can do is this is the wrong one.
This is the real one of my real company.
Didn't I?
I thought so.
I was smart enough to actually make bookmarks and then I didn't use them.
So the user name of this person is CadenceR.
So first of all, this is basically the login screen that every user will see.
Hopefully only once a day.
The way this works is you log into the system, there is a cookie that gets set for key cloak
in this case and key cloak then does all the authentication with further back ends.
So generally speaking, if everything works properly, your users will only have to log
in once a day, also meaning that your password policies and things like that can be a little
bit stricter because they really only have to remember one and they really only have
to type it in once a day.
So oh yes, this user actually doesn't have access to this.
That was part of the demo, but I forgot that in this case.
We will get there.
Let me show you something that the user does have access to, their email box.
So you see that I just switched from the next cloud to the email server and you also noticed
hopefully that there was not another login prompt.
That is again because these single sign on systems, if you deploy them properly, are
in fact single sign on.
You sign on once and then it should just keep working.
So this is the email box for our user Cadence.
We can see we have an address book with all of the people, all of her colleagues in it.
And here is Chatwick Parsons.
These names are also all AI generated by the way.
So what we can do is we can send an email to Chatwick here.
Let's see, am I doing the right thing?
I can send a little email to Chatwick here.
And now hopefully when we switch to the Chatwick, there we go, Chatwick there, sure it's now
have received an email.
And you see also that the things like small little things like the fact that all of the
users have their own little profile pictures, et cetera.
And these are all consistent across all the applications as well.
So if you look at the Chatwicks, Chatwicks does have access to the next cloud.
There we go.
And you see that this actually shows the same.
You click the same button twice, the same thing happens.
This is very surprising.
All right.
And you see here that the user has this, oh, sorry.
You see here that the user actually has the same profile picture as well.
These profile pictures all came from Active Directory, thank God not.
And from OpenLDAP as well.
So what can you actually do with this?
What is the big thing that I kept talking about?
For instance, here we have a human resources folder that Chatwick has access to because
Chatwick is part of the human resources department.
And so is the guy.
Maxwell is also an HR person.
So Maxwell and Chatwick.
So far everything is still working.
Very good.
You see that Maxwell here has access to the same document.
And there's not been any like sharing here.
It is just a matter of being part of the correct group.
I will show that in a second.
But if you look at the access that this is Alba Kelly.
Thank you for getting this nice handy dandy.
It's not exactly single sign on if you're doing a demo with five different users.
It is only once per user, not once per demo.
I'm afraid.
You see here that the user Alba here does not have access to the shared directory and
cannot see it.
And trying to just send a link to this other person will also not work.
As you see, you just get a found not found error.
Now, what if Alba does become part of the human resources team?
Well, at this point, it's just a matter of adding the member here.
And then in a couple of minutes, hopefully, maybe immediately.
No.
We'll get back to that.
All right.
What's the next thing on my list of things to show?
I also created this user, Mary J. So what you've seen so far is basically what it looks
like for people who have been working for a while who already know the system.
So what does this look like for a completely new user?
Because that's kind of like another problem, right?
Being people signed up onboard in your organization.
I keep forgetting I made these.
So let's say you tell your new user, okay, the first thing you need to do is just go
to the chat system to say hello.
So we have given the user their initial temporary password.
I sign in and you see that you get just this one little prompt for people to change the
password.
And after that, they're just signed up like everything else.
So this is basically the only real onboarding that your users have to do.
So they don't have to create accounts for multiple things.
You don't have to create accounts for multiple things.
They don't end up having to tie their personal Gmail accounts to some kind of Google Drive,
nothing like that.
And there we are.
The same thing goes for things like the access to, for instance, channels on your instant
messaging server.
You see here that Chatwick being part of the human resources group has access to this channel
HR that is not visible to this user, Maria Johnson.
So Maria Johnson is not part of HR, does not see the group.
This is not something that you have to manage yourself either.
We also see here that since Elba was recently promoted to be part of the HR group, she now
has access to the HR channel as well.
Again, this speaks to this access control that I was talking about previously.
You don't have to think about, okay, what things does an HR person have access to?
Did I give them access to the right folders?
Did I give them access to the right shared email address, et cetera?
It's all just taking care.
You only take care of this one time when you set this up, basically.
So there's a couple of other things that people like to use, like editing documents together.
We can do that if I probably should have kept more tabs open.
It turns out navigating a computer is much easier when you're writing a talk and sitting
down instead of facing a room of 700 people.
Not 700 if you're here.
So we have two people logged in here.
And you'll be able to edit things collaboratively much like Google Docs, et cetera, as well.
So you don't really need to lose any features over any of this either.
Let's see.
This is all done.
We have the chance.
Yes.
So these are the services that I added to the demo for this demo.
If anyone has any questions about what other things you could easily do, we have a question
section in a minute.
All right, it lets me go back here.
So I'm assuming that it went super well when I wrote this.
I'm going to give myself three and a half out of five stars on that one.
So can you do this?
I think this little demo shows that for most purposes what people are used to on a daily
basis using their systems, collaborating with each other, et cetera, it is in fact possible
to do it.
I think the user interface is far more consistent than if you compare this to a hot patch of
different cloud services with different login systems.
Different access control systems.
Again, predictable and controllable cost.
You know how much it's going to cost when you start the month compared to how much it's
going to cost at the end.
I think you end up spending less time managing access control.
You just have this one list of groups and members.
You look at who is a member of that group and you know what access they have and you
also know that if you take them out of the group, they will cease having that access.
And that way you also lose less time on people not being able to access things that they
need for their jobs.
So as part of writing this talk, I was setting up the mega corp.icu, various containers, et
cetera, and taking some of the containers that I was running in production and filing
off the serial numbers of the specific things that I used them for.
And I realized that maybe these could be useful for other people as well.
So I created a GitHub project called mega corp.icu that has the containers that were
used in this talk in it as well as some of the tools that I use to manage this.
Perhaps if other people are interested in running their own infrastructures in at least
somewhat the same way that I'm proposing, perhaps we can do some kind of collaboration
with each other and do a sort of CS admin support group.
I don't know.
So questions?
I think I'm a little ahead of where I'm supposed to be, but maybe there will be a lot of questions.
A little plug, as I was just told, that you should always be selling.
My company, Romatuck, is actively hiring people.
So if any of this sounds like it could be you, please contact me.
Okay.
So we've got one roving microphone for questions, but we're going to go online first because
there's some online questions.
Yeah.
The chat's blowing up with this question right here.
What do you think about so-called totally automatic solutions like Unohost or Sandstorm?
Would they also be sufficient for a small business?
So I actually started off using Sandstorm, but found that the access control that Sandstorm
offers is actually not quite...
So with Sandstorm, what usually ends up happening is that you deploy different instances of
the same application that different people will have access to.
What I found is that moving people between groups didn't work properly for that, specifically
if somebody gets kicked out of a container, sharing things between things tended to get
a little weird.
I would say that if it works for you, use it, it didn't work for me personally.
So I have another story.
I started with a small startup.
I was the assistant administrator.
I set up...
Can I ask you the question, please?
So I started to install all the FOSS infrastructure.
It was beautiful.
Next cloud.
I had the audio and many other things.
And then the company got bigger.
And then the president of the company said, I don't like how next cloud link calendars
to email.
And so the next month we switched to Google Doc completely entirely, and the throwaway
all my work of two years and I cried.
So how do you do with the users?
You are the boss that would love to have you as my boss.
But how do you convince users actually to comply?
Well, again, do you need me to repeat the question?
So in my case, indeed, none of that really applies because I am the boss of these companies
and the CEO of both.
So to a certain extent, if you don't like it.
But in practice, people tend to do like it.
Of course, if you have someone that says, okay, I only know how to use this one thing
and I refuse to use anything else, if that person is the CEO of the company, that is
a problem.
I don't really have a good answer for you other than try to convince them that there
are some benefits to this.
In the end, it's their money, right?
So if they are willing to pay, I don't know, $30, $40 a month per user because they don't
like how these things are linked, there is only so much you can do at some point.
Okay, we are going to take an online question and then I am going to go over there for the
next question.
Keep your hands up if you want to ask a question.
I have got a chance of keeping an eye on you.
Okay, so what do you think of Cloudron?
So can you repeat the question, please?
What do you think of Cloudron?
I am not familiar with that.
Have you heard of Cloudron?
Are you aware of Co-op Cloud?
That's another question on the...
I am not, no.
All right, some good ideas here from the people.
What do you use for documentation?
Can you repeat the question, please?
What do you recommend for documentation, like an alternative for conference or notion?
So it's the question, what do you use for video conference?
No, no, no, for documentation, internal documentation for the company.
Oh, what do you use for internal documentation for the company?
Yes.
So in the case of prehensile tales, I use XWiki, which also integrates beautifully with
this whole thing.
People get access to sub pages based on group memberships, etc.
Or user documentation that's not intended to be changed.
So I wrote a little manual on how to do certain simple things on the mail server.
Those are just files that are in a shared folder on the next cloud that everyone has
access to.
Thanks for the talk.
Very interesting.
One question, I guess all your services are publicly available.
So does Keyclog support something like a two-factor authentication?
Yes.
Keyclog does support two-factor authentication.
You can simply add, actually let's not do a demo for something I haven't looked at.
I will not make that mistake.
But yeah, you can add an authenticator app to your account on Keyclog.
And I do that for myself because my account tends to have admin privileges, etc. on a
lot of stuff.
It is possible to also tell configure Keyclog such to make it mandatory for every user that
logs in to set up a two-factor, with an authenticator app.
One thing to keep track of though, because this is something that can in fact take you,
lose you a lot of time.
If you do set it up, make sure you have an MTP client running on all your servers, because
that's going to take you a while to figure out.
Yes.
I have a question.
How do you deal with security since you're running Nextcloud and Keyclog on premise?
You said in some slides before that you update your systems like between 12 and 18 months.
That is not a problem.
But then again, security issues like rapidly rise up, and especially if you're on the public
internet or facing the public internet, you run into, well, huge risks when you are not
on the problem at hand.
I mean, huge risks, sure, in the sense that if a worm were to be developed that goes through
Keyclog directly and it doesn't get patched until it is all wired over the internet, then
that might be a problem.
But in the actual so far security updates for things like Keyclog, Nextcloud, et cetera,
you just become at a cadence of once every month, month and a half, you basically just
tell your Potman container stack to pull the new images and you restart them.
It's two, three minutes of work usually.
So again, it is a concern, but it's not something that's going to be your job to deal with this.
It's two minutes, three minutes to install more security updates most of the time.
Okay, so the question is how do you know that you need to update something?
I just run these pools and updates like every two, three weeks, because like you pointed
out, I don't want it to be my job to figure out all the security updates that are available
for everything, so I just install everything every couple of weeks.
Next question is can you use Purelyfoss for the non-engineering aspects of the company?
For example, accounting software that is compliant with state requirements for regular digital
submission?
So the question is can you use it for things like administrative software and stuff?
I frankly don't know, because I cheat in that regard is that I have an accountant and every
month I send them an email with a pile of PDFs in it and then I get a PDF pack that
says how much taxes they have to pay or return.
I don't know.
I don't have the answer to that question.
But hiring an accountant is a good idea.
If you're ever at the size of one or two people, just get an accountant.
Thanks for the cool presentation.
Since the key word here is to keep things simple, I believe in Key Clock you can have
all the users created locally and have them in Key Clock.
What's the benefit of having LDAP behind that to keep track of the users and having...
So the question is why, if you want to keep things simple, why not just create local users?
Because then you end up with the same problem that you started with with different cloud
tools.
Now you have to manage individual access to different tools yourself again.
The fact that there is a group, human resources, that easily works across all the systems means
that the mail server knows who's a member of human resources, next cloud knows who's
a member of human resources, and rocket chat knows who's a member of human resources.
So it just lowers the burden to take that one little bit of extra complexity.
In return you get back this one single thing you have to administer instead of figuring
out how to do that across multiple things.
Also from a purely practical point of view, most programs will support LDAP.
Fewer and fewer programs now support things like PAM or anything like that.
LDAP kind of is what PAM used to be in that respect, for good or bad.
You've been talking about using this in small or small-age companies.
Do you foresee at which point this would not work anymore, like in terms of size of the
company?
So I think there's going to be an inflection point specifically when vertical scaling stops
to work, basically.
So if I need more than one piece of hardware to run all of the chat users on, I think at
that point it's going to be a problem.
If I get so many files that I cannot reasonably store them any longer on a server that you
can reasonably rent, right now you can get a rate one NVMe server with two times four
terabytes of disk space for like $100 a month.
Once things like that stop scaling, I think that is when you might start to have a problem.
The way I think about that, though, is by the time I have that problem, I will also
probably have enough people to get a sysadmin to figure that stuff out for me.
How often have you had to report or fix bugs in the stack that you're using?
How often do you have to fix and report bugs?
So that is exactly how often I don't know.
I'm not going to lie, that happens with some regularity.
I currently have a bug open with Nextcloud, for instance, that sometimes the avatar icons
disappear.
That is annoying.
Things like that are annoying.
But then again, I also have had bugs open for pieces of software I've paid for that
are never fixed.
It's not a panacea, I believe is the word you, is how you pronounce that.
But it's not something, it's not like the things are constantly breaking and I'm constantly
fixing things.
Absolutely not.
A minute ago there was a question up here.
Has it gone away?
Just in this front block here.
No, right, okay, we'll go over here.
Keeps me fit.
Somebody's getting some steps.
Hi, thanks.
That was a really good talk.
I think the question is, is there anyone in the room who does know how to do open source
accounting?
Is it certainly not me?
That has a second vote from me as well.
Anyone?
Hold up, put your hand up.
VRP Next, you say?
PRP?
I'm sorry.
No, that's not.
No.
Every regulation is in it.
You have to build it yourself.
But ERP Next is an open source solution to manage your accounting stuff.
Cool.
Thank you.
Did we have more questions?
I have a question here.
How much time is needed in on average per month to set up the infrastructure and maintain
it?
up the infrastructure, well, I felt like it wasn't too much work to set up an entirely
new infrastructure just for this talk.
So I mean, it should give you some indication that it's not like a weeks-long process.
As in how much time does it take me per month to run this?
It is a little bit variable.
So just installing security updates and just keeping those things running maybe...
So it's never consecutive, right?
I think it's fair to say that I spent about an hour a month maintaining the infrastructure.
I don't think I spent a whole lot more than that.
Of course this number can ramp up rather dramatically if you get a hardware failure, like a broken
hard drive in a server can now mean that you have to spend two or three hours talking with
your data center people planning to get a disk replaced, waiting for the disk to be
replaced, putting it back in your rates at et cetera.
So at that point you might lose a couple more hours.
But yeah, it's in the order of hours per month, not days.
Hi.
Have you tried to do it in high availability?
So do you have any problems with like a next layer of the complication?
If you have one key clock in machine A, then second key clock on machine B or data center
B, what's your idea here?
Because if you use, I don't know, Google, it's just one Gmail comment.
Yeah, you are fine.
Yeah, so the question is what do you do about redundancy?
So there's actually one of those things where it's very easy to fall into a trap and which
is kind of what this talk was hoped to be about.
It's that you don't really need that most of the time.
Make sure that your data is safe.
But if you have a company of 10, 15, 20 people, if people can't log in in the middle of the
night, it means that you are also sleeping and all your employees are also sleeping.
So this is not something that worries me at all.
It's not to say that, again, not to say that you should never worry about it, not saying
that anyone who does worry about it is wrong.
But just in the type of deployment that I'm talking about, a couple of hours downtime
is not the end of the world.
And we've seen it's not the end of the world because Azure just went down for like seven
hours and we're all still here.
Okay.
Thank you all very much.
Thank you, HP, for your talk.
That's great.
So a question.
Thank you for coming.