So, hello. I'm Edward, and I'm going to be talking about some tools that I've been building
for adding links between OpenStreetMap and Wikidata. I've been working on these for a
few years. This is all a hobbyist project. I'm not being paid to work on this, but I
thought I'd come here and share with you some of the work that I've been doing. So, I'm
going to use as an example to talk about the software that I'm building, this building
which is in Brussels, the Royal Palace of Brussels. It's in the city centre. So, you
can see here, this is it in two different systems. You've got OpenStreetMap and you've
got Wikidata, both showing the same building. So, I'll describe OpenStreetMap just for anyone
who's not familiar with it. It's a collaborative map. I've been going since 2004. It covers
the whole world and anyone can come in and edit the map. It's got revision history. It
works a lot like Wikipedia, but for maps. So, within OpenStreetMap, you've got three
types of objects, nodes, ways and relations, increasing complexity. Each of those objects
can have tags. Tags are pairs of keys and values. I've got some examples here for my
example in Brussels. And the tags are not controlled by the software. You can put anything
you want in, but it won't get rendered on the map unless it's one of the standard tags
that gets used on OpenStreetMap. So, there's a community process for discussing, you know,
how things should be tagged in OpenStreetMap and then it gets documented on the OpenStreetMap
wiki. So, everything in OpenStreetMap can be uniquely
identified by the type and the ID. Like, the ID on its own isn't enough. There's nodes
and ways that have got the same ID. You have to have the type as well. So, in this example
of the Royal Palace, you can see it's a relation. It's a complex polygon. You can see there's
holes in the middle of the building, so you can't represent it as a way. And you can see
there, it's got an ID as well. So, what about the other system I'm talking about?
Wikidata. So, Wikidata is part of the Wikimedia Foundation, like the same people that run
Wikipedia. And it's a wiki for structured data. It's newer than OpenStreetMap, 2012
it launched. And it's big. Like, it's got 102 million items now. And for comparison,
English Wikipedia has 6.6 million articles. Like, English Wikipedia is the biggest Wikipedia.
And most of those articles have a Wikidata item as well. But then there's a lot more
data, a lot more items in Wikidata than there are articles in English Wikipedia.
So, if I take my example of the Royal Palace of Brussels, and you look it up on English
Wikipedia, you can see there's a link in the sidebar that will take you to the Wikidata
item. And you click that link, and you end up on the, this is the Wikidata item for the
Royal Palace. I'll talk you through some of the pieces on this page. So, you've got,
on the side, the site links. These are links to Wikipedia articles in different languages.
Like part of the reason for the existence of Wikidata is to store these, they call them
inter-language links. They used to be stored in Wikipedia and had to be maintained across
all the different languages. So, if there was a new article written in a new language,
every existing article in one of the existing languages had to be updated with these links.
So, much better to centralize them and store them in Wikidata instead. All the bits and
pieces you get on this page, you get a label, a description, and aliases. So, by default,
when I look at Wikidata, I just see them in English, because that's the language I speak.
But I can click the, a link to show me in more languages, and you can see that there's
names of the thing available in lots of languages and descriptions and so on. The other main
part of this page you see is the list of statements. So, statements are a bit like tags in OpenStreetMap,
but they're more controlled by the software. You can't just make up a property. You have
to use ones that are already in the system. And again, there's a community process in
Wikidata for determining new properties. And the other big difference is that there's different
data types, like in OpenStreetMap, everything is a string, but Wikidata has different data
types of values. Here you can see there's an image, and there's also a link to another
item used as values in the statements. So, the interesting, in terms of maps, is Wikidata
has got coordinate locations. There's almost ten million items with coordinates. So, those
are the kinds of things that we're interested in, and we'll probably be on OpenStreetMap
as well. And there is a property for storing geo shapes in Wikidata, but it's quite new,
and it's not used so much. There's only 29,000-odd items with a geo shape. So, you know, it's
mostly about the coordinates. So, the thing that I'm interested in is adding links between
the systems. So, if we have another look at OpenStreetMap, I've got highlighted here one
of the tags for the palace, and it's the Wikidata tag, and it's got a Wikidata QID. This is
the unique identifier for the Wikidata item. So, now, the two systems are linked. Like,
if you visit this object on OpenStreetMap, then the user interface has a hyperlink that
will take you to the same thing on Wikidata. So, why do I want to add links between Wikidata
and OpenStreetMap? Well, it makes the data in OpenStreetMap a lot more useful. Like,
Wikidata tends to have labels in more languages. Like, if you want the name of a thing in a
different language, you can get it from Wikidata. You can link to the Wikipedia articles. It
gets images from Commons and identifiers from other catalogues, data catalogues. So, there's
Wikimedia Commons is the Wikimedia location for storing photos of things. So, we get loads
of photos of our building, and we also get lots of identifiers in Wikidata. So, you can
think of Wikidata as a bit like the Rosetta Stone of linking different data catalogues.
It makes sense to store all this information in one place, and so, why not use Wikidata
as that place for storing this kind of info? So, this is a good thing. We want to add links.
The other thing you get is Wikidata gets access to the shapes of things, the polygon outline
of the building, which otherwise it wouldn't have without a link. So, adding these links
by hand is kind of laborious and time-consuming, so better to write some software to do it
instead. So, the software I've written, I'm calling it AWL or OWL Places, and the web address
is osm.wikidata.link. So, this is what the software looks like when you visit it. It
asks you for a place name where you want to search for some matches, so you can put in
the name of your town, somewhere you're familiar with, and can check that the matches are valid.
So, I've done a search, and I've found the place where the Royal Palace is located, and
this is the page you see. You've got a map with some blue pins, and these blue pins represent
Wikidata items, but the software has found something that matches OpenStreetMap. So,
if I scroll down this page, you can see some example matches. So, I show you various bits
of data that come from Wikidata and Wikipedia to help you try and identify if these matches
are valid. Like, sometimes the software doesn't get it right and will give you an invalid
match, so it's important to look through this list and check that all the matches are correct.
And to help you with that, I show you the first paragraph from the Wikipedia article,
and I show you any images that come from Wikidata. You've got the Wikidata description there.
The paragraphs I show you, I'll talk later about how it decides which languages to use
for showing those, but it supports various languages, and then it shows you some of the
details from OpenStreetMap, just so you can compare and make sure that they match. So,
if I click on one of those, then it will zoom in on the map, and it shows you the polygon
outline of the thing. You can see the red pin there is the selected thing. So, that
looks like a pretty good match. It's probably the same thing, so we can go ahead and save
that. So, we're interested in saving these matches to OpenStreetMap. So, then the software
has a button that lets us log in via OpenStreetMap by auth, just put in a username and password
and log in, and then you come back to the confirmation page, where you just see the
same list again, but kind of abbreviated. These are things that I've checked, and I've
said, yes, these are valid matches, and I want to save them. You can put a change comment.
So, everything gets saved together as one change set, like it goes in as a single edit,
and the change comment on the change set is generated automatically based on the location,
but you can change it if you want to. So, I'll carry on with describing the software,
and I'll show you some more features that I've built. So, I've added a type filter,
like at the top here, you can see it says type filter, and there's a list of different
types of things that it's found that are possible matches. So, it's got statues and buildings,
and if I tick, I can tick sculpture to say I just want sculptures, and then when I scroll
down, it will just show me things that it thinks are sculptures. So, I can focus on
one particular type of thing. Sometimes, when you put in the name of a town, you might get
200 matches, and it's a bit overwhelming to do them all in one go, so it's useful to do
them bit by bit, just specific types that you're interested in. And then, when I go
to the save page, it generates a change comment that's based on the type filter that you've
selected. So, here it just says add Wikidator tags to sculptures in this area. So, I'm just
going to talk about how it determines what is a match. So, if we have a look at one of
these examples, this is a sculpture. So, if we have a look at the same thing on Wikidator,
you can see that there's a statement in Wikidator, which is the instance of statement. So, this
is saying that this thing is a sculpture. So, we can click through and have a look at
the sculpture page. This is the Wikidator item for the concept of a sculpture. And then,
if we scroll down this page, we get a Wikidator property, which is for OpenStreetMap tag or
key. So, there's actually two values here, and the second value is uninteresting, like
it's shown in red because it's a deprecated value, like it's a kind of old value that
used to be used in OpenStreetMap and it's been documented in Wikidator. So, the interesting
one is the top one, which is tag colon artwork underscore type vehicle sculpture. So, you
know, the information is stored in Wikidator about what tags are used in OpenStreetMap
to describe things. So, using this information, we can say that these two things are the same
type of entity. So, when it comes to matching things, I'm looking for the coordinates to
match, like the two things in the two systems have to be close to each other. They're not
necessarily, you know, a perfect match, but within like 50 meters or something. And the
entity type has to be the same like I just described. And then I'm also looking for a
matching name or street address or identifier. So, I pull names from all over the place in
both systems, like in Wikidator there's a bunch of different fields, or rather in OpenStreetMap
there's a bunch of different fields where names can be stored, and I look at all of
those, and then in Wikidator there's different places to get the names. I look at the, the
labels that are in Wikidator, the aliases, the names of any Wikipedia articles. I look
at the file name of any images that are in Wikidator just to get as much, you know, many
possible names that I can use for matching. And then I normalize the names a lot, so I
lowercase them and I remove stop words, and I process them a lot to try and get as many
name matches I can. And then similarly with street addresses. So, there's street addresses
in OpenStreetMap and Wikidator which I compare, and the software also looks for street addresses
in the first paragraph of Wikipedia articles. So, and then in terms of matching identifiers,
there's lots of standardized OpenStreetMap tags for different identifiers, and then there's
also properties in Wikidator for those same identifiers. So, if, you know, I've got a
railway station that's got the same station code in OpenStreetMap and Wikidator, I can
be pretty sure that it's the same thing that I'm matching, so I can be confident about
that match. So, one of the things I'm not using at the moment is the Wikipedia tags
which appear in OpenStreetMap. Like before Wikidator came along, there was lots of Wikipedia
tags added to OpenStreetMap, and they're not completely consistent in their formatting
for how they link to Wikipedia, and sometimes they're wrong. So, you know, I've left the
work for now working on trying to match up using Wikipedia tags for somebody else to
have a look at. But I've been waiting for a few years now and no one has, so I might
have to have a go at this. So, just in case anyone's interested in the technology behind
this, this software is written in Python with Flask. I'm using Postgres as my database,
and then on the front end, you know, various bits of JavaScript. I'm not really a front
end developer, but, you know, I'm modelling my way through, and it seems to be working
quite well. I'm using a bunch of APIs to get this data, so in terms of searching for places
to look for matches, I use the OpenStreetMap Norman Artem API, and then to grab more data,
I use the Overpass API, and then on the Wikidator side, I do a lot of sparkle queries against
the Wikidator query service, and I use the Wikidator MediaWiki API to get the details
of the Wikidator items. So, there's a bunch of things that don't work in my system at
the moment. One of them is tunnels, like I designed the software with the assumption
that there would be a kind of one-to-one mapping between a thing in OpenStreetMap and a thing
in Wikidator, and that doesn't work for tunnels, because tunnels tend to get represented as
two ways in OpenStreetMap, where, as in Wikidator, there'll be a single item. And so, you know,
my assumption was wrong, and I need to change my software to say that you can link, you
know, add the Wikidator identifier to ways in OpenStreetMap, but I haven't done that
yet. Incidentally, bridges, we don't have the same problem with bridges, like the way
that bridges get represented in OpenStreetMap is they're often two ways, but then there's
a relation across the whole bridge that represents the bridge itself, and tunnels, there isn't
a relation for representing, you know, the whole concept of the tunnel. So, that's another
possible approach. Maybe OpenStreetMap should change and start mapping the tunnels with
a relation that contains the two ways, you know, for storing Wikidator tags and any
other information about the tunnel that is the same across both ways. So, another thing
that I don't support are rivers, because they are linear relations, and my software that
I'm using to import data from OpenStreetMap, I'm using OSM to PG SQL, and it can't handle
linear relations, it just, you know, expects relations to be polygons. So, at the moment,
rivers don't work in the system. And then similarly for tram stops, tram stops are kind
of complex objects in OpenStreetMap, like you've got, you know, stop positions of where
the tram stops on either side of the road, which are nodes, single points, and they're
collected together into a relation, and that isn't supported properly by OSM to PG SQL,
so I can't handle tram stops properly. I've got to talk about a few more features that
are in the software. So, again, this is the center of Brussels, and I've got the language
selector. So, the software has figured out all the languages that get used in for the
labels of things and the OpenStreetMap objects that are in this area. You know, unsurprisingly
for Brussels, the most popular languages are French and then Dutch, and English is the
third most popular. Interestingly, we've got Latin at the bottom there. There's 22 items
that have got labels in Latin in Wikidata. But, so, by default, this page is opened in
French, and you can see the type filter is appearing in French, but I can't read French
very well, so if I want to change it to Dutch, I can reorder these languages by drag and
drop, or I can click on move to top, and you can see the type filter is now switched into
being in Dutch, or if I want it in English, then I can move English to the top of the
list, and it will show me the type filter in English, English labels and descriptions.
And if I scroll down the page, you can see this is the page appearing in French. You've
got titles in French and the extracts from Wikidata in French, or again, I can change
it into Dutch if I want, or I can have it in English. And this works without reloading
the page. You just change the order that you prefer the languages to appear in, and it
does it all on the client and switches it over. So, some statistics for you. People
are using this tool. Well, first of all, there's more and more Wikidata tags appearing in OpenStreetMap,
so not all of them are coming from my software. There's other people figuring out how to add
Wikidata tags to OpenStreetMap. So, here's some more stats. 26% of the Wikidata tags
in OpenStreetMap were added using this tool, and we're up to 400 people, and there's been
23,000 change sets, and we're getting close to 700,000 Wikidata tags added. So, I'm going
to talk about the licensing. Wikidata is CC0 or public domain. You can do anything you
want with Wikidata, and OpenStreetMap uses the Open Database license, which is a license
that was pretty much written for OpenStreetMap. So, you can't copy any data from OpenStreetMap
into Wikidata because you'd be relicensing it CC0, which is not allowed. But even more
than just the licenses being different, the intellectual property jurisdictions are different.
So, OpenStreetMap asserts database rights. Like, the argument is that it's a lot of effort
to go around collecting all this information and putting it in OpenStreetMap, and they
want to protect that, whereas Wikidata is part of the Wikimedia Foundation, which uses
US intellectual property rules. And so, under US law, facts are not copyrighted, not protected,
rather in law. So, the two things don't mesh that well, but it's fine because I'm not copying
any data between the systems. I'm just adding links between them. In some cases, it might
be nice if we could, you know, tidy up the data in one system based on the other. But
I'm not doing that, and, you know, you've got to think carefully about the intellectual
property rules before you try and do that. And so, also, just while we're talking about
licenses, my software is GPL, and the code is on GitHub. It's all open source. Anyone
can have a look at the software behind it. So, an important aspect for being able to
add these links between the systems is to have stable identifiers. And for a long time,
OpenStreetMap has talked about the identifiers not being stable. You know, sometimes, say,
a railway station might get mapped as a single point, and then later on, somebody comes along
and traces the outline of the building. And so, it changes from being a node into a way
or a relation, and the identifier will have changed. So, you know, there aren't stable
identifiers for concepts in OpenStreetMap. So, that, you know, the thinking is that that
makes it difficult to link into OpenStreetMap because the identifiers might change. And
there's been discussions within the OpenStreetMap community of having a permanent ID. And these
discussions have been going on since 2017, and they haven't, you know, come to a conclusion.
There's been an argument that maybe the right thing to use in terms of stable identifiers
would be Wikidata IDs. Just say, anything that's important enough to need a stable identifier
is probably on Wikidata, and so you could use the Wikidata IDs as a permanent ID. But
another way to look at it is, in reality, you know, most of the world is mapped now
on OpenStreetMap, and the IDs aren't changing that much. You know, things tend to be mapped
as polygons, like outlines of buildings, and people aren't coming along and making changes
that are destructive in destroying the IDs. So, maybe the IDs that are in OpenStreetMap
already, the IDs that I talked about earlier, maybe they're stable enough, and maybe it's
okay to just link to those and not worry about them changing. Whereas, Wikidata, on the other
hand, and Wikidata was designed always to have stable identifiers, that was, you know,
a big part, I think, of the initial approach to Wikidata. Like, Wikipedia identifies things
by article title, and over time the article titles can change, and then, you know, things
get moved around, and so they don't have, you know, long-term stable IDs. And so, the
Wikidata QIDs was an approach that gave you stable IDs, but it turns out that they're not
completely stable. There's also redirects appearing in Wikidata, like, with some of
the work I've been doing, I find a lot of duplicates in Wikidata. Things have been imported
from different sources, and say, for example, I found a lot of duplicate churches in Wikidata.
So when I go and I merge the churches, then the ID that represents, you know, one of those
churches will change. So, you know, I've got on the slide here, there's 10,000 OpenStreetMap
objects that point to a redirect in Wikidata, and somebody needs to go through and update
those, like, resolve those redirects and fix OpenStreetMap. I will probably do that at
some point, if no one else does. So, a recent change to Wikidata is that there's a new property
called OpenStreetMapElement, and that is for storing OpenStreetMap IDs. So now it is possible
to add the links in both directions. We can have links from Wikidata to OpenStreetMap,
which we never used to be able to have. So I need to change my software to start adding
these links in. Like, when you save things at the moment, it just uploads them to OpenStreetMap.
It should be uploading them to Wikidata as well. But to do that, I need to make the user
log in to both systems, you know, which is possible, but it will break the flow of it.
So I am going to try and do a demo. Let's see. So this is the software I'm describing,
and I can say I want it in English. And you can see the type filter there. And if I scroll
down, it shows matches that weren't very good at the start. So it's got some difficulty
with this match, and it can't handle it. So we scroll past those. And here's the first
match that the system can handle. And if I click on it, then it shows you the match.
I can click toggle OSM tags. This is showing all of the tags from OpenStreetMap. The green
ones are ones where it's found a match that's using those to figure out what the match is.
I'll show you some more. Here's another one. You can see it appearing on the map. If I
think this is not a correct match, I can click here, and it's deselected it. Thank you. So
I've got a whole pile of matches here. I've checked these ahead of time. They're all good.
So I'll scroll to the bottom, and I can say add tags to OpenStreetMap. And this is the
confirmation page that I was telling you about. So I can hit save. And the software goes through,
and it's saving my matches. So it has done it. And I can say view my change set. And
you get to see my change set on OpenStreetMap. I can scroll down. And you can see these are
all the things I've edited. So nice and quick to go through and edit OpenStreetMap. And
I've just got another example. Another bit of Brussels. I can change to English. Say
I want squares. And then if I scroll down, it will just show me some matches that haven't
worked. So I scroll past those. Here's some squares that the software has managed to match
up. And these all look like good matches. I've checked these before. So I can scroll
to the bottom. There's another one. And I can say add to save to OpenStreetMap. And
it's in the change comment, it's put the word squares. So I can hit save. And that is working
to edit OpenStreetMap. I'll go back to the presentation. So that was my existing software.
That's been running for a few years. People have been using that. And I've been working
on a new version of the software that I'm calling LMap. This is what LMap looks like.
So when you open this, you go straight to a map. It tries to guess where you are, locate
you based on your IP address. And then it shows you this interface, much more map based
rather than a list of things. You see the red pins are where there isn't a match already.
Green pins are where there is a match. And the yellow pins are OpenStreetMap things.
So you can see some of them have a line between the green pin and the yellow pin. That's showing
you which, you know, the green pin is a Wikidator item that matches a thing on OpenStreetMap
which is the yellow pin and there's a line between them. And you've got a filter at the
side where you can filter on different item types. This is an example where I've selected
one of the pins. I've clicked on a pin and it changes the color slightly. And it shows
you some details. You get to see the photo and bits and pieces from Wikidator. And then
underneath it shows you a list of possible matches. It just says, you know, this is a
building. Here's some other buildings nearby. And I can see the street addresses on here
and, you know, the nearest building, the street address matches. But in actual fact there's
two street addresses on there. And if I scroll down this list, I can see that there's two
buildings next to each other that both match this warehouse. So for some reason Wikidator
is representing it as a single item whereas OpenStreetMap has got two separate objects.
But this version of the software supports it. So I tick the boxes next to them and then
I can hit save and it'll add the Wikidator tag to them. So this bit of software I'm still
working on. It's live but it keeps breaking so I'm not really advertising for people to
use it. I need to do some more work on it. And in fact I think I need some help. I'm
just a hobbyist and I'm running out of time to work on this stuff. So I don't know if
anyone knows how I can get some help with this, whether there's someone out there who
wants to pay for this work or whether I can find volunteers to help me. I don't know.
It's sort of a tricky like trying to work out managing people to work on this. So yeah,
that's the software built. And I guess has anyone got any questions?
If you have a question please raise your hand so I can see you. Oh there, I'm coming.
Thank you Edward for that. Hi, I'm Seabroant. I'm a volunteer at Wikimedia. Wikimedia has
a service called Wikimedia Cloud Services where you get free compute resources. Oh,
where you can get free compute resources. I would highly recommend that you look into
that. So like the machine I'm running some of this stuff on is 60 gigabytes of RAM and
two terabytes of disk. Would I be able to get that much from Cloud Services? I would
highly recommend that you talk to someone there. Okay. As you may be having a project
that's quite valuable to the Wikimedia movement, I'm sure that someone will try to help you.
Yep, sounds good. Anybody else? Over there. Hi, thank you for your contributions and for
the talk. Have you considered interfacing or linking with Osmos? It's a quality assurance
project from... Licking with what, sorry? Osmos. Osmos is Osmos.opestreamad.fr. It's
a quality assurance project. It's a matter where you see alerts on the map, dangling
ways, etc. I think it's somewhat extended and it has an existing user base. Maybe you
could benefit from that. I haven't looked at this. Okay, I will write you later. Thank
you. Hello. I have two remarks. First of all, I'm the maker of MapComplete, which also
has an etymology team to link Wikidata to Straits so we can work together on that.
And then second, a small remark on adding an ID of OpenStreetMap to Wikidata. That's
a bit of a float approach because IDs aren't very stable in OpenStreetMap. Say that a new
park is opened, I place a point where the park is and then a few days later someone
else passes by and says, oh, we have aerial imagery now. There was an outline as a polygon
and then it removes the alt point. That means that the link would be broken in Wikidata.
I mean, I guess we just have to deal with that. We can have software that looks for
these broken links. Maybe it would be nice if OpenStreetMap could add redirects like
Wikidata has. Yeah, except that it's way more difficult than that because, for example,
sometimes you have a big street and then you have properties which are different for parts
of the street and then the street gets split into three parts. So then suddenly you'd have
to redirect to three different parts. So it's better.
Do you think that it's a mistake to add OpenStreetMap IDs to Wikidata then?
Yes, basically. It doesn't make sense at first glance, but technically it will break down
over time. So it's better to add a link to OpenStreetMap to Wikidata and then look at
that perversely because the editing tools will keep track of the Wikidata link. So if
the roads get split into multiple pieces, every single piece of the road will get a
backlink to the Wikidata item. Yeah, you might have a good point.
But let's have a discussion after the questions. Hi, Ed. Thanks for sharing the new software.
It looks great. So I was fascinated by the example where you showed more than one potential
match and I just wondered, does your software have a role to play in improving the quality
of the data by cross-referencing between the two sides?
I think it can improve the quality. Like I say, when I run this, I find duplicates in
Wikidata that are difficult to identify from just Wikidata itself. I feel like the coordinates
that are in Wikidata don't get much use. Like for a long time, you didn't even see the map
appear in the Wikidata pages and then a lot of the coordinates were wrong, people transposed
digits. Since the map is visible, people are more likely to check their data. And yeah,
you can, the fact that the two systems exist, you can cross-reference them and find errors.
Yes. I'm wondering how relevant it is now based upon the question just a moment ago.
But I was wondering, can you search Wikidata for a lot longer window and find all objects
within it when you're adding data to OpenStreetMap? So the, the, the, the, underneath I'm doing
sparkle queries to Wikidata and Wikidata sparkle queries do support coordinate bounding boxes.
I can say, you know, you can write your own query in sparkle that will give you all the
churches within a given bounding box. The, like I demoed two separate systems that should
really be combined into one and the old system doesn't support bounding boxes. It's all based
on kind of place polygons. You have to say, show me things that are in Brussels. You can't
say, show me things within this rectangle. And the new system is more kind of bounding
box based in that you see the map and it just shows you all the matches that are in the
rectangle that's visible on the screen. I'm not sure if that answers your question.
It doesn't think, it's very valuable what you've done. Thanks.
Any other questions? Raise your hand. Okay. Hi. Thank you for your talk. I had a question
about the OpenStreetMap, OpenStreetMap tags that are in Wikidata. I think you show this
in one of your slides. So how often are these tags uploaded from OpenStreetMap and does
it pose any problem with the license compatibility issues that you talked about?
I think you mean the property for OpenStreetMap tag or key. So things like I showed the palace
type. Is that right? Is that the one you're thinking of? There's a few properties in Wikidata.
Yes, the OSM tag like the structure one. I don't think there's any problem in terms
of the intellectual property. It's kept pretty up to date. Like people invent a new tag to
use on OpenStreetMap and then they go and find the matching Wikidata item and add the
tag to it. And some unofficial tags that are used on OpenStreetMap, the information is
in Wikidata. So it's pretty current, I think. So similar question from my side. So nice
presentation. You explained the licenses nicely. Then you said that you cannot copy data from
the OpenStreetMap to Wikidata. But what about the other way around? So that's an interesting
question. And the OpenStreetMap community is a bit suspicious of the information that's
in Wikidata. Like there's a feeling, you know, where did the coordinates come from? Were
they just copied from Google Maps? Like do people look up a thing on Google Maps, find
the coordinates, put the coordinates into Wikidata? And then does that make Wikidata
a derived work of Google Maps? And so, you know, it's probably fine to copy any data
from Wikidata into OpenStreetMap. If you want to copy a name in a different language, that's
probably fine. But my software doesn't do that. I just add the links. And once the links
are there, it's easier for somebody else to come along and find these things and copy
the data over if they want. So my question is, does the software do the
requests, the API requests on the back end on your hosted service? Or is it the client,
the user that will do the browser will do the API requests?
I showed two versions. The old, you know, the more established version is using the
Nominate API to find things and then it's using the Overpass API to grab lots of map
data. And then I use the OpenStreetMap API to push the changes you make to upload the
Wikidata tags back into OpenStreetMap. And the new system I built maintains a full mirror
of the OpenStreetMap data just to make things faster. So I'm not using APIs for downloading
the data with that one. I just use the API for saving the changes. Does that answer your
question? Yeah, partly. But does the request to fetch
data from the Wikidata, does that go from your servers? Do your servers fetch data?
Oh, I see. It is all going from my server, yeah. It's not from the client browser. It's
going. Like I do a lot of preprocessing before I show you the list of matches and then I
store them all in the database. So when you load the list of matches for a place, it's
not doing any queries either on the server or the client with the APIs. It's all stored
in the database. I mean, that's a problem. The matches get stale, there's a refresh button
that you can hit and it will go off and rerun the match and get fresh data from OpenStreetMap
and Wikidata. Yeah, OK. Thanks.
There was a question here? No? OK, so I'll be back. All the other side.
Hi, I'm Valerio from Milano and thank you so much for this tool. Again, thank you for
the person who mentioned the possibility to host this tool on the Wikimedia Foundation
infrastructure because it would be really, really nice to propose this on the Wikimedia
Fabricator and I would be interested in discovering how the discussion will go. And second thing,
you asked how to found your development. I think you can just contact your local Wikimedia
chapter that maybe they provide microgrants or something like that. In my local community,
some volunteers often in one week can obtain a microgrant to develop small tools or to
boost some activities. Maybe this can be interesting for if they are useful for the universe and
to produce software and the software and that's all. And one feedback for the user interface,
it's not clear to me how to contribute on just one element. So if I have one minute,
if I want to visit the tool and connect just one item because I'm 100% sure about that
item and so I just want to press save on that contribution and be kidnapped. So this maybe
can be useful if it's not already possible.
There are two approaches for that. If you click on the title of an item, it takes you
to a page where you can just edit a single item.
Okay, wonderful.
Or at the top of the page, there's an uncheck all tick box and then you can just tick the
box next to one thing and scroll to the bottom and hit save. Both of those will work for
adding a single Wikidator tag to.
Okay, thank you.
And thanks for your comment about contacting my local Wikidator.
Okay.
That's a good idea.
Last thing, can you repeat, sorry, why do you need two terabytes of data to have this
working?
The OpenStreetMap.
Thank you so much.
The OpenStreetMap database is big. The world, the earth is big and I keep a whole copy of
it to make things fast. And so it's probably 1.6 terabytes to store all of the OpenStreetMap
data.
I think that's time up.
Okay, so thank you.
Thank you.