So, welcome to the Postgres Girl Dev Room.
If you weren't here before, can I please ask you to silence your phones and extend a very
warm welcome to Peter Zaitsev.
Okay.
Well, thank you.
We are going to talk about query performance today.
But before that, let me understand a little bit who do we have here.
Now, which of you would mostly see yourself as DBA, SRE, sysadmin kind of on the operation
side?
Just, you know, can we have it?
Okay.
And which of you are developers?
Ooh, lots of developers.
Okay.
In terms of developers, right, now if you do it again, but now for sort of like a front
end developers, right?
Something not, you know, database, or some, you know, other complicated stuff, but something
more simple.
Front end developers.
Any?
Hello!
Okay.
Well, anyway, so one of the points of this talk for me, right, is really to try to bring
the gap, what I see a lot, between how their operations people, right, the people who are
deeply vested in a databases, right, development, think about them.
There are just people who just happen to use those databases for the application, right?
And often their relationship to the database is, well, really quite different, right?
As a database, current developers often deeply care about all those kind of internal algorithms,
have it, you know, discussion, what is the best way to implement this and that cases.
But for many developers writing applications, well, you know, they think about databases,
you know, as you think about like a plumbing, right?
Well, it just got to work, you don't want to think about it.
Well, it just, if it doesn't, then that becomes a problem, right?
They think about database in many cases as a black box.
And I think that is increasingly happening now, especially when we have so many databases
which are deployed in a cloud as a database as a service, right?
Because in this case, especially, well, you just have a database and somebody else focuses
on other stuff.
So what does that database means from developer standpoint in many cases?
Well, that means you get some sort of service point, you should use any application, right?
You can connect to that service point and get that quickly with no problem, right?
And then you run the queries you need to run, right?
Of a database or maybe even what your or a RAM framework, right?
Or something generates.
Now what do you want from those queries?
Well, as a selfish developer, you want those queries to run with no errors.
You want to make sure they get you correct results, right?
And you want to make sure you run them the same response time, which is appropriate for
your application and for query time and for query time.
And I think that is very important to understand here.
What if I am looking as a developer and a database from performance standpoint, I understand
that as how quickly that database responds to my queries, right?
Now if you think about their software design in general, right?
And I think especially maybe not developers, but architects often have to care about a
whole bunch of other things beyond just the performance.
For example, we often have to care about security, right?
And typically security costs stuff, right?
It comes with overhead, both in terms of performance overhead and organizational overhead and so
on and so forth, right?
That's done two-factor authentication always takes another couple of seconds, right?
But that makes us more secure.
Availability is also important as well as things like costs.
I think that is especially important again in the modern age when they have a lot of
cloud which is elastic, right?
But that elasticity comes also with spend, right?
You often can say, hey, you know what?
If I just need my queries to run faster, I can blow up my instant size, right, or something
else.
But well, guess what?
That also will be expensive, right, if you're not doing efficiently.
And there is, let's say, a bunch of other things you want to consider about, right?
So I don't want to simplify that, let's say, to what everything is also only about query
performance but that is what I am going to focus in my talk.
Now when you think about response time from the database standpoint, we often think about
that from a query context, right?
Well I see my database response to the queries XYZ, you know, in average or something, right?
You think about that query basis.
But if you really look at from a business standpoint, right, how you boss or bosses
bosses boss, right, where it thinks about that, it's mostly about the users which are
using your applications, right?
And I typically would define it what really folks are after is what the users of your
applications, right, and all users, right, have outstanding experience in terms of performance
for all their interactions.
Because in application you often may have different interactions, right?
And I want to make sure I have a search which is fast and place in an order which is fast,
right, and wherever other things all working quickly.
Now as database engineers, we often want to talk about performance and availability as
the different things, right?
Like saying, well, no, no, no, the database was up.
It just was overloaded so that query took 15 seconds, oh 15 minutes, right, or something
like that, right?
But reality is for the user, their very bad performance is really indistinguishable from
downtime because, well, A, people have a limited variance, right, and if something is taking
too long, we'll just go into close the page.
And even if you have something with unlimited patterns, there's going to be a whole bunch
of timeouts, including your browser timeouts, which will show you what the page cannot load
well before 15 minutes, right?
So I think that is another important thing which I find also important talking to some
maybe business people about why spend resources on performance, query performance optimization,
and so on and so forth, right?
Because, well, you know what, if it doesn't perform, it is done, right?
Another thing what I would point out, right, is in many cases you see people talking about
the averages, right?
Well the query performance was so many, you know, milliseconds or something in average,
right?
And while it may be helpful for comparison standpoint compared today to yesterday, really
it is not very helpful, right, because, well, the average may be what you're looking for,
there may be way too many queries which are too slow, right, just balanced by the queries
which are high, right?
And as I wrote here, I really like this saying, where once lived a man who tried to cross
a river in average one measure deep, right?
Where once lived a man.
So in this regard, I think it's very helpful to look at things like a percentile response
time at the very least, right, if you want to look at one number because you're looking
simplicity.
99 percentile for query response time is much better than average response time.
What is even better is, of course, is to look some sort of distribution, you know, query
histogram distribution and how it changes over time.
That often can give you a lot of insight.
The thing from percentile, though, is it's interesting how it works as you go from that
query to the user experience, right, you spoke about it.
Because think about this, right, typically when you may have a single user interaction
as a page view, it may require multiple sequential queries, right, or even maybe some queries
run in parallel, right, which all need to be fast in order for user to get the outcome
they're looking for, right?
And then typically user through his session will have a multiple of those page views,
right?
So that 99 percentile being excellent may only translate to half the users having that
kind of outstanding experience through all the session, right?
That is why if you look at companies which have a large number of users, they would either
have some very high percentiles, like 99.9 percentile response time as a goal, right,
or would have those tolerances, you know, rather high, right, so there is, well, additional
sort of accommodation for which there's going to be many queries.
And I think to consider when you measure query performance is how you relate to errors, right?
In certain cases I've seen people saying, well, you know, we only go into either measure
response time for only successful queries or we're going to put successful queries and
queries which are completed with errors in the same bucket, right, which really can,
you know, change a picture for you a lot.
Why is that?
Well, because actually if you think about the errors, they can be both fast errors and
slow errors, right?
Imagine, for example, table was dropped for some reason.
Well, then all the queries hitting that table will return the error and vary very quickly,
right, because, well, there's nothing they can do.
On the other hand, if there is something, let's say some data is locked, right, and
some timeouts happen, that may take quite a while before error is returned, right?
And you better not to mix those with the rest of your successful queries but to be able
to, you know, look at that separately.
You also want to look at the query performance, not just as like an overall number, but how
it changes over response time with a reasonably high resolution.
Why is that important?
One thing is what in many cases you would see query performance kind of slowly drops
before it goes so bad, what that seems like downtime or really, you know, really incident
for all kind of reasons, right?
Maybe you have some application which has a bad query, right, and then you have the
one instance of that query running, two, three, four, five.
Now you have a hundred instances of that bad query running, right, so saturating all the
system resources, guess what?
All the other query performance, right, is going down.
If you are able to, if you are going to notice that what some queries are out of bounds,
right, and maybe alert on it or something, you are able to take an action before the
small problem becomes, basically, because of downtime.
The other reason, of course, there is shit that is always going on, right?
There is something's database does in the background, if you have a cloud, there is
also certain other things happening which you may not even know anything about it.
Like for example, blocked, elastic block storage, right, or similar stuff, right?
Well, guess what?
It doesn't always have uniform performance.
You know, sometimes something is happening at like Amazon back end, but you know what?
You don't really know anything about that.
They don't tell you each time they have to replace a hard drive, right, somewhere, right,
or you know, rebalance the load for some reason, right?
But those things, they can pop up.
Often you may see something like, oh, I have that like a spike in a query response time
which I can see for all queries on my or all instances and wow, that's very likely like
something is in the environment.
Now when you look at the query instrumentation, one of the questions I see people asking is
where do you want to instrument the query, right?
And we can instrument the query on the application data point, right, an application, issue that
query, right, and we often have some, you know, tools like, you know, new relic insights
which are doing, you know, just that.
And hey, that query took this amount of response time and this is very good data because it
actually includes real response time as application observed it.
If there was some, let's say, network delay, right, of whatever reason, that is including
that response time where if you just measure from the time database received the query,
it's a push, pushed the result in the network, right, that is not included.
But measuring on a database gives you a lot of other valuable stuff like you can get a
lot more insight about what has been going on on the database size that that query was
executed because typically when you get the query result and you get response time, maybe
you know, some other little additional information like obvious query, return, so many rows,
so many bytes, right, but not specifically, you know, how much CPU it uses, right, and
all the other important things in the world to use.
Okay.
So let's go back to our definition of response time from a business point of view, right,
and we can say, well, what we are looking for have our old users to have outstanding
experience with all of their applications, right?
Great.
Now, how do we translate that to the database, right, and kind of maybe read that gap without
what BOSS wants and what DBA is able to answer.
Now I think there is some great work in this regard done by Google which have been working
on this L2L commenter project which allows to pass a lot of metadata, right, from your
application all the way down to your query.
The cool things they've done is also integrating that directly with some of the frameworks,
right, so it's kind of, hey, you know, you need to do nothing, right, and you just get
that aftermatic information.
What could be valuable query metadata possibilities, right?
If you ask me, well, here is a bunch, right, there is this actual user and tenant which
we can do the application functionality, right, often single database is used by a lot of
applications, right, and we want to know where the query comes from, right.
I see a lot of DBA's, especially from a large company, say, well, you know what, here is
this nasty query came in.
It was not here yesterday but it's very hard to figure out who is responsible for introducing
that and how you can come and hit his head with something heavy, right.
That's maybe hard, right, without proper instrumentation.
You also as a primary breakdown want to look at the query and I mean by query in this case,
query of all parameters, you know, normalized because often you would see the different
queries response for different functions and through that have a different response time
tolerances, right.
Let's say some very quick lookup queries you often want them to complete in fraction of
milliseconds as acceptable stuff.
While some of you search queries, right, or some reports, well, it may take a few seconds
and that will be quite acceptable and it's good not to mix those all together, right,
in this case.
In many cases when you have the SaaS applications, we would have multiple users or what often
cause like multiple tenants.
Like one of the ways you split them is to have a different schema or different databases
for all of them and that is also, I find, very helpful to be able to separate that so
you can say, oh, this query is not slow for everybody but then it drill down, we can see
only that particular tenant is slow and why is he slow because unlike other, he has five
million images in his album, right, if you would think about some, you know, for the
hosting application.
So that's just an example.
And I think what you find very helpful is being able to go for the query, right, or
to look to understand what tables it touches and reverse to find out all the queries which
touch a specific table.
Why is that helpful?
Well, in many cases our database operations are table specific, right.
You may think, hey, you know what, I'm dropping this index as I don't need it or maybe I add
an index, I add a column, right.
You do some sort of maybe kind of partition table, right.
You can do a lot of things with a table in scope, right, and then it would be very interesting
to understand how that particular, how all the queries which touch that table have been
affected because they are much likely to be affected by that change compared to everybody
else, right.
I find that's a pretty cool feature.
Database user is another one.
If you do not have something like a SQL command to enable, you often do not really see very
well from what application a given query comes in.
But one of the practice you may follow at least is having a different application touching
the same database using different user names, right, different users with different privileges,
right.
Even else that is a very good security practice, right, and that is where filtering and breakdown
allows that.
In a large short environment, we also want to make sure we aggregate the data from many
database hosts, right, and can compare between each other.
Typically, when you have a short application, you want to load and hence response time between
different database hosts to be kind of similar.
But often it is not, right.
It's often hard to achieve a perfect balance in between the nodes as one cause of the differences.
But also things may just, you know, happen.
You know, like you may have a settings which drift away on different nodes.
You may have some, you know, differences, right, in the performance, especially in the
cloud which, you know, happen virtually from nowhere, right.
I mean, I know a lot of people work in the cloud, you know, sometimes you just get a
lemon, right, or just like a bad note which for some reason doesn't perform as well as
its peers, right, and you just want to, you know, maybe toss it and get another one, a
better one, right.
But to do that, you better understand what that is not performing particularly well.
And the same also applies to their application server or web server.
Again, like if you deploy application on, let's say, the 100 application servers of
web nodes, right, you may say, well, it all should be the same.
I have my, you know, automation which takes care of that.
But again, well, things are not always as they should be.
In many cases you have something which doesn't work out.
I have seen so many cases when people say, well, you know what, I already fixed that
nasty query and I deployed the fix.
When you look at that, well, it actually was not deployed all the instances for whatever
reason.
Or you may say, well, you know what, I'm using the caching to reduce the query load on the
database but that caching is misconfigured to otherwise inaccessible on some of the web
nodes, right.
A lot of stuff can happen.
Or maybe you're lucky and one of your web nodes was actually hacked and is also getting
some additional queries to, you know, download your data and send it to someone.
So I find making sure you can look at the query patterns separated by the different
client hosts are something very valuable.
I already mentioned with SQL commenter which allows you to extend some additional metadata
which I think can be quite cool, right.
And you can find the usage for custom tags in many cases.
I've seen people, for example, tagging different instance types.
And I'm saying, well, you know what, this kind of new generation instance looks good.
So let me put some of them in production and being able to compare.
Well, is it actually working better?
I mean, yes.
Sometimes, you know, no.
The database version, right, maybe you're running out when you minor post-release release,
you want to do it like on some subset of the nodes and to make sure there's no regressions,
right.
I mean, I think it's always good in this case to practice, you know, trust by verify, right,
because sometimes you do run into unexpected changes, you know, you can validate configuration
changes this way and so on and so forth.
Query plan is another area which I think is quite interesting.
In many cases, you'll find the same query depending on the parameters, right, or some
other situations will have different plans.
And in fact, different plans may have different query performance.
And it is very helpful if you can break down the performance by the different plans a query
has so you can understand if that is a plan issue or not, right.
Otherwise you may be looking at the query and say, well, you know what, sometimes it's
fast, sometimes it's low, you know, why is that not very clear?
Their plans give us a very good information.
Now then you find the query and see that as a problematic and you need to make it go fast.
In this case, it's very good to understand there is that response time developers care
so much about is coming from.
And there are quite a few possibilities here.
Some of them are instrumented better than others.
For example, if you're looking at data crimes in this guy, you're right, those are typically
pretty well instrumented.
You can find how much, you know, of CPU query consumes or does.
In terms of contention, that is typically more problematic, right, to say, hey, you
know, what exactly those kind of internal synchronization object query had to wait,
right, that is more tricky.
You know, wait on CPU availability is even more tricky, right.
And what I mean by this is this, right.
So if you have a system which has much more runnable threads, runnable processes, right,
and available CPU, then they will spend a lot of time waiting for available CPU, right.
And that is very hard to see on its impact to query response time.
You typically can see that from the general node stats, like, hey, my CPU is pegged, I
have, like, ton of runnable CPU, right.
CPU is also in recent kernels.
You can see the information about their run queue latency, which is very cool, right.
That's, you know, tells you how long the processes had to wait to be scheduled on CPU after they
are ready to start running.
So a whole bunch of stuff here, some of them are easy, some of their work is still remaining.
Now from our standpoint, with all this kind of view on approach to query monitor, we have
been working at the extension for Postgres.
Sorry.
Yeah, called Pgstat monitor.
Well, and look, right, we specifically built it for Postgres, right, not for MySQL, even
though we had a lot more experience with MySQL, because PostgreSQL extension interface is awesome
and much more powerful than MySQL, right.
So you can read a little bit about this here.
And this is extension which allows a lot more insights and getting kind of such slicing
and dicing, which I mentioned, right.
If you think about the traditional PostgreSQL extension Pgstat statements, it really aggregates
all the data from the start, which is very helpful to be used directly.
But we look at the modern observability system where we expect to have many PostgreSQL instances
anyway, right, and some system getting that stuff constantly and consolidating that.
So that means we are capturing a lot of information, but keep it only on for a relatively short
time in a PostgreSQL instance, right.
And that allows to get much more granular information without requiring huge amount
of resources, which would be required if you would have it for a time.
So you can, you know, read more about what that does on the web pages.
Now some folks asked me, saying, well, folks, like, why do you work on a separate extension
not improved Pgstat monitors, and my answer to that is we really wanted to experiment
with different approaches, right, to find what works, what doesn't, how users do, and
that is always easy to do in a separate extension, right.
And then if something is liked by the community, then we can see how we can get that in the
official list of extensions.
So that is their feedback, is very valuable.
And also if you look at this case, while we are providing Pgstat statements compatibility,
right, so you can get that view from the same extension instead of getting, you know, two
extensions with additional overhead, Pgstat monitor has kind of different ways to aggregate
and present the data, right, which kind of, well, you cannot get in the same, in the same
view.
Okay.
Now, as I spoke about the query performance, I wanted to highlight a couple of other things
which are quite interesting to consider when you are looking at the queries where I see
number of issues.
One is what I would call the bad queries versus victims, right.
In certain cases, or like in many cases, right, you may see even your otherwise good queries,
like hey, this is just a lookup by the primary key starting to be a lot slower than it usually
is, not because something changes the relationship to that query, but because of some other bad
queries, right, have been running in parallel.
And imagine that if you will over saturate your node, right, with hundreds of bad queries
running at the same time, right, well, then everything will become slow.
And I think that's important to understand what if you are seeing some query being slow,
you cannot just think about that as that query problem, it may be entirely something else.
The next thing to consider is currently running queries.
That is also rather interesting, right, because they may not be reflected in the log, right,
or something which say, oh, that query completed and it was, you know, five minutes response
time or 15 seconds, whatever, right.
But running queries can be a problem.
In many cases that is actually how things start to snowball, right, you have some application
or even kind of user starts a lot of, you know, bad queries, you know, forgot like a
wear clause and a join or something like that and they just, you know, run for a long time,
right, so you want to make sure you're paying attention to that as well.
The next is to consider what not all activities are directly visible from a query standpoint.
The database often tend to do a bunch of background activities, right, additionally you may have
something else, like maybe you are taking a snapshot, right, or taking a backup in another
way which uses also the system resources, right, which are not seen from query standpoint
but same importance.
You also have a lot of things which can be happening on the cloud level, right, again
which can be, you know, completely invisible for us and wherever you are looking again
at the query performance it's important to consider there, you know, maybe something
going on, right, additionally what those queries tell you.
Next question is about, or last thing I would say, is about sampling.
In certain cases I see people saying well, you know what, let us only capture queries
over X time.
A lot of APM frameworks, right, for example, you know, like New Relic and such may be
very focused on that, saying hey, you know what, we are going to also give you some examples
of queries which take more than one second or whatever execution time, so focus on those.
Well, and yes, looking at those queries may make sense, right, if they take a long time
that may be a problem, but it is often what your medium of performance queries, right,
I would say are creating a whole bunch of load on your system and they contribute the
greatest response time to user applications, right, and ignoring those can be problematic.
Well that is the main overview, right, I hope that was helpful, right, and my main goal
here is to make sure maybe to give you some thinking tools, right, as you noticed that
is not like particularly technical talk, right, which tells you how exactly to find out which
indexes to create or something, but hopefully you get some tools in this case, how to start,
how to approach that, which can prevent you from tuning by the credit card, you know,
scaling the instances to inappropriate sizes, because hey, that is good for both your wallets
as well as good for environment, right, we don't need those servers generating more heat
than absolutely needed.
Well, with that, it's all I have and I will be happy to take some questions.
Thank you very much for your talk.
My question is about when do you have to increase the box?
As a developer, you're in front of a situation where you need to decide between optimizing
or asking the CEO to just pay more because you have the time constraint, so do you have
the thumb rules where in front of a problem you will say okay, better to optimize or better
to increase the box, you know, how can you decide?
The question is to like wherever it's better to increase the box size or optimize the query.
And I think it's interesting, right, that it's not often either or question, right,
I think the time in this case is also often essence.
In many cases I've seen people saying if they have a problem, right, in this case, and they
absolutely need to get like an application up, scale the box, right, and then kind of
can currently work on the query optimization, right, and to bring it back and scale down.
I think that is a very, very reasonable approach, right, because well it gives you kind of more
briefing room.
What is important in this case as in many things in life is not to be lazy, right, like
you don't want to just, you know, scale the box and forget about that.
You want to scale the box, optimize the queries and so on, right.
Now I often when I look at the queries, right, as you look at that, you can see which of
them are low hanging fruits, right, or when a query is already optimized pretty well,
right.
If you're saying well you know what, actually majority of a workload is driven by lookups
for prime, by the primary key for a table which is already in memory.
You can say well, you know what, there is very little I can do to optimize this thing,
right.
And you're saying oh, that is a query which does massive join if no indexes, well totally
different store, right.
You may be able to make that to run thousand times faster, right, with relatively easy
index app.
Any other question?
Hi, so as part of your slice and dice approach to monitoring queries, would you advise that
concurrently queries on the application side are never written as dynamic queries or as
anonymous prepared statements and only follow say named prepared statements so that you
know you have a fixed set of queries that are always the same?
Well the question is I would say like it's kind of like a cart in a horse, right, from
my standpoint, right, like you can of course talk about those kind of practices but developers
like to do what is there, what keeps them productive, right.
In many cases saying well you know what, oh you don't use like ORAM frameworks, right,
only this and that, that is complicated, right.
Now even if you're using dynamic queries, typically they're still going to be, relate
to a limited number of variations, right, and especially limited number of most important
variations which are going to be generated and you will still see that from the query
time, right.
So in many cases like if you look at that, I would say like a whole set of queries you
would find well this application has let's say ten thousand of a distant queries but
if I look at top 20 that will be responsible like for 99 percent response time, right,
and that of course can change it but often focusing on those first, right, as well as
maybe taking care of outliers, right, is a good kind of practice how then you deal with
that information that you have.
Make sense?
Cool.
Any other question?
Exercising.
Hello, thank you for the talk.
What is the overhead of to collect this statistic because if you have like very.
Yeah, well that is a, that is a good question, right.
Of course there is, I would say it works, right.
Typically there is more overhead if you have like this like a very simple fast queries,
right, if you have like a logic queries for which take you know many seconds for them
it's, it's less like our design goal, right, which we are able to get it is being similar
to PG stat statements, right, and you know be a couple of percent or so, right, which
I think in my opinion, right, many people when they think about that observability you
will tend to obsess about the overhead, right, but really often having that insight, right,
often allow you to get so many things optimized in a manner, right, what the benefits are
far out of it.
Do you have any advice for catching bad queries before they reach production and kind of like
guarding these things, like missing indexes or whatever, before they even.
That is a very good question, right, so I didn't talk about this but it's also a question
where, right, in my opinion and I think that's also what is very helpful with the open source
solution, right, what you can really deploy it everywhere in, including your kind of CI,
CD environment, right, because what I often see people saying well you know what, data
dog, right, is expensive, it's only in production, right, what, what you want to do is make sure
you have solutions in development so you can catch bad queries before the hidden production,
but also assume you're not going to catch all the bad queries, right, some queries will
only maybe misbehave in production, right, the other good practice which comes to that
is you make sure once you're like a test environment is good, right, so you can test variety of
queries that really want your application and you have a good data set, right, for that.
I think in this regard there is like some, you know, cool features coming out from neon
for example like given like branches, branching right, then you can get like oh the full copy
of production database, you know, mess with it, run tests on it on a full-size data set,
right, instead of testing on, you know, table with hundred rows, right, which this kind
of uses.
Cool, any other question?
Okay, thank you very much.
Thank you.