Thanks very much.
I leave you in the capable hands of Karen Jax.
Hi, thanks, Jimmy.
Hi, so I'm Karen Jax, and I'm going to talk to you today about DBA evolution or the changing
role of the database administrator.
So you can see that my title at the moment isn't database administrator, but I was a
DBA administrator over 20 years.
I'm not going to talk through the agenda, I've just left it there so that you can keep
track of where we're up to and when I might stop talking.
So I promised that this would be a talk for everyone that's pondered life's important
questions.
What does a DBA actually do?
Why are DBAs always so grumpy?
How has the role of the DBA changed over the last couple of decades?
What's the DBA of the future going to do?
And will autonomous databases finally have put us all out of work?
So this year marks the 25th anniversary of the start of my career as a DBA, so I thought
that I'd allow myself a bit of a self-indulgent retrospective.
So first, the evolution of this particular DBA, and I'm going to apologise to Claire
at this point because this is going to be a bit of a me, me, me section of my talk,
so I'm just going to have to get through that bit.
Being a DBA definitely wasn't an ambition of mine at school.
Anybody here say database administrator when they were asked what they wanted to do when
they grew up?
I didn't even know I was going to go into IT until about a year before I started my
career, although with hindsight it's fairly obvious that that's what I was destined to
do.
My dad taught me to count in binary before I could even properly count in decimal.
He built me my first computer, an Acorn Atom, which he later replaced with a BBC Model B.
And obviously I used the computer for playing Chuckie Egg and other games, but I also learnt
to code in BBC Basic.
And I actually looked up the spec of the BBC Model B in case anyone's interested, so it
had a 2 megahertz processor and 64K of RAM.
I then went on to do a maths degree because I still had absolutely no idea what I wanted
to do, and maths was my favourite subject.
And after that I figured I probably ought to get some real world skills, so I did a
Masters in Software Development.
Towards the end of that, one of the graduate schemes I applied to did some aptitude tests,
and they came back to say that they thought I'd probably be good as a DBA.
So once I'd asked Jeeves what one of those was, I thought that sounded like a fairly
good fit, and that I'd give it a go.
Fortunately, it turns out that Jeeves was right, and the aptitude tests.
This is what my careers looked like so far, so I really haven't strayed very far from
my DBA role.
Obviously the things that I do in my job have changed over time because I've gradually moved
into more senior roles, and I've gradually changed the focus of what I do, but I've tried
not to let that influence what I talk about too much, I'm trying to talk more about the
DBA role in general.
So let's set the scene for the start of my career as a DBA in 1998.
The 90s brought us grunge and Britpop, they also brought us the first truly portable
and affordable mobile phones, for example the Nokia 3210.
They brought us the first text message, the Palm Pilots, and also for better or worse
Amazon and Google.
But what does a DBA actually do?
Just so that we're all on the same page, I've taken highlights of definitions of a DBA from
various places, I looked at career services, DBMS vendors, and job sites, and the general
consensus is that a DBA manages and secures computer systems that store data using specialist
software.
So they're all pretty much agreed, but that doesn't really tell us anything about what
a DBA actually does.
So first of all, one thing to note is that there are lots of different types of DBA,
and the different types of DBA will be different from organisation to organisation.
So at Acme, for example, we might have the DBA role split into many different DBA roles,
whereas at Wonka Industries we might have DBAs who are in one pool who are all responsible
for all DBA tasks.
A traditional split is between the production DBA and the development DBA, so the production
DBA will be responsible for keeping all of the databases in the production environment
up and running, so looking at things like availability, performance, security.
The development DBA would work more closely with the developers, so they've got a focus
on building and maintaining the database environment that's supporting the application development
lifecycle.
In some organisations you might see a split of system versus application DBA.
So here the application DBA will be more looking at the logical application related aspects
of the database, whereas the system DBA is going to be responsible for the underlying
software and the physical infrastructure.
And the split's not clear cut.
The roles often overlap, they may or they may not, and you might see lots of different
types of DBA as well, so you might have a data warehouse DBA who will look after the
data warehouses, particularly ETL from various data sources into the organisation's data
warehouse.
A cloud DBA I think I've got in there as well, who will be looking after cloud hosted databases,
including liaising with the cloud provider.
Also you might see database architects, I know it doesn't have DBA in the title, but
it's a very closely related role and often overlaps.
It's a role that's existed for at least a couple of decades, but it's gradually become
more popular and seems in a lot of cases to have split out from the traditional DBA role.
And it's not an exhaustive list, you could see all sorts of different types of DBA.
You might also get DBAs that look after just one particular task, such as backup and recovery
or replication, and any or all of those might be split into junior DBA and senior DBA, with
the junior DBA doing a lot of the day-to-day tasks and the senior DBA having more of a
strategic focus.
Wrong button.
So we saw the definition of a DBA role, but as I said, it didn't really tell us much about
what a DBA actually does.
So what does a DBA do in 2023?
I looked at the different definitions that I showed you earlier and there were lists
of responsibilities that went with those and I've taken information from different job
adverts and tried to pull together the list.
So most people seem to agree that a DBA will do some or all of designing, implementing
and managing backup and recovery policies.
Designing and implementing security policies and managing database access, although in
a lot of places the security role has been split out into a separate security team these
days, implementing monitoring and ongoing monitoring of the databases, design and development
of the database, including data modelling or maybe just reviewing data models that have
been created by the development team.
Support and troubleshooting, including often being on a 24-7 on-call rotor.
And database software install and upgrades listed in a lot of them as a specific task,
but in a lot of places that's automate or the installation side of things is automated,
so the DBA would either be responsible for implementing that automation or another team
would do the automation and the DBA wouldn't actually have anything to do there.
Upgrades I would say it's more of a strategic role in working with the application team
to make sure that upgrades are tested correctly so that they're successful.
And there's a whole other page, a whole other list of responsibilities, so providing database
expertise to other teams, performance tuning, enhancement, often troubleshooting, capacity
planning, creating databases, including for development and test environments, database
maintenance and data protection and GDPR considerations.
So that was a massive, sorry, before I move on, it's a massive long list of responsibilities,
so clearly in most cases one person can't do all of those things.
This chart shows some of the most requested skills for a DBA in the UK.
I've taken this from IT Jobs Watch, so it's for the six months up to January 2023, so
we can see that SQL is the first requested skill and I went up to number 23 because there
we've got PostgreSQL listed there as well.
On the next page I've summarised those different responsibilities, sorry, the different skills
that are being asked for.
So consolidating the list of skills, it boils down to SQL, so writing SQL, making it more
efficient, potentially knowing procedural languages, integration and everyone's favourite
ORMs.
One or more database management systems, usually still asking for relational.
Charge of operating systems, so this will be traditional operating systems but also
various different cloud environments.
Performance tuning, database migration seems to be quite a popular thing, people are always
moving from one database to another.
Disaster recovery, social skills is listed most of the places as a separate thing, I
don't know what they're trying to say there.
HA replication clustering type skills, and then not listed in any of the things I found
as specific skills but most DBAs I know are actually expected to know about different
DevOps tools and methodologies and they're expected to know how to use automation tools
like Ansible or Puppet to do things.
So how does all that compare to what a DBA did in 1998?
On paper it actually looks very similar, so there I've just reproduced the same list of
responsibilities as I had for what a DBA does in 2023, although I've taken off GDPR because
that didn't exist yet.
Does that mean nothing's changed?
Well obviously, although the responsibilities are pretty much the same, the skills that
a DBA needs and the tools that a DBA is expressed to be able to use have changed massively because
a lot of the tasks that they do day to day are done very differently.
And obviously that's not limited to DBA tasks or even IT tasks, we do loads of day to day
tasks differently as well.
So I've used send my sister a birthday card as an example, so that's the flow chart for
1998, I would have gone to the shop, I would have browsed the racks, chosen a card I liked,
I would have paid for that card and probably bought a stamp at the same time, taken it
home, written a message in it, put my sister's address on it, stuck the stamp on and then
walked it to my local post box to be collected by the post delivery.
I can still use that method in 2023 if I want to, but this is what I'm more likely to do.
I'm going to open the app of my favourite online retail, greetings card retailer, I'm
going to upload a photo from my phone, type in a message and my sister's address, pay
using my disposable online credit card and just get them to send it directly to my sister
as soon as it's printed.
So if we go back to DBA tasks, I've taken install database software as an example, I
have not put this there to be read.
This is an extract from the Oracle 7.3 installation guide, which was my first database installation
that I did.
I can't imagine that many DBAs in 2023 need to first walk to the machine room and put
the CD into the server before they start their installation.
It used to take me, I think, two days to prepare and perform a single database install and
we didn't have a repeatable process.
There was a silent mode that was supposed to allow us to script it, but because none
of the servers were installed using any kind of automation, they all had their own particularities
so it didn't work and we didn't bother with it.
In 2023, a DBA wouldn't be expected to know how to use an automation tool such as Ansible
to do a database software install and they probably not just install a standalone database,
they can install the whole database infrastructure, including high availability monitoring, backup
and recovery all in one command.
What kind of skills did a DBA need in 1998?
I can't reproduce the list of skills quite as easily because that has changed, but a
lot of the general skills were the same.
So you'd be expected to know SQL and probably a procedural language.
You'd be expected to know one relational database management system.
You'd probably be expected to know how to do Unix, basic admin and shell scripting,
database performance tuning and disaster recovery, which was probably calling someone to bring
the tapes back on site.
So that's what a DBA was doing in 1998 and is doing today.
What will a DBA do in another 25 years' time?
Well I'm going to hedge that question for now.
So before we start looking at what a DBA might do in 25 years' time, everyone likes a bit
of buzzword bingo.
So I thought we'd have a look at the buzzwords, trends, hypes from the last few decades just
to give us an idea of what's changed around our vintage DBA and what's still changing.
So the 1990s.
The 90s brought us the World Wide Web, first with painfully slow dial-up access and finally
broadband internet, which meant that remote work was finally a possibility for some DBAs,
even if it was just to avoid having to trek into the office when doing 24-7 on call.
The concept of big data was introduced.
Data warehouses became popular and we needed massively parallel processing, MPP, to analyse
all of this data, so Teradata became popular.
Neteaser didn't come along until 2000s.
Scrum started to creep into our normal everyday work process.
Object-programming and from their object-oriented databases were the next big thing in programming
methodology.
Everybody was talking about AI and machine learning, even though they weren't new concepts,
with Deep Blue beating Grandmaster Kasparov at chess.
We were blessed with PostgreSQL and Linux.
SSDs started to replace spinning disk hard drives, but that's still a gradual ongoing
move.
And a lot of us missed out on New Year's celebrations because we were on call to make sure that
planes didn't fall out of the sky and fortunes weren't wiped out due to the Y2K bug.
The 2000s.
We were introduced to blockchain.
Cloud was and still is one of the biggest buzzwords with a move away from the traditional
data centre.
Everything started to be provided as a service.
We had software as a service and platform as a service.
We were all expected to be agile, to embrace DevOps methodologies and to implement continuous
integration and continuous deployment.
The Internet of Things and social media contributed to a massive growth in data volumes.
We got Hadoop, Exadata, NoSQL and JSON as new ways to store, process, analyse and describe
data.
Base was proposed as an alternative to ACID, favouring availability over consistency for
distributed systems.
Access to data on the move started to be possible with WiFi and containers were introduced,
although they weren't at this point quite ready for databases.
I'm going to take a deep breath and drink some water.
Okay, 2010s, infrastructure joined the as a service party.
NFTs, non-fungible tokens were introduced.
We started to store our data in data lakes which sometimes became data swamps.
Columna databases, even though they were actually a concept from the 1970s, became popular and
joined the other NoSQL databases.
We started to avoid putting all of our eggs in one basket with multi-cloud strategies.
Oracle announced their autonomous databases which meant there was not going to be any
need for DBAs any more.
Cloud Native was the next big thing with microservices, Docker and Kubernetes.
And the EU caused DBAs all across Europe, massive headaches by introducing the general
data protection regulations, GDPR.
The 2020s haven't all been a bed of roses in tech so far with a global pandemic and
massive layoffs.
On the other hand, remote work has started to become the norm for a lot of us.
Access to data on the move is getting faster with the introduction of 5G.
Zoom became a household name.
Everyone's now heard of Mastodon.
And apparently we're all going to be living in the metaverse and using chat GPT to write
all of our reports and presentations.
And that's just the first few years.
So who knows what's going to have happened by the end of the 2020s?
So we can look at a few ways that databases, I'm going to slow down a bit now.
We can look at a few ways that databases have changed in response to all of those things
that have been going on.
This is a massively simplified view of the history of database management systems.
Please don't quote me on this.
So in around 1980, the relational database pretty much started to replace the old navigational
databases.
And it's been going strong since then and still is.
In about 2000, various post-relational or NoSQL databases became popular and are still
popular.
And of course everything goes in cycles.
The NoSQL databases were around before the relational databases, just that they weren't
called NoSQL databases at that point.
It's easy to think that relational databases are going away when we hear about all the
different NoSQL databases there are and how popular they are.
This is a chart from dbengines.com from January this year.
And it shows that actually relational databases are more than twice as popular as all of the
different types of database management system put together.
And their figures also show that the popularity of relational database management systems
has stayed fairly static over the last ten years.
We've got more variety of databases.
So in the 90s there was a handful of database management systems.
And organizations would usually use one of those for all of their databases or maybe
two.
There are now over 400 different types of database management system.
Most organizations don't restrict themselves to just one or two of those.
So you'll get not just within one organization multiple database types but also within one
application.
So that means a DBA might be expected to know not just several relational database management
systems but also various different NoSQL types.
They might be expected to know about spatial databases, time series, graph databases or
document store.
Because I've got bigger.
So the terms big data and very large database were introduced in the 90s but they don't
actually tell us very much about the specific volume of data.
The definition in most places I found a very large database is a database that stores so
much data that its maintenance and architecture needs specialist tools and methodologies.
So it's basically just a database that's so big that we haven't yet figured out how to
manage it.
So in the 90s most people I spoke to seem to think that a multi gigabyte database was
fairly big.
These days people have multi terabyte databases and they're seen as fairly normal.
Once you start to get multi tens of terabytes you might start needing, might start to need
some specialist methodologies.
In 2018 IDC said that the global data sphere was predicted to grow to 175 zettabytes by
2025.
I haven't managed to find any later figures so I don't know if that's on course to still
be the case.
So the global data sphere is apparently all of the data that's created, captured and replicated
in core edge and end point locations.
And one zettabyte is a trillion gigabytes.
So for anyone like me who has difficulty visualizing 175 trillion gigabytes, apparently if you
burnt that onto CDs you'd have a stack of CDs that either took you to the moon 23 times
or around the earth 222 times.
So it doesn't look likely that there's going to be any shortage of data to manage any time
soon.
Databases have got more complex.
I suspect we've all seen an application architecture diagram that looks approximately like that.
We've got multiple database types not just as we said not just within one organization
but also often for a single application.
We've got multi cloud strategies.
We've got containerized databases.
We've got distributed systems.
And we've got many interrelated components.
So how has the DBA adapted in response to all of these changes?
The DBA has had to develop a cloud mindset.
I was really reluctant to embrace cloud.
I can't remember when I first heard the word but I thought it was just a hype that was
all going to blow over whether we like it or not cloud is here and it's growing so we
have to work with it.
So with the advent of cloud computing many DBAs are no longer actually responsible for
managing on premise databases.
The hardware and software is often managed by somebody else.
So the cloud DBA will need to have knowledge of probably multiple different cloud platforms.
And even organizations that keep their databases on premises are often moving to a cloud-like
architecture, a cloud-like model with self-service databases.
The DBAs had to learn to be flexible.
So as I've said they would be expected often to know multiple different types of database
not just relational but also no SQL.
They need to be able to work in lots of different database environments.
So the traditional operating systems but also cloud and things like Kubernetes.
They're expected to know how to use DevOps and automation tools and methodologies.
And they've got to keep up to date with all the changes in all of these different types
of tool and methodology.
The other side of the coin is that actually a lot of roles have been separated out into
different teams.
So you might now have different teams that are responsible for infrastructure, for data,
security and the application.
We already looked at the different types of DBA but actually there are a whole host of
different roles related to database and the data in it.
And this is just a few of the ones that I've seen by scanning job sites.
All of these changes mean that the DBA has to collaborate with other teams.
So not just with other database experts but also with teams that support the entire application
stack.
I often say to people that I've been forced out of my little database bubble.
And the DBAs have to develop a strategic focus.
So the DBA is more likely to be looking at the overall architecture of the database,
analytics and data processing, improving automated processes, collaborating with other teams
to make sure they've implemented business solutions rather than looking at the day-to-day
technical details of managing the database.
So as a reminder that change isn't all bad, I asked colleagues and contacts to tell me
some of the DBA tasks that they used to have to do that they are glad to be rid of.
And these are just a few of the answers.
Vacuum cron jobs, data file reorganizations, commuting to work.
That's a controversial one, some people probably do still have to do that.
Writing complicated backup scripts and installing post GIS via scripts rather than create extension.
So you've probably all got your own tasks that you are glad to be rid of.
So the million dollar question.
A variation of the question is the DBA role obviously is asked constantly all over the
Internet and of course database conferences and probably more so since Oracle announced
its autonomous database in 2017.
Is the DBA the clock winder of the future or the lamp lighter, the switch board operator,
the video rental clock or probably more likely the COBOL developer?
Because even if things change so much that modern databases don't require a DBA, how
many decades is it going to take before all databases are migrated over to this new DBA-less
technology?
Fortunately, data from the US Bureau of Labor Statistics says that there isn't a shortage
of DBA roles.
So we can see this goes from 2003, so 2003 is the first year in which those stats listed
database administrator as a separate role.
Before that I think it was computer scientists or I can't remember the exact role but there
wasn't a specific DBA role.
From 2020 it's listed as database administrators and architects so that supports what we saw
before about the two roles splitting out from the same thing.
So this is the total number of DBAs, thousands across the left there in the US.
So we can see that it's going up slightly.
It's not growing massively but it's definitely a slight upward trend.
And the Bureau actually projects a 9% growth from 2021 to 2031 which is higher than the
average of all other occupations.
So that's good.
I tried to find similar stats for the UK but unfortunately the lists of job roles are more
generic, they don't have database administrator listed.
So instead I've gone to IT Jobs Watch and I found the numbers of job adverts that have
DBA, for DBA or database administrator and those numbers are looking pretty healthy for
2022 and 2023.
Well how about automation?
Surely once everything is automated we don't need DBAs.
So one of my friends is a pilot and people like to ask him, well the plane just flies
itself doesn't it?
You just put it in autopilot, you don't really need to be there as a pilot.
And he says, well yeah, if everything is going well that's fine, you could just have someone
with a lot less experience sitting there watching the dials.
But as soon as something goes wrong, as soon as there's any kind of emergency situation,
you want someone there that knows what they're doing.
And okay, it's not usually such a life or death situation if a database has an emergency,
but you want someone on hand that knows what they're doing to fix that and get things up
and running again.
So you still need someone there to make the decisions.
And actually if each database takes less time to manage, that means that one DBA can manage
more databases.
Well we've seen how much more data there is and a similar number of DBAs, so that seems
to probably work well.
What about the junior DBAs?
I've not been able to find any figures, but I wonder whether there are fewer junior DBA
roles.
If automation's replacing a lot of the tasks, the day-to-day tasks that junior DBAs use
to do, do we still have roles for them?
And if that's the case, how can somebody become a senior DBA if they haven't been a junior
DBA?
Does that mean that the career path's changing?
And back to autonomous databases.
I mean if we believed the headlines when Oracle announced autonomous databases back in 2017,
DBAs were soon going to be a thing of the past, there was absolutely no need for them.
So even if all databases were moved over to autonomous databases, we've got the day-to-day
maintenance and patching is automated, but you still need somebody to design the databases,
to do the data modeling, to make sure that there's efficient code accessing the database.
And actually if you look at some of the reviews, these are just extracts from a couple of recent
ones, apparently it's an extremely complicated thing to put in place.
So you still need somebody who's an expert to be able to put that infrastructure in place
in the first place.
So fortunately the answer to all of that was no, the DBA role isn't obsolete.
So what conclusions can we draw from all of this?
The DBA role has changed since 1998 and it will continue to change in response to changes
in database technology and methodologies.
The DBA of 2023 has similar responsibilities to the DBA of 1998, but does them in a very
different way and so they're expected to be able to do very different things.
Relational databases are still going strong, they're still the majority and we're not
expecting them to go anywhere, but DBAs will be expected to know about other databases
as well.
The amount of data is growing exponentially but being managed by a similar number of DBAs,
so that suggests that we really do still need those DBAs.
And things are moving either to the cloud or to a cloud-like infrastructure on premises.
So the main thing for me is don't panic, as we've seen.
Quantity of data is growing, a lot of that data is going to be stored in databases and
that's going to have to be managed somehow.
Even if things are automated, you want someone on hand in an emergency, you want somebody
to design those databases, you want somebody to write and improve the automation code,
you want someone to fix the interesting queries that have been created by ORMs.
So it's a role that's evolving, like any other role in IT, like any other role anywhere else,
but it's not going away.
If you're happy to embrace automation and to try new things, you've got a long and happy
career in front of you as a DBA.
And even if you're a stick-in-the-mud old-fashioned DBA and you don't want to change, well, there
are going to be enough legacy systems to keep you in work for a long time to come so you'll
be fine until you retire.
That's all I've said.
I got through that faster than I expected, so I've got time for questions.
Hello.
Hi.
Just a note from my side, what I discovered is very interesting for me is the operator
concept in Kubernetes.
Instead of using a managed PostgreSQL database which is expensive, I just use an operator
and the operator itself, it doesn't just install a database automatically for me, it also does
piggy bounds and it does switching from left to right.
I think this will be the future.
So a lot of knowledge we have right now will be moved into operators more central and it
will be much better for us.
Yep, I agree.
If you're going to have a containerised environment, operators are definitely the way to go.
The problem that I've seen, and I guess because of the role I do, I see when there are problems,
is that people think, well, we've got an operator that does everything.
We don't need DBAs.
So you still need that DBA knowledge behind it, definitely.
So working in smaller companies, the DBA is basically if you're lucky, the DevOps team
and if you're unlucky, the developer team, which means a lot of people don't have the
knowledge or the interest or time.
And things are done in a sort of not proper way.
So as somebody who is interested but has a job as a developer, how can you foster that
environment where developers will start to understand if they're making inefficient queries
or if they're building the database wrong and get them to both know and be interested
and also get the company to kind of care about those things rather than keeping them until
it's an emergency, like you said, and the plane is crashing down.
That's a really good question.
So I wish I had all of the answers to that because I've been in lots of organizations
as a DBA or helping, and we've had exactly that situation.
So I would say one thing is make friends with, make sure that all teams are actually talking
to each other.
As a DBA, I was always kind of trying to integrate the other teams and actually be useful.
I mean, obviously, sometimes I was that typical GRUMB DBA.
No, you can't do that.
No, you can't have all these permissions.
I was enforcing rules, but I tried really hard to be there and helpful and show that
I could actually help to make this query run faster or help to make that better.
So I think that's, and I did training courses for developers as well to teach them about
the basics of databases.
So that's great because I found that most developers are really open to that because
they want to learn.
As far as people higher up in the organization go, I'm not sure.
I don't know what the answer is there, but probably just showing them how it benefits
the organization is the only way to go there.
Hello.
Thank you for your talk.
I feel completely, I agree completely with your talk.
I'm a DBA as well.
I have a couple of questions.
First thing is the role of the DBA is still an old male role.
So what can we do for making more attractive for the woman?
Because it's something very stressful.
Something that is very stressful.
Another thing.
Another million dollar question.
Something that is not changed yet is still old male.
And I don't think is a good idea to continue this way.
I know it's an horrible job, but how can we make more attractive?
And the other thing is a lot of companies, a lot of my customers struggle to find DBA.
How can they make more attractive for getting hired permanent DBA?
Because I give advice of hiring DBA because it's important to have in house, but they
struggle to find DBA.
Thank you.
Yeah.
So the first question, I wish I knew the answer to that.
I have no idea how to get more women into being DBAs.
That's something that's a problem across the whole of the IT community and something that's
not changed since I started 25 years ago.
The only things that I do is I go into part of an organization that does coding workshops
for girls to try and get people in early.
I mean, I was so lucky because my dad was a self-taught coder.
He loved IT.
He, like I say, he built me my first computer and showed me how to play with it.
That's what people need.
They need to see that it's fun.
I mean, well, we think it's fun.
I know it's not everybody's idea of fun.
I know.
My husband still doesn't understand.
And I say, no, I know, but it's my hobby as well.
So I think that's it.
It's just, and that's probably the same as that first question, is that we need to make
this look like fun to people.
And maybe we need to try and get rid of that image of the Grumpy DBA.
I don't know.
We need to clean up our ugly aspects.
Exactly.
More flashing badges.
Thank you.
Hello.
Thank you very much for the talk.
I wanted to ask you, I'm a data engineer myself.
Okay.
I'm a data engineer myself, and I feel that it's complicated to get across what we do
every day because we don't do any very visual things.
We're not web developers, so we can show really nice pages or nice graphics.
Do you have any advice to give for somebody who's in the field of databases and behind
the scenes to make their work more noticeable?
Yeah, that's a very good question.
So I don't know.
I mean, I suppose it depends which audience you're looking at.
Are you looking at kind of internally within an organization or outside to the general
public?
Yeah, I think some of it is showing the value that they bring.
The problem with a lot of things, like I can speak for being a DBA, is that when everything's
going right, you're not noticed.
Because what's the DBA doing?
We're not with nothing's going on.
We all need to start putting little things in the code to cause problems every so often.
So maybe just try and bring attention to the value that you bring.
Claire is probably a very good person to talk to later because I don't know if you saw Claire's
talk earlier about how to write things in blogs so that you get your point across clearly
and that kind of thing.
But Claire has some very good ideas on how to communicate.