So, hello everyone.
Thanks for your patience.
We're going to start with a slight delay, but I think it will be all right in the end.
Can I please welcome to the stage Andreas Scharbaum, who's going to talk about tour
the data types.
Okay, thank you.
Good morning.
I hope you had a good time yesterday in Borsets.
How was the restaurant?
Well, we got some food.
This is not switching.
So, I have the pleasure to talk to you today about data types in Postgres.
I actually have two talks about this.
This is a, I would say, basic talk about regular data types we have.
I also have an advanced data types talk, but let's focus on this one.
So, my name is Andreas.
I work with Postgres Science about 97, 98.
I'm one of the founding members of Postgres Europe.
V1 conferences like Post and PG Day on Friday here, Postgres Europe, which is in Prague
this year in December, Postgres comes Germany, Belgium, Postgres comes Malta in April, so
if you're interested in a couple more.
Currently, I work for a company called Adjust in Berlin.
We have about a thousand Postgres databases running everything from a couple gigabyte up
to like 30 terabytes in Postgres.
Okay, if you already know everything about data types in Postgres, if you're regularly
reading hackers' mailing list, this is maybe not the right talk for you.
I don't want to occupy your time, but otherwise, have a seat and we start.
So, quick poll, how many data types do we have in Postgres?
Any idea?
40?
Anyone else?
I see you're still sleeping.
And we talk about each and everyone today.
So, first of all, we have to exclude a number of data types because every time you create
a table in Postgres, you also create an according data type which matches the structure of the
table.
So, we don't want this.
If we look at regular data types, we have about 80 depending on which Postgres version
you are.
It's still more than you expected.
There's things like Boolean, you know this one, or text, or time stamps.
There's also things like trigger and void and cardinal number, which you never heard
about and you never need.
And we focus on mostly the ones I marked highlighted here.
At any time, you can also go and check the Postgres documentation on Postgres.org.
And it has a very long list of all the data types here in Postgres.
The basic ones, the advanced ones, all the ones I listed in the slides before, it's all there.
Okay.
How many different data types are you using in your application?
Sweet.
Which ones?
What about numbers?
So, every single is workshop.
Okay.
Anyone else?
I'm a doctor.
I mean, yeah, it fits you.
Okay.
No, that's too much.
Better?
Good.
We are going over this basic type, so numeric, so when you come back, you can rewrite your
application and finally you start using numbers.
Text types, maybe XML if anyone of you is still using it, JSON, Booleans, and a couple
more.
So, text types.
We basically have one text type in Postgres under the hood.
It's all the same.
So, we have watcher and char and text.
Text types in Postgres by default are case sensitive.
So, if you want to compare two texts, it's always case sensitive.
If you want to compare it case insensitive, you have to use something like lower or higher
to make a string uppercase or lowercase.
A string can Postgres and hold up to a gigabyte of text, roughly.
It cannot hold binary data.
So, if you want to store images in text, that's not going to work.
If you specify a length, like this larger n here, this is where Postgres stores up to
these number of bytes or characters in a text data type, excluding white spaces at the end.
A char by default is only one byte.
That's most likely not what you want.
So, for char, you always want to specify a length.
And then, of course, if you say text, it's just the text you cannot specify your length
here.
Hi, everyone.
How does char and watcher differentiate?
Mostly how they handle white spaces.
So, we have a watcher 1 and 5 here and 10 here, and I cast five white spaces to both
watcher 1, 5 and 10 and char 1, 5 and 10.
And as you can see, we get different lengths here.
So, our five white spaces here, if we cast them to watcher 10, we only get five at the
end because we only have five white spaces in it.
What char is doing, char will fill up the entire string to the lengths we specified.
If you say char 10, we get a string back with 10 characters in it.
That's mostly the difference for char and watcher.
How it's saying that if you specify your lengths in char, it will actually give you that many
bytes back, including white spaces.
If you use a watcher, it will only give you the string back, excluding white spaces at
the end.
So, it will cut off white spaces.
We have a sink in process which is called a page.
By default, it's 8 kilobyte.
That's where we store all the data in it.
So, we have one page header.
Then we store rows in it, and a row can be anything from just one column up to 1,000,
1,500 columns.
As I said, by default, it's 8 kilobyte.
You can increase it, but almost no one is doing this.
How does Postgres store a text?
A text can be up to one gigabyte.
So, we cannot store one gigabyte in 8 kilobyte.
I mean, you can if you compress, but usually it doesn't work.
Any data type in Postgres which has a variable length is only a pointer into what we call
a toast table.
Sorry.
So, in our regular table, we have a 4-byte pointer, which is a pointer into the toast
table.
And in the toast table, we have as many rows as we need just towards this gigabyte of text.
So, it's 4 bytes here, and as many rows as we need here.
Which brings me to my one question.
Why are so many people using char 255?
Just two weeks ago, I've seen a customer who does this all over the place, street names,
customer names, everything is char 255.
Does it make any sense?
Well, there are certain databases where this might make sense, but it doesn't make any
sense in Postgres.
When Postgres doesn't make a difference if you use 10 bytes, 200 bytes, 1 kilobyte, you
always end up, almost always end up with a text pointer into your toast table.
There are other databases that make sense, like if you look at one of the competition
in the market, they can only have 255 bytes in an index, or just 255 characters if you
use UTF-8 up to 700 something bytes.
That's what they can use in the index zone.
That might make sense to use 255 as a char.
But every time you see this construct in Postgres where someone says, char 255, go and question
why is the reasoning behind this?
Why did someone say 255?
Not 200, not 1 kilobyte.
Technically it doesn't make sense.
Numeric ties.
Pay attention, please.
So we have integers.
We have floating point numbers.
We have numeric, and we have sequences.
Integers, we have small int storing 2 bytes.
We have integers, regular integers by default, it's 4 bytes.
So anything from minus 2 billion to plus 2 billion.
And then we have big int using 8 bytes.
This is 9.
No idea how much this is.
You might get some small problems if you store something, okay, small int integer, small
int integer, because the compiler will actually go and say, okay, we need to have some space
because we need to align the next integer on a 32-bit boundary or 64-bit boundary depending
on your operating system.
So what you really want to do is have all of your big data types in first in your table.
There was things which is like text and big int, and then start with your regular 4-byte
types and then 2-byte types at the end so you can compress the table a little bit more.
It doesn't really bring you much if you only have a small table, a couple million rows.
But if you're talking about billion rows, it's actually quite a big saving you get if
you can compress and save like 2 bytes, 4 bytes per row.
Then we have floating point numbers as wheel and as double precision with 4 and 8 bytes.
Keep in mind a floating point number, even though post was my choice, accurate number
you have, is always rounded internally.
It's always a base and an exponent.
I want to give you an example here.
We have 6 digits here, 100,001, and you see if I return this, Postgres still shows me
the 100,001, even though internally it's already rounded.
If I expand this to 7 digits, you see I get a rounded number here.
The 4 bytes can no longer store the precision required to store this 1 at the end.
So you only get 1 million here.
The same is true if I have my 100,001.5 as a 4 byte floating point number, Postgres starts
rounding it internally.
So if you want to store anything like money or data where you really need precision, please
do not use floating point numbers.
But same example for floating point with double positions of 8 bytes.
If I have 15 digits here, it still looks okay, but once you start expanding the number a
little bit or add DCMA digits here, you see it starts rounding the number.
So if you really want to store floating point numbers, but you cannot use integers, what
else can we use?
Ah, this one comes later.
We can use numeric.
There's data type code numeric, which stores up to 1,000 digits of precision in Postgres
square.
Basically any number you need to store, you can store in numeric.
Keep in mind there's no real headdress support.
If you add two integers, in the end, the CPU will load one integer into one register and
the other integer into another register and just use one operation internally.
Everything is fast.
That's not how it works with numeric.
So it will be a little bit slower.
Not much, but if you have to use it all the time, you might see it.
There's also a type called money in Postgres.
Don't use it.
Never.
Internally it's a big int, so we have the same position here, eight bytes.
However, you only have one currency.
Whatever you assign as LC monetary in your environment, this is the currency Postgres
is using to show you this number.
You cannot say I want to store two currencies in my database.
You cannot store like an exchange rate.
All of this is not working.
Money was deprecated I think two times, three times, something like this.
There's always one user who comes back, oh, I really need it.
It's still around, but please don't use it.
Is anyone from India here?
Ever met him?
You know the name?
Would be surprised if you know the name.
Anyone knows this game?
Okay.
How many, the story is that he did something for his king and the king asked, okay, what
can I give you in return?
And he said, okay, give me some waste wings.
One on the first chest feed and a doubly number.
How many waste wings are we talking about?
Yeah, it's hidden.
So we can actually use numeric for this.
So it's two to the power of 64 minus one.
So we have 64 fields.
We start with one, so it's minus one.
If we use floating point for this double position here, you see we don't get an exact number.
It's way too big for floating point.
If we use numeric, it's just 20 digits.
We have 980 left.
We can store much more in numeric than just this number.
I did a mess at some point, and it's like 1,000 times the speed we are currently using
or producing on Earth per year.
So 1,000 years of waste production on Earth will happen to solve this problem.
Okay, we also have sequences in Postgres.
Internally these are just integers which are used as a default type in a table.
We have small serial which gives you two bytes, 32K plus minus.
Then we have regular serial data type which is four bytes from zero to or from one to
two billion, and then we have big end for everything which needs larger numbers.
If you create a data type or a table with a data type serial, what Postgres will do
internally, it will create this data type in a table.
If you look into the table, it's actually an integer in four and eight.
It will create a sequence for you, and it will make this sequence a default value for
this color.
So every time you insert something into this table and you don't specify this color, Postgres
will use the next value from a sequence.
If you specify something for this color, it will not use the sequence.
So if this is your primary key and you're mixing values you are inserting and values
from a sequence, at some point you will have collisions.
Please don't do this.
Also sequences are not transactional.
If you roll back a transaction, a sequence will not roll back.
Sequences just mean to provide you a unique number.
That's all.
So we can ask the current value of a sequence, select current or my sequence name here.
This will only work if you already used the sequence in a current session, like you did
an insert into a table.
This will tell you what is the last value this current session I have inserted into
this table.
So if you have five different sessions inserting data, it will always show you what you, the
current session inserted.
You can also ask for the next value by using next wall.
Keep in mind it will not roll back if you roll back the transaction.
It will only ever move forward.
You can also set a sequence by just saying set wall and then specify your key, what is
my new value I want to have.
If you do this on a table, where you use the sequence on a table as primary key and you
reset it to a previous value, you may run into collisions again because it will reuse
the same values again.
Okay.
A sequence internally in Postgres is just another object, another table.
So what you can say, select star for my sequence.
It will show you all the data about a sequence.
So what's the sequence name?
What's the last value we used here?
What's the minimum maximum value with the sequence cycle around so when it comes to
an end, will it start again?
Will it wrap over or not?
So by default it will not wrap over because otherwise you will end up with the same numbers
again.
Just another object.
Good.
Any questions about numeric types?
What is this?
Come again.
South pole.
South pole sounds good.
How did you figure it out?
That's one way.
Yeah, it tells you here 90 degree south latitude.
This is south pole.
What time is it there right now?
That's one valid answer all the times.
Let's see if we can answer this question.
So we have a couple of date and time types in Postgres.
So we have time stamp without time zone and time stamp with time zone.
Depending on your use case, make a good choice which one you use.
Any time you just want to store a time, date and a time, you want to use a time stamp without
time zone.
If you work with multiple time zones, we really use with time zone.
Internally Postgres will store the time as UTC time, but it will make sure to handle
the transformation for you.
We will see a couple examples.
We also have time without time zone and time with time zone.
And we have date and interval.
Postgres will not know about any kind of leap seconds.
So occasionally we have a year which is a second longer with the leap seconds.
I think they are planning one because earth is going slower so we use it.
I don't know how this will go.
But anyway, Postgres doesn't know about leap seconds because the time zone database doesn't
know about it.
So we have something which looks like a date.
I cast it to a time stamp.
And we see that Postgres makes it this date midnight.
So if you don't specify your time, it's always midnight.
We can also say, okay, January 5th, that's a format Americans using months first.
We also see it's midnight here.
We can also specify a time zone.
So I have here 325 afternoon in UTC time zone.
I cast this to a time stamp.
What does it say?
525.
Any idea?
Postgres will always return times in my current time zone which is set on my system.
So many companies use servers which are set to UTC.
My laptop which I use for this example is set to Berlin time which in summer is two
hours before UTC.
So we see I specify a time zone as UTC here.
And in August I get 525 back.
So it transforms the time I specify to my local time.
Same in winter.
This is December here.
1023 UTC.
I get 1123 back as my time.
This can be very convenient but also very inconvenient depending on what you're working
on.
We can also say any time zone as any time zone your computer knows about.
So we have a time zone database in computers.
And we can use any name from there to specify as a time zone.
We can also say just plus or minus the number for the time zone.
Obviously if you specify a time zone as a name Postgres knows about summertime.
If you just say plus four it never knows about summertime because you just say plus four.
The example I'm using here is because at some point Russia just said okay we are no longer
doing this dance with winter and summertime.
They just stopped at some point and said okay year round it's one time zone.
In Postgres time is stopped if you start a transaction.
So we start a transaction here.
If you say select now multiple times you always get the same time back.
That's the transaction time.
So I'm using this here.
Now I'm setting my time zone to Europe Moscow.
What changed?
My output changed.
This one is my brilliant time.
This one is my Moscow time.
Two time zones difference.
What I can also say any time stamp I have in Postgres at a specific time zone.
So previously everything here was always returned in my own time zone which is set on my computer.
I could say change everything to this specific time zone or I can just say format one specific
time stamp I have at a given time zone.
Then of course you can say okay select now at Berlin comma now at New York comma now
at Buenos Aires in one single query.
So we can return as many time zones or time stamps you have at as many different time
zones you have.
A couple more examples.
So Postgres does not know about leap seconds but it knows about leap years.
So we have two thousand fifths of January minus two thousand first of January.
This is four days difference.
It's an interval now of four days.
We have two thousand first of January minus fourth of January.
It's minus three days.
We get an interval back.
So if we have time stamps Postgres will do all the calculation for us between the two
time stamps including years dates including leap dates everything.
And we can use this to figure out of a specific year is a leap year.
Two thousand twenty eight of February plus one day interval gives me two thousand twenty
ninth of February.
Of course if I do this in 2001 I only get three hundred sixty five days back.
In 2000 I get two hundred sixty six days back.
It's a leap year.
Makes all of this into account.
Which brings me back to my initial question.
What time is it at South Pole?
This station at South Pole is operated by the Americans.
It's called Scott Amundsen station which is however supplied from New Zealand.
That's the closest airport they have for all the planes they're operating.
And by now we know how to figure out the time in New Zealand right.
Right now at time zone in New Zealand.
That would be cheating because your operating system actually knows about Antarctica.
So every station which humans have on Antarctica got its own time zone which is usually aligned
to the country operating the station.
Because this one is well operated by Americans but supplied from New Zealand conveniently
they're using the same time zone as New Zealand.
Select now at time zone and Antarctica South Pole gives you the time at the South Pole.
Anyone here using XML?
Fine.
Let's.
What's your use case?
Some data feeds.
Where there are some basic support in Postgres for XML.
You can set encoding.
You cannot search directly in XML.
So Postgres stores the XML as it is but you cannot really search in it.
There's no support for this.
What you could do is cast it to text and then try to make some sense out of it.
But that's about it.
We have two different types.
We can say it's a document type here.
So I specify a text and I tell Postgres, okay, pass this as a document in XML.
It will fail if it's not proper XML.
And tell me, okay, this doesn't work.
So I get back an XML document here with all the formatting and the entire tree.
I can also say I don't want to have an entire document.
I just want to have a piece of XML content that's working with XML paths and content.
But then again, I cannot search in it.
There's no support for it.
I can serialize this and unserialize this if you want to store some larger XML documents
in Postgres.
That's working.
So this one is a text now.
No longer an XML document.
So if you really want to search in something and say, okay, does this specific text appear
in my XML document, go and serialize it and then maybe apply some like or wakeups on it.
But then again, if you search for name, you will find plenty of this.
Reality is if you want to store something like XML, go for JSON.
We have two different JSON data types in Postgres.
One is the older one is called JSON.
JSON as it is stores the data as it comes in.
So it basically takes the entire JSON blob, stores it as it is.
And then later on, if you work on the data type, then it does all the parsing.
So at insertion time, it doesn't really know if your JSON object is valid or not.
It only figures out when you try to operate on it.
And then at some point, there came a better JSON type.
It's called JSONB.
I think one of the big mistakes this project made was not to duplicate JSON and say, okay,
the new one is the JSON type.
So I called it JSONB and now we have to live with it.
The new one is better in almost every way.
So it does parse the JSON when you insert into the database, when you create this type.
You can create an index on it.
It already tells you on creation time if it's valid or not.
And then you have a decomposed object, a JSON object in your database, which you can work
on.
All of this is using regular transactions, like some other databases using JSON.
You don't get JSON support on this.
And Postgres, it's one more data type we use supporting transactions, everything supporting
replication.
How do we use this?
This is a regular text here.
I need to quote my text in JSON with a double quote to make it a JSON text.
Then I have my single quotes for Postgres telling it this is a string.
And I cast this string to JSON and I get my JSON text back.
We can use arrays and lists and hashes in JSON.
So here we have an array.
As you can see, we have several text types, JSON text types in the array.
Then we create this array.
And we make this a Postgres string.
It's a JSON type and we see, okay, I still have my JSON text types here.
My JSON array.
And for Postgres, all of this, one string passed as a JSON type.
The same works with key value pairs.
So we have key and value here as JSON, make it a hash, and then make it a string in Postgres,
cast this string to JSONP.
Of course, since we passed the JSON, I already Postgres knows what's in there.
So we can say, okay, I only want to have this key number two.
Here my text is D, E, F.
I can access whatever is in my JSON value.
I can ask if the white element is in the list on the left.
GHA is actually in there.
So I get a tool back.
It's a yes, no question in Postgres.
Same for the keys.
So here's the value.
Is this value in this list?
Is this key in this list?
So any of the questions you usually have from an application using JSON, like, is a specific
value there?
Does a specific field exist?
All of this you can answer directly in Postgres.
You don't have to extract the entire data type, transfer it into your application, and
then try to make sense of it.
All of this can be answered directly in Postgres in one query.
On top of it, because Postgres already knows what is in the JSON, we can have an index
support on this.
This only works on JSON B, by the way, not on the old JSON type.
So what I'm doing here is I have an index.
On my table, I have to use the GIN type.
And I only create this index on one specific field in my JSON object.
This is not indexing the entire JSON field.
It's just one field in my object here, the name field.
And then I can use this index to answer queries.
So if you have this typical web application, we are storing 20, 50, 100 JSON values in
one object, you don't want to index all of them.
You maybe just want to have an index on one or two of the fields.
This is possible in Postgres.
Booleans.
We have a real Boolean type in Postgres.
So we can say two faults.
We have a couple of alternatives you can specify.
So for two, you can say it's one or two or yes.
For faults, you can say it's faults or no or n.
Can you please be a little bit silent back then?
In the end, what Postgres does, it transforms all of these values into the two or fours
value for the Boolean.
We have a couple of other databases in the market which say, yeah, we have a Boolean.
Under the root, it's maybe just an integer.
Then you can insert not only zero and one but also five, eight, 50 and then try to make
sense out of this.
Here we only get two and fours back.
So two, cast as a Boolean, we see it's getting two.
And fours, we get an F back.
And we can use this in queries.
So I have one table here.
Let's say that's a table where you store log file messages.
And yeah, we have some content here.
And we have one field which tells me, okay, this log entry is an error.
Usually we don't have a lot of errors.
But this is an entry in our table that we are mostly interested in.
So maybe one, 2% of the queries of the entries in this table will have this flag set.
What I'm doing here, I create a million rows and about 2% of them have this flag set just
to have some basic test data here.
And when I go and say, okay, I only want to see all the entries in my table where the
error is true, because that's what I'm interested in, you see by default, process has to scan
the entire table.
It's quite expensive.
What I can say, I create an index and make this a conditional index.
And only every row where error is true goes into this index.
So the 98% of the table where there is no error I'm not interested in, because the
cardinality is not high enough.
I will never see this data in my index.
Only the 2% here go into my index and now suddenly the cost of the query came down from
16,000 something to 68.
Very fast now.
There's one use case for Boolean index.
So for the cost of this, I have another index now on the entire column and you can see the
entire index needs 2,700 pages and my Boolean index only needs 57 pages on this.
So much, much faster.
We have a bit type in Postgres, so not only Boolean, we can also say we want to store
bits.
Or you can specify how many bits you want to have.
The interesting part is you can tell Postgres by using the B in front.
This is binary value and it does all the transformation for you.
From this which looks like a string with bits in it to sorry.
Postgres will do the transformation of the bits for us.
So we don't have to do the middle calculation which bit is which value.
We can also do bit operations on these values.
So I have some data in my table and I want to only select where this bit is set.
Or specify that's a binary value here, a bit value here.
And that's a logical end for a logical OR.
And then of course because OR gives me any value which the bit is set on the left or
the right side, I get everything back here.
We can have exclusive OR on bits.
We can also do mathematical operations on bits like shifting left and right for multiplied
by two or divided by two.
All of this works.
We can also search in bits.
It looks a bit complicated because we need to make this a logical operation.
So I want to search everything where this bit is set and because it gives me a value
back I need to say okay this is greater now than I get to result.
If I search for everything where the second bit from the right is set, there is no value
in it so I don't get anything back from my database.
I can cast bits to any value.
Like that's an integer.
I can cast it to bits and get my bit value back any other way around.
I can cast from bits to integers to any other value.
Good.
Anyone of you storing binary data in a database?
Good for you.
We have a byte A type which can do this.
All I want to say about this is please use the functions of your programming language
to transfer the data in and out of the database.
Please don't write your own code to try and transform this data.
Every language we have which supports Postgres has functions for transferring binary data
in and out of the database.
We have two different formats.
One is called the old escape format which is hard to pass.
And the new one is the hex format so this will always store hex values for binary data
in a database.
We also have network types in Postgres.
So E-Net can store any IPv4 or IPv6 address.
The network type CDIR can store the networks.
And we can store mega address in Postgres.
So any time you work with network addresses, please don't store them as a text.
Use the proper data type for it because you can go and have an index on it or you can
go and ask Postgres is this IP address in this network?
I created a table with a couple of IP addresses in here.
And then I can ask Postgres give me every IP address which is in this network.
So you don't have to do all the manual handling of IP addresses in text matching and whatever
people do to find IP addresses.
And on top of that, it supports an index.
It gets very, very fast.
Any kind of address and IP address parsing can be very fast in Postgres.
I'm almost running out of time because we started late.
You can create your own data types in Postgres.
So we have enums and a couple more.
We have Postgres as extension.
This is part of another talk I have.
Not here, not today.
So I keep this part.
Any questions you have?
Jimmy, do we have any questions?
During the part about the timestamp or timestamp C data type, you said that the database handles
the conversion from UTC type.
Does it store the UTC type and also the offset in time zone or does it always convert to
the current time zone of the database, I guess?
Whatever you insert into the data type and you don't specify a time zone, it will assume
your local time zone.
If you specify a time zone and use this time zone, it always converts it to UTC internally.
When you select it, it returns in your time zone you specify.
Thank you.
Nice talk.
So, different type, particularly since interesting, what do you say, like, can I use Postgres for
my non-intellectual use purposes or something like MongoDB?
I think you're in a wrong room.
The answer is yes.
Almost everything you can use MongoDB for, you can also do in Postgres.
Hi.
Is there ever any hope of getting an unsigned integer type in PostgresQL?
I think there's an extension which can do that, but it's not there by default.
If you check the Postgres extension network, PGXN, there are a couple more data types you
can use for this.
I didn't get it quite right.
You recommended JSONB data type over JSON.
Yes.
Okay.
I got it.
Basically, everything you can do in JSON, you can also do in JSONB, but it gives you
more functionality in JSONB.
It usually is, yes.
Okay.
Thanks, Jimmy.