We are starting. Please be quiet. Couple of things. First of all, welcome. Here I am to
introduce our next speaker, Pablo in our PostgreSQL Dev Room, who's going to talk about Go. Just
a few practical things. When you exit, please exit from the back. And if you want to go
out in between the talk, please be quiet. Because this Dev Room is very loud and these chairs are
very freaky. So yes. That being said, enjoy. Hello people. How are you today? It was yesterday fun.
Um, because first two talks were not really crowded. But mine is good already. Yeah. My
name is Pablo Golop. I'm working for CyberTech. So I'm a senior consultant in the body of a young
developer. So today, a couple of words about my company. CyberTech is purely PostgreSQL company.
We work with clients only if they have PostgreSQL. If they don't, we install it. And they can work
with us from that point. We are having several branches all over, not all over, but the world,
some of them in South America, most of them are in Europe. Not now.
I wanted to restart. So some of our customers, so choose your fighter. Some of our products.
So we are not only consulting people, but we do products. Yeah. Why PostgreSQL? You know why.
It's cool. Absolutely. So what I'm, what will be, I'm talking about today. So first of all,
I want to introduce you to the Go language. How many of you have an idea what the Go language is?
Okay. So I don't need like start from the beginning explaining what the compiler is,
and etc. So yeah. Okay. Then I will say a couple of words about IDEs and editors we are using.
Then I will describe drivers for PostgreSQL specifically. Some useful extensions.
How we do testing, how we do releases, how we do continuous integration, development, etc. And then
probably I hope we'll have a question session. Okay. So why Go? First of all, when I start my
first project, I like that Go produces the native one binary for every platform. I said, wow.
Wow. I just can build everything from the same command line for every previous system and
architecture I want to. And I don't need virtual machines and other crap. Just like Go.
It's simple enough. It has a good community. It now has already very comprehensive tools
and support by GitHub, et cetera, et cetera. Yeah. So cross-platform is somehow connected
with the native binaries for every architecture. So this is the last developer survey for Go
asking how people are using Go language for what kind of. So speaking about Postgres,
I would say the data processing is somehow connected. Before that, we had like these answers
where you can see that databases is like half of the projects people were using. Probably you know,
if not, so the top products written Go are Kubernetes and Docker, OpenShift, then
Hugo, the fastest framework for building statistical sites, etc., etc. Postgres-related
Go products which are written in Go are the CockroachDB, both Postgres operators from
Zalando and from Crunchy, WallG, PgCenter, PgWatch, PgTimeTable, so on and so on. So if you
want to find more projects, more applications written in Go, please go to this site, to this repo.
There are a lot of them. A lot of them. Yeah. Okay. So what about tooling?
Because when I was starting, I used Sublime Text. There was no proper IDE to work with,
no debugger, no these kind of things. Right now, according to the last year developer survey,
the most used IDE is VS Code, then Goland by JetBrains, and then Vimeo Veeam and Sublime Text is 1%.
I was saying at the conference that I will try Goland and will tell you about how it is different
from VS Code. No. Still didn't try it. But I think it's good. So these are the answers
from the previous years. So as you can see, the intention is the same. So VS Code and Top
and Google Language, etc., etc. Goland. Sorry. What I'm using, I'm using VS Code with the official
plugin installed. Then I'm using the T-parse, command line utility to make these fancy tables
out of test output. Linter, of course. Tip 9. I tried GitLab CoPilot. It's not bad. But I don't
want to spend my money on this. I have my own head. Go release to produce the packages and
binaries like in one go. Then PostgresQL, of course. And the last, but at least the Gitpod I.O.,
which is pretty much the same thing as a GitHub workspace. But it's free for open source developers.
So it's good if you want to try something new and you don't want to install everything on your
machine or to set up the virtual machine. You can go there, run it in your browser, drink
and beer on the beach and try something new. It's okay. If you're done, you just close your browser,
close your top and it's gone. Now, about drivers, about the PostgresQL part of the
stock. The whole idea of the stock started after I tried to find good tutorials about how to start
to work with PostgresQL. A lot of them, not all of them, but a lot of them say, okay,
just use ORM and you're fine. Well, why? If I need to like to create utility to use like three
commands, right? Why should I use like ORM? And yeah, don't get me wrong. ORMs are fine if you
know what you are doing. They solve the problems, but you don't need to put it everywhere.
And you don't need to start from it. Because otherwise you will be learning ORM,
but not learning PostgresQL itself, right? Yeah. We have SQL for that.
So, during this talk, I will not be explaining ORMs and how to work with that. I will explain
the basic drivers. Anyway, ORMs are using drivers on the low level to speak to the PostgresQL,
right? So, we should know how to use them. So, the thing is in Go that we have these databases
QL interfaces, interfaces is just like an agreement on what methods are available from,
I don't know, from object, from structure, whatever. And for each database, there should be
a special driver, an implementation for these interface, right? So, the first official
implementation for the PostgresQL in the Go world was libpq. It's good. It's proven. It's
a long time on the market, but it is in maintenance mode right now for two years probably. It's not
bad. It's okay. You can be sure that this functionality is solid. But if you want more,
and if you start a new project, jackcpgx is the way to go. Because
you can use it with whatever you want. I will show you later.
So, yeah, we are scientists and we do graphs. So, unlike of Python or not Python, but
the NPM, JavaScript work, we don't have this statistic for how many times a particular
package was downloaded, used, whatever. So, the most funny way is to use GitHub stars
and, yeah, to build this stuff. So, as you can see, the pjx is one year,
started one year later, but now it's going to be very popular. So, in 2019-20, there was an
announcement that the libpq is going to maintain small and the pjx started to grow.
So, what if you are, if your project is using already databasesql or you want to follow
tutorials or techniques and to use this databaseql standard de facto interfaces? For that purpose,
pjx has a special wrapper. So, you can still use databaseql interface,
but you can underneath on the low level, you will use the pjx package.
So, you should use pjx solely if you are starting a new project or your project is
aiming only post-baseql, right? Then you don't need databaseql, but if you are dependent on
orm or you are dependent on other package which want you to use databaseql, right? You go for
wrapper. In that case, the dependency will use this wrapper to speak to databaseql and you will
use the power of pjx. So, there are a lot of unique features that are not present, not implemented
in the standard library and they cannot be implemented because this interface is
common, it is the same for every possible database. So, for example, you cannot add
methods with a copy support because only post-baseql do copy support, right?
So, the most cool feature is that pjx supports binary transport protocol and it supports
natively all built-in Postgres types. And if you create user types, it will support them out of the
box unless they are very complicated. But even in that case, you can create a special interface or a
special object structure that will tell pjx how to encode, decode the values of your types.
So, as I said, yeah, copy protocol, logging, yeah, and for connection pooling, you have this
afterconnect hook. So, the idea in your language is that the database object that you have is
pool by default. So, it can create additional connections and you never know how many active,
well, you can know, but you can never tell how many connections you have right now. And this,
for example, afterconnect hook helps you to prepare your session, prepare your new open
connection for something, like add some identifier, log in or whatever.
Yeah, listen notify is implemented natively. What else? Yeah, different JSON,
HStore, large objects. So, everything you need is already there.
Nice thing about pjx is in December probably the new major version 5 release was, and it was a
huge step forward, especially in the term of dependencies. V4, version 4 was good, but it has
so many external dependencies that, for example, it's not the thing anymore, and it's very cool.
So, yeah, hello world. You probably all know how to write it in the database SQL.
With the interface, so you're just using that import package. But instead of using
libq, you are specifying pjx as the lead, which is the wrapper for the standard library.
And then all things are the same. No difference. No difference. So, if you want to update your
project, you just change the import part, the import of libq to the pjx standard lib and you are fine.
If you want to use pjx directly, you are fine to do that. The thing is here that
the pjx return the one connection only. So, if you don't need a pool of connections or if you want
to be sure that only one connection is live, one connection is used, you are going with pjx connect.
But please remember that you cannot use this structure, this connection, in parallel. So,
you need to know that at one point in time only one thread or one go routine can talk to the database.
Otherwise, you're good. But if you want a pool of connections, you are going with pjx pool.
And I don't know, what can I add here? It's obvious. It's pooling. You can pass it to the
go routines and it will create additional connections as you go and you can limit
upper number of connections, et cetera, et cetera. It's very flexible. Okay. About useful extensions.
For my first project, I started with the libq as well. It's way to go. That's how we grow.
And later, I understand that I want this copy functionality badly. I need that.
So, I started to look at the pjx, how to switch it. And I didn't want to lose this SQL things
because when you're encoding, decoding your structures, slices, arrays, whatever, write
from rows or two rows, right? That's what most people think the ORM do. It just translates the
rows into the structures. But, yeah, it's very useful. So, like, if you are working with the
old database SQL or libq, you are importing this SQL thing and you can have a lot of new methods
like you can struct the row into the structure or you can scan the color into the variable or you can
create a slice from your rows, et cetera, et cetera. It's very cool. Pjx at that time
provided that. But with the latest version 5, everything is already there. Better is included.
Probably you can find cases where you want more control over decoding and coding.
But after this guy was introduced, wrote to struct by name, written by me, by the way.
Yeah. Everything became very easy. So, before that, we had only row to struct by position.
So, if your structure fields are in the same position as your field in your row,
result set, you're fine. You're just, like, doing the back and forth. But if you want to skip some
fields or, for example, if you have some nonpublic fields in the structure but still want to use this
functionality to decode and code from the result set, this is the way to go.
Yeah. Now about testing.
We all know it's very essential, right? And I heard a lot this statement that you need to write
your tests first and only then implementation. I never did. Maybe one of us tried it. Oh, go.
Go. I'm too lazy. Because I never know where at the end I will go with my code. I'm starting,
like, okay, I will implement this thing that will return this integer. And then, oh, no, let's do
this. CTE with a lot of things. Yeah. And if I write a test before, I need to follow it.
Right? No, it's not funny. How we do testing? So, I would say there are three main approaches.
The first one, obviously, is to start a real PostgreSQL server. You can have your local
installation on the test environment or you can download it during the test running, install it,
initialize, et cetera, then cache. But it's still the same. It's a real PostgreSQL server.
The second approach would be mocking libraries for database SQL that would be Datadog, go SQL mock.
And for PgX, I created this PgX mock, which is the brother of the SQL mock, but, yeah, works with PgX.
I hope you know what is mocking and how these things are working, right? So, yeah.
We are pretending that we are a PostgreSQL server and our application, our tests,
are thinking that they are speaking to the real server. But, in fact,
we just throw the needed answers to the application. So, the rows, okay, this is row,
this is row, this is the answer. Oh, no, that was a row. Let's see how you will react with that,
et cetera, et cetera. But if you want to test on the protocol level, there is also some
very low libraries, like PgMock, which is just the real low-level mocking protocol.
CockroachDB has its own test server, which is just like an import CockroachDB test server and
use it in your test. And another library is copyist. Okay. Let's try to maybe...
It's not very useful.
No, let's get back...
Okay, so how to create a test, how to use this PgMock thing. So, if you read the readme on the
repository, you will see that no change is required to your application. That's a lie.
Okay. You need to provide an interface because the PgX return structures is a connection or a pool.
We cannot mock structures. We can mock interfaces. So, I'm defining PgXe interface here and say to my
method, to my function, that I will use this interface. Please use that. And for my function,
it doesn't care, would it be a real connection or would it be mocking or anything. It just knows
that this object has this method and it's enough for that. Okay. So, yeah, we write a code kind of
shitty. We're trying to come in, we're trying to roll back, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera, how to
test it. So, I will start with the successful test cases. I'm a very positive person.
So, first thing first, though, I'm creating the mocking object. PgX, mock, new pool.
Then I will tell my mocking object how should my session looks like, right? So, I'm saying I'm
expecting that we will start a transaction. I'm expecting the game. Then I'm expecting that the
code will try to execute update statement, right? And when this happens, please return to this code
the new result that update was successful and we updated one row, right? After that, I expect
that the code will try to insert something and I expect that the arguments for this statement
would be two and three. If that is the case, please tell that everything is good. We insert one row
and after all that, I expect that the code will commit the transaction, right? That is what I'm
expecting from the code. Then I'm calling my function record starts and instead of the
PgX, I'm passing the mocking object, mock, and two and three arguments, right? And if anything goes
wrong, the test cases fail, right? But another thing I want to check, if every expectation I
set were met. For example, after the commit, my code might want to write a log to the database
or do other things. I don't expect that thing from it and these expectations were met will fail
if something else is happening inside this function which is not being expected,
right? So for fail, for failure is pretty much the same. We are telling that we wait, we expect to
start transaction, we expect to start update statement, but let's pretend we want to test
how our code will behave if the insert statement will fail. So we are telling, so when insert
statement is coming with the arguments two and three, let's pretend that error happened. Return
error to our code and the error with some error text, but very beautiful. We are starting our
function, but in that case, we know that it should fail. That's why we are checking our error to be
not nil. We are waiting error, right? And the same for expectations were met. So for example,
if we failed and our code tries to do more than we are expecting, we say, no, please don't.
Please don't. Yeah. So and then you are just using go test and with the tip parts,
thingy, I just love how the tables look after this output. So like for this case, we have like one
package and we have two test cases, right? But in real application, you might have hundreds,
hundreds of test cases and dozens of packages. They all be listed and you can see a coverage for
every package and you can see probably coverage for every test case, how many passes, how many
fails, et cetera, et cetera. Also, you want to probably investigate what is the coverage.
For that, you are using the built-in go to cover tool that will produce temporary HTML files and
will open them in your browser. So you see a combo box with the list of files in your application
and you just go through all your code. The red one is not covered by our test cases.
The green one covered by our test cases. For example, in this case, our main function
is not covered at all because it's tricky to test the main function. That's why you should
like put it outside of everything and make it like two, three lines and only use your packages
inside. Okay. So time for continuous integration and continuous deliver.
Yeah. So we are working as a company, we are working in GitHub. But I'm pretty sure that
the same functionality is available on GitHub and Big Bucket and everywhere.
Right? So for every my project, I want to have at least five actions, GitHub actions.
The first one is dependable. I want my repository is constantly being checked if any package I'm
dependent on is updated. Right? So it will update, okay, we have a new minor or whatever version of
this package. It will automatically create the pull request. I will check the output. I will check
if tests are fine, if everything is okay. Okay. Very good. I like this, you know, because
you can do three pull requests per day and you are super productive.
Then what I want to also always have is a code QL which will build your
own sources and will investigate the possible security vulnerabilities.
Build and test. I'm using that for pull requests only because if you are firing them on every push
and the test is heavy, it's not fine. The release will produce the binaries and packages
when the new release is created. And the docker is the same, like, for release it will produce
a special tag and push it. But for every commit it will produce a special docker image which you can
try immediately, right? Like a night build. Yeah, so dependable is very simple. For example, for
almost all my repositories, I first want to check the go code itself, so package ecosystem go mode,
and I want to use the latest GitHub actions as well. That's important. So I like check them
check daily and that's usually enough. For code QL, nothing special when you create these actions
from the GitHub interface, it will fill all the fields for you. I never changed the important
thing there, only removed some comments and we're fine. Build and test. I hope you can see what is
going on there. No? Sorry, I didn't want to switch to the editor because I cannot work like that.
Yeah, so I will tell you, so I usually run all my tests on three different platforms, Windows,
MacOS, and Linux. The good thing is all the workers already have PostgreSQL installed on them,
but the thing is that it's not started. So for you, essential is to start PostgreSQL and then run
your tests, and you are fine. Usually, the version of PostgreSQL is behind two or three minor versions,
but it's okay. If you want just like the latest one, you can go with the Docker images instead of
that one. So there in the build action, we have Linter. So no, without Linter, we cannot accept
any changes or pull requests. And then we are using we are generating the coverage report to
put them everywhere. See, 99% of code is covered. Let's lie. Okay, so release is a little bit simpler.
As I said, we are using Go release. It's absolutely fabulous piece of software. It may produce
everything for everything. So the GitHub action code is simple because everything is stored in the
YAML configuration file where you set up the name, the architecture, the O-system, everything.
And then you're just like, okay, let's check out our code and let's release it. And the
cool thing about this, this is the Go release. The Go release will create a change log automatically
for you based on your pull requests. So when I'm releasing, it's just like I copy paste it,
just sort it by the like what added, what fixed, and whatever. And I'm done. The release is very
simple for me. Absolutely. Before that, I spent two days on each release to produce all these
binaries, et cetera, et cetera. Okay, Docker. Go release can produce Docker images.
I'm too lazy to rewrite this. And yeah, I'm using like another special GitHub actions to build a
Docker. You can build them for every possible platform. And this Apple M1, M2, silicon thing
is whatever. It's just working. Okay. Takeaways. Oh. The Go is popular.
Devrim doesn't like Go. Yes.
Maybe this is the last time you see this talk, like when everything goes right. He said that
I need to switch to Rust. So maybe next, I will go out when Rust goes right. So no, no. Should I
stick to the Go? Okay. We can do both. Yeah. So a lot of developers are using databases with Go,
of course. You can use whatever it did or whatever operating system you are. By the way,
a lot of people are using Windows, which is not common for like Postgres community, for example.
But it's fine if your system can produce whatever you want. You don't care. You just work on what
you have. Right? So Kubernetes, you can use whatever you want with the Postgres. If you want
to use Orm, please do. But remember, you're responsible for that. Use it wisely. Otherwise, you can use
libpq package or new pjx. And you can use whatever GitHub, GitLab, Bitbucket you want.
And the most amazing thing about Go is the backward compatibility. You can build whatever in the
future. Whatever code you want. And it still will be compatible with the oldest something
written ages before. Even now, when we have generics, when we have a cool thing is in Go,
they are still compatible with that old things. Okay. So, yeah. Don't be stranger. Check my
GitHub account. Check our blog. Yeah. Some of our projects. And if you have questions,
or maybe you have a question to Devrim, why he hates Go. Okay. I'm not sure what the problem is.
I provide everything you need. Take my binders and put them in your packaging whatever.
And either it should be a binary or download the internet.
Which is not. Not internet. No. Not internet.
There are only four dependencies. Okay. For a new created application which uses pjx to connect to
the PostgreSQL, there are only one direct dependencies. There are only four indirect dependencies.
Two of them are libraries from Google. One of them library from CoreOS.
I don't remember. And one of them is by the same author because he's using this package
in other ways. Yeah. So, questions? Microphone.
Hi. A couple of slides back. You went to a certain functionality where you were asking,
you did select and then you put in a structure in order to get results from. Like, it's like,
yeah. I have a question on that one. It's, yeah. This one. Yeah. That's one. Exactly. Yeah. Yeah.
So, you're asking a select star. And then some stuff. And then you ask me by the rows. Does the
actual connection. So, if you're running this on one machine, you're running PostgreSQL on another
machine. There's a network, of course, in between. There's data going back and forth. Is all the data
being sent from PostgreSQL server to your GoPro or not? The reason I'm asking is because let's say
there's a fourth field which is a huge JSON field or a huge binary field which contains like a
megabyte of data per record. Is it then sending, if you're asking a hundred records, a thousand
records, is it sending a gigabyte over the network or is it only sending those three fields? Okay.
I got you. Yeah. Thank you. Very good question. So, in this particular case, it shouldn't be star.
First of all, we should always list a column we want to have. I'm just too lazy.
And this is not my code. But it's like, you know, it shows. Yeah. So, in this case, yes. Everything.
Can we do automatic, can we add columns from a database automatically?
Yes, we can. But for that, we should use SQL C,
SQL C package, which is exactly for that. So, you are, it is pre-built or hooks or whatever.
So, when you say go build, you have a special like SQL files like I want this field from that
and that and it will go through it and it will build automatically the appropriate structures for go.
And then you can use it. Yeah. It's just a lot of information. I cannot like put it into the one target.
Yeah. But yeah. About if we are loading at all at once, yes, we do in this case.
But the Postgres protocol itself supports row by row functionality. And it's possible to use
that functionality with this package. So, we can like, yeah, say that.
Hello. Thank you for the talk. I have one question about this driver. Actually,
it's kind of only way to work with Postgres, for my opinion. And I'm a little bit worried that this
driver is not supported by Postgres community, let's say. It's supported by someone. And what is
the life cycle of this software? And it may be it will die, you say, how is about new features to it?
And all this question arises when you work with it. Because if your management says, okay,
let's use Java, and in Java, it's kind of stable, this Postgres driver, and you know that you always
have the new version. What is about this software? Yeah. Thank you for the question. So, versioning
and all who is owner, and that kind of stuff. So, as a Postgres community, we support on the C library,
which is libpq, and Java, which is JDBC, right? That's all. All others... Yeah. Who uses C++?
Okay. So, all other libraries are maintained by someone. By the way, libpq is not a standard
library in terms of made by Go. It's also maintained by one person. So, how we do in this case,
we just fork it and use it if we want something new. If I did everything better than the maintainer,
the owner of the Pgx will accept my Postgres proposals, and we are stink, right? If not,
I will beat them, and I will be popular.
I have a question regarding testing strategies in CI CD, so you have shown that it's possible to
mock Postgres scale, right? But sometimes you are relying on some feature of Postgres scale,
or possibly you are relying on some extension Postgres. You want to test with a real Postgres scale.
Yes. What you can recommend. So, I have seen in use CI CD, you are executing some PSK commands.
Do you have a dedicated instance for running tests, or are you using screen containers?
No. So, my GitHub actions are using preinstalled PostgresQL on the GitHub workers. They already
have Postgres, like, 15.1 probably nowadays. So, I'm okay if they are behind several versions.
I don't need to test for a specific feature or a bug or whatever. But if I want to,
in my GitHub action, I may specify the Docker image against which I want to test. For example,
if I want to test the latest master from the Postgres community, I will build my own image
docker and will run my test against it. And I'm fine. Okay. Thank you.