you
so that's all from my side in this little review on the elliptic itself and thinking and
and the implementations in pretty so far
hi
homomorphic encryption, NPC, VDFs, and then even when you start to mount recursion and
curve cycles and pairing friendly curves, each time it seems to be we will try to standardize
curves, and then discover like, oh, there's some new property, like maybe unknown order
groups or hyperlyptic.
I think the movement of this restreto and decaf goes in the direction in instead of
standardize an elliptic curve itself, it is standardizing a variety of elliptic curves,
then you have the operations and the maths to work with any elliptic curves in this variety.
So this will bring us the possibility to have this, like another service that is providing
random elliptic curves on the net, and you can pick one from there and forget about the
thing that we are showing the same elliptic curves of this.
The way that the current standards that exist are fixing an elliptic curve, one or another,
but fixing it in a specific way.
I have answered it because you say about homomorphic, but the homomorphic is huge.
It's a very interesting field, but it's a huge field.
Okay, I can see.
Another question.
In many protocols and also in IoT devices, you are bottlenecked by speed and also by signature
size.
You said that with Jacobi-Quartic curve, you can go faster and also smaller.
How fast, how much faster and how much smaller?
I have in the paper of the Jacobi-Quartic people, the speed is explained.
I don't have the numbers of mine now.
I have the numbers of mine about the size because the sizes in signatures in elliptic
curves are 64 bytes, and the proposal, the schema they propose for the Jacobi-Quartic,
it's 84 bytes.
So it's like a third, smaller.
But it's still bigger than BLS signatures who are about 32 to 48 because you only need
a single point on curve.
In the signature, in the signature, you are not putting only the point.
There are three, if I remember correctly, there are three.
BLS signatures, it's only one point.
Which signature?
BLS from Danbony.
But it's shorter than 48 bytes.
It depends on the base curve you use.
But it's only, so if you use, well, 32-byte signatures are not deemed secure enough because
you have pairing issues.
But 48 provides 128 bytes of security.
What I know is that the 8-volt curves variety is 64 bytes.
Okay, are there any questions?
No, then.
Okay.
Have you looked at Genos II curves because I saw that they actually outperformed Genos
II?
Yeah.
They outperformed Genos I. I saw DJB was really in the center.
You are hyper-eliptic curves.
Yeah, the Picard group.
This is a very nice subject also.
I think banks are the ones that are putting more money in hyper-eliptic curves.
They are not using points.
They are using a matrix of the Jacobian of the point.
Right now, I only heard about banks putting money there.
I haven't seen an implementation in open source.
Any other?
Well, no.
Thank you.