Thank you.
Hi there, I'm a technology information security
enthusiast. I start my career as an information security
ninja defending information against cyber threat using my
out at night, that of a beloved hacker, I love using my skills to support the value
of open source and fairly believe in it.
I believe that technology can be used to improve people's life, but it can only be done if
we work together and share our knowledge.
That's why I'm also a strong advocate of collaboration and openness in the technology industry.
So may the open source be with you.
I will present a project we have made at the hospital where I work during the COVID crisis.
Hospital information system is really complex.
It's more than 3,000 applications, 4,000 virtual machines, 2,000 people working in
a critical infrastructure, 7 days a week, 24 hours a day to save people's lives.
To secure this environment, we need a global view of all elements that compose the information
system to obtain a better readability and thus a better control.
So we start to build a cartography based on the NC guide mapping the information system.
But when we look at four tools, we didn't find one that fills our needs.
Then the COVID crisis comes, all IT projects were stopped or at least slowed down.
So we took this time to work these tools Mercator.
Mercator helps organizations mapping the information system in order for them to meet the operational
requirements of cybersecurity.
It helps to build a map in five simple practical steps.
It can be used by any organization irrespective of the type, size, maturity, in terms of cybersecurity
or complexity of the information system.
It's an open source.
It can be used by any organization in public or private sector alike.
So what is Mercator?
Mercator is a web application that allows you to manage the mapping or the information
system as described in the information system mapping guide from the NC.
What is mapping?
Mapping is a way to represent the information system of an organization as well as its connection
with the outside world.
The term mapping refers to a schematic representation of a set of informations.
Mapping is different from inventory.
Typically, you manage your assets in different inventory, but you don't know the relations
between them and the importance of relations between all the information.
In mapping, we will try to have a complete view from the outside world, from business
requirements, down to your application, your servers, and your physical inventories and
your IT rooms.
So Mercator is a cartographer.
Mercator is a author of the Mercator projection, which is a conformal projection.
It keeps angles.
It's very useful in the sailing in the safety centers.
Why mapping?
Mapping is essential to control the information system.
It's allowed to have a knowledge of all the components of your information system and
to obtain a better understanding of it by presenting it in the different view.
It's allowed to fulfill the fourth challenge of digital security.
It's to control the information system.
The cartography allows you to have a common and shared vision of the information system
within the organization.
It protects the information system.
Mercator mapping makes it possible to identify the most critical and most exposed system,
to anticipate possible attack paths on this system, and to implement an adequate measure
to ensure their protections.
The defense of the information systems, mapping makes a more effective response in an event
of an incident or a digital attack to qualify the impact and predict the consequence of
the different actions taken.
And then the information system resilience, mapping make it possible to identify the organization's
key activities to define the business continuity plan and use essential tools for crazies management
whether they are digital or not.
The map is composed of three main assets.
It's defined in different view.
First, you have your ecosystem view that represents the entities of the system which use the information
interact to fulfill these functions.
These are your providers, your partners, your customers.
Then you have the business view of the information system that presents the information through
the main process and information.
So, then all your processes, your activities, your actors.
Then you have the application view that describes the software components of this information
system, the service they provide, and the flow of information between them.
Then you have the administration view.
This is the list of scope and privilege of users and administrators.
You have the infrastructure, the logical infrastructure view illustrates network partitioning, including
the definitions for IP address, VLANs, filtering and routing functions.
And then you have the physical infrastructure that describes the physical equipment that
are used by the information system.
Your mapping can be built in three steps.
And each of these steps, they have a level of granularity which will fulfill some of
this information or some of these objects.
To be migrated to level one, you have also initial element essential for digital operations,
for security operations.
At level two, the second level of granularity, you have the digital security oriented for
the mapping.
The digital information system must have a mapping which is at minimum at this level.
And at level three, you have the fine ability.
You have a comprehensive data mapping that incorporates all digital security requirements.
This is the main screen of the applications.
We have on the top the different materials or three materials levels.
You have a breakdown of all your object by domain.
And then you have all global proportional view of all those assets of your cartography.
We have on the left on the top your subpanel.
Top on the top panel your views, previous documentation.
And on the left panel, all the data entry.
Mercator computes the maturity level.
An item, an asset in the cartography is complete if we have all the information, all the related
information within them with other assets.
For example, an asset in the cartography is not confirmed.
There is no distribution, no responsibility, no type.
Or there is no link between other assets.
For example, an entity without relations, a process without operation.
An application does not support any process or a server without applications.
They need to compute the maturity level, that is, the conforming asset divided by the total
number of assets.
And the percentage represents the effort to be compliant.
So the more, the better.
So we have a lot of lists.
In the asset, we have about 20 different types of assets.
And you can show all types of assets.
You can sort, export them, hide and colon, copy.
You have a lot of form to fulfill.
So which form is the STF?
You can define the link between object.
There is a role management within that is implemented within Mercator.
You find that you can define within your IT team the obligation to fulfill the cartography
in different teams.
For example, you have the network team that will fulfill all the information that is related
to the server.
But you have the operating system team that will fulfill the virtual server.
And the application manager that will explain the application and where they are installed.
And so you can divide this different role within the applications.
There is a history of change.
Whenever something is changed, it's automatically traced in the applications.
So this is a data model.
So you have your entities and your relations.
And entities support different processes that define business in macroprocessors and activities,
operations, process use operations.
You have at the middle here is the application that is divided in group, application and
state on virtual servers.
And these virtual servers are on physical servers.
Mercator drives the dependencies between the object.
It was object in a irrational view.
You can view your macroprocess, your process, your activity, which also why your network
and your server within this villain, but also view the physical infrastructure, the building,
the rooms, the servers, the physical servers on the bay.
Mercator draws also the physical network schema.
You can define the physical link between the different elements.
And you can view where they are installed.
You can also explore the cartography.
You select an object.
You double click on the object and it pops all links between all these objects.
And you can explore all your cartography and view what are the different links between
all your assets.
The main interest in the cartography is to generate reports.
So the first major report that the cartography can do is the information system mapping report.
It's a complete work document where you have all your assets of your information system.
My hospital is 600 pages, imagine.
And in this report, you can explore the cartography by clicking on the link.
You have an application.
You can view who uses this application or where the application is installed, on which
virtual server it is installed, on the physical server, on which building, and you can follow
the link within the word document.
You can generate a list of supported entities and their application.
You have all your entities and what applications they are using.
Application by group.
You have all your application by group.
You can view is it a web application, is it a external application, who supports, where
is it installed, on which physical server, and you have a list of all your applications.
Your list of all your physical servers, what is the size of the server, where is it installed,
how many disks, RAM is it using, and you can also make projections year by year and see
how is it growing.
You can analyze your security needs on different objects.
It's a list.
So this application denormalized the link between macro process, process application
database, and information.
You have this on the list.
You can view here if you have correctly placed your security need in terms of confidentiality,
integrity, traceability, and availability by denormalizing it.
You can view your logical server configurations.
List of logical server with a configuration, what operating system, what is installed on
this logical server, who is responsible of it, and so on.
And you finally have the inventory of all your physical infrastructure, a list of all
your physical equipment.
You can take this list, go in the IT room and check if it's correctly installed in the
correct place and correctly labeled if you have information that are not in the list.
So this is an example of information system mapping report.
With a table of contents, you have your schema, and you can start browsing through the information
system.
This is an example of the physical inventory with your site, your room, your building,
and your examples.
This is an analysis of your security needs.
So you denormalize, a link between macro process, process application database, and you can
analyze difference in the requirement between each object.
You can try to transmit to the characteristics of the last three months.
You can track the update of the Mac.
You can demonstrate to an auditor.com that your mapping is updated.
For example, if you have in December some new application.com, you should have seen
some change in the category by the different teams.
May the category help you in the ISO 27001 certifications for the inventory of assets,
for the ownership of assets, for the labeling of information, location protection of assets,
management, you can see why a change impact other assets, which other assets does it impact.
Capacity management, you have a view every year.
You can take a view every year of what is your capacity.
You can do vulnerability management because you know what type of operating system application
you are using, and you can share from C-search and CVU what types of these vulnerabilities
present in your inventory.
You can do segregation of networks, security and supplier agreements, assessment of human
security events.
In case you have a security event, you can quickly search in your cartography.
I heard about this, and you can directly search on journey cartography.
You type a word.
If this word appears in the name descriptions of type of equipment, automatically you get
the information.
availability of information processing resource, you know how many servers are using what application
so on, so you can do it really easily.
The application is available on GitHub.
It's under open source.
It's used in three hospitals in Luxembourg and ten hospitals in France, three as myself
and French municipalities.
In fact, for the moment, ten contributors.
We have a roadmap.
We have tons of ID for the extension of Mercator, or main ID for the moment, treatment plan,
treatment registry, it's an obligation by GDPR.
You have all the treatment that must be in a registry.
Crisis directory, whenever you have an incident, you would like if Mercator is not available
because there is an incident.
Have it on a paper, have it on paper.
What are the essential assets?
What are the call phone number of your provider?
What are their email address?
We plan to make a link with Monark, Monark is Luxembourg-ish risk analysis methodology,
so we can start by your asset and extract a model for risk analysis to analyze correctly
your risk.
Okay, so thank you.
Do we have some questions in the room?
Thank you.
I have a question related to application and operating specific assets and files.
You've mentioned vulnerability management.
I wanted to ask, are you consuming software materials in this specific tool?
Second question, in addition to that, would be how do you consume that data?
If so, thank you.
For the moment, you have to enter all your assets by hand.
There is no automatic tools that can explain who are your provider, what are your main
business process, what are your inventory or physical inventory.
There is no automatic tools or artificial intelligence that can do it for you.
So for the moment, you have to enter it by hand.
If you have already some Excel sheet with this document, there is an API, a REST API,
which you can use to enter or extract the information.
I don't remember the second question.
Did I open it to both?
Any other questions, Alvaro?
I saw some question on metrics asking what was the URI for Mercator.
It's there.
UL?
They were using for URI, so I'm a universal resource identificator.
I don't know what context.
So no other questions?
Another one, okay.
Hi.
First of all, thank you for the talk.
It's not much of a question, but more like a comment, following what the other guy asked
or talked about, because basically the issue I see is how to populate the application.
So basically you need to connect somehow Mercator with your CMDB or to explore your network.
I don't know, for instance, if it could be with Blue Hunt or whatever.
I don't know.
OSCRE could help also.
So how do you see that kind of connection?
How could you bind Mercator with those tools that are already existing?
Is there a way or are you already thinking to create some API or I don't know what could
be like some magical way to interconnect those things?
Yes.
So for the moment we have a REST API.
You can fulfill any table that are in the Mercator database with any inventory you already
have in place.
So we can make the link and update these tables automatically.
For the moment we use it, for example, for the configures of our virtual machine.
Every few months we update Mercator with the configuration of actual machines.
So we don't have to do it manually because this is a boring task that has not a lot of
value.
But most of the time you have to do it manually because this information exists nowhere.
For example, how many users is it in this application?
Is it a critical application?
What kind of application is it?
Who uses it?
What is the FTO or FPO of these applications?
All these questions have to be fulfilled manually and it's really important information you
have to enter because you want to know them.
What are my critical applications?
What are my critical business processes?
This is a critical process but you choose non-critical applications.
Is it normal?
You have to think about it to build this complete view of your information system using a cartography.
Okay.
So one more question.
One question which is related to the other one.
There are available open source inventory tools that you can use to automatically populate
hardware and software inventory by just installing an agent on computers or just using a computer
or using one agent which does remote inventory and use these agents and push the information
into your tool.
Are you considering using this kind of software?
Yes.
There are so many tools that does network inventories and tools that we do not plan
to for the moment to build our self-connectors with these tools.
We try for the moment to improve the Mercator tools by itself.
But as I say, there is an API.
If you have an inventory and you want to populate this in Mercator, there is a REST API so only
push.
We have in the documentation a few examples of usage of the API in C, in Python, in Bash
and so on.
So it's really simple to build the scripts from your inventory you have to populate the
Mercator database.
But as I say, there are so many tools that you don't want to be linked with the tools,
with specific automated tools to fulfill the Mercator.
And also, these automatic tools fulfill less than 10% of the job you have to do to complete
your cartography because most of the work you have to do is probably things you do not
have already.
And you cannot automate this process of completing the cartography.
You cannot, there is no artificial intelligence that can explain to you what are your critical
processes, what are your critical entities, what is the relation you have with them, what
are your critical applications, what is the RTO and FPO of these applications.
So something you have to do by hand.
Okay, some more questions or we can enter earlier.
So thank you for your talk.
Thank you.
I don't know why it goes so fast.