Hello, everyone. My name is Amzah and this is my colleague Sebastian. We are working
at CrowdSec and today we're going to introduce you CrowdSec, show you how, explain you how
it works and show you how we can protect your Kubernetes cluster using it. So how CrowdSec
was created. We start with the basic statement that... Yeah, so, cyber security, we start
with the basic statement that cyber security is not a problem of means. As you can see,
those big companies have huge amount dedicated to cyber security. They have security teams,
but they get still hacked. And the reason we think that the reason why is because, sorry,
because they try to fight alone, like using the superhero approach, fighting alone attackers
while those attackers are sometimes collaborating together to attack. So as we are a lot of
users that want to run legitimate businesses, why not collaborating all together to fight
those attackers? So how this collaborative IPS works. So basically, CrowdSec needs to
ingest logs. So we have a lot of handled data sources like flat file, basic. It can also
act as a syslog server to receive syslog inputs. It can also read your Docker container
output logs on the cloud part. We have a cloud trail on the stream processing. We also can
have Kafka, Kinesis, and so on. Then we have the IDS part. So the IDS part is a component,
what we call the agent. The agent is here to pass the logs and detect bad behaviors.
And this is where the community aspect starts. We have a hub, like Docker Hub, where we wrote,
sorry, our scenarios to detect the common attacks. And we share them with the community.
And then here the other users, they write their own parsers to handle the new services,
new bad behaviors, et cetera. And they share them with the community. You can also write
your own scenarios to detect, like, a specific behavior in your internal infrastructure,
for example, and not share it, of course. And once this detection is done, we have the
IPS part. So the IPS part is what we call, it's another component of CrowdSec called
the bouncers. And the bouncers are here to allow you to do a remediation in multiple
parts of your infrastructure. So, for example, the basic one is to have the firewall bouncers.
So the firewall bouncer will communicate with the CrowdSec, get the decisions, and block
them at the firewall level. That you want sometimes have a smarter remediation. Like,
for example, you run an eShop. And we know that sometimes we have a lot of clients that
are behind a single IP. So what we want to do is to, when a bad behavior is detected
from an IP, we want to push a capture to the user. So we let humans steal access to the
website, but block the bots. And, of course, we have a lot of other bouncers on the cloud
side or also other bouncers that are written by us and by the community, of course. And
they are also available in the hub. And when this remediation is done, we have the reputation
part and what we call the community block list. So we receive the signals for, we send
the signal to the community, to the central API, sorry. We receive all those signals,
we create them, and then we return to the community the most aggressive IPs. So you
are protecting yourself and protecting the community. And you benefit also from the community
feeds. So we are, CloudSec already deal with a lot of common attacks, more than 50. Web
scan, post scan, conditional scan, stuffing. But also, thanks to the inference engine of
CloudSec, you can, it allows us to detect more complex attacks, like, for example, LCV
DDoS or credit card stuffing, which is a very business-specific issue. So, for example,
when you have for credit card stuffing, it's when an attacker buys some credit cards from
a shady website and wants to test if those credit cards are valid. So here we go to the
eShop and try to do small purchases. So you can detect this kind of attacks, also bot
scalping, etc. Basically, you can detect, if it's in the logs, as CloudSec, in just logs, you
can detect it. And thanks to that, we are building a real-time map, sorry, of cyber
criminals. It's kind of like ways between cybersecurity. So the more we are, and the more
efficient is the radar. And, of course, it will allow us to kill the most important resource
for the attackers, which is the IP addresses. Now I will let my colleague take the next slide.
Hello, everyone. So first thing, so about privacy, because as Amza mentioned, you do send us
data about the attacks you see. But we do collect only the strict minimum to be able to build
the community blockage. This means that your logs will never, ever leave your own server. Logs are
processed locally by CloudSec, and you will only send some metadata about the behaviors that are
detected by CloudSec. So those metadata are just the IP that you blocked, the reason why, so for
example, the SSH could force, and the time at which you block the attack. And that's it, nothing
else. And also, this part is totally optional. If you do not want to send anything to us or the
community, you don't have to. But if you don't send data, if you don't share with the community,
in return you will not get the community block list. And also we keep the data for the least
amount of time possible. So basically every IP in the community block list will be automatically
deleted after one week if the IP does not perform any more attack on the community. And for the
raw data we receive, after three months it's degraded and after nine months it's totally
deleted. Now, how do we build this community block list? Because we receive reports from all
over the community, but we cannot trust those reports because it's just an API. If someone
wants to, if someone wants to send us the information that ISO 1.1.1 performing a SSH
could force my server, we have no way, basically, to know if it's true or not. So we build, we
build something called the consensus. So we get the report from all over the community. And
then each user in the community has a trust score. So this score is really how much trust you.
It's built over time, so the longer you are part of the community, the more your score will
increase. But it will also take into account how active you are in the community. So if you
report just one IP per day or someone that is reporting 100 IP per day, we will just give a
slightly better score to the user reporting 100 IP per day. And we will also correlate your
report with other community members. If you are the only one sending us the information about
a particular IP, this IP will never go into the community block list because we cannot confirm
that it is indeed an IP trying to attack servers on the internet. But if, uh, if multiple users
report the same IP, then we will be more confident about the fact that this report is
uh, exact. We do also run some uh, oniparts and because those are fully controlled by us, they
are fully trusted. So if someone tried to attack them, we know that this is an actual report.
Uh, we do also have some whiteles because if someone send us IP belonging, for example, to
uh, to have a cloud flare, uh, obviously this is not something we want to redistribute uh, to
the community. And again, if you do send us too many uh, false positive report like this, your
score will be reduced because we know that your report are potentially false. And lastly, we
do also have some more um, advanced algorithms that for example, we look at the bigger picture,
uh, if you take a slash 24 network and like 50% of this network is already uh, in the community
block list, when if we see another IP belonging to this network, it's quite likely that this
IP is also bad. Same thing for example, if the IP report it to us exposes uh, like I don't know,
attended server, uh, 20 different service on the internet, again, it's more likely that the IP
has been compromised. And so when a report goes through everything, we will take a decision
and it will go into what we call the fire database or the community block list and it will
be pulled automatically by all uh, the community member. Now also for the usefulness of the
community block list, a while back we ran a small experiment where we had two different
servers exposed on the internet. Uh, on the same thing provider, those two server had the exact
same set of services exposed on, exposed on the internet so to adjust the web server and
the SSL server. The only difference between them was one was using the community block list and
the other one was not. On the one using the community block list, we saw a one 92% less attack
uh, on the server detected by protect. So because basically most of the IPs that are trying to
scan uh, your server exposed on the internet are basically trying to do it for all the internet
and so this is just some background noise you don't really care about it, you can just block it
before it can try to attack you. Another thing that we get uh, asked quite often is, okay so I
want to replace my firewall with
I want to replace my auditing system with scratch or whatever. Please don't do that. It's
not designed uh, to do that. We don't compete with this kind of solution but on the contrary, we
can help them to, to be more useful. So for example, uh, if you have an auditing system
telling you that, okay so I saw uh, command execution on the server and to the car by
batch or something or whatever. But you, you can configure a code select to pass this log to
detect this behavior and just to send you a notification. It does not have to be something
about an IP address, it can be a local behavior as well. Or something, something with fire
wall. You don't have to uh, go into uh, the configuration at the IP, just add the IP in
code sec with one simple command and then you code sec will take care of pushing this
information to your firewall and the IP will be blocked. Um, so for the uh, architecture uh, of
code sec, so as I, as I mentioned before, so code sec will ingest some logs, pass them. So this
is the, the, the role of what we call the agent. Uh, the agent will read your logs, pass them
and confirm them against scenario. So scenario just something that describe a malicious
behavior. For example, a brute force and wondering to scan your website and so on. When the
agent detect a malicious behavior, it will create an alert and will be sending this alert to
another component of code sec, the local API. So this means that the agent can live on one
server, the local API can live on another server. The local API will take this alert and
transform it into a decision. For example, by default it's a four hour ban on the IP. But you
can customize this behavior and for example you can say, so uh, this IP is French, uh, it
performs something related to uh, an HTTP attack. So instead of just banning it, I'm going to
uh, ask my uh, bonzer to display a capture for this IP for four hours, for example. Um, so and
when uh, so when the local API receive, receive a decision, it will be sending us information
about the alert. And in exchange you will receive the community blocklets. Uh, the local API
is also used by the bonzer, so the components that do actually apply the decision because
code sec by itself will just do the detection part. It will not block anything. For that you
need bonzer. So we have uh, quite a few of them. The most popular one is probably the fire
all bonzer that will interact with the local firewall uh, of the server where the bonzer is
only to block the IP. Uh, but we do also support uh, web server for example in Genix. And in
this case because we are at a higher level in the network, you can display capture to the
user instead of, instead of just grouping the request. Um, so here uh, it's the um, design
that will be uh, used in the following uh, demo. So, very small kubectl-scr running locally
with just two nodes. One agent per node deployed as a demand set. Uh, one local API for the
agent to be able to send the alert. Uh, the agent will be reading the logs of uh, the ingress
of the cluster and this case is Angelix ingress and we will have a, a bonzer, the Angelix
bonzer running on the ingress to uh, block automatically the IP if code sec wants to
bonzer. Okay, thank you. So uh, as we have, we are crazy guys, we gonna do a live demo. And uh,
yeah, uh, just think I have some. So, as Sebastian said, we gonna, we have a small uh,
locally of course, not online. Uh, thanks. Ah yes, of course, sorry. Thank you. Okay, so, uh,
what we gonna do is to um, so, sorry for that, but I will uh, so this terfum uh, will create
uh, Kubernetes cluster with two nodes. Uh, with the ingress controller, uh, Angelix and uh,
uh, a hello world app like it's a demo application. Uh, nice. Okay. So here we can see that.
Okay, we have one, uh, ingress controller and we have two nodes. Okay, so what we will do now, uh,
I will not spend time to explain you like the, the, the crowd sec values because we released
an hand chart that will allow you to install crowd sec in a Kubernetes cluster. As he said,
it's deployed a demo set, so in each node, it will deploy a crowd sec agent and one lapi, so
local API in a, in a specific name space. And of course your decisions will be centralized,
uh, across all your, uh, nodes. So here we will install, uh, crowd sec. So basically just
install the crowd sec is in these values. Uh, and this is the hand chart. Of course I already
import my repo in the name space, card sec and create it if it's not exist the name space. So
here if we are, okay. Ah yeah, as I popped a new cluster, I have to wait for the, uh, image download
better. It will come tomorrow. Okay. What I can do, yeah, of course, uh, what I can do is to show
you that I'm able to access my hello world app. So it's basically a Nello world. So each return,
uh, two O O and okay. We have one pod that is running. Okay. So this is the, this is the
demo effect as usual. Uh, let's install wait. Ah, okay. So now, uh, yeah, we're gonna fetch this
one. So, okay. I will, uh, follow my logs from the, this agent. So logs minus F agent and, and
all right. So here's my crowd sec logs. So now what I will do is to, uh, run Nikto, which is a, a
simple, okay. A simple web scanner to attack my, uh, hello world application. And here we can see
that I can even already, okay. Here we can see that it automatically detects as it's automatically
parsing the logs of the ingress controller. It detects some bad behaviors because I already
installed, uh, like a collections that are bundles of parsers and scenarios. And you can see that
it detect bad user agent, some sensitive file access, pat traversal, et cetera. So if I, uh, do
something like that and get a shell on crowd sec, sorry for the noise, uh, local API. And if I list
the decisions that were taken, we can see that we have, uh, six, uh, other entries like this one
because we detect several times my IP as I'm working locally. That's why we have those IPs. And
this is the last, uh, behavior that was detected. So now what we will do is to install the bouncer
because we are detecting, but we get still, uh, access to the, to the application. So now we will
patch our, uh, ingress controller, uh, to install the new app plugin to communicate with the local
API and get banned of course. So now here we have the command so we can go fast and head and at
time. So I'm upgrading my capabilities, uh, my English controller. Sorry. Uh, okay. Okay. So now if
we try to access now to, uh, the hello world application, we can see that we will be, we will
receive a four or three. So if I do this, oh, ah, it was failing. Sorry. I didn't see that. Uh, why?
Yeah.
Let's wait for this and upgrade.
Okay. Okay. Nice. So it's popping the new, uh, ingress controller. Of course it's local. That's why
we have only one pod. I don't recommend that in production. Um, so it's deploying the new ingress
controller, uh, and loading of course the crowd sake bouncer. It's a new library that is talking
with the local API and on each request we have this check. Come on.
Yes.
Uh, and yes, of course, uh, I think we ended. No, we have still time so we can take some questions and
I will follow up for like one question. So there is one fast question for one minute. Feel free to
answer it. Oh, okay. Uh, to, to hand, just to hand the demonstration, uh, it's running and now we
have a four or three. So that's it. And, uh, okay. So thank you.
This is the challenge with the demo demonstrations. Uh, if you have some questions, don't hesitate.
And of course we have some, uh, stickers, so don't hesitate to, to, to come to us.