We are starting in a couple of seconds, so welcome Norbert.
Thank you.
I hope you can hear me, right?
So yeah, my name is Norbert Poj.
I work at Red Hat.
And today I will talk about hybrid public key encryption.
And later we will source it with some post quantum.
OK, so is here anybody who already knows about HPK, please raise your hand.
Oh, nice.
There is quite a few people.
OK.
OK, so who doesn't know?
HPK stands for hybrid public key encryption.
It's symmetric and asymmetric.
Like it's combining both into a scheme.
It uses a key encapsulation mechanism.
It's used for key exchange.
It's like key exchanges, like you have like Diffie-Hellman.
This is a bit different approach.
You can find the RFC and the 9180.
So yeah, we have the fundamental parts of the HPK scheme.
You have like key encapsulation method, the key derivation or key schedule, and AEID,
which provides the encryption of the messages itself.
Below you can see listed the algorithms which are supported.
For the key encapsulation method we have prime curves and the Edward curves.
For the key derivation we use SHA versions and the AEID supports AES and Chachapoli.
So yeah, some familiar like words you will find later.
For the CAM operations we have key generations, encapsulation and decapsulation.
For the KDF we have extract and expand, the extract generates a key from some input data
and expands this extracted K to some length we wish.
For the AEID we have seal and open, which are encrypt and decrypt.
It's just an alias to it.
So let's talk about how does it work.
At the one side you can see the CAM and the K schedule, encryption context and AEID.
Encryption context divides asymmetric on the left and symmetric on the right.
This is really important because like you will see later that this diversion enables
us to change parts in it and leave the scheme still impact.
So let's say we want to use different algorithms for the K encapsulation method and we just
change it and proceed with the scheme itself.
So we use K derivation to the K encapsulation, create an encryption context which means,
which will consist of data we will need to do encryption of some data or messages in
the AEID.
And the last part, like symmetric part is the AEID where we like grab some messages,
encrypt it and send it over.
So this is the communication part.
Now I want some feedback from the last row.
Is it readable?
Okay thank you.
So this is a formal diagram.
How does it work?
I will go through.
So we have Bob on the right and Alice on the left.
We will assume that Bob have some private key which already shared with Alice.
We don't care in the HPK how.
So let's pretend that Alice knows the public key of Bob.
Then we will start with the encapsulation.
So Alice generates a temporary key pair called ephemeral.
So here it's the P key E and S key E. And we will use Bob's private key and Alice's
public key and private key to make Diffie-Hellman which will give us a shared secret.
Then we use the shared secret in the K diversion function to create a common key.
Then we send over our public ephemeral key to Bob so he can do the same to get the shared
secret.
Here, like so we encapsulate it, send it over and now we are at Bob.
Bob does the encapsulation.
He has his private key and Alice's public key.
Does the Diffie-Hellman get the same shared secret?
The shared secret is again used at the KDF and we have a common key.
So the common key is the same at Alice and Bob.
This is the end of the K encapsulation part.
Now we move to K schedule.
So we get this common key, use the extract to generate some salt, let's say.
Then expand it to get a key and expand it one more time but with different information
as you can see here to get anance.
And then the third one is secret for exportation.
So now we have set up the communication and we can do actually encrypted message conversations
which is the seal and open.
As you can see, we use the key, the nonce, some additional information and the key, the
private text, plain text.
Thank you.
So here you can see XOR.
The messages are counted so every message has a counter and we XOR it with the nonce.
Therefore every message will be different even if the message is like the same.
So if the plain text is the same, we will get a different cipher text.
That's the reason.
So we have this nice scheme.
What can we use it for?
Possible messages are the MLS or messaging player security.
It's quite new stuff, I think, maybe one year old.
And MLS uses, so MLS solves a problem where we want to communicate.
We have communicating parties more than two.
So let's say I want to communicate with you but I want to communicate with you and you
and you.
So it's harder to exchange keys this way because then we have like a two-way communication.
It's easy, right?
So this is the problem that MLS solves.
Then we have the TLS client hello and Obelvios DNS over HTTPAs.
The last one is I think new one too.
That solves the encryption of the IP address of the requester.
Okay.
So HPK comes with three modes.
The first one is the basic and then there are two more providing authentication.
We have authentication mode with private key or a pre-shared key in the PSK mode.
Or we can combine the both and have the out PSK mode.
What about the security?
The base mode is programmed to be secure against indistinguishability, ciphertext, and the authenticated
modes are outside there and inside there is secure.
So later on you can find the report at the references.
So let's move to the post quantum stuff.
As I said before, the K encapsulation and the AEID are separated.
So to make a post quantum we can just put post quantum algorithms to the K encapsulation
method and we will get post quantum HPK.
The proposal was for Kyber and Syke but as most of you know, Syke is already out of the
game.
Kyber is one of the NIST finalists for K exchange methods.
It uses CAM the same way instead of DH style K exchange.
It is a lattice based game standing upon learning with errors and running problem and Kyber
is proven to be IND, CCI2, secure2.
So we have this NIST diagram again where we can see hybrid version.
We have post quantum only version of HPK and hybrid.
Hybrid uses post quantum and the old algorithms too for the K encapsulation method like if
one breaks you can still have some security.
So you can see gray boxes here.
These boxes are the old algorithms which means if we eliminate them the post quantum version
will be visible.
That means the same way.
So first I will go through the post quantum.
Game vape generates a key pair pre-OR HPK and let's say that Alice already knows that
key.
A difference here is that we don't do classical Diffie-Hellman but we encrypt some random
data and we will get a shared secret here.
And the ciphertext of that shared secret.
Then we do the K derivation to get the common key, send over the ciphertext of the shared
secret to Bob who can decrypt it and do the same here.
And as you can see everything else is the same as the basic HPK.
For the hybrid mode the only difference is here.
So for the KDF the post quantum and the basic shared secret is concatenated and everything
else should be the same.
So what is the security of the post quantum?
In the base mode it's still INCCA2 secure because the KAM algorithm is proven to be
INCCA2 secure.
For the hybrid mode it needs more proof because the concatenation there and the auto-education
for both like both hybrid and PQ only would need more work.
So let's see some benchmarks.
I got this benchmark from the paper which you can see below.
They were done on Intel Core E7 with four cores, eight megabytes of cache and eight
gigabyte of RAM using AWCLST cryptographic library.
And the environment each algorithm was run 10,000 times and the first and fourth quartile
was eliminated of the measures to make it more accurate.
The measures are in CPU clock cycles and I think it was medium or something like that.
So here you can see psych which is now eliminated but I think it's a nice reference but it was
a lot slower.
Blue one is the basic HPGA, then the green one is a hybrid one and here the yellow is
Kiber only.
And as you can see it is faster than the Edward curve which is interesting.
Then there is one more graph.
Here you can see the green lines which tells us that the K-accapsulation method is constant
time so it doesn't constant in a way that it doesn't affect the encryption itself because
the tests were done for data encryption for one kilobyte of data, 10 kilobyte, 100 kilobyte
and one megabyte of data.
So as you can see the cost is more on the encryption of the data itself.
So there is a red line.
You can see that's for reference.
This is a version of RSA encrypting 240 bytes of data.
So here you can see references if you want to read more about it and thank you for attention.
So any questions?
We had some question on metrics so I will try to read it.
The question was how do we make quite quantum resistant crypto work on constrained devices?
How do we make quantum resistant crypto work on constrained devices?
Well, that's a good question.
I don't know the answer for.
Sorry for that.
So any other question here?
Thank you.
The last slide, I think page 15 you showed some benchmarks but these are on the whole
encryption, right?
Like not only the exchange of the keys and the setup of the symmetric key but the whole
exchange, right?
They are both.
So as you can see the green line is like the key exchange itself and then you have like
the seal and the open operation here.
So if you take for example one message and one key exchange, that's what the benchmark
says.
Like it's together.
Yeah, okay, all right.
And which was expected because anyway the quantum, the post quantum part is only in
the beginning of the exchange.
And then when the symmetric key is established, you continue with using your AEAD.
Yes that's correct.
All right, thanks.
So the post quantum part is only at the key exchange and later on it is the same.
Okay, any other question?
Yeah, I just wanted to say that the post quantum is more about like a symmetric key.
It doesn't really affect the symmetric part so it's okay.
Any other questions around here?
If not we can probably thank you for your talk.
Thank you for the questions.