Okay. We can't start? Oh. Okay. Hello. I'm Fraser. I come from Australia. I work at Red
Hat on identity management and PKI solutions. Talking about Kerberos PKInit protocol. I'll
give an overview of the Kerberos authentication protocol. Then I will discuss PKInit, what
its advantages are, how it works, and a short demo. Then I will discuss the security considerations
and give a demonstration of a recently discovered attack against the implementation of Kerberos
PKInit that we have in free IPA. So Kerberos is an authentication protocol based on symmetric
cryptography. It's a single sign-on protocol, so you can authenticate once per day, for example,
and using a token from that initial authentication, you can then authenticate to additional services,
hosts, or users in the organization's infrastructure. It was started at MIT in the late 80s. The current
major version of the protocol is version 5, and it came about in the early 90s. The most recent
IETF document describing the base protocol is RFC 4120, and that was from 2005, so even that version
is nearly 18 years old, but there have been many extensions and enhancements since then. The major
implementations are MIT Kerberos, Microsoft Active Directory, Heimdall, and free IPA, or identity
management in RHEL, which uses MIT Kerberos under the hood with some additional extensions.
The parties in the Kerberos authentication protocol are the client, the key distribution
center, and services. So the key distribution center, or KDC, consists of two services that
are logically distinct within the protocol, but typically combined together into this one party,
which is called the KDC. Users, services, and the KDC itself are all represented as principles
in a realm. So a principle is just a name for a user, host, or service in the realm,
and the realm is the name space for those user, hosts, or services. So often you'll see one company,
one organization might have one realm, but as companies grow or have mergers and acquisitions,
then typically you'll end up with multiple realms in your organization.
Each principle has a long-term secret key, which is shared with the KDC. For users, it's typically
derived from a pass word or pass phrase, so using pbkdf2 or some other key derivation algorithm.
And for hosts and services, the file is often stored in just in a flat file, which we call a
key tab. And the authentication tokens themselves, which are exchanged in this protocol, are called
tickets. So let's do some diagrams. The parties, clients, server, or services, and the KDC.
We can see the client has a key, the server has a key, and the KDC has all of the keys,
including the ticket granting service, TGS key, which is one of the KDC services. So the initial
authentication exchange involves what we call an ASREC or authentication service request. The client
says, hey, it's me, I want to authenticate. Actually, it doesn't necessarily carry any
authentication information. The authentication happens when the KDC responds to the client,
and the response includes a session key randomly generated by the KDC, encrypted to the client's
secret key. So the client does not authenticate to the KDC. There are ways that you can do that,
but in the base protocol, the authentication happens because only the client can decrypt
the response containing the session key. The response also contains a ticket called the
ticket granting ticket, which is not encrypted to the client's key, but rather to the ticket
granting services key. It also contains a copy of the session key and some information about the
client. So the client can decrypt the session key and store the ticket granting ticket.
Later, when the client wants to authenticate to the server, it sends a TGS request to the KDC,
saying, I would like to talk to such and such a principal, in this case, a server.
It includes the ticket granting service ticket, or TGT, and it also includes a time stamp for
a replay attack prevention and some client information encrypted to the session key.
The KDC can use the TGS secret key to decrypt the ticket, pull out the session key,
decrypt the client authenticator, make sure the client info matches up, make sure the time stamp
is within an allowable SKU, and if everything checks out, then in the TGS reply, the KDC can
return a ticket for the server, which contains a new session key, and it also returns the new
session key encrypted under the existing session key for the TGS session. So the client can decrypt
the second session key and store the ticket for the service, the service ticket, and finally,
it can talk to the service. So it sends the application protocol request, it includes the
service ticket, it includes an authenticator encrypted using the second session key.
The server can then use its long-term secret key to decrypt the ticket, pull out the session key,
and then it can use that session key to decrypt the authenticator, make sure the client info
all lines up, make sure the time stamp is within the allowable SKU, and then there's a shared
session key between the client and the server. They can talk whatever protocol they want to talk
using that session key. Okay, so that's the base Kerberos protocol.
Kerberos has a bunch of extensions and integrations. There's a pre-authentication
framework that allows you to integrate additional authentication mechanisms,
such as a TOTP or an HOTP. There are mechanisms for embedding Kerberos authentication in the
GSS API and in SaZL, so that will allow you to use Kerberos authentication with other protocols
that support those authentication frameworks, such as LDAP or SMTP, IMAP, etc. For HTTP,
there's a protocol called Spenego or Spengo, and we can also include authorization information
in the tickets, which contain additional information about the client, how they
authenticated to the KDC. So this is what we call the authentication indicator extension,
and there are other kinds of authentication data. For example, Microsoft Active Directory
includes what's called a PAC. I can't remember what that stands for, but Alexander will know.
Privileged attributes certificate. There you go, so that's the MS PAC extension,
which you'll frequently see when you're working with Active Directory or cross-realm trusts.
With Active Directory, that's that final point. I explained that there were situations where
you're dealing with multiple realms. What if principles from one realm need to communicate
or authenticate to principles in a different realm? That is accomplished by trusts and the
cross-realm authentication mechanisms. So the advantages of Kerberos, well, it's single sign-on,
which improves efficiency and reduces password fatigue for users. The client has to expose their
long-term secret only once until the TGT expires, so maybe once per day at the start of the day,
logging into your workstation, a single authentication happens, and from then on,
you no longer need to explicitly authenticate. It is resistant to the replay attacks. That's why
all of the authenticators include timestamps, and it works well for HTTP as well as bare network
protocols, which is a shortcoming of the predominantly HTTP-centric SSO protocols like SAML
and OpenID Connect. But the problems are, of course, that passwords are not great,
and dealing with passwords or the secret keys in key tabs, making sure that they are rotated,
making sure that they are secure in the first place, can be challenging and burdensome with
substantial administrative overhead. So this brings us to PK-INIT, or public key cryptography
for initial authentication in Kerberos, as the RFC is called. In this protocol extension, the
client can use asymmetric cryptography to authenticate to the KDC,
and the client presents an X509 certificate in its initial authentication request,
as well as a signature made with the public key, or the private key corresponding to the public key
contained in the certificate. The KDC verifies the certificate, the signature, and the binding
of the key in the certificate to the client principle, and if everything checks out, it can
respond with a response encrypted either using Diffie-Hellman or some other analogous key
agreement algorithm, or another public key encryption algorithm, such as direct RSA
encryption. So visualising this, the client in the authentication service request says,
hey, it's me client, but this time it includes some additional pre-authentication data.
It includes a timestamp, and if it wants to use Diffie-Hellman, a client DH value
assigned by its public key, and it includes the X509 certificate containing that public key.
The KDC, once it has verified everything is happy to proceed, then its response
includes the TGT, and it includes the session key encrypted using the public key algorithm,
in this case, Diffie-Hellman, as well as the KDC Diffie-Hellman value that the client will need
to compute the secret with which the session key is encrypted, and then it can decrypt it,
store the session key, store the TGT, and from this point forward, the rest of the protocol
is exactly as before. In Free IPA, by default, we can perform the binding of the certificate
and key to the principal object using an exact certificate match only. So in the principles,
LDAP entry will store a complete copy of the certificate. We optionally support certificate
mapping rules that allow you to be a bit more versatile in how you establish the binding
between the certificate and the principal. For example, if you're using certificates for hosts,
you can pull out the DNS name from the subject alternative name field in the certificate and
construct an LDAP query saying, well, we're looking for hosts whose FQDN matches that DNS name from
the certificate. And the client certificates can be signed by Free IPA's internal CA or by
a third-party CA that the KDC trusts. The user experience for PK unit, you can do it from a CLI,
it's not very pleasant, but you can use SSD integrated with your login manager to improve
that experience, particularly if you're using smart cards or TPM for storing the private keys
or doing additional pre-authentication mechanisms like two-factor authentication. And Windows
offers a similar experience. It should be, in fact, it must be easy for users and friendly for users,
otherwise people will not use it and you will not get the security benefits. So a quick demo.
KList shows me what tickets I currently have. The answer is none. If I K in it as Alice,
I can type Alice's passphrase and I now have a TGT for Alice. So that was a password-based
authentication. And if I ping the IPA server, that's just talking to the Free IPA HTTP API.
Now if I KList, I can see that behind the scenes it's acquired a service ticket
for one of the IPA HTTP servers. I'll just destroy those tickets now and I'll do a PK unit.
So if I change directory here, here I have a certificate and a key.
And I'll just pretty print the cert for you.
So what can we say about this cert?
Actually, I'll tell you what. I'm doing things in the wrong order here. I'm going to do a host
authentication first. So if I do K in it dash X, X509, user identity equals file and the certificate
and the key and a host name. Not a host name rather, but the principle name, host slash
ral78.ipa.test and KList. Here we have our TGT for the host principle.
So PK unit advantages. No more passwords or client shared secrets. The keys can reside
on the smart cards or, for example, in a UBKey, in a TPM or in a hardware security module.
And as I mentioned earlier, the rest of the protocol after the initial authentication
service exchange is unchanged, which makes it easy for services. The complexities. Well,
you need an X509 PKI. This brings in the renewal considerations and revocation considerations.
The hardware. If you want the benefit of the hardware security, that will cause an additional
financial cost to buy the hardware. And binding the public key to the principle is an important
consideration. So in the RFC, RFC 4556, it says, the KDC must also check that the client's public
key used to verify the signature is bound to the client principle name specified in the
authentication service request. And it goes on to suggest how you can do that. A couple of ways you
can do it. You can encode the principle name directly in the certificate in a specialised
subject alternative name. Or you can associate the key directly with the principle in your database.
That is what we have as the default behaviour in free IPA. But that introduces administrative
overhead because when the certificate is renewed or the client rekeys, then you need to make sure
that those entries are up to date. Or you can use other heuristics. For example, if the cert has a
DNS name, pull that out and use that to look up a host. If the certificate has an RFC 822 name,
which is an email address, pull that out, use it to look up a user principle. And you better not
mess this up. Which brings us to the CVE. So if we have a look at the certificate that I used to
get this host principle, server.pen, we'll see something interesting. It doesn't actually mention
that principle name anywhere. The rel78-0. But it does have a subject alternative name. It has two
in fact. One of them is a wildcard DNS name. So what's happening here? It's an LDAP filter injection
vulnerability. Free IPA is not vulnerable in the default config because, as I mentioned, only exact
certificate matches used by default. This bug is in the SSST component. It was already resolved
when I found it. So it was only older but still supported versions that were affected. And the
fix has now been released and the details are public. So what's happening is that the certmap
rule is just pulling the DNS name out of the certificate and concatenating it directly
into the LDAP filter without sanitization. And in LDAP, asterisk is a substring match character.
So using that certificate would let you get a TGT for any host principle in your realm.
And another interesting question is what happens if this is your email address?
Now, this might seem like a stretch but that is a valid email address. And I'm sure many of you
work at companies or have worked at companies where you can request your own email alias at
Red Hat. We certainly do. So if you managed to request an email alias such as this and the
system approved it, and you've got a certificate with that email address on it, and you have a
certmap rule that looks something like this where you're stuffing the subject RFC 822 name
into the query and using it to look up a mail attribute and that was somehow nested inside
an or list expression, then you've just got yourself a domain takeover. So let's see a demo of that.
If there's time, there might not be time, I think. How much?
Five minutes left. So I'm going to skip it. Sorry. I'll tell you what, after I finished the talk,
I'll, if I can, I'll just do it. But let me discuss now the mitigation. So yes,
if you're running a vulnerable version of SSD, you should update it.
The and list rules are harder to exploit than all lists. Just by nature, how the LDAP filter
expressions work. The or list, if you have a single sub expression, then the whole list
expression will match. But an and list, you have to match every sub clause. So it's just
easier to exploit an or list. You should definitely audit what data can get included
in certificates, where that data comes from, and how it's included or encoded in the cert.
And you could use exact certificate matching to avoid this issue. But that does come with the
administrative overheads to handle renewals or rekeys. General security considerations for PK
unit. Well, and this first point is for just all software always, probably escape and sanitise
your inputs, according to how you're using them. You should review your CA trust. So which CA's are
you trusting? What profiles for issuing certificates used or templates? And how are the attributes
that go into the certificates validated? Who can issue the certificates that you trust,
both in terms of their software systems and the agents, human or otherwise, who act to
issue certificates? And can any of the attributes be influenced by users or other parties, such as
if you have your email address alias request system? Just because a value is valid in a
particular context does not mean that it's benign in another context. And the key and principle
binding is a critical aspect of PK unit security and PKI application security in general. It
is as critically important as validating your certificate chain and validating signatures.
The full write up about this issue is at that link on my blog. And there's a link also to the
entry about this issue in the Red Hat CVE database, which includes the list of which
products were affected and where the fixes have happened and where they are not happening.
And that's also all last questions. And then maybe I do the domain takeover demo in a minute.
Maybe we have time for one question. So is there anyone with a question that will be answered in
one minute? They want the demo. Okay. So let's, I need to just change the cert map rules, which
ones are active. Oops. If I can authenticate. Okay. So IPA cert map rule. Find. This is just
the setup. So I need to disable cert map two and enable cert map one. Okay. So this is the rule
that I'm enabling. I didn't enable it. Oh, thank you for that. Okay. Now it's enabled. And I can do
a K in it. Let's see. It'll be there in the scroll back somewhere.
That's server. That's okay.
So the naughty certificate and the naughty key. And I want to be admin.
And now I'm admin and I'll show you the certificate.
Okay. So this certificate was issued to Alice.
And the subject name includes Alice's malicious email alias. Okay. There you have it.
Thank you. Great. Thanks, man.