Thank you.
Good afternoon.
Can everyone hear me?
It seems to be working.
All right.
I'm going to talk about Git checkout authentication in the context of supply chain security.
It's one of these buzzwords that we hear a lot today.
And I guess that's because there's a lot to be done in this area.
I have to tell you this is going to be a talk about pre-quantum issues.
So it's going to be different.
All right.
So I'm going to talk about work that has been done in the context of GNU Geeks like Simon
was saying.
Who has never heard about GNU Geeks in this room?
That's a show of hands.
Very few people, actually.
This is weird.
I'm surprised.
Anyway, so this started as part of Geeks.
But as you will see, this is useful beyond Geeks, I think.
So just, yeah, I have to introduce Geeks a little bit.
This is an actual birthday cake that we ate a few months ago to celebrate 10 years of
Geeks.
So it's an actual, yeah.
And it's a real cake.
That's the thing.
Yeah, so it's a distribution, a GNU Linux distribution that you can install standalone
like you would install Debian or something.
You can also install it on top of your system.
If you're already running Debian, for example, this is great.
And you can also have Geeks on top of Debian and that gives you an additional package manager.
But anyway, I'm not going to go into the details of what it's like as a user.
I want to talk about the, you know, what's behind the scenes, right?
So what it looks like from a supply chain viewpoint.
So this is a package definition for Geeks.
Maybe some of you are wondering about the parents, right?
That's okay.
It could be JSON, it could be XML.
You have similar things with other tools.
It's just basically metadata that describes how to build a Hello package.
It's telling you where to get the source code.
That tau.gz file is telling you how to build it with GNU build system.
So configure, make, make install, you know, that kind of thing.
And there are now like more than 20,000 packages in Geeks and they're all defined like this.
So this is source code, right?
And the thing is, Geeks is able to build packages from source.
So conceptually you could think of Geeks as some sort of gen 2, right, in the sense that
it's building packages from source, except that you can actually get pre-built binaries
and that's what people usually do because, you know, it's faster.
Especially if you want to use LibreOffice or, you know, whatnot.
But Geeks is basically as a distro, it's all source code, right?
Package definitions.
And then when you go and build a package, that's also a salient feature.
So if you've ever used or heard about Nix before, this is entirely inherited from Nix.
So this is a functional model.
Basically you say, all right, I want to build that Hello package.
And you run Geeks build Hello and it's going to talk to a daemon that makes an isolated
build of the Hello package.
So it's fully hermetic and that, you know, that removes a whole class of issues of non-reproducibility
issues that you would have without that isolated environment.
Yeah.
And so that means that if you look at all these things that we have in that GNU store
directory, we have tons of packages and stuff in there.
Now they're all going to be bit identical for everyone.
Or nearly.
There can be issues, you know, but usually it's going to be a bit identical.
So typically if I look at that GNU store, blah, blah, blah, Hello thing up there, well, if
I build it actually on my laptop or if you build it on your laptop, you're going to get
both the same hash.
It's going to be identical.
So it's all about reproducible builds, which you've probably heard of.
So this is an effort where many distros are involved.
Debian, of course, has been leading the effort, but there's also NixOS, Arch Linux, blah, blah,
blah, many distros.
It's called reproducible builds, but we could very much call it verifiable builds.
The whole point here is that you don't have to press binaries that you get from a server.
You can always verify that the source that appears, you know, in the package definition
that we saw before actually corresponds to the binary that you have, because you can
always rebuild locally.
You can challenge the servers that provide pre-built binaries and see if it's the same.
So from a supply chain viewpoint, that's pretty big deal, I think.
And Gixx, we're trying to go a little bit further.
So reproducible builds are nice, but it's not sufficient.
Like if you're reproducing bit for bit malicious software, you still have a problem, right?
So you've probably heard about that twisting-twist attack, you know, illustrated by Ken Tamsum
in 1984.
That's a long time ago.
Well, this is a story.
We want to be able to have fully-auditable code that's entirely built from source.
And actually someone over there in the back of the room with other people has been working
on this, has been presenting this last year.
We could talk about it for ages, but I have other things to tell you.
But I encourage you to take a look at that talk by Janneke last two years ago, actually.
The thing is we're about to be able to build the whole Gixx distribution starting from
a binary that's just 357 bytes, I think, right?
So pretty big deal.
All right, now to be more on topic.
So we have these fancy things, you know, reproducible builds, put strappable builds, building everything
from source.
That's nice from a supply chain security viewpoint.
But, you know, for several years we've had that tiny issue, specifically in Gixx.
If you want to update your packages, well, your package collection, the available packages,
and the toolset, you would run Gixx pull.
So it's similar to update in Debian, for example.
That's roughly the same kind of tool.
But it's implemented by fetching code directly from the Git repo of the project.
And you know, as you can imagine, you have to think about the implications of this, right?
We're delivering code directly on users' computers, so we'd better be sure they're actually getting
the real code coming from the Gixx project and not something different.
For example, if the server that hosts the Git repo is attacked, well, we'd rather have
some mechanism to detect that, you know, to make sure that users are not going to download
to clone a Git repo that contains malicious code, right?
So we need something here.
You know, we thought about this for quite a long time, actually.
And the typical answer to this question is the update framework, tough.
I don't know if you've heard about it.
It's sort of the reference for all things update in general.
So it's a specification with implementations in different languages and in different frameworks,
like for Python packaging, for Debian, I think, different things.
But there's one thing.
It's not quite a good fit for our case.
Our case is we're just pulling from a Git repo in the end.
The update framework is more about distributions that look like Debian or FedAware, where you
have binaries on the server, and, you know, people are actually downloading those binaries,
and those binaries are built by machines or developers, blah, blah.
It's a different setup.
So to illustrate that, let me show a bit what the workflow looks like in Gixx.
So here we have what Gixx packages do.
So as a packager, well, you define packages.
So for example, Python, and that's the kind of definition that I showed you before, right?
And then you can test it with Gixx build Python, for example, like Risso.
And eventually, the packager is satisfied with the package, where they eventually push
it to the Git repo.
And as a user, at some point, I'm going to run Gixx pull, which is very similar to Git
pull, except it's also going to compile a few things, but roughly that's like Git pull.
And so at that point, I'm getting the new package definition, and I can run Gixx install
Python, and I'm getting that package.
That's the idea.
And optionally, like I said, you can get prebuilt binaries.
I'm not going to go into details about this.
This is optional, but this is something you usually want.
But it's not baked in the model, like you would say in Debian or Fedora.
It's really something additional.
And because we have reproducible builds, prebuilt binaries are, it's substitutable, right?
The key thing here is that people are going to pull from the Git repo, and we need to
make sure that they are getting the right code, the real code.
So we're really looking at these two things where the users are running Gixx pull or the
build farm that builds packages is running Git pull, and how can we actually make sure
they get the right code?
And this is about authenticating Git checkout.
It's just Git, after all.
There's nothing special here.
So with millions of people using Git, you would think that it's a solved problem, right?
Oh, sorry, I thought.
It is not, actually.
So if you go, for example, to GitHub or GitLab, you can see these verified badges.
This is a screenshot from GitHub.
So you have verified badges.
It's green, it's nice.
You have partially verified, hmm, what does that mean?
And you have also no badges.
So what conclusion can you draw from that?
Is it the real, the authentic repo, or is it not?
You can't really do anything with that.
So at that point of the talk, we need to talk about authentication.
Authentication is about making sure we're getting the real thing, the undisputed credibility.
So we would say we want to make sure that people are getting the Gixx code as coming
from the Gixx project.
That's what it means to me.
So specifically, we want to protect against a number of things.
So we want to assume that potentially an attacker can gain access to the server that hosts the
Git repo.
And from there, the attacker can push more commits on that repo or could introduce malicious
changes in many ways or even make a so-called downgrade attack where the attacker would
revert or actually remove the latest commits, for example, so that users would be tricked
into pulling an older version of Gixx with potentially vulnerable packages and stuff
like that.
So this is what we want to protect against.
What we want to protect against.
There's a couple of additional goals.
We want to make sure we can do offline authentication.
Like we don't want to call out a number of services out there and key ring servers, whatever.
And of course, we want to support changing authorizations in the sense that people contribute
to Gixx and they come and go.
So we need to add new people, new contributors, official contributors, packages, and eventually
maybe we'll remove them.
We need to be able to deal with that.
So the solution, well, we're not yet at the solution, but the intuition at least that
well, this is Git.
So this is a graph of commits, right?
We're just dealing with a graph of commits.
So we have commits here, actually, A, B, C, D, F. And each commit is made by someone.
And the intuition is that we would like to be able to annotate each commit saying, well,
at this point, there's a certain number of people who are authorized to make commits
in the project.
And maybe it's going to change at each node of the commit graph.
And yeah, this is what we would like to do.
The solution we came up with is to have basically inside the repo a file that's called Gixx
authorization that lists the open PGP keys of authorized committers.
It's pretty simple.
And the thing is the file lives inside the repo.
And then we need to have a role to determine whether a given commit is authentic.
And so the role is actually very simple as well.
So commit is authentic if and only if it is signed by one of the authorized committers
of the parent commit.
I got it.
This is the main part of the talk.
I'm almost done, actually.
I could stop here.
So we call this the authorization invariant.
So let's see in practice what this looks like.
So if I go back to my commit graph here.
So let's assume for commit A, this is the first commit.
Let's assume Alice is authorized there, all right.
And then in commit B, Alice is adding Bob as an authorized committer.
So we have this label here.
So at that point, Bob will be authorized to make commits.
And if we look at commit C and E, well, they are made and signed by Bob this time.
And it's perfectly fine because if we look at the parent commit of C, for example, so
this is C, the parent commit is here.
And we can see that Bob is authorized in the parent commit, right.
And likewise with E, we can have a second branch, the purple branch.
And Bob is also committing in that branch.
And this is fine because the parent commit is the same line.
And Bob is authorized here, all right.
And we can keep going that way, you know, remove people and so on and so forth.
So the second example, if we take almost the same one, except that on the purple branch
here, Bob removes Alice from the set of authorized committers, all right.
And then what happens if Alice tries to make a merge commit that has D and E prime as parents?
Well, if we apply the authorization invariant that we showed before, this commit is not
authorized.
It's not genuine.
It's going to be rejected.
That's the idea.
Yeah, there's a small problem that perhaps you've noticed.
We kind of didn't discuss the first commit, right.
There's something to be said about that one too.
Well, we need to introduce the repo in a way.
So we need a way to say, well, this B commit is the first commit where we will start applying
the authorization invariant.
So we call this the introductory commit.
And it's needed because, you know, perhaps you have some history already in your Git
repo at the time you start using this mechanism.
And so we need to be able to say this is the one where it starts.
We call that the introductory commit, and so users are expected to know, you know, what
the introductory commit is.
So for example, this is a specification of a channel in Geeks.
So a channel provides more packages.
And as a user, you would provide not just the URL of the channel, of the repo, but also
the introduction information that tells from which commit we're going to start authenticating.
And that solves the bootstrap problem.
So concretely, now that we have this, if we run Geeks pool, and it's been in production
for a couple of years actually, if we run Geeks pool, well, we are going to have a message
that says we're authenticating channel Geeks and a number of new commits, right.
And it's cached, so it's pretty fast.
If I tell Geeks pool to use a different URL with a mirror, I'm going to get a warning
saying, all right, you chose to use a mirror.
That's fine.
But be aware that this is not the canonical URL, so perhaps it's mirror's tail.
But at least we can tell it's authentic because we've verified the authorization invariant.
But then if some evil attacker, you know, does something bad with the repo, then we're
going to get a narrow message directly saying, no, this commit is not signed by an authorized
key.
You have a problem.
And this is it.
So this is all when using Geeks pool, but there is actually, you can use the same thing even
if you're not using Geeks or even without using a channel.
You can use the Geeks git authenticate command that works the same except it's slower level,
so you have to specify the introductory commit and the key that's signed the introductory
commit.
And the thing is, I think we should all be using that kind of stuff with our git repos
because right now it's a wild west.
But yeah, the key is a bit not super usable, so I understand we'll have to do some work
on this.
If you have ideas, I'm open to them.
Yeah, and you can specify where the key ring, the open PGP key ring is to be found because
this is not going to talk to key servers which are very unreliable, as you probably know.
All right, I didn't mention downgrade attacks.
I have to be fast, right, I guess.
Downgrade attacks.
That's another kind of attack we want to protect against.
And the good thing with Geeks is that Geeks keeps tracks of its own provenance.
So for example, when you are running Geeks, you can run Geeks describe and it's going
to tell you, I was built from this commit.
So it knows where it comes from, so to speak.
And because we have that provenance information, then if you run Geeks pool and it detects
that it's not going to a commit that's a descendant of the one we're currently running, you're
going to have a narrow message, right?
Commit coffee is not a descendant of cabbage, of course.
And this is pretty cool.
And likewise, even at the system level, when you deploy your system, the system itself,
the distribution actually running on your machine records which commit it was built
from.
So we have the information here if we run Geeks system describe.
And so if I run Geeks system reconfigure to update my system, well, potentially I could
get a message that says, no, you're trying to reconfigure to a commit that's older than
the one you're currently running.
That's a problem.
I can override that if I know what I'm doing, but usually you'd better not.
All right.
It's time to wrap up, I guess.
So, to summarize, we have two things here.
We have authenticating Geeks checkouts which is good for Geeks because it gives us safe
Geeks updates.
And because we have safe Geeks updates, we can have unattended upgrades, for example,
and this is super cool, you know, you know that the unattended upgrades are either going
to work and run the right code or they're not going to run at all.
And this is important, I think.
This is inbound and offline, which means all the data needed to perform this authorization
while this authentication step is all inside the Git repo.
There's no need to talk to key servers and stuff.
And you can and should use that kind of tool on your Git repo, I think.
We really need to think collectively about this issue.
And we have, again, protection against the ungraded attacks, which is good for unattended
upgrades, and it's deployed in Geeks for a while now.
There's a paper, if you want to see all the nitty gritty details, there's a URL here.
And yeah, to conclude, I'd like to think a little bit, to reflect a little bit about
all these issues of supply chain security.
I know I'm sharing this one with speakers about SeqStore, for example, and other projects.
And we have a different approach to things, for example, with Geeks we have a unified
deployment toolbox, so we are very much talking about end-to-end integration of the toolset,
verifiability with reproducible bits, for example, auditability, we have the commit
graph, we have all the details available at our disposal, when often popular approaches
are more about assuming that you have a different set of tools, you can have a distro, you can
have Docker, you can have Kubernetes, whatever, and you're just combining everything and thinking
about artifact, flow integrity, attestation, version strings, and stuff like that.
So I think the key is to really think about going from source code to deployed binaries,
that's very much the free software ethos as well, and thinking about ensuring we have
proper provenance tracking and the ability to verify things.
This is it.
Thank you.
Thank you, Ludvig.
We have three minutes for questions.
Hello, thank you for the talk.
A really common workflow is to use GitHub to merge pull requests.
And whenever you merge pull requests, there usually is a merge commit signed by GitHub.
How would you go about allowing mergers by GitHub without allowing GitHub's keys to be
used for arbitrary commits?
That's a very good question.
Actually, there's probably a limitation of this model.
So we're not using GitHub or even GitLab for gigs.
And actual developers are making merge commits, for example.
But typically for automated merge commits, like you have on GitHub, it's not going to
be practical.
It's a limitation.
Hi.
Thank you, first of all, thank you for your brilliant presentation.
I see that Gwigs or Gigs, I have Gigs.
Yeah, thanks.
He's a very promising package manager or even the Linux distribution.
I probably have some off-topic question regarding to your talk, but I still believe that you
can answer it.
It would be enough, yes or no, for me.
Is there some kind of cross-compilation supported by Gigs?
Sorry.
Yeah, there is cross-compilation support, yes.
You can even cross-compile systems.
Quick question.
Thank you so much for your talk.
I saw you're using PGP keys to verify the commits, but these days you can also use SSH
keys to sign your Git commits.
Is this also supported in Gigs?
No, it's all open PGP.
That's a good question.
We started before Git supported anything else as an open PGP, actually.
Yeah, so it's a trade-off, I guess.
Have you considered upstreaming this into Git?
Oh, sorry.
Have there been any ideas about upstreaming this into Git itself?
I did consider it.
It's a bit of work, I guess.
Also we have very tight integration with a small-scale open PGP implementation that can
only do signature verification.
So that would mean also having that into Git itself, which is quite a bit of work.
I think it should be in Git proper eventually, yes.
Okay, final question here.
Thank you.
Have you considered a six-store integration?
Oh, sorry, can you repeat?
Yeah, have you considered a six-store integration?
Is it possible?
Is some work in that direction happening?
No, there's no work in that direction happening, as far as I know.
I guess I'm not sufficiently familiar with six-store to see how it could integrate with
Gigs, but I don't know, maybe there's something we could do.
Thank you.
Thank you, Ludovic.
Five-minute break.
Thank you.