Thank you.
So my name is Joost van Dijk.
Disclaimer, I work for a commercial company called Yubico.
So maybe you've heard of Yubikis.
Yubico produces those Yubikis.
But I'm not going to talk about Yubikis.
I'm going to talk about a technology called Fido.
And many of you will have seen the previous presentation that was about an application
of Fido.
So the goal of this presentation is to move on to the next slide somehow.
Yep.
To explain what Fido is.
So I give a quick introduction to Fido and then what you can use it for.
And many people will already have seen it for, for example, for authentication.
But I'm going to talk about things that are, so for authentication on the web primarily.
I'm going to talk about things that are, that Fido can be used for that is not involving
a web browser.
And these things are less, less are well known.
So I think it's interesting to have a look at the applications.
And I'll give examples of open source software that you can use today that are actually using
Fido to do, to do things that are, that don't involve a browser.
So let me first explain about Fido.
So Fido is actually a set of specifications.
One is by the World Wide Web Consortium.
That's about using it in a web browser primarily.
And the other one is using security keys.
So the tokens like this that are typically in your key ring, this is called a roaming
authenticator in Fido.
And the idea is that you protect your private keys on a piece of hardware that has protection
against extracting key material.
So this protocol is called CTAP.
And that's by a different organization.
It's called Fido Alliance.
And so this is specifically talking to authenticators like this one.
So how does that work?
So I'm simplifying things because there's a lot of details that I don't want to get
into because that takes too much time.
So if we have some relying party, so let's first look at the web authentications part.
So using a web browser typically.
So a relying party that will be typically a web server.
And authentication works by, yeah, like many authentication protocols, you use a challenge
response mechanism where you use asymmetric cryptography to sign a challenge.
And then you have the verifier so the relying party can check the signature.
And if it works out, then you're authenticated.
So the idea is that these two protocols, the web of N is basically used in a web setting.
So for example, the web server can send a challenge to a browser.
And then the browser uses the web of N API, which is simply a JavaScript API to initiate
the registration of a public key or authentication using that public key.
So that's web of N. That's in the web part.
And then on the back end, your web browser will communicate with a security key, so this
roaming authenticator, just relaying that challenge, asking the key to sign it, and
then the response is passed on to the relying party and will verify it.
So what's all the fuss with the pass keys and FIDO and anti-phishing?
Well that's the merit of FIDO2.
It has phishing protection.
And that is because in this challenge, the web browser can help you secure things by
injecting the origin of the site that you are authenticating with.
So this is included in the signature.
So if you end up at the phishing site, the signature won't match because it will have
a different identifier for the web server.
So this is why FIDO is phishing, protecting you against phishing.
But actually I'm not going to talk about this use case.
I'm going to talk about the right part of this image where we use CTAP to communicate
with an authenticator.
So these are all kinds of authenticators.
I work for a company that produces these authenticators, but it's an open standard, so anyone can build
a security key.
So I'm using security key and roaming authenticator interchangeably.
But these are all security keys by different vendors.
So of course my employer is there.
But there's also Fayshaun, for example, Google, NitroKey, SoloKeys.
And that's interesting because that's actually also open source hardware.
So anyone can build a solo key.
The firmware is open source, everything.
NitroKey actually uses the same software base, firmware base.
So these are all anything I talk about in this talk will work with any of these security
keys.
So how does this protocol work?
So I'm focusing on CTAP, the backend.
So talking to an authenticator.
Well the idea is that first you have to register.
So registration is just to register your public key with this verifier, this relying party,
whoever that is.
And then later you can use that public key for authentication.
So there's two steps, registration, authentication.
And so in the registration steps, so I'm not going to talk about all the details, but you
just register your public key with a relying party.
And this is including something called the relying party ID.
So in web of N this is the identifier of the web server.
But in other applications it can be anything.
But the idea is that it is included in any signature that you generate.
And so you fix this relying party ID when you register.
And later with authentication this relying party ID is included in the signature so you
can as a relying party verify that it is used for your application.
So you cannot use the same public key for some other application with a different relying
party ID.
So I'm not going into too much detail.
Now you might think, well, I can do this stuff with PGP, I can do it with smart cards.
So what is different about security keys if you're not using it in a web browser?
Well actually many of the things that I'm talking about will also work with PGP or other
technologies.
Although there are some specific features that are not always included.
And one of them is attestation.
So attestation means that you can prove that some signature was generated with a security
key.
So of course if you know that the public key is generated on a security key then obviously
that is the case.
But if you're dealing with someone that claims to have a security key but you're not sure,
you can actually verify it by this process called attestation.
So you can prove that someone uses, let's say, a Google Titan key to generate a signature.
So this is what's called attestation.
And there's a service hosted by the FIDO Alliance, or the organization that actually produces
those specifications.
And they host metadata.
So if you have a security key it will have a unique identifier.
So not unique for that particular YubiKey but unique for the Maker model.
So any, let's say, any Titan key or any Fayshaun key or any YubiKey that is of a particular
Maker model will have the same identifier.
And in the specs it says that at least 100,000 keys need to use that same identifier if they
are the same Maker model.
So it can be sure that, let's say, that the signature is generated by a Titan key.
And that is also interesting.
So attestation together with metadata, they really add something to this process.
So here's an example of the metadata.
So someone built a nice web view of the metadata.
So you can look up things like, of course, who's the vendor of this YubiKey or this security
key.
And also is it using protected hardware?
And is it certified to a certain security web?
So all these things you can actually use in a, actually, yeah.
So I'm not going to do any demos.
So I include all my demo slides for you to try yourself.
So we don't have time here.
But I'll just leave them in the slides so you can actually try.
So this is a way to extract metadata.
So it's a bit technical.
But if you want to try it, please do.
Then about open source software.
So Yubico publishes a FIDO library.
And it's actually used by a lot of open source projects.
So this is open source, although it's produced by Yubico.
And yeah, if you look at, for example, GitHub and you look at all the projects that use
this library, then there's lots of interesting projects that do it.
And that means that you can use a security key, any security key, by any vendor using
that software.
And yeah, what I'll do in this, in the rest of the talk, is give you some examples.
Because it's interesting that although FIDO was primarily intended to do authentication,
you can actually do other things.
You can do encryption.
You can do signing.
And you can actually store things on the Yubico.
So I'll give an example of all these features.
So let's start with a very simple example, like a pluggable authentication module.
So that's another open source library that is included in many Linux distributions.
The idea is that you can...
Oh, yay!
you
open source software
you can try it out yourself
but let's give a practical example
let's say that you want to encrypt your hard disk
you're on a Linux system you're using the lux
and typically this is done using a password
instead of using a password you can also use a security key
a FIDO key
that instead of deriving some encryption key from your password
it will derive the encryption key from this extra key that is generated on your security key
so this this means that if you want to decrypt your hard disk you just need to insert your security key
so this is what you have factor to extra to get some extra confidence that only you can decrypt that hard disk
so worth the look now
then there's another extension called large blocks
and this is for storing things on your security key
and so it doesn't have a lot of space but this is typically used for storing certificates
so let's say you're using SSH and you use SSH with SSH certificates
these are small files
and it's it's feasible to store them on your security key
so this is an extension that is not very often implemented at the moment
so the
I think there are a couple of vendors that actually implement this
but it means that if you if you move to a different system and you want to log in there
you can actually take your security key and extract both the public key and the certificates
of course the privacy stays on your key and your security key
and then log into a remote server from there
because so everything is contained in the same security key
here's an example how you do this with the tools
do it yourself if you have the key that supports it
finally last example about this attestation
so if you generate an SSH key that is backed by a security key
you can actually ask the security key to provide attestation
so there's this extra parameter in SSH keygen that will extract the attestation data
it's called that you can look up in the FIDO metadata service
and this way you can prove that the signature was generated
by some security key and you can look up exactly which one
and you're certain that this is done with secure hardware
okay
you can try it out
so getting to a conclusion
so I'm not saying you have to stop using PGP or anything
this is an alternative to doing things with secure hardware
and the idea is now that since all the big vendors like Apple and Google and Microsoft
they've jumped on the FIDO bandwagon so we can see a lot more support for FIDO in the future
that means that a lot more people will own a FIDO security key
for example, already mentioned this morning is if you have an Apple iOS device
you can protect your Apple ID using a FIDO security key
so it's built into iOS 16.3 I think
so this means that it is a viable alternative
that's actually also a lot cheaper than many of the other hardware keys that you can buy
like a smart card
so I think for 20 or 30 bucks you can buy a FIDO security key
whereas smart cards are usually, especially if you consider all the middleware
and everything else that you need to get it working
that can be a lot more expensive
so just a list of our resources if you want to look up things
of course you can also contact me, I'll be here all day
and happy to take questions if there are any
Hi, I have a question about the attestation process
and open implementations of FIDO2
if you have an open implementation is it possible to get that certified with FIDO2 Alliance
my understanding is that in order to enable people to compile their own binaries
to put on their own open keys, is that possible or is it not?
Yes, so as a relying party
so there's a certification process that you can use to test if you are compatible with the FIDO standards
and so there's different certification programs
the most heavy ones are for the actual security keys
so there you have to actually do a lot of work to get it certified
but there's also a self certification toolkit I think
that you can use to see if you are compatible with FIDO standards
so there's a lot of tests you can run against your own relying party software
you can use them at least, right?
yeah, yeah
any other questions?
what is publicly known about hardware tokens failure rates
at least for popular models
and how many identical devices would you enroll for the most important things personally?
the question is I think twofold
first is about failure rates
actually I don't know about failure rates but of course there's different ways to do user verification
and I skipped over it a bit but to use a security key you need to either touch it
and sometimes also prove that you are using it
and this is done typically with a pin or with a biometric
so I've never seen a security key fail
except when it's using biometrics because of course that is a less
so every biometric has a false acceptance rate and a false rejection rate
and yeah I don't know numbers but it differs with different vendors
so I think Apple doesn't say anything about their false acceptance rate for example
so I guess you just have to trust them and that is with many vendors
I missed the second part of your question
do you have any identical devices to enroll at once or use of a line?
oh yeah, so already mentioned if you lose your security key you have a problem
so you want to have multiple public keys registered
and how many that depends on the relying party
so some relying parties initially only allowed you to register one
so that's pretty useless because if you lose that one then you're out of business
so usually there are several and I think for example on an Apple iOS device
you can now register six but that's really depending on the relying party
so some have an infinite number so you can just register as many as you like
but that's really depending on the relying party
okay we've got time for our last question, there is an icy hand here
so I guess if you have now a single point of failure with a USB socket
especially if you are travelling so are there any plans to have implementation
for the Bluetooth FIDO standards
so we can still work if USB is broken maybe at the phone or whatever
keep it a little quiet because I have trouble hearing the question
are there any plans for the Bluetooth support in the libraries
because especially if I'm travelling I often have problems with USB sockets
so I would have a single point of failure there
so you're saying if you have problems with your USB sockets then you cannot use a key
so is there an alternative?
and I would prefer to have some Bluetooth fallback then
and the FIDO standard also specifies FIDO over Bluetooth
but I don't see it's only implemented on Windows
and Android but not on the Linux side please
sorry, Bluetooth, yeah
so Bluetooth support is not in this libfido 2, it only has USB and NFC
no Bluetooth but there may be an addition in the next version of CTAP
there will be a way to, and maybe you've seen it in Google Chrome
you can generate a QR code so that you can use your phone
so if you have to introduce your phone as an authenticator
you can do it over Bluetooth low energy but the Bluetooth channel is only used for proximity
it's not used to actually transfer anything
for example if you register a key, your public key is not submitted over Bluetooth
but that will be in the next version of CTAP
thank you for the talk, we are out of the time, so applause