Welcome, Ruthvik.
Thank you.
Good evening, everyone.
Thanks for coming back for the late evening talk.
I appreciate your time.
So my name is Ruthvik Shih-Sagar.
I work at Tredad as a senior technical support engineer.
I mainly work on solving open-ended problems,
and I'm also working on solving the problems
in the future.
And I'm working on solving the problems in the future.
So with the recent time and security threats or attacks,
we have seen that container-run Kubernetes adoption
has equally increased.
With that, security has become a biggest concern, right?
So we'll see how Strykerox is paving the way
for Kubernetes native security.
So I'm going to talk about the future of the future.
So I'm going to talk about the future of the future of the future.
And how Strykerox is paving the way for Kubernetes native security
and helping us to achieve or resolve the security issues
with ease and automation.
So this is the brief agenda for today's talk.
So in the first few slides, we'll discuss current state
of Kubernetes security, what are the best practices,
and how DevSecOps benefits into the security posture,
how to shift-left the security for your developers
as well as your security admins.
And then we will see how Strykerox ecosystem
is helping end users, developers, as well as your security teams
to overcome the security issues with ease.
And then we will have some demo at the end.
So first of all, let's understand what is zero-to-security,
why we require zero-to-security, right?
Zero-to-security is basically a framework which requires
all the users to be authenticated and authorized continuously
before they're being granted an access to your application and data.
So if you manage to achieve zero-to-security model,
then I would say that we could resolve or minimize the impact
at the very early stage of your application lifecycle.
Then how exactly zero-to-security fits into the software supply chain?
So what exactly is software supply chain?
It includes everything, everyone and everything that touches your application code
into entire software development lifecycle, right?
It could be your deployment, it could be your final artifact,
it could be your CI-CD pipeline.
So it's essential that we build the application in such a way
that the assurance at every stage of application is being taken seriously.
That way we could achieve the pressure of software supply chain.
So yeah, we can see that securing dependencies,
securing code, securing containers, as well as the infrastructure
are all part of the software supply chain.
Let me ask you this question.
If you are using Kubernetes or in general any applications,
have you ever delayed or slowed down the application deployment into production
due to container security concerns?
Any one of you?
All right, I assume so because that's how we go through application lifecycle.
We deploy the application, then we analyze the application behavior
and we detect the vulnerabilities.
So in the recent trend, we have seen some common factors
or common anti-patterns which were causing delays for an application
to get deployed on the production.
So misconfiguration has topped the percentage.
Following that, we have vulnerabilities to remediate, right?
So for example, we kind of able to detect the vulnerabilities
but somehow we tend to overlook them or we could not assess them accurately.
That leads to the vulnerability.
I mean, we get to know that, okay, vulnerability exists
but there are no proper ways or tooling to fix that kind of vulnerability.
Then we ultimately have security issues at the runtime,
you know, which could be costly or it could affect your entire production.
So how can we make sure that these kind of issues are reduced, let's say?
So in today's world, we need DevSecOps approach.
DevOps, just DevOps isn't enough, right?
We need DevSecOps approach to shift-flave the security
from our traditional security practices.
So DevSecOps helps us define microservices architecture.
It provides us declarative definition to, you know,
harden your security parameters, network policies and deployment conflicts.
It also makes sure that the infrastructure stays immutable
so at the runtime, nobody else is allowed to touch the software
or your application deployment.
At the same time, it is important that we know
Kubernetes native security is increasingly critical
and securing supply chain is also equally essential.
So what are the basic Kubernetes security scan challenges?
So we know that containers are numerous and everywhere.
If I have to put analogy, like we say that everything is a file in Linux.
In a similar way, everything runs in a container
when we talk about Kubernetes, right?
So they may tend to pose compliance challenges.
Every container image is tied up with some of the other container registry, right?
So sometimes we even forget to add TLS-based authentication
to our image registry that may expose security threats
or the internet if at all we expose that.
And we are also aware that containers, by default,
talk to each other without any network policies.
So it is important that we define network policies at the early stages.
And this one, I think most of you can relate that when we talk Kubernetes,
all of the configurations looks pretty easy,
but defaults are usually the less secure, right?
So we as admin or developer have to proactively understand
what configuration or what risk tolerance required
for my organization or developer environment.
So in Kubernetes, application lifecycle span across three phases mainly.
That is build phase, deployment phase, and runtime phase.
So how we can make sure that we secure each and every stage of the application, right?
So when we talk about build phase,
it's important that we isolate the vulnerability of security issue at the earliest.
Otherwise, it would be very costly and risky to detect the vulnerabilities at the runtime, right?
So what we can do, we can use minimal base images
so that we can avoid unnecessary package managers
or any executable programs into your container images.
Then we can always use image scanner to identify known vulnerabilities.
I think identifying vulnerabilities just once is not enough.
You need to make sure that whatever security integration scanner you are using,
that will continuously validate your container images
and send the real-time alerts to your development team as well as security admins.
Then, yes, at the build phase, we need to integrate CI CD pipeline.
So that way, most of the things become automated,
and you don't have to look around each and every build config
to understand where the security issue lies through CI CD pipeline.
If the stage gets filled, your production won't be affected
and build would be stopped over there.
Then at the deployment phase, as I mentioned,
the default deployment config doesn't come with a network policy.
We need to understand what services that deployment is trying to communicate,
what are the ports that are defined in the deployment config,
and accordingly, we can define our own network policies.
Then we also need to make sure that the deployment doesn't allow root level privileges
or any unknown users, user IDs to access your application.
You should be always aware what users are going to access your application.
And then, yes, we can extend the image scanning to deployment phase.
So it's important that we do not restrict our image scanning at the build phase,
but we continue doing that at the deployment phase as well.
Then runtime phase, as I mentioned, we need to extend our scanning at the runtime as well.
So we can easily understand and quickly understand what issues have appeared
and what actions I need to take.
It also helps monitoring network traffic to limit unnecessary or insecure communications.
Then if we find any suspicious activity, and at the same time,
if we have multiple replicas of your application,
then we can compare all the replicas and processes runtime
to understand what anonymous activity is happening.
So to overcome all the challenges, we see Strykerox is helping the end users and the community as well.
So why Strykerox is open source, right?
Red Hat believes open model when it comes to your software or developing the application.
And we believe that open source software can significantly help developers to drive the project with innovation
as well as foster the collaboration within community.
So Strykerox is working towards providing the open source solution,
which will allow end users to decide how they want to protect their Kubernetes clusters.
So let's understand what Strykerox has to offer us.
It enables users to address all significant security cases across entire application lifecycle that we discussed, right?
Right from your build, deployment and runtime.
It also gives you greater visibility over vulnerability management,
configuration management, network segmentation, compliance, threat detection, incident response,
and risk profiling and tolerance.
So Strykerox has a policy engine that allows users to run the policies out of the box,
meaning that let's say if I have a severity with a CVSS score greater than or equal to 7,
then I could have an alert for the same CVSS score and understand what deployments are associated with it.
Then Strykerox API allows users to integrate with the image scanning tools, CI CD tools,
container runtimes of their own choice, secret management, DevOps notification,
to ease security flow end to end.
You can also run it on any cloud or hybrid cloud,
or if you want to choose on-prem, you can deploy it over there.
So this is the bird-eye view architecture, I would say,
where you would see a central in the blue box as a central hub,
which gets exposed over load balancer for the clients to consume the Strykerox API.
It is written in the REST API.
And then we have sensor admission controller collector,
which is logically group and called as a secured cluster, right?
So you can, once you configure this set of components,
you can call a Kubernetes cluster as a secured cluster.
And then you can keep on adding as many Kubernetes clusters as you want into the central.
The central also has scanner, which aggregates the vulnerability feeds
that are fetched from the central.
So central basically collect vulnerabilities feed from option sources
as well as in the database.
Then on each and every node, we would have collector agent,
which will collect host level data for the container network and the runtime.
So this is the UI where, let's say, if I have integrated 100,
100 Kubernetes clusters, then how can I manage or understand
how those are behaving?
What are the healthy components and what are unhealthy?
So we can have a quick look to see how systems are performing.
So what problem set, when Strykerox going to solve?
So these are four problem set statements,
which I found very common between developers and security teams
to understand whether my container contains,
contain compromised infrastructure.
Are there any known vulnerabilities?
Are there any runtime and OS layers contained up to date?
Is my Kubernetes cluster compliant with industry certified security benchmarks?
So let's see how Strykerox solve these problems.
So Strykerox scanner identifies the vulnerabilities in the base image
package that are installed by the package managers,
then programming language specific dependencies,
programming runtime and frameworks.
It supports package formats, which I have mentioned there.
And I believe most of you work with the same package formats.
And there are supported operating systems like Alpy and Amazon,
CentOS, Red Hat and the President.
So managing compliance is equally important for our organizations
to the security standard.
So it supports out of the box compliance standards like CS,
benchmark for Kubernetes Docker, then HIPAA, NIST, PCI.
So you can run scans through this profile.
So Strykerox basically collects snapshot of your Kubernetes cluster.
Then it aggregates the data and analyzes what checks are being passed
and what checks are getting filled.
It will help to evaluate your for the regulatory compliance.
It will help to harden your Docker and underlying container runtime.
So this is the UI where you can see passing percentage across your
cluster, across namespaces, across the nodes, right?
So you can have a better idea where the issue or what compliance
checks are filling.
Accordingly, you can navigate to that in the right section.
Here you will see what controls are filling, what needs to be set.
For example, here I have taken example of CNF files,
which says that the file permission should be more restricted.
You can accordingly take the actions and fix that control.
So what is collector?
Collector overall helps all the Strykerox ecosystem to maintain
and manage the container runtime activities as well as host level processes information.
So it's an agent that runs on every node under strict performance limitations
and gather data via the kernel module or a BPF probes.
It collects, it analyzes and monitor content activity on cluster nodes, right?
It collects information about runtime and network activity and sends
collected data to the sensor.
Sensor will help center to display all the data over the UI.
Okay, we will quickly see.
This is a traditional way of how we used to see at kernel when we
deployed the application, right?
We have user space where user application runs.
And for every resource that we need in user application,
we need system calls.
So when user requests any data, the kernel copies that information
from kernel space to user space.
But due to some limitations, it is not possible for user to access
everything that is into the kernel space, right?
And this was not a problem when we talk about a single Linux source,
but the container adoption, we know that the number of processes
that may run on a Linux source has increased,
the density of containers has increased, right?
So resource overhead managing container issues,
container runtime issues has become a great challenge.
So all these activities require kernel support that we know.
So how do we overcome that?
We can use EBPF probes.
What is that?
It is an extended bucket packet filter, right?
It is not just a packet filter.
It is more than that.
It helps us in networking, pressing, profiling,
observability and monitoring, and security.
I will quickly go ahead because of time constraint.
Then we have network policies.
In Kubernetes, we know that by default network is,
network policies are not there.
We need to define our network policies by our own.
But considering a production grid environment,
it is really difficult to write each and every network policy,
I mean, because sometimes we do not understand what source,
from what source the traffic is coming.
At large scale, it could be difficult, right?
So it provides network graph, network segmentation to understand
or to modify baselines so that we can define, okay,
if traffic is coming from this source,
then this should be blocked or network policy should be created
according to this baseline.
So this provides this.
So, yeah, we cyclops provide a network simulator,
a network policy simulator through which you can understand
what are the active connection from where the connection is coming,
whether it is allowed by the deployment or whether it is anonymous.
Accordingly, you can define your baseline and restricted traffic.
It will help us to create the network policies at the runtime.
So we can just copy that network policy
and configure it in our Kubernetes cluster.
Then we have admission controller.
So it basically helps control to enforce the security policies
before Kubernetes creates workload,
for example, deployment, demonstrates.
It intercepts the API request when any program runs
or application runs into the pod.
So in StackRocks, we use admission controller with security policies
so that any policy gets violated, then it will immediately prevent
the deployment from getting into running straight.
Okay, so I'll quickly show a demo where I have given an example
of log forces for Shell CV and to understand
how it can prevent the deployment.
Just let me show it quickly.
I hope screen is visible.
Yeah, so this is the cluster dashboard
where I can see images at the most risk,
what are the policies, current policies violated.
So StackRocks provides some default policies
as per the best practices pertaining to the security posture.
So considering the criticality of the log forces,
we have included this policy as well.
So you can configure policies into two modes,
inform as well as enforce.
So currently, if I look at this policy,
it is into inform mode only.
So I have edited it and make it enforce.
Yeah, so it executes on build stage, deployment stage.
I marked inform and enforce and enable it for the deployment phase.
So once the policy created, it will show whether any existing
deployments are violating this policy or not.
Then for the demonstration purpose,
I have run a vulnerable deployment which has this log
for Shell CV80.
So this container image has the vulnerable app.
So in the parallel terminal, I have
keep a watch to trace the events in the runtime.
So as soon as I create this deployment,
you will see that the ports are getting terminated because
of the policy violation.
So it won't allow the port to get into a running state
because of policy violation.
And in the events, you will see that stack
document enforcement has been detected,
and the deployment has been scaled to zero.
OK, time is up.
I have one more demo, quick demo, if you would like to see.
Let me know.
Quick demo, yeah.
That would be interesting.
So in this demo, I have explained how we can leverage the DevSecOps
approach to shift the security.
For that, I have used Tekton in the pipeline operator,
which is deploying an open shift.
So this operator is nothing but using Tekton framework
under the hood.
Let's see it quickly.
So it provides a standard CI-CD pipeline definition
in a declarative approach, right?
So we can define the task as well as pipeline,
which further than can be portable across all your Kubernetes
infrastructure.
So I have defined this three tasks where images,
image will be checked and scanned.
In the task, in the background, it is calling a StackRox API
through rockctl.
It's same as kubectl.
It talks with the StackRox API and performs the scanning
for the image.
So these two tasks I have mentioned in the pipeline
definition image check and image scan.
And there is one more secret where I have provided StackRox
API endpoint and the credential.
Yeah.
So we'll create a namespace called pipeline demo.
Then I have created secret as well as the pipeline definition.
Next, we will execute those tasks.
We'll switch to development mode and see that pipeline
has been defined, OK?
So these two tasks are there.
Pipeline run is not initiated yet.
So we'll initiate the pipeline run.
We'll pass the container image that we want to scan.
For example, here I have provided MySQL 80.
So pipeline has been created.
You can check the logs, real-time logs, through tecton.
It provides a client for tecton through which you can perform
the operations.
So it also gives you better visibility if in case your
tasks are failing.
For example, here my credentials were expired.
So I had to refresh the credentials and then I ran
the pipeline.
Now we will see the pipeline gets into running state.
The tasks has been passed.
Now we will see all the CV that are associated with this
particular container images.
You can get each and every CV ID, each CVSS code, and you can
accordingly share those security with the security admin.
You can also check policy violation through image check
task to understand what policies have been violated, what are
their ratings, whether those are rated as low or moderate
or risky.
Yes.
That is it.
So I have put some resources for you to go ahead and get
started with the community project.
You can also hop into our Slack channel.
And, yes, that is it from my side.
So do we have some questions here?
Thanks for the excellent presentation.
I have one question regarding you mentioned a lot about the
agent which is kind of scanning and detecting the
vulnerabilities.
You briefly touched upon the object central.
I think if I understand correctly, you pushing that
detection of vulnerabilities into the central, is that right?
Yes.
So central fetches the vulnerability feeds from the
option sources.
Or let's say you have a database.
So every five minutes it will keep on checking what
vulnerabilities are present in the option.
So accordingly, once in download, then the collector or
the sensor fetches those data into your respective
Kubernetes cluster.
So what if when the container is running, the pod is running
and suddenly the agent checks the vulnerability database and
detects possibly that the version running in the pod has
having some critical vulnerability.
What actions would it do, actually?
It actually depends on us what actions we want the admission
controller to perform.
Either we can have it in formal so that we understand, okay,
policy is violated.
But whether that is really affecting my workload or the
runtime, accordingly we can take actions.
If we want strictly not to allow any deployment to run as
soon as the policy is violated, we can put it into
enforce mode.
And we can decide at what stage we want to terminate that.
At the build stage, deploy stage, or at the runtime.
It's basically based on your policy.
Yes, yes, yes.
And the central is kind of accessible by is it like a
closed environment or it is open where anywhere anyone can
access that.
It can be configured in online mode as well as air gap
environment.
So again, it depends on your organizational requirements,
how you want to install it.
In terms of offline mode, you can always download those
vulnerability fields or kernel probes modules in your secure
host and then you can inject those to center offline.
That option is also there.
Thank you.
Any other questions?
Yes.
I just have a question.
Can you use Stack Rocks as a honey pot?
I mean, can you just let the intruder or the security thing
to go to actually get a like a description of all the things
it's doing, the attacker instead.
So let's say you not just cut it because you just right now
basically applying a policy, you're cutting the thing.
But can you let it just isolate the container and let it run
just to have four and six out of it, see how things are
behaving?
Yeah, other than policies, we can always do the risk analysis.
Sometimes it happens that vulnerability that may found
as a critical, but in terms of my application, I might not
have that vulnerable code at the runtime stage, right?
So I can always mark that vulnerability as a false
positive or I can defer that vulnerability.
Does that answer your question or you have something else?
Yeah, I mean, as long as you can get, I mean, sometimes
the scenario is that you have the port actually in production
and something happens to it and you want to actually isolate
it, but you still want to have four and six.
You don't want to just cut it.
You just want to understand the attack.
That is my...
Yeah, so in terms of isolation, it gives us a rich context
from the UI at what layer the vulnerability is present.
For example, we can inspect each and every docker layer.
It allows us to see at what component the vulnerability exists.
So you can always modify the image.
You can build it again and patch the changes.
Thank you for the question.
Thank you for the talk.
I think we are out of the time.
Thank you.