We will start, so I guess, yeah, we can start.
Hello, my name is Radovan Sorka.
I'll be presenting how to harden the system with the File Access Policy daemon.
So I'll start with the brief introduction of the framework.
Can you hear me?
Is it better?
So, FPCD is an acronym for File Access Policy daemon, and it's in a lightweight implementation
of application whitelisting.
It has many features, I will just highlight that it has integration with RPM, and it
can load some data from RPM database, and it can log events to audit or syslog, and
it heavily relies on FA notify API from kernel.
So when we look at this framework architecture, we can see several components there.
The main component of the framework is the daemon.
This daemon usually listens to this FA notify event from kernel.
When it loads up, it reads all the data from the backends, and it creates its own database,
which is called trustDB.
The first backend is RPMDB, which handles data from RPM database, or metadata, better
term.
And the second one is File backend, which loads all the trust information from user-defined
trust lists.
And there is also CLI component, which can manage trust, and also the daemon's properties.
So how does it work?
When we look closer, we can see that, at least on this image, there are two processes on
the system.
The first on the left side is Bash, and the second on the right side is FAP policy daemon.
FAP policy daemon in this situation listens for these events, and it's just waiting.
And Bash is trying to execute PS command, and it calls exactly system call.
And this execution of the system call is on hold, so it's like post.
And it's also waiting.
Meanwhile, on the other side, kernel sends an event to the daemon that something is happening
on the system.
And daemon can read from this event that there is some process called Bash, and it wants
to execute this PS command, and it has PID 500.
So it does a rules evaluation, and when the decision is allowed, it sends an effective
response to the kernel, and kernel will let this execv eventually finish with success.
If the decision was denied, then this execv will return error code.
So the daemon is the main part of the project, and it works with the rules.
There are rules and trust, and both have power over what to do with the files and their execution
of the system.
So these rules, they are pretty similar to SELinux.
They have also subject object notation, and they start with the decision part.
Decision part is it can be allow or deny, or it can be combined with syslog or audit
attribute.
The second part of the rule is permission, which can be open or exec, but that refers
to the original system call from which that event comes from, and any is placed on the
room, match both of them.
They also support this tool, because this is because FA notified us that our subject
is what is executing, and object is what is being executed.
So this trust is a very important concept here in FA policy date can be defined by user,
and it's usually done by CLI, and that there is also, or we don't have to add system binaries
or files to the trust, because they are trusted by default, they are loaded by this backend,
RPM backend.
So this is done automatically.
So when we run FA policy by default, it somehow works.
So these are some rules example.
I don't know if you see them, but the first one allows loading of trusted shared libraries
on the system, and the second one, it opposed to that, like denies untrusted libraries.
Third one will allow execution of trusted files on the system, and fourth one allows
using of scripts, which are trusted on the system, and fifth is deny this untrusted file
of scripts.
And there are two casual rules, first one is for execution of all files, and the second
is open for everything.
So they are also described here.
So when we want to install FA policy, it's very simple, we can just use normal federal
program for installation, which is called DNF, this is one liner.
When we install it, the installation consists of, it installs three packages to the system.
The first one is FA policy, which is main package, which contains daemon and CLI.
The second one is RPM plugin for FA policy, which during the RPM transactions, it sends
the new metadata that are needed for correct behavior, so it sends it to the daemon, and
then daemon can work with them, and they are up to date.
And it also notifies the daemon when the transaction ends, so the daemon can behave accordingly.
And the third one is the service package for FA policy, the service policy.
So when the installation is complete, we can start FA policy.
There are several ways how to do that.
In our examples, we will use debug deny because we are interested in the deny events, or debugging
of the deny events, and we don't need anything more.
If we would like to see also allowed events or something else, some other debug information,
it can be done via the bug option.
And when we want to run it on something more like production environment, we can use system
still.
So when we run it, FA policy will tell us that it's listening for these events, so it's
okay, and we can start playing with this.
So there are a few scenarios to demonstrate how it works.
So the first scenario is called execution of untrusted software.
So I downloaded this file, this is Python script, it's called exploit.py, and I want
to try to run it.
I make it executable, and when I run it, I can see that it's blocked, and we can see
down there that there is a deny event from FA policy that says that this exploit.py is
not trusted, so it cannot be run.
So it blocked this unknown program.
So that is it for the events.
you