Thank you.
My name is Johan Pascal.
I've been contributing on the Linphone project for the past ten years, more or less, and
going to talk about the introduction of post-contem cryptography in the voice of our IP source phone.
So quickly the agenda.
First, some context.
Then we'll dive into the RTP protocol.
And then how we had to modify it to use post-contem cryptography.
Then a few words about hybrid post-contem and classic key exchange and some conclusion.
So first, some context.
Advertising for Linphone first.
It's a project which is around for now more than 20 years.
It's available on lots of platforms.
The idea is that we have a common library and then on top of that, different applications
for different platforms.
It's tried to use at most SIP standards and everything standardized.
I have seen so on.
For audio, video, instant messaging.
We also provide secure group messaging.
It's based on a derivative of single protocol that we presented years ago.
We also provide a SIP proxy which is called Flexi SIP, also open source.
Everything is open source.
And I encourage you to use our free service on SIP which is SIP.linphone.com.
So basically, I don't know if you're familiar with VoIP, but basically you have two streams
of data.
First stream is a signaling path which connects the endpoints together.
And then you have the media stream which actually sends data, video, audio encrypted.
And this one we end to encrypt.
So how it works, there is an RFT for that and a protocol which is called SRTP.
And SRTP is symmetric encryption.
So far we are not very concerned by quantum computers.
Main problem with that is that it occupies an external command engine.
So we have to exchange our symmetric keys.
So for that we have three choices.
The historical one is called SDS.
So on this one, the keys are transmitted in the signaling path which if the signaling
path is protected, which is normally the case by TLS, is okay.
The only weakness is that the SIP proxy gets access to the symmetric keys.
So we are not actually end to end encrypted.
So basically people running the service could decrypt your media stream.
So there is another one which also gets an RFT which is called DTLS SRTP.
Basically on this one, on the media stream you perform a TLS and check, actually a DTLS
and check because it's over UDP.
And this one works well but you have to deploy PKI and you have to manage certificates for
all of your clients and everything.
So it's a bit heavy.
And also you still have to trust someone.
I mean you trust certificates, sure, but still.
And then there is another one that we favor.
Well, all three are available and in front.
But the last one which is called ZRTP, which is one we'll focus on this one today.
And this one on the media path you perform ZRTP protocol which is based on DFLMAN which
using electric curve or a simple DFLMAN.
This one has no salt part of your grade, so which is good.
The only small thing is that you have to confirm, make some kind of spicing that you have to
tell secret code on the phone.
But as you are talking, one with each other.
For the end user it's a bit an annoyance but you have to read once in the world call history
with your other endpoint.
So we think it's acceptable for users.
Obviously one has to get involved in security.
But normally it works.
The experience tells that people focused on security tends to not be driven away by this
small drawback of the protocol.
So it's an Earthie which is now more than 10 years old.
It has been mainly written by Phil Zimaman, the guy behind PGP, which are always focused
on avoiding salt parties.
And it's probably different properties.
I won't explain the key continuity and stuff because this one is unchanged.
And we'll focus on men in the middle attack detection.
So first a small reminder of what is DFLMAN.
So basically it's a protocol where it's completely symmetric.
One part, most part will generate key pair and send the exchange public keys and with
this secret key and other side public keys we'll get to share secret.
So for us it's kind of easy.
Only drawback is it's obviously vulnerable as many key exchange protocol to manage middle
attack.
So main middle attack what it is is basically someone putting herself in the middle and
exchanging keys with both sides.
Exchanging keys with both sides.
So the side cannot know, basically Alice cannot know that Eve is sending her key.
She thinks that Bob is sending the key and she performs the exchange and at the end what
you get is that Alice gets shared secret with Eve and Eve gets another shared secret with
Bob but Alice is convinced that she exchange keys with Bob and she has no ways to actually
detect this.
She has actually some ways.
No?
Yeah?
Okay.
Yeah, sorry.
So the RTPN check is the first phase of discovery.
So what is happening is both endpoints will exchange their capability, their choice of
preferred algorithm stuff like this and then start the actual RTPN check.
So first you have one packet of commit.
I will go into detail now and then you actually perform the DHL man exchange.
So Alice is sending her key, Bob is sending his and they both compute from this.
They will compute the shared secret and adding all the transcript of the communication they
will generate S0 which is a base secret, the output of the RTPN check.
From the S0 they will derive the SRTP keys which what we are trying to do now here and
they also derive some single SAS short authentication string that will be vocally compared over
the phone because we are, Alice and Bob are actually talking to each other.
So the end of the protocol is just some updates and writing in cache for key continuity mechanisms
and stuff that's not really interesting now.
Then after that the SRTP streams start actually and they can talk.
And once they start to talk, once in the cold story they will do this vocal SAS comparison.
What is it for?
The SAS comparison is basically if they want to detect man in the middle attacks they have
to ensure that Alice is using keys that Bob are sent and also Bob want to know that the
key that was sent by Alice is the one he actually got.
So what they could do as they are talking, they could basically read the own keys to
the other.
But the key is something which is few hundred bytes so it's a bit long to read few hundred
bytes of hexadecimal chain over the phone.
No one would do that.
So what they do instead we derive this short authentication strings which is only four
digits and has 20 bits actually derived from 20 bits.
And this SAS is also derived from the SQL 0 which is output of the protocol.
The only problem with that is that you can actually perform a SAS collision with that
because the SAS is very short.
How it would work?
So actually the beginning of the protocol as soon as Alice sent a public key to Bob,
Bob is able to compute S0 because he has his own secret key and he is able to compute the
SAS then.
So what one could do is that if you perform first the RTP exchange with Alice, she got
the SAS one and then she receives Bob's public key.
When she got Bob's public key she can generate a huge set of key pairs until she finds a
SAS that collide.
Basically she will try a lot of, she generates the pairs.
SAS is only 20 bits so if you generate one million keys and try all them you will for
sure find the collision of the SAS.
So to prevent this, Eve is forced to send a commit packet.
In the commit packet what we have we do not have a public key but we have a hash of the
public key.
And so when you receive the hash of the public key Alice will receive for example Bob's hash
public key, she will store it and then when Bob sets the public key she will compare,
she will just hash Bob's public key and she will compare so that way she is sure that
Bob did not wait for receiving a public key and cannot generate millions of key pairs
to find the collision on the SAS.
So this is quite effective and so far so good.
Now we want to switch to using, to use post-pon-tomb cryptography.
Problem with post-pon-tomb is that on the NIST call for standardization they required
all the algorithm to use key encapsulation mechanism and not deferment.
So key encapsulation mechanism is a bit different because there are two sides that are not the
same.
In deferment the two sides were exactly doing the same thing.
They are both generating keys, exchanging public keys and then computing secrets.
There we have one side generating keys, one side encapsulating the key a secret and the
other side will be able to de-capsulate the secret that was encapsulated by the first
one.
So it's not symmetric so we cannot switch directly from deferment to KM form of key exchange.
Obviously KM is still vulnerable to man-in-the-middle attack because nothing has changed.
You can still put someone in the middle and perform the exchange with the other side without
them knowing.
So what we have to do is adapt the RTP and change a little bit the actual handshake,
the central part of the protocol.
So S0 is still derived from the exchange secret and transcript of all the conversation.
I got only commit and two packets but you also have a little packet and stuff.
So in the commit packet the one which used to hold only the hash of the H part of the
second packet from Bob, Bob will now insert his public key.
Why do we do that?
So Alice can encapsulate the secret.
So at this point Alice receives the public key from Bob, she encapsulates the secret
but at this point she is not able to compute S0 because she is missing the second packet
from Bob.
So she will send back the ciphertext so they will put off the encapsulation and at this
point she has the shared secret from the encapsulation but she cannot compute S0.
Bob now receives the shared secret and he can't compute S0 but he already committed
on the H part 2 that he has to send to Alice so still he cannot manipulate the final secret
S0.
And what is in this packet?
It's just a random number that is used once.
So now another problem is that we don't want to focus only on using only a post-quantum
algorithm because we know that sometimes they got broken like for example SIKE which was
broken a bit late in the standardization process.
So it might happen or not in the future so to protect against this weakness, it's possible
weakness, we still want to use a mix of post-quantum and a classic algorithm.
So we'll use both at the same time and in order to not complexify the protocol too much,
the idea is to have one version of the protocol which is being different and the other one
a key encapsulation mechanism and the other one, the protocol won't know exactly if it's
using a mix or not because probably in the future at some point we'll be confident in
us with some post-quantum algorithm and then we'll stop using the classical one, maybe
or not but still the protocol should not be modified at this point.
So protocol is done to use a Kyrium interface without even knowing if it is a mix of classical
and post-quantum or just post-quantum or several post-quantum.
So we made first we have to make a Kyrium interface from a different, this is quite
a standard construction, you can directly use the Diffie-Lman construction to generate
Kipir, then you can send your public key to the other side, the other side will encapsulate,
how would the other side do that?
It would just generate a Kipir for Diffie-Lman, compute the Diffie-Lman and then hash it with
the transcript of the exchange and send back its public key to the other side.
So the capture is quite obvious, same thing on the other side.
And then we combine two or more Kipirms together, so one we just built from a classical Diffie-Lman
or electric Kipir with post-quantum one.
So this way of doing it has been published by Nina Binder, sorry I don't know how to
pronounce the name.
A few years ago, so it's a bit convoluted but if you want more details on why we are
doing this I encourage you to read the paper, it's quite interesting.
So basically what you do, you want to generate the Kipir, you generate Kipir for sets of
algorithms and my example is there, it's only two but you can do more of that and send concatenated
both public keys or all the public keys to the other side.
The encapsulation will just split your public keys to retrieve the individual ones and perform
the encapsulations on all the components.
Then you use hashmax to combine your results, chaining it, so first you combine key one
and then key two and you can add several layers there and the final step is to use the transcript
of all the public keys you received and the encapsulation is completely symmetric.
The paper from Nina Binder is quite clear on why this step is handed, I have no time
to explain it here.
Few more words, we also tweaked the protocol packets because in the D-field man form, the
size you can get is around few hundred bytes but if you start using Kipir for example or
Hqc, the one you will use, you reach several kilobytes and several kilobytes you cannot
send in one datagram of UDP, it's not possible to probably want to arrive.
So what we have to add is a way of fragment the RTP packet, so it's kind of classical
way as just as DTL, C2, or other protocols using UDP.
The only thing is that we made it in a way that packets are not fragmented and the header
is modified but if it's not needed the packet remains exactly the same than the old packet.
The objective in this was to be able to start deploying the new version of the RTP but still
keep compatibility with the old one, old deployment.
So how it's done, in the end we use crypto libraries, Libokus which is from the Open
Quantum Safe project which basically collects all the NIST candidates and Kiber also which
is no more candidate in a convenient way and we use libdecaf and then embed TLS for the
ECDH and hashback functions that we need.
So we've packed it all in an independent module, so our RTP library will use this module but
it's completely independent actually from it so if anyone want to directly use this
hybrid KMM mixing varieties of first quantum and classic exchange it's fully available.
You can combine usually more than two KMMs as it was printed, it's written in Safe Displussed
and in our RTP implementation we deployed it with some already preset combination so
we have X, well you can see them, we tried to mix algorithms with more or less the same
level of security for mixing Kiber R5.12 with X250, this one and it is, as I said before,
fully compatible with the old version so the deployment is progressive, it's basically
in the agreement phase at the beginning if one, if most parties support this version
of the RTP with this algorithm they will use it, if one is old and don't support it they
will just fall back on a classical deployment or electrical deployment.
So just how it looks like, so first you have the RTP and check going and the call is starting
and once the call is started if it's the first one the two endpoints are calling each other
you will get a pop-up that asks you to confirm the security string so most parties will just
confirm it if more or less just say it on the phone, it's written like you have to say
this, the other one confirms you said what is expecting to say and you confirm it then
this will be saved in the RTP cage and we will never be asked again to do that.
During at any time during the call you can check on the call stats and see what kind
of algorithm we use to perform the exchange so on the screenshots you see that it was
using Kiber R5.12 and X250.19.
We have some links just if some of you download the presentation towards the Linfone website
directly pointing to the GitLab where you can find the source code of both the RTP and
our post-contour crypto module and to the publication from Nia Binder explaining how
to hybrid several types.
Here we are, thank you for your attention.
So we've got time for questions and I've got one question on metrics and there is a question
why post-quantum encryption is not enabled in the pre-compiled Linfone SDK?
Sorry, I didn't.
Why the post-quantum encryption is not enabled in the pre-compiled Linfone SDK?
It is now.
It is now?
It is now, okay.
Based on the record.
Yes, sorry.
Hi, given that we are dealing with threat actors that might be capable of dealing, you
know, cracking quantum cryptography.
Sorry.
Okay, given that we are dealing with threat actors that might have a lot of resources,
it seems like one particular attack factor might be to essentially use real-time deep
hate technology to intercept the vocal SAS comparison.
Do you see any particular mitigation for an attack like that?
Well, some kind of attack like this has been already studied and published.
So basically what came out of what I found is that it's kind of easy to use pitch and
detail to synthesize the voice of someone else.
As main problem there would be to insert the SAS at the right moment in conversation without
adding a huge delay in the conversation so that people won't be able to talk.
Basically, if you had like two to three second delays because you have to analyze the signal
and like buffer it to be able to instant back your SAS, people won't talk with three to
four second delays.
There is no way people will talk.
I agree.
I think it's going to be very difficult to do something like that in real time, but I
think that's probably, you know, because your solution looks really, really solid in terms
of being able to fix it like that, so it looks like that might be one of the weaker aspects
of it.
But it's a...
Since now I've been trying to monitor the publication on the subject and I never found
someone able to publish an actual attack on the RTP working really.
So it might depend on some point.
That's great.
Thank you.
Can we be quiet to ask questions, please?
I think I missed it, but then in this particular method that you are doing, is it actually
trusting the middle server that you're using or is it using keys from another like a phone
or something, SIP assuming?
Is this running with the SIP protocol you said?
Wait, I'm sorry, I cannot...
Hello.
The sound is very low.
Better, yes.
Yeah.
I wanted to ask if this was being used with a mobile phone to connect to the SIP server
and then use post quantum cryptography as you demonstrate.
Can you go back to the two slides before this?
Yeah.
That's one.
Yeah, so the phone, is it actually trusting the server which is running or is it like
the end-to-end, the actual key is being checked with the other host?
Yeah, this is the main point of the RTP that basically the idea is to not trust anyone,
not your server.
So server will be in charge of connecting the two phones and then the media will go
directly from one to the other one.
The media pass will go straight from one phone to another one and it won't go through the
server.
That's why the RTP exchange is performed on the media pass and not on the SIP signaling
pass.
When you establish a connection, actually, you go through ICE protocol, I don't know
if you're familiar with that, which basically find a way to connect directly because at
the end, you don't want the media to be relayed because you lose too much time.
You have to send media packets directly from one endpoint to the other endpoint.
Hi.
You said that you have to compare the SAS only once.
Yeah.
Is it once per phone or once per user?
It's one per endpoint.
Basically in each endpoint, you have a cache of previous, each time you end the RTP exchange,
you'll keep some shared secret that you'll use the next time.
And so during the exchange, at some point you will compare the shared secret and if
they are the same, you use them to compute a SAS, which is always a verb.
You can always ask to compare the SAS, but it won't pop because the protocol will know
that you performed the exchange before, but it just went from one phone to another phone.
This cache is not shared.
Okay.
So in practical terms, if I buy a new phone and I install the same app with the same account,
I have to do it again.
You have to do it again with all your respondents.
Okay.
Thanks.
We've got time for our last question.
Is there any other last question?
If not, thank you for your call.
Thank you.
Always a pleasure.