We have to do with the six store.
Hello everyone, my name is James Strong and we're going to talk about rugby and six store
today.
But something's really interesting is happening today right now.
So Seven Nations started today and Wales and Ireland explained.
What's the score right now, Lewis?
I think we should concentrate on the talk.
I think it would be most enjoyable.
Last time we checked it was 327 Ireland.
Where are you from?
Wales.
Anyway, awesome.
So, like I said, my name is James Strong.
I'm a solutions architect at Chain Guard.
I do a bunch of stuff with networking and Kubernetes.
And if you're here to win the book, meet me outside afterwards.
If you sign a container image during the talk and come hang out with me, I've got five copies
of my book.
So sign your container images, everyone.
And if I broke your Ingress Engine X release on Thursday, I apologize.
Please don't come outside and hang out with me.
Hi everyone, I'm Lewis.
I'm similar to James and Wales, not in others.
As well as being at Chain Guard, I'm the coach for Rubina Squirrel's Under 8 Rugby Team.
That's why you're listening today to a talk about Six Door and Rugby from myself.
If you wouldn't mind keeping the score away from me with Wales versus Ireland right now,
that would be beneficial for my own sanity.
Yes, next slide, please.
So at Chain Guard, we support a lot of open source projects.
We're talking today about Six Door, but we're also part of CELSA, doing some assessments
here.
We've got Tekton, Knative, OpenSSF, and DistroRes.
Does anybody use any or all of those?
I do.
There's a couple of them that aren't listed, like I said, Ingress Engine X.
Chain Guard supports me to support Ingress.
We also have our own container image out there.
It's called Wolfie.
You can check that out, wolfie.dev.
But like I said, we're going to talk about Six Door and Rugby today.
Okay, so who here has heard of Six Door prior to walking into this room?
Okay, we've got a couple.
Thank you for coming.
Who here has heard of Rugby today prior to coming into this room?
Yes, hello.
All right.
So, when we submitted this talk, James found this very special diagram.
And when we zoom in, we can see the similarities between Six Door and Rugby for this talk.
Incidentally, this lasts about 22 minutes, hence why we've had such a long introduction.
So what do people think Rugby is?
It's really not doing a haka.
It looks cool and intimidates your opponents, but that's not really what it is.
It's a very difficult game with highly specialized positions.
And it all was required to help everyone work together to achieve a goal.
And that's really what we think Six Door is and what we want to talk about.
So there's lots of components about it.
And we think that Six Door is tackling supply chain security.
And we're going to talk about how, why, and hopefully make it fun along the way and learn
a little bit about Rugby and Six Door and probably a lot about neither.
So why is Six Door tackling supply chain security?
It has started to improve the supply chain technology that we all use.
It's made by open source maintainers for open source maintainers.
A lot of you may not be aware, but a lot of things are being signed right now.
So thank you to Adulfo there from SIG release for signing all of the Kubernetes releases
with SIG store.
Thank you.
That was a lot of hard work.
I know PyPy, a lot of package maintainers are going to be supporting that.
I know Maven, so there's a lot of people that are using SIG store.
You might not even be aware that you're using it, but it's a direct response to some of
the challenges that are there right now.
So who here has had someone else sign their GPG key?
Been through a signing party?
Two, three people?
Four?
Okay.
I was really glad not everyone shot their hand up because that would have been really
fun.
Anyway, we're going to talk about how we're going to be doing that.
Not knowing where your software comes from, and without having identity checks and safety
protocols, it's leaving our, well, we're leaving it open to exploits and attacks.
So SIG store attempts to make software and their infrastructure frictionless and invisible.
And as James just mentioned, we're integrated with a wide range of systems.
... to an identity and know where it came from and who made that piece of software.
And just like in SIG store, rugby also has lots of positions that are available, highly
specialized.
I play a hooker.
That's much different than what a full backward do.
We all have different responsibilities to be able to win the game.
So we're going to tie those two together.
I'm going to start off at the very top of the play.
So we're going to talk about trust roots.
So with signing, it requires trust.
So knowing who is making available this piece of software.
So think of it from a PKI perspective.
We have a root of trust in SSL certificates.
What we're also trying to accomplish with SIG store is that same root of trust.
So think of automated software for SSL certificates.
I was thinking of Johnny Sexton.
Oh, Johnny Sexton.
That's not the answer.
But think of it from that perspective.
So SIG store has a root of trust.
It was initialized with tough.
So the update is...
Let's encrypt.
Thank you.
Thank you for that.
Let's encrypt.
Think about SIG store as let's encrypt for software signing artifacts, making it easy
and transparent for everyone to use.
So the fly half is very influential player on the field.
And in order to start that root of trust, we have to have that trust there.
So there's a bunch of links there.
We actually did a live stream of the SIG store key signing.
If you want to figure out how they initialize that and did all that work, there's a great
YouTube video from that.
So going from the fly half to the loose head, from a play perspective, they're going to
be the certificate authority.
So now we've got our root of trust.
We have our certificate authority to be able to produce those certificates to sign those
artifacts.
So a lot of responsibility is on the CA from that perspective.
And of course, being a loose head, you carry a lot of weight on the team.
You're very important into the scrum.
So again, very important position on the team.
So OITC allows us to identify the end user.
We obtain some basic information about the user.
And falsely use this OITC to authenticate requests.
Subject related claims can be extracted and included on the certificate.
SIG store runs a federated OITC identity provider in DEX, which creates a DEX OITC token from
the original OITC.
False code supports OITC from additional configured users, as we can see from the screen shot.
And the play that we selected for this was Martin Kasrujevani.
Does anyone know of Martin Kasrujevani?
No?
Okay.
Well, there's something to learn today.
He's a massive identity within the Italian game, even though he's originally from Argentina.
And the reason I selected him is because you can identify him because of his sleep with
all the identities of his family members on his arm.
Next slide.
And so now we've come to false seal.
False seal is the API that drives all of this, that ties the OITC and the certificate at
the OIT together.
So when you're making a request to get a signing certificate, you're doing it through false
seal.
And you put that together with the hooker, and yes, I was self-serving, that is me.
And do feel sorry for that guy.
So false seal is a free code signing certificate authority.
Anyone can make a request to get a signing certificate, tie it to their identity, and
make it available for everyone to verify.
They are short-lived certificates, so that's going to come into play from another piece
of technology perspective.
We're going to talk a little bit more about that with ReCore.
So with ReCore, it provides a mutability with ephemeral certificates.
It's based on a Merkle tree, and it fulfills the transparency log, which means that it's
searchable for all.
So you can use that URL there to be able to search via your browser, or you can use ReCore
CLI to be able to search.
So for this one, I'm looking towards Martin Johnson.
Again as a Welsh person, for putting all these names out, it was quite difficult for me.
But Martin Johnson was a powerhouse for England.
He was a captain who led them to numerous victories.
The reason why this is comparable to ReCore is he went on to a successful coaching career
as well, providing insights for the next generation that has to hire to play the game.
Yes, next slide, please.
So we want to take some time and talk a little bit about how a developer interacts with that.
So when we think about it from a rugby perspective, the scrum half is the connector between the
forwards and the backs from that perspective.
And cosign is that glue that ties all of these pieces together.
Think of it like kubectl, right?
You don't actually directly interact with the API.
You do it through kubectl.
Cosign is how you do that with Palsio and ReCore and the rest of the other six-door environment.
So you can actually sign and verify signatures.
It also creates in-toto attestation.
So if you wanted to generate and sign other metadata about your container images, maybe
how many CVEs are in it, if you're generating an S-bomb, things like that, other metadata
you can make available, sign it and store it with the container.
All of that can be done through cosign.
And we're not talking about just container images as well.
That's where it's highly targeted right now.
But you can also sign other pieces of information.
So when I send, as for fun, when I send documents to clients nowadays, I also sign it and it
generates the hash of the document and the signature and they know that that document
came from me.
So it's basically a free DocuSign.
So this is Gareth Edwards.
He was an influential player in the 70s, played 88 consecutive games for Wales and one of
the key reasons to our success in the 70s, not so much in the 2020s.
And yes, Scrum Halfness instrumental in communicating between the backs and the forwards within
a game, which I can also see with cosign.
Not necessarily cosign in rugby, but yes.
Next slide.
Yes Canada.