the security room. Um next speaker is Dimitri Veljatski. He's talking about OpenCell in
RAL, uh FIPS 140-3 certification. Hello, do you hear me well? Yeah, looks like that. Uh first, who am I? My name is Dimitri
Veljatski. I work in Red Hat as a senior software engineer. I also am OpenCell Committer since
the year 2019 and since the year 2021 I am a member of OpenCell Committer since the year
2019. I'm a member of OpenCell Technical Committee. It's a group of people that manage the project,
the OpenCell project from the technical point of view. My beloved pet project is also related
to OpenCell. It's Russian ghost script implementation. Okay, let's go to the topic. First, what we
shall speak in the first part is what's FIPS, what's FIPS certification, what's certified
from FIPS for FIPS in Red Hat and the OpenCell brief introduction into OpenCell 3.0 architecture
changes. So FIPS is a set of standards, American national standards, requiring which cryptography
and in which limitations should be used. It consists of a series of documents. Some documents
are available public. Some should be bought in the NIST. Some should be bought in the ESO.
These documents are permanently updated. So you should consider the FIPS set of documents
as a code of laws. It is as consistent as code of laws. It leaves subspace for interpretation.
Nobody knows it all. So there are always discussions how to interpret this or that point of the
document. So on and so forth. FIPS certification process is done by some accredited labs that
get the sources from some company that pretends that the code is certifiable. So the code
is set up. They do quite comprehensive tests. Some of them are public. Some of them are not.
Then they return back to us with notes like you should fix this and that. Then we go to
the next iteration. And then the process, if we are lucky, we get the FIPS certificate.
FIPS certificate is necessary for using system in many American government institutes for
many big customers. And again, it provides very good recommendation from security points of view.
So if you use FIPS certified software, it means that you are on the safe side from the security
point of view. Current version of the standard is FIPS 140. That's the first version of the
standard is FIPS 140.3. We in Red Hat certify our distributions for FIPS for several versions.
We usually certify our kernel and several crucial libraries such as an SS, a LIGGICRETE,
LIGGIT, LIGGIT, LIS, and of course OpenSSL. We have a nice blog post explaining what
we certified for Ralot 8. And the approach for Ralot 9 will be basically the same. It's
still ongoing process. So sorry, it's always a problem how to properly add a link in the
presentation. I believe that you can download the presentation from slide or just find the
blog post by the title.
The support of FIPS in OpenSSL has a long history. It has native support in 1.0 series of OpenSSL,
which is currently long out of support. In 1.0 series, there was a set of invasive
runtime checks. If we are in FIPS mode, then please do that. This algorithm is allowed,
this is not, and so on and so forth. Upstream did not provide the native support in 1.1.1
series, but we had explained the original patches. So FIPS support in OpenSSL 1.1.0
series in Ralot was basically a set of patches for libcrypt and libSSL with even more invasive
runtime checks. In OpenSSL 3.0, 3.0, the upstream decided that the model with invasive checks
is badly maintainable, and they redesigned the architecture from scratch and created
so-called provider models. All algorithms are implemented via separate plugins named
provider, and one of these providers, the most important for our purpose is the FIPS one
that contains only FIPS compatible algorithms that build from the same sources with compile
time checks. It's individual library, so we also simplify only this library, not libcrypt
or libSSL as a whole, that also simplifies the process of applying some changes. And
to be sure that you are FIPS compatible, you should use only relevant API, and it costs
a massive open access API duplication in 3.0. So if you pretend that your application is
FIPS compatible, please don't use deprecated API. If you are a software developer, just
add the warning for using a deprecated API. So now let's talk about our patches. Upstream
FIPS provider was designed to match previous version of the FIPS 140-2, and we wanted to
adjust it so it would match FIPS 140-3. Let's begin with the initialization of the library.
Upstream approach implies that FIPS provider is loaded via configuration file, and the
checksum, which is necessary to be sure that provider is the same we want to use, is a part
of this configuration file. This approach was found suboptimal for our purposes because
we can detect that the system as a whole is in FIPS mode. So when we see that Red Hat-based
system is in FIPS mode, we automatically load and activate the FIPS provider. We also get
rid of external checksum. We embed the checksum into the provider, and it significantly reduces
the problem when the checksum is in a separate file or in the integration file. It can be
damaged or just forgotten to copy the file, and it causes unpredictable diagnostics. So
when you have checksum embedded into the provider, everything is much simpler from a maintainability
point of view. And also we removed several algorithms from the FIPS provider. Well, I
will speak about it some minutes later, some slides later. What is the next change we implemented
in our FIPS provider is indicators. Indicators is a new requirement of FIPS 140-3 standard.
We have too many algorithms. They can be combined in too many ways, and not all of the combinations
are approved. So we should use only approved combinations. First, well, there are two possible
approaches. We call it implicit indicators and explicit indicators. The implicit indicators
implies that if you perform the crypto operation and it succeeded, then you are on the safe
side. Unfortunately, as I mentioned before, some combinations of permitted crypto algorithms,
crypto primitives are not permitted by FIPS as a whole. So we had to partly switch to explicit
indicators. The approach with explicit indicators is you try a crypto operation. If you failed,
assuming it was properly set up, then it wasn't approved. If it succeeded, then you probably,
it's well-documented, should check the indicator and see if it's permitted from the FIPS point
of view. Well, this approach is better from several points of view. First, it covers the
caveats when you have a legal combination. And second, well, in real life software, you can use
FIPS non-approved cryptogarism for non-cryptographical purposes, such as MD5 for as a fast enough
cache sub of files. So application knows better what is the purpose of the algorithm usage
sometimes. So we implemented some combination of explicit and implicit indicators. And some
implementation details. Well, we removed the adverse curves from our provider. It was done
because when we were tuning our provider, adverse curves were not permitted for usage in FIPS,
but well, the use of yesterday, the standard that allowed using adverse curves, curve 255.19
and the curves, curve AD448 are permitted. So we probably will have to consider if we
switch these curves on or we'll switch it in some upcoming versions because there is much interest
to discuss. We also removed support of RSA-PQC-S1 encryption in FIPS provider, which is potentially
breaking changes and we are aware of some of our applications that have had to change the RSA
encryption model from PQC-S1 to OAP. And we removed the triple S support from FIPS provider.
One more change we had to implement, also a requirement of new FIPS standard is switching
to non-unser tests for the RSA signatures. The RSA signatures require using a random number,
so every new signature has a different value if you properly implemented the algorithm.
If you use the same random values for the signature, it means the attacker will be able to find out
your private key, so it's dangerous. So we had to add a patch that allows in the test mode
specifying well-known hard-coded random value just for test purposes. We know that upstream
in its upcoming version of the provider used a different approach. They used the predictable
random number generator and probably it's a better approach, we will think about it on some
respine of our certification. Also, new standard implies some strict changes for key derivation
functions. It limits the seeds. You should not use the seeds shorter than 112 bits for
most of the KDF functions. And also it specifies sub-requirements to accept the random number
generators which were not implemented in the upstream provider, so only shell2 functions
are basically allowed for the hash-based random number generators, and all providers support
these requirements. One more change worth mentioning is that according to the 5th 140-3
requirements, it's necessary to clean up memory not only after using private keys but also
for public keys, and there should be consistency checks for freshly generated public keys from private keys.
And the last two points is about other patches in RHEL that are not related directly to FIPS.
They are about overall hardening. We have implemented so-called crypto policies in RHEL 8.
It's a way to ensure that all the crypto libraries and all the applications using these crypto libraries
are consistent from the point of view of algorithms that are permitted to use.
Also, as the FIPS 140-3 standard requires formal allows using shavanko signatures, we remove the support
of it in our FIPS provider because of, well, you can't really rely on security properties of shavanko.
And it may cause problems to application developers, and some application developers have already complained about it.
But please don't use shavanko signatures. It's just and secure.
Okay, thank you. Thank you for your invitation. Feel free to ask questions about the details.
Hey, so you said you're using the provider API for the FIPS stuff. Now, what I was wondering, not all of the
OpenSSL API gets routed through the provider, right? So what I'm doing about packages like SSH that are using
old API, those don't work with FIPS, right?
Well, yes, not all the application use the new API. I correctly understand your question.
Well, my question is, to use that, I need to use the new EVP underscore API, right?
Well, yes, you need to use the EVP underscore API, but it's, well, I don't think you should call it new because it exists for more than 10 years.
That's right. But as like OpenSSL does not use that.
Yes, it's my pain as a maintainer of OpenSSL. We are writing OpenSSL in downstream to use the new API to make it FIPS compatible.
Oh, yeah, that's what I wanted to know. Thanks.
In which of your Red Hat distribution are you supporting this and I guess you don't have backwards compatibility with older applications for OpenSSL.
It only works with FIPS compliant applications, right?
Sorry? Again?
Yeah. Which of your Red Hat distribution supports the FIPS standard? One.
And two, how do you do with backwards compatibility because I guess applications that are not FIPS compliant won't run with your OpenSSL API.
So I'm talking now about a real nine series, but we have we have certificates for a real eight series for a previous version of the standard.
For about the application that use all the PI. Well, as I mentioned before, it's a common approach to provide downstream patches and pull this patches upstream to make this to make the application use the new API.
It's the only possible way. Well, I participated in pushing libfido2 for example, we have downstream patches for OpenSSL, but it also should be libfido2 compatible and it adds problem.
But the general approach is to implement a downstream patch and push it upstream.
Okay. Any other questions? Hands up. No one.
Okay. Thank you very much. Feel free to contact me directly.
Thank you.
Thank you. Much nice.