Okay, so hello everyone. We'll start in a minute. The talk will have 20 minutes and
after that there will be space for questions. If you have questions, please write them into
the metrics room or we will try to run around with the mic. So thank you all for coming
and I will give a word to Alexander Bocovoy who will have the first presentation about
enabling FIDO for remote-limonaged users. Yes. Thank you, Jakob. Thank you everyone
who came today in this drizzle day into a room that is not so easy to find. Let's fight
security with obscurity. Okay. The talk I'm giving here is actually, it was supposed to
be done by Iker who drives this effort at Red Hat. And I have another talk in the afternoon
in the main tracks about passwordless Linux, where we are. This is part of it, but not
the full stuff. So it's kind of a preview of where we are, hopefully with demos and
without demo effect. Let's go. I hope I will be able to get something working. Nice. My
laptop actually locked up. Really? Yeah, I'm trying. It doesn't want to. Okay. Okay.
We'll get there. No, no, no. So the fun part is this is old laptop. This is really old
laptop. My actual laptop got the battery puffed up. So it literally looks like this. It's
sort of a hat, right? Here we're working there. But it means that I cannot fly with that kind
of laptop. And this one is maybe six or seven years old. So it's a bit surprisingly slow
for contemporary software. We have Putin Fedor. Okay. So the old, this talk about is about
a very simple thing. Basically, this is the hardware incorporation of what people call
nowadays as a PUS key or web orphan, which is known as FIDO tool set of specifications.
And actually we start with a small demo, right? If I get the screen working. Okay. I'm not
getting, I don't know what you see there. Maybe you're not seeing anything, but I actually
was able to log in with this token. And what I will be talking about is how I actually
get it. Let's see. Yeah. Yeah. This is the, because I logged in without password, the
storage manager asks me to enter the password to unlock the storage manager, not the, not
to log in with the password. That's another part of the stuff that we have to fix before
we will be able to get into the Linux without all the passwords. Okay. Let me get to the
top. It's really slow. Given. I really hope to get this working. Okay. So, I'm going to
get it. Yay. Finally. So, some time ago, we at Red Hat working on the identity management
on security on the stuff like free AP and SSDS. We started looking into a couple things.
One of them is the how we can get passwordless into our systems. Mostly we talk about remote
service and because that's what most of our customers are using. And many of those customers
started asking about the thing that sort of required them to be enforced for them from
the governments and so on. So, one of those things that is forced is FIDO2 or WebAuth
because well, everybody else supports it. Where everybody else means all these web applications,
all the other operating systems like Microsoft Windows and the others. And, of course, there
are properties that related to this. They are all nice. But the reality is that you
get all of this nicely working mostly in browsers. At least on Linux. And not in all browsers.
Some browsers do not support WebAuth and workflows. Some do. But we need to get these logins into
the actual systems. Because if you are not able to log in into these systems, you cannot
use this passwordless thing. And, of course, from the technical point of view, it's a combination
of some PAM modules and some changes to applications and so on. It shouldn't be that hard, right?
So, there are already PAM modules that implement this. The problem is that if you look at this
from systematic point of view, if you manage thousands of hosts where you need to get access
with the credentials stored somewhere, you need better than just everything defined on
the single machine. So, we started looking into what we have. We have centralized identity
management with free IPA. We have SSDS on the client side that allows to query these
different identity management and so on. So, we started looking at what we can create all
of this. And we wanted to enable use of Fido 2 in the console for these remote managed
users. We start with local authentication. This is what works now. It didn't work a couple
weeks ago. We already have some progress. And the second part will be remote authentication,
but with a twist. Because all the things like remote authentication using native SSH, for
example, protocol, it's really not about this. It's not compatible with the local use of
the Fido 2. It encapsulates some of the principles, but it converts kind of user or assertion
of the Fido 2 into a different form specific to SSH and cannot be reused for anything else.
So, the reality is that's coming from where all these governmental admins or big organizations
admins are getting the pressure from. This pressure came actually a year ago in the form
of what they call zero trust memorandum. The zero trust memorandum is effectively announced
by the executive office of the president of United States to the set of threats that they
got over the last decade or visualized at least in public. So, this memorandum basically
states by the end of fiscal year 2024, a number of things should happen in the governmental
organizations. There are, I think, five big targets that they have to go. And one of these
targets is to switch to passportless everywhere. And to say the truth, governmental organizations
in the U.S. already using passportless form with smart cards. But WebAuthn is called
out as one of the recommended ways of doing it in the memorandum. So, zero trust memorandum
says that basically you have to use either personal identity verifications or smart cards,
we already support that, and WebAuthn is another approach. And go there. There you go. You
see the customers or prospective customers getting pressure from those who drive them,
who give the budgets and so on. And then these customers come to Red Hat and all other companies
and ask to get this working because they have to comply. Not ask comply with this, but the
customers comply with this. The lucky part we have is that all of this actually in the
interest also of the community because, well, it simply improves our state. Not only at
work, but also at home. If we switch to passportless, everywhere we get a bit secure environment,
I hope, given the practices that we preach to at home. But this is the part. So, if you
have remotely managed users, basically define somewhere centralized your accounts, your
POSIX identity, your home directory, your shell and so on, somewhere should be defined
which passwordless credentials you can use. These credentials should be delivered locally.
And if you have a device like this one or maybe the one on the phone, which we do not
support yet, it needs to be verified. It needs to be engaged with applied and so on. And
in this centralized environment, we often have to deal with the fact that you are not
only logging into the single machine, you are jumping somewhere. You are interacting
with other applications. Typically, this transfer of authentication state happens through a
transition from your local authentication to something like Kerberos, which issues a
ticket recording your authenticated state and then uses this ticket to issue other tickets
to other services in the environment that's being built. So, on the high level, in principle,
all the stuff that we deal with in FreeAP and SSD already. For FIDO2, we kind of, this
is the new thing for us, but we use the FIDO2 library that's already existing and shipped
in many distributions for the implementation of the FIDO2 stuff. We store the data at the
LDAP server and fetch there, that's SSD Excel set. And the other part is we integrate with
FreeAP Kerberos implementation to provide the transition from FIDO2 to Kerberos. So,
for the local authentication, what happens is that you have the SSD running on the machine,
it picks up the user information from LDAP record for that user. Part of that record
is the specification of the passkey record, the details, pretty much like in the traditional
way you store them somewhere on the disk, but here you store them remotely. Then, when
token is added and there is a need to log in over PAM, any PAM service, you get a lip
FIDO2 communication with the device and performing its magic, comparing with the record that
you have. So, in LDAP this looks like this. I intentionally included a bunch of stuff
here, but literally all we care about is that we have this passkey attribute and obviously
in LDAP it's a structured store, so you have to have an object class that defines the use
of this attribute. And on IPA level this looks like this. There is a user information which
also has this passkey mapping. This is not in the released version of IPA yet. Hopefully
by, I hope by spring we will get this, but later I will show you where you can get the
test version. So, in IPA case only you get after this login which is currently not working,
so you get a Kerberos ticket. This is how I have a lot of view how it goes in. The presentation
is available on the side, so I'm not focusing on describing these details, but effectively
we extended MIT Kerberos implementation to allow us to communicate with the KDC all these
details related to web often implementation. So, behind KDC on free IPA server we have
relay and party implementation that performs part of this authentication and then uses
Kerberos protocol to transfer the bits between the two sides. So, test it. So, this is actually
a demo of what I kind of ran before I got my presentation working. So, this is the login
screen this morning. And to unlock I have to insert this passkey and press enter. You
don't see the full message because it's so large compared to the actual input string
that GDM shows. Then I just activate the device and magic happens. I log in. How you can play
with this yourself if you want to set up, Iker wrote some instructions in this blog
post and he maintains copper for Fedora. Fedora 36 and 37 at this point. So, you can
get SSDS packages. There is one package that is not installed by default. This is exactly
the support for FIDO2. Then you need to enable it in the SSDS configuration. But if you follow
Iker's instructions, you should get it working. Right now it only works with free IPA because
we have free IPA from that corporate because it has the support for storing passkeys in
the old app server. Okay. And I will stop here because I have like three minutes and
I would like to hear any questions and feedback. This is sort of early stage. I will show a
bit more in the afternoon with the bigger presentation that they have at the main track.
There will be a bit more demos there. But we really would love to hear your feedback
and what you want to see it working there. I have a question. So, what happens if the
key is lost or stopped working or something like that? So, what happens if the key is
lost or stops working because it's a hardware that might blow up, right? That totally depends
on how the system is defined. If the system is defined to allow fallback to other passkeys
or it's allowed to use a different authentication method to fall through to those methods will
happen. If you want to, if the key is lost, for example, user or admin can remove from,
let me get here, from the user entry, you can remove the passkey mapping and then this
user wouldn't be able to use this passkey anymore. So, it's in practice this is a process
thing. You have to define your policies for organizational policies, how you handle any
lost credentials. There's no difference with this. Some systems like, for example, Apple
and MacOS actually forces you to define two separate passkeys, two separate tokens if
you enable one because they think that you most likely will lose one. They probably figure
it out something about the users. Okay. Any other question? Pass the hash. There's nothing
to pass here. So, the whole, I'm not going into details of web often implementation.
It's all, it's fairly secure in this context. Yeah. You have to have actual hardware or
software implementation of the token. You have to have exactly the same key. Key is
not, the private part of the key is typically not leaving the device so it's fairly secure
in that case. Hi. It's Stefan here. Is it possible to add yet another factor to this
authentication? Can you please speak up louder? Sorry. Can you add another factor to this
key that you will bring? Like a, like a, I'm sorry, I'm not here. Guys, could you please
silence a bit? Sorry. I will speak out loud. Can you add another authentication factor
to the process? Like a token next to this physical key? So, you're asking if there's
a possibility to amend use of passkeys with something else. Exactly. I believe it's possible
to, because all of this available over a PAM interface, you can stack up several PAM modules
in it. In SSSD, that wouldn't be possible at this moment to get it, but maybe this would
be a good idea for going forward to allow extending and forcing to use several methods.
Yeah. I will write this down. Okay. I guess I'm out of time. I think we can still have
one last question if there is some. Okay. Nice, nice technology. I have a question about
user nameless login. Is it also supported? Because this is the promise of FIDOT2 that
you can have discoverable credentials stored on the token. So, the only thing you do is
plug in the token and use a fingerprint. Does it also support user nameless and passwordless
login? So, the question is whether login where a system, when you insert the token, identifies
to which user this token belongs to. Does it work or not? Implementation, as right
now does not support it. There is a plan to support discoverable credentials. There are
few things that I would like to address in a presentation in the afternoon related to
UX. Basically, right now we have very limited in how graphical environments allow to do
this discoverability. So, for example, for the smart cards, a couple years ago we changed
GNOME, GDM to extend to allow picking up different identities from the smart card. And if user
has, for example, several identities associated with the same smart card, then GDM allows
to pick up the right one. The same problem comes with the PUS keys. Maybe I'm ended with
the idea of discoverable ones, but it's the same story. So, it's more like not the back
end but the front end, the one that presents you. And user experience is pretty bad right
now on this. But the plan is to fix it eventually. Okay. Thank you, Alexander, for the talk. Thank
you for all the questions.