All right, thanks for having me folks.
So let's have a quick chat about Suricata, open source ideas, network security monitoring
and all those sorts of things.
And what it used to look like before and what it looks like now, at least from our perspective,
and all the things that we need to take care of and the things that we have still challenges
with.
So a quick overview of the agenda.
We're going to talk about what is Suricata, how it started, how it evolved, challenges
when we're monitoring the traffic and how to get involved basically and how it worked.
First of all, I'll introduce Eric, he's my colleague.
He was supposed to be here today, but he flies gas cancelled and he couldn't make it.
But we did the presentation together.
So apologies.
He actually just touched down at the Brussels airport.
So Eric is the CTO of Staunles Network.
He's part of the OSF team.
That's where I met him during the Suricata, developing during the Suricata project.
He's also an OSF member of the board of directors.
Linux kernel developer, he maintains also Sirius and Celcs.
And that's the Twitter handle in there.
So apologies Eric could not make it.
And that's why I'm making the introduction with him.
He's a great open source colleague and a friend.
My name is Peter Mannev.
I am 13, almost 14 years with Suricata.
I'm part of the OSF exec team and where I usually do a lot of things around Suricata
queuing and trainings.
I'm also chief strategy officer of Staunles Networks.
I'm one of the maintainers for the open source distribution in Celcs.
I really like thread hunting and lots of open source around it.
I'm guessing lots of people here in the conference too.
So what is actually Suricata?
So basically a high performance network security monitoring engine.
That can do active or passive monitoring and also produces a lot of application and process
protocol metadata.
Open source, GPL2 code is available on GitHub of course.
And basically produces when you plug Suricata in the network, it just gives you this high
level situation of what's happening on the network, what's going on, something you should
be aware of or something you didn't know or to confirm things.
For example, you know, you have these a lot of angles like trust but verify to use the
famous quote.
You know, when you have zero trust architectures, you want to confirm that they're actually
implemented.
It's one thing to implement, it's another thing to confirm that it's there.
And actually Suricata is used by a lot of organizations, a lot of people.
It's awesome to see it.
I'm really, really thankful for that and all the feedback.
And sometimes organizations will use it even without knowing because it's embedded in a
lot of vendor appliances and similar.
So what can Suricata do?
Well, today it's a few options there.
It's an IDS system, so intrusion detection system.
It could be in passive mode, right?
So it could be inline, intrusion prevention system where it actually actively stops or
enables a connection to pass through or not.
It can also be just purely network security monitoring perspective.
You know, it works without rules.
It can just generate all sorts of protocol flow data, file extraction and similar.
It can also store everything it sees on disk, so it can also do full packet capture.
And very often you see uses of Suricata in combinations like this.
So for example, IDS plus NSM mode with all the network protocol data and full packet
capture and similar.
There is also something new coming up in Suricata 7.
Suricata 7 RC was just released this week.
And it's called conditional PCAP capture, which is actually code introduced and developed
and donated by Eric.
What it allows you to do is, so for example, if you have an alert, it will save that whole
session.
So not just the packet, but the full session.
So in that way you actually have the full sessions for all alerts stored in PCAP as opposed
to having to do full packet capture, which in a lot of cases might be prohibitive.
So basically use the network to defend ourselves.
Observe protect adapt.
That's what we do.
That's what we try to excel at every day.
And this is a quick snapshot from actually our website.
So some major features.
To name a few, YAML configuration, JSON for output, multithreaded, there's hardware acceleration
and that becomes more and more relevant these days because the speeds are going up and up
all the time.
Network metadata login by a lot of protocols.
We're going to name all of them here.
Some of the main ones are here.
More advanced parsing and automatic detection of HTTP DNS, SMB, SMTPTLS, all those guys
and more.
One thing that Surigata does very well is file extraction.
SMB, FTP, HTTP, HTTP2, SMTP, all that.
And the cool feature about that is actually it automatically deduplicates when it's extracted.
So if the same file is seen 10 times, it will only be saved or extracted once to disk.
So in other words, saving a lot of space.
Really a lot.
And of course, support for SCADA, that's upcoming and we need more and more of that.
But it's also very relevant these days.
So why the network?
Well, because everything happens from the network.
Everything from social media to finance to name it, everything is on the network.
So the good people are there, the bad people are there.
So even if you have malicious actors getting in, even to get in is actually 99% of the
cases, it's over the network.
And once they get in, they need to either exfiltrate or move laterally or do some other
part.
That's still happening on the network.
So you have to be able to observe that.
It's not the only place where you need to observe from security perspective.
There's others, of course, but the network is one of the major ones.
And while you're doing all that, when you're confirming if things are configured as expected
or not, or if all the connections are correct, or there's no some anomaly and all things
like that, you have to be able to identify and stop this activity.
Granted, there are differences.
So a university network is totally different from a bank corporate network.
There's totally different things.
So network metadata logging.
So we actually provide a lot of metadata around any alert event or metadata just on its own.
You don't need to have an alert.
So default output format is JSON, right, JavaScript object notation.
And on the right hand side here, you can see actually a picture, a small snippet actually
of an event type, HTTP or an HTTP protocol.
So all the different protocols have their own event type and they're logged in like
that.
And then next to that, you also have alerts.
So file identification and extraction.
One thing to mention is that file identification is done on the fly.
And it's automatic, regardless of extensions and similar things like that, is just using
lib magic and those tools to be able to identify a file.
So if it's like an executable, it's a PDF or if it's a PDF, but with an extension TXT,
we'll still be able to match and extract if you want to that file.
You can also match on share sums and other attributes of the file info events.
So as I mentioned, extract the storage system, deduplicate it.
That really saves a lot of conversations with finance about sizing.
So we have some pickup capabilities.
Now what do I mean by that?
Besides the fact that Srikata can actually store everything on disk and do full packet
captures, Srikata can also read pickups.
It's actually, that part is also used a lot in a lot of sandboxes, including, so for example,
there is a few out there.
If you Google sandbox, for example, there's a few that even offer free public services.
But to name one, anyone is like that actually automatically when a sample is detonated,
they also save the network traffic.
And that's also run by Srikata just to see what network protocol data and alerts are
in there.
So Srikata can, you know, it can read a single pink app.
You can actually spin up a unique socket, let's say, and just feed pickups to it every
now and then.
You can point it to a folder and it will keep reading from that folder until it reads all
the pickups.
Or if there is nothing there, it will pause and it will stop.
And when you throw a pickup in the folder, it will continue really automatically.
It's really, really automated in that part.
And of course, you need to have multiple instances just to be on the safe side with that new
chain.
So in QA, you want to move it into PROB.
So passive monitoring, how does it actually work?
Here's an example.
Basically, we hooked up to a tap or a mirror port on a switch and we just sniffed the traffic.
Now, where you place that, you're going to need probably multiple sensors in different
scenarios.
You know, it depends where you have on-prem cloud, virtual infrastructure and all that.
So you have to probably have multiple things.
But in general, this is basically where it sits in passive mode.
So it logs all the alerts, the protocol metadata, any file instruction events, pickups and all
those things based on the monitoring that it does for that network.
Now active monitoring, this is a little bit different.
We stay in line.
So we allow or not traffic to pass.
This is a bit more business critical.
Well, no, not a bit more.
It's much more critical because it's actually able to stop effectively traffic.
So a lot more testing and due diligence and queuing is needed there.
But basically, how does it work?
So basically, you have this setup here.
You have a user employee that receives a malicious document.
Usually in a lot of cases, it all starts with some sort of link or attachment that is being
without intention opened by a user or clicked by a user.
So you have a network request and usually there is some sort of a signature or a rule
that vets the traffic or inspects the traffic and says, yes, you can pass, no, you cannot
pass.
And this is a very basic example here, for example, a PowerShell script.
And then based on that, there is a verdict.
Yes, you can go or no, you cannot go.
Either or.
And that's the inline mode, right?
So there you're actually actively making decisions of what can and cannot pass and similar.
So one is much more acute.
The other one is much easier because in the passive mode, you're just monitoring traffic.
So a little bit about our history and how we get there.
How did we get here?
So first lines of code, 2007 by Victor Julian.
As a lead developer of Suicata, first release was in 2009.
I joined the project 2010 April, May, somewhere around there.
So we are open source GPL.
We actually have actively contributors and people contributing code, test, donations
from 23 different countries at the moment.
Or at least that was the last statistic, but basically all continents.
Suicata is owned by a nonprofit foundation.
The Suicata code, it's open source and it's on GitHub, but it's owned by a nonprofit foundation
on purpose and the purpose is actually so that it could never be sold.
That's it.
And this is basically how we started.
OSFnet, you'll find a little bit more info.
So as I mentioned, a little bit of a visual representation in there.
So our first Suicata training, believe it or not, it was in 2013 and our first Suicon
was in 2015.
And those were a lot of fun events and we learned a lot just by talking and interacting
with the community.
So a big help there from the community.
And how did it used to work and look back in the day?
So I had to generate that.
This is basically an alert of what it looked like 14 years ago, what it looked like 20
years ago as well.
So I had to generate that manually to look at what it produces.
So basically that's an alert from 14, 15, 20 years ago, things like that.
Not much to see there.
Not much to say there, right?
So you have an IP and a port and a message.
What are you going to do with it?
Now you need to go find other tools, other protocol logs.
You need to go to different machines to figure out what this IP is, what's that port, what's
happened before, what happened after.
Is it a server?
Is it a laptop?
Is it, guess, whatever it is.
So you needed to do a lot of work.
This was just like a message.
But back then it was one of the few things that were there, right?
So there was nothing more than that.
So fast forward to today.
So this is an example for an alert, but in a graphical interface anyway.
So you have the alert, you have the signature metadata, you have in this case its HTTP protocol.
And a lot of things do happen over clear text, by the way, because it's not vetted that much,
especially in some environments.
And you also have the flow record, packets, bytes to clients to server, similar things,
durations, and all those things.
So you have a much better understanding when you look at an alert now, aha, okay, so this
is the status code, this is the request, this is the file, and all those things.
So you can actually judge much more.
And one thing that actually came with time in Suricata is something called Flow ID.
What Flow ID allows you, this was natively introduced in Suricata in 2014, what Flow ID
allows you to achieve is basically to correlate the specific alert to any and other protocol
data from the same flow and session.
So if you have an alert over SMB or something like that, you have all the SMB protocol records,
the extracted files, you know, a pickup saved if you need the pickup, you have all that
in the package.
So much bigger evolution than what you saw in the previous screenshot.
So how it works, this is a screenshot, for example, from ebox.
It's a tool developed by Jason Ish, he's our colleague from the Suricata team.
And here's a quick example.
Yeah, every session has a Flow ID, right?
So here is an alert with a Flow ID, and that translates to, in this case, the Flow ID correlates
the alerts to the flow record, to the HTTP record, to the file info, which is actually
the file metadata for that file transaction.
So much bigger, much better visibility, and you can actually make a decision much faster
than needing to go look in other tools.
This is actually a showcase of Flow ID by Sirius, which is an open source web interface
as part of Celcs that they help maintain.
But in any way, here is the file info on the bottom that is highlighted.
You have the shad, the file magic, and everything is correlated between alerts, file info, flow
protocol logs by the help of that Flow ID, which helps glue everything together.
So really, really powerful.
If I need, often enough, I need to explain Suricata in one slide today.
This is what Suricata does today.
One IDS plus NSM mode.
So you have the alerts, you have the protocol data, you have the network logs, the file
transactions, you're doing file transactions, and the pickup recordings, right?
So you have everything in a package.
It's much different when I started the list.
So we have evolved.
And here is another run that is possible.
So you could actually, it's a little known fact that Suricata alerts are only about 5,
10% of all data that it produces.
The rest of the data is all protocols, data, metadata, and things like that.
The alerts are very, very small part.
And alerts, now at least I look at them as just a context.
It gives me something.
It gives me an idea of what's happening.
That's it and that's all.
I don't necessarily look at it as true or false positives.
It's just like, okay, so that's what happened.
I need the context around it.
Suricata can function without signatures or those two, although it's not recommended because
they help highlight certain events.
So what challenges do we have?
Well, all those years we need to keep the pace, right?
We need to adapt.
We need to move forward.
Signatures have evolved at least in Suricata.
Back in the day, it used to be a pattern match, a buffer overflow, some content triggering
in the payload.
It was very bounded with the IPS mindset.
So you have to stop it.
You have to look for something specific.
It's expensive.
It's CPU intensive actually to look on the fly at the 100 gigabit a second, for example,
for a pattern.
For example, in IPAC, you need to block, stop, protect the assets and similar.
So we need to evolve from that to actually a bit more behavior analytics and including
from the perspective of infrastructure, right?
So I can say, hey, how many proxies they have on the network, right?
That's interesting.
Do you have proxies somewhere that, NGINX, for example, proxies that somewhere in the
network that they don't expect them to be?
That sort of visibility, that kind of difference.
So TLS, okay, TLS is encrypted, sure.
But the handshake is encrypted.
And during the handshake, you can see a lot of things, including ciphers and things like
that.
What do you care about the cipher?
Of course you do.
Is it secure?
Is it degraded?
Is it recommended?
Do you have applications that are using degraded ciphers?
How do you know?
Network security monitoring.
That's the easiest way to do it, actually.
For one, much easier than the other way.
Put it that way.
So you have system updates.
You know, who's updating Debian, who's updating Ubuntu, things like that.
They're very visible on the network.
You know.
And it's not about the actual system of data.
It's about actually do you expect it to happen where it happens and where it happens.
So, yeah, we need to evolve towards that direction.
And we have managed actually to do a huge leap there.
More protocol implementation, right?
So we need more and more protocols.
Of course we do.
But, you know, as it says here, it's no longer a network grip.
So you have different protocols.
You need application layer identification regardless of the port, you know.
So it has to be automated.
You need parsing.
You need logging.
You need to parse the protocol.
You need to log it correctly.
All those things require time and effort.
You need specific keywords so you can hook up detection to for different parts of the
protocol.
And we need like secure protocol implementation.
So by that way, Suricata needs to parse everything and anything on the network.
And trust me, everything and anything on the network doesn't fold the RFC.
It just doesn't.
So we need to follow the RFC one and two, we don't.
Because we can't, you know, we can't crash.
We need to actually keep inspecting and alert for problems.
Everybody has, not everybody, a lot of tools have vulnerability based on protocol process.
Work Shack has a lot.
Suricata has a few and similar.
So one way to battle and combat that is the combination of Rust and known for.
Memory safety, thread safety.
C is not safe, right?
C memory requests manual.
If it's not done correctly, it's not done properly.
Sec false memlix, they can all occur in there.
Here's an example of Rust known parser that we use in Suricata.
So the Suricata is a combination of C and Rust known implementation.
And that started only a couple years ago and it's more and more of that just to help us
be more safe when we inspect and do things.
There's the outside evolution, right?
So networks, speeds increase, demand increases.
There is encryption, there's less visibility.
But a lot of data.
I was earlier, in January, I had a talk at a different conference and after the talk
a person approached me, he's like, do you have any recommendations of how to improve
Suricata performance?
I'm like, yeah, sure.
And I said, what's your setup?
He's like, we have over 25, 100 give it solutions.
I'm like, okay, we need to talk.
So it's very interesting.
Things like that are dominant and happening.
So it's different, you need to keep up with those evolutions too and make sure that these
people actually can, these setups and people can benefit from everything we do.
Challenges, there's a lot.
Everything from mirroring the traffic to one-sided traffic to encryption to NIC of loading because
we actually do need to inspect the traffic as the end user or the end device will see
it, not as the devices in the network pass it over to one another.
The volume, size of logs, it's not uncommon to have, depending on the link speed, of course,
it's not uncommon to have one, two, three, five more billion of logs a day.
What do you do with them?
That's a different topic.
So here it comes, the deduplication and all the stuff that we actually also need to take
care of.
And QA anyone while we have this?
It's quite an effort.
So when we talk about encryption, I mentioned, so depending on the protocol version and similar
things you have TLS one, two, one, three, one, one, all sorts of things.
But during the clear handshake, you can actually extract a lot of information.
These are some of the things that we extract actually.
The SNI, the subject, e-shore, you can deduct Cypher calls from there as well, J83, J83S,
fingerprinting, TLS version is similar.
So we need to tell Suricata what to do when it detects that the connection is encrypted.
So what do you do?
You want to keep inspecting it?
You want to keep it pointless because it's encrypted or you want to pass it to a specific,
some hardware has already built a function so it can say bypass it on the hardware level
as soon as it takes it's encrypted because there's nothing more we can do.
There's certain things that we can take, continue on tracking and generate logs, for example,
the flow, how big is it and things like that.
But we need to be able to relate that information because it's pointless, as I mentioned, if
it's encrypted.
We know a lot of decryption devices in similar things that Suricata sticks next to or behind,
but that's a setup, that's an architecture issue.
So these four major factors that impact Suricata performance, rules, Suricata version, hardware
using type of traffic.
Again, university traffic is much more different than a regular corporate traffic where everything
is vetted.
So you learn a lot from both deployments, for example, just using these two as an example.
We're software, right?
So we need to run any hardware.
Now that's not easy to achieve.
We need a lot of resistance, QAing and all those similar things.
So what actually happens, so here's an example of workers more than Suricata.
As you can see, this is a network card and it has different cues.
In each protocol, sorry, each thread, each record actually enters and goes through these
points, capture the cold stream, detect output, output, especially when you're writing.
So it needs to be in that, this is an example of that specific order when the traffic comes
to the network, how it's passed to the Suricata and what Suricata goes through in a very high
level.
Most of Nixxer are made for web file servers at scale.
They're not specifically made for ideas, some are.
But ideas need to see the traffic, the network security monitoring needs to see the traffic
as this end device will actually see it in order.
Everything needs to be in order in the same flow so that we can expect it properly.
And a small word, so back in the day when I started, there was different capture methods
and they evolved over time.
But one of the fastest things that was back there was PF ring and that was actually, we
received a lot of help from Luca and Alfredo.
Thank you guys.
So kernel 2.6 and 2.0 above, the PL frame was the only thing that offered speed and
performance.
There is others that we were upcoming in the Suricata 7, you know, DPDK, A
packet XDP and similar, but we need to have different methods.
I am going just to finish up here.
And so QA and Suricata, a lot of, we need to cover a lot of angles.
We have called on GitHub, we have called in GitLab.
When you submit a PR publicly, it goes through an automated checks to as much as possible
before we put it in the coldest.
Private runs, there's units, there's thousands of checks.
So anytime you submit a PR or a code, it automatically triggers checks.
And some of them could finish nightly.
This is a GitLab screenshot going through some checks.
Some of these checks can include thousands of definitions inside.
In one check, we have 22,000 files extracted.
We need to make sure all of them are there the same way they were there before the code
change.
Things like that need to happen.
And here's an example of a PR that's going through a regular checks on GitHub.
That information is actually public on GitHub.
You can see in all the different OS compilation that it goes through, address sanitizers,
leak sanitizers, code analysis, CPP checks, all those things need to actually happen before
we can say, okay, we could put this code without affecting us.
Regressions, traffic replace, and similar.
I am going over with a time apologies.
This is how to contribute.
Any feature and code can be donated, put in on our redmine ticket and start the discussion.
And the current reviews could be done on GitHub.
They're public.
So in conclusion, it has to work because you need to create a community around it.
And the power is in the community because it's going to have a lot of ideas, a lot of
feedback, and you need to be open about it.
You need to have open discussions about roadmap and input from all the different people that
are actually using it.
And that is the, our point is that is the ultimate power comes in numbers.
Thank you very much for having me here.
Much appreciated.
Open to questions.
Thank you, Peter.
Anybody has one question?
One question here.
I'm just wondering, I don't know what the current debate is, but have you had NVIDIA
Blue field as well?
And how was the circuit in the process?
Have I looked at, sorry I'm not here.
NVIDIA Blue field, it's this part of the process.
Oh yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
We have a conversation going, yes?
Okay, cool.
Yeah, yeah.
That's part of the whole process, staying and keeping on.