Hi everyone.
So that's the last speaker of the day.
So I'm going to talk about a cumulative spot connecting to multiple networks.
So Doug already spoke about this in a slightly different way.
We all want to take a slightly different approach.
So first a few things about myself.
I'm a software engineer at Cisco working on continuing networking things.
And I'm a maintainer of Calico VPP, which is going to be the topic of this talk.
This talk is also a bit particular.
It's a result of a collaboration effort with many awesome people like I
mostly in Cisco and direct collaboration with Mitika Ganguly, which is a P at Intel.
But she sadly couldn't be here today because it's quite far from the US where she lives.
But I'll do my best to present her work.
So first a bit of a background story of this work.
So in the world of endpoint applications, Kubernetes has really become the solution
of choice when it comes to deploying large scale services in various environments because
it provides the primitives for scalability, so Metal-LB that we saw in previous talk,
services, house checks and so on.
It also provides the uniformity of deployment.
And it's also far from the second, so you don't need to know what you're running on.
But coming from the CNF land, so trying to deploy network function in this environment,
the story is not the same.
So I'll define a bit more what I mean by CNF because it's a bit different between the standard
CNF use case, the 5G one.
What I mean by that is, so I'll take an example for the sake of this presentation.
So typically what I mean by that is the WireGuard head end.
For example, you have a customer and you want to deploy a fleet of WireGuard head ends to
give that user access to a resource in a company network.
So typically a very private printer that everybody wants to access to because people like to
print.
So the particularity of this use case is that it's dynamic enough to benefit from the abstraction
that Kubernetes brings.
And I've lost my mouse.
So typically load balancing, scheduling and those kinds of things.
But it has a lot of specific needs.
For example, Ingress has to be done in a peculiar way because you have a WireGuard encrypted
traffic, so typically you want to see which IP it's coming from.
You also constraint on how you receive traffic because typically, and that's the place where
you need multiple interfaces to go into your pod.
And you also require high performance because encrypted traffic, so typically you want those
things to run faster and you have a lot of users using them.
So not for that printer, but assuming it's a bigger use case.
So we tried to design a solution for that.
So there are lots of components at play.
I'll try to go quickly into them.
So in the top we have our application.
So here are the WireGuard VPN head end.
We want to deploy it on top of Kubernetes, so we had to choose a CNI.
So we want to work with Calico mainly because of the cuteness of their cats, but also because
it provides a really nice interface into supporting multiple data planes and also a nice BGP integration
that allows us to tweak the way we process packets.
And for carrying packets, we used the FDIO's DPP as a data plane.
That gave us more control on how packets are processed.
And so that allowed us to go deeper into the way networks actually managed at a really
low level.
And there are also other components that are going to play, but more on this later.
So I'm going to go quickly over Calico and VPP because they have been presented many
times.
So in short, Calico is a community CNI providing a lot of great features, policies, BGP, support
for really huge clusters.
And the point that's important for this presentation is that it has a very well-defined control
plane, data plane interface, allowing to plug new performance-oriented software underneath
it without much hassle.
And that's what we are going to leverage.
So we choose to slip VPP underneath Calico first because we were originally contributors
in this open-source user space networking data plane.
So it was a solution of choice.
But also it has a lot of cool functional ITs that are built in, and it's extensible.
So I am doing a bit of publicity for the software I'm coming from, but it was a good tool for
this use case.
And also it's quite fast, so it really fits the needs for this application.
So how did we bind it together?
What we do is we built an agent running in a demand set on every node.
So deployment is the same as a simple pod, just with more privileges.
We registered this agent in Calico as a Calico data plane and used their JRPC interface and
their APIs that they exposed to decouple control data plane.
That agent listens for Calico events, and then programs with VPP accordingly.
And we also built a series of custom plugins for handling NAT, service, top balancing,
and so on.
And we tweaked the configuration so that things behave nicely in a container-oriented environment.
And with all this, we have every break to bring VPP into the clusters, and so to have
really control on everything that happens in the Kubernetes networking.
How does that happen under the...
So what happens exactly under the hood?
What we do is we swap all the network logic that was happening in Linux to VPP.
So from this configuration to there.
In order to...
So, yeah, the thing is, as VPP is a user space stack, we have to do a few things a bit differently
compared to what was previously done in Linux.
So in order to insert VPP between the host and the network, we will grab the host interface,
the app link, and consume it in VPP with the appropriate driver.
And then we restore the host connectivity by creating a turn interface in the host root
network namespace.
So that's the turn tab here.
And we replicate everything on that interface, the resist the routes.
So basically we insert ourselves as a bump in the wire on the app link.
It's not very network-ish, but it works pretty well in that configuration.
And that way we restore pod connectivity as before with turn tabs instead of a leaf.
We create an interface in every pod.
And then everything runs normally.
The calico control plane is running normally on the host.
And it configures the data plane functions in VPP via the agent.
So now we have the green part covered.
So all those components run neatly.
And what we achieve with that is that when we create a pod, Kubernetes will call calico,
calico will call VPP.
And we can provide an interface that we fully handled on a network layer directly in VPP.
But for this specific way we got an application, we need a bit more than that.
We need multiple interfaces.
And we also potentially have overlapping addresses.
So we don't fully manage where the IPs are going to end.
So for the multiple interface part, all we got to show was to go with Moltus that provides
multiplexing.
And we showed you also a dedicated IPAM that we patched, which we were about because it
was quite simple to patch and brought those two pieces in.
But so when I mean multiple interfaces, what does that exactly contain?
So the thing is, the typical Kubernetes deployment looks like this.
So each pod has a single interface.
And the CNI provides a port-to-port connectivity, typically with an encapsulation from node
to node.
But in our application, we want to differentiate the encrypted traffic from the clear text
traffic, so before and after the head end.
But we still want Kubernetes as the end to operate.
So we still want the nice things about Kubernetes, so service IPs and everything.
So it's not only multiple interfaces.
It's really multiple interfaces wired into Kubernetes.
So it's more multiple isolated networks.
So conceptually, what we needed was the ability to create multiple Kubernetes networks.
And each network behaving a bit like a standalone cluster stacked on top of each other.
So with this, we request networks that provide complete resolution between each other, meaning
that traffic cannot cross from a network to another without going from to the outside
world.
And so that means that we are to bind Calico, VPP, so on, integration, and Moltus together
to create a model where everybody is aware of that definition of networks, have a catalog
of isolated network, specify the way they are going to communicate from node to node
via VIX and encapsulations, and have a way for pods to attach to those networks with
annotations.
And so that, in the end, Kubernetes is aware of these networks.
And we can still maintain the SDN part of the logic.
So the way this works quickly is that the CNI interface will call Calico once per pod.
So once per pod.
So the thing is Moltus will call the CNI Calico once per top-all pod interface.
And we will in turn receive in our agent those calls.
And we can map those with annotations and do our magics to provide the logic.
And having also the IPAM patch allows us to support multiple IPs and to have different
realms where the IP lives and gets located from.
So from a user's perspective, what we expose is a network catalog where networks are defining
CRDs for now.
We are starting a standardization effort to bring that into Kubernetes, but that will
probably take time.
So right now we kept it that simple.
We've just specified a VNI using VXLAN by default, just passing a range.
And we also keep a network attachment definition from Moltus with one-to-one mapping to network
so that things, we don't change too many things at once.
And then we use those networks into the pod definitions.
So we reference them the Moltus way.
We can reference them as well in services with dedicated annotations.
And so that way we tell all agents to program IP in a way where the services apply only
in a specific network.
The policy is the same way.
And also that gives us the ability for pods to have a bit more tweaking on parameters
exposed on the interface.
So specify the number of queues we want, the queue depth, and also support multiple types.
So that gives a lot of flexibility to get the performance right and to get, so first
to get the functionalities.
So the fact that we have multiple interfaces and so also size them so that the performance
is appropriate for the use case that we want to achieve.
Last nice feature of this is that as we have GobiGP support, we can pair those networks
with the outside world if we have a fabric that's VXLAN and if GobiGP supports it.
So that part is still a bit work in progress and there are a lot of things to get right.
But that's the end picture we want to go.
And this could, so if we put everything together, we would get probably something like that,
that looks like that.
So basically when the users want to connect to this hypothetical VPN and that hypothetical
printer, it would get into the cluster via GobiGP peering, so traffic is going to be
attracted to the green network, hit service IP in that network, so get some load balancing
across the node.
Then it's going to be deciphered in a pod that then encapsulates traffic and passes
for example to a NAT pod running in user space.
So here I put another type of interface that is more performance oriented and then exit
the cluster on a different VLAN paired with the outside world.
So some parts still need to be done but the general internal logic of the cluster is still
something that works and that brings the ability for container networking functions to run
unmodified with their multiple interfaces directly in a somewhat regular cluster.
So we spoke about improving performance of the network, of the underlying interface,
but we can also improve the performance with which the application in the pod consumes
their own interfaces.
So the standard way applications usually consume packets within pods is via socket APIs, so
it's really standard but you have to go through the kernel and it's a code path that wasn't
designed for the performance levels of modern apps, so that's why GSO came up as a network
cycle organization.
But here with VPP running, it would be nice to be able to bypass the network stack and
pass the packets directly from VPP and not touching the kernel.
So fortunately VPP exposes two different ways to consume those interfaces.
We'll mostly go into the first one which is the memory interface.
So basically it's a packet oriented interface standard relying on memory segment for speed
and this can be leveraged by an application via a simple library, so either GOMEMIF, LIMEMIF
in C or DPDK or even VPP and so provide a really high speed way of consuming that extra
interface in the pod.
And the really nice thing about this is that it brings also the connection between the
Kubernetes network, Kubernetes SDN and the pod into user space, meaning that now that
that connection lives in a regular C program, we can also leverage...
So it's easier to leverage CPU optimizations and new features and that's where the silicon
reenters the picture and the work from Mritika from Intel and their team.
So they benchmarked this kind of setup and also introduced an optimization that's coming
into the fourth generation Intel Exeons that's called Data Streaming Accelerator.
Basically it's a way to optimize copies between processes on some CPUs.
And so what they did is compare the performance that we get with Kubernetes clusters, multiple
interfaces and a simple pod, so not bringing the old VPN logic, just doing L3 patch and
seeing how fast things could go between regular kernel interfaces, the turn, the memory interfaces
and the memory interfaces leveraging those optimizations in the CPU.
So that gives those graphs that are really...
So that have a lot of numbers in them.
But basically I tried to sum up quite quickly what this gives.
There are two MTUs, 1500 bytes and 9000 bytes here.
The performance for turn interfaces in dark blue.
Blue is the first memif and the DSA optimized memif is in yellow.
And basically what this gives is that with...
The performance is really...
So it brings really a huge difference between...
So sorry.
Vote with DSA is 2.3 times faster than with regular memif for the 1500 byte packets.
And if you go with DSA enabled, it's 23 times faster than turn tap.
And with a 9000 byte MTU, basically you get more than 60 times faster with the memif that's
optimized with DSA.
Basically the digits, so the number that's really interesting is that bar, is that with
200,000...
So basically you get a single call doing 100Gs with that.
And that without too much modifications of the applications.
So basically you just spin a regular cluster.
If the CPU supports it, you use a regular library and you're able to consume packets
at really huge speeds without modifying the application too much.
So there is another graph looking into the scaling with numnor calls.
Both with small MTUs and large MTUs.
Basically that shows that we can spare calls when going...
So turn tap does not scale very well.
So for a memif scales with one, two, six calls.
And DSA achieves the same results with two to three less calls than its regular memif
counterpart.
So basically you achieve 100Gs which was the limit of the setup with a single call in the
case of large MTUs and three calls in the case of smaller MTUs.
So that's all for the talk.
Sorry I went into a variety of different subjects because that topic is quite...
It goes into a lot of different directions.
Basically that was to give you another view of the direction we are trying to go.
Trying to bring all those pieces together in a framework that allows us to make those
CNFs run into a community environment.
This work is open source.
There are the details of the test that were done in the following slides.
You can find us on GitHub and there is also a Slack channel open where you can ask questions.
And we have a new release coming up in beta aiming for GA that's going without soon.
So thanks a lot for listening.
So here are the details.
And I'm open to questions if you have any.
Just one question for the sake of it.
Have you ever thought about some shared memory between the different parts to eliminate the
needing to copy over the packets?
So we thought of this.
So there are different ways to do that.
If you use...
So there is the VCR which I haven't spoken about.
Which is a way of opening the sockets directly in VPP.
So basically you do a listen in VPP, 40 CPE, UDP or a given protocol.
So that supports directly...
So basically the data never leaves VPP.
And you can do direct copies between processes without having to copy.
Because everything stays in VPP in the end.
For MEMIF we don't support that out of the box but nothing forbids you to spawn two pods.
Make them share a socket.
And it's only shared memory so you can directly do it without having to spin up the whole
thing.
So you could even do that in any cluster or directly in bare metal.
So MEMIF is really a lightweight protocol so you can do that just with regular socket.
Okay, cool.
Thank you very much.
Thanks for listening.
We'll see you next time.
Okay Eastern.
No?
Yes.
Okay Eastern.