Thank you.
So guys, there are some more seats.
Please have a seat.
And whenever you want, we can start.
Okay.
All right.
So let's start.
Welcome, everyone.
My name is Fernando.
I'm a senior software engineer at Red Hat.
I work on the networking services team, mainly focused on network management.
So today I'm going to talk how we can do networking management more simple and how we can make
the life of sysadmins a little bit better.
I know that network management can be complex, especially because most of the sysadmins
need to sometimes configure networking, and maybe they are not network experts.
So all right.
The first thing is what is network manager.
So network manager is the standard Linux network configuration tool suite.
Basically it's almost on every distribution, and it configures networking.
It's just like that.
It takes care of setting the IP address, all the properties, manage routes, manage DNS,
manage almost everything, and make sure that when other to modify the network configuration,
it will notify network manager, will update the status, et cetera, et cetera.
Network manager provides the bus API, and also they have their own library to communicate
with the daemon, which is libnm.
And this is why there are some tools built around network manager.
For example, I know that some of you know them, Nmappler, Nm2, Nmcli, or Nmcloud setup.
And there are more, and we are building more of them.
So as I said, the network manager daemon is the backend that we are going to use for the
new tool, NMS state.
And NMS state is a little bit special because it's declarative.
So the idea here is that as a user, you just need to define what do you want to configure,
and you don't need to care about the hope.
So you can define the state, you can define what IP address do you want, you can define
what properties, if it's a bond, the bond properties, if it's a bridge, whatever you
want, and NMS state will take care of it, and will do, will resolve all the interdependencies
between the interfaces.
We configure the routes, we configure everything that is needed to make it work.
And we use network manager as a backend, we communicate with network manager for applying
the configuration, but we perform some operations that we are going to talk later, and we needed
Nispor to communicate with Kana.
So we had a problem, initially we were using CFS, and it was not working well, and we decided
to create Nispor, which is another library, written in Rust, that allows you to communicate
with Kana and get real-time network configuration from Kana.
So the first question could be why Nell link, and why not CFS?
So CFS is not an API.
You need to understand that, because I know that a lot of people build their tools parsing
CFS, writing on CFS, using CFS everywhere, and this could be problematic, because CFS
is not an API, and if you read the documentation, it's not stable.
It can break between releases.
But Nell link is an API.
Nell link is stable, it's not deprecated, because CFS is deprecated, so most of the
new network options that they are adding into Kana, they are not providing a CFS interface.
And also, Nell link use sockets, and that's great, because you don't need to open a file,
read it, parse it, and then get the proper value.
Using sockets, you can get the attribute, you know the type, you communicate through
the Nell link sockets, you get the value, and you get proper errors, so everything is
better.
Okay, so then let's go to the important part.
So NMS.
NMS does everything, you don't need to do anything, you just need to define what do you want, and
ideally you will apply that state, and everything will be configured after some operations.
Sometimes it's not like that, so we have a lot of steps in the middle.
We do, for example, validation, we do normalization and verification, we are going to explain
them later.
And also, it will point you what is going wrong, so you can fix it.
So for example, if you are configuring a MAC address, and this MAC address is not being
configured correctly, it will point you which MAC address is configured on kener, and what
is the one that you wanted to configure.
And right, you need to solve that.
Also if you put invalid IP address, it will tell you this IP address is not valid, please
change it.
Okay, or for example, if you configure one great thing is that if you configure an MTU
that is bigger than the one supported by the driver, it will let you know about that.
Okay, so one thing is that, did you misconfigure something?
Good, we can do a rollback.
Let's talk a little bit about rollbacks.
So this is already supported in Node Manager, this is not new from NMS state, but it's a
little bit complex to use.
And in NMS state, we simplify it.
So basically all the time that you do an operation, and NMS state do the verification, and if
something goes wrong, it's rollback to the previous state.
But we can also, maybe nothing go wrong, but you lost connectivity because you removed
the IP address, and we cannot know if that is what you wanted or not, I mean, we as NMS
state.
So we allow you to define an option which is no commit, so you can say this simple command
NMS state CTL apply, the jammer file, we are going to see the format of the jammer file
later, then no commit and a timeout time.
If you don't specify a timeout, it's going to be 60 seconds by default.
So what happened if it went well?
It's what you wanted, you have connectivity, everything is good.
Okay, then NMS state CTL commit, and the configuration will be there permanently.
But what happens if you notice that you mess up?
All right, NMS state CTL rollback, and you're going to be on the previous state.
This is really great because it's really time when you misconfigure something and then you
need to undo it manually.
So this time you just do a rollback and everything will be like before.
And what happened when you are working on a remote on a server and you lose connectivity
and you end free travel to the data center?
Right, now with this tool you can, with a timeout, if you lose connectivity, you are
not going to be able to do the commit, so at some point it will rollback and you will
have your connectivity back, hopefully.
All right, and well, verification is optional.
But personally I like it a lot because what it does is NMS state gets the desired state
from the user, then apply it, and then get the current state that is applied to the system
and compare them.
And if they are not equals, then it's going to fail and it's going to rollback to the
previous state automatically.
That is great because sometimes you don't know about some options and there are some
requirements to set up these options on interface.
So what you can do is apply this if it goes wrong because kernel is not applying the option
correctly because they are incompatible, for example.
So it does a rollback automatically and you don't end up with a wrong configure interface.
But you can skip this using dash dash no verify.
Okay, so let's see some examples of YAML files.
These are a little bit simple but I think they are great examples.
Here, for example, we have a bond interface and you can just define the state, IPv4, the
link aggregation options, you can define the mode, the options of that mode, and then define
the board.
And one thing that is really, really useful is that we have partial editing.
So imagine that you want to change only the MAC address but you don't want to change the
IP address.
You don't need to define the IP address because you just define the interface and the type.
So this is just enough.
Then the MAC address and apply the state.
An NMS state will get the current status of the interface and will merge.
So you won't lose any property.
All right, so then we have, for example, another example in the middle is the Abilang interface
over adh1 interface and another great thing here, as I say, is that NMS state will solve
interdependencies automatically.
So basically you don't need to know if, in which state needs to be the adh1 when creating
the Abilang, needs to be up or down.
It doesn't matter.
We are going to handle it.
So you don't need to worry about it.
And then, for example, we have a Linux switch with the port and some options on the port.
And also one great thing here is that you don't need to care about the state of the
port.
NMS state will solve the dependencies and will bring the port up if needed or will configure
as needed.
Some more examples because, as I say, NMS state is not only focused on interfaces.
It's also focused on DNS, root configuration, and also some other interfaces like OBS and
OBS dpdk.
So for example, here we have our interface adh1 configure with a static IP address.
And then we have the adroot.
So you can define adroot and it will be applied to KANA.
The same for root in policy.
It's also supported.
You can define from IP2 and IP4.
It will be for one mask.
It will be applied.
The same thing for DNS solver.
As you can see there, the last example, it's an OBS interface with an OBS reach.
So you can define it.
And then the great thing is that you don't need always to define the OBS interface.
You can define only the OBS reach and add ports or delete ports from it.
So it's quite great.
All right.
So having seen these examples, I would like to do a demo.
Sorry if it doesn't work.
I hope it will.
I have an environment.
So let's try it out.
All right.
So it's big enough.
I can make it bigger.
Yeah?
Okay.
Right.
So okay.
I'm using the main branch belchion, which is 2.2.6.
And here we have, this is really great.
We have an example base.
So you can, if you are learning how to use nmsday, this is quite good.
You can go here and see different examples of how you should do it.
So one that is really simple is, for example, this one.
Right.
So this one, one similar to what I showed before.
So this is an adh1, and then you have the config, a root config for the adh1.
So let's check before the state that we have already.
Okay.
This is the IP address that we have.
Here we have adh1.
adh1 is a base, but it's defined as an definite.
So according to us, it will behave as an definite.
So let's apply the state.
This, set the attachment and add root.
That's it.
It's done.
If we go to IPA and we go to adh1, we can see the IP address configured here.
Right.
Then if we do IPR, we are going to see the root here.
One for the IP address and the other one, the root that we set.
And also if you are willing to check what happened in the one manner here, you can do
this.
Whoops.
Okay.
Sorry.
All right.
You can do this.
You will notice that the device is up, and we can check the connection that we generated.
But let's go to a, sorry.
Let's check a more complex sample.
What we need first to clean up the state.
So I'm going to show you how we clean up the state.
We have adh1, then all roots.
All right.
So here, for example, we just need to define the adh1 and then define the roots with the
nethup interface and state absent.
And this will clear all the roots that are defined for that interface, which is very
great because when removing something, you don't need to define everything.
You just need to define the properties that you want to match and then state absent, and
it will clear them.
All right.
That's fine.
So it's applied.
Let's check it.
Okay.
And then we can, oh, it's active.
Right, because we didn't bring down the adh1 interface.
That's fine, but we dropped the root.
So let's create a more complex one.
One that I especially like.
It's this one.
This is going to be the last one.
So here we are going to define this.
We have two Ethernet interfaces that are connected to a boy interface, which has also another
port which is going to be a bridge and a B-land over another bridge.
So all right.
This is the state.
We define the B-land interfaces with the IV, the Linux bridge, which the board is the B-land,
and then another Linux bridge up, and the board is going to be the bond.
And then for the bond, we have the two Ethernet interfaces, adh1 and adh2, and we have adh1
and adh2 defined.
So let's apply it.
All right.
This will do a little bit more.
That's fine.
Right.
So in the board manager, everything seems set.
Then we can do IPA.
Plenty of things.
Let me, this is the B-land.
Then we have here the bond with the other's configure.
No, sorry.
We have the bond here and the bridge, 29.
We can also remove them as we did with the other example.
And let me show you how it looks.
Right.
So this is quite simple.
You just need to define adh1, adh2 as down because adh1 is an Ethernet.
It's a, well, it's a mutlating Ethernet, but it's a physical device.
So you cannot remove it completely.
And then you have the bond, which can be dropped, the bridge, the B-land, and the other bridge.
So that's it.
If you apply it, it will be gone.
Check.
All right.
So it should be done.
But first, as you can see, they are not anymore.
You cannot see any more of the link, nor the roots, nor the connections because we didn't,
we removed also the network manager connection files.
So I think that's it.
It was a little bit, a little demo about how it works.
I really encourage you to try it out.
It's really simple.
If you're already using network manager, you basically do not need to do anything else
because installing NMS state will be enough.
NMS state is packaged basically on Fedora, CentOS, and rel.
And, well, if you use the Rust library, you can also use the create to use it whenever
you want.
All right.
So that will be all.
And now some questions.
Thank you.
So you basically use network manager to do all the settings and everything.
But you also use Netlink.
Why is it necessary?
Don't you get all the information from network manager?
No.
Because Nebo Manajer is not getting real-time information from Kana all the time.
He's not updating it directly.
If you look to the devices, the devices doesn't have all the properties.
And in Nispo, we care about all the properties that are defined on Kana.
So this is the main reason.
Are there settings that you need to do the Netlink as well?
No, no.
We don't do the settings through Netlink.
We just get them to compare.
We found out the problem that as network manager is a service and is listening on events of
Netlink, sometimes takes some time to update the device cache.
And that's a problem because when you do an operation, you want the result immediately.
Isn't that the bug in network manager?
Well, it isn't.
In the end, you have a very good cache.
And it's hard to keep everything updated.
So they perform a lot of operations.
Obviously, it could be improved.
But right now, this is the solution that we thought about.
Nispo can apply settings to Kana, but we don't use it on NMS.
This is like an extra feature that we work on it from time to time.
Hello.
I would like to ask if dummy interfaces are supported?
And if not, are they planned to be supported?
Dummy interfaces?
Yes.
Dummy interfaces are supported.
And that's it.
You can check the documentation.
I think everything is supported for them.
Thank you.
Any more questions?
All right.
I think we're good.
Yeah, we are good.
Thank you very much.
Thank you very much for attending.