Hi, welcome to my talk. So you want to build a deterministic networking system, a gentle
introduction to time-sensitive networking, just out of interest how many of you have
heard of TSN or time-sensitive networking so far? That's quite a few for a networking
session, that's great. How many of you have already worked with that? Not so many. Okay,
you will after that talk. Yeah, who am I? I think I'm a former system engineer. I worked
a lot with time-sensitive networking and its predecessors. I also took part in standardization,
so I also did some of that. And since last summer, I work at the current developer at
Pangrotronics, that's a German Linux consulting and support company. We have roughly 7,600
patches in the kernel and we also do consulting for real-time networking amongst many other
stuff. And by the way, we're hiring, of course. Now, to what we will look into today, we will
look into applications. I will give you some examples why you would probably want to do
networking over real-time data transport over networking and what the implications of that
is, what the requirements of these applications are. We will look into the basic building
blocks. So, sorry for the folks who already know about that. And we will talk a bit about
which Linux user space and kernel components are used in building these applications. And
I will sum up the state of the union a bit and then just as an announcement in advance,
there are some bonus slides where I will give some more details and some references to open
source projects already working with TSM. So, if you're interested in that, just download
the slides from the Penta and, well, check out the links. And I also gave an example
of how to basically glue together a stage box, so a transport system for audio data
over the network. I won't make that into the talk because it has been shortened to half
an hour. So, the example I will focus on today is audio video bridging. So, if you want to
transport real-time data over a network for an application just as this talk, you want
to have as low JIT above or as much JIT above as possible to reduce latency in the system
because if you transport data over a traditional network, packets could get dropped, so you
have to resend them or you have to make sure that somehow magically interfering traffic
doesn't do you any harm. And that usually involves quite large JIT above us of up to
several seconds. And if I talk now and you hear me from stage and you hear me from the
EPA four seconds after that, that would be quite annoying. So, you want to cut that down
to as low as possible transmission latency overall, end-to-end latency. Of course, for
TSN, we started as audio video bridging or A-V-B as a standard. They came across the
fact that this technology could also be useful for quite some other applications. Most of
the customers do like machine control stuff with that. So, if you have a large production
line and you want to transmit data between your PLC and your server drives or your robot
arms and stuff, you also want to make sure that your control data arrives in time at
the actor or your sensor data is read in within a certain point in time. And that's quite
important to keep that timing. Same holds, of course, for aerospace and automotive and
railways and stuff. I won't go into these applications today because we're, as I said,
short on time. The first requirement of said applications is that you need to establish
a common time base in the network. That's due to the fact that while measuring time
in computers is basically hooking up a hardware counter to a crystal oscillator. These crash
crystal oscillators tend to have frequency drift over time, especially with temperature.
And due to the different switch on points in time, you also have quite large offsets.
So if you start one device, say at 12 o'clock and the other at 1 p.m., they have one hour
of offset in there. So you want to make sure that all your network devices have a common
meaning or a sense of time passing and a common sense of what time it is because lots of scheduling
decisions for networking traffic may depend on timing. Also, for some applications, as
the audio example, you also would like to regenerate your audio sampling clocks. So
basically in order not to introduce any additional degradation in audio quality, you want to
make sure that your sampling clocks of your ADC and DAC run basically in lockstep. And
that is why you want to make sure that your time is distributed evenly. And the way this
is done usually in networks is just shown basically in this old style picture. You elect
a so-called master clock. So basically that's the best clock reference in your network or
the most stable clock reference in your network. And then basically you compare all other clocks
to that clock reference and they have to adjust their local time for that reference time.
It's basically just as those three gentlemen do in that picture. I like that comparison
because you find a lot of analogies and the standards to just the way that works with
like pocket watches. And if you look into that, you will find that basic idea quite
useful to keep in mind. Now, the other thing we want to have guaranteed is, as I already
said, bound transmission latency. So if we go across the transmission of a data stream
in the network, so that's what the standard calls a talker at the left. And that's what
the standard calls bridges. Usually as we're dealing with layer two, that's ethernet switches.
And in the right, that's what the standard calls a listener. You also call it a source
and a sink. But the standard talks about talkers and listeners. And the packet goes from bridge
to bridge along its path across the network. And each switch, basically a bridge, has an
ingress queue and a switch fabric and an egress queue. That's due to the fact that you can
only transmit one packet out of a certain network port at a time. You can't just, if
another packet at another port arrives for that destination port, you have to store it.
And you have to wait until last transmission is done. And then you can transmit the next
packet. And this introduces what's called a residence time in each switch. So even if
you have a perfect pass through through network without any additional interfering traffic,
you add a little time. At each step, your payload packet travels through the network.
So if our audio starts here, it's a bit later when it arrives here and a bit later when
it arrives there, and so on and so forth. So that's fine, as long as you have no interfering
traffic. Because if you have additional interfering traffic, and that might be because we of course
want to use our audio on converged networks. So we want to use the same network for, say,
our live PA system and for our network internet connection. And we want to download a large
file because we want to download a presentation recording from Fostem. And basically that's
where this entity arrives and it's introduced or it creates a large amount of traffic here.
This will cause the packet here to be delayed until it's sent out of the egress port. And
basically it won't arrive in time. And if we go for as small Jitter buffers as possible,
that's a problem because we have a buffer underrun at the listener side. And basically
we have audio dropouts in the audio case or we have stolen motors in the industrial control
case. And that's something we have to avoid under any circumstances. So basically something
we want to have is quality of service. And so the picture, of course, you're a professional
networking engineer, so you don't need that picture. But the picture I like to use for
that is a bus lane in the street because also the bus runs in a more or less isochromous
way. So you send those bus or packets down the lane and the way not to be hindered by
the interfering traffic there is just basically to introduce a priority lane. And that is
what we also use in networks basically when we introduce quality of service measures.
Another thing we need for at least some of these applications is link layer redundancy.
So imagine if there's a mixing desk right in the back and we run a network link back
there and someone just trips over that link, rips out the cable or maybe it's a fiber link
and someone stomps on the fiber link. Bad things happen and basically if host M is over,
we don't want to have that. So we want to introduce means of having redundancy schemes
there. Basically you can't think of it as a real time capable, real time healing with
no waiting time like spanning tree-ish thing. You want to have the standard spanning trees
quite don't cut it for these kinds of applications so we have to introduce other stuff there.
We have some other application requirements there. They're not so important so I leave
them out for now. Now what does the or what kernel and user space components do we have
to implement that? We will look into what the TSM components are later or what the TSM
components are because that's basically just numbers and letters. So for time synchronization,
for especially TSM we use GPTP. That's a flavor of the precision time protocol, basically
generalized precision time protocol of which you can think of PTP, standard PTP, IEEE 1588
boils down to layer two. So of course we're dealing with raw, ethernet frames so we can't
use UDP for transport and it also has some other quirks but they're not too important
right there. And the way we do that with Linux kernel we have the hardware time-simping units
and the PTP hardware clocks. That's basically the interface to hardware clocks in your ethernet
MAC or PHY and the user space component to run all the remaining stuff is PTP for Linux.
That's basically the way it works and it works quite well. You can achieve down to several
nanoseconds precision from point to point with that. For traffic shaping that's the
quality of service measure we want to employ. The kernel has the TC subsystem and usually
if you configure that manually you use IP
where it works and we will look into a bit of detail later for network management. So
basically if you have to reserve a data flow from a talker to a listener that's where it
gets a bit sketchy because that's of course user space demons and there aren't much. There's
also a problem because there's several ways of doing that. The traditional way of or ABB
style, the initial implementation used the so-called stream reservation protocol. Modern
ways for especially pre-calculated or pre-engineered networks is using Yang-Nadcon extensions.
And there are some demons for that but support for the TSN extensions is not too great. So
if you're into that that's quite a nice thing to work on. For the real-time data packetization
that's mostly user space. Of course you want to use some kernel features like ETF, Qdisks
and XDP to have as low overhead as possible and to make sure that your transmission is
sent out as asynchronously as possible and you want to use offloading for that. And then
there's some very application specific user space components. So for audio video stuff
you can use the G-streamer plugins and for industrial control I'd recommend to use the
Open6651 implementation that's not quite finished yet but it's a good starting point at least.
And for the link layer redundancy that's what PCR and FRAER is. Basically the standards
are finished since one or two years. There's not much hardware supporting that yet and
you really want to have hardware offloading for that so you're basically down to proprietary
vendor stacks at the moment. There are efforts to put stuff mainline but they are not quite
there yet. But stuff is coming and that's the good thing with that. So I think one slide
is missing there which is not a too big problem. Yes, one slide is missing. So basically the
stuff how to put stuff together with TSN I will summarize it without a slide. With time
synchronization we have GPTP that's IEEE 802.1AS for the IEEE standard fetishists here in
the room. Traffic shaping the basic standard stuff is the credit based shaper but there
are more time aware shapers available right now. They are basically making more efficient
use of your network and the way that works is basically reserving bandwidth along your
data flow path in your network. Network management again that's a bit application specific so
the audio video and professional audio video stuff is still using the stream reservation
protocols and for the payload as I already told that's really really application specific.
For redundancy we use PCR and FRER. Usually there are some exceptions to that especially
for professional audio video PCR and FRER weren't standardized when those standards
were written so there are some proprietary or not proprietary but some other redundancy
schemes where you basically send two different streams and try to separate your networks
by means of VLANs usually and try to force different data paths through network. Basically
nowadays you want to go PCR and FRER whenever your hardware support starts. So state of
the union the hard stuff is already done so there's already implementations in the kernel
there are user space demons available. That's again the stuff that's difficult to get right
so if you want to implement those standards first of all you have to read like tons of
paper I did that for an employer took me two years so that's really hard to get right and
the good thing is that that is already implemented you just have to use it and you have to use
the right knobs. For some stuff like GPTP and traffic shaping you want to really really
use for GPTP you have to use for traffic shaping you want to use hardware offloading. You
have to bear in mind that your network gear has to support explicitly GPTP and traffic
shaping so the band with reservation and basically making sure that your traffic shaping is
applied properly. That's not true for every hardware especially not for commodity hardware
and bear in mind that sometimes configuration especially for traffic shaping can be quite
tricky. As I said I have added bonus slides to the presentation I will check that they
have the right slides in there later on or just contact me and the point is especially
credit based shapers can be really really tricky to set up properly and to make sure
that you reserve the bandwidth you want because you want to have the remaining bandwidth to
be available for best effort traffic so the idea is that you can use like say 70% of your
link for your audio video stuff and still have like 30% of your gigabit link which is
what we are usually dealing with for like audio video available for just best effort
network management traffic and whatsoever so you really want to make sure your shapers
are configured the right way to you and it's quite hard to tweak the right knobs in IP
2. So there are good examples and I strongly recommend to read the docs on that there's
also a link to the TSM read the docs for Linux it's quite a good starting point for getting
into that whole topic and yeah basically I think that's it do you have any questions?
Any questions here?
Questions?
Hey thanks for this what's the highest speed Ethernet implementation of this you've seen
like have you gone seen anything beyond like 10 gigi for example or?
I have seen a 10 gig implementation for that as far as I recall the standards and have
some limitations with respect to how you communicate your bandwidth requirements and they're a
bit capped I'm sure and I know that they are working on that for future revisions of the
sun it's because of course now faster links are becoming available more and more most
applications for TSM like the control stuff or the AV stuff are running on 100 megabit
links still you want to go to gigabit links because you can achieve quite a bit lower
end to end latencies on faster links but I haven't seen personally haven't seen faster
stuff than 10 gig so far but I'd be interested to do so.
Do you have happy stories or really users that have put this in production and can you
tell more about this?
Yeah so if you want to check that out you can just google for Milan and TSM which is
the professional audio video stuff and they just before covid started shortly before covid
started they ran the Bumstein concert concert in Munich over a TSM system it's a really
large system with several video balls and several like hundreds of thousands of audio
streams and pyrotechniques and light control and stuff all in the same network converged
so that's the largest installation for live audio I know of and I think that's quite a
good story to tell.
I was curious if you had the chance to play around with synchronous Ethernet as well?
I haven't looked into that too deep yet so I can't tell you too much about that.
You mentioned XDP are you aware of any applications of XDP in that area?
To be honest I haven't seen them and I will start working on some of them for a customer
project in just a few weeks probably.
The idea is that basically because it's layer 2 you don't have much network stack above
the hardware layer so if you can cut some of the Linux networking stack because you
don't use it anyway you work on raw sockets anyway you could just cut some of that out
and try to achieve lower latencies in your basically Linux stack there.
Probably on the next Fostom I can probably give you a talk on that.
This is probably a big question but how do you go about debugging this sort of stuff
so like setting it up or if you think there's a problem how do you go about finding problems?
That's actually a bit of a pain point and you have to know at least a bit what's same
values for like path delays for the PTP and stuff are and one of the most useful debugging
tools I found so far is a good Ethernet switch because it will give you like output for your
stream reservations so it will give you output for your PTP or GPTP.
You can also like sniff traffic with wire taps basically and analyze it in Wireshark
or Skypy or whatever your tool of choice is.
That works best to be honest for 100 megabit links because you can use passive taps.
It doesn't work that great for gigabit links because it violates some of the sounds a bit.
You can also use like mirror ports and switches to exfiltrate traffic but basically it's a
more manual approach of debugging and I'd like to get in touch with if anyone is interested
in just write me an email to start a community based project of automated analysis of TSN
links basically because I think it's something we really really need especially for people
who aren't that deep into the standards and we need to make sure that we can basically
have a one click check and set up and can tell from a tool that at least if that looks
okayish or not what you're doing but I'm not aware of any project so far so I'd like to
start but I'm not too experienced in how to start such a project so if you're experienced
in that or are interested in that just write me an email get in touch and maybe we can
set up something.
Any more questions for the last one?
You mentioned some protocols for link redundancy, can it also be used for node redundancy?
I'm not entirely sure.
I would have to look something up.
I think basically it should because it's about the data path so if one node drops out basically
that would work as well but it won't work for the endpoints so for the talk of the listener
of course it won't work but for nodes in the middle of your graph that would probably work.
Thank you very much again for your presentation.
Thank you.