All right, good afternoon everyone.
Before I get started, how many of you attended the session about Service Mesh this afternoon?
Sorry about that.
If you're fed up with me, you have to stay with me for another session.
I will repeat some parts of it to introduce the topic, but otherwise, I'm sorry about
that.
Welcome to the session, Golden Signals with Siljem and Grafana.
My name is Ray Medión.
I'm field CTO for EMEA at Isovalent.
Isovalent is a company which originated Siljem.
And today I'm going to talk about Grafana and how Siljem enables you to get golden signals
out of the box.
Introduction about technology, a little bit about EBPF and Siljem, then about observability
challenges and how we can tackle those challenges using our observability.
A bit on monitoring, day two operations and the default dashboards we provide.
And then hopefully the demo gods are with me for a small demo to actually see how we
get layer seven metrics and we can see return codes and monitor application response times,
etc.
So to start this topic, I want to introduce Siljem and EBPF.
How many of you know about EBPF?
Quite a lot, awesome.
How many of you know about Siljem and are using Siljem?
Cool, great.
So Isovalent is the company behind each Siljem and EBPF.
We maintain it with the community.
And to start with, EBPF is explaining what EBPF is and how it works.
So we like to say what JavaScript is to the browser, EBPF is to the kernel.
What we mean by that is that we make it extensible in a dynamic way.
So that means we're not changing the kernel, but at kernel speeds we can run programs based
on kernel events.
And for the context of this session, what's important is that considering metrics, considering
getting useful information from your applications, what we're doing here is whenever a process
opens a socket or a packet gets sent on the network device on the node, we can expose
metrics or we can export those metrics using EBPF and we can use tools like Raffana to
display it in a good way so you can do data operations or you can see how your application
or cluster is performing.
Siljem runs on EBPF.
The good thing about Siljem is you don't need to be an EBPF engineer to run and operate
Siljem.
You just set certain configuration options and EBPF programs will be mounted on the nodes
and will run when they need to run.
And Siljem and the high level provides a number of capabilities, networking capabilities,
observability capabilities, also surface mesh and using Tetracon solution we can also use
runtime feasibility and observability security based on processes such as opening files,
process execution, etc.
Today we'll focus about on the observability part.
So besides networking we can get rich visibility of metrics on your cluster.
As you may know, Google uses on data plane V2 actually under the hood Siljem.
Microsoft has moved.
Azure default AKS clusters to Siljem so all the cloud providers see that Siljem is a powerful
technology to run clusters at scale and to get useful metrics running them.
So let's start with common challenges we see.
One of the main challenges if we talk about performance of your application or performance
of your cluster set scale is that you run into this issue of the finger pointing problem.
What I mean by that is that network connectivity is layered and when you run into issues you
need to, especially at scale, you need to be easily aware where a possible problem could
exist.
And it can be in multiple layers and if you look at the OZ layer obviously it can be at
the data link layer, the network layer, the transport layer or in the application layer.
So the goal of Siljem with Kefan is to give you the tools to quickly inspect what's going
on and to be more efficient in troubleshooting your cluster and or applications.
Another common issue, especially at scale, is obviously the signal to noise problem.
You may run in the clouds, you get data from your nodes, you see IP addresses communicating
with each other.
But IP addresses by itself mean nothing in Kubernetes clusters.
They come, they go and at scale it's impossible to track and trace what's going on with service
to service communication in your applications.
Also where are existing mechanisms falling short?
So first of all network devices, think about centralized monitoring or firewall solutions,
think about Splunk.
They are great to get our alerts, to get dashboards, but again at scale they can be very costly
or they can be a bottleneck.
Also these devices don't have awareness of the identities of your applications running
on your Kubernetes clusters.
Cloud provider network logs are nice for node to node communication but don't provide identity
as well.
You can monitor the host, you can see Linux host statistics but that gives you only visibility
on the node level and again a Linux node doesn't have any awareness of the identities of the
services running in your Kubernetes cluster.
You may want to try to modify application code and this applies a bit to the service
mesh session.
You may want to install libraries which gives you visibility of the application but then
you don't have visibility on the networking layer.
Service mesh, main goal of service mesh is obviously visibility of the network and trend
communication to get metrics out of that but that with the sidecar based implementation
comes with a footprint and with induced latency plus you have operational complexity maintaining
your service mesh solution on top of your Kubernetes clusters.
So this is where Cilium comes around the corner instead we provide identity aware based observability
and security.
What that means is based on the labels you set on your workloads we create unique identities
and we're able to attach that identity in the data plane using eBPF and using that identity
we can do things with that.
So we can secure the connectivity in this example a front end to a back end is allowed
to communicate based on the network policies we set and identities we are aware of and
this identity is a cluster wide property but in terms of observability this also means
that we can use this identity to get rich metrics and data for that identity and you
can monitor it effectively.
This means that you're not looking anymore at IP addresses you're looking at identities
so the whole set of workloads the surface to surface communication for a front end to
a back end.
Hubble is our observability solution built on top of Cilium how it works is that Cilium
runs as a democet on your cluster nodes as an agent and Hubble can retrieve data from
those agents through a CLI or UI and we can export metrics based on your workloads.
So there are three parts first of all the Hubble UI gives a service dependency map so
on a namespace level you can see what's deployed what is communicating with each other what
kind of protocols they're using what's coming between namespaces so you would see for example
if there's inter namespace communication you can identify the source namespace if you use
cluster mesh you can even identify the source cluster you can also identify egress traffic
and ingress traffic on a namespace level the Hubble CLI is more a power users tool to give
you detailed flow you can export it to JSON you can do a lot of filtering based on labels
Hubble metrics is the part where it's mostly the topic for today is where you export metrics
and you use Grafana for example to observe the performance of your cluster and application
this is all fueled through eBPF so again think about a network device sending a packet that's
a kernel event eBPF program gets attached to it gets the metrics and it's done this
is a small screenshot of the CLI so this gives you flow visibility using Hubble observe
commands you can follow for example based on the label in this case xwing so we're following
all the workloads labels with xwing so again no IP addresses just labels in purple is highlighted
these IDs we use so again each unique set of labels gets a unique cluster wide ID and
based on those IDs we can track based on labels what communication is going on and there's
a lot of metadata you can filter on things like headers things like ports things like
protocols obviously labels in QNAD spot names surfaces worker nodes DNS we also have cilium
network policies which allow you to filter and observe two FQDN rules meaning we can inspect
queries to external domains and we can filter based on that and obviously cilium related
identities such as world ingress egress host and that kind of stuff policy verdict matches
things like dropped allowed and stuff this is the Hubble UI service map like I said before
this gives you a namespace level view in this case we have a jobs app and I'm using this app
as well in the demo I'm showing a bit later so here you're looking at a namespace level view
where you can see all the service to service communication of your application running in that
namespace in this case it's only intran namespace communication and you can see for example that
the recruiter is talking to core API the core API is talking to elastic search we have a zookeeper
component we identify Kafka also identifying Kafka protocols so there are a number of protocols we
can inspect and see and we also see layer 7 information so in this case HTTP calls to a
specific URI or URL with specific method and return calls and this is triggered through
just simple construct as a cilium network policy if you just allow let's say intran namespace
traffic and you are accepting HTTP that already triggers this visibility for you to see now using
this data we can also export metrics to Grafana so we have into we are working with Grafana a lot
more lately that means that we are building a lot of more useful dashboards and also integrating
with things like tempo for getting transparent tracing in Grafana all powered through cilium and
eBPF this allows us to not only see on the network level metrics on performance on the node but also
for service to service communication to provide golden signals things like HTTP request rate
latency response codes and error codes which would as an application engineer would allow you to
quickly see which components of your application is not responding as it should
but also detecting transduced network layers so this will be more network related we may see
retransmissions we can see byte sent and received and we can indicate things like
round-trip time to indicate a network layer problem so maybe in a data center you have a
specific reg switch or top of reg switch not performing as it should so nodes connected to
that switch will have improved will have reduced performance and you would see latency increasing
now with the latest dashboards we also able to see programmatic API requests using transparent
tracing this goes to the integration with Grafana so at the moment your application
need to be able to support it so you need to be able to inject traces but we're working on
out of the box getting also this support and be able to help by help support HTTP
traces as such and then you get this exemplar so i'm pointing at a small exemplar here
after which you can inspect this with with tempo and you can see a span of specific request
and see where the problem may reside a bit more on monitoring so this is more day to ops
i want to highlight that if you run cilium and you are also using Grafana make sure that you
install the agent hubble and operator metrics plugins these are out of the box plugins we
provide through the Grafana marketplace you can download and this gives you visibility
in the performance of your cluster so first of all agent metrics everything on the node level how
the node is performing how many throughputs they are processing how many memory the bpf is using
all that related stuff hubble metrics gives you the visibility across your cluster in terms of
application layer seven return calls policy verdicts so allows versus drops so you can
monitor on the cluster level the performance of your applications and in some cases you
run an operator so you may want to track the number of identities how the cluster in general
is behaving api responses and such and finally what we released just a few days ago thanks to
rafael who is also here is the cilium policy verdict metrics dashboard which gives you the
capability to get meaningful graphs if you have workloads actually hitting network policies you
set what i mean by that is that when we work with customers with cilium is they want to go to this
micro segmentation zero trust model and you can use obviously hubble to monitor service-to-service
communication and to see if traffic is allowed and denied but this dashboard also is a very useful
tool to confirm if you have either ingress or egress policies which are matching with your traffic
so in this case we see a green graphs which means that on ingress and egress we have matching
traffic the purple represents dns matching traffic but if there's some yellow traffic that's either
allow all match traffic which is too broadly which should trigger you to get even better
network policies to make sure that kind of flows are actually related to a network policy to ensure
that both ingress and egress traffic is secured as such if you do so all the grounds will turn
green and you know and you can confirm for that given namespace that you have securities
all right i've prepared a little demo this runs this tenon jobs application i mentioned before
i'm running this on kind so just a simple kind cluster on my laptop i'm showing here the
components of my application so this you know a number of of workloads i've shown before on a
grid screenshot to help me through this demo i've created a little script and what this does it only
updates a helm chart for this application so it makes my workflow a lot easier i don't have to
enter commands but we should see some things changing in our confana dashboard before i
start this let me highlight the metrics so i need to log in so i've installed graphana i've
installed tempo i've installed prometheus and configured cilium to export those metrics
so this is currently the performance of my application running on my kind cluster on my laptop
so as you can see we have 100 success rate we have
uh incoming 100 and we also have good graphs of information for the performance of the application
okay so let me start with starting this script
yes so i mentioned before that the hubble metrics are available as soon as you configure some kind
of layer seven cilium network policy because that triggers the collection of those metrics
for layer seven and i'm showing this but i will show this a bit better in in in a different window
so what i'm going to do now is i want to increase the request volume so i'm configuring the crawler
component to get more requests in my application as you can see it's redeploying the crawler
component so this would is something we should see in the graphana dashboard while this is redeploying
i can show the helm chart i've used i'm using you need to be a bit patient with me because it takes
one minute before the graphics the the graphana dashboards are updated you can actually see
the impact of this new version of the application so typically you configure cilium through a helm
values file so in this case on the operator component i've enabled metrics and prometheus
on the hubble side i've configured hubble relay together the metrics and also prometheus and metrics
so and this part is very interesting because if you want to have layer seven visibility you need
to have specific metrics being enabled this will be documented in the cilium i.o website
once we have the new release ready so as you can see we are matching HTTP v2 we have enabled
exemplars we are looking for labels in terms of context source ip source namespace etc so these
are important sets of labels you need to set and on the prometheus side we've enabled it to get at
the graphs the cilium network policy i mentioned before this is just a simple example we allow
everything within the namespace we have enabled dns visibility so we're inspecting all dns traffic
to cube dns that allows us to get visibility of dns queries we've enabled ingress and egress
for the purpose of the demo so we can also see that traffic and what's important is that we have
an empty or open rule HTTP which allows us to see all traffic it allows all traffic
but that triggers the collection of metrics all right so on the demo site so it has deployed a
new version of my application looking at my metrics i can see incoming request volume increasing
so you see already an increase of volume we also see requests by source response codes increasing
so still 200 always fine always good just a number just an increase of requests per seconds
and also on the incoming site okay all good
okay let's now deploy a new configuration of our app and this app is has an error
so let's see what we can see there again redeploying the core api components
and now we should be able to see the error rate increase as a result of core api configuration
changing so this will take one minute
here i can select the destination workload so i can switch between core api or the loader
component to see how the traffic for that destination is matching and how it's performing
let's give it a few seconds to actually show what i'm looking for is the incoming request success
rate apparently this application has version as an error so the success rate will be lower than before
okay it's running okay
okay yeah it's always a bit takes a bit longer than i wanted
bear with me you know what in the meantime i'll already start the next step so i can
i don't have you waiting
ah there you go so here you see that the success rate is decreasing because of this faulty version
of my application so i can really see there's something wrong with my application and as
application developer or owning this namespace i should now be able to investigate what's going on
this also means that here on the incoming request by source and response code i would see
the resumes components showing 500 and 503 error return codes which triggers me to check that
component and communication between those components also on the destination site all right
so now i've introduced a new version and what this does is changing the request duration so
again a new version of the application and let's see how we can monitor this performance of the
application in grafana so let's check the request duration increase as a result of core api
configuration changing okay so let's use here so i'm monitoring http request duration by source
and destination so if the demo works well we see an increase there
so
okay
takes a bit too long uncomfortable with but should be there any minutes
with me
should appear any moment
let me just
post in the meantime i will deploy a new version of the application which also introduces
tracing so again for tracing to be supported you at this moment your application needs support that
so in this case i deploy a new version of this application to support tracing
and this is using open telemetry so let's deploy that in the meantime
that's deploying in the meantime i can check how the request duration is doing
okay this part is not working yet but we should see a request duration increase
oh god yeah thanks that doesn't help i clicked on something ah yes thank you so much
yeah here you can see the request duration increasing and i just deployed a new version
of my application which supports tracing using open telemetry and then you already can see that
i have this exemplars appearing so i now only can not only inspect htp request duration
but i can also inspect specific traces and exemplars so let's if you click on this little
box you get this window you can get valuable information about this trace point and then you
can query it with track tempo go yep let's leave this side so here you can see a specific trace id
and you can see a node graph so this is also nice you can see between nodes what's what's going on
and you see highlighted in red here what's has a high latency as such and here we can see that in
this specific uh api call there is an error so post scroll and it has some events exception
random error so something is wrong with my application so this enables me
as an application owner to troubleshoot my application effectively so this concludes the
demo um let me quickly move to here all right so if you want to know more how to configure cilium
to enable metrics how to configure cilium to uh with the right values for layer 7 monitoring
i recommend to read the documentation on cilium.io um if you're using cilium or planning to use cilium
you have questions go to our slack channel we're happy to help you there the community is out there
and very helpful answering questions if you want to know more about eBPF go to eBPF.io we also have
released or close to release a lab with this kind of dashboards as well so feel free to check them
out at isovalent.com forward slash labs and if you want to know more about isovalent as a company
or you may want to contribute we also have open uh positions for engineering as such so if you
want to know more please check us out i'm happy to take questions any questions
hello um thank you for a talk is it possible in the service graph of the hubble um
um ui to show um transitive dependencies of services with the tracing enabled
so with hubble ui the open source version you will see uh service to service community connectivity
only so that related information is not integrated in hubble as such so you would switch between
hubble and grafana to get that information on the enterprise we have been built in dashboards for
getting that specific
areas of monitoring so let's say application or node performance or cluster-wide performance we
have some dashboards which should quickly highlight performance issues there okay thank you okay
um other question hello did you measure the impact of a matrix my correct of matrix on
network performance yeah we do have some performance related reports on cilium.io so
yes it comes with a price using ebpf we keep it as low as possible it's a very hard question
to answer because it will depend on which flags you configure right so if you have full layer
seven visibility across all workloads in your cluster of course it will have some performance
impact for sure yes using ebpf we keep it as low as possible um but yeah it's a multi-dimensional
question depends on the amount of traffic the amount of applications how big your cluster is
etc so we have some performance reports you can check so that's 500 nodes thousand network
policies helpful enables and you get some feel of how memory consumption and processing is
with cilium so feel free to check them out on the cilium.io website but in practice it's
it's a multi-dimensional story welcome any other question in the back yeah hi thanks for the talk
a couple questions about the integration of cilium on aks and gke is there anything specific
regarding those implementations or all the tools work natively on on these kind of clusters
and second questions regarding uh abo UI it's possible to see uh inter namespace
traffic flows or is it limited to intran namespace okay good question so to answer the second
question first yes you can see that so if there is communication between from a different namespace
ingress to your namespace and monitoring you will see that you will see those labels and you will
see the workloads even across clusters if you enable cluster mesh so yes that works out of the
box on the cloud provider side um so if you run aks with azure cni powered by cilium you have a
limited set of metrics which is are enabled and that's obviously from support reasons for microsoft
to support that solution out of the box however you can also choose to bring your own cni with aks
and that also applies to gke and eks to manage cilium yourself right so then you have the freedom
to configure the flags i just shown and to configure configure cilium as such but keep
in mind that you're responsible obviously of monitoring managing cilium um and the cloud
provider will manage the cluster any other question cool we have to oh yeah sorry okay
thank you very much thank you so much