So great to see you all. So many people here. That's awesome. I'm working with my talk.
It's called Decentralized Search with IPFS. Maybe first of all, like a quick pulse, how
many of you have used IPFS? Please raise your hand. Okay. Okay, nice. And how many of you
have heard about IPFS? Okay, all of you. Okay, cool. So you know all about it already. Yeah.
So the talk is called How Does It Work Under the Hood? So we will dive in pretty deep at
some points of the talk. But yeah, first things first. My name is Dennis. I'm a research engineer
at protocol labs. I'm working in a team called Probe Lab, and we're doing network measurements
and protocol optimizations there. I'm also an industrial PhD candidate at the University
of Götting, and you can reach me on all these handles on the internet. So if you have any
questions, reach out and let me know your questions, or just hear the venue after the
talk. So what's in for you today? First of all, just in words and numbers, what is IPFS?
Just general overview. And at that point, after we covered that, I would just assume
we have installed a local IPFS node on your computer, and I will walk you through the
different commands from, yeah, we're initializing some of the repository, we're publishing content
to the network, and so on, and we'll explain what happens in each of these steps so that
all of you hopefully get a glimpse on what's going on under the hood. So we are importing
content, we connect to the network, I explain content routing, this is the very technical
part, and at the end some call-offs, basically. So what is IPFS? IPFS stands for the Interplanetary
File System, and generally it's a decentralized storage and delivery network which builds
on peer-to-peer networking and content-based addressing. So peer-to-peer networking, if
you have followed along, or if you've been here earlier today, Max gave a great talk
about LIP-to-P, about browser connectivity in general in peer-to-peer networks, and IPFS
is one of the main users of the LIP-to-P library and builds on top of that. And most importantly,
it's very tiny at the bottom, IPFS is not a blockchain, so also a common misconception,
I'd like to emphasize that. In numbers, given these numbers are from mid-last year, so probably
in need of an update, but its operation has since 2015, that hasn't changed. Numbers of
requests exceed a billion in a week, and hundreds of terabytes of traffic that we see, and tens
of millions of active users also weekly, but a disclaimer, this is just from our vantage
point, in a decentralized network, no one has a complete view of what's going on, so
these numbers could be much higher or just different in general. On ecosystem.ipfs.tech,
you can find some companies that built on top of this tech, and it's all in these different
areas, social media, and so on and so forth, so worth looking up. What's the value proposition
of IPFS? The most important thing that it does, it decouples the content from its host,
and it does this through a concept that's called content addressing. And content addresses
are permanent verifiable links, and this allows you to request content with this, or request
data with the content address, and anyone can serve you the content, and just from the
address that you ask with, you can identify and verify that the content you got served
is actually the one that you requested, and you are not dependent on the authenticity
of the host, as it's the case with HTTP. Because it's a decentralized network, it's also censorship
resistant, and I like to put here that it alleviates backbone addiction, so what do I
mean with that? Let's imagine all of you, or all of us, wanted to download a 100 megabyte
YouTube video here in this room. We would put pressure, so if we were 100 people, we
would put pressure of about 10 gigabytes onto the backbone to just download the video into
this room. Wouldn't it be better if we could just download it once and distribute it across
each other or download different parts and be a little bit more clever about that? In
a similar vein, if we were working on a Google Doc here inside this room, why does it stop
working if we don't have internet connection anymore? It actually should work, it's actually
ridiculous. Also, for us into the same category, this partition tolerance for emerging networks
could also become very important, or if you're just in Apache coffee shop Wi-Fi. All right,
so how can you install IPFS? I put down three different ways here. IPFS in general is not
you don't install IPFS, IPFS is more specification, and there are different implementations of
this specification. The most common one is Kubo, which was formerly known as Go IPFS,
so it's a Go implementation. There's a new one called Iroh, which is in Rust, and I think
the newest one is in JavaScript called Helia. I think that's also the newest kit on the
block. I will talk about Kubo here. The easiest thing to get started is just download IPFS
desktop, which is an electron app that bundles an IPFS node, gives you a nice UI, and you
can already interact and request CIDs from the network and so on. Then there's the IPFS
companion, which is a browser extension that you can install to Firefox or your browser
of choice. Or you directly use Brave or Opera, which comes in with a bundled IPFS node already.
If you enter an IPFS colon slash slash and a CID, it will resolve the content through
the IPFS network. As I said in the beginning, in this talk we will focus on the command
line because we're in a developer conference. I will also assume that we run Kubo, which
is the reference implementation basically. Now we have downloaded Kubo from github.com
slash ipfs slash Kubo, and we want to import some content. We just want to get started.
We downloaded it, and now we have this ipfs command on our machine. The first thing that
we do is run ipfs init. What this does is it generates a public provide key pair per
default in ed25519. It spits out this random string of characters, which is basically your
public key. Formerly it was just the hash of your public key, but now it's just encoded
your public key in here. This is your peer identity, which will become important later
on. Then it also initializes your ipfs repository. It's a default in your home directory under
.ipfs. This is the location where it stores all the files. If you interact with the IPFS
network and request files, it stores it in this directory in a specific format similar
to Git, how Git objects store basically. Importantly, I will point this out a couple
of times. This is just a local operation. We haven't interacted with the network at
all yet. Now we are ready to go. I have a file I want
to add. What I do is I run ipfs add and then my file name. In this case, ipfs gives you
a progress bar, or Kubo gives you a progress bar, and spits out again a random string of
characters, which is the content identifier, the CID, which is the most fundamental ingredient
here. This is the content from its host. As a mental model, you can think about the CID
as a hash with some metadata. It's self-describing, so the metadata is this description part.
You can see the ingredients at the bottom. It's just an encoded version of some information,
like a CID version. We have version 0 and 1 and some other information that I won't
go into right now. Then it's self-certifying. This is the point where if you request some
data from the network, you certify the data that you could serve with the CID itself and
not with the host that served you the content, just reiterating this. It's an immutable identifier.
All this structure, like the CID structure at the bottom and so on, is governed by a
project that's called Multiformets and is also one of protocol lab's projects here.
The talk is called What Happens Under the Hood? What actually happened here? IPFS saw
the file, which is just this white box here, a stream of bytes, and IPFS chunked it up.
It's in different pieces, which is a common technique in networking, actually. This gives
us some nice properties. It allows us to do piecewise transfers, so we can request blocks
from different hosts, actually. It allows for deduplication. If we have two blocks that
are basically the same bytes, we can deduplicate that and save some storage space underneath.
Also if the file was a video file, we also allow for random access so we could start
in the middle of a video and don't need to stream all the previous bytes at all.
After we have chunked that up, what we do now, or what IPFS does now, is we need to
put it together again. What we do here is we hash each individual chunk. Each chunk
gets its own CID, its own content identifier. Then the combination of each CID again gets
another CID, and we do this for both pairs at the bottom. Then the resulting common CIDs
again will be put together yet again to generate the root CID. That's how we call it. This
is actually the CID that you see in the command line up there. We took the chunks, put the
identifiers together to arrive at the final CID at the top. This data structure is actually
called a Merkle tree, but in IPFS land, it's actually a Merkle DAG because in Merkle trees,
your nodes are not allowed to have common parents. A DAG means here a directed acyclic
graph. Let's imagine you didn't add a file, but a directory. How do you encode the directory
structure and not only the bytes and so on? All these formatting and serialization, deserialization
things are governed by yet another project. It's called IPLD, which stands for Interplanetary
Linked Data. IPLD does also a lot of more things, but for now, this is specified in
the scope of this project. Now we have imported the content. We have chunked it up. We've
got the CID, but again, we haven't interacted with the network yet. People think if you
add something to IPFS, you upload it somewhere and someone else takes care of hosting it
for you for free, which is not the case. We added it to our local node. Now it ended up
in this IPFS repository somewhere on our local machine. Only now we connect to the network
and interact with it. For that, we run IPFS daemon, which is a long-running process that
connects to nodes in the network. We see some versioning information with which Go version
was compiled, which Kubo version we actually use. We see the addresses that the Kubo node
listens on and also which ones are announced to the network under which network addresses
we are reachable. It tells us that it started an API server, a web UI, and a gateway. The
API server is just an RPC API that is used by the command line to control the IPFS node.
The web UI is the thing that you saw previously when you saw the screenshot of the IPFS desktop.
Your local Kubo node also serves this web UI. Then the gateway. The gateway is quite
interesting. This bridges the HTTP world with the IPFS world. You can ask under this endpoint
that you can see down there. If you put slash IPFS slash your CID inside the browser or
in your SAD URL, the Kubo node will go ahead and resolve the CID in the network and serve
it to you over HTTP. This is a bridge between both worlds. ProCollapse and Cloudflare and
so on are actually running these gateways on the internet right now, which you can use
just with a low barrier entry to the whole thing. Then the daemon is ready. In this process,
it has also connected to bootstrap nodes, which are hard coded to actually get to know
other peers in the network. You can also override it with your own bootstrap nodes.
Now we are connected to the network. We've added our file to our own machine. Now the
interesting or the problem or the challenge, how do we actually find content hosts for
a given CID? I give my friend a CID. How does the node know that it needs to connect to
me to request the content actually? I put here the solution is simple. We keep a mapping
table. We just have the CID mapped to the actual peer. Every node has this on their
machine. Everyone knows everything basically. As I said, the mapping table gets humongous,
especially if we've split up those files into different chunks. I think the default chunking
size is 256 kilobytes. We have just a lot of entries in this table, so this doesn't
scale. The solution would be to split this table and each participating peer in this
decentralized network holds a separate part of the table. Then we are back to square one.
How do we know which peer holds which piece of this distributed hash table data? The solution
here would be to use a deterministic distribution based on the Cardemna DHT. Cardemna is an
implementation or a specific protocol for a distributed hash table. At this point, many
talks on the internet about IPFS gloss over the DHT and how it works. When I got into
this whole thing, I was lacking something. My experiment would be to just dive even a
little deeper into this. I will cover a bit of Cardemna here. This is very technical,
but at the end I will try to summarize everything so that every one of you guys gets a little
bit out of this. This whole process is called content routing, so this resolution of a CID
to the content host. IPFS uses an adaptation of the Cardemna DHT by using a 256-bit key
space. We are hashing the CID and the peer ID yet again with SHA-256 to arrive in a common
key space. The distributed hash table in IPFS is just a distributed system that maps these
keys to values. The most important records here are provider records which map a CID
to a peer ID. Remember the peer ID is what was generated when we initialize our node.
And peer records which then map the peer ID to actually network addresses like IP addresses
and ports. Looking up a host for a CID is actually a two-step process. First, we need
to resolve the CID to a peer ID and then the peer ID to their network addresses and then
we can connect to each other. The distributed hash table here has two key features. First,
an X or distance metric. That means we have some notion of closeness. What this XR thing
does, if I X or two numbers together, the resulting number or this operation satisfies
the condition and the requirements for a metric. This means I can say a certain peer ID is
closer to a CID than some other peer ID. In this case, peer ID X could be closer to CID
1 than peer ID Y. This allows us to basically sort CIDs with peer IDs together. Then this
tree-based routing mechanism here. In this bottom right diagram, I got this from the
original paper, we have the black node. With this tree-based routing, this is super clever
as in each bubble, so all the peers in the network can actually be considered as in a
big try, a prefix try. If we know only one peer in each of these bubbles, we can guarantee
that we can reach any other peer in the network with O log N lookups by asking for even closer
peers based on this XR routing mechanism here. This was just abstractly what the distributed
hash chain IPFS does. How does it work concretely for IPFS? We started the daemon process. What
happened under the hood was we calculated the chart with 56 of our peer ID, which just
gives us a long string of bits and bytes, or just bits basically in our case. We initialized
the routing table at the bottom. This routing table consists of different buckets. Each
bucket is filled with peers that have a common prefix to our peer ID, the hash from our peer
ID at the top. When our node started up, we asked the bootstrap peers, hey, do you know
anyone who is chart with 56 from peer ID starts with a one? This means we have no common prefix
and we put them those peers in bucket zero. Then we do the same for a prefix of 00 and
011. We go through all the list until 255 and we fill up these buckets. These buckets
are these little blobs in these little circuits that you saw on the previous slide. Why did
we do that? Because when we now want to retrieve contents, as I said, I handed the CID to my
friend and my friend enters the CID in the command line with this IPFS get command. Their
node also calculates the chart with 56 of the CID and then looks in its own routing
table. Cs, okay, I have a prefix of two. I take one peer out of this bucket two and ask,
yeah, locate the appropriate bucket, get a list of all peers. Then I asked all of these
peers in the bucket, hey, do you know anyone? First of all, do you know the provider record
already? Do you know the CID and the peer ID to that CID? If yes, we are done. If not,
we are asking, do you know anyone closer based on this XOR metric? Then this peer yet again
looks in its own routing table. We get closer and closer and closer with this log n property
that I showed you previously. For publishing contents, basically the same. We calculate
the chart with 56 of the CID, locate the appropriate bucket, get a list of all the peers from that,
and then we start parallel queries. Instead of asking for the provider record, we ask
for even closer peers. We terminate when the closest known peers in the query actually
haven't replied with any peer that's closer. It hasn't replied with anyone closer to the
CID than we already know. Then we start the provider record with the 20 closest peers
to that CID and we do it with 20 because there's peer churn. This is a permissionless network.
This means peers can come and go as they wish. If we only stored it with one peer, we would
risk that the provider record is not reachable when the node comes down and in turn all content
is not reachable. This is the very technical part of that.
Let me summarize this. This is probably the easier way to understand all of this. First
of all, we added the content to our node and so this is the file, enters the provider.
The provider looks in its routing table, gets redirected to a peer that is closer to the
CID and gets redirected until it finds the closest peer in this XR key space metric to
the CID and then stores the provider record with that. Then off-band, the CID gets handed
to the requester, to my friend. What I didn't say or told you yet, it's also IPFS maintains
a long list or I don't know how many it is right now, probably 100 or so, constant connections
to other peers and opportunistically just ask them, hey, do you know this CID or the
provider record to the CID? If this resolves, all good, we are done. It's very unlikely
for people to actually know a random CID. Let's assume this didn't work. This requester
also looks in its own routing table, gets redirected, gets redirected even closer to
the peer ID of that CID and then finds the peer that stores the provider record, fetches
the provider record, then does again the same hops to find out the mapping from the peer
ID to the network addresses and then we can actually connect with each other and transfer
the content and we're done. This is the content life cycle and this is already it. Well, already
it is quite involved actually. With that, it's already time for some callouts. Get involved.
IPFS is an open source project. If you're into measurements and so on, we have some
grants open at radius.space. If you want to get involved with some network measurements,
get your applications in, all action is in public. You can follow along our work, especially
my work of our team at this GitHub repository. We have plenty of requests for measurements
that you can dive into and extra ideas are always welcome. In general, IPFS is I think
a very welcoming community, at least for me. That's it. Thank you very much.
Any questions? Is the way you describe using the DHD how all nodes in the network share
files with each other? It's one content routing mechanism. There are multiple ones. It's a
bit, this first thing that I said here, this opportunistic request to your immediate nodes
is also some kind of content routing, so you're resolving the location of content. Then there
are some new efforts for building network indexes, which are just huge nodes that store
the mapping, centralized nodes, which federated centralized nodes, so not as bad. I think
these are the important ones, basically. There are more ways to resolve. Also, MDNS could
also be one part. If you're on the same network, you're broadcasting. No, that's just for... Sorry?
We're still to the DHD and the DNS. We're using the DNS to find the location.
For the local, yeah. Okay, true. Luckily, we have a core maintainer of IPFS here. It's
actually not a joke, but yeah. Sorry. I see that the provider records get replicated,
but does the content actually get replicated across the network too? No. Only if someone
else chooses to. You're publishing the provider record, so it's public somewhere, and anyone
could look that up and also store the record themselves. This is the idea. If content is
popular and you care about the content staying alive in the network, it's called pin, the
CID, and this means you're fetching the content from this other provider and store it yourself
and become a provider yourself. Because of the CID mechanism, which is self-certifying
and so on, other peers that request the content from you don't even need to trust you because
the CID already encodes the trust chain here. But there's nothing that's not happening automatically
here. But you can have multiple providers for the same company. Yeah, definitely. That's
part of it. Another question is how does the project fit in the concept of identity and
trust and personas into IPFS? I'm thinking metadata, reifications about the content and
stuff like that. What do you mean exactly? For instance, just a history of the content
and can you trust that this content is from a certain person or from a certain... I won't
argue this, but this would probably be some mechanism on top of this content and identification.
This is more for IPLD then or for... Perhaps. I would say, if you want to say some content
is from some specific person, then you would work with signatures, so signing the data
and so on, which is something you would bolt on top of IPFS, but nothing I think IPLD has
encoded there right now. It's partly the same question about how it is entered that there
are no collisions in the content ID. No collisions? Yes, because if you publish some other content
with the same content ID, he said it's happening locally, the content ID generation. You could
fake contents. Yeah, but then all these cryptographic hash functions would be broken then, which
would be very bad. If you have a hash collision, then it actually means you have the same content.
That is the assumption right now. We just use a Shadow 56 by default, and you can use
also one like Blake 3, Blake 2, but if you find a collision in Shadow 56, you have bigger
problems and IPFS not working. Exactly this. Follow on on this. How resilient is this against
malicious actors that want to prevent me from reaching the content? It's a big question,
but maybe something. Yes, on peer-to-peer networks, often these kind of civil attacks are an attack
vector that is considered, which means you generate a lot of identities to populate just
some part of the key space to block some requests from reaching the final destination and so
on. From my experience, this is quite hard, and I haven't seen this happening. I cannot
say that it's impossible, probably hard to tell. Max, do you want?
True. This civil thing is just one attack vector, but this is the common one that is
considered. There are many points in the code base where you need to think about what happens
if this attack is going on. One thing that Cardimna does is to prefer long-running nodes,
and the routing table. If someone immediately generates a lot of identities that they don't
end up in your routing table and pollutes your content routing here or interferes with
that. I'm not sure if I want to ask it, but removing content, deleting. We got GDPR, so
is there any solution that can be done? It's hard. That's part of the thing. If you could,
then it's not censorship resistant anymore. One solution, one alleviation maybe, is to
have blacklists of CID that you may publish or may not to say, okay, don't replicate this
CID and so on. If you have such a list, then it's very easy to just look it up and see
what's inside. Deleting content is very tricky. However, I said it's permanent links. The
links are permanent, but actually, content still churns in the IPFS network. These provider
records that you publish into the network expire after 24 hours. If no one actually
reprovides the content or keeps the content, the content is gone as well. A delete operation
doesn't exist, so we just need to hope that no one will be provided anymore, which you
could do with these denialists, for example. Who is able to write into that blacklist?
This is just one, I don't know, to be completely honest, but this is just one, maybe Geropo
knows. There is no blacklist in the network right now. It's some people, it's a few people
that want that. But we have, so, sorry, earlier you said that we have gateways, and gateways
is just a node that publicly is reachable. Those gateway, because many people say that
they find some content illegal on IPFS, and instead of reporting to the actual node, storing
the content on IPFS, they just report it on the gateway, because they know HTTP and they
don't know IPFS. Our gateway has some blacklist that is somewhere, but it's not shared by
the complete network. It's just for our gateway IPFS.io.
CloudFare, for example, and Percolabso, are already writing these gateways, or more, anyone
could operate a gateway. You could file a request for this, don't replicate the CID,
it's a phishing website, for example. Then these CIDs are not served through the gateways,
which is a common way to interact with the network right now.
Just the gateway that follows the list. It's not automatic.
Yeah, of course. Of course, yeah.
Okay, we're running out of time, unless there is one more. I have a question regarding searching
through the stored content. Is there any mechanism on how to go through or index the files that
are there to have some sort of a search engine for that?
There's a project called IPFS Search, and this makes use, among other things, of this
immediate request for CIDs. It's just sitting there connecting to a lot of nodes. As I said,
if someone requests content, you immediately ask your connected peers, and you're connected
to a lot of peers. These IPFS Search nodes are just sitting there listening to these
requests. They see, okay, someone wants the CID, so I go ahead and request that CID as
well, and then index that content on myself. You can then search on this IPFS Search website
for something with Google, and then you see CIDs popping in, and then you can request
those CIDs from the IPFS network. This is one approach to index content.
Okay, thank you.
Thank you.