Hello, thank you for coming.
I'm very happy to see lots of people here.
I hope you will enjoy my presentation.
So I'm Pawel and I will talk about DDoS detection using open source tool.
So first of all, where and why I'm talking here.
I'm software engineer.
I got formal educational software engineer and since beginning of my career, I started
working on open source and my first programming language was quite unusual, I would say.
It was Perl.
So not fortunately choice for so many people, but for me it was a way into industry.
So I worked for domain name register.
I worked for cloud compute company.
I worked for internet exchange.
And finally I got a job for global CDN provider and I ended up working in cybersecurity.
So what I'm doing now, I'm in charge of development of cybersecurity product for network security
and this product is called FastNetMonter.
So I would like to start from brief description of what is FastNetMonter.
FastNetMonter is an application.
So it's a very first thing to clarify.
It's cross-platform application and why I'm saying cross-platform, I mean Linux, MacOS,
VBSD, OpenBSD.
It's not yet on Windows, but it's still.
And main purpose of FastNetMonter is the DDoS detection for networks.
From technical perspective, FastNetMonter is implemented using modern C++.
Back in time it was quite interesting story when FastNetMonter was started, very, very
first version of it in 2013 was implemented in C++11.
But because of compilers in some way, not so very modern distribution, they had to move
back to C++98.
Since that we still support modern versions.
No way to like, no reason to maintain compatibility with this very outdated stuff and now it's
like, it's really good for C++.
It's kind of C++ actually in Rehacking, Creding, and changing if you prefer to do so.
And I know this feeling.
When you hear about new stuff which may be relevant for you, that's the first urge to
maybe, should I try it now immediately?
Because what is the point with documentation?
What's the point to hear my presentation?
If you can just install it right now.
It did very long.
It was very long journey.
I would like to thank our maintainers who made it possible that FastNetMonter has so
many distributions.
For almost every single popular distribution, I used mostly for server environment and production
environment, you may install FastNetMonter on just single command.
So you may start it right now if you prefer.
And if for some reasons your distribution have no distillation FastNetMonter or you
want to just install it for some distribution is not covered by our official packages, there
is installation tool.
Let's go forward.
Because most of the time we talk about what our tools and our products can do.
I would like to start from an unusual angle.
I would like to highlight what we can do because it's important.
Because there are so many tools for DDoS detection.
There are so many angles of DDoS detection.
It's detection part.
It's mitigation part.
It can be implemented on premise and in cloud.
And before we go into details what we are doing, we need to highlight what we are not
doing.
And if you have any issues with your website or your blog, I'm sorry.
We can't help you.
It's not the point of FastNetMonter.
It may indirectly help your carrier or service provider.
But for your case, it's better to use cloud services because it's not that complicated
to move site around.
Because normally if I'm talking about really a normal site, it's quite easy to move into
a content delivery network and then cover it from the desk.
And if you have some issues with DDoS when you play on your Xbox or PlayStation, also
I'm sorry.
We cannot help you.
I explicitly decided to add this slide because you have too many questions.
And I think it's one of the really serious problems in modern days because you cannot
play because of DDoS.
And if you use managed service provider, it may be public cloud.
It may be private cloud.
And when I say managed, it means that somebody is in charge of keeping your service running.
And in this case, it's very unlikely that you have access for your network.
I mean, administrative level of access is a bit change policy, inspire policy, change
router configuration.
And in this case, it's better to escalate to your service provider like, how for help?
So we have something.
We have some problems.
Help us.
And finally, what FastNetMonter can help you?
FastNetMonter is not to protect specific service.
FastNetMonter here to protect your network.
And when I'm saying to protect network, it has very different meaning from protecting
specific entity.
Main purpose of FastNetMonter is to keep up time of all network in general.
And when I'm saying in general, it means that keep it running for 99% of customers'
eyeball services behind the specific network.
And I'll explain how we can do it.
What kind of attacks we can protect your network from?
Again, there are so many types of attacks.
There are so many opinions about classification of attack.
I'm not going to go into details about what the kinds of data are.
I would like to focus it from well-described OSI model approach.
So what we can help you?
We can help you with IPv4 and IPv6 at the same time.
If you still use IPv4, please don't.
Please move away from it.
And in terms of layers of OSI model, we can help you only with levels L3 and level 4.
And if you have some specific ideas what is the option to filter out traffic using HTTP
or two or three protocol encrypted by TLS, it's better, I guess, to just present it like
Suricata because FastNetMonter is a little bit autoscoped.
Because main purpose of FastNetMonter is to detect volumetric DDoS attack.
And when I say volumetric, it means at least hundreds of megabits.
But mostly in general case for average size of DDoS in modern days, it's around 8 gigabits.
And in some cases, it's exceptionally high.
It's maybe hundreds of gigabits.
But on average, it's just a few gigabits.
And that's purpose of FastNet, to take this kind of attack.
So what is the very first step when we assume that network is under DDoS?
Because when I say assume, can we say for sure is that DDoS?
Because in so many cases, how we actually can observe DDoS attack against our network.
Like you check your phone, it's not working.
Your website is not working.
You check laptop in your office, and for some reason, something doesn't work as expected.
Our customer is calling you.
And first step is to confirm that actually DDoS.
Because it may be not DDoS, it may be fire alarm in your data center.
Why it's extremely important to assume that it's actually DDoS?
Because it may be something different.
And in case of fire, it's way more important and way more different kind of actions to
remedy the DDoS detection.
And if you know by accident that some people, your colleagues working in data center right
now, and it's like the same timeline, you receive call from customer like, something
doesn't work.
It's very unlikely that it's DDoS.
It's maybe caused by this configuration because there are so many ways how we can figure downtime
in our networks.
And okay, we covered most of the sources which can cause network DDoS, network downtime.
We said actually DDoS, but...
And look, even this one, it's not DDoS.
This one is it can cause havoc.
It can bring down whole cities, countries, data centers, but it's still not DDoS.
And what is it for how we can say like this was for sure DDoS and graphs.
The only way to be 100% sure it's graphs.
And by looking on this graph, if you know like, okay, my network generates like 100,000
packets per second, or like 100 gigabytes.
And if you can see spikes by 20 gigabytes, it's very unlikely it was caused by Samsung
normal.
It's very, very like it is DDoS.
So it's first level of remediation, at first level how Fasten one can help you.
Fasten one can say for sure, in this kind of dashboard that you are under DDoS.
And then you can actually do it appropriately because you are well prepared.
You know what you can do.
And what we can do in this case.
Fasten one provides lots of different dashboards.
And main benefit of those dashboards is that they're built not on physical level of network.
But when I'm saying physical level of network, I mean a port counter, slot for specific interface,
slot for specific router.
And what Fasten one can do, it's more of the review of your network from logical level.
When I say logical level, it's more from networks, prefixes, specific services.
And in this case, Fasten one can provide a required amount of granularity.
It's like total traffic for your network.
In this case, you can say, total time coming back.
And in case of any spikes here, you may see it almost immediately.
It's one of the benefits of Fastenet Monet.
It's not historical data.
It's data which actually was just received from your routers.
It's almost real-time data.
And so in the same case, again, from logical perspective, it's not a button.
Instead of seeing what is the load for specific interface on my router, you can see information
about how much traffic you have for specific prefix.
And you're well aware what kind of service is trying in specific prefix.
And so you can understand something wrong with this specific prefix.
And again, the latest level of granularity, you may find island traffic for per host because
you may know that for specific prefix, you just have two services, very important services
running.
And then you can check what is the load, for example.
And you can see immediately, again, in real time, what's wrong.
If you can see spike for the specific service, OK, we found it.
And Fastenet Monet graphic capabilities include complete sub-platform, fluxDB, graphit, and
plenty of graphana dashboard.
I would like to thank the community for contributing so many great dashboards because when we started
this idea, we implemented a few of them, quite basic ones.
But the community did a really great job by playing two of them.
And actually, most of them are way better than our official dashboards.
And what is the source of this data?
Is it AI or something different?
No.
So we receive this information from routers or switches in your network.
And from perspective of protocols, we support almost all available protocols in market.
And of course, one of the most popular ones.
It's NetFlow, it's IPv6, S-Flow.
And in case of last resort, if you have no Nethly, but NetFlow or IPv6 in your network,
you can try to use PortMirror.
All cases, Fastenet Monet can handle a really significant amount of traffic.
And there are plenty of confirmed deployments of Fastenet Monet, exceeding at least two
terabytes of capacity in total.
So after you've got all information, you may check it manually.
For example, again, at this moment, this Fastenet Monet, you will see what's your total load.
What is load for specific network?
What is load for specific cost?
And for small networks, you may find immediately what is the victim.
Because in case of small network, you know, OK, I have 12 services, maybe 20.
And you can check one by one.
Can we do it for DDoS detection?
And this one is just not very precise map of United Kingdom.
And you can see there are lots of interconnections.
This is the largest country of the planet.
But you can see amount of interconnections.
It's incredible.
Even for medium-sized internet service providers or telecom providers, they may cover at least
multiple countries.
And you can see amount of towns, even regions, is incredible.
And if you talk about networks covering multiple European countries or multiple countries in
maybe, for example, Asia, it's an incredible amount of locations, an incredible amount
of entities.
You cannot check, like, for example, we are under DDoS.
You know for sure.
Let's check every single one plus million city in Europe.
We cannot do it manually.
It's just impossible.
And every single time, moving from large cities, we need to move to regions.
Then we need to check household, by household, because this specific attack, it may begin
specific person playing like a four-night game.
In this specific building, you cannot do it manually, unfortunately.
If we move a little bit to data centers, data center normally, as we can make here, it's
single building, maybe huge building.
But it's still just one building.
It's not scattered over like continent.
It's not scattered over like thousands of kilometers.
Is it easy to find out?
No, unfortunately.
Because sadly, in data center, we have more entities, more potential victims of DDoS than
actually for large telecom networks.
And what we can do?
Of course, as I mentioned, you can manually check every single host available in your
network because we already got pretty great dashboard and we have real-time data coming
from your routers.
What is the logic?
What is the way how we can actually find that?
Again, we have data about what is the bandwidth for a specific network?
What is the packet rate for a specific network?
And we can check every single host in our network and find out.
And again, in case of data center and large telecom networks, it's impossible to do it
manually.
That's the reason how FastNet1 can help you.
FastNet1 can do it for you.
And it can do it really fast.
For almost all protocols supported by FastNet1, we can offer detection time in less than five
seconds.
So it's not about FastNet1 can say, look, you're under DDoS.
Because it may be clear from graphs.
And this point of time, FastNet1 can find out what is the specific service in your network
which is under attack right now.
And you will have this information in five seconds.
So why it's important, like five seconds?
Why?
Can we wait a little bit?
Like have a cup of tea or coffee and wait?
Unfortunately, we cannot.
That's the main problem.
Back in time when I started to work with DDoS attacks, it was around 2008.
You can wait for around half hour when DDoS attack starts from something like 10 megabits,
maybe then 15 megabits, 100 megabits.
And we have a cup of coffee, wait a little bit, 20, like something like 50 megabits,
100 megabits.
It's growing.
And now what we can see attack on the skeleton from like 100 megabits to tens of gigabits
in like a few seconds.
And human being, unfortunately, ahead of me, cannot handle it so fast.
We need some machines because people who actually run DDoS, they have lots of automation.
And without having automation in place, we cannot defend it.
So FastNet1 provides this option for you.
And instead of checking every single host in your network vendor, because it's still
an option, you can verify when you receive reports from FastNet1, you can check graphs
like is it DDoS?
Is it looking like DDoS?
Because FastNet1 inside, it uses very simple rules like each specific host in my network
generates more than five gigabits of bandwidth.
And each specific host in my network generates more than 100,000 packets per second.
It's clearly DDoS.
And after detection, what we can do, and very first step, which is available for every single
carrier on this planet, unfortunately, it's free.
Everything called BGP black hole.
BGP black hole needs a little bit more clarification how it works.
And because of name, you may guess if you put something into black hole, you never see
it again.
And that's the point.
And how FastNet1 can help and can rely on BGP black hole to stop DDoS from network.
At the beginning of my presentation, I mentioned that FastNet1 here to protect your network,
without specific service.
And it's really important because BGP black hole can be described in many words because
it's quite complicated abstraction.
But I would call it, it's like religion sacrifice made by network engineers to keep their network
running.
Why is it sacrifice?
Because when you do black, because like at this point of time, you know, for example,
for our network, we have 20,000 of hosts.
Just imagine every single host, it's residential building in somewhere in Europe.
And we know for sure, we are receiving DDoS right now.
And our service degraded.
Our customers calling us.
Our site doesn't work.
Nothing works fine.
And we can find out what is the victim of this specific attack using FastNet1.
And we know specific host, which is IPv4 or IPv6, which is a target of this DDoS attack.
And what we need to do using BGP black hole, we need to stop all traffic from coming to
this specific host.
Which means if we effectively disabling and unplugging this specific customer or service
from the internet, and that how BGP black hole works, it's not about like firewall, which
may block attackers.
In this case, we literally manually voluntarily block target or attack.
Just to save our network.
And that's only purpose of FastNet1, to stop it and do it automatically for you.
So after you stop it, and you can see exactly on this diagram.
So we maintain uptime of network.
And everything is skip working by sacrificing just one host on your network.
And it doesn't mean that you just block it and go away, send it.
I can give you an email to customer.
Look, we block it your service.
We can help you.
There are so many ways how you can actually keep this host running.
But again, before you apply some actions, create plan, what we can do, maybe you can
call some specific providers to provide the fence for it.
You need to have some actions.
And better to apply these kind of actions in quiet environment.
Instead of having to deal with 20,000 of calling customers every single like minute, you may
block specific target.
You may keep uptime of your network back.
And when your network is back to operation, in quiet environment, in way quieter environment,
nobody here, nobody calling you, decide, I would like cup of coffee or tea, what is the
option, what we can do for this specific customer.
And then how FastNet1 can help you.
And since beginning, when FastNet1 was built, it was open source from very fast version.
And a lot of features, I just explained it.
They were implemented by our master plan or our roadmap.
They were part of community requests.
We received a GitHub because of look, there is an option.
I have a problem and I would like to solve it.
So since the beginning, FastNet1 was community-driven project.
And we have lots of community channels, how you can collaborate with us, how you can share
your stories, how you can ask questions.
And please join all of them and I will help you to answer your questions.
Thank you.
Anybody has questions?
Hi, thanks a lot.
Quite interesting.
So I just wanted to ask you if you ever felt the need to extend the way you want to.
Hi, thanks a lot, quite interesting.
Like for example, any flavor of open config specifications or eventually BMP instead of
BGP.
That's a great question.
So the question was, is it possible to use protocols like Open BMP or OpenConf to feed
more information to FastNet1?
In current generation of FastNet1 detection tools, we mostly rely on traffic telemetry
protocols, which actually carries part of network packet.
It's maybe header of network packet or it may be some meta-information about source
port, source IP, destination port, destination IP.
And we don't use data about BGP directly.
The only way how we can actually interact with BGP is that we have internal BGP demand
based on Go BGP, which actually injects information and announces routers to your network.
So we have no backward integration from network.
So we have no way how we can learn information from your network.
But because of different APIs, we offer different ways to automate and run callback scripts
instead of just running BGP.
You can run your own Python script and then you can rely on information from third-party
source and combine this information and make decisions using this information.
I was merely asking because, for example, with the GNMI, you can have a sort of retroaction
on the network.
So you can, according to what you're receiving using IP fix, for example, you can have an
action directly on routers, for example.
Yes.
It is one of the ways how you can actually use so-called callback scripts because when
Fastenit on detects attack, it can run specific script, it may be Bash script, Python script,
Perl script.
And in this script, you will have access to basic information about attack and information.
What is the target?
What is host target?
What is the type of attack?
What is prefix target?
And then using any automation protocol, you can run actions on routers.
And because of most of the routers, there are no standard way how we can inject this
kind of information for every single vendor available on market.
And we decide to earn more, more these tasks to market communities, so to implement it
on your own.
Thank you.
And if you implement it, share this community.
Can you do BGP flow spec to like Blackhole?
That's a great question.
So back in time, we had BGP flow spec support based on exaBGP, but it was like POC level
quality of implementation because it was just literally hardcore, at least for DNS and SSDP
amplification.
But it worked well.
So the only, but unfortunately, because of complexity of working this API of exaBGP flow
spec protocol, we decided to remove this capability.
And now the only one way how you can actually inject flow spec roles, like because you can
implement Blackhole using flow spec, you can run it using go BGP command line from callback
scripts of fast-forward.
Okay.
Thank you.
Any more questions?
No.
Thank you very much.
Thank you for listening.
Thank you.