Welcome to the first talk in the Network Dev Room, peer-to-peer browser connectivity.
We're going to talk a bunch about WebRID-C and the new Shiny Web Transport Protocol and
in general how to get the browser connected to a larger network.
Before we start, very grateful to be here, thanks to all the organizers, thanks to all
the volunteers making this event possible.
That's wonderful.
Yeah, and then thanks for all of you to be here and listening.
Cool.
Just a quick introduction about myself.
I'm Max.
I'm a software engineer at Protocol Labs.
I'm starting the LIPIDP project.
I'll do a brief introduction about LIPIDP.
So don't worry too much about that.
Designing the rest implementation of the library.
In the past life, you might know me from my Prometheus time.
I worked a bunch on Prometheus and its integration into Kubernetes.
Still a little bit active in that community.
You find me anywhere on the web with MX Engine and then on the website you find emails in
case you want to get in touch.
All right.
So what is LIPIDP?
Just a small disclaimer.
The talk does mention LIPIDP from time to time.
It is not particularly important.
So in a sense, if you want to build your own LIPIDP application, all the content here is
applicable for you as well.
But if you want to have this pre-built, you can leverage LIPIDP.
So what is LIPIDP?
LIPIDP, as you can infer from the name, I'm guessing, is a peer-to-peer networking library.
It has one specification.
And then that specification is implemented in many, many different languages, like, for
example, Go, JS, Rust, NIM, C++, Java, but a couple others as well.
The goal of LIPIDP is provide low-level features, like encryption, authentication, hole punching,
and things like that.
And then on top of that, leverage those features to then also provide higher-level protocols,
like, for example, DHT, distributed hash table, or gossiping protocols, or things like that.
My big slogan always is, LIPIDP is all you need to build peer-to-peer applications on
the internet.
OK, wonderful.
One small disclaimer that's important later on is that I want to highlight here is LIPIDP
always encrypts and always authenticates, and we'll go into that later on, what that
means.
But that's very important for me.
We don't ship any traffic over the internet that is ever unencrypted or not authenticated.
And in terms of authentication, I'm talking about mutual authentication.
OK, that's enough introduction for today.
And now to the actual topic.
What I want to convey today is how we can get from here, from the left side to the right
side.
So my great motivation is for browsers to be first-class citizens in networked applications.
Now on the very left side, you see the typical internet application today.
So you have a browser.
I'm using the Firefox logo here, but you can use any browser, really.
That tries to interact with the networked application somewhere in the internet.
Instead of interacting with the nodes directly, it acts through a server, and that server
acts on behalf of the browser.
The browser pretty much never interacts with the whole network.
And to put this with an example, if you, for example, have a file sharing, you want to
share a file.
So for example, from my laptop here, I want to share a file with all of you.
I would usually upload that to a server, and then all of you would download it from that
server.
We would never interact directly.
Now there are many reasons for that to be a good architecture.
Browsers usually move a lot.
They might be in the living room, then in a cafe, and then at a conference in Fosdam.
And they are usually low power.
But what's the most heard argument for this kind of architecture in comparison to the
right architecture is that you cannot connect to browsers, and that browsers cannot connect
to other nodes.
That's oftentimes heard.
And what I want to convey here today is that you can actually nicely connect a browser
to a whole network, and that the browser actually has a lot of connectivity options out there,
and I want to go through these.
And the next time you design a networked application, maybe you want to consider the architecture
on the right, versus the architecture on the left.
All right.
Cool.
When it comes to connectivity for a browser, I want to differentiate this in two dimensions.
And the first dimension is whether my node, whatever, for example, my computer here, is
public or private.
So can it be reachable directly, or is it behind an at or firewall?
And or firewall.
And public, you would usually refer to as a server.
And then private, you would, for example, refer to my laptop or the browser running
on my laptop.
Cool.
Then the other dimension, when we talk about connectivity, I want to differentiate in two
platforms, which is browser and non-browser.
Why is this relevant?
Well, there are a lot more platforms, I know.
But usually it's the non-browser, which is very unrestricted, in terms of, for example,
I have access to UDP or TCP socket.
And then I have the browser, which is very restricted, where sometimes I can't make a
connection without, for example, that TLS certificate.
Wonderful.
Okay.
So, and my goal today is kind of we fill this matrix now with the different options that
we have.
And this way I can convey the fact that actually browsers can be first class citizens in network
applications.
All right.
So let's talk about public non-browser to public non-browser.
I'm in the network dev room.
This is the easiest one.
I'm not going to explain this much.
Reachability, both nodes are public.
We can just reach out them directly over IP and TCP or then UDP and the shiny new quick.
We don't have file walls and apps on either side.
And the platform, which is non-browser, so, for example, an application running on my
laptop has direct access to the TCP and UDP socket.
Cool.
So we have that.
Then private non-browser to public non-browser.
Again, really easy.
You do this every day by any application on your laptop going to a server.
We don't have any file walls and the server side.
The left side is private, but we don't really care as we have the direction from the left
to the right.
And then the platform, again, we're not running in a browser, so we're pretty unrestricted.
We probably have access to a TCP or UDP socket.
Wonderful.
To make this a little bit more complex, what if I'm a public non-browser connecting to
a private non-browser?
So what does that mean?
For example, on the left, that could be a server, and then on the right, that could
be some application running on my laptop right now.
What we can do here is something called connection reversal, simply where my laptop connects
to some public node.
Then whoever wants to reach out to me reaches out to that public node as well, relays the
message to me, my laptop, and then my laptop dials whoever wanted to dial me initially.
This is depicted here.
So B connects to the relay R, and then A relays a network over R to B, and then B connects
to A, which is commonly referred to as connection reversal.
In terms of platform, again, we're a non-browser, so access to TCP and UDP sockets, so we're
all good.
Cool.
And then the last one I want to fill before it becomes complicated, namely before we introduce
a browser, is private non-browser to private non-browser.
You see this depicted down there as A and B. Reachability really sucks.
Both are probably behind NATs or firewalls, so not much luck there.
So what we need to employ here is a technique called hole punching.
I don't have much time today in this talk, but we have another talk later on.
So if you want to learn all about hole punching or what success rate we have across different
protocols or IP stacks, join the talk.
I think it's at 11.45.
So we'll go a bunch into that.
Just short, brief one.
A and B want to connect.
Both are behind firewalls.
Both connect to a relay R. That R is public.
They coordinate a hole punch over that relay and then execute that hole punch through both
of their firewalls.
Cool.
In terms of platforms, again, we're not on the browser yet.
So we have access to a TCP and UDP socket.
All good.
Life is pretty easy.
Wonderful.
All right.
Now comes complexity, which is the browser world.
And what I want to talk about first is what if I'm a private browser?
Now private browser is somewhat of a weird term.
Usually you're not at FOSTEM and you don't have a public IPv4 or IPv6 address.
So browsers are usually always private, which I'm not suggesting to change.
Definitely not.
There are many security considerations to keep it that way.
But what if I want to connect from a private browser to a public non-browser?
So what if I, for example, want to connect from my laptop within my browser to some server?
Now this, again, sounds pretty easy to everyone, except one small disclaimer.
Again, we don't have a firewall or NAT at the receiver side.
A server is public, depending on the firewall rules obviously.
But we can easily reach out to them.
In terms of platform, we are on the browser, so we're quite restricted in the sense of
what we can do.
Eventually I want to end up with a byte stream between the two endpoints.
So what I'm restricted to is either WebSockets.
Everyone knows that.
So TCP, TLS, HTTP, then an upgrade, and then I have WebSocket.
The problem with that is I need a valid TLS certificate.
So I need the remote server to either have a signed IP certificate or based on a domain.
So that's a bummer.
What I can do as an alternative in the browser is use the shiny new WebTransport, which is
basically, I'm simplifying a lot here, but basically WebSockets on top of Flick or HTTP3.
WebTransport actually allows us to handle self-signed certificates.
And then as an alternative, we can use WebRTC to get a byte stream.
WebRTC gives us data channels, so in the end we can run on IP, UDP, then SCTP, and then
use data channels from WebRTC.
Now before you scream, this is insecure, the smallest gamer that I did at the beginning
is in case you built this to yourself, you still need to figure out proper authentication,
right?
Best would be mutual authentication because self-signed certificates, you're not part
of the authority trust chain.
But otherwise, yeah, these are your options.
So WebSocket, WebTransport, and WebRTC.
Cool.
So what if I want to connect from a public non-browser to a private browser?
We had this in the past, a couple slides back.
In terms of reachability, my left side is reachable, my right side is not reachable,
so what I can do, I don't need to do fancy hole punching, I can just do connection reversal
right over the relay where A asks B basically to dial it back over the relay.
In terms of platform, we don't have direct access to the TCP or UDP socket, given that
on the right side we have a browser in the whole stack, so that's a bummer.
We can do WebSockets in case we have a valid TLS certificate signed by some authority.
If not, we can do WebTransport and WebRTC.
Cool.
And now comes the very hard part, or not very hard part, but a little bit more difficult
part, which is private browser to private browser, or what is basically the same is
was it private non-browser to private browser, or private browser to private non-browser?
All the red boxes down there.
In terms of reachability, we need to leverage hole punching at this point.
Both endpoints are behind the firewall and are not.
So again, we'll go more into details on how hole punching works.
Probably a lot of you are already familiar with that.
In terms of platforms, at least one of our two sides are behind our browsers.
So that means we don't have access to TCP or UDP socket directly.
Why am I always saying no access to TCP and UDP?
That's relevant because you don't control the ports, and this way you don't have the
capability of hole punching yourself.
But what the browser gives us is WebRTC.
WebRTC has hole punching built in, so what we can do is leverage WebRTC and some signaling
server R in the middle to then do the actual hole punch.
Web sockets doesn't work because we can't hole punch with WebSockets, and WebTransport
doesn't work either because we can't hole punch with WebTransport either.
Okay.
Wonderful.
And that concludes the whole matrix, and what I'm pretty much showing here is you can connect
a browser to everyone out there that runs on IP, and that means your application can
actually make the browser a first-class citizen within your network.
Cool.
That's all from my end.
Yeah.
I'll be around the venue for quite a bit.
If you want to learn more about Lippy2P in general, which makes all this nicely packaged
for you, you can visit docs.lippy2p.io.
If you want to see all the nitty gritty details about the different transports and what that
means for, I don't know, for example, your signed TLS certificate or where you can hole
punch, that would be on connectivity.lippy2p.io.
There are various forums.
There's a specification online, and then, yeah, all the implementations are open source,
so you can just check that out on github.com slash lippy2p.
Cool.
That's all from my end.
Thank you very much.
Okay, I'm going to tell you about this place called Lippy2P.