Hello everyone, welcome to this session about psyllium surface mesh.
My name is Raymond Dion, I'm field CTO for Isofalent, the originators from psyllium.
Today I'm going to talk a bit about eBPF and psyllium as an introduction, after which I'm
going to talk about how the surface mesh is evolving, after which we'll talk about the
psyllium surface mesh features, what we can do today and what we're planning to support
in the future.
Quick highlight of some upcoming features and some current features and if we have time
I have a little demo to show how it works.
Can I see some hands from you if you know eBPF?
Quite a lot, good.
How many of you know psyllium?
Cool.
How many of you use psyllium actually?
Not as much.
Okay, cool.
For the ones who don't know what eBPF is, I'm going to do an introduction here, eBPF
is standing for Extended Berkeley Packet Filter.
By itself that doesn't mean a lot.
What we like to compare it with is what JavaScript is to the browser, eBPF is to the kernel.
What that means is that using eBPF we can attach programs to kernel events and for the
purpose of this session is that we can attach eBPF programs to kernel events related to
networking.
So that's either a socket being opened network packet being sent on a network device, that
means that's a kernel event and that means that we can attach a program to it and we
can get a matrix from that packet for example or we can do load balancing and such.
So psyllium is built on eBPF, you don't need to be an eBPF developer to actually work with
psyllium.
Psyllium abstracts this complexity and technology under the hood.
So based on the configuration you set, psyllium will mount the required eBPF programs for
you to run and psyllium in short provides networking and load balancing capabilities,
security capabilities and also a lot of observability capabilities using eBPF.
So this is the 30,000 feet view where we are today.
We started with plain networking, IPv6, IPv4 years ago and now we expanded all the networking
capabilities with BGP implementations, net4.6, 6.4, extended load balancing out of the box
we're working on having go BGP control plane fully supported with psyllium.
On top of that we have an observability layer with our Hubble technology which is an observability
tool which provides service to service communication for your name spaces so you can see what's
components, what services are talking to which services.
After which you can make informed decisions for example what kind of network policies
you want to apply.
Also exporting metrics to tools like Raphana and surface mesh on top of that to provide
authentication layer seven path based routing and such.
On the right hand side we also have Tetragon that's not something we'll talk about today
but that's runtime security using eBPF which is also very interesting and we'd run across
clouds doesn't matter if it's on-prem or hybrid or multi-cluster so it's agnostic of the
platform and supported by multiple cloud vendors.
So as you may know Google Enforce data plane V2 on the node is actually psyllium.
Microsoft has recently adopted psyllium as the default CNI for AKS clusters and all their
clusters will be migrated to psyllium and AWS EKS anywhere by default is psyllium so
we see huge adoption in the field of psyllium.
So let's talk about surface mesh.
So obviously if we talk about surface mesh we talk about observing traffic being able
to secure traffic from application to application across clusters doing traffic management building
resilience across applications across clouds.
Surface mesh originally if you needed that capabilities originally you would program
your application either in python or go to get that observability.
That wasn't really useful because you have to maintain all those libraries to get the
information you need.
That's where the sidecars came in right so that they abstract that complexity from the
application to have a standard sidecar implementation to monitor traffic to be able to route traffic
and to be able to extract metrics from the traffic.
However now with psyllium our goal is to move as close to the kernel as we already
run in kernel with eBPF.
So we're moving from a sidecar model to the kernel and where we can we will support it
using eBPF.
The only part which is not yet there is layer 7.
So all the low balancing capabilities routing capabilities in terms of IP to IP metrics
are already available with psyllium using eBPF.
Layer 7 routing is not yet in eBPF for multiple reasons of which one is that eBPF has constraints
in terms of how big a program can be.
Obviously it runs in kernel space so it has constraints for a good reason but in the future
maybe we can even transport complex layer 7 routing in eBPF.
However we already provide layer 7 visibility and ops of ability in using psyllium and eBPF.
We already have the capabilities to inspect traffic using eBPF.
We can already do the low balancing with equip-prosper replacement.
The only part is the layer 7 but the visibility of traffic so HTTP traffic and such is already
there.
So surface mesh capabilities are extending those capabilities moving forward.
So how does it work?
Some of you may know that psyllium runs as an agent as a daemon set on the nodes.
It programs the nodes to be mounting the eBPF programs for the capabilities you need.
We have an embedded envoy running inside the psyllium agent.
This is a narrow down envoy proxy in the agent for networking capabilities.
We leverage this envoy proxy on the node level to do surface mesh capabilities.
So all the things like HTTP path routing and such.
So for each namespace you would create and where you create for example an ingress resource
or a gateway resource that means that a listener will be created through the envoy for that
specific namespace, for that specific work.
And we leverage C groups and stuff to have separation as well for the security reasons
to not be able to have traffic across namespaces as such.
So what is different with psyllium service mesh compared to other service mesh implementations?
First of all our goal is to reduce operational complexity by removing sidecars.
Resource usage reduced better performance and avoids sidecar startup shut down race
conditions.
So obviously if you're not running sidecars at scale this makes a huge difference.
You don't have all the sidecar pods running alongside your normal pods.
It will save memory, it will save CPU, it will save connection tracking etc.
So a lot more efficient.
And also in terms of latency running a sidecar has a cost.
So in this diagram you see that an application wants to send traffic to another application.
What that means technically is that it goes through the TCP IP stack three times with
the sidecar.
First from the app then inbound in the sidecar where the sidecar does its processing and
then external from the sidecar to the physical network device to hit the network to reach
another node.
With eBPF we are able to shortcut that connection and improve the latency because we can detect
the traffic and we can see if it's destined for the physical network or it should be routed
through the proxy.
So once this app opens the socket using eBPF we can shortcut that connection to the physical
network device to be routed on the physical network.
If we need layer seven processing that means that using eBPF we can shortcut the connection
on the socket layer directly to the Envoy proxy where the Envoy proxy on the node does
its HTTP routing and then forwards the traffic again on the physical network.
So a lot less hops there.
And it means that latency is much, much improved because we're not going through this TCP IP
stack multiple times.
In terms of throughput there's also a small difference because we can push more packets.
And in terms of pod ready performance this is also a consideration at scale because when
you're scaling out your applications you always with traditional sidecars you need to wait
for the sidecar to be spun up as well and to be ready to serve connections for that
application.
So without the sidecars with Psyllium Surface Mesh it's already there.
It's running on the node, it's embedded in the proxy so once you scale out your application
the proxy immediately on that node can serve connections.
So in short Psyllium Surface Mesh provides traffic management, observability, security
and resilience.
The goal is to bring your own control plane.
We are not developing a control plane on our own.
What it means is that you can already use Ingress resources with Psyllium 1.13, we'll
support Gateway API.
We are working on Spiffy integration so with the 1.13 release actually the groundwork for
MTLS and Spiffy integration is already there.
You're not really able to use it yet but the goal is to support both MTLS and Spiffy using
Psyllium network policies so you can reference for example a Spiffy ID as a source and destination
using Psyllium network policies and then under the hood the Psyllium agent part will connect
to a Spivey server where that identity is tracked and confirm if that's allowed.
In terms of observability you can leverage the already available observability with Grafana
or Hubble.
If you need to export events you can use scene platforms such as Splunk and OpenTelemetry
is also supported.
If you're new, if you're running new classes you have an option, you can run Psyllium and
you can already use Psyllium Surface Mesh out of the box.
This is obviously the preferred method but if you're running already an Istio based implementation
there's still a lot of benefit to run Psyllium under the hood there as well because for example
we already encrypt the connectivity between the sidecar from an Istio based implementation
towards the destination pod.
What I mean by that is that when you run sidecars, when you run MTLS between applications, that
connectivity may be secure but the connection between the sidecar and the actual destination
is unencrypted on the node.
Anyone with specific privileges on a node could potentially listen on that virtual interface
and eavesdrop traffic and that's obviously not secure.
Running Psyllium under the hood already gives you the benefit because we can encrypt on
layer 4 directly on a socket layer to the destination pod obviously.
With 1.12, so currently we have 1.12 available since I think seven months, we already have
a production ready Psyllium Surface Mesh, a conformant ingress controller which you
can use for HDPath routing, canary releases and such.
You can use Kubernetes as your Surface Mesh control plane.
Prometheus Metrix OpenTelemetry is supported.
For power users we have Psyllium Envoy config and Psyllium Cluster-wide Envoy config CRDs
available.
These are temporarily I would say because the goal is to replace all that capabilities
with Gateway API.
And we're releasing more and more extended Grafana dashboards for layer 7 visibility
so you can actually see between surface to surface what kind of metrics there are and
what the latencies are and what return codes are, so golden signals.
The roadmap for 1.13 and we're very close for releasing 1.13 expected somewhere this
month hopefully.
You can already try a release candidate for Psyllium 1.13 which includes a Gateway API
support for HTTP routing, TLS termination, HTTP traffic splitting and waiting.
So this allows you to do percentage based routing or canary releases as such without
configuring Psyllium Envoy config resources.
And also the capability to have multiple ingresses per load balancer.
What that means is that currently when you create a Psyllium ingress we rely on the load
balancer to attract traffic and forward that to the proxy.
Obviously at scale having a load balancer for each ingress especially in clouds is
expensive so this with an annotation we allow multiple ingresses per load balancer so you
can save cost there.
So how am I doing in time?
So today ingress 1.12 also with services we are having support for annotations so imagine
you have received traffic from your ingress you forward it to a service that means we
support annotations on a simple cluster IP to forward traffic for example to a specific
endpoint.
If you know what Psyllium cluster mesh is we can connect Psyllium across clusters.
With simple annotations you can have even high availability of services across clusters.
Gateway API which I will show a bit later and the Envoy config.
So this is a simple example of ingress and this is also something I will show in the
demo.
You have an ingress and from a specific path you want to forward traffic to a specific
service.
We also support GRPC so you can also have specific GRPC URLs to be forwarded to specific
services.
TLS termination to terminate TLS using secrets using ingress.
A question I get a lot is what about SSL pass through that's on the road map so keep that
in mind.
And obviously new in 1.13 is Gateway API and how it looks like is you will configure a
gateway resource you specify the gateway class name for Psyllium to make sure that the gateway
is created and maintained through Psyllium and then create listeners so in this case
an HTTP listener on port 80.
Then additionally you create multiple HTTP routes one or more and this specify for example
a path prefix for values forward slash details to be forwarded to a backend reference service
called details.
In terms of TLS termination same constructs.
You can also have for example a host name in there to only accept traffic for this given
host name and you reference a secret in the gateway resource and then in the HTTP routes
you will specify the host name, you will reference the gateway you want to use and then again
a path prefix for example to forward to a specific service.
And then traffic splitting very simple also using HTTP routes again referencing your gateway
a path prefix and then you have in this case an echo 1 and echo 2 service where you want
to introduce slowly echo 2 in this case 25% of that traffic will be forwarded to the echo
2 service.
And this is the example what I talked about earlier using simple annotations you can extend
service miss capabilities by annotating services so in this case this service will receive
traffic for gRPC and we can attach load balancing modes for in this case weighted loss request
to be forwarded to backend endpoints.
And using multi cluster capabilities you can extend these capabilities across two or more
clusters depending on your cluster mesh configuration.
And can we roll out so you can even introduce new clusters have the new version of the application
running on the new cluster so we're absolutely sure that you have no resource contention
on your original cluster and then on the service annotate traffic to forward slowly to a remote
cluster before you do the flip over.
So this concludes the presentation part so for example when you want to know more about
cilium go to the cilium community I encourage you to join our slack channel if you have
any questions our team is there as well to answer questions for in slack any issues you
may have or any roadmap or feature requests you may have we're very interested to hear
from you.
You can also contribute so obviously if you want to develop on cilium join the cilium
GitHub and contribute if you want to know more about eBPF go to eBPF.io and if you want
to know more about Isovalent the company who originated cilium and want to for example
work there have a look there we are looking for engineers as well so feel free to have
a look and if you want to know more ask me after the session as well.
All right let me do see how I'm doing with time so in order to run ingress and gator
API you need to set a certain amount of flex on your for example your mvalue style so this
is an example I've run a small demo on GKE so this is a GKE cluster with cilium installed
what you need to do is you need to enable the ingress controller and in this case I'm
also enabling metrics just because it's interesting to see what's going on for gateway API there's
also a value so gateway API enabled through this will trigger gateway API to be enabled
for surface mesh it's important to configure the cube proxy replacement to strict or probe
strict is recommended because you have the full cube proxy replacement capabilities in
your cluster this is also required for surface mesh and that's that's basically it to get
started so for the simple demo this I've created a simple gateway the gateway class name name
cilium so this is running cilium 1.13 release candidate 5 which has the gateway API support
and then a simple HTTP route for the book info example application which has matches
for the details and the default path prefixes so when I go into my environment I want to
show quickly the following so if I do a kubectl get surface you can see I already for sake
for the sake of time created this gateways what I wanted to show you is that obviously
a low balance is required so GKE proficient me a low balancer and low bands IP I can use
to attract traffic in this case I'm demoing a default HTTP gateway and a default HTTPS
gateway so I have two low balancers with each an external IP addresses assigned so this
configuration is applied so if I do a kubectl get a gateway good point you also obviously
your cluster you also need to install the CRDs for gateway API support here you can
see I have my gateway and a TLS gateway and if I do a kubectl kubectl get HTTP routes
I can see I have my book info HTTP route installed and this relates to this part obviously so
with that I can should be able to connect to the details so this is running the bookstore
example so I'm using that public IP as you can see it works and if I go to details I
should be forwarded using the gateway API HTTP routes to that specific detail surface
and that works as well for HTTPS again a simple example I've created that gateway TLS gateway
I've created two listeners so a listener for book info dot psyllium dot rocks and a listener
for hipster shop dot psyllium dot rocks I don't have installed I didn't have installed
the hipster shop but for demo purposes I'm also referencing two secrets so I've using
I've used make cert to create a simple self-signed certificate installed it in my certificate
store and created a secret which I reference using this listener then again HTTP routes
for the TLS gateway for book info dot psyllium dot rocks matches to only the details path
prefix on port 9080 and again a part for the hipster shop so that's what I'm going to show
here so if I do the default URL that doesn't work there's no list there's no HTTP route
configured but for details I can see I can connect it securely and this certificate is
being run from the gateway resource as well obviously this is a self-signed certificate
but obviously you can create signed certificates as well with that that concludes my presentation
and the demo I'm open for questions any questions hi thank you very much for your presentation
okay when you talk about a no layer 7 support in BPF yeah you said maybe in the future and
what you spec is it going to come or not I'm not sure about that HTTP routing requires
quite a lot of memory right so obviously memory is limited to the BPF programs for good little
reasons so it will depend on the EPF foundation and the roadmap there what we can support
technically there's no reason why we shouldn't be able to do that but yeah in terms of memory
we have constraints so if those are being raised we potentially can have parts of even
all parts using eBPF any other yeah hi does it provide or can you provide end-to-end encryption
between especially between the node automatically or not yes so our vision there is that you
should configure for example IPSec or wire guard for node to node encryption in transit
and if you want authentication and authorization on top of that to configure SPF or NTLS between
your applications so it's a multi-layered approach so we're not doing the encryption
on the NTLS part but on the node level as that makes if that makes sense so NTLS again
a SPF is on roadmap hopefully for 1.13 any other no okay thank you thank you