Okay, good morning. This time it's our turn to talk about something different, end-to-end
G. What is end-to-end G? It's an open source application, of course, we are here. And you
can download the code on GitHub, you'll see the link at the end of the talk. What is end-to-end
G doing? It is, first of all, a real-time network traffic monitoring application. So
it means that it displays you on a web interface what is happening in your network live. Okay,
no delay. This unless, of course, we are receiving flows coming from a router that are somehow
a little bit delayed because by nature they are on average, so they have a certain lifetime.
And it is designed for network monitoring and cybersecurity. It means that there are
some behavioral checks. So we are not bound to rules. You have seen Surikata presentation
before. You see there are some rules in case this happens then. So this is not our case.
So we work based on behavior. So it means that if you have a host that is misbehaving,
more or less similar to what you have seen before, that suddenly start to send too much
traffic with respect to the past or starting to, you know, fire up a new application. So
accept connection on a certain port for TLS that was not open before. This is a typical
example. So therefore it means that the application simply starts up and learns what is happening
on the network. There are some levels of learning. So sometime it is an immediate learning because,
you know, you specify some sort of configuration. But usually this is not the case. The case
is that the application learns what is happening in case something goes wrong, goes different,
fires up an alert. This is the idea. And the architecture is actually divided in two parts.
First of all, the pocket processing part. That is based on more or less PF ring or lead
pickup. So this means that you can run Windows, Linux, MacOS, FreeBSD, whatever. Instead,
PF ring is something that we have co-developed that is a Linux technology for accelerating
packet capture. But not only for that, but also for merging traffic for multiple adopters,
for distributing traffic. So it's much more than simply RX acceleration. On top of this,
there is an open source library that we still maintain at the end of call NDPI. So this
is the only open source library that is doing the pocketing spectrum. But for us, it means
that we try to understand from the traffic what is the application protocol. So if it's
TLS, if it's a generic protocol, if it's Google MA, but it's a very specific protocol. And
out of the traffic, we extract the metadata. So for instance, we extract certificate information
and we generate something we call risk. So we're looking at the traffic, we see if there
is something wrong, okay, such as an expired certificate just to give you an idea. And
we trigger an alert. On top of this, there is a top NG because this is the first part
that is basically provided by the operating system. And top NG has a C++ engine that is
processing packets that is, in essence, doing traffic analysis creates internally, okay,
the representation of the data based on the concept of network interfaces because we can
have a multiple network interfaces from which the traffic is received. It can be a virtual
interface such as, you know, NetFlow collection or a physical interface, ETH0. And then we
have something we call behavioral checks, where we check flows and host. Flows means
that each independent communication such as a TCP connection is checked. Instead, a host,
we take the host as a whole. So in essence, if host is doing a port scan, each individual
communication is okay or more or less okay. But the fact that this host is doing this,
you know, in a sequence, in a network, on a host, it's a problem. So this is called
behavioral checks. And on top of this, we trigger alerts, okay, that can be consumed
locally or sent elsewhere. This is the first part. On top of this, we have the Lua interface,
why Lua? Because we like C++, but C++ is something not for everybody, okay? So we need
to simplify, for instance, the development of the web interface. So for instance, the
REST API is written in Lua sitting on top of C++. So we have created an API that allows
us to avoid typical problems of C++. At the same time, we simplify the way the application
is working. So therefore, we use Lua for operations that are not critical, such as the Web GUI
or for checking interfaces that are not necessarily real time. So for the SNMP, for SNMP, we fetch
the data every five minutes and do the checks. So traffic injection, as I said, is done in
multiple ways. Sometime in serial traffic, so packets. Sometime it is not. It's a flaw.
And it is handled by the C++ engine. So the C++ engine is doing it efficiently. And then
we have other type of ingestions based on events. So something that we don't really
control completely, but that are relevant for us. So we have seen Surikata, the presentation
before, some minutes ago. This is a typical example of input. Why this? Because as I said
at the beginning, we don't have rules. We don't want to have rules. So we don't want
to say if the payload contains this and this and this and this then. Because we don't believe
that this is what we should do. Instead, there are wonderful tools such as Surikata that
are doing that very well. So therefore, the idea is to combine natural monitoring and
behavior analysis with this type of tools. So therefore, indirectly, through tools as
Surikata is optional. Of course, you don't have to run it with Ntoppenji monitoring.
You can have this type of information that can be combined directly by Ntoppenji. Of
course, we have five more logs and syslog. Why this is important? Because we can have
a look at information that is not visible from the traffic. So we always play with packets
like mine and Osprego. But we understand that packets have limitations, especially for encryption.
So we have seen before, a rule saying if you are downloading a binary application. That
is fine if it's plain text. But if TLS, you will never see that happen. So you have to
use things as a rule on top of this, on top of this, but they are just guesses. So instead,
if through syslog or other means, we know that. So for example, we see an attacker or
a WordPress saying that this host is trying to guess the password of the administrator
user. This is much relevant information. And from the network standpoint, it looks simply
nice. Everything is OK. The problem is from the application. That's why we believe in
network. But at the same time, we need to have some other information that is injected
into the application. And of course, we have historical data. We use a database called
Clickhouse. So we can put a billion of records. Everything is working very fast. This is also
an open source database. And for time series, we use round-robin database or InfluxDB. And
as I said before, we have checks that are divided in two parts. C++ for efficiency.
So the fast part, in essence, where you have to process traffic in line, such as when you
have a packet, an incoming packet, you have to check if this packet belonging to a flow
is relevant. And then we have other type of checks that are not so real time. So for a
check on an SNMP interface that need to be easy to be developed. But at the same time,
that don't need to be fast. Because as I said, if we pull SNMP in five minutes, we have plenty
of time for doing that. And of course, we have notification that we send out. So for
things, we trigger a shell script, a webhook, syslog, email, telegram, you know, usually
things. Nothing new here. Okay, let's now start the talk after this introduction of
Ntof-NG. The problem is the following. So we have added over 150 checks, behavioral
checks on the traffic. But there is always somebody that comes and says, I want to do
something different. How can we support these people? How can we enable new programmers
or let's say people that used to use Python, shell script, you know, this type of running
language or that don't want to learn the antennas of our application? How can we do that? And
many times this happens when you are in a rush. So there is an attack. There is something
happening on your network that you want to check. And we have, you know, two levels of
the problem. First of all, we have to extend the behavioral checks in order to have some
behavioral detection in a different way. And in the second part that Alfredo will describe
later. So how can we use Ntof-NG as a data lake from languages such as Python, for instance,
that is very popular? So that you can use Ntof-NG as a source of data for your application.
Of course, you have time series. As I said, we save data in InfluxDB if you want. So therefore
you can use Grafana for creating your own dashboard. But these are simple dashboards.
So if we want to do something more complicated, if we want to go beyond that, in addition
to that, how can we do that? So this is the idea today. So we like C++. C++ is super efficient.
We like it. Okay. We are used to play with it since many years. But we understand that
it's not what everybody wants. Okay. We need something easier. And we would like to understand
also how it was possible to develop checks in minutes for people who are saying, okay,
if I see this specific certificate or if I see this specific behavior, then there is
a problem. Something very peculiar to an organization. So not general for everybody, but for specific
people. So for instance, how do I trigger an alert if there is traffic, TLS traffic
within host A and B? So for instance, a printer should not make any TLS traffic just to make
an example. So if this happens and how can I trigger an alert? Another problem is the
following. If I have a certificate signed by a certain organization, or for instance,
if I have a bit tolerant connection is going above one gigabit or notify me if there is
a zoom call with bad quality, things like this, things like, you know, very, very peculiar,
very specific checks that people wants to do. Maybe on an operating, sorry, on autonomous
system and not on another or an network and not to another. So things that are not general
that we can implement for everybody. How can we do that? So let me talk how it works in
top NGA internally. Let's have a look at the flow. Also our communication. So on top NGA
creates a data structure inside itself as soon as we see the first packet of the flow.
So we see IP source, IP destination, source parts of destination, protocol, VLAN, whatever.
And then this is the first event that is relevant for us. And then as I said, everything sits
on top of NDPI, so the yellow part. So we have another event when the application protocol
is detected. Actually, this one is divided in two parts. First of all, as soon as the
main protocol is detected, such as TLS, okay, and then we can refine this information with
metadata saying, okay, this is TLS that is going to Google mail and not Google search
or Google something else, okay. So second event and NDPI. And then we have for long-standing
flows some periodic activities. So in essence every minute we do something different, something
like I want to trigger an action. And then at the end, the flow and notification. So
as soon as the flow is over. So what we wanted to do, we wanted to create a low API that
allows people to create the simple checks that are efficient, efficient enough for most
people because not everybody needs one on the gigabit, but many people have one gigabit
networks or, you know, two, five gigabit networks. So they have, they need some sort of efficiency,
but they are not super extreme. So let's say use Lua for prototyping a check for some
people who need speed or use Lua for people who have, let's say, an industrial network
or a network that is, you know, running at one gigabit or two. So in essence we have created
an API that allows from Lua to see internally in NtopNG properties of the flow. For example,
the number of bytes, multicast, layers seven information, this type of things. And the
API calls are very small. So in essence we don't want, you know, the application to be
inefficient simply because we download to Lua the representation of the host, the representation
of the flow. Simply the method that we are interested in. So in the left side you will
see the C++ code, how it implements the stuff. On the right side you will see an example
of the Lua code. So in this case, just to give you an idea of how it works, so whenever
there is one of the events, so for instance we have to check the flow because, you know,
NDPI is over, so the protocol has been detected. So if you want to block, let's say, a Google
Mail, okay, so what you need to do is to execute a Lua check after this happened. So in essence
inside the C++ code we have put the code to the Lua VM that executes a script. A script
can be applied to many flows, not just for one. So this is where this happens. And this
is an example of a check. So with a simple example, if you have a flow that is either
TLS or QUIC, started from host 192.68.1.178.2.1.1, and if it's TLS and if the protocol issue
is, so a very simple check that a friend of mine has asked because it's monitoring IoT
networks and they found a vulnerability on a specific type of rule and the client was
a specific device. So something that is not JIRA. Okay, so this is the way it works. Very
simple to write. The problem is the following. That the overhead introduced, this is a very
slow Intel I3, so just to give you an idea of the super-waste case, is 30 microseconds
for everything, okay, in average. Whereas with C++ we can do it in one microsecond.
Now you say this is bad. In a way it is bad, I agree, because we are 30 times lower. But
you have to think, first of all, on one gigabit networks that this is not the problem. Also
you have to think that most of these checks are asynchronous. This is one of the few ones
that are synchronous. So in essence, as soon as the protocol has been detected, we call
this method. But it is not why the packets are coming. So in essence, we have another
threat that is calling this while the traffic is coming. But we don't stop the execution
tree. So in essence, just to make it short, so if you take this overhead that you have
introduced and you sum to everything and you stay below certain boundaries, so if you want
for every minute to execute the flow checks on all the flows, you are good, okay. And
of course we trigger another. And the result of the alert is a notification on the GUI
that can be sent, for instance, through Microsoft Teams, just to give you an idea. Or we can
trigger a shell script for something or can send an alert to my friend on Telegram. So
this is the way it works. Okay, now I have this. Okay, so we have seen how to extend
the Entopng engine with lower scripts to access traffic information and use those information
to check the traffic and trigger alerts, for instance. Now recently released also a Python
package that you can install with pip install Entopng that allows you to, you can use it
as a library to create a Python script which is able to access traffic information in Entopng.
And this happens through the REST API. This means that you can run your script even on
a remote location. For example, you can access live data in Entopng. In this case, we're
importing the Entopng class. We are connecting to Entopng using the Entopng class. We get
an instance of an interface, Entopng, for instance, ETH0. We use this method to get
all the hosts which are active in my network with all the metadata. And there are plenty
of methods in this class or in another class in this library that allows you to get traffic
information. So you can get alerts, flows, hosts, whatever. And you can also get historical
data. So same way, you connect to Entopng, you get an interface. From this interface,
you get an instance of the historical class. And you can run queries in the database. For
instance, you can get alert statistics from this time to this time, for instance, for
the last 24 hours and just print all the alerts that you have.
Now those are two examples of querying the engine to get the data. Of course, we have
seen that Entopng is able to run a check or an external event that takes something, an
event. We can trigger an alert. And we have seen that Entopng supports several endpoints.
So we can send this alert using mail, a messaging system like telegrams, like we can run a share
script, we can call a webbook. So we can run a share script, for instance. And this script
can be a Python script.
So let's try to put all the pieces together. So we receive an event, which is generated
by an internal check or an external check. This event can call a Python script. This
Python script can get information from the alert itself or can query the engine through
these API that we created to get more data, to fetch more data and argument the alert information.
And this can have some logic and trigger some action. So you can write your actions here
to react to this event.
In order to implement these, what you have to do in Entopng is, first of all, you have
to enable the check that you want to use to analyze the traffic. For instance, in this
case, we are using a custom check that the user creates in Lua's look up here before.
Then if you want to write your Python script that reacts to this event, you have to write
an alert tender, which is a script that you place on the Entopng script shell. And this
case is a simple script, which is just getting in a standard input the traffic information,
metadata. And for instance, if the other type is our user script, I want to do something.
In this case, I'm just logging the IP address related to the host that triggered the alert
and a message from our custom script.
Then you have to go inside Entopng. You go under notifications. You set that you want
to send alerts to the shell script. Here you have all the options like email, whatever.
You select your handler. And then you specify for your handler that you want to receive
just critical alerts. So you specify the severity. You specify the category that you want to
have alerts that you want to handle, in this case, cybersecurity and the entity. In this
case, I want to handle alerts about hosts.
And then we can extend our handler. We have seen how to print just the alert information,
but we can, again, we can use our Python library, Entopng, to access more information about
the host. So we receive this alert, which has been triggered on a specific host in our
network. For instance, this host has been infected by a malware. It's generating unexpected
traffic, whatever. We want to get more information about this host to build the report, for instance.
In fact, in our library, we also have the ability to generate a report, or you can generate
your own report using the API that we have. So we build this report and send an email.
So this is a simple script that you can use. It's a few lines of code to handle alerts
and generate reports and get, for instance, an email or your mobile phone with the alert.
So this is the big picture of the example that we are seeing right now. So we have defined
user script that triggers an alert, or we receive, again, events from any other source
or internal checks. We are calling our script, which is getting more information from the
engine to build the report and send this report by mail. So the result is this. So the system
is checking your traffic, is building a report when something happens, and will send you
an email with a report of the traffic for the host with the top alerts sorted by severity
or by count, the top contacts for the host, the chart of the traffic generated by the
host where you can add more, like the top applications used by the host, et cetera.
Do you want to wrap up? OK. So we have seen that within TopNG you can collect traffic
information from traffic, flows, events, events from S
udigada, for instance, et cetera. And when we started with, actually, Luca started with
on top, then we moved to TopNG. It was mainly a traffic monitoring tool. Today is also a
cyber security tool able to do behavioral checks, not just for providing visibility,
but also providing cyber security monitoring. And you're now able to extend this engine
both with your scripts integrated in TopNG or even with C++ plugins, let's say checks,
if you need to scale with performance, or you can use our Python library to write Python
tools that can run externally, even remote boxes to access traffic information in the
TopNG engine and be, for instance, a PDF, as we have seen, with reporting what's going
on in your network. Of course, all the code is available on GitHub. So if you want to
contribute, you are welcome, especially now you don't have excuses. We have a lot of libraries,
scripting languages for interacting with the engine. So something else to add?
No. The only thing I want to say is that this is an efficient way from our point of view
to do network monitoring and cyber security, and at the same time to extract information
in a way that does not interfere with the main engine that allows, I believe, most of
people sitting in this room to do whatever they like to create a monitoring tool that
is tailored for their own needs. And that's a fair set that is open source. That's all.
Thank you very much. Any questions?
It's just a simple question. How does it compare with CN2s? It looks like it does everything
CN2s.
Yeah. I don't know the tools.
No problem.
I am not familiar with them.
Any other question?
The scripts can be compiled to be more performant, or do you not have this task in your develop
timeline, to compile scripts to have more performance? Lua script or like CCC, we saw
that CCC script take one millisecond, but the Lua script take 30 milliseconds. Microsens.
Okay.
Yes, of course. You can compile them, but you have to call it in C++ at the moment.
So we use Lua just in time to compile the one seen before by some switch, but it is
not available everywhere for its own arm, and we want to support it as berries. So yes,
it is possible, but again, these are microseconds, not milliseconds. So one million of them per
second.
Any questions? Anybody else?
Hi. Thank you. Do you have some figures about performance you are able to achieve on typical
server about flow per second? Some figure to share on the Lua scripting, and also some
example on Python, which should be less efficient?
Okay. When you process packets with Entopng itself, you are able to process like a few
gigabit per second, depending on the driver's use, how you tune Entopng, let's say, to scale
with the performance, you can get 10 gigabit for instance, but more or less, we range from
a few gigabit to 10 gigabit in Entopng itself. You can use it in combination with our probes,
which is Mprobe, or we have other probes like Cento. In that case, you can scale with a
performance up to 100 gigabit per second, but the architecture changes a bit.
Yeah. It's one 100 gigabit in plus.
Yeah. As of the checks, it depends on the checks that you enable, of course.
Okay. I think we are running out of time. Many thanks for being here now.