Okay.
Thank you for being here.
So good morning.
My name is Daniel Mediado.
I'm here today with my colleague Miguel.
We are both principals of our engineers at Weihat.
I'm currently working in the
episode of the DTT team, basically monitoring.
And he's on the OpenShift virtualization team.
We just wanted to speak today a little bit about CNI, which stands for
container network interface, which this is basically all the networking in
Kubernetes, but not only limited to that.
Because I think one of the things that this product lacks the most is
documentation and how does this work, how you create a plugin, what are the
primitives.
I think that's something that is super simple, but there's little to
no documentation besides the spec.
So let's go walk through that.
Yeah, this is a quick intro.
So you may have been noticing that we are going to be speaking about
CNI plugins change specifically.
That means that we are going to be basically putting a couple of plugins
in serial mode.
But first of all, CNI stands for three different things and I want to be
a little bit clearer here.
You can have the CNI specification itself, which is a document.
It's fine.
You can read it.
Then you've got the plugins.
So if you go to GitHub, you can see the CNI plugins.
This is a set of plugins basically maintained by the community.
Bridge, Mac, VLAM, you name it.
There's a couple of those.
The third thing, it may be just a couple of plugins.
So those are basically the three things that you may be interested
into.
We are going to be always speaking about the plugins here in this
session, but we'll be happily discussing anything after that.
So just in case, I mean, here we are going to be speaking about Kubernetes,
but let me take a note that the CNI specification on the plugins, they
do work totally without Kubernetes.
So with any runtime and time, SaaS rocket, and in fact, it started
out with rocket.
I guess Casey started that out.
You can be running this out with cryo rocket, whatever you want to play
with this.
So what is the CNI plugin specifically?
CNI plugins are binaries, which are basically copied over any of the
hosts that are in your Kubernetes clusters.
So if you want to install this out, you probably need a demo set to deploy
it on or do that manually.
So here, who runs this CNI plugins?
You could either run that yourself, but usually you would need to have
the kubelet run those for you.
Is there anybody here who doesn't know what a kubelet is?
Okay.
The kubelet, you fucker, anyway.
They were trying me out.
So anyways, I'll go ahead.
So basically when you go and have the kubelet, which is a mystery thing
that you don't know what it's about, runs the binary here in the host.
It basically creates a network namespace, which is tied to a bf interface.
As this guy doesn't know what a bf interface is, I'm going to be basically
speaking out of that for him.
So it's a bit trial point to point, you know, tunnel.
You can basically hook this up into whatever you want to.
Like usually these are connected to OVN, open bit sheets or whatever
virtual streets or it depends on this CNI implementation.
How do I configure the thing?
These are usually configured by a configuration file.
We're going to be speaking later on a little bit about how this changes.
But yes, FYI, Miguel will be speaking later on about this more.
Prior to the CNI specification 0.3.0, you weren't able to, you know, put your
plugins in CNI mode.
It would just break.
So you would need to know basically there's a couple of CNI components
that you need to put.
Basically the name of your CNI plugin, the type, and the type should match
the name of your binary or it would probably break afterwards.
Then later on you need also some mbars which basically are specifically
about telling you like okay, I can switch, but do I run this?
Because it may be a bug or the bugs or whatever.
If you put all this out, again recall a CNI plugin, it's a binary so you just
run it as any binary you would run.
It goes to your CNI plugin and then you can exit code.
If you did your things right like that, this should be getting you an exit
code 0, not error.
And then you would be getting your standard out here which is just JSON.
Why JSON and why not using the RPC and the daemon like everything in Kubernetes
you may ask?
Because again, this wasn't meant to be used on Kubernetes.
If you get to stay at the more CNI working station, they'll probably be
speaking about some point using the daemon for that too.
But here for the sake of this session, what you would need to remember here
is this preps results basically and advancing some stuff later from my
colleague.
This is the previous results as per JSON at the plugin and if any plugin
gets a previous result here, it should output the next one just in a serial
mode way.
I was speaking about the specification.
What the hell is that?
So if you're implementing your plugin, you need to make sure that it
observes several primitives which is add, dell, check and version.
So for instance, you may want to add a pod.
I want to delete a pod network interface.
And second version to be honest and even if the specification really
requests you to honor this and observe this, they aren't really used by
most of the commercial plugins.
For instance, Celium, I guess they don't do any kind of tech, maybe version,
but those aren't really needed and we'll be discussing that later on.
So this is what a config file usually looks like.
So this is nothing like a big deal.
Super simple CNI version again.
For example, I'm getting you backwards like with the things that we were
speaking before.
This one would work with CNI plugin sense because it's 0 to 1.
If you put 0 to 0, it would basically fail miserably telling you that
he hates you and it would crash.
Then you got here the name, I don't care, but this type should match the name of
your binary there later on.
Then you can put out some plugin specific things that are, for instance, this
basically comes from the bridge plugin which Michael will be showcasing later on.
So you can put here, okay, this, what do I need for a bridge?
I need the name.
You see the default gateway.
I'm going to be forcing the address later on.
This is a little bit special, but I won't be discussing that because you'll be
seeing that later on in the conflict.
Again, like, okay, so you told me about CNI plugins or binaries and also like
our JSON configurations.
So where do I store these things out?
So basically when you define the cube of the configuration, you tell the CNI
binary path.
And by CNI binary path, it's just a directory where I store all the plugins.
Sadly, there's little to no login in most of the plugins, so if something
breaks you would have to go and see what's going on here.
So you would just go, one of the things that usually fail the most is just like
you don't have the binary here installed and it would fail until you use the
H2N.
And the config directory is here and you just have a couple of JSON who maps to
the name of the binaries usually and where you put the specific plugin configs.
Plugging chains, let's go for that.
So that's the big deal.
Again, available since CNI or CO2 zero.
Those are required since the version one because now everything is the same, even
if it's just a single plugin and everything is accomplished.
Again, even if it's just a single plugin.
So if you just want to put the things from the old way, it would just break.
I was also pointing out that now let's assume that you've got a couple of plugins
here like Abinell.
You've got the Bricks plugin, then you've got Abinell Firewall plugin, which is
one of the most useful use cases for this.
And then Abinell, let's say put a couple of plugins, bandwidth, Abinell, Abinell,
Abinell Firewall because I like to and I am going to be putting Abinell in another
Macmill interface here.
So all these plugins are expected to honor that they are going to be passing the
properties to each other.
So even if they don't know anything about what comes before, because the
Bricks plugin will know how to make a Bricks, but the Macmillan plugin won't.
So everything comes through the plugins, all the info goes through using prep results
and we'll be showing you later on with the demo if it doesn't fail.
This is the config, this is not a config for CNI plugin, this is a conf list.
So if you see this pretty much resembles what you had in the config file for a plugin
like before, so now we got CNI version, okay, I know I'm guessing this a lot, but it
should be greater than three of these here, otherwise this would just break.
This is your conf list and then you get basically a list of plugins.
Instead of one, we got a few of those and those would be just working together.
So in this case, we got a name because all the plugins would need a name and would need
a tie which would match the binary and then we got the specific configurations.
So in the demo, we'll be showing you how these plugins get to link with the prep results
and so forth.
But if you see, it's just a list of plugins with name, type and then specific configurations.
But if you just want to do something, okay, I'm buying this, I want to create my own plugin,
you probably need a name and type even if it doesn't do anything.
Okay, go ahead.
Now use cases and then I guess I spoke maybe a little bit too much and even if we are late
because we could have rushed to the airport to that, but I'm handing over to Michael Miguel
who's going to be showing you this a little bit around and then if it works again, demo.
Go ahead, Miguel.
Hello?
Well, I'll use this.
So this is like a list of the plugins that are provided by the CNI maintainers and are
available on the container networking slash plugins repository.
So the first is tuning CNI.
It allows you to configure like a list of syscuttle.
So if you need some syscuttle to happen inside of your pod, you use this tuning CNI.
The bandwidth CNI as the name implies, like quite evident, what it does is to throttle
either the ingress or egress traffic to your pod.
If you want to do those kinds of things, the firewall plugin, what it does is only allow
access to and from the IP addresses that are referenced in the results that the plugin
got, for instance, and the port mapping as the, well, the name kind of implies it, well,
does port forwarding configures port forwarding from the host into the container for the set
of ports that you specify in the configuration.
Now having said this, let's go to the demo and I'm now wondering how can I do this while
holding the microphone.
This doesn't work.
I think.
Yeah, go ahead.
No, I do like.
Of course, of course.
Really sorry.
Right.
Okay.
Awesome.
Easy.
Okay.
So the first thing that I should mention, like Daniel, like reference Kubernetes a lot
like, but please remember that CNI is more is like Kubernetes is a user of CNI.
Like it's not that you can use CNI by itself.
And as such, we're going to be using something called CNI tool.
It's just a binary that you point at your, at a certain CNI binary and give it like a
set of environment variables, the plugins configuration via standard then as Daniel
said before, like you basically pass the configuration of the plugins.
You give it the input parameters, which are the environment variables and you execute
the binary.
And this is how we're going to be seeing the demo.
You can follow it on this on this link, but yeah, the first thing I think I should explain
is like the scenario we're trying to achieve.
And this can be seen here in the bottom right corner.
So very simple thing.
We just want to have like a bridge to namespace is interconnected via this bridge.
And we're going to be configuring a static IP on a static IP addresses on each of the
namespaces.
And then we'll run a sniper from the client to the, to the server.
And we're going to see how it fares.
So first I also need to show you the configuration that I'm using for this.
Okay.
It's this one.
And this is the configuration that we're going to be using to achieve this scenario.
Like we're going to be using the plugin of type bridge.
This is the name of the binary that will be invoked on the host to create the bridge.
Give it the name.
We enable the IP's capability so you can put a static IP in it and you tell it that you
want static IP.
And that's pretty much the configuration that you need to give it.
So let's just run the example.
Okay.
Like this parameter here that you see, can you see it?
Oh, it's like the font big enough.
It's good.
Okay.
Thanks.
Like you have to give this like the name of the configuration.
If you see like unlimited bandwidth, it's the attribute here on the upper left corner
that you see under name.
It's the same thing.
It must match.
And now this configured the scenario and it's now running the IPOS session between the both
the client and the server.
And as you see, we're getting like a very big bit rate of around 60 gigabits per second.
So this is with a straight configuration.
Now let's use a different configuration where we put, we use the first configuration, but
we use it in a chain.
And afterwards we put like the bandwidth plugin.
Again, what this does, it will throttle the input traffic into the network interface of
both namespaces.
So we're going to be doing the exact same thing, but with this different configuration
and bandwidth limiter.
And as we see, like the bit rate that we're getting is literally a lot less and it should
map somehow to the values that we've configured here.
So what this shows is that you can use like this bandwidth plugin in a chain in order
to achieve a different use case than you had before.
Like you want to throttle traffic to this, you use this type of plugin.
I think that's, let me just check the time.
Yeah, we're good.
Still have 10 minutes.
So let's run the second.
The second demo we had, we have actually, sorry.
Okay.
The scenario is a lot simpler this time.
Like we just have the same bridge as before, but we just have like a network namespace
connected to it.
And what we're going to be doing is showing you how the chain actually works, focusing
on the, on what Daniel said before, like you need to handle always the previous result
and you need to account for it and you need to pass it along the chain continuously.
And okay.
Let's just show the configuration of this plugin.
So this chain might look a lot more complex than the one before because it has more things
in it, but it's very, very, very simple.
So this thing first will, and it will call the bridge plugin.
It will create the bridge.
Then we'll invoke the debug CNI, like this CNI plugin is very, very simple.
The only thing it does is print the result it got from the previous plugin.
So what we're going to be seeing is here is the result of the first plugin in the chain.
Afterwards, we run the tuning CNI plugin.
And what we're going to do is to change the MAC address that we got on the interface of
this dummy namespace that we see here.
So the idea is we first run the bridge plugin.
This thing will assign a random MAC address to the interface that is on this namespace.
We'll print that.
We'll run tuning to change that MAC address.
And we're going to print that again to see like the result of the previous plugin.
And that's pretty much it.
Let's just run the example and show you what I actually mean.
So here we see like...
So this log here is the result of the first call of the debug CNI.
And as we see in the pods, in what would be the pod interface, which is identified by
this attribute sandbox that points to the name of the namespace or actually to the path
of the namespace, we see that in its result we have the interface name that was created
on that network namespace.
And we see that it was assigned like a random MAC address that is identified here.
We then run the tuning plugin that changed this MAC address.
And we finally printed the previous result again.
And we see that this changed to the MAC address that we specified statically in the plugin
configuration, which is exactly what we wanted to show.
Like that's like very simple demo, but I think it kind of illustrates in a very neat way
how chaining actually works in a step-by-step manner.
And with this, we arrived at the conclusions.
And I'd like to basically tell you again what we just told you, like focusing on the most
important things that we think are about this.
First thing is like these plugins, remember what they do.
They add more stuff to the pod, so they enable different use cases.
You can prevent IP spoofing.
You can throttle bandwidth, as we've seen.
You can configure port forwarding from the host to different containers.
You can configure differences cuddles.
And actually, you can also create an allow list of the syscuddles that you can use inside
of the pod.
And finally, I think like if you have to keep one thing from this presentation is that a
meta plugin must always handle the result of the previous plugin.
Like you need to account for it, first of all, because you don't know if you're a plugin,
you don't know if anything will run after you in a chain.
Like the user will configure it, so you don't know what's going to happen afterwards.
So you need to send a result.
And if you're somewhere in the middle of the chain, least you can do or least you must
do is grab the result you got from the previous one and echo it into the next one.
Now finally, remember that two things.
Chain chains are only allowed starting from CNI 0.3.
And they're the only configuration type allowed starting from CNI version 1.0.
Like if you use the first configuration example we've shown on CNI 1.0, it wouldn't work.
It will explode, it will fail, make you miserable.
And the idea here is know your previous result always because that's probably the most information
you'll get from anything that ran before you.
Like as Daniel said, logging is clearly not the thing that's most prevalent on, at least
on the plugins that are maintained by the CNI maintainers.
And yeah, this concludes our talk.
Thanks a lot, guys.
Questions?
Thank you.
Can you tell a little more about use cases of CNI without Kubernetes?
Okay.
That's a really good question.
And it's going to probably eat all the time that we have.
Like I can, like I work for Kubernetes.
And one thing we do in it is, so there's a pod and inside the pod you run a virtual machine
in it.
Now CNI, what it does is configure the pod interface, but what you want to have is like
networking inside of the VM.
Like you need some way to get like the extended connectivity from the pod, from the pod interface
and into the VM.
You need to have something there.
And we have code in our code base, in the Kubernetes code base to achieve this.
Like one of the thing we could do using CNI chains is to all flow that entire code to
CNI plugins that would create, for instance, the bridge that you have inside of the pod
to extend that connectivity that would create the tap device from which the VM would create
the emulated network device from.
So I really think this could be modelled using CNI.
That's something we still need to see.
Like it's a very rough idea yet, but it's an example, I think.
Now somebody says that I guess the quickest one is, as you know, he was mentioning CNI
tools.
CNI tool is just used to develop CNI plugins and it doesn't have Kubernetes at all.
And you can see that the plugins don't have to run there.
Even that rocket, so rocket, it was on its own.
It didn't have to use Kubernetes at all.
And it's where most of CNI plugins were originally developed.
Just put any kind of, you know, random engine and it would work.
No Kubernetes needed.
So if I have a CNI plugin that sets up some external state, for example, a firewall that
might even be a separate device, and something goes wrong and I lose the delete, how do I
recover from that?
So that's an amazing question.
Like you need all, like you must design everything assuming that CNI deletes will be missed.
Like it might happen like all the time.
So you need to have a reconcile loops of sorts that knows about your state, relevant state,
and reconcile this somehow.
But I didn't see a way to even check if the state should still be active.
How does my CNI plugin know that something is still there?
It's clueless.
Like you need to like, I don't know, like to monitor this little kid and assume that
he will not fall and hit the head in the corner of the table.
You need to do that out of bend.
Like it's not designed to allow for that.
I'm sorry.
Hi.
During the presentation you mentioned that some CNI plugin like Selium, but I guess that
you were also mentioning other plugins, they're not doing the loggings and they're not using
the entire APIs.
How comes?
I mean, it kind of depends on your CNI.
I guess you hear me.
It's okay?
So it kind of depends on your CNI plugin implementation.
So for instance, some CNI do implement logging, but it's not something that is within the
implementation itself at all.
So you may be totally fine doing no logging at all, but then go back to debugging it so
you have to go to the kubectl, you have to go to Cribal Labs, and then go back to debugging
all those.
So it depends on your implementation, for instance, that which is here, he implements
some of his logging for inamulties and so forth, but that's not something that is on
every plugin.
For sure it's not in any of the community-maintained ones.
Okay, thanks.
Any more questions?
Well, thanks a lot for your time and for listening to us, and bye-bye.
Enjoy the question.
Thank you.