Okay.
Yeah.
Hello, everyone, and welcome to my presentation.
I am Frélic Kombogert.
I work for a company called Mind.
And I'm here to present to you the Purple Mesh Project, which is an open source Wi-Fi
mesh solution.
So who am I?
Like I said, I'm an embedded software developer, and I work for Mind.
And since 2020, I've been a project manager for this Purple Mesh Project at the Purple
Foundation.
And, yeah, feel free to email me if you want after presentation, if you have any more questions
afterwards.
So what is the Purple Foundation?
So the Purple Foundation is really a very big conglomeration of the telecoms industry.
So if you look at the logos that I have there, there are a lot of ISPs in there, like AT&T,
like Doge Telecom, like Dish, like Verizon, Vodafone.
So there's a lot of big ISPs in Purple Foundation, and also some hardware manufacturers, so
like ASCII, MediaTek, MaxDinier, Kowm.
And so basically what we do is we sponsor the development of router firmware.
And yeah, so how this came about is essentially operators, they want to provide their users
– so with operators, I mean internet service providers – they want to provide their users
with access points and routers, because not everyone can go out and buy them and configure
them themselves.
But all of the software development is not really their core expertise.
So traditionally they've relied on stacks developed by hardware, the hardware partners,
but they also – this is not their core expertise, and so Purple Foundation was kind of created
to collaborate on this with various partners.
So the main projects that we're working on are Purple OS, which is a router firmware
based on OpenWRT.
Purple Mesh, which is a subject of this presentation, and also Noteware VS Lifecycle Management,
which is kind of an attempt to create an up-store infrastructure, which is really cool actually.
And we are also heavily involved in talking about router security and router data models,
so basically the API of a router.
So that's kind of the overview of the Purple Foundation.
So Purple Mesh itself is an IEEE 1905 stack, so this is a layer 2.5 protocol, so it sits
on top of Wi-Fi and Ethernet, but below IP.
And the stack itself is based on open-source Intel codes.
So we are fully functional, easy mesh implementation with both agent and controller roles supported,
and I will talk later about what that means.
And we have extensive API standardization effort as well in collaboration with the Broadbent
Forum.
So we don't just want to write an API, we want to really think about it, and so we are
collaborating on that with industry, other industry fora.
And we also have very heavy emphasis on testing, so we have some Wi-Fi alliance test buds that
we extensively test with.
So I said Purple Mesh is an easy mesh implementation, so what do I mean by that?
So this is the easy mesh protocol, it's a Wi-Fi alliance standard, just as Wi-Fi 6 and
Wi-Fi 7 are Wi-Fi alliance standards.
And this is all meant to simplify your Wi-Fi management.
So for Wi-Fi, often the problem that we have is you want to add an X point to your network,
and so you want to add an X point to your network, but then you need to configure it,
and then it needs to, and that can be quite tedious.
So the easy mesh protocol can do that for you, so you just onboard new devices using
WPS pairing, which is also extended by the easy mesh standards, and the device will automatically
join your network and have all of your settings, including pass phrases, and the bands it needs
to operate on, the SSIDs, any guest networks that you have configured, and so on.
And another thing that the easy mesh standard does is it shares the configuration, so if
you want to change that configuration, if you want to add SSIDs, if you want to add
guest networks or change any other part of your Wi-Fi configuration, you only need to
do that in one place, and it's applied to all of your X points in your entire network.
And finally also, it gathers a lot of metrics about your network, which can be used to optimize
how devices connect to your network.
So in the image there, you see various X points, and you also see various network devices,
and so what can often happen is that an X point that is used in your network simply
gets overloaded because all of the devices try to connect to that X point, and your other
X points don't see any use, and especially if you have a precarious backhaul that can
lead to some performance problems.
So applications that use the easy mesh standards, they can monitor this, they can see that there
is a problem, and they can try to steer this device to use different X points.
Just solving performance problems in your network.
So purpose mesh is an easy mesh implementation, so basically we implement all of the functionality
that I've just described.
It is portable to a number of different router operating systems, all based on Linux, so
OpenWRT, Purple OS, and RDKB in particular, it's also portable in theory to other Linux-based
operating systems.
The main dependency that we have is we rely on software bus, like Ubisoft or Arbus is
typically used in these router operating systems, but we could also support something like Dbus
for other platforms.
The main problem that we encounter when trying to port Purple Mesh to new platforms is we
need really good Wi-Fi drivers, because something like mesh networking tests your Wi-Fi drivers
like nothing else, and we find that most Wi-Fi drivers simply are not good enough to support
all the functionality that we need.
So that is one thing that we are also active in within Purple, is we try to spur innovation
in the Wi-Fi drivers, so we collaborate, or we try to collaborate with hardware vendors
to make sure that their drivers are not just capable enough to support mesh, but that this
is also done in their open source drivers.
So we do still support some proprietary drivers for some hardware, but this is very much transitional,
and we hope to get various vendors to open source their wireless drivers and make sure
that all the functionality that we need is supported by those open drivers based on config
82.11 and NLL82.11.
So why did we develop Purple Mesh?
Basically like I mentioned, Purple is a whole community of different service providers coming
together to develop a single solution, so instead of everyone having to develop their
own software, it makes sense to collaborate. Also, by developing the software ourselves,
the service providers, they get independence from system chip vendors.
So what we've seen in the past, and what we still sometimes see, is that there are SoC
vendors that try to force you to use their own proprietary software and to depend on
that their proprietary interfaces, and that creates a vendor lock-in within the ecosystem,
and that is something that we are very much aware of and are trying to combat as well.
And another good reason to develop Purple Mesh, and in fact the original reason, is
as a stress test for the wireless drivers, because like I mentioned, Wi-Fi Mesh, it taxes
your Wi-Fi drivers in ways that nothing else does.
And that was kind of the original motivation of Purple Mesh was to act as a test for open
source Wi-Fi drivers, but it kind of ballooned from there.
And one other thing that we do is try to encourage the development of a common API for easy mesh
implementations. This API is usable for remote management, for network diagnostics, and to
enable others to create router apps to configure Wi-Fi so they can plug into Purple Mesh, and
use it to smartly configure your own Wi-Fi. This also is enabled by the LCM project, which
allows you to add router apps to your router, and some of those might use Purple Mesh to
optimize your network, or to show you more information about your network.
Okay, so let me check the time here. We do have time. Okay, so yeah, easy mesh itself.
Like I mentioned, it's based on IEEE 1905. This is a very extensible protocol on top
of Ethernet and Wi-Fi. It's used a fixed multicast address, and the main feature of it is it
works with TLVs, so type length value tuples. And you can add as many of these as you like.
And the way easy mesh works is it defines a set of TLVs that have specific use. So for
instance, TLVs to configure access points, or to report certain metrics, or to discover
devices on the network, things like that. So one thing that easy mesh does is it uses
– so one thing that easy mesh can also be used for is discovery of devices on the network.
So all IEEE 1905 devices, they can report all of their neighboring devices in the network,
and that helps you get a topology map of all of the devices that are present in your network.
So it's easy to discover what's currently living in your network. And so this is also,
of course, a vital tool to allow you to optimize the network. And one other thing that we get
is metrics, like I mentioned, so you can see how well the connection is between various
devices that you might have in your network, like your laptops and your smartphones and
your smart TVs. How well is the connection to their access points? And is there any possibility
that we can connect them to a different access point that has maybe a better connection?
So this is also very useful. And yeah, once we've determined that we would actually like
advice to connect to a different access point, this is something that we can also do. So
the easy mesh protocol includes messages to steer advice. And what we will do is the controller
will tell the agents, try to tell a station connected to you to disconnect. There's a
number of mechanisms for that in the Wi-Fi standards, like 8211K, 8211V. They are not
always supported by all devices, in particular, smartphones have a habit of ignoring them.
So what we can also then do as a final option is to just blacklist the device, not allow
it to connect to an agent anymore. So it's forced to connect to a different wireless
access point. One other very crucial functionality is onboarding. So if you add a new agent,
it's easy for them to find the controller and then onboard through WPS or DPP, new standards
from Wi-Fi lines. So in conclusion, so Wi-Fi integers, they are getting more complex. And
that means they also need to get smarter. And that is really what we are doing within
the PRP mesh project and PRP ecosystem in general, is we are trying to make Wi-Fi smarter.
And we can use your help with that. One thing that's also crucial to know is that open source
is also very useful to get vendor independence. So no more vendor lock-in. That is really
a very big deal. And also, yeah, sometimes you can find open ecosystems out there, even
where you might not expect it. So all of the things that I've talked about is these router
operating systems, this LCM, App Store ecosystem, and PRP mesh itself, it's all open source.
But right now, it's still developed by the ISPs, basically, and PRP Foundation itself.
We don't get a lot of external contributions. But yeah, we welcome everyone who wants. So
yeah, check us out when you can. And yeah, related to that also, so you can make good
money developing open source codes. So yeah, this is where I plug my own company, Minds.
We are software consultants, especially focused on embedded software and open source. And
we are hiring. So yeah, I'll be around here outside of the hall after presentation. So
yeah, hit me up if that sounds interesting to you. All right. Any questions?
So the operators and ISPs have previously gotten together and made something called
HomeNet. And that went very much the same direction. And then they decided they didn't
like it because it supports you getting more than one internet provider and using that
at the same time, which this does not support. And this also doesn't support other things,
for example, meshing well with Zigbee or HomeNet automation stuff. So I would ask you, have
you actually evaluated whether this is a good standard to implement? Do you think this is
a good standard to implement? And if yes, why?
Yeah, an interesting question. I am not familiar with this HomeNet you're talking about, although
behind you, Walter, definitely is. Maybe I can answer that because I'm one of the operators.
And I was in the HomeNet working group as well. I rejected being the chair at some point
in time. HomeNet was very challenging in the sense that it decided to remove all existing
protocols to communicate with the individual devices, such as let's get rid of the HEP,
let's go do something else. So from a point of view of a realistic framework, a realistic
path to get there, that was a problem. There are some parts of HomeNet such as HNCP that
have been reused by some proprietary vendors here and there, but it's all died. Now, when
it comes to the lineage of EasyMesh, that's a whole different story. And why it's based
on 1905, it was essentially a few companies that got together and said, what are we going
to do? Are we going to do it at layer two? Are we going to do it at layer three? And
it's mostly based on internal pressures of, well, we have something that's 1905 based.
It works together with our power line devices already. Let's use that as a basis. It wasn't
too fond of it, but VHS versus Betamaxa and V2000, right? So to me, I still see value
in HomeNet in trying to get some of the concepts in there. Now, the other problem with HomeNet,
and I had the discussion with the chair at the time as well, is this mentality that there
was that every access point had its own IP range rather than what the reality is in a
wireless network in a home, which is that it's all a layer two. It's all one single
layer two. If you do this steering that's really explained by our device in milliseconds
switches from one access point to another while consistently maintaining a video call
or something like that, you're not going to get a different IP address. You're not going
to restart your TCP connection or whatever. It doesn't make any sense. So doing this at
layer two just makes a lot more sense than the HomeNet concept of multiple segments and
passing on from there. So HomeNet does have the advantage that you don't need special
hardware support in supporting the four frame 802.11 to get the data along. I do actually
agree with most of your points, and I think that the best solution is somewhere in the
middle between the two because this is so Wi-Fi centric that it can't really support
things that aren't Wi-Fi, but it is better for Wi-Fi itself, which I think is to a good
degree your point, especially with the mobility. So the question is, is it possible to build
both into one thing maybe? Let's continue this conversation. Yes, so right. So the it's
that's the nice thing of being in based on so Wi-Fi Alliance has focused purely on the
wireless side. The rest of us are making sure that wired connections retain support, especially
Ethernet. Now, the good thing about 1905 is that it is a protocol that supports also other
not only Ethernet, but also other things. 1905.1a added standard support for G.HN. You could
have so there's a modeling for on top of Mocha. So you have you can have coax a twisted pair,
an intern in home fiber, etc. protocols are all supported. We just need to keep the Wi-Fi
Alliance almost from time to time because they're modeling using Wi-Fi Wi-Fi Alliance
data elements of the network. Topology tends to ignore everything that's not wireless.
But when it comes to supporting network ports on a particular switch, etc. That's all that
all comes natively in 1905. So that's fully supported by by easy mesh. And we make sure
that that is supported in purple mesh. Indeed, that is indeed very important. We try to go
beyond Wi-Fi. You mentioned that most hardware is not compatible, but can you give some examples
maybe which hardware is? Yeah. So what I think Qualcomm is tends to be fairly good about
their hardware drivers. Broadcom is not as good. So yeah, a message for anyone considering
basing trying to make a new SOC avoid Broadcom. A bit more detail. I did get Broadcom to agree
to support this as well. And it is supported. There are some gaps in what the proprietary
drivers support at the moment and what they supported in a later 2011. So Linux wireless
does need to get upset. We've identified the gaps and we hope to work with the with the
host AP and the Linux wireless community fix that. Now me as an operator, I've given it
a hard requirements to all our silicon vendors who want to do a gateway or an access point
that they must comply with this. And we do have general support for it. It's just that
every time there's a new standard coming out, such as Wi-Fi seven now that they first develop
proprietary interfaces and we need to keep them on the right track. That's a bit of the
that's the challenge, essentially. I did mention before that the purple foundation is also
involved in trying to set standards for for Wi-Fi drivers and low level API. That's my
part of the low level API. This definition of that's I'm the chair of that to make sure
that they're that's all the proprietary silicon uses standard Linux interfaces. Some more
questions. Someone over there. Yeah. Hello. In terms of vulnerability management, is there
a way for the agents to be updated from the central agent or in some other way without
losing connectivity or would would the need to patch something because everything to drop.
So if I understand correctly, the question is where it's possible to steer a device without
causing the connection to drop. Right. Either steer it or because you said that it's highly
demanding on the wireless driver to to do that. So I'm guessing that in case you also
need to patch something you're risking the connection. So is there some handling internally
to ensure that even during an update could be a rolling update, for example, one agent
at a time or something like that. Is there some like provision to make sure that it's
not gonna cost connectivity if it doesn't update or is something that's still not being
developed yet. I think if you reconfigure a network like change as I this and so on
connection will drop. No. Okay. Yeah. My apologies. I'm not I'm not super into all the technical
details. But apparently there are ways there are ways to manage that and so that your connections
are not dropping. And I should also mention the virtual BSS projects, which we are also
collaborating on with with an organization called cable apps. And there the goal is to
have a single virtual AP per device. So basically an AP that follows your device around by by
means of by way of speaking. So it means that your phone, for instance, will always see
the same AP regardless of where you go. And and this means that no connections ever need
to get dropped when you move around. This is also a very interesting project that we
are working on at the moment. So this, yeah. But yeah, in general, no, the answer to your
questions is no, the connection doesn't need to drop. Any more questions? So it is all
very interesting. The question is, is there any off the shelf equipment, which are more
so it's made, right? Yes, we have some some reference hardware that you can just buy on
Amazon or other places. This sort of separately available that you can test the permission.
Yes. So we have two reference devices, the G line, it's B13 hundreds and the two is only
are that are readily available. And we will be adding more in the future as well. And
I guess it is mentioned somewhere. So yes. So if you if you go to our to our page for
purple mesh, we have a lot of documentation on the wiki, including documentation about
which hardware to get. So I think, you know, so, yeah, actually, I had it there. So we
have in the getting started guides, we have a section here on device purchasing options.
So as you can see, I would recommend the tourism and the G line. It's the net gear Rex 40 is
no longer really supported because it's it lacks a crucial feature that's required for
wireless back also, I would not recommend that one. Okay, thank you. My questions. I
think we're good. There are no more questions for you. Thank you very much for the presentation.