Hello, everyone.
Thanks for joining today.
Welcome to our talk on hole punching in the wild.
Sometimes I would say we're going to talk about the biggest hack of the Internet, which
I would refer to as hole punching.
We want to talk a bit about learnings from doing hole punching on larger networks.
Some might remember me from last year in Fosstem where I introduced our way of doing hole
punching and today we're coming here with a bunch of data.
So who are we?
Dennis, do you want to introduce yourself?
Yeah, okay.
My name is Dennis.
I'm working at ProcoLab as a research engineer at a team called ProbLab and I'm mainly focusing
on network measurements and proco-optimizations that come out of these measurements and, yeah,
I was working with Max on this hole punching campaign.
Very cool.
And Max, again, software engineer.
You can find us anywhere there online if you want.
Yeah, happy to communicate online further after the talk and we're also around at the
venue.
Wonderful.
Okay, what were we doing today?
I want to do a very quick intro to LIP2P, a peer-to-peer networking library, but then
dive right into the problem of why firewalls and nats are rather hard for peer-to-peer
networking.
The solution, which in some cases is hole punching, then how LIP2P does all of that
and then we have been running a large measurement campaign on the internet in the wild collecting
data how well hole punching works out there and we're going to present those findings
and then have takeaways of what we learned from there and where we're going from there.
All right, LIP2P, just a quick introduction.
It's a peer-to-peer networking library.
It's an open source project.
There's one specification and then there are many implementations of that specification,
among other languages in Go, JS, Rust, NIM, C++, Java, many, many out there.
It provides, I would say, two levels.
On the low level, it provides all kind of different connectivity options.
It takes care of the encryption and authentication, here being mutual authentication.
And then things like hole punching, for example.
Once you have these low level features of being able to connect to anyone out there
in an encrypted and authenticated way, you can then build higher level protocols on top
of that, which LIP2P also provides, like a DHT distributed hash table or gossiping protocols
and things like that.
My big statement always about LIP2P is it's all you need to build your peer-to-peer application.
All right.
To zoom out a little bit, that's LIP2P.
All the things that we're talking about today are implemented in LIP2P, but that doesn't
mean you can't implement it in any other networking library if you want to.
Our great motivation for LIP2P and in general for peer-to-peer networking is that we have
full connectivity among all the nodes within the network to the best of their capabilities,
obviously.
In this talk, we're going to focus on the problem of NATs and firewalls for peer-to-peer
networking.
Now, before all of you yell, I'm not saying let's get rid of firewalls.
Please let's not do that.
They have a very important purpose, but in some cases, we want to get around them.
Okay.
Cool.
Yeah.
I'm here in the network dev room.
I'm not going to explain what NATs and firewalls are.
I forget, let's say, it is firewalls.
But we will go a little bit into what that means for hole punching.
In general, for hole punching, NATs and firewalls are our big ones that we can have to get around.
Okay.
What is the problem in some fancy pictures?
A wants to send a packet to B, whether that's a TCP SIN or anything.
And A and B are both behind their home routers.
Just imagine two laptops in two different houses.
And they want to communicate directly with each other.
So A sends a packet to B. It crosses A's router.
A's router sets a five tuple in its routing table for that packet.
And the packet makes it to B. And obviously, a very good thing is that B drops that packet
because it's a packet that has no clue where it's coming from.
Probably some wider internet.
And it might be an attack.
So it's dropping it.
It doesn't have any five tuple in its routing table.
Right?
Okay.
So that is the problem.
And we somehow want to make A and B communicate with each other.
So the solution here, in some cases, it's hole punching.
We want A and B to connect to each other.
Instead of only having A send a packet to B, we have both of them send a packet at the
same time.
I'm talking in a little bit about what at the same time means.
But let's just for now say we have some magic synchronization mechanism.
So A sends a packet to B. B sends a packet to A. The packet from A punches a hole in
its routing table.
So adding a five tuple for it.
The packet from B punches a hole in its routing table on its side.
The packets cross somewhere in the internet.
Obviously, they don't.
But it's a nice metaphor.
And at some point, packet B arrives at router A. Router A checks its routing table.
A little bit simplified here.
It lets packet B pass same on router B. And this way, we actually exchange packets.
Cool.
So now the big problem is how does A and B know when to send those packets?
It has to happen at the same time, at least for TCP.
We might go a little bit into what that means for UDP.
But at least for TCP, this needs to happen at the same time for TCP simultaneous open
to happen in the end.
So how do we do that?
This is LIPIDAP specific.
It doesn't need to be LIPIDAP.
You can use any signaling protocol on top.
Let's say A and B want to connect.
And they need to hole punch at the same time.
They need to send those two packets from both sides at the same time.
So one can go through the hole of the other to the other side.
What do we do?
We need some kind of coordination mechanism.
So some kind of public server out there that is not behind a firewall on that.
B connects to the relay.
A learns B's address through the relay.
A connects through the relay.
So now the two, A and B, have a communication channel over the relay.
B sends a message to A. You can just think of it as a time synchronization protocol.
And at the same time, while sending that message, it measures the time it takes for A to send
a message back.
So at this time, we know the round trip time.
And then once we know the round trip time, B sends another message to A and waits exactly
half the round trip time.
And once A receives that sun down there, you can do the math.
If now both of them start, so A when it receives the packet, and B after half the round trip
time, they actually do the hole punch.
They exchange the packets, they cross somewhere in the internet.
Both of them punch the hole into their routers.
And ta-da.
We succeeded.
We have a hole punch.
We have a connection established.
Cool.
Okay.
A little bit in terms of timeline on all of this.
Hole punching is nothing new.
It's definitely nothing that Lippy to P invented.
Not at all.
The most obvious mention I know is an RFC 5128.
But again, it predates that for sure.
But I think it's a nice introduction to hole punching in general in case you like reading
ITF documents.
Since then, we have been implementing it around 2021, 2022, basing on a lot of past knowledge
around that.
I've been presenting this work at Fostem 2022 last year remotely.
And since then, we have rolled it out on a larger network, which is the IPFS network,
in a two phase way where all public nodes act as relay nodes, very limited relays.
And then in a second phase, all the clients gained the hole punching capabilities.
And now on this large peer-to-peer network, we actually have on the public nodes relaying
for the signaling.
And then the clients actually being able to do the hole punching work.
And so we have this deployed now in this large network.
But it's very hard to know how it's working, especially across the internet, across all
the networks, across all the different endpoints, across all the routing hardware and so on.
So that's why we launched the hole punching month, which is kind of like a measurement
campaign, which Dennis now is going to introduce.
Sorry.
Can you hear me?
Yes.
All right.
Thanks, Max.
Yeah, as Max said, the LIPDP folks conceived this new DCUTR protocol and then deployed
it to the network.
And now we want to know how well does it actually work.
And for this, we launched, as Max said, a measurement campaign during December.
I will get to this in a second.
But how actually do we measure these hole punching success rates?
And the challenge here is that we actually don't know the clients that are DCUTR capable.
So where are the clients that we want to hole punch?
Because they are behind nets.
We cannot enumerate them.
They don't register themselves in a central registry or so.
So we conceived this three-component architecture.
And the crucial thing here probably is this honeypot component, which is just a DHT server
node that interacts with, as Max said, the IPFS network.
And it's a very stable node.
And this means that it gets added to routing tables of different peers in the network.
And this increases chances if peers behind nets interact with this IPFS network come
across this honeypot.
So peers behind nets is in this diagram, the top right corner, some DCUTR-capable peer.
This one, by chance, by interacting with the network, comes across the honeypot.
And the honeypot then keeps track of those peers and writes it into a database.
And then this database is interfaced by a server component that serves those identified
and detected peers to a fleet of clients.
And the hole punch measurement campaign consisted of a deployment of those clients to a wide
variety of different laptops or users that agreed to run these kinds of clients.
And this client then queries the server for a peer-to-hole punch.
As Max said, it connects to the other peer-to-relay node and then exchanges those couple of packages,
tries to establish a direct connection.
And then at the end, it reports back if it worked, if it didn't work, what went wrong,
and so on.
And so we can probe the whole network, or like many, many clients and many network configurations.
So we did this measurement campaign.
We made some fuss about it during November internally at ProCollapse and also reached
out to the community.
And starting from the beginning of December, we said, OK, please download these clients.
Run it on your machines.
And let's try to gather as much data as possible during that time.
And as you can see here, so we collected around 6.25 million hole punch results.
So this is quite a lot of data from 154 clients that participated.
And we punched around 47,000 unique peers in this network.
And on the right-hand side, you can see the deployment of our clients, of our controlled
clients.
The color here is the number of contributed results.
So the US was dominant here.
But we have many other nodes deployed in Europe, but also Australia and New Zealand, and also
South America, and also one client from the continent of Africa.
And these clients interacted with these other peers that are basically all around the world.
So we could measure hole punch success rates all across the globe.
And I think we have a very comprehensive data set here.
And so we now gathered the data.
And at the beginning of January, I started.
So I said, OK, the hole punch link month is over.
And I started to analyze the data a little bit.
And what you can see here on the x-axis is the, so each bar is a unique client.
And on the y-axis, we can see these different outcomes.
So each hole punch result, as I said, can have, so the clients report back these results,
and each result can have a different outcome.
These outcomes are at the top, so it can be successful.
So we actually were able to establish a direct connection through hole punching.
Then connection reversed.
This means I'm trying to hole punch, so I'm connecting to the other peer through the relay.
And the first thing before we do the hole punching dance is for the peer to directly
connect to us, because if we are directly reachable because we have port mapping in
place in the router, we don't actually need to do the hole punching exchange.
This is a connection reversed.
And as we can see here, it's a little hard to see.
But some clients actually have a lot of these results.
So this means they have a unique router configuration in place.
Then failed is the obvious thing.
So we tried, we exchanged these messages.
But in the end, we weren't able to establish a connection.
No stream is some internal error that's unique to our setup, so probably nothing to worry
about here.
And no connection means we try to connect to the other peer through a relay, but the
other peer was already gone.
It's a permissionless peer to peer network, so it could be from the time that the honeypot
detected the peer to the client trying to establish a connection to the peer that the
client has already churned and left the network.
But actually looking at these clients is a distorted view on the data because we allowed
everyone who participated in the campaign to freely move around.
So I was running this client on my laptop, and I was moving from a coffee shop, Wi-Fi
network, to a home network, to a university network, and so on.
And hole punching is actually dependent on those network configurations instead of just
me running the client.
So the challenge here with the data analysis was, so I'm also not done with that yet, and
happy to open for suggestions, to detect these individual networks that the clients operated
in.
With each hole punch result, the client reported their listening IP addresses and so on, and
I grouped them together to actually find out, to identify unique networks that those clients
operated in.
And at the end, I arrived at 342 unique client networks, and then the graph looks like this,
probably not much different than before.
But also there are some interesting unique network outcomes here that I will also get
to in a bit.
The most interesting graph is probably this one, so what's the success rate of this protocol?
And on the x-axis we have the success rate, binned by, yeah, just 5% binning, and on the
y-axis the number of networks that had the success rate by probing the whole other network.
And the majority of networks actually had a success rate of 70%, so I think this is
already, actually I think it's amazing, because from not being able to connect at all to having
a 70% chance to establish a direct connection without an intermediary, it's actually pretty
great.
But then also there are some networks that have very low success rate, and these are
the ones that are probably the most interesting ones.
Then also, the IP and transport dependence is also quite interesting, as an angle to
look at the data.
Here we can see the top row we used IPv4 and TCP to hole punch, so when these clients exchange
these connect messages, they actually exchange the publicly reachable IP addresses of those
two peers that want to hole punch.
And in our measurement campaign we restricted this to actually only IPv4 and TCP, and with
some other hole punches only to IPv6 and QUIC, which is on the bottom right.
And so we can take a look at which combination is more successful than the other.
And here we can see that IPv4 and TCP and QUIC is actually, if you average the numbers,
has a similar success rate, but on IPv6 it's basically not working at all.
And these unexpected things are actually the interesting ones for us.
Either it's a measurement error, or there's some inherent property to the networking setup
that prevents IPv6 from being hole punchable, basically.
So if we actually allow both transports, so in the previous graph we showed we were only
using TCP and QUIC, but if we allow both transports to simultaneously try to hole punch, we can
see that with 81% we end up with a QUIC connection, and this is just because QUIC connection establishment
is way faster than TCP connection.
So this is like an expected result here, just to verify some of the data here.
And now two takeaways for us for protocol improvements.
So if we took at private VPNs, so if clients are running in VPNs, we can see that the success
rate actually drops significantly from around 70% to less than 40%.
And my hypothesis here is that the router time that Max showed previously is measured
between A and B, but what we actually need is the router time between the router A and
router B, and if your router basically is your exit node or your gateway that you're
connected to from your VPN, this can differ by dozens of milliseconds actually, and so
the router time doesn't add up and the whole synchronization is a little off.
So this is potentially a protocol improvement here.
And then also interesting, so Max said they are exchanging these messages during the hole
punch, but actually we tried this three times.
So if it doesn't work the first time, we try it again, and if it doesn't work the second
time, we try it yet again.
But when we look at the data, if we end up with the successful hole punch connection,
it was actually successful with the first attempt in 97% or 98% of the cases.
So this is also something for the next steps for us.
We should consider changing our strategy on the second and third try to increase the odds.
So if we stick with the three retries, we shouldn't do the same thing over again, because
as we saw from the data, it doesn't make a difference.
So we should change our strategy here.
And so one thing would be to reverse the client server roles in this quick hole punching exchange.
This would be something.
And also the other protocol improvement for us, as I said, would be to change the measurement
of the round trip time.
And for the future, the data analysis, right now what I showed here is basically aggregates
across all the data.
And the interesting part is basically, so why is a specific client or a specific network,
why has it less or a worse success rate than others?
So these are these individual things to look into to increase.
Maybe there's a common pattern that you can address with a protocol to increase the success
rate and then identify those causes.
And also, at the end of all of this, we want to craft a follow-up publication to something
that Max and some fellow friends, I would say, have published just last year.
And we want to make the data set public and so on and so forth for others to benefit from
the data and can do their own analysis.
And with that, get involved.
Talk to us here at the venue about all of this.
LIP-ITV is a great project.
Have a look at all these links.
Get in touch and contribute.
Join our community calls.
And I think that's it.
Thank you very much.
This is what you implemented there.
Is it exactly Ice turn stuff or how different it is from this?
So we differ in some cases.
It's definitely very much motivated by Ice in turn.
So a couple of things.
We don't do turn itself.
We have our own relay protocol.
Because nodes in the network act as public for the public as relay nodes.
And the problem is you don't want to relay any traffic for anyone, but you want to make
this really restricted in terms of how much traffic, how long.
If you run a public node, you don't want to be the next relay node for everyone out there.
And then what we built here is very much TCP specific, but it also works well with UDP.
We need the synchronization.
And as far as I know, at least the WebRTC stack is very focused on UDP where timing
doesn't matter as much.
So you saw the timing protocol.
And that is very TCP specific where we want a TCP simultaneous connect which allows two
sends to actually result in a single TCP connection.
This is for your analysis.
I guess a lot of this depends on the default configurations of the firewall.
Did you kind of find out what are the branch type of firewalls or configurations that stops
hole punching in your research?
So yeah, so not in its entirety, but what we did is people that signed up for the measurement
campaign gave us information about the networks.
And so if we find something fishy in the data, we could also reach out to them and ask what's
the with the firewall setup in your specific network.
We also gather data about port mappings that are in place.
So what the host tries to do is establish a port mapping inside your router.
And this is also reported back.
And what we also did is try to query the login page from these routers and get some information
about what kind of firewall or router actually was preventing you from connecting to someone
else.
So these are the data points that we have to get some conclusions around this.
But more than this, we don't have.
But I think this is already pretty conclusive to a wide variety of analysis.
What I was just wondering about is, do you have any data?
How many clients actually were behind the net?
So all these clients that the honeypot detected were clients that are behind the net.
So these are all LTPP hosts.
And with the default configuration of LTPP hosts, if they only announce relay addresses,
this means that they must be not publicly reachable, which is for us equivalent with
being behind the net.
So it should be.
There's probably some error there.
So then all of the IPv6 kind of hosts you were trying to connect to also were behind
the net.
Kind of IPv6.
Yes, yes.
And this is the interesting thing.
So I cannot explain this yet.
Maybe it's a measurement error from us.
Maybe it's some, as I said, inherent property to something.
Maybe it's a protocol error.
I don't know.
And this is the interesting stuff in these kinds of things.
Thanks.
I'm very curious.
I was wondering, does it also work with multiple nets?
Can you hold punch through two nets?
So if another friend of mine who I convinced to run these clients actually was running
behind two nets and it was working.
But I'm not sure how many people actually ran behind two nets.
But in theory, maybe Max you can explain.
Right now we don't have really a lot of data about two nets.
And also we don't have the data, which I think was it called needle.
I don't quite know where you're within the same network.
But you don't know that you're next to each other.
And you actually want to hold punch through your own net, even though you can't connect
to each other.
So there's some challenges.
Do we still have time for another question?
Yeah, yeah.
Sorry.
So you said that for UDP should work similarly.
Did you do any experiments with that?
Because in the past we had a custom UDP hold punching thing and the routers were pretty
brain-dead.
They forgot the mapping within 20 seconds or something.
So we run this measurement campaign on TCP and quick.
And quick in the end is just UDP.
And what we do is something similar to stun in the ICE suit where we continuously try
to keep our mapping up.
And then on nets that do endpoint independent mappings, that actually helps.
So as long as we keep that up for like, I don't know, every 10 seconds or so, then our
mapping survives even on UDP.
Okay, cool.
Thank you very much.