Great, yeah, sorry for the old, the usual, I'm sure you're used to it now.
Great to see so many people here, amazing.
Thanks for your interest in the Co-op Cloud.
Yeah, I'm decentralized, that's my internet name, and these are my enterprise slides
for the Co-op Cloud.
So I've been working on this project now for, yeah, maybe two to three years, I would say,
so there's a lot of knowledge of the project, how it happened, and what came to pass, locked
up in my head, but I am only one person involved in this project, which has now become quite
a wonderful project, I would say, which involves a lot of different collectors, a lot of different
groups.
So yeah, this is just kind of like a moment to offload what we've been up to for the last
two years, and yeah, all the hot takes are mine, mine alone.
Some of the images are taken from, yeah, shout out to fellow worker Trav, the internet gardening
collection on Arena, I totally recommend checking that out, it's great.
So yeah, Co-op Cloud, this is the official website ready description of what the Co-op
Cloud is, a software stack that aims to make hosting Libra software applications simple
for small service providers, such as tech co-ops who are looking to standardize around
open transparent and scalable infrastructure, which is a lot.
So I was thinking, how am I going to explain this?
Because we come straight in with a software stack, but actually it's much more than that.
I think you could argue our project is more a social endeavor, social organizing, more
than a technical thing, but of course they're overlapping.
So I thought, well, okay, we'll just go back, we'll do a history lesson on how the project
started.
And I feel like that is an important angle for introducing the project, so I want you
to understand where the project is coming from, and then maybe you feel welcome to join
the project and shape the future of the project.
And I think this historical view on where things are coming helps to ground the project
in an actual need, human need.
There's a lot of software projects out there that are just like, why does this exist?
But we're trying to show that this is socially useful, and why we have come up with this
project and initiated and tried to make it work is based on what we needed at the time.
But that may necessarily be the case in the future.
So yeah, put that to one side, and let me introduce you to the magic brain of autonomic
co-op.
So these are some people in the co-op.
There's me on the banjo.
That's not all of them.
There's 13 of us, as far as I remember.
We have a new website that was just put up last night, so check it out.
It's hilarious.
I don't know if I can get up here, but I'll try maybe at some point.
So yeah, we're a technology cooperative, a worker-owned cooperative.
That means the people who work in the business own the business.
It's run and managed by ourselves.
And that means we're, yeah, this is like a, you know, when we come into where we work,
we have the chance to make decisions about every aspect of how the workplace runs.
So you know, what kind of work do we want to do?
How do we want to make decisions?
How do we deal with money?
How do we find the new work?
Who do we want to work with?
Another member wants to work with this group, but someone else disagrees with that.
How do we work this out?
How do we deal with conflict?
It's kind of an end-to-end workplace situation where you have the chance to, you know, be
involved in every step of the process.
And of course, you don't have to do that alone.
You can do that with your friends.
So that's the kind of model of the cooperative.
Yeah, and one of the kind of, yeah, I'll come back to the website maybe in a bit.
So one of the ideas behind what a cooperative is, is this listing of cooperative principles.
You can see them on the right-hand side there.
For example, autonomy, independence, you know, economic participation of the members, open
voluntary membership.
These are kind of like non-binding principles of what it means to be a co-op.
Principle six, for example, that you will work with other co-ops.
So you know, we want to expand cooperation in the ecosystem of groups that are trying
to do this as well.
And a lot of these hinge on actually having money to survive in order to practice what
it means to be a cooperative.
So we are a technology cooperative, and what do we do exactly?
And you could kind of say we do basically everything and anything.
Like we would happily develop a new piece of software, but we'd also come to your house
and fix your toaster.
We try to work with people that we want to work with, that we want to support, that we
like their work, or that connect with our values.
And one of the things we've done quite successfully, in my opinion, is to run a free software stack
boat internally and for the people we work with.
So we have like all the things we use, our free software.
So we're pretty good at that, managing our own internal infrastructure.
And so necessarily we would then just offer that to groups.
Like do you want a website?
Do you want your own chat system, like a matrix?
Or do you want a wiki?
Or do you want an xCloud or whatever?
This kind of stuff, this classic hosting situation.
And one of these problems that has come up, Autonautics is running like several years
now, five years or so, is that it's difficult to make money when you just do hosting.
People are used to just getting stuff for free, for very understandable reasons.
Big tech.
And at some point, we want to scale out of the code.
We want to involve more people.
We want to be able to make a living from it.
We want to be able to survive, pay the rent, and so on.
And then we started realizing that, OK, actually we're making more money, or people are happy
to pay us more when we are doing support.
And this is talking to people, getting on a call and being like, what is software?
And then talking about it.
Or what is a wiki?
Everyone's saying wiki.
I don't know what a wiki is.
And just having a chat about it.
But then also being around later.
So once they ask for the thing, like an xCloud, you set it up and then you don't disappear
because you're a cooperative and you intend to continue.
So sustainability is one of the core principles.
So we stick with them.
We chat.
We're contact on mail and so on.
So this is kind of the dilemma of like, we want to definitely do more hosting because
people need digital infrastructure to do their work.
This is just like a base layer of how to organize things.
But it's difficult to survive.
As a technology cooperative, only doing hosting.
So you need to expand what you do.
And one of the places we ended up was using Cloudron, which is a kind of like one-click
install open source system, which I would still recommend.
It's great.
It got us really far.
A lot of the next slides criticize it.
So I'm just going to say it's great on this slide.
So you can see you have your classic selection of open source apps if you're familiar with
that stuff.
Like RockaChat, for example, we use RockaChat to communicate in the co-op.
And what this enabled us to do was basically work with different groups that may not necessarily
have money to support us, like to make it sustainable to work with them, but still support
them to do their work.
And Cloudron was like a really kind of like get out of jail card in that sense.
It was like, okay, I can just like hit five times on this WordPress button.
And we've got five WordPress sites.
And people are going.
They're posting.
They're organizing.
They're working.
We're supporting them.
It's brilliant.
And for those that don't know, Cloudron is just like you fire up a server, you SSH into
it, you run a command, it spins up this thing, and you're going.
You can install multiple apps on the same server.
So this really reduces the costs for rolling out digital infrastructure.
Let me check time, sorry.
Yes.
All right.
So yeah, remember I said that Cloudron is cool.
But at some point, the core of the part, the front end, the web front end became proprietary.
So they made a switch.
In some sense, I can't blame them because, as I said, if you want to survive, you need
to make a book, and you need to pay the rent and so on.
But yeah, that made us nervous.
When we work with people as a cooperative, we want to say we'll be around for you.
We want to continue.
We want to do this sustainably.
And if you remember, one of the principles is like our independence.
Can we exist in this world?
There's, of course, interdependencies, but can we continue to do what we want to do
without relying on one specific thing?
So when Cloudron made the decision to make the front end proprietary, you can still use
it, whatever.
It's a great system.
But we thought, oh no, what's going to happen?
And then we started looking a bit deeper.
And we realized that Cloudron, when you click and install an app, the apps are...
Yeah, it's an image.
So it uses a container system.
It's kind of like a light virtualization layer.
They're packaging all the apps themselves.
So the people who work in Cloudron, Inc., or whatever, when they want to provide a new
app, they say, okay, let's make a new Git repository and let's package this thing.
And that's great, and it works really well.
But then we realized that they had packaged...
I can't remember specific apps, but take, for example, Nextcloud.
They had gone, and some worker in Cloudron had packaged Nextcloud.
But then we went to the upstream Nextcloud repository, and we saw they had provided an
image.
And then we thought, well, why aren't we just working with them?
Because that would connect our values with expanding cooperation in different layers
of the software stack and so on.
And then the more we looked, we realized that free software communities were really converging
on the idea that you have a packaged image inside your repository.
So you're hacking on your source code, and you just have an image that's building.
And we can use that.
That's what Cloudron needs.
So we were like, okay, that's interesting.
Maybe let's think about that.
And then the logical end of the paranoia or whatever was that we were relying on this one
company, this one group.
Autonomic is a cooperative that supports maybe 20-plus groups, but a large selection of them
have very little money to pay for the infrastructure.
So if you could imagine that Cloudron would somehow make a bigger step into more proprietary
solutions or somehow increase the cost or who knows what, we'd be in a position where
we can support those groups.
And that's not something we wanted to deal with.
So we started to try to think, like, you know, where do we make this better or whatever?
And that is the start of Cloud.
So now we're getting back into another take on that original really long sentence that
had things like software stack in it.
Yeah, we were like, let's just eliminate this issue of proprietary angles or whatever.
Oh, yeah, here's where I just couldn't get the emoji in the slide, so I just gave up.
Yeah, we were just like, we'll just copy left the entire thing.
Let's just do that.
That seems sensible.
Cool.
And then, as I mentioned, Yee Ha, Terrell, favorite emoji, we want to work with the upstream
developers of the software because a lot of precarity is in the open source ecosystem
in that there's, you know, certain developers which are doing unpaid labor to develop the
software that a lot of us rely on.
And they're providing these, you know, a lot of them are providing these packages.
And we thought, well, OK, we can just meet them where they're at, engage with them on
the issue tracker, you know, speak to them, make them aware of our hosting efforts.
And you know, we're in a sense like closer to end users in that, you know, it's like
developers, hosters, users, you know, summarized.
And often developers, well, they've got their hands full trying to make the software work.
So we can like help that connection.
So we're trying to bridge that in that sense.
And also, which we'll see later on, they're also providing, so they're packaging up their
apps in images, but they're also providing this kind of extra configuration around it,
which kind of tells you how to deploy the thing, which is great for people who are doing
hosting because, OK, we have an app, but does it need a database, for example?
So what database?
But they're also doing that for us as well.
So if you develop over our software, thank you.
Yeah.
And then the democratic governance.
We were going to initiate this project, let's say.
I wouldn't say we like invented it.
We just like collude a bunch of stuff together.
But we wanted to not be in control of that.
So not become the new Cloud Run, which is like, OK, let's set up some clear rules for
how do you interact with this project?
And also, on what basis?
Are you also a technology cooperative?
Are you a personal developer?
Are you a user of the software?
Do you want to support the host?
Or do you want to support the device?
We can start to engage with it where we're at, but meet in this kind of common project.
And obviously, the goal then is to sustain open source digital infrastructure and expand
cooperation.
Yeah.
So moving out of the history phase and now into what it actually is.
Yes.
So this word kind of pops up if you've checked the website or the docs.
Democratic tech collectives.
So what is that actually?
We are so Autonomic is a more public registered in the UK.
We're publicly regulated.
We're a cooperative society.
We have gone through the paperwork to make that happen because we wanted to do that.
But we recognize that not everyone will want to do that or be able to do that.
And this really depends on a per country basis.
If you're in the Netherlands, it's a different model.
If you're in the UK, the way you relate to the legal system and the state is like, in
Germany, it's quite difficult.
I've been told there's no way to kind of just like slot yourself in.
You're like, yeah, it's not like very easy to find information.
And we don't want that to be a limiting factor in working together.
So we were trying to conceptualize this idea of like what other groups would we be willing
to work with but not close that definition down from the outside.
So we were thinking about other groups who want to work with their friends or together
with other groups and have set up decision making, for example, collective decision making.
So they're able to navigate what they want to do together.
That was kind of like a thing we wanted to do.
We want to be able to interact with each other.
We want to be able to disagree and receive and send constructive feedback, reach, compromise,
stuff like this.
This is kind of easier to do when people are already organized in their own groups.
But yeah, this didn't really rule out individuals who are active in the project at the moment
and also other technology cooperatives.
We're kind of just trying to like saddle through it somehow and be like, just work with us.
Let's figure it out together.
And this has been in progress for some time, the formalization of what this means.
And that's an open process which I would love to invite you to come check out.
The configuration commons.
This is a, so as I said before, we have open source apps that we can package them in images
and then we can specify a configuration around those images to describe how that app should
look like in a deployment on a server live and well, people using it.
And one of the things we noticed was that, as I said before, the configuration that was
being provided by the upstream repositories was useful, but it didn't specify the full
kind of end-to-end production kind of scenario.
And that's kind of a big word, but for example, how to back up the app data.
Like the thing is deployed, people are using it and we need to make sure their data is
safe, so we need to back it up.
How do we back the thing up?
How do we restore it?
This is kind of like a step from it works to it works and it's safe for these people
to use it.
And we wanted to encapsulate that into our configuration.
So this is a big part of it.
We'll go through each one of these deeper.
I'm just going to overview them now.
Yeah, Abra is a command line tool, so our own digital tools, we wanted to be involved
in how the tools are shaped and how we use them.
That's a great situation where you're dog-fooding your own system with your peers and you're
trying to figure out how does this best suit us.
And according to our own constraints, we can't spend all day learning this obscure system
or we can't invest too much time in some things.
So we need to cut corners and it's best to be involved directly in that process.
And if we remember back to Cloudron again, sorry, I'm not going to be bashing them at
all, but yeah, like how do we interact with the system?
In the case of Cloudron, it was a web front end.
But if we're talking about interacting with technology cooperatives and other tech collectives,
there's kind of a difference to begin with because Cloudron is maybe trying to provide
for the, say, let's say, non-technical user or someone who can just kind of get in, click
a few buttons or whatever.
But we're already dealing with groups that are actively deeply involved with Linux system
administration and so on.
So do we need a front end?
So those are the kind of questions we can ask and answer them ourselves in those moments.
And the collective infrastructure, so there's a lot that goes on in between getting an app
out and someone using it.
People have to meet each other and talk and who are you and what's going on and what do
you do and all this kind of stuff.
And then money, where does the money go?
What do you charge?
It's just this end to end, all the social processes that go in and around that.
We wanted to build those up too because that is a huge problem when you're starting off
as a collective and you're like, oh no, where's my bank account?
Like how do I get a bank account?
And you can see Open Collective, for example, doing this, just like mutualizing this financial
infrastructure and just getting people going.
So yeah, docs, Git hosting, getting off GitHub, that's cool, stuff like that.
So I'm going to go through these a bit deeper.
We're trying to form, so our proposal at the moment as autonomic, which is, yeah, now I
can say the sentence and I hope it's a bit clearer.
We initiated this project and we're deeply embedded inside it, but we're attempting to
step out of the project and reenter on an equal basis with other collectives.
So in order to do that, we're proposing a federation model, which is based on a great
project called Co-op Cycle, if you've heard about.
But basically different groups can interact with each other.
There will be democratic decision making and some laws and we'll come up with a constitution
together and all this kind of stuff.
I couldn't fit in on this line, but it's not just chaotic nerds.
It's also open to, we can imagine the people who are using the software grouping together
and joining our federation as well to say, hey, this button should be over there.
Could you just fix that?
But in a more collective sense, we could be gathering money, we could be figuring out
how to improve things.
You don't have to be able to just write software to join this kind of stuff.
We could be connecting the different struggles to build up a better open source ecosystem.
So this is a process that's going on right now.
There's invites going out.
We have a new round of private funding.
Thank you, Private Funders.
And yeah, there'll be more news.
But check the website if you're interested in this.
If you're also part of a collective, love to hear from you.
This is a massive problem that we, of course, experience as being six-admins.
And we've seen a lot of people join in on the old Matrix channels and that would be
one person setting up a few apps for friends, family, maybe their local community, a food
co-op, what have you.
And then a few months down the line, it's completely overwhelming.
The email broke, or it doesn't do this, or who knows what.
If you do any sys admin, you'll know the story.
But when you step into the Cloud project, you have this chance to meet your peers who
are also doing this work.
They may not be involved in your project whatsoever, but that's not important.
We have this idea of the config comments that means we can share work on the next Cloud
recipe.
That's what we call them.
We'll come to that in a bit.
So we can work together on the same configuration.
And that means we're sharing tips, tricks, we're talking together.
It's like, this group of users wants this.
Do you want that?
Oh, I tried this.
This kind of stuff.
This has been seen to be a great feature of trying to just open the door for people to
come in and work together.
Because there's a lot of tools that propose reuse and mind share and collective point
of reference, but don't really live up to that, the ideal of reuse.
Just not doing it again, repeating yourself.
So we were conscious of that.
We're trying to work on that.
Focus on training and collaboration.
So we wanted it to be easy to onboard.
We want more democratic tech collectors to pop up.
We want more technology cooperatives to be able to start.
We want people to be able to decide, I want to own and run my own workplace, and I want
to bootstrap some infrastructure for groups I find cool in my city.
And that's what Cloud is about.
It's like a tool set for these people.
It has to be easy to use, of course.
And we're very focused on that public.
So groups who have already decided that that's what they want to do.
They're on the terminal.
At the moment, we only have the terminal clients.
And they're getting into that.
We can't do everything for everyone, but we can definitely, with that public in mind,
we can be focused on how we attempt to make it accessible and usable.
And yes, cooperating with other networks.
So we want to, within our network, of course, we want to have groups join.
But for the groups that don't want to join, we still want to work with them.
If they have the same values, if they're doing similar things, we can also interface with
them.
And we've already seen that happening.
And I'll come back to that in a bit.
But once things are clear and they're getting clear, like we are a group of cooperatives,
we have this configuration commons, we have these tools, we're just specifying what we
are, then it's easier for other groups to say, OK, I understand what is happening here,
and I would like to do this with you.
So there's kind of like a concrete example, find funding together.
So yeah, the conflict commons, yes, the open source apps you love.
It's this catalog of software that is out there, and people are developing the next
cloud, the media wikis, the synapses, the GITI, the whole thing.
So we have quite an expanding conflict commons so that you can deploy a lot of apps.
So that's a thing.
People come to us and they're like, oh, I need a calendar, or I need a note taking app
or an app, or whatever.
And then we're out hunting in the open source ecosystem for apps to add to the catalog.
So that's that.
So to come back to this idea of the image is the app, which is the packaged thing, and
then the kind of wrapper around that, which specifies the end-to-end, kind of how they
should look in production.
And we were conscious to not reinvent a packaging format, and we didn't really know what to
do at that point because we thought, OK, we need to be able to say how, in one file, let's
say, in plain text, a config file, like, here's the app, and how do you back it up?
How do you restore it?
How do you take it down?
How do you bring it up?
How do you configure it?
How do you plug it?
This kind of stuff.
And as it turns out, the Docker Compose ecosystem and Docker has kind of been moving towards
the Compose standard they're calling it.
And it's basically, if you've ever seen the Docker Compose file, it's a YAML text file,
and it kind of just specifies what we're looking for.
So we just figured, great, upstream developers are already using this.
This is a developing open standard.
Great.
Let's just build on this.
And I think, as it turns out, that was a good choice and has had many benefits, which we'll
come to on the next slide.
Yeah.
So we're working with upstream developers, and yeah, we're...
So in my background, I've done a lot of configuration management tool, like, for example, working
with Ansible, which was always the grand ideal of reusing roles.
If anyone has used Ansible before, it's kind of like a packaging format for, you know,
you have a server and you want to install, like, Apache on it or something.
And you tell Ansible, install Apache for me.
And then you want to install a new thing.
And then you kind of package this into a role.
And at some point, I realized that everybody is writing the same roles.
It's very difficult to, like, share and to reuse other people's stuff.
It's definitely happening, but not on the scale that I was looking for.
And so I was looking for alternatives.
Yeah.
So in the project so far, we've seen people, like, we have, for example, Matrix Service
Synapse installs.
We've seen multiple collectives look at the config and say, this works for me.
I'm going to use this.
And then changing the config in collaboration with other groups.
So we're already seeing that people are able to make the changes that works for them without
breaking other people's installs.
And then when things need to be worked out, they speak to each other.
And things move along.
And again, the Compose standard really helps here in that it's quite flexible and helps
us.
People can move around each other inside the configuration, which will hopefully become
clear on the next slide.
Yes, great.
We are calling the app configuration a recipe, cooking inspired, and it's a key repository.
Here you have Git.
Git.
The main cause of this format is that if you've ever used, I think it's a Docker, I think it
was a Docker Compose command line client.
You can kind of chain the Compose files.
So you can say like Docker Compose up, Compose.yaml minus F, Compose.some-other-thing.yaml.
And the system will internally merge all of these configurations together and then roll
out the app, which I never had occasion to use until I realized that maybe somebody wants
to use Postgres and maybe someone wants to use MariaDB.
These simple choices for deployments, if it's not possible to kind of like make this easy
to do between different groups, it would never work out.
So very, very thankful to the people who wrote this standard.
So you can see here, you can kind of, and it'll become clear when we talk about the
command line client, you can kind of specify, okay, I want MariaDB and I want the SMTP config
bundle all together, roll it out.
And I don't want Postgres or I don't want this or I don't want that.
And this allows people to just expand the config to suit their needs, document it, let
people know this is a new feature.
So it's quite nice.
You can be just hosting some software and then somebody says, oh, great, OpenID Connect
now works with this, just load this thing in.
And, you know, this is really helping us move forward and get things done.
Yeah, at the moment, we have a command line client called Abra.
And this is the kind of day-to-day interface for how you manage your call cloud installs.
So you have a server, you deploy stuff to the server, you're using Abra on the command
line.
That was a real, that was a large decision for us at the time because we didn't have
much money.
We didn't know if we would be able to pull off a web front end.
And again, as I mentioned before, we were trying to target specifically, like, who is
the public of this project?
Are they people who know and are comfortable on the command line?
Yes.
Okay, let's just go ahead with this and try to make it work.
So we wrote in Bash, the first one, and I still completely recommend it.
Just unleash your inner Unix.
It was great.
It managed to get us to, you know, zero to hero in relatively short amount of time and
have a system that was working.
One of the kind of core ideas behind developing our own tools, we were very conscious that
we might fail.
We wouldn't be able to get it done.
And we wanted to have that, the conflict commons would kind of live separately.
So these would be kind of not interdependent in a way that if one broke, the other would
break.
So if you even today, if you just ignore that, you can still drop into the command line,
run a bunch of commands and roll out the app, which is great.
And that's kind of how we originally conceded with the Bash system.
We were just running a bunch of commands and we had kind of laid it all out in a way that
kind of said, okay, you can just push that out.
So yeah, thanks to Kalex, a fellow worker who's great at Bash programming.
We wouldn't have done it without them.
Yes.
So then we rewrote and go.
We actually managed to get some funding, which we'll come to after.
I guess they're not Bash programmers, if they read the source.
They might have felt otherwise.
But at that point, we were running into issues with the Bash implementation, which we felt
quite proud about, that we had gone ahead and found the limits of the simplest possible
thing that we could do.
And the issues were it was difficult to install on multiple systems.
It relied on a number of built-in commands that were not always available on, you know,
like a Fedora, Debian or whatever.
So yeah, portability.
We were struggling with, we wanted to kind of develop other aspects of, like we wanted
the tools to be able to speak to the config commons, but not directly parse each other.
And that ended up being a kind of like JSON catalog.
But then parsing data formats in Bash is difficult, so we were kind of pulling our hair out on
that one.
And then concurrency.
We were struggling to manage horizontal scaling.
So if you work with 18 groups, they want to have their own VPSs.
If you have 10 servers, you know, the tool has to, like, fire a request at each 10 of
them or whatever.
And then if it's going through each one at a time, you have to wait.
And as a result of kind of scaling up and using this absolutely pre-alpha software and
autonomic for production purposes, we reached the limits of the software.
So we ended up rewriting it in Go.
Somebody knew Go in autonomic at the time.
That's the reason.
But also we saw that it was really, you know, we could get this concurrency issue sorted
and the portability.
So Go kind of gives you a language-level feature that's quite easy to say, like, fire a request
at these 10 things immediately.
And you can build a binary, so you can just fire them out.
So people just get, like, a binary in the system, and this stuff is all baked into it.
So the new problem with this is that it actually works.
It does what it says, and people are starting to use it.
So we're now into this kind of maintenance cycle.
It's kind of approach.
We've done the public beta, so people are using it and starting to rely on it.
And we've seen people hacking on it and submitting pull requests and checking it out.
It's all good.
Yeah, so in essence, Abra is a Docker swarm client.
So no, we don't run Kubernetes.
We run Docker swarm.
And no, it's not dead.
Docker swarm is a technology that is still alive.
We have, like, a strange, pyrocynical relationship with, like, some installs.
Like some banks have, like, a swarm install of, like, you know, 10,000 nodes or something.
And the current owner, I believe it's Marantis or something that's been in exchange of who
owns it or who, yeah, I can't remember.
But it's still being maintained, and we're happy to see that it is being maintained.
Because we identify that swarm mode in Docker is kind of the appropriate feature set that
we need without having to deal with going into learning how to, you know, roll out a
large system which is built for, like, large scale.
Our, you know, and again, this is, like, what was Autonomic doing at the time was, like,
rolling out single servers, deploying a few apps, no greater than, like, 10 to 30, 50,
100 users or whatever.
And swarm mode provides you with the ability to kind of roll out the app, and if it fails,
it will roll it back for you.
And we can bake that into our config.
So we were kind of getting the stability guarantees that we needed.
And not a lot of groups were demanding, you know, when they had, like, a media wiki installed,
they weren't saying there must be 99% uptime in this contract or whatever.
But we still wanted to push that to the limit, like, a high quality, stable service when
we're rolling stuff out.
This should be, yeah.
And then, yeah, this swarm mode just covers that for us, the runtime, the container runtime.
Yeah, this is kind of like the Abra architecture, let's say.
So on the left, you will install Abra, for example, on your local workstation, the command
line tool, and then you'll, via SSH, kind of tell Abra to manage this server.
So it'll read the SSH config and it'll connect to the server and say, okay, I recognize this
server, I see there's a Docker daemon running on this and it's got swarm mode enabled.
Cool.
And then it can, you know, you can do this horizontal scaling where you can have several
servers.
You can load multiple servers into Abra and then you can be sharing the Abra state between
multiple people.
So in a co-op of 13 people, you know, each one who runs Abra, appLS, or whatever, to
list the apps and the servers, we'll see the same state come out.
And we can go into that a bit later.
So yeah, it's built for basically collaboration in the organization that you're in.
And then the other mode is you install Abra directly on the server and it stores the state
on the server, which could be useful if you're, yeah, for specific scenarios, this was requested.
Yeah, some people run this.
I don't myself.
Yeah, and then the final points.
Moving on.
Collective infrastructure.
Yeah, docs, Git hosting, recipes.cloud.tech here.
You can see the list of all the apps we have.
We have an open collective, which is the fiscal host is autonomic.
Bank account in the UK.
And that's been nice because we've been able to, once we got the funding, we were able
to tell people, if you work on this, we can pay you just immediately.
Anything you do, you'll get paid.
And that's great because we know there's a lot of unpaid labor going on in open source
world.
So we didn't want to be a project that said, contribute to our commons and get nothing
back.
No, we could actually pay.
So we set an hourly wage there and we said, this is how much money we have and away you
go.
That worked out great, I would say.
And the server firm, Server Co-op.
So I wanted to plug this other project.
You can go to the website, servers.coop.
Yeah, we've been working with a group who have been developing software called Capsule,
Siberia, great hackers.
And they're trying to develop a system.
Well, they have developed a system, which is basically a server provider infrastructure
like Hetzner, for example.
So VPSs.
I need a server to roll one out.
I need another server to roll one out.
And then we, and a couple of other people, myself included, were thinking, okay, this
is great because a lot of collectors are centralizing on server, Hetzner VPSs, right?
And if Hetzner rolls up the price or, you know, we've already seen this with the increase
in cost in IPv4 addresses and the 10% increase this year.
It's getting more costly to run on Hetzner, but it's always been super cheap and that's
been super accessible.
But it could change.
So what do we do?
We need to build up this aspect of our stack.
So we kind of like expand the cooperative layer down to the servers.
And that is the idea behind server's co-op.
And Abra already supports an integration.
So you can do like server new.
And if you've got Capsule running on your server, it'll spin up a VM.
So we were already trying to like, you know, just take a turn into cooperatively managed
infrastructure and build those integrations from the start.
Whether or not they're working that great is for me to be seen.
But yes, so European Cultural Foundation gave us upwards of 30 grand in funding last year
and the year before for in the context of the Culture of Solidarity Fund.
That was amazing.
Thanks to them.
They were really great.
And I would recommend applying to them.
They support us the whole way through.
It was.
Yeah.
It was just fantastic.
We wrote our application and sent it into them.
So pretty happy with that one.
Great.
Nearly done.
Yeah.
I want to just jump.
So this is in paperwork.
Again, I want to plug like, I just find it so important to explain that people are actually
using this and this isn't just like some idea in our heads and we think it's cool.
It's like people are actually running, you know, they rely on some of the things that
have been deployed.
The London Black Space is a project which is about like 13 apps, I think, on a server
somewhere, which was initiated by an artist collective called Ron Grupa, which is like
an Indonesian based collective in the context of Documenta.
And they wanted to kind of approach a group that connected with their values.
At some point they were so they were invited to Documenta to do the work and they thought,
okay, we're all the way over here.
In Indonesia, we need to work with people who are based in Europe, so we're going to
need digital tools, but we don't want to be immediately going on the Google drives of
the world.
So how do we build up, you know, extend our ways of working and our values into the digital
realm?
So then they came looking for collectives and co-ops.
Fran put us through to them.
Yeah, and here's just some photos of us just engaging in this massively multiplayer shared
infrastructure project.
So it was really great.
People from my perspective understood what Co-op Cloud was and the mission behind it
and felt invited to kind of look at the technology and what we were doing and comment on that
and give us critique.
You know, we're often in a space where people want to talk about digital tools, but the
first thing they say is, oh, I don't know anything about technology, which is kind of
like a hallmark.
You have to like excuse yourself or something.
But we got past that in working with this group of people that may not find themselves
technical.
But as we moved on, again, Co-op Cloud allowed us to just kind of like deploy the tech and
just like just forget about it and then go on with the support work.
And we ended up with like the last great thing I saw from this project was the people involved
in using the tools were publishing videos about how to use the tools in the stacks.
So they were like in the matrix chat and on the peer tube publishing.
Here's how you use peer tube.
Amazing.
Great educational practice.
Totally check it out.
TV.Lum
Among Us Space is the website.
This was another project we met kind of in the context of the documentary.
So this is a comic illustrator's union, which is bootstrapping at the moment.
And they felt, you know, they saw Lum Among Us Space and they were like, this looks cool.
And I like the idea of what is going on.
I understand what is happening here.
There are two groups cooperating here, this kind of like cultural based initiative and
this technology collective.
And you know, I can see the Co-op Cloud website and this looks like we want to check this
out.
So we kind of got over that fear and anxiety and moved through the money exchange and,
you know, let's work together.
It was quite smooth.
So I would say Co-op Cloud is then helping us just again, put these things to rest.
Like this is the project we're based on, you know, when we work, when we deploy your infrastructure,
it will be contributing to the commons, copy left, democratically managed.
You know, you kind of just get over the hump.
And yeah, Kotec is a new co-op, which is starting in Poland.
And that was a major boost.
So they've deployed a bunch of services.
Some members are in the room.
Super nice.
Yeah, it's a software stack which is in its, you know, initiated and developed by Co-operative.
So it should suit other cooperatives to food strap.
And of course, if you want to start a new technology cooperative, how do you start?
It's overwhelming.
But now you've got this off the shelf project and it's like, get going.
And once you enter it, you just see all the other collectives and you're like, great,
we can learn, we can share, you know.
And again, it expands beyond the technical.
So we have the infrastructure for payment and bank accounts and all this stuff.
So people can really get moving fast, I think, is good.
And we want to expand the, you know, we want people to start technology cooperatives, start
technology cooperatives.
Yes, Enterprise Metrics, 21 collectives.
Somebody counted them.
Maybe it was me at some point.
But there's a lot of groups involved in this.
If you go on the website, it's in the blog post, a list of them.
We've got 160 plus recipes.
This is a lot of open source apps.
You could probably find what you need in there.
And yeah, we're running 146 apps.
I think I ran Abra app LS at some points.
So Autonaut because heavily invested in this.
And there are other collectives which are running the stack.
Yeah, and maybe just kind of coming to the end.
It's been a lot of details.
I'm even overwhelmed myself.
The last few slides, kind of philosophy take, you know, we wanted to be another project
in the ecosystem and not just become the project in relation to decentralization, let's say.
We really posit ourselves against this big tech discourse and what's happening.
And we thought we could contribute to internet and digital infrastructure decentralization
by proposing Cloud in its format.
And we're only one project.
So I thought it would be good to plug some other great projects which I just find super
inspiring.
And I would say Uno host is maybe one of the gold standards of community organized infrastructure
hosting.
It has a different kind of set of priorities and goals.
Everyone can be a system administrator.
It's kind of their goal.
Let's make information available to people.
Anyone can do this.
Get going.
Brilliant project.
Whereas we're going for specific groups, co-ops.
You're already in the game.
How can we make it easier to keep going?
So it's a bit of the different layers.
But I absolutely recommend Uno host.
Nubo is based in Brussels.
Check them out.
Chateau's great network.
Co-tech is a network of cooperatives based in the UK.
I think it's like 35 cooperatives.
Check them out if you're looking for a job.
Get stuck in.
Social co-op trying to build cooperatively managed mass-on-instances.
MIT, great collective already involved in co-op cloud at the moment.
Small technology foundation.
Always find this worrying.
Check that out.
Just plug in them.
Yeah.
Oh, five minutes.
Cool.
The roadmap is, as I said, building the federation.
So now is a great time to join.
As an individual, a collective co-op, please get involved if you want to.
We're trying to find more money, of course.
One of the goals of the federation is to achieve financial sustainability.
So the co-ops that join or the groups that join the project will be...
We're going to have to decide, all right, how do we fund development of the tool?
And can we pay for hours around finance, admin, triage, all this stuff?
Yeah, Kadabra is a kind of new effort to kind of have a server-side component which is...
And this is the thing that Cloud Run did amazingly well, which is just auto-updating the apps.
So we're trying to replicate that in terms of the server-side component, which understands,
you know, oh, someone who takes care of that recipe has uploaded a new version.
I'm going to roll it out.
And yeah, web interface.
I forgot to add maybe because it's still under discussion if we need that or not.
Yes, getting to the end.
I could do a demo, a chaos demo.
Your demo or questions?
Yeah, we have five minutes.
Yeah, okay.
Maybe I'll just do a chaos demo.
So I wanted to, like, run...
Yes.
Just show you the command line client.
So, again, to contextualize, this is the tool that people who maintain the service will
be running on a daily basis.
So it's supposed to make the job easy.
And I won't go through all of that at the moment, but, you know, it's...
You know, we try to take effort to, like, explain the concepts that are involved in
the project and what you can do.
You know, you can list all the recipes that are available from the command line, for example.
And yeah, you can also do operations on recipes here.
So you can, like, attempt to upgrade...
Oh, I probably don't have internet.
Yeah, right.
Okay, well, anyway, you can kind of, like, do the maintenance commands on the spot.
So again, you're on your local workstation.
You realize that there's a new version of Next Cloud is coming out.
Okay, let's get that upgraded.
And then you can run the commands here.
And that'll basically operate on this directory, Abba recipes, where you can see a selection
of the apps.
And then, you know, this is just the...
What I showed earlier, the recipe repository.
So this is the configuration that specifies how to deploy this app.
Yeah, and there's some other details that I didn't really go into.
But basically, one of the nice things that we've wired up is that if you deploy this
app called Trafic, that when you roll out Next Cloud, it automatically configures the
lesson-crypt stuff.
So you just don't have to deal with this HTTPS issue.
It's already in the config.
You just say, give me a thing.
Yeah, I don't know.
Is there much more?
Oh, yeah, I guess, yeah.
And then there's just kind of this, like, command and control interface where you can see, like,
okay, what apps have I got on what servers and, you know, what do I need to do?
And you can kind of, like, you know, filter it by server or whatever.
I won't type it out now.
But yeah, maybe I'll call it a day.
Thank you for listening to me talk for so long.