Okay, so thank you very much for attending this talk and obviously thank you for the
organizers of the bedroom for accepting the proposal.
So that's my name and coming from Open Nebula Systems.
My idea today, I'm coming here not as a competitor of OpenStack, I'm coming here to talk to you
about the work we're doing at the European level along with other European companies
to align the geo-strategic interests of the European Union with what we are actually doing
at the open source sector in Europe.
So that's my email and you want to just follow up with any questions after the session today.
As I mentioned, apart from being at the part of Open Nebula Systems, I'm also part of the
European Alliance for Industrial Data, ETS and Cloud, which is an initiative I'll explain
later today or later now, run by the European Commission and also part of another initiative
we call sovereign heads, which I'll explain also in a few minutes time.
Okay, so just to bring you some ideas, I'm sure most of you are already familiar with
some of the concepts and the strategy, let's say, behind what we're doing right now at
the European level.
You've mentioned before and you're perfectly aware of the fact that the cloud market in
Europe is, I wouldn't say broken, but it's not balanced at least, let's say.
So these are just some figures of the growth of the cloud market in Europe in recent years
and how the share of European cloud providers has evolved over time.
So what we basically see is that the market is growing enormously, but the share of the
European cloud providers is actually declining.
So all of that business and all that value has been generated by also through the pandemic
to cloud computing, that is mostly benefiting hyperscalers.
So also you're perfectly aware of this.
So we are now witnessing this kind of change of paradigm, so we are moving away from the
cloud centralized model to a more decentralized approach, this shift of paradigm between cloud
computing and edge computing, and that most of you I'm sure you're aware of.
And we all know it comes with a number of benefits.
We're talking about deployment of applications, ultra low latency applications, improving
user experience, think about sectors like online gaming or healthcare.
I mean there are a number of functional advantages to this, but from a European perspective there's
also a key element in moving away from cloud computing, a centralized cloud computing model
dominated by hyperscalers to a decentralized edge computing model in which other companies
have a say.
And that is to also foster here in Europe a new ecosystem of infrastructure providers
that can bring some balance to that market.
So we are assuming that the cloud market is dominated by hyperscalers, non-EU companies,
that's honestly unlikely to change.
What we can do is leverage this shift, this new paradigm of edge computing where we know
there are going to be a number of demands for this new infrastructure that doesn't exist
yet, or this technology that doesn't exist yet, to bring some balance to that market
and allow a smaller companies in Europe, for instance, to build their own infrastructure
offering, bring that to the public with these new platforms, new technologies, hopefully
based on open source, as I will explain in a second, and bring some balance to a market
that's now heavily, heavily unbalanced.
And to the point that we all agree and also the commission that we call it a market failure.
So it is so complicated, so unbalanced, that now it's very difficult for a new company
to get into this market and actually survive against these big players.
Okay.
This is especially relevant in Europe because we have a powerful tool here, which is the
telecom sector.
And as I explained in a second, many of the initiatives that are taking place now in Europe,
they rely or they hope that the telecom sector in Europe will come together and will help
to build this alternative edge infrastructure that will be able to bring and offer an alternative
to hyperscalers.
We need to get the telecosm involved and that also means we have to fight sometimes from
the open source perspective, but in general for this new change of paradigm, we have to
fight against the temptation in some companies in Europe to align their priorities or get
some agreements with hyperscalers to speed up the deployment of edge infrastructure in
the market.
But we all agree that this might come with some risks in the midterm.
I think we all agree on that.
So I'm going to explain today what we are doing at the European Alliance for Industrial
Data Edge and Cloud and other initiatives that we're moving on promoting from the European
open source sector.
The main challenge here, if you think about what the future is going to be or what kind
of challenges we're going to have in the future, in the near future, I mean, there are obviously
there are many technical challenges and political challenges as well.
A basic one, which we still don't have an answer for that is how we're going to manage
if by the end of the decade we have, we actually have tens of thousands of edge nodes across
the continent, how on earth we're going to manage all that infrastructure.
How are we going to manage thousands of edge nodes with different architectures from different
brands from all of those managed by hundreds potentially, potentially hundreds of different
infrastructure providers.
That's the whole idea.
So how we bring all this new emerging infrastructure together, how we build the tools for a user,
for a customer to actually leverage all this new infrastructure that's still to come and
how to make that in a way that doesn't bring us against a new scenario of vendor locking.
So how can we make sure that all these workloads can move freely from one place to another,
we automate all these deployments, how to make this really easy for people to actually
use this thousands of edge nodes that will be available in the market here in Europe,
hopefully in a few years time.
So that's a very specific technical challenge that we have to solve right now.
And we have to decide how we fix that and whether we want to fix that as Europeans or
we want to again rely on non-European organizations and companies to do this for us, which is
very comfortable.
But then at some point we realize we don't have the skills in Europe to take over these
projects if something happens.
So I talk about the alignment.
So there is a gravel alignment and sometimes quite explicit from what the kind of the signals
we get from the commission in this case and what the industry as a whole in Europe is
doing but specifically the European open source technology providers.
So there are some very clear declarations from top EU figures about the need to achieve
this kind of technological sovereignty in some way or another, trying to coexist with
hyper scalers but hopefully creating some alternative scenario for Europe.
Happily there are also quite explicit declarations on the role that open source is expected to
play in all this and there is a commitment to do this and I'm happy to say that the discussions
we have within the alliance define these technology priorities and these coinvestment priorities,
they are quite well aligned with the fact that these technologies have to be open source
and open source is the way to mobilize this collaboration between different companies
in Europe.
Obviously that doesn't mean proprietary software is not going to be there because it has to
be there and it's the base of some business models out there but open source is going
to play a key role in all this.
Again we see this aligned with what we've read from the commission through a number
of documents that I'm sure you're familiar with and also with declarations from people
like Commissioner Tereviathan.
As I mentioned before one of the practical challenges is how we believe what the digital
decade strategy says will have by the end of this decade thousands of etanotes across
Europe how are we going to manage this infrastructure.
What's the technology that's going to allow new infrastructure providers to offer this
to their customers so that technology doesn't necessarily exist right now.
That technology in any case we think should be European if we want to extend this concept
of sovereignty down to the technology stack not just leave that at the data level or at
the cloud provider level.
We see also in the reviewed industrial strategy from the commission that the role that edge
computing is expected to play in this and all this and this data processing that's moving
away gradually quite rapidly sometimes from the from a centralized cloud to the edge.
We're going to use that actually bring some balance to the market so make sure that European
companies have something to say in that and it's not and the model doesn't replicate again
the kind of oligopoly structure we have in the cloud market.
So that's the role of edge computing and that's also increasingly the role that open source
is perceived or expected to play in bringing different companies together to build this
in the long term and maintain the whole thing running because obviously we can release same
things but we need a long term commitment from the European industry not just to consume
technologies but also system integrators as well not just to consume technologies and
sell them and resell them but also maintain them in the long term.
That's one of the main challenges we'll have.
So the European alliance for industrial data edge and cloud that's one of the steps one
of the one of the initiatives that the Commission has put in place in which the European industry
is playing a leading role here.
So it comes back from the from a declaration from member states the commitment to support
these new technologies cloud edge technologies.
If you read the this original declaration which they committed to expand spending all
this transformation around 10 billion euros I don't think we'll get that much but it's
as I explained later is that it is a quite decent amount of money in both in all this
but we see in this even in this declaration there are already some references to at least
something that sounds a bit like open source something so open source standards whatever
that is but it's still it's good to see it's it's in there somehow.
So the alliance was born in 2021 there was an initial publication of an industrial technology
roadmap from a number of European companies at the CEO level.
It was then launched at the end of 2021 by Commissioner Keirah-Ree Britton and I'm happy
to say that by the end of February probably will be in good condition to publish the updated
version of this technology roadmap with all the technology priorities that have been identified
and deployment priorities that have been identified in Europe from the industry perspective but
also in alignment with the division of the of the European Commission.
The alliance brings companies private companies European only European companies member states
and then also a number of experts are involved in this and in this discussions we had our
first physical General Assembly here in Brussels in early December it was quite successful.
The ideas again as I mentioned align and then identify this investment needs these priorities
how to bring together the expectations and the needs and the potential of the industry
in Europe with what the Commission is actually expecting or they vision what Europe needs
in coming years and these challenges.
Right now there are three working groups one for them one of them is for the four member
states this is mainly people involved in discussions on procurement so they're looking at how to
from that procurement perspective help European companies and cloud providers in the daily
business with the administration in different countries.
The main question we get from them is should we restrict contracts to European to only
European companies and then it's very tempting to say yes but personally I will say well
you take the decision I mean I'm not I mean as a company just that's something for you
to decide obviously that will benefit us but I mean discussions are more complex but that's
one of the that's one of the topics that keeps coming up many times.
And then there are two working groups for industry one of them is the cloud edge working
group that we from open ever we we chair along with another two companies with CapGemini
and SAP and then there's a specific working group for the for everything that has to do
with cloud for defense and aeronautics sector which I'm happy to say some of you were earlier
this morning in this debate I had with the Gail from Eclipse foundation it was a striking
for me personally to see all these people coming from the defense industry saying that
they they want to use open source so the debates and the internal debates is not about proprietary
source open source code or open source they want to use open source it doesn't need help
to make sure that they can use open source under the very specific restrictions that
they have in this sector so I think that's a good news for for everyone.
So the alliance that not all the logos here because it's an old version but as you see
some of the main actors in the European industry as a whole not just technology providers but
people from from other sectors as well contributing to this cloud providers as well there was
as I mentioned the first version of this document released in 2021 and we'll have that released
in probably end of February so one of the ideas is also for those of you are familiar
with all the different programs that the Commission has have has in place things like Horizon
Europe or Digital Europe or SEV to to make sure that from from industry we feed the Commission
with what's actually the challenges and the needs we have in terms of advancing all these
technologies for cloud and edge and to make sure that the new calls and the new actions
under these programs are aligned with what we actually from the industry identify so
it's like given a quick channel to give feedback to the Commission to what this this this topics
could could be in terms of helping us also advance that.
So that is that's the structure of the of the Alliance I'm also here for to invite all
of you if you come from a European company and you are I mean your business is relevant
to cloud and I guess that's why you're here right now.
There's an open process to join it goes through the through the European Commission you can
join the Alliance you can join the different working groups and participate maybe it's
a bit not too late for the for this new version but there will be new versions and new working
groups through the rest of the of the year and it's a long term commitment from this
companies to participate in this.
So that's from the what the European Commission side has to do in the meantime from the more
specific from the open source from the European open source industry where we've also been
working in in having some more cooperation and collaboration among ourselves.
In 2021 we launched kind of an informal initiative or community you could call we call sovereign
edge it's about bringing together European open source technology providers that have
some they develop some technologies or we develop some technologies in Europe that are
relevant for for edge computing and this this change of paradigm and we think it makes sense
to get closer to each other and get to know each other a bit better and integrations and
all that and going together to to some of these projects that will be coming up in the
near future.
So we've started with an informal community of European open source companies we produce
software and we already have some level of integration among ourselves the objective
is at some point to offer an alternative stack of European open source technologies for public
administrations and companies and systems system integrators also with making sure we
have connections with all the European relevant European cloud providers to offer at least
an alternative that goes beyond data and cloud it also covers the technology that sustains
all this.
We launched this as I mentioned in 2021 informally in 20 at the end of 2021 I'm quite proud of
this we didn't get this money but I'm quite proud of this because this was the first time
the European open source industry came together to apply a submit a horizon Europe project
to the Commission we didn't get this money but it was it was a very nice experience to
try to bring people who have never ever considered to to to go into to get into into a research
and innovation project a European project coming together and preparing this proposal
which as you know is a lot of lot of work.
Happily we got it the second time so this is the COVNIC project it has started now in
January we from up and able to coordinate this project with a number of other organizations
involved it's going to be running for three years and I'm happy to say this is the actual
implementation of this this initial collaboration between open source European open source providers
and their research and innovation ecosystem in Europe to produce some some technology
together and respond to some of the these calls from the horizon Europe program.
And finally just to finish a very quick introduction to another initiative just that's now ongoing
which is the import let me see if I get this right important project of common European
interest for next generation cloud infrastructure and services.
Okay so it's it's I says for friends we've been preparing this for what a couple of years
or so this this is this goes to the next generation funding it's led by Germany and France with
heavy support from the Commission and well in total it's 12 member states are going to
mobilize funding from the Commission I mean from European funding through the national
budgets state aid school to to set up this huge project for the for cloud that's continuum
and at different levels we have I cannot disclose in the companies the specific companies but
it's it's European industry telecommunication companies software developers coming together
to cloud providers coming together to build a whole stack of the technologies and the
advanced services we need for infrastructure applications on data so it's really exciting.
It will cover a number of challenges that we went into the details here but it was we
have it will be available on the on these slides but yeah things big topics like interoperability
portability I mean meta orchestration across different providers avoiding vendor blocking
and managing all this huge heterogeneous edge infrastructure that we expect to be in Europe
in the coming years this is going to run we pass all the tests and all the questions from
the from Digicompetition and the rest of the Commission it will start hopefully this year
or the second semester so we've been running for five years and yeah that's my personal opinion
but I think the components that we are we're building or will be building in this project
they have the potential to actually come you'll see even when this is published the equivalent
to the semiconductor or the hydrogen upside project that already approved but I think that
these the open source I will be producing here hopefully will have the potential to become the
probably largest open source project in Europe in the coming years so stay tough to stay stay
in touch because that will need help and also an invitation for you to follow the this new
project that we are we are starting now under the horizon Europe program thank you