So, hello and welcome to FOSDEM 2023 and I hope everyone is awake and looking forward
to two days packed with lots of talks, at least I am.
And we, that's Kristi, Torsten and me, we are the organizers or deaf room managers for
this room.
So, if you have any questions, you can approach us.
We are here to guide through the day.
And we are also the ones who submitted the idea of the sovereign cloud deaf room to the
FOSDEM.
And we did that because, well, with our day work, we actually work in that space.
So, Torsten is from the operate first project by Red Hat.
I work on the sovereign cloud stack, which is also a project that is centered with a
focus on sovereign cloud infrastructure and standards.
And of course, as we work with it on a day-to-day base, we think it's an important topic.
And also, the term, digital sovereignty is often a term that is used a lot lately and
it actually needs proper definition and it also, there needs to be a discussion about
it, what it actually means and what is needed in order to work towards sovereign infrastructure.
And that, if you looked at the talks that are happening today in this room, that will
be what will be discussed a lot.
And yeah, I'm not, I don't really have much more to add to that.
Torsten, do you want to?
Okay, yeah.
So, I'm working with Red Hat and I'm in the project operate first, which is the idea of
open operations.
You can see the stickers here and if you want to pick them up.
The idea there is that we offer more or less free service, I mean free service by where
you can open up your own Kubernetes clusters, you can deploy your project there and you
have also a kind of open SRE there because you can see the different infrastructure data.
And so that's the basic idea of open operations.
And with open operations, you get the chance to be sovereign with your data because it's
easy to move, it's easy to see, and we are totally hybrid so it doesn't matter if it's
on your own premise or in whatever cloud or you're switching in between.
So, operate first is kind of the idea, one of the proof of concept that the idea of sovereign
cloud can work in a practical idea.
Hi, I'm Krista Nicola.
I'm a software engineer with Boston University.
I work on the MOC Alliance project out of Boston University whose goal is to create
an open cloud for academia but not only.
I also work on OpenStack.
I am on the OpenStack technical committee and I am a maintainer of the OpenStack Keystone
project which is for identity management.
I also work on varying degrees on operate first with Thorsten on open infra labs and
on various acronym rich things like NERC, NSE, et cetera.
And working on OpenSource and having worked on deploying and maintaining open clouds,
the topic of sovereign clouds is very important to me and I see it as the next step in not
just opening up the telemetry and how you're deploying it and how you're running it but
also opening up the governance and all of those other aspects to actually create a place
where everyone can contribute to on all aspects of the cloud and not just take what you're
doing and apply it to a different degree.
So with that, Thorsten already had a first highlight for me because I did not know that
you are the PTL for Keystone.
So that's really useful for me to know because we just submitted patches to Keystone for
federated authentication and so we should really talk a lot more.
So with that, the first one who will talk will be my colleague Max and he will prepare
and then we will give a proper introduction to Max and start with that in 10 minutes,
right?
Yeah, 10 minutes, right.
Okay.
So feel free, here's some candy, some chocolate if you want to.
There are stickers there and yeah, enjoy the day, right?