If you can hear me at the back, coming through the sound, can you?
Okay, it's, I think, it sounds like you can hear me at the back.
Excellent, alright.
Okay, well, it turns out I'm a little bit early, but I'm going to use those two minutes
for questions at the end of the talk if possible.
Alright folks, welcome to Responsible Clouds and the Green Web Triangle.
How to make the climate place for a diverse cloud ecosystem.
I work for the greenwebfoundation.org and the URL for that non-profit is written across
the bottom of this screen as you can see.
In case you can't see me, that's my face.
This is a bit of a hangover from when you're doing remote talks because, yeah, it's weird
being in a room with other people again.
I have a background working in wacky environmental climate tech startups like, as you can see,
Loco2, which is a triple layer pun around locomotion, low carbon and like going to local
on a crazy holiday.
I also work at a company called AMI, which stands for Avoid Mass Extinction Engine.
We burn through something in the region of 20 million US dollars of VC money trying to
put a carbon footprint API on anything we could find.
These days, I work at the greenwebfoundation where we track the transition of the internet
away from fossil fuels to something greener.
I also work with the green software foundation, which is a large industry body where I'm the
policy chair there.
I also run a podcast, a co-host of podcasts called Environment Variables, get it?
Which is all about green software.
I also am a contributing editor to a magazine called Branch Magazine, which is all about
the stuff, this kind of intersection between climate and tech.
This is what we're going to cover today.
I'm going to frame a kind of problem that you might think about when it comes to sovereign
tech, sovereign cloud and sustainability.
I'm going to talk a little bit about the drivers for sustainability at a regulatory level that
happen in Europe specifically.
Then I'm going to talk about the idea of competing on transparency as a basis for a more diverse
cloud ecosystem.
Off we go, framing the cloud, framing the problem with the green web triangle.
Most of you know that we basically build services by compiling them these days of lots of different
processes.
It's a bit like a kind of graph where things people see at the top is actually comprised
of all these things that we might build all the way through that.
When you're trying to actually use a service, you kind of end up with this kind of problem.
If you want to make a service available to other people, or if you want to use a service,
there are kind of like three things you want, in my opinion.
You want something to be convenient, ideally hosted by someone else a lot of the time,
or at least so you don't have to be doing it all yourself if you're a kind of medium
to small size company.
You probably want it to be fossil free because there's a whole kind of climate emergency
thing going on.
Ideally you'd like it to be kind of diverse, so you're not dependent on only one provider
who can jack up their prices or do all kinds of things that bad things happen when you're
only relying on one provider.
You basically have, I think there are different failure modes when you think about this triangle
because most of the time you can only pick two.
So for example, let's say you wanted to go for convenient and diverse.
This is like the common thing that a lot of us kind of default to.
It's basically the default, it's fossil fuel powered.
It's a bit like being in a spaceship that you know is on fire and then you go to work
and you type in a keyboard and you know things are on fire.
Then you go home and you realize things are on fire.
Then you feel kind of a little bit anxious, unlike people call that climate anxiety.
That's one of the things that some of you might feel when you think about this.
On a kind of global scale, there's an issue there.
So that's the thing that we probably are in right now that we don't want to do all the
time.
The other one is diverse and fossil free.
Maybe you do care about this and you're going to look for, say, green providers, but you
also care about having diverse ecosystems and building everything yourself.
This is cool, but it kind of has another failure mode in that you spend loads and loads of
time on undifferentiated heavy lifting, which isn't necessarily creating the kind of value
that you're basically employed for a lot of the time.
Or alternatively, you can go for convenient and fossil free because lots and lots of large
companies now, like say Microsoft and Amazon and Google, are telling a really, really loud
story about how much they're really kind of running on green energy and doing a load for
the climate.
Now there are kind of all kinds of problems, which I'm in a sovereign cloud dev room where
I don't need to kind of talk too much about.
But there is also issues because these folks tend to be the people who are often the market
leaders in helping people get oil and gas out of the ground and burn it.
So even if you're running on, say, green software, like they may be doing things which you might
not be aligned with as an organization or you might feel somewhat uncomfortable about.
So these are the three ways.
This is the triangle and these are the kind of common failure modes that I think that
are useful to talk to other people about and how I explain the problem with basically sustainable
digital diverse services to people who want to actually make a switch and start using
something which is not necessarily a number of really large providers but don't understand
why you can't just move to like next cloud for everything.
So that's like the problem, that's the triangle.
Now let's talk about the drivers for sustainability in tech at regulatory level that might kind
of help for some of this.
So this graph is from Dr. Robert Rode from Berkeley Earth, which is an environmental
data science nonprofit and they're using data from the Global Carbon Project.
And what you can see is historically, like we've been growing in emissions however long,
and you can see this trajectory which people might refer to as business as usual.
There's lots of different scenarios and it's actually titled SSP2.
There's a bunch of these.
Then you see the kind of changes we would need to actually make to get down to like
1.5 degrees of global warming, which is considered like the least worst option that you'll typically
see a lot of the time.
And this is, you might have heard like 1.5 versus or 2 degrees for example.
Like in 2015, pretty much every country on earth agreed that we should probably do something
about climate and we should go for not more than 2 degrees of warming.
And then they actually, you had a bunch of people say well actually 2 degrees is still
pretty bad and then we did a bunch of research and found out that yes, 1.5 is what we should
be thinking about naturally.
And despite that, we've actually had people thinking okay, well what does that mean for
us as a sector, as a technology sector?
And in 2020, you had a bunch of digital and sustainability focused organizations trying
to figure out what that would mean for us as a sector.
Like how would we need to kind of drop our emissions for example?
And as you can see, this quote that came out when it was issued from this press release
basically said yeah, to actually have the Paris Agreement which is less ambitious than
that 1.5 thing, they basically said you need to halve emissions by 20, you need to reduce
emissions by 45% by 2030 in 7 years' time.
So that's basically making a reduction of around 7% each year, year on year and well
we haven't really been reducing things by 7% each year so it's actually going to be
larger.
So this is basically what the science is spelling out for us.
The thing that's quite interesting this year is that you've had people talking about net
zero for a while but now people are starting to actually say well what does net zero really
mean in the context of this science actually?
And has anyone heard of the ISO here?
ISO, the standards folks?
Okay they come up with something really interesting that they published in November.
They basically said if you want to call something net zero, you actually need to have some teeth
behind it and need to actually mean something now.
So while there's been lots and lots of kind of green washing net zero targets and things
from those organisations, they've basically come out and said actually this is the kind
of stuff you need for net zero now.
And they've basically said if you have net zero claims by 2050 without having about anything
related to halving emissions by 2030, they're not credible.
If you don't include your supply chain, do you just only think about your own things
rather than like who made a computer or anything like that, not credible.
And also if you don't have any interim targets in the next few years, also not credible because
this is quite important because seven years is about the same time as the average tenure
for a CEO which basically means you can say oh we're going to be net zero, leave, then
it's someone else's problem to solve.
And this is then basically saying actually you need to have something now so you can't
do that kind of stuff.
What's also interesting in Europe specifically is the catch-all titled European Corporate
Sustainability Reporting Directive.
Basically if you were in a company which has more than 250 employees, you need to be recording
and reporting some information about what your carbon emissions look like.
And you need to start reporting in 2024 which means you need to be reporting two months
ago to start doing this.
So that is interesting because lots and lots of organizations don't even have a sustainability
team and don't even know how to start reporting this stuff.
And then finally the IFRS, sorry about all the acronyms, these folks are, you can think
of them as like the Pope of accounting.
They're the people who just basically set a decree which everyone then follows in accounting
land.
They've basically said that supply chain thing that people talk about, yeah, actually we
should be doing that and you can't just say about your own organization rather than all
the things you buy from other people for example.
So that's what people have been saying and how are we doing so far?
Like as a tech sector, right?
So there's good news and there's bad news, all right?
The good news is that well, we have seen lots and lots of use and more people are connected
to the internet which I think is in broadly speaking a good thing and I don't know about
you folks but I quite liked having access to the internet during the pandemic.
I think that's been more useful and it would be a lot more kind of lonely and sad and cold
and everything if I wasn't connected to that.
And you generally see that we've basically been using much, much more in the way of digital
services over the last say 10 years or so but the growth hasn't been that large really.
It hasn't been proportional and there's a number of reasons for this.
Let's, okay, we can just, can we just not talk about cryptocurrency?
I'm sorry, like it's not helping billions of people, right?
The two billion people who joined the internet, pretty sure it didn't help two billion people.
Yeah, it's using like about half the impact, half the energy of all the data centers on
Earth, all right?
So that's the thing.
So we're basically going in the direction which is not ideal at the moment and we need
to kind of be reducing this.
And I guess there are now some companies which are trying to step up on this and they're
trying to basically say, well, we want to keep growing which has issues of its own but
maybe one thing we can do is actually make the energy we use greener.
So you now see very, very large companies like say Google say, well, 2030 is an important
date.
We're going to make sure that all of our energy is running on all the energy we use is coming
from green sources 24 seven and 24 seven is important because okay, you know how like
you bill for cloud like an hourly basis and there's about maybe 9000 hours in a year.
Yeah.
All right.
Normally when you look at green energy and people say I'm running on green energy, it's
an, it's like an average basically saying for all the power I've used, if I've used maybe
actually the way that I describe it to people is like this.
We all know that we should probably get about eight hours of sleep, right?
Yeah.
Like a, or a route that in a 24 hour period.
And if I wanted when you normally have green energy right now, you can basically say, well,
I've, it's a bit like me saying, I know I need to get eight hours of sleep every night
and I've got a year.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to have 3000 hours of sleep at the beginning of the
year.
All right.
And then I'm just going to run on Red Bull and chocolate bars for the rest of the year.
And that's going to be sustainable.
That's kind of like annual energy balancing.
That's kind of what the accounting is kind of a bit like, and there's more to it than
that.
But like, that's what we currently have at the moment, which is why 24 seven is actually
allowed upon quite an important goal.
Microsoft is also doing this.
They've said, well, they're going to run a hundred percent, a hundred percent zero coming
with zero carbon purchases, which again, sounds kind of cool.
And like these are companies with almost infinite money.
I say almost because they use as a basis for firing lots and lots of people despite being
through really, really profitable still.
But there are turns out that actually you don't need to be a ginormous company with
infinite money to actually kind of set this kind of target and actually be moving this
quickly.
This is a peninsula, the clean energy.
They're based in California.
They're a small community choice aggregator, which is basically a bit like a nonprofit
energy company.
And they've said, well, actually we think we can do it by 2025 because we built the
idea of avoiding an absolute climate kind of crisis into our governance board, basically.
And we, if it makes us slightly less profitable, that's okay because we're not answering to
shareholders.
So they've showed that they can do that.
And they've also actually shared all the actual underlying model in Python to show how they
actually bought all this stuff as well.
So you can actually do this.
And there's something interesting in Europe that's happened in the last week, actually.
Do you know how Elon Musk did that whole thing where he just cut off API access to Twitter
and then everyone's like, oh, now this thing I was going to do and like a massive enough
start using now because I should be using and I meant to do it anyway, right?
There's this kind of idea that you get ran to it.
Kind of the same thing happened with fossil fuels in Europe, right?
So we basically had this idea where Europe has been using loads of fossil fuels from
Russia.
And then Russia basically switched off the pipe.
And now you basically see press releases like this saying, well, we've got off Russian gas,
folks.
And now we've got all this money we can spend on that we would have otherwise spent on fossil
fuels.
So it's a bit like lemon and making lemonade.
But basically the upshot is that you basically got the European Commission president and
the people who essentially run Europe saying, well, we've got a quarter of a trillion euros
that we would have spent on gas.
And now we're planning to spend it on kind of more cool things like net zero technology
and wind and solar and stuff, which I think is actually, well, I'll take it, I suppose,
right?
So that's kind of what's happening at a kind of regulatory level that I think is quite
interesting.
And anyway, let's talk about competing on transparency for a diverse cloud ecosystem
because the thing is we basically have the science telling us we need to reduce emissions.
And there are ways of, there are some organizations which start saying, yeah, we're making all
this, we're doing all this kind of big splashy stuff.
And it's turning out there's more in the way of resources to do this stuff.
And there is this kind of narrative in policy circles right now where all the innovation
has to come from very, very large companies.
And I think it's not really true, particularly in like, well, basic cloud, for example, there's
low all kinds of cool stuff that you see from small providers in Europe, for example.
So OVH cloud pioneers in say, liquid cooling and service, as you can see here.
And then we're doing it for ages, scale way, like a French cloud provider using ARM service
for ages as well.
Like this is the thing that people make a big thing of, but it's been like just standard
as well as, okay, adiabatic cooling is basically using some ideas first developed in Iran to
basically reduce the use of water, but still make things cool.
They basically use it inside their servers rather than drawing loads and loads of water
out of like the local kind of aquifers.
This is important because in some parts of the world, there are Google data centers which
use the same amount of water as the city they're in, basically.
So like, you should be caring about this kind of stuff.
And anyway, there's loads of other examples that I've listed here.
I'm sure you can read them as well.
And there's also an interest at a kind of regulatory or kind of public sector level
now where people are trying to actually figure out what sustainable software really looks
like and how do you standardize it and how do you procure for this.
So Ocular, which was released by, which was kind of celebrated by KDE recently, they have
the first kind of Blau angle, Blue Angel kind of sustainable software kind of certificate,
which was issued to Ocular, a PDF reader around September last year.
And this is interesting because this is the kind of stuff that people who spend money
on trying to actually procure green and actually buy green in digital services are actually
getting now.
And if you work in a company and you're using some of the large providers, this is important
because it turns out to be quite difficult to get the metrics from the very, very big
hyperscalers.
This is an actual A table from a person called Mark Butcher at Positive Cloud.
He shared some of this with me because he was trying to figure out, well, okay, if you're
using these big providers, what information can you get from them when they're in your
supply chain that you need to report against?
And well, basically, I won't go into all the details here, but the red stuff is bad, right?
So if you're using the stuff on like those two providers, not really a good one.
Even on the left hand side, you do see some information.
So Microsoft is probably one of the better ones right now, but there's still some questions
about what they report.
Amazon, the level of reporting they give you is so, so, so low resolution that you can't
tell if the emissions are coming from like one data center or another data center, which
is on the other side of the country, thousands of miles away.
So you have some issues here because you might have one data center running essentially on
coal and you have another data center running on hydropower, which is definitely cleaner
than coal, all right?
And you have all this stuff here.
And this is one thing that you don't really have access to that if you're going to try
and report, if you need to report, you're going to have to be able to figure out how
to actually get these numbers so you can see if you're making, if we're going up or if
you're going down like we saw before.
There's also loads of really cool open source tooling, which makes it possible to get these
numbers out.
So the most well-known one is Cloud Carbon Footprint.
This is maintained by ThoughtWorks.
It plugs into billing APIs from, say, Amazon, from Microsoft and Google.
Then they do some guesstimates based on available data to tell you what your figures might be
because the various cloud providers have their own native ones, which have very different
assumptions to the open ones that you can challenge and you can ask questions about.
Green Coding Metrics, they did a talk today.
They basically put, if you have a digital service, they'll put every single service
in a kind of docker container, then track the energy used.
And I've got a really nerdy kind of part of a talk at 5 o'clock later today where I talk
about some of that.
Scaffandre, I'm not going to pronounce that properly.
It's a French word for diving helmet or diving suit.
It basically gives you process-level energy usage metrics from any machine you run it
on if you have access to the bare metal.
And it spits this out that you can kind of put into like dashboards and Grafana.
Kepler does more or less the same thing, but for Kubernetes, using Berkeley, no, Extended
Berkeley packet filters.
That's what they're called, right?
Yeah.
So that's another thing they do.
And there's another talk again about that kind of stuff.
So there's all this stuff which you can use and plug into your tooling, or you can ask
people to use.
So you can actually get the numbers to show that you're kind of putting this in the right
direction if you're interested in.
And I think that's my time.
I'm just going to wrap up.
That was a green web triangle.
There are three things you can have.
Convenient, diverse, fossil-free.
Most of the time, you can only really pick two.
There's pressure right now to really push towards fossil-free being a key thing, which
then really makes you decide, am I going to be diverse?
Am I going to be fossil-free?
I mean, the other one, convenient.
You can compete on transparency.
And I think this is some area that you could actually really kind of lead on.
And I think this is actually a way that this is probably underexplored right now.
And finally, diverse ecosystems are healthy ecosystems.
There's policy support, and there's money, and there's funding to make this stuff possible.
And I think you should do it.
And I think that there's actually even a policy idea around this.
The kind of words you need to use is twin transitions.
That's the kind of pseudo-password you need to use when you speak into a policymaker.
And I think that's it.
Thanks, folks, for my time.
There's a talk about a fossil-free internet.
This talk is online with links to everything I showed you.
I'm on mastodon.social.
And, OK, there's probably Mr. Chris Adams on Twitter, but I don't really use it very
much.
But you're welcome to tweet there, I suppose.
And yeah, that's my email address.
Thank you, everyone.
Thank you.
Thank you, Chris.
Open for questions?
Yes.
I'm also in the element matrix thing-o, so if you've got a question there, I'll try and
answer it as well.
There we go.
Well, hello.
I suppose I waited for some serious questions, but I have one maybe weird one.
What do you think about low-Earth orbit data centers?
You've talked about data centers in space that beam things down.
Yes, exactly.
I think there...
If there was a way that you could get them into space without the rockets, and you can't
have...
There are actually some wacky ways to do that.
I think it'd be cool.
I think astronomers have really strong opinions about that.
And also, the whole idea of, like, privatization of space makes me feel a little bit uncomfortable,
because we're not great at dealing with our waste right now.
And if you have all the waste that stops other people trans, then I feel like that's maybe
not the ideal solution, basically.
Also, a little bit worried about having the guy in charge of Twitter, in charge of the
future of space.
Maybe let's look at how he's handling Twitter, and think we want to see where that goes.
I'm not sure about that.
That's my answer, I suppose, but probably not related to climate.
Anyone else?
Hi, I just wanted to ask, what can you do as a small company, 10 to 15 people, you are
developing software probably for bigger clients?
I think what you can do, you can write into your contract.
Actually, there's a website called the Chance Relaying Project, which has all these clauses
for working with larger companies.
You can also allocate some of the revenue, 1.5% of my revenue, for 1.5% of us being alive,
and then use that to allocate that to fund things, either internally making your own
organization greener, or by funding things like non-profit groups who are actually pushing
for policy change.
Stuff like that.
I think those are the things you could do, which are easy to write into a contract, which
would actually show that you were demonstrating leadership compared to other people.
This is also what we do in terms of training and consulting.
I'm very happy to chat about that, because I probably should have told you everyone that.
This is what we do as well.
But yeah, I'm happy to chat about that in more detail, or answer questions on the element
and stuff from that.
Okay.
One more?
Yeah.
Hi, thank you.
You showed a few list of tools that help you get energy.
This one?
Yes.
How precise are they, and how much do they go around?
How many assumptions do they make to get the numbers, and what would be needed to don't
make assumptions at all?
Okay.
Someone mentioned Ili before, didn't they?
Ili was one of the German cloud providers.
Sorry, not cloud provider, energy provider.
All we need to do is get carbon emission figures from the energy providers, so they can tell
you how dirty or clean the energy is at any moment in time.
So you need that.
Basically, Scaffronger is very, very, very good.
It gives you very, very good numbers.
But you need hardware support to actually share the information about this.
So Intel, they have something called RAPL, which is running average power limit, which
gives you idea of the energy used by the CPU, but not necessarily the GPU or the disk.
So you need all this stuff kind of instrumented for you to get this.
Kepler, because you're going into the kernel, you can get really, really, really detailed
information.
But I'm kind of out of my league here, because I can write docs, but I can't write Rust,
which is why I contributed docs to Scaffronger instead of Rust to Scaffronger.
Grid coding metrics.
There's also a talk online where Arna Tarara, he talks about this in really, really good
detail, and he's actually very, very knowledgeable.
About carbon footprint, everything is open source, and it's all in TypeScript, where
they are very explicit about the assumptions they make all along, and they're also open
to pull requests.
I've committed to code to that one, and, yeah, I haven't committed code to the other two,
but they're cool people, and I really support the projects.
I hope that helps, and I'm, again, happy to chat in more detail.
Thank you.
Cool, folks.
meaningless without Chesapeake Canal own