Let's go.
Okay, so the goal also of this talk is to talk also about the progress and challenges
of alternatives facing the big techs.
So I want to first explain a bit why apps is key, why end-user apps is important, and
also where are we, what are we doing with these apps, do they exist.
So first, who am I?
So I'm Ludovic Dubas, I'm the creator of Xwiki, so I created the Xwiki software, so I don't
know, does anybody, who knows Xwiki here?
Oh cool, that's already nice.
And we also created a second software in my company, which is CripPad, who knows CripPad?
Cool, and that's pretty nice.
And so we've been doing collaboration software for 20 years now, like 19 years, and we've
been competing with software from the big techs, and it's not an easy thing to do.
You get lots of challenges there in order to actually build that software and get to
the level that you can compete.
And so I've done this at the same time I created the company, so it was a business goal to
be able to live from building these applications as open source, and we have 50 employees,
we're a remote first company, and we have employees in France and Romania, and also
now in Germany.
And actually, we hire, so if you're interested, come see what we do, and we are currently
having more success, and that's not happening every year, to be able to hire.
So if you're interested, to see how it works inside a company that has a goal of doing
open source, of building open source applications, not only using them or installing them, but
really creating them, come see what we do.
So as a company, we're also a member of our ecosystem, we're a member of associations
in France, for example, the Systematique, OW2, the CNLL, the Consé Nationale de l'Orgice
libre.
We're not a member of OSBA in Germany, but we actually want to be in its plans.
We're also a member of Clidia.
So Appel is actually a European entity over CNN and OSBA.
We're trying to be active also in order to try to promote the type of things that our
companies do, and I'm a strong believer that European companies should work together more
than they do together, and I know how difficult it is, because it's super difficult, because
we're all very focused on what we do every day, but collaboration is actually super important.
So first, one thing is, in 1995, technology was more like you buy machines, you buy or
you build software, you install that software.
And not all activities in our lives were actually dependent on software in 1995.
It was not that important, but in 28 years, actually a lot of things have changed.
Now you're renting cloud servers.
You could even run your server just on the cloud without worrying about buying a machine,
just take the service.
But you could also rent cloud servers.
You could build and make your own software and run it.
But also one thing is that almost everything, there is no business that's not dependent
on software.
It's really starting to be really hard to find anything that won't use any software.
Maybe some independent agriculture people might not need any software, but even though
might still use some of them to be more efficient in their job.
But you have a lot of activities that are highly, highly dependent on software for every
day work.
And it can be a major competitive differentiator to use software in your business.
We also see that there is a business in balance.
Actually, these are numbers, so I didn't put the source.
I should have.
Actually the GDP of the tech sector in the US is 10%.
There is data from Europe's websites where you see GDP is 4%.
So it's not easy to know if they're actually exactly talking about the same thing.
The scoping of what is the tech sector is not always easy to match from one country
to another.
But we kind of intuitively know that there is much more tech in the US.
And that actually makes a huge difference.
And if we look at the problem from the sovereignty point of view, so what I try to do here is
to look at the different levels of what we use in technology and what the situation is
and how Europe competes from that point of view.
But there are some differences also in the way it works.
So for example, you might not know how to make a hardware component.
You might not have the people that can do it.
But once you bought it, the hardware component is yours.
And that actually is something that is significantly different from the top where you might not
know how to do the cloud service, but you also don't own it.
You don't have it.
You use it.
You use it remotely.
Now, it's true even in hardware, you're seeing evolutions where the world of software, the
way software works, of SaaS software works, is starting to happen on the hardware level.
Now, you can turn on a feature in a Tesla remotely, and you can turn it off also remotely.
So we might have situations where we don't own the software that is inside a hardware
machine.
So you have a lot of hardware that contains software.
Even a chip can contain software.
Whether or not they can turn off feature remotely from the internet is another story.
Software is something that you can turn on, turn off remotely.
And that's something very important.
Now, we're not actually looking that good all over the place.
We know in Europe how to make some semiconductors.
For example, RM, the European company, was almost acquired by Nvidia, but it didn't happen.
But it's a UK company.
So we still own a semiconductor company in Europe.
We have some actors for hardware, but most of it is manufactured in Asia.
So that's something important.
And we know that with Covina, when we wanted masks in Europe, we didn't get them as fast
as we wanted, as we needed them.
So being able to manufacture our technology can be important.
So now, cloud services, we do have European actors.
But the good thing is that we have standardized open source tools in cloud services, so Linux,
things like that, like Kubernetes, Docker.
These are open source software.
We don't always have the competences in Europe.
We are not the ones that build them, most of them.
But we do have access to the source.
And we have actors, but it's possible to run VMs all over Europe.
That's not a big problem.
Now when you go to PaaS software, Platform as a Service, you have a major dominant from
the actors.
In France, there's been a complaint about the fact that the Health Data Hub, which is
a national service doing statistics on health data, was run on Microsoft Cloud.
And basically, a lot of people say, what?
You're running health data of all the people in France on an American system.
How is that protecting our data?
It's not compliant with GDPR.
And basically, the answer of the people that had made these decisions said there are not
enough good APIs on the French Cloud services to run it on the French Cloud service.
Obviously everybody said, no, there are.
You have enough.
There is enough to.
Maybe you're going to miss a little bit of stuff.
Maybe it's not going to be convenient for you, but it's possible.
But basically, the argumentation was that it was not good enough.
The ministry in France basically bashed the French companies for not being good enough.
And the answer of the ecosystem, what are you waiting for to give money to the French
company to allow them to be good enough?
What are you doing instead of putting that type of service on foreign systems?
So the technology, it's possible to develop it.
A lot of it is open source, but companies like Amazon or Amazon Web Service, Google
Cloud or Microsoft, are very ahead in terms of number of services that they have.
When I looked at a company, what technologies are available to deploy XWIKI software and
Cripat software in an app store on cloud providers, you have different technologies on all of
them, but they all have a lot of options for how you would sell your software on their
app store.
When you look at what European companies have, they don't have systems to automatically deploy
applications and sell them and put a price on them and people would start buying them.
So they're really ahead.
And when you go to SaaS, you have thousands of services all around the world, startups.
We do have national actors and a lot of these actors are not open source.
So you have a lot of SaaS services and a lot are not open source.
And even the ones provided by Microsoft, Google and Amazon are not open source or they can
be based on open source, but they're not themselves open source.
That means you cannot decide to self-host them and take control of them.
And that's actually something that we'll see is important.
Now in the collaboration space, when you ask to the big companies what they need, they
don't need one collaboration software.
They need a whole stack.
It was interesting in the previous presentation about the co-op, it was about deploying multiple
apps and this is actually bigger companies want all these software, they need multiple
software and they need them to work well together.
So they need authentication, user management, they need of course email, chat, video conferencing,
file storage, they want to edit documents, they want collaboration tools and then they
even want to build custom apps.
So they want a lot of different software and they want all this to be simple and easy.
And when you start using apps, you become very quickly locked in.
Even when the app is open source by the way, when you put your data in a system, the way
you put that data in makes you quickly locked because it's complicated to get the data out
and to adapt the way you work to other apps.
Even if the app is standard, in 20 years of Xliki, I've heard so many people say that
how they use to the fact that the button in Microsoft Office version X something, it's
here on the screen and you give them another tool where the button is on the right and
they say it's difficult to use.
Like, okay, it's difficult to use, it's difficult to use because the button is on the right.
No, no, well, they don't even know why it's difficult to use but it feels difficult to
use to them because they're so used to the way they work before that it's very difficult
to change.
And we have been trying to move people from office to wikis.
So imagine how they tell you that it's difficult to use.
No, it's not that difficult to use.
You need to adapt your way of working, you need to learn a new tool.
It's not that difficult to use.
It takes time to adapt.
You need to try to think how it works and try to adapt your way of working.
So the lock-in is very high and on SAS software, the lock-in is actually immense.
I worked at Netscape in 1995 and we were talking about the lock-in of Microsoft on software
when it was on-premise software.
And it's like, oh, Microsoft controls your software like you're blocked on their software.
But at least the software was in your company and you could put a firewall around it and
potentially no data would go out.
Here now it's on the cloud and so they will tell you it's going to be double the price
to upgrade but you didn't have to upgrade.
You could decide to stay on the older version for a bit longer and you didn't have to pay
every year.
You paid licenses for a long time.
Now you're paying every year and if you don't pay on the 1st of January for your renewal
or every month, they turn off the software immediately.
So you're actually in an immense lock-in.
The lock-in is actually way higher than it was in 1995 when a lot of the industry was
complaining about that lock-in.
And the data is controlled by the provider.
There is a huge lack of standards on the structure of the data.
So how that data, your basic formats are standardized but in collaborative apps, even in wikis,
I have to recognize that the xWiki software formats are not that standardized.
We tried at some point to work with other wiki providers to work on common syntaxes
but never happened.
Like our syntax was based on something called wikiCrayol which was discussed 15 years ago
but now everybody is using Markdown.
So there was something that people said that should be the standard.
Like a lot of wiki providers discussed, especially said that that's a good common standard but
it's a completely other one that a lot of people now say, ah, it's great.
But not many people discussed the Markdown standard.
They were just, oh, people liked it and it started to become very light.
So the standards are very difficult to have even when they exist.
They're not necessarily adopted.
And so if they're not adopted, they're not very useful to move data from one system to
another.
The complexity of the software make it very difficult to switch.
And one key aspect of the software industry is a winner takes it all approach.
Like this is basically why VCs love the tech industry.
They put a lot of money, they try to win, and they like the fact that when you win,
everybody else is dead.
The winner makes 95% of the revenue.
All the other people fight for the 5% that's left.
And they love that because that's actually their goal, trying to be the winner.
So what's interesting is that they don't necessarily win that much because they create
10 companies or 100 companies and only one makes it to being the winner.
And so in the end, they don't win that much money because they drop a lot of money on
the way.
But this is their goal, basically, of what they're trying to do.
And one of the problem of the lock-in also is unfair business practices.
You have a lot of unfair business practices because the providers are so powerful that
it's very tempting to use that power to make more money.
So if you ask a business lead to make 10% more revenue next year, if there is no difficulty
to increase the price because everybody's locked, they will just increase the price
10%.
It's easier than work hard to try to get new customers.
And in order to keep that approach running, they also try to...
Another approach is to, okay, let's make other people buy my second software.
I have a first software.
If I can force the other people, if I can encourage them to use it, I give for free
the second software, then at some point they become used to it.
It's free.
And at some point, I say, no, it's not free anymore.
Microsoft Teams is typically that approach.
And Slack has actually complained about it.
They actually sued about it because Teams was free.
Office 365 is very expensive.
They just gave Teams to everybody that has Office 365.
And at some point they say, no, you have to pay.
And all the others are dead in the meantime.
So you have a huge amount of risks of lack of sovereignty associated to this.
So if you can stop all the software remotely, if we disagree with the US government, knowing
that all these companies are US based, if we disagree with the US government, they could
turn off the software.
And even worse than that, by the way, is that they don't even need to turn the software
because they just need to remind our government that they can turn off the software.
And then the other government will start being want less to disagree with the American government
because they know it's possible or in negotiations, it could be vaguely reminded that it's possible.
And that's actually a big problem.
Our ministry in France of economy and finance said no political sovereignty without digital
sovereignty.
I'm not sure what they actually do to try to avoid that situation, but they actually
acknowledge it, that there was a problem.
That you at some point, you cannot state your political opinions if you're dependent so
much on other people that have a different opinion than you.
And at this point, I'm not sure how many businesses would still function if you shut down their
collaboration tools.
If you shut down Microsoft today, what's the impact?
It's a bit difficult to deny, but how long would it take for the companies to start being
able to do work again?
And so from my point of view, that makes really collaboration apps very important because
we don't have the control on these apps.
And it's the primary set of tools that people use.
Actually, I didn't ask that question.
In your company, which ones are using Microsoft or Google?
And so it's the primary tool that people are using, and they get really used to it.
And it's also the primary authentication system that people use.
Most companies will put Azure AD, active directory as the authentication system.
And basically, they end up also being almost ready to deploy servers.
So when you have Azure AD, you have an Azure account, you're one click away from deploying
servers on the Microsoft system.
So people buy Office 365.
They tell people, ah, you need to connect Office 365 to Azure AD to manage your users.
And then you're one click away to deploy servers.
And a lot of users like simplicity.
If it's simple to click, they start using the other service.
And they do a lot of work to make all this work as easy as possible together.
Do they do a good job is another question.
But they have the possibility to make it easy.
We might be happy that they're not always very good at it.
And so that gives us some opportunities to provide other solutions.
And so it's the entry point of all software.
And the biggest problem from my point of view has been the bundle issue.
Is that a lot of software becomes bundled as a package.
And so when you go to Microsoft's website to buy, you say I need Office, you will be
proposed the whole Microsoft suite, not only Office 365.
And you will have this software plus this software plus this software.
And you'll see that the difference of pricing is not always very high between the package
with, and I'm not even sure it exists only Office 365.
Only Office, you will get for free one thing, even what you don't need.
This was actually the problem of computers bundled with Windows, which were bundled with
Internet Explorer.
I said I worked at Netscape and I can remember how it killed Netscape's business around the
browser.
When Microsoft bundled Internet Explorer in Windows, who would buy a browser if you have
one for free with Windows when you get your computer, which at the time you were paying
Windows.
Well in the meantime there's a lot of things that have changed because now browsers also
got free because you can make money through advertisement.
But that's actually potentially a problem because you can make money through advertisement
but we also got tracking thanks to that.
So we get browsers for free but we get tracking.
And that's also a problem of sovereignty.
So now they bundle even more.
They bundle apps but they also bundle Office 365 with the cloud, with the pass, with the
yes.
Microsoft has a whole offer.
Servers, yes, a pass, and apps.
And when you go see a client with you, ah I have a wiki.
Would you like my wiki?
Well sorry, I already have it for free in the whole offer.
No, you need to, you know.
And I even, I think I had a few cases like that, is for a department that's part of a
big company, if they buy another software, they pay for it.
If they use Microsoft software, the central entity pays for it.
And it's divided and they pay the same share of it whether they use it or not.
So basically you come as a provider and you have a cost and the Microsoft software you're
competing with has no cost.
It's free.
But it has a cost in reality because everybody then will start, some people will start using
some of these software and when they renew the license with Microsoft three years later,
Microsoft comes and counts everything that is being used and they set the new bill.
And so the company will end up paying it, the fact that they started using that software.
And so it's very difficult to compete.
And so everything's bundled.
So actually Nextcloud has sued on this, I think antitrust.nextcloud.com, I think.
I think I have the link a bit later.
And so because it's a real antitrust issue, in the end you cannot compete with that type
of situation.
And so some people say, and especially this is true in France, on our government, they
say we need to build better software companies.
So the problem is not the way the competition works or the way these companies operate and
so on.
That's not the problem.
The problem is we don't have a French one or we don't have a European one.
And so say let's build unicorns and make companies.
But in reality, when you look at unicorns, is that first, well, if they actually get
very big, if they manage to get very big, they will behave exactly the same way.
And it's not going to help the people and the small companies.
It's going to be a bit less a sovereignty issue because maybe our government will have
a little more control on them.
But we are not going to get our own sovereignty because we're going to be very dependent on
this big company.
The other problem is that most of these unicorns are made with VCs.
Most of these VCs are actually not even European.
And VCs want to make money, so they want to sell the company at some point.
And it's much easier to sell it to the ones that have the most money, which are the current
American companies.
So in the end, there is a very big chance that all these unicorns will either die because
they don't work well enough, or they're going to be bought by the same companies that are
currently leading the market.
And another thing, yeah, and that's actually they usually use the American cloud providers
for their services.
And so these cloud providers see everything they do.
So when something works well, they can replicate it.
This is actually a complaint against Amazon, even in the US.
That small businesses that sell on Amazon are showing to Amazon everything that works.
And surprisingly, at some point, you get products that pop up made by Amazon instead, and they
take the market.
And so they're supposed to not look at the statistics, but we don't know what really
happens.
Now how can open source help to solve these type of problems?
So one thing I believe is very important is that if you try to build local companies,
French ones, German ones, UK ones, even though UK is not in Europe anymore, but still in
Europe physically.
That if you try to build your own local companies, and you all do it at the same time, at some
point you'll have a problem.
And because suppose one of them buys the other one, you're going to have one very big French
company, or one very big German company, and maybe, I don't know, a Swedish one.
And the problem is that this won't be sovereignty for the countries that don't own these companies.
So, you might have a bit of sovereignty in France, but no sovereignty in Poland.
And so if you try then to tell, so let's invest all, let's start using the software from this
European company, like in Poland, they're not very interested to use the software from
a French one.
That doesn't give them that much sovereignty.
So, an open source works very differently.
If we invest in open source in France, it can be used in Germany, and it can give sovereignty
to Germany because Germany can control the software.
German companies can build competence on top of that software.
And that's true in Poland, and that's true in Romania, et cetera.
So, if we all in different countries co-invest in open source, we can all get more sovereignty
out of it, and we also can get individual sovereignty out of it because any individual
can then make use of it.
So, I'm sure I don't have to convince that much about open source here, but it's important
to remind these arguments which can be useful if you meet people in your own country.
So, also open source is usually a bit more open to standards, and if the provider doesn't
want to adapt this software to standards, then somebody else can do it.
You have this possibility.
So, open source will allow to adapt software to standards when providers don't want to
do it because it's not in their economical interest.
It's very hard.
Like, if you look at software, you very often have a lot of import tools.
You very rarely have export tools, but anybody can build the export tools on open source
software.
And one aspect that is also interesting is that we can reuse also US open source software.
But we need, however, to build local competence.
If we use massively very large US-based software, but we're not building local competence on
it, we will risk having a lack of sovereignty because we don't have the people that can
take over.
So, we can reuse open source software from anywhere in the world, but it's also important
to invest in the competence.
So, if we start building massive solutions and not only competence about how to use them,
but competence how they're built, how they're made inside the software.
It's very easy to use open source.
It's much more difficult to improve an open source software.
You need to build competence on the software itself.
So, now I want to look a bit at what actually exists because we're looking, and I've been
maybe a bit looking pessimistic because it's hard, it's tough.
But actually, what's interesting is that we have tons of great open source software in
Europe.
And I'm sure I missed a lot because I spent most of my time on our own software.
And I'm sure I missed a lot, but I mentioned the list of types of software that companies
are looking for for collaboration.
And so, for example, in video conferencing, we have software like Jitsi, which has been
created in France.
Actually, core developers are in the US now, but it was created in Strasbourg.
Big Blue Bhutan, Canadian, it's open source, not developed in Europe.
Next Cloud Talk, developed in Europe.
Only Office is developed in Letoni, if I'm correct.
There are also issues around Only Office because it's linked to Russia.
So we also need to have more control on it, on the development of it.
Collaboration, Next Cloud, Xwiki, CripPad, project management, projects like Tulip, open
project.
We have a lot of software on authentications, software like Lemon L Dapp, UniVention.
On email, we have Open Exchange.
We have Sogo, BlueMind.
And on file management, software like Next Cloud, PDO, CripPad.
And on chat, we have great solutions like Matrix.
So we actually have all the bricks existing.
Now, they're all provided by different companies, different providers, and they're not as integrated
as the other solutions will be.
And another aspect, I'll come back to that, the integration aspect.
Another aspect is that actually building open source business, it works.
Like all these software have core teams.
The software I mentioned, they do have core teams.
Most of the companies, most of the software have a core team that is working for at least
one company that has regular revenue out of this software.
And they're able to fund the roadmap and have a regular development on top of this software.
So it's possible, and I can attest of it, with my company, we didn't raise any money.
And for 19 years, we've been able to pay the people in the team and grow.
And we've even been able to create a second software out of the work that we were doing
on the first one.
So it's possible to fund the company.
Now at the beginning, it's not easy.
Like the first years, you need to build critical mass.
And sometimes you have an issue of competition.
So you're not necessarily finding enough money to build it quickly at the level that it can
compete.
But it's possible to find business.
And it progresses.
The better your software is, the more companies are interested in it.
When it's good enough, the companies get interested in it.
So you have moments where companies will just go to the other provider.
So winner takes it all.
So you get very little market share.
But then at some point, they get more interested.
And you get more prospects.
So how does open source business work?
Clients do buy support.
But you need also to have the price right.
So if you put it too expensive, then clients might just go away.
But if you put the right price, you get clients that buy support.
You also have clients that sponsor development.
But you have issues of dumping and bundling that slows it down.
You cannot sell to everybody because you have competitors and their software is given for
free or cheaper.
And Xwiki knows it very well because we've been competing with Xwiki with conference.
Anybody has conferences in their company.
So while you can try to convince your companies to switch to Xwiki, we have importers.
And Atlassian has kept increased the price over the time.
And they actually changed a lot the strategy.
So they had a pretty low price for small businesses.
And now they say small businesses, you have to go on the cloud.
We stop doing the small priced software, even though it makes money.
If you look at the finances of Atlassian, it does make money.
So it's a conscious choice to make more money.
It's not something that doesn't work.
It's something that works.
But now that they've done that, we have a lot of calls and we get much more clients.
And even though we never got the money of these clients to build our own software.
So we've been able to build the software with the money of other clients.
And now we're having more clients coming.
So I think it's a clear proof that the dumping and the bundling approaches are slowing down
open source and there are unfair practices.
There are also some good news.
For example, European initiatives, NGI.
So we at Xwiki, we've been able to benefit from that on CripAd in particular.
Because CripAd doesn't have that many clients.
There has almost no enterprise clients.
It's just starting to have enterprise clients.
And it's been mostly funded with research money.
We do have some clients.
We have donations and subscriptions on our instance.
But it would not be enough to pay for that software, which requires a lot of work.
And so NGI is providing funding for companies and that's really a great thing.
There also the EU started to pay for bug bounties on open source software.
We've been able to benefit from it also.
And that's been great.
Gaiyaks is interesting, but there are also issues with it from my point of view.
It's not easy to understand, to see how four small providers like us that are doing apps,
how to work together with the big cloud providers and big companies that are currently running
Gaiyaks.
We're not seeing also open source being put in front in the Gaiyaks project.
So there are initiatives in Europe to help.
And we've seen that it's becoming more and more in subject.
That's interesting.
In France, we have the French government decided to put some funding.
So on one side, they're opening the door to American software.
They also reacted to the fact that from the GDPR perspective, there is a huge problem
with the Cloud Act.
This is the Max Shramps Act.
And basically, they're recognizing that it's illegal to host data on American companies'
systems.
But it seems to be illegal, but we don't really know if they consider it illegal for everybody.
Is it illegal only for the public service?
It's illegal for all the companies?
It's unclear.
But they started to say, OK, for example, the national education should not use Microsoft,
should not deploy Microsoft software anymore.
But on the other side, they're proposing that French companies are going to build clouds
to deploy Microsoft and Google software on them and host it instead of Microsoft and
Google.
And that will be OK.
So they will control the software, but they won't control the hosting, but they won't
control the software.
On the other side, they say, OK, let's fund a little bit of alternatives.
So they decided to put 50 million, but they didn't put it on open source.
We have partners in some of the projects to try to get funding for XWIKI and CripPad
and try to build also additional solutions.
So you have a bit of a mixed message on one side.
They like open source.
On the other side, they don't promote only open source.
So it's not always clear.
So you have messages.
There are better news in Germany, where you have specific funding for open source platforms
with the sovereign workplace project.
Actually at XWIKI, we have had the chance to be called in.
And that is actually great news for us.
And you have a bunch of great open source software that are part of that project.
You also have additional initiatives like the sovereign tech fund, and there is a specific
entity called the Centrum for Digital Superimitate.
Then this, my German is good.
And you have the open code project.
So a bit better news, but at the same time, it's never completely won.
You have internally a government, some people pro and some people that will continue to
push for, oh, it's not so important.
Let's use American software.
So the challenges, I've talked about them.
The antitrust is clearly bundling and unfair practices and trying to kill competition with
aggressive pricing.
I've seen cloud develop.
I mean, the typical cloud business model is let's give things for free and then increase
the price.
Let's get the users when they're in, when I'm sufficiently known, let's change the price.
You could say open source does the same thing.
Let's make it open source.
And at some point, let's give it for free and let's change the price or let's stop being
open source.
So some companies do it.
There is a big difference.
However, is that what you put as open source, you can never take away.
So maybe you can change your price, stop, do open source and do your own life and turn
your back on the people that helped you because you have a lot of people that help you when
you do open source.
You give them a lot, but they also give you a lot.
I can say that I have a lot of people that gave us things, gave us contribution, make
the software known.
The users' crypto platform wouldn't be what it is with all the people making it known.
So we have a lot of people helping.
So you can do that, but you can never take away the code.
And that's a very, very important difference versus a strategy of the cloud providers that
gives things for free and increase the price later.
And this is also why on my side, I'm a big proponent of a GPL with no CLA.
So no retaining the copyright of everything that people give you because this shows that
you will not turn your back on open source or at least you will have to give back all
the code and redo what people gave you.
For CripAd, it's a GPL.
Xweek is LGPL.
And we don't want to change it because this is what we did and we don't want to change
that.
But CripAd is a GPL and we have never taken any CLA on contributions.
And we believe we cannot go away of what we're doing.
There is another challenge, which is open source financing.
So the initial financing of an open source project is very difficult.
It's something that is tough.
There is one thing that is very important is that a lot of people, when they build open
source software and they try to live from it, they question the open source business
model.
Is that, yeah, but somebody is going to steal my software or somebody is going to compete
with me, et cetera, et cetera.
And you have difficulties.
You always have difficulties.
But sometimes it's very important to understand that the main difficulty is not the business
model.
The main difficulty is do a good enough software.
In many cases, when you tend to think that you should be selling it, you should be selling
it instead of giving it away as open source, well, sometimes that's not the problem.
The problem is that the software is not good enough.
You need to be better.
The competition is too good.
And you need to work more on your software.
We had phases where it was a bit difficult at XWiki.
And what we did, we worked on the software and things improved.
So you have to look at that.
We also decided at XWiki to do extensions that are open source but paying.
And so I usually have a bit of a complexity to explain that.
I even had some people that said, so they asked, but can I take it or can I reuse it
for free?
I said, yeah, take the source, rebuild it, remove the license check, and you can use
it.
It's open source.
So it's not open source.
I cannot use it for free.
No, that's not open source.
It's about the source.
It's not about whether or not it's easy for you to use it.
So we decided to have some extensions of XWiki which are open source.
But either you go find the source and you go and take it and build it yourself and install
it yourself, or you use our app store.
And in one click, you can use it, pay for it, and buy it.
And it's been very useful for us because it allows also to explain to companies that concept.
The fact that the important part is the fact that it's open source.
It's not that it's free.
That's what is important in what we do.
But it allowed to explain that and it helped actually improve the relationship with some
of our clients which tend naturally to say, OK, if I don't have to pay, I don't pay.
I don't help the project.
I don't need to pay.
So you have to find that balance also between the commercial offers and the freedom.
Sometimes when you build open source, you're too idealistic in a way that, OK, everything
should be free.
But the problem that when everything's free, you have a lot of people that don't understand
that they actually should help the project because this project will not survive without
funding.
You need money to survive to make the software.
It's necessary.
Another aspect is that it's actually very difficult to make partnerships with service
and cloud companies.
Right now, Xwiki has not been able to do good partnerships with other service companies
to distribute our software.
It's not simple.
And I'm not really sure how to do partnerships with cloud companies.
Cloud companies can be very tempted to just reuse all the open source software available
and sell it and not fund in any way the software that are in these offers.
And we need a model for that.
So if we want to separate the work of cloud service and of software, we need to find a
model to how to sell open source software when it's sold to companies.
Otherwise, the software will not be able to fund themselves.
So Matrix, for example, has made a blog post about the fact that they have major success
in terms of usage and deployments.
But many of these deployments are made by other companies that are making money off
of it and are not giving back anything, not even developers, to work on the project.
Neither funding, neither developers.
And in the end, they had to fire people.
And so in order to...
I mean, if you want to do good software, you need great people.
You need great developers.
And so you need to find a funding model that works.
One aspect for open source company is to work with less cash.
So I don't believe in VC investment because I think that doesn't allow to keep the independence
of what we build.
But you have to work with less cash.
So even when you're growing, it's difficult to hire because you need a lot of cash to
run the company itself, like to advance the money, and you are taking risks.
And it's not a simple problem.
Another problem is integration and fragmentation.
So clients want things that are integrated.
That's actually also one of the reasons you start to see packages that bundle the software.
So trying to make them all installable together easily.
That's actually something that's important.
And cloud providers providing multiple software together.
This is very interesting.
But there is a lot of integration work that is necessary.
And sometimes that work is not brought back to the projects.
And we need to make that happen.
There's also a lot of fragmentation in the EU market.
So you need to go to multiple countries to sell.
It takes a lot of time.
So we need also partnerships between the companies in the different countries to work together
in order to make that work.
And I'm very happy to have partnerships with Univention, for example, Peter, because for
us it's a major win of time to go on the German market.
If a company says, look at this French company, it changes a lot the way the German market
will see a French company.
And that is going to be true the other way.
So we need to work more together.
So that's a bit the next step I have.
So first is we need to believe in ourselves.
So we have great offers.
And the companies that are building open source software are able to make it.
And the difficulty sometimes they have is about competition, is about being considered
good enough so that a lot of companies invest in them.
There is a huge amount of money sold on collaboration.
I think we count billions of euros that are given to Microsoft and Google.
And if we sum all the open source companies we were talking about, we're talking about
$50, $100 million, something like that revenue, I don't know exactly because it's not always
easy to get the numbers.
But we're spending billions on collaboration software to American companies.
So there is a lot of money.
And just we need to convince the clients that were good enough as a group, not only as individual
company.
And open source provides good openness and flexibility.
And that's useful to clients.
So there are also good technical arguments for open source when it comes to company.
We have had a lot of clients that were very interested in the flexibility of our software.
But they also want easy to go solution, one provider to buy from.
And that's a real difficulty.
We need to work more on European collaborations.
I talked about it.
So at Xwiki this is something we're trying to do more.
So the intervention partnership we did last year.
And we're also looking at the partnerships with Nextcloud, with Open Project.
There are multiple companies in Europe that think the same way.
They just lack a lot of time to actually make it happen.
And so it's going to take time.
But there are many companies that want to do that.
And sovereign workplace project is really great to create also this integrated offer,
bring the providers together.
Now we will need to find ways to do partnerships with cloud providers.
I've yet to see how this will happen.
And we need more open standards.
That's also another aspect that's transversal.
We need more open standards.
I've also been a believer that we need an open source marketplace.
So a way for cloud providers to sell open source software in one easy way.
But I thought, I hope that Guy Eix would be a place for that.
I haven't seen that happening.
The most important thing we need is clients.
So any clients that are brought to the companies that are providing this alternate platform
are helping these companies bring the software a little bit better.
And it makes a difference.
So everything that as individuals you can do to tell your boss, employers that maybe
they should look at what these companies are doing, that other companies are actually deploying
these software is helping.
So I mean, if you can help us, do it and make it known.
And that's it.
If there are any questions, I think there's two minutes left.
So everybody fall asleep.
One.
Hi.
You mentioned earlier in your talk that the French government deemed it illegal to host
data on American companies because of the US Cloud Act.
Could you expand on the Cloud Act a bit more?
Yeah.
The Cloud Act is the fact that the US government is able to access data from American companies
and even from American people.
So first, I'm not a lawyer.
So don't take everything I say for granted.
So it allows to access data even if that data is in a foreign country.
So and they can even, I understood from a paper in Holland by lawyers that they could
even ask to an American person secretly to give the data that these people can access
and they cannot refuse basically.
Like they risk a lot.
So Microsoft, if asked, would secretly have to give money that they have on servers in
Ireland and that is not compliant with GDPR.
That's what the Mac Shremf judgments said.
So it's been written.
But then the problem is that it needs to be recognized and decisions need to be made to
stop doing it.
And it seems like everybody's waiting for Europe to sign another agreement to say that
it's okay so that you don't have to make the decision to stop hosting it on American systems.
Hi.
Thanks for the presentation.
So you were saying that actually like open source collaborative software would help solve
the issue or improve the digital sovereignty.
If we suppose that Microsoft tomorrow makes office source code available on GitHub, let's
say, how would that change the actual stage of the digital sovereignty in the EU?
Well it will change it if people start to take that software and host it and verify
that it solves the business needs.
So but yes, it would improve it.
For example, Microsoft does not give the source code of office.
So if you want to do office editing, you have to work with software that has been built
by other people, not by Microsoft.
And Microsoft and Google have better software, more compatible with office formats and so
on and so on.
So it would improve.
It still would need to be packaged.
There would still be a lot of work.
But it would improve the offers, the alternative offers and then companies.
But so about digital sovereignty, the thing is, if tomorrow we have a political problem,
they can turn off the software.
So all our companies will have problems.
The question is, OK, do we have alternatives to replace that software at this point?
Not necessarily as good.
And they are not as good because we're not buying these alternatives.
So we cannot fund them.
So the distance between the American solutions and the European solution is increasing instead
of being reduced.
And so it's all about whether or not we would be able to replace that software.
If Microsoft made it open source, it would be easier to replace their own services, their
online services.
Sorry.
I want to follow up to the first question, basically.
So US Cloud Act, regarding it, as far as I recall, Privacy Shield was the first one that
has been taken down by your court.
And I'm not sure if US Cloud Act somehow replaces it or not.
No.
No, privacy, the Cloud Act is an American law.
The Cloud Act makes it a problem that makes Privacy Shield illegal, basically.
Privacy Shield said it's OK to put data in the US.
And basically, the judgment from Mike Schremms goes to his website.
He explains the problem much more precisely, says that this is not true.
Privacy Shield says it's OK, but it's not OK.
Because of the Cloud Act and the FISA warrants, the laws in the US that allow access to data,
even if it's hosted in Europe.
Yeah, and the European Court accepted that Privacy Shield is not valid.
It's not valid.
They accepted.
A couple of years, I believe, now.
Now, the European government is right now negotiating, the commission is negotiating
with Biden some new paper that says it would be OK.
But it's already kind of validated that this paper is not OK.
But there will need to be another judgment to say that it's not OK.
So it's a kind of a cat and mouse, because some people in Europe don't want it to be
illegal to use American system.
And Biden doesn't want to change the Cloud Act.
Thank you.