We are starting with the first talk in the Sovereign Cloud Devroom and it's my great
pleasure to open the stage for Max, who's going to elaborate on how he created a documentation
framework for the Sovereign Cloud Stack.
Enjoy, have fun.
Thank you very much.
Hi everybody.
Thank you.
How did we create a documentation framework that works across a group of vendors in the
Sovereign Cloud Stack community?
This I will show you.
My name is Max.
I'm a knowledge management engineer at the Sovereign Cloud Stack and my background is
broadly in web development.
The talk, TLDR, what is it?
Basically it's a set of GitHub action workflows to copy markdown folders and files from many
a's to one single b and once that's done, b is being built into a single page application
resulting in the Sovereign Cloud Stack documentation at docs.scs.community and here, pull out your
mobile phones and have a look at it.
I will now elaborate what's behind this.
What is the Sovereign Cloud Stack?
The Sovereign Cloud Stack combines the best of cloud computing in one unified standard
and SCS is built, backed and operated by an active open source committee worldwide.
This is the SCS stack and it's made up from many modules and it's quite complex and there
is of course documentation but it's heavily distributed at different places on the internet
and that's quite difficult to keep track on.
Where do we have to go?
Where do I have to be routed as an integrator developer?
That's quite a challenge.
As an integrator and operator, you have to manage different documentations in different
Git repositories and different docs and it would be nice to have them within one platform
to search and to have guides and tutorials and references and a great DX or UX.
But how could you do this?
This was my challenge and the aim and requirements for the documentation is it has to be like
a minimal rule set where the approval is basically a no-brainer and all doc files will reside
in one place and it must be probably the biggest challenge, a low entry hurdle for companies
with existing repositories because no one wants to change the whole documentation if
it's being consumed by another stack basically.
So no one has to make any major changes and then we are thinking about could it be made
up with Git sub modules and no, it's too complex to manage and Git subtree was then
okay this could be nice but actually it would, yeah, it's not cool too and then other vendors
said no we don't want to change anything in our existing repositories.
So then we had a great community hackathon in Cologne in November 22 hosted by PlusServer
where we have developed in eight hours straight in a tunnel a working prototype with a custom
GitHub actions workflow or combination of this and this is one of the great things with
the Sovereign Cloudstack community that everyone is joining forces to actually elaborate on
the common challenges.
So yeah thanks also shout out to Ramona and Tim who worked on this prototype with me on
this day from OSISM.
So how does it work?
Basically it's GitHub actions workflow, it's actually three workflows as you see here and
the whole concept is a docuosaurus react based static side generator you may have heard of
it's source by meta and the three action workflows are divided in collecting all the different
documentation files then distilling them that you only have the markdown files from the
repository and then it's being built and deployed.
Let's jump into how this works and we defined docs.package.json where you define which doc
files you need from which organizations repositories and so basically it's a package manager for
docs.
So in the first line you have the repo with the organization so sovereigncloudstack.docs
is the first one and then you define the source directory where the docs files reside in or
the folder and the next line is then you define the target where should it be placed in the
site currently there's a community page and a docs page and docs for technical documentation
the community page for how we organize in a community and also contributors guide and
the labels then how it should reside in the navigation.
Then the first workflow is reading the JSON and then defining a matrix strategy within
GitHub actions so for each element in the docs.json a workflow is being run.
So this is the whole synchronizing and distilling workflow we call it distilling because it's
like in a distilling process refining what has to be done and all the source code because
most of the time there's a source code and then in one doc file or docs folder there
is all the documentation which we want the other source files we don't want so we're
distilling it.
So we'll quickly go through the workflow.
The first one is checking out the repository with secrets action token then it's first
doing a clean install so it's removing all the previous files which resided in the documentary
so just removing all that was there.
Then it's cloning the repository A which is about to be synchronized into the checked
out repository.
In the next step then it's removing the git folders then it's removing the readme files
and then it's creating the docuser sub directory so either in the docs sub folder or in the
community sub folder with the target folder of the docs and the label and then it's copying
all those files from A to B then it's removing all the stuff and then it's committing it
directly to main so there is no pull requests it's pretty nice and then it's doing this
not parallel but one after another and then it's taking roundabout for one repository
it's taking about 10 seconds currently and the whole build process takes two minutes.
Then there's the build workflow which is just standard NPM CI, NPM build and then it's being
deployed to a static server and this is the result of it or documentation page.
Where you see on the left side the docs that are currently distilled and part of the SDS
documentation and this will of course grow because we are currently in the process of
defining the standards and putting it all together so there will be a lot more than
in the future.
That's basically how we managed to do it and if you have ideas feedback critics then have
a look at our repository and we are meeting up in the SIG documentation, special interest
group documentation every second Tuesday from 11am central European time at you can have
a look at the docs.scs.community page or scs.community page.
What is still to come we are currently in the process of creating the whole framework
so we are structure wise adapting towards the ATAXIS framework you might know it's
I wouldn't call it framework but it's more like a text on me for writing excellent documentation
and currently the workflows are triggered manually and yeah soon to be automated fully
and there will also be interactive overview about the whole standards which worked out
currently within the sovereign cloud stack community and there will be a fancy community
space which is currently also in development.
Thank you very much.
Questions?
Do you do releases of scs?
Yes we do releases.
Okay so how do you handle versions of documentation?
We have we can if there will be a new version we will use the version versioning tool of
docusaurus which is basically a command line command and then it packages all files and
folders that is currently there and puts it into a version directory basically.
There are no separate versions on the website for the documentation it's just the latest
always on the website.
No there will be there will be a future different version on the website.
Okay yeah currently it's the latest.
No there was a person first here.
Thank you for this talk it's very informative.
So my question is what was your documentation pain point that inspired you to say hey let's
have a hackathon and let's put our documentation docusaurus and did you solve for those pain
points using your workflow?
Yeah actually thank you for a question.
Actually the hackathon was planned prior to this so it was it was perfectly placed for
us to solve this problem and the biggest problem was that no vendor wanted to change anything
with their existing documentation so no metadata and and then the thing is with this workflow
you don't have to manipulate the like external organizations documentation files or folders
and you just can copy them distill them implement them and have like the navigational thing
is only yeah we do it in with an hour repository so it's not it's minimal invasive basically
or folks updating your documentation before you change platforms.
I'm just not clear about what the problem was that was being solved.
Yeah thank you for the talk as well.
Just a question what are your input files I mean documentation appears in several formats
for instance as part of c files where you have to extract it in to I don't know PDF
or HTML or whatever.
Yeah we are we are only accepting markdown files.
And the problem the problem was that you have different vendors and for example if you if
you want to pull all those markdown files and throw it into one folder then it's going
to be a mess and so but we want to to curate how the docs is being built so that's the
nice thing with docuSaurus you can define within the sidebars how you how your whole
navigation is being built so you don't have meta data like lying directly in the vendor's
target repository with the individual documentation.
Any more questions.
Do you plan to support any other documentation formats like askyi doc or r text or something
like that you know like Sphinx is using askyi doc for example or more actually is you just
restart your text.
Yeah currently currently not but it would be possible to convert it in a separate workflow.
OK but also we use markdown because there's also markdown linting process that's refining
everything.
Any more ideas.
OK yeah thank you very much.