So, welcome to the second talk of today in the sovereign cloud def room.
And I'm very happy that Peter, founder of Pecona, is with us.
And this is now your stage, Peter.
Welcome.
Okay.
Thank you.
Oh, one.
That's fantastic.
Okay.
Well, so we're going to talk today.
And about wonderful topic of open source and its relationship with the cloud.
Now, I think most of you don't know me.
And I thought I would highlight my perspective first, right?
So you can understand maybe where I'm coming from better.
Myself, I was involved in open source since late 90s, which now seems like a long time
ago.
I was at that time building my first startup back in Russia.
And I took unconventional decision to use open source rather than stealing property
software, which was the most conventional thing to do in Russia in late 90s.
Afterwards, I joined MySQL AB before Oracle, before Sunmet.
That was like a tiny company without 40 people.
And that's where I got a lot of exposure in building and sort of promoting open source.
And I also was their founder and until recently CEO of Percona, a company which specializes
in open source databases, right?
And we release all our software as open source.
And since that time, I was also involved as advisor, mentor, investor, in some case, in
various companies around open source space, right?
If you want to summarize all that kind of presentation, a couple of words, would be
probably this, right?
I believe what everything being equal, open source is a better choice, right?
Of course, you tell me it's never everything equal.
But then I think this second thing applies, right?
I think as a member of community, employee, right, maybe manager of a company, it is always
better for you long term to invest your time, invest your resources into the open source
rather than just send that to some, you know, proprietary vendor, right, which will provide
more value to them than to you.
Now one thing to understand about open source is that the open source takes time.
This is a slide I shamelessly stole from a talk from Bruce with his last name, nobody
can pronounce, so I won't ever try it, right?
But this is the Bruce in PostgreSQL community, right, who often talks about PostgreSQL and
open source, and he uses this chart which says, hey, you know what, if you look at compared
to the property software, open source tend to take a long time, right, because if you
think about saying, hey, you know what, I get one kind of, you know, get a small team
together, you know, fund them and say, hey, build this, they can do it faster compared
to open source, which is kind of a lot more organic fluid, a lot more discussions, you
know, a lot more, you know, people operate maybe on a volunteer basis, each takes time,
but then over time it overtakes the property software according to many criteria in many
areas.
And as example which I would use is this, like Linux and Solaris.
When I was getting started with open source, I have a lot of friends which were running
a real unique super-
ration system, you know, Solaris, HPUX, AIX, anybody remember those?
Right, and they would think like, well, Linux, that is a toy, right, that's like a 32-bit
super-ration system at that time, doesn't handle, you know, multiple CPUs, well, you
could not even at the time have a file more than 2 gigabytes in size, right, I mean, you
know, like sounds like a joke, right, and right for if so, but well, where are we here
now, right, I mean, how many of you guys still run in HPUX, anyone?
No, like, AIX, Solaris probably, maybe there should be one or two people, no?
No Solaris folks?
Well, we can see what over time Linux, if it's kind of slow and messy at times, development
progress, right, really overtook that there are other operating systems, right, especially
if you look at the server side, right, then Linux is well-dominated.
Now we can also look, if you look at the cloud, we can see another comparison here, right,
I remember also back in those early 90s, where folks would be using, you know, ASP.NET with
Windows stacks, and wow, it is so fantastic, if you graphical user interfaces, whatever,
to us open source folks who would be coding, you know, PHP or Perl in VI, right, or Emacs,
right, if you are from the other camp, right, in that time, right, which was very different,
right, but if you look at how things developed right now, now we have a fantastic development
framework, right, very efficient for many open source frameworks, right, that things
evolve.
Now, at the same time, if you look at the cloud standpoint, we are kind of in a similar
situation.
You can even go to this kind of very polished, integrated, yada, yada, but very proprietary
stacks which Amazon or many other proprietary huge cloud vendors are ready to provide you,
right, or you can have open source solutions which are not yet as polished, powerful, integrated,
and so on and so forth, right, but I believe, well, they are going to get there.
Now what I want at this point to talk a little bit more about where we are now in kind of
a state of ecosystem, what is happening and what the trends are.
One, if you think about relationship with clouds and open source, you can say, well,
from one side, the cloud vendors have been making the open source a lot easier for other
people, right?
And if you look at deploying some open source technology, especially it applies, I would
say, to the databases, it's much easier to get, let's say, Postgres running in a cloud
vendor compared to getting your kind of, well, you know, highly available, monitored backup
for a Postgres cluster on virtual machines, right?
But on the other hand, we can also see all those cloud vendors use this kind of an old
strategy, which actually they used even before the cloud, which is called Embrace, Extend,
Extinguish, right?
And what that means is, hey, you know, why don't we take the open source, we make it
fancier?
Fancy may mean more features like in a database space, well, where I come from would be something
like Amazon Aurora.
It's wonderful, there are those kind of additional features, better performance, wherever, or
maybe more usable, maybe there's like a fancy GUI, so you can deploy it with a couple of
clicks, right?
Instead of, oh, I have to put some elbow grease, right, to do it the open source way, but then,
yes, you go there and you kind of check in in the Hotel California, right?
Which if you know the song, you can't really ever leave, leave again, right?
Now what I think in this case, it's important to understand and for all of us as open source
developers to recognize what really the usability and ease of view is increasingly becoming
that is a new frontier of the competition, right?
And I think that is especially hard maybe for people for my generation, which got used
to that very kind of hairy open source, right?
At that time, we remember, you know, compiling open source from source, right?
And kind of we have all that skills, right?
But if you think what is happening right now in a software industry in general, as well
in open source is this, one is a software just, you know, absolutely explodes in amount,
right?
Everything is software those days, right?
Amount of software which is being written will need to be written, need to be maintained,
extend, and so on and so forth is, you know, absolutely amazing and growing every year.
The same happens with data, right?
We're having more and more data and more and more ways to process and whatever that data
for good and for evil, right?
But at the same time, we are have to do that with less and especially with skills, right?
You can see as a software engineer and technology industry as well, we have a lot of people
getting in that stuff which are not going to really be able to debug Linux kernel code,
right, to, you know, have some, you know, just obvious basic skills, right?
Well, for them, you need to build a software which is easier to use.
The fact I think what is very interesting is what we can see increasingly some expert,
even in related to open source technologies which actually only have cloud specific skills,
right?
Well, especially in the US, right, I think adoption of a cloud is substantially forward
on, right?
You may have somebody saying, you know, I am, you know, post-gres-ql expert, right?
And you talk to them what that means.
He is very capable of provisioning, you know, post-gres-ql aurora on AWS with two clicks,
right?
But you say, like, well, you know what, what is patroni?
You say, what?
What?
Well, that's like some high-availability solution for post-gres, right, if you guys don't know,
right?
Which is very basic.
I think another interesting thing is what, especially in the large corporation standpoint,
a lot of them run to build their businesses by the book, right?
So if a management made a choice, what we are adopting, let's say, Amazon cloud or Google
cloud, Azure doesn't matter, they often then would come to them and say, okay, how do we
do that?
Give us the book, right?
And what are those cloud vendors going to tell?
Oh, they're not going to tell you, well, you know what, use our basic services which you
find in the other cloud.
They are going to tell you to use the most proper, advanced, you know, managed solution,
right?
If you read with Amazon, they'll say, hey, you know, go use DynamoDB, right?
It's awesome, right?
Or it's Amazon Aurora, Redshift, all that kind of stuff which makes you the most sticky
for the cloud and which is also providing the most margin to those folks, right?
So what is also interesting in this case, right, if you look for Amazon Aurora, for
example, as they see their customers getting more and more lock-in, the price differential
between their, your computer sources, right, you know, storage, right, and essentially
like in the software, it becoming larger and larger, right?
If every new generation of CPU can actually, you know, find that excuse, right?
So find that changes.
So that means it becomes more and more expensive over time, right?
And also you will see in this environment also really embracing scaling by the credit
card, right?
Because scaling is easy, right?
You don't have to figure out how to run the TAT server you have because getting the next
one would, bigger one would take three months, right, even if you get a budget approved,
right?
Like we used to have like 10, 15 years ago.
Now, you know, screw that optimization skills, right, you can just go to the larger instance
size, right, and that's easy.
And again, like from what we see from a database standpoint, a lot of databases in the cloud
are optimized very poorly exactly because of that trend.
Now what is interesting for me also is how that plays with their venture-funded open
source, which is a lot of open source those days, of course, right?
And what we can see is what they are really for protestions against unfair competition
from a cloud vendors, yada, yada, right?
And many of them abandon open source licenses, right, and go to something else, right, which
is well, really shifting to a proprietary software models.
Now this is, in my opinion, is very different from a community-driven open source, right?
If you think about, well, compare something like PostgreSQL to Mongo, right, which I think
is in the database space very opposite on that kind of open source, the
from a adoption standpoint, right, because cloud made PostgreSQL much easier for a lot
of people, right?
But at the same time, of course, now there are different players which dominate the ecosystem.
Yes, it used to be enterprise DB was the biggest dog, right?
Well now it is probably Amazon, right?
And other cloud vendors make more money, but you know what?
They are hiring a lot of PostgreSQL engineers and investing a lot still to make a PostgreSQL
better.
So at large extent, PostgreSQL community still benefits in this regard.
What also have been interesting for me in the last decade or so is the idea of growth
at any cost, right?
For a lot of companies you can find, well, at least in the US stock market, you know,
the more money company is losing, the better its valuation, right?
As long as you can grow a user base as well, right?
And in this case, you really gravitated saying, how can I grow faster?
That means focus my resources and cloud, which often allows you to, well, things simple,
though expensive, right?
Was very much adopted, right?
And for those companies, often didn't make sense to invest in efficiency, which I think
open source often brings ease, right?
Even though it requires a little bit more investment than elbow grease kind of and management
attention to make those things happen.
Even more though, you can see the cloud has been quite good at giving you your first short
of heroin for free, right?
You can find what every cloud author is saying, hey, oh, you're a startup, great.
We'll give you some big chunk of money so you can spend on us, right?
Or given the free tea, right?
And wherever solution.
Well, but I guess with this analogy, you understand, right?
Well, if somebody giving you a short of heroin for free, they may not always have your best
interest in mind, right?
Now, I think what is interesting is what there are some revelations which are coming, right?
I think in this case, and things are changing.
And I will provide a bunch of links to the detailed articles here, right, which you guys
can check when you saw the cloud.
Like this is interesting from this trillion dollar paradox, right, which talks about,
well, you know what, cloud is damn expensive.
And for many cloud companies, the very large portion of their cost of revenue is actually
cloud spent, right?
So if you are choosing to go with that cloud, especially kind of most expensive persons
on that, well, you know what, you have to be giving up on a lot of potential profit
margin.
Recently, you may also have this 37 signals which talk about while they are leaving the
cloud and they detailed that stuff.
That is also like a very influential company, right?
It's not very big dollar amounts, right, compared to enterprise here.
But I think it's very nice what they kind of went public in this case and say, hey,
guys, even in our scale, even if you spend in maybe, you know, like a less than $10 million
dollars, right, a year on the cloud, it makes sense, right, to actually do things differently,
right?
And $10 million may sound like a lot of money to some of you, but if you look at even kind
of like a mid-size and, well, especially more like logic operations, they often spend hundreds
of millions on dollars on the cloud spend.
Now another trend which I think is interesting, which is coming out, I think is GitOps and
generally the approaches where we have declarative versioned infrastructure as a code approach,
right?
Because when you do that, then often those kind of fancy, gooey point and click I can
do in the cloud is not exactly how you do things anymore, right?
That's where you kind of sort of do it more of a, well, through, you know, API, you know,
command line, if you will, right, things there.
Open source tooling is already better.
Hybrid cloud is another interesting trend, right?
And what I want you to see from this graph is what if you look at the larger the corporation
is, the more of them are embracing the hybrid cloud, right?
That's from the CNCF poll, right?
And if you are using public, if you're using hybrid clouds, multiple cloud vendors, you
know, public and private cloud to give event, you probably do not want to rely too much
on those, you know, property services, right?
Because they tend not to be as portable.
In the end, I think what you are, what we are seeing the open source kind of catches
up again, leaving us with kind of two choices here.
If you look at the AWS, which is obviously the biggest dog where you can replace that
with, you know, Azure, GCP, right?
Or, you know, some other major cloud.
You can really lock in the approach of a cloud vendor, right?
Or you can use their cloud native foundation stack, right, among others, right, where you
are really treating cloud as a commodity and building the value through their open source
software.
What I think is interesting from a cloud native environment is how big it is, right?
You guys probably cannot even see all the logos, right, on the slide, right?
There is a lot out there.
There is typically more than one solution for a single problem, right?
And some of you say, hey, that is too much, but that is also the open source way, right?
In many cases, we need in open source multiple solutions to the same problems, right, which
will kind of evolve, right, and maybe some of you will die off, I will join forces together,
and that is how great stuff happens, right?
But I wanted to show that just to illustrate how much momentum there is behind their open
source approach.
Now, I think in this case, what that allows us is to really, given the proprietary cloud,
it is originally intended role of commodity infrastructure.
Why am I saying originally intended role?
You can see this, this is actually the slide I took from some very old AWS presentation.
Then they were just bringing the cloud to the master's and say, hey, guys, you know
what?
You don't usually run your own generator, right, at home.
It's not convenient.
Well, yes, in some cases it makes sense, but mostly you buy electricity.
So you should buy the same from a cloud when it comes to compute resources, storage, yada,
yada.
It will make sense.
But here is a key difference, right?
If you buy the electricity, it is commodity.
You can buy the electricity from a variety of vendors or make your own, and you're still
all appliances going to work.
You don't have to change your TV or your fridge if you're doing the other electricity, right?
And that is kind of what a lot of cloud vendors want us to do, right?
Well, we'll provide you commodity thing, right, electricity, but you know what?
We also really want you to use those appliances which will only work with our kind of electricity.
Well, that sounds like bullshit to me.
So with this, I think we have really two choices, right, how we can approach those, the cloud,
which I will call as the cloud of software on account of freedom.
One is to use a lot of property features of your cloud vendors, sell your soul to the
devil, right, and all the other stuff, right?
So let's vote.
How many one is going to use that way?
Any hands out there?
No?
I would surprise, I would accept there's some people working for Amazon here on some,
I would say, yeah.
Yes, yes, okay.
And then we can use cloud of freedom, which is saying, well, cloud vendors are fine.
It's like a good commodity infrastructure providers like the internet providers, right,
just give us those commodity resources and we will build the rest of the stuff using
open source.
How many of you think that a good idea?
Okay, okay, that's better.
Okay, now in this regard, what I think is a very good API in this regard?
Well, it is there, the Kubernetes, right?
I would not say that Kubernetes is absolutely perfect.
It's not, but I think what every successful open source project started as a piece of
crap, right?
I mean, it's just how things go, right?
Because you build successful open source projects not having a solid technical foundation despite
what engineers want to believe, but building the movement, building the ecosystem, right?
And then those ecosystems, right, well, is able to redo the code, right, mistakes, wherever
and to build something, right?
With Kubernetes example, I remember there was messes.
Anybody remember messes?
Well, that was a very cool project, right?
I remember talking to those girls and they have, let's say five years ago, a lot of very
cool things which Kubernetes did not have, but you know what?
They lost adoption game.
And now you can see with things like I have next, oh, no, sorry, next, their container
storage interface and some other stuff.
Hey, you know what?
Kubernetes is getting a lot better for data intensive applications, right, not just for
this narrow use case of stateless applications it was originally designed.
We also now have either the data on Kubernetes community, right, which is a special community
which is focused on running data intensive applications on Kubernetes, right?
And what is interesting in this case from also the CNCF survey, we can actually see
what from 2001 to 2002 the databases, right?
So something which is technically was not something you would ever think to run on Kubernetes
five years ago is one of the fastest growing application type which is being run on Kubernetes
those days.
Now I would say even more, what we see right now is if you look at a lot of modern independent
database as a service providers, am I right?
All of those folks, they are actually using Kubernetes on the back end to build their
database as a service solution.
You may not know that, you may not care, but they are doing that and that means for them
well that is both efficient way to build it, operate it and that can be run, you know,
stable enough like at least with a good skill.
Another interesting result what's going on with Kubernetes is what we are having, well,
despite having Kubernetes already quite ubiquitous, right?
Hey, you can run it on pretty much any cloud if you look at many, you know, every distribution,
a little distribution now have their own Kubernetes destroyed, at least a major one, right?
You steal Kubernetes from VMware, right, and many other solutions right now, right?
But we are also having Kubernetes come into other places like I like this K3S solution
which is lightweight, Kubernetes, right, which you can deploy on the age IoT devices, right,
or if you just have, you know, couple of servers in your basement that you want to run Kubernetes
on.
We also are getting more solutions for visual kids, right, because if you look at, you know,
like a ROC Kubernetes you often would be seeing that, you know, console and YAML files, right,
and everything.
But now we are also have a pretty good dashboard which comes with Kubernetes, a Skibernetes
project, and as well integrations with applications, like there are solutions like kubep apps or
Rancher application catalog, right, you can say, hey, you know, if I am running Kubernetes
I can deploy open source and appropriate applications on my Kubernetes solution in a couple of clicks.
Kind of similar to what we see now in their major clouds, right, where we have their marketplaces.
Okay.
So, with that, where do I think things need to be going and will be going next as we are
getting more and more open source software in a cloud?
One, we still need to continue working on the better integrations because I think that
is the name of the game right now, right.
We expect really all the software and the software and hardware to be very well integrated
with each other, right, and that is something where I think a lot of property vendors put
a lot of folks in, right, because if it is not easy to make two things work together,
then for majority of the people it would not be accessible because remember what we spoke
about?
A lot of people do not have very advanced skills those days.
Related thing, of course, is the better usability, right.
I mean, we have expectations of usability very high, attention span very low, right.
I mean, I am not sure if any of you have like teenage kids or am I just too old here, you
know.
What do you think about the attention span those days?
Okay.
Well, and remember, right, those teenagers are probably already doing some work with
computers, right, you know, it is often taught as a middle school those days, some programming
skills, right, and they will be going in the industry in the next few years.
And the last thing I would mention and that is again maybe comes from my database background,
right, is making sure we also have a good experience if at day two operations, not just
day one.
In very many cases I see there is a lot of application catalogs and where ever say hey,
look at that, you can develop that application very quickly, right, but then if you really
want to maintain that, it is like, you know, with database you can't just, you know, tear
it apart and deploy a new one.
Well that is something which can become instantly quite complicated, right, if it is not handled
well.
Well, with that, I will end with my call to action, pretty much saying what I started,
right, I would encourage you to embrace the open source in the cloud, also invest both
in terms of your personal time and efforts and as well motivating your company to invest
in making it better because open source very much depends on our collective effort, right,
for its success and of course spread the world, that is how the movement grows.
Well with that, it is all ahead and I would be happy to answer some questions.
Thank you very much for your talk.
You said in your final slide that people should be investing in open source and invest in
making it better.
What are your thoughts on the new kind of trend you see of organisations like the sovereign
tech fund in Germany allocating millions to open source projects and things like that?
Where do you think the money should come from rather than, or is there a structured way
it should actually be allocated?
Well, so where should money come from, right, from open source?
Well look, I think that is a variety of things, right.
I think if you look in this case like from the government standpoint, right, it is classically
have been supporting, you know, public good with investment in research, right, the medicine,
right, wherever, like I think that open source is one of such ways how you can create a lot
of public good, right, which is wonderful.
I think though in many cases probably where majority can come from, right, these are the
public corporations, I don't know what probably private corporations, right, acting out of
their own interest, right.
I think in this case we all need to also work with that kind of like mentality change, right,
because you see like for years, right, even before like a Microsoft changed it and became
like all, you know, we love open source kind of company, right, it was all about like oh
open source is evil, it's like, you know, communists run open source, right, that's
how you, you know, lose all your, you know, property, right, open source is insecure,
yada, yada, yada, right, and I think that is something there that's kind of spread the
word is important, right, is to make sure well that is actually none of those things,
right, and really embrace an open source and the focus on the real open source can be very
good long term ROI for a corporation, so maybe not a short term, right, but the long term,
right.
Well in this case I probably want to mention one other thing which I think is still challenge
those days, right.
I think what the open source term is being bastardized, right, we can see many companies
they try to say oh our software is kind of almost as good as open source, right, and
but then they put you like well some very specially restrictive licenses, right, in
this case, right, and we need, right, or have like an open core when you have like a crippled
open source, right, and real property software and we need to make sure the company understand
where is what is open source, right, and focus on growing that compared to those, well, others.
Make sense?
Thank you.
Hello, thank you for the presentation.
In the beginning we started with a good willingness to make it very portable to other cloud and
that kind of stuff having the deployment that can be multi-cloud and we missed something
because at some point the experts that were there to help us were pushing for some proprietary
or non-compatible deployment and we are totally stuck now in one cloud provider.
How do you manage such a risk and what would you put as a rule set at the beginning so
that you would not fall in that pitfall?
Yeah, well I think that's a very question, I can say hey we made a mistake and now we
are stuck, right, well, I think in this case, right, if you're looking at portability, right,
I think it's important what that portability is being tested, right, so in your case, right,
maybe you say hey we are mostly around that one cloud vendor and we want to be able to
move to other cloud vendor if we need, well that means what you need to regularly test
your software that actually works on that cloud vendor so if incompatibility and over
reliance is introduced you can instantly squash that because if you don't do it, right, then
you know like three years later, right, then you finally want to do that you can say oh
my gosh, it actually turns out so much the things what we did not do, right, and I think
in many cases what is also important is what developers do not read docs, right, they tinker,
right, and often then you think like oh I'm using this kind of feature, right, in this
case I assume it works everywhere but maybe they are actually, you know, using something
which only works in this particular place, right, that is why testing is important, you
cannot rely on, you know, the developers, right, infrastructure engineers just, you
know, using their subset they are supposed to be using.
Okay, well, thank you.
Hi, thank you.
When we have some companies using proprietary cloud provider, we, it is difficult for us
to say that they need to move all their infrastructure as you just said, so is it a problem of offer,
it is a problem of the free software cloud provider offer to provide some easy tools
to use or it is really a problem of politics from the companies to say that yeah, we should
go to the difficult but free software, how do we manage with that?
Well, I mean, you're asking like is that like a technical question, right, or is it politics,
right, and the question is both, right, in this case, like yes, I mean if you look from
a technical standpoint I think there easier is if open source software where more is going
to be, you know, easy to convince, adopt, right, and so on and so forth, but in many
cases it is possible, it is also like a politics, right, because there are, can be some entrenched
interest for whatever reasons, right, or some belief, right.
I have seen a number of companies in my works, right, where people say oh my gosh, we are
running on, let's say that like a Microsoft stack, there is no freaking way it's possible
we move to open source, yada, yada, yada, yada, right, and then we have a new CTO, right,
and boom, right, you can say in a few years, right, like more than half of workloads are
moved to the, you know, to the different open source solution, right.
So I think in this case, like if you look at what is a primary thing, right, it is politics
and desire of a management, right, that is always a primary thing.
Thank you Peter.
Okay.
I will now like boundary this.
Thank you Peter.