Okay, well, some of you may be here for my first presentation.
This one is going to be different in much more technology focused, if you will.
And we will talk about their distributed storage in the cloud, right?
And my goal of this presentation is kind of provide you a very general overview as an
of options which exist.
I am not an expert, right?
And probably something I'm going to say is even going to be wrong, right?
So if it is, then say, say like, this is fucking wrong, Peter, you know, so I can fix my slides.
So when I talk the next time, I am, has a wrong stuff, right?
So don't be shy.
Be engaged and that's going to be fun for, more fun for all of us.
So the thing I would say to start with, we discussed about it, as I believe there is
a different ways you can approach your cloud, right?
One is where you really kind of walk in with the cloud provider and then another one is
what you really use, one of the really there open source solutions out there.
And as I spoke in my previous presentation, we can see what's, well, like I would imagine
that is how the cloud was originally taken.
Well, I won't spend too much time on this because I already had a presentation, but
and also because we are not have too much time.
Now one thing what I often have people asking me is about their open source, right?
Which I think this conference is about.
And if you are thinking in the open source from the business standpoint, right?
We often see a lot of those different companies, right?
Which promote them as open source or somewhere around open source.
But how do you know if it is for real, right?
And of course, one of those you can look at the open source license and so on, right?
And this is all their good stuff.
Another is also to make sure what you ask yourself, right?
Or maybe even kind of company representative some of the questions, right?
About how things look, right?
One is you always think about how you can deploy that kind of solution product, right?
On your own without getting any additional cost, right?
Because software may be kind of open source, but they can, right?
And the source is available, but well, actually maybe their, you know, binaries are provided
only to four people who have a commercial subscription.
Well, in this case, it's maybe technically open source, but on the practical side, there
is some of those problems, right?
And especially I have seen some open source projects which would essentially, you know,
withhold details about the build process, right?
So it's not easy, right, to do that, right?
And another question that I always like to look at is a choice of vendors if you need
any help, right?
For many companies, just saying, hey, we're just doing to go ourself is not going to work
or want to hire somebody.
And in some of the new kind of license around open source have been kind of some restrictions.
Well, you know what, you cannot provide the consultant services around this software,
right?
Or something like that as a license, right?
And I think the very valuable thing about the open source is to see wherever you can
improve the software for your purpose.
If something in an open source doesn't really fit, right, can you contribute to that?
And again, that I think is another very interesting property of open source software where maybe
different shades, right?
Sometimes open source vendors may be more or less open to that kind of things.
Well, now we've had maybe open source public service announcement.
I would touch briefly about open source.
I think I spoke about that, the previous speaker spoke about that as well.
That is a fantastic API, right?
And that is something we are going to focus on here, right?
And why I mentioned Kubernetes here, right, as we are going to talk about the open source
storage in the cloud, I will focus a lot about, hey, what exactly choices you have in the
Kubernetes environment, right, because if you're really speaking about the cloud, right,
modern life scale application, a lot of that is now being built around Kubernetes.
Okay.
Now this storage in the cloud, what does that really correspond to?
Well there are a lot of different storage types we really can't consider those days,
right?
And here is the list which ranges from the simple stuff as a node local storage all the
way to the databases, right?
I define storage myself in a very general way in this case, hey, we're all you need
to store the data somewhere, well that is a storage, right?
Now there are some of those things like a node local storage are relatively simple,
right?
You know, direct replacement from like a, well, file systems we have on our operating
system for a long time.
The others such as databases can be very complicated.
It is not just, well, a database, right?
But we can see databases being different by data model query language like various internal
design decisions and so on and so forth, right?
Even if you look at the data model, right, these are some of the most common data models
which you would see.
And what is interesting, or the last I think like maybe 10 years by now we see really this
explosion of the different special purpose databases versus approach before where we
I think had like relational databases absolutely dominating ecosystem.
What is also interesting in this regard is what we are having the databases right now
not just being focused on a single data model, but many databases are able to support multiple
data models, right, which is I think is a big trend and even potentially speak multiple
protocols, right?
Like here are some examples, right?
If you look at the click house which is data analytical database, it is able to talk click
house but as well as postgres, SQL and MySQL protocol, right?
So the idea is, hey, you know, wherever programming language and libraries you already use, you
can just connect to us and, you know, run your queries, you know, fantastic idea, right?
Or the time series database, Victoria Metrics also is able is implementing things like InfluxDB
and Graphite API for data ingest, again, to think very, very smart.
We also see some frameworks which allow us to do some of conversion and translation.
For example, FEREDB, the projects allow you to use postgresQL backend with MongoDB front
end, right?
Or Amazon released recently Babelfish which turns your postgresQL in Microsoft SQL compatible
database, right?
So a lot of this, I think, you know, interesting integration is going on those days.
If you look at their databases, you also see a lot of difference in a database for a purpose
and design, right?
Like we are speaking about operational analytical, how is it used, how it's internally structured
and so on and so forth, right?
And why am I listing that is because if you look at their at a complicated environment,
right, with a lot of complicated database, it's very unlikely you will be limited only
to one database, right?
Of course, as the previous speaker mentioned, well, you know what, you probably don't want
to have 50 because that is way too much complexity, right?
And you want to be very mindful about how you introduce them to you, to your environment,
but it's probably going to be more than one those days.
Now we also speak about besides storage about distributed storage.
Like why is that important?
Well if you think about this, that is all of redundancy performance and scale, right?
I mean, saying if I just have a storage which is not distributed, right, which is kind of
really sort of leads with one device only, I will be limited and all of those.
I think this is even more important in the cloud, right?
Because if you look at the age before the cloud, often we would be in a case where we
have some one very powerful, very redundant server, right, maybe with a hot swap rate
and redundant power supplies, right?
And we expect that beast is never going to go down, right?
Well, that is not how we operate in the cloud anymore, right?
We assume any company in the cloud is going to die, right?
And they actually do die more frequently, right?
If you look at the stats within like a mean time within failures, let's say 4 VMs compared
to what you could get with some beast from the past, well, it's going to be different,
right?
But that means we need things distributed at least from a high availability standpoint.
Okay.
With that, let's look a little bit about storage types as promised.
One is our commodity storage types, right?
And this comments to the previous talks, I did this.
Commodity storage types, they are pretty much the same in every cloud.
Their minor differences, but they are, I would say, like a commodity building blocks, right?
We have a relatively simple interface and usually it is relatively easy to migrate.
So the lock-in, right, the word we don't like on this track, right, is going to be relatively
low with them.
One is node local storage, I mentioned.
Hey, well, it's pretty much every major and even your second tier cloud typically offer
you some kind of local storage, right?
And it can vary in terms of performance it offers and so on and so forth.
But that is pretty much the same, right, from what that gives you, right?
And that is fantastic, right?
But again, that is where I would, if you are looking from that, I would focus on the performance
because that is where surprises can await you, right, and say, hey, this cloud vendor
and dad both have a storage, right?
One of them has its, you know, implemented as a very fast NVMe flash storage, other something
not so fast, well, that may have a very big difference for your application.
The second most common one would be natural block storage, right?
That's typically how we store the data so that can, in the cloud, so it can survive
their death of an instance and Amazon would be EBS, right, and all the other cloud has
something similar.
We also have some additional solutions, in this case coming from the property vendors,
right, like from those vendors, right, which, you know, provide you some additional features.
And there is actually quite a lot of different solutions which exist if you want to roll
out their block storage in the open source, right?
And I think this is kind of very cool and that shows how things evolve in open source
space, right?
We had a surface block storage idea for a long time, so a lot of projects evolve, right,
and they have a lot of choices.
The next type of storage in the cloud would be your file storage, right?
Like when you can say, hey, I can mine something, mount something locally, not as a block device,
but as a file system, in many cases that would be your NFS or SMB-compatible file system
or both, right?
Again, all the clouds will support something other.
File systems, there are a number of major property cloud vendors, they support sort
of solution.
In this case, and again in open source, there are also solutions in this case, right?
And you can see there is like some connections, right?
So many open source protocols, you just say, hey, we are focusing on the storage, right?
They may provide different interfaces, right?
And well, and if you, and that's kind of makes sense.
The next one would be the object store, right?
And that is, I think, a very important component which appeared in the cloud.
And that is interesting when you come over to storage, right?
Because if you think about the age before the cloud, we always had that, you know, local
file system, we had like, you know, network servers, right, with your remote file system
for a very long time.
But we didn't really have anything like S3, right, until the, like at least kind of in
any common use, right?
And that has appeared and used a lot those days as a building block for many applications.
Because it's actually very cool, right?
It's kind of bottomless, right?
You can access it on HTTP directly, so you don't have to, you know, process the past
data through your application all the time, right?
It's very scalable and so on and so forth.
Even many databases, those days, again, like both proprietary and open source are now starting
to be built by using object store as a backend instead of your conventional file system.
I think what is interesting in this case is what there are a lot of also object store
cloud vendors which exist, right?
So it's not just Amazon, like, or even kind of major cloud anymore, right?
And here you can see like two types of commercial vendors, right?
Our usual suspects, NetApp and Portworx, they do have a solution for S3 compatibility, right?
But also we have solutions like Wasabi or Blockbase, right, which are offering you S3
which you can, comparable services which we can use as less costly replacements or kind
of like a supplemental to your main cloud, right?
For example, you may say, well, you know what?
I have my stuff in Amazon but I want to make sure also backup somewhere else, you know,
just so well.
There are numbers of vendors out there.
And then if you want to like run the storage in your, well, locally, right, there are also
now number of vendors.
And I specifically wanted to flag with Minio in this case because I think they have been
the most successful, right, as providing S3 compatible interface in their, for private
cloud in those days.
Okay.
Now let's look at the databases and data stores.
I think the interesting thing about the database and data stores is what unlike the previous
storage types which are kind of related to the commoditized, right, have relatively
simple interfaces and relatively simple to replace.
Like if you store data in S3, right, and now want to store it with Minio, well, guess what,
right?
You have a different endpoint, maybe have some, you know, little configuration differences
that that is not a big deal.
Database is very different, right?
And even so-called, I would say, like a similar offerings actually often end up to being very
distant because of their, well, of a lot of complexity which exists in the database space,
right?
So that is, I think, where using some open source solution is especially important.
So let's look at some of the databases in this case.
What I would call Q stream data pipelines, right, wherever we want to call it, right?
That is increasingly is a very important component of modern, you know, data driven architectures,
right?
You often want to say, hey, we have a data comes in, right?
And maybe it kind of flows to a number of, you know, consumers being maybe, you know,
processed along the way.
It's kind of your data plumbing, right?
It's not conventional database, but it's very important.
What I think is interesting in this case, right, is what there are actually a lot of
options.
Well, you see at the Amazon AWS, right, and they probably will have more services than
that, right?
They have a huge amount of solutions in this case.
Some of that is because they kind of started first, right, maybe implement something and
then open source solution exists, right?
And in general, right, because Amazon has a huge number of different services those
days.
I think it's like more than 200.
If you look at the proprietary solutions, in this case, you can see Kafka is the, I
think, the most common solution these days for building your plumbing.
And then additionally, we can see this technology Red Panda coming up, which is saying, hey,
we are providing to you something which is Kafka compatible.
Remember, I mentioned earlier, right, those days people are often building compatibility
of existing protocols, but it is faster, simpler, yada, yada, right?
I put them in a proprietary side, like specifically Red Panda, because they are one of those companies
which started as an open source and then later changed the license to, you know, something
not quite open source.
We do have a lot of solutions in open source.
It's good to point out that Kafka instead is Apache open source project, right?
Confluent has a commercial offerings built on a Kafka, but Kafka itself an open source
as well as actually many other open source solutions in this space.
What I think is interesting in terms of like queues, there is also often certain solutions
which exist in the given programming language ecosystem, right?
So you will find what often, you know, go-long people will have their own choices compared
to the Java people, right?
And so on and so forth.
If you look at relational databases, well, in the cloud, we have a lot of choices often
ranging from providing you a wrapped and extended open source databases to also a proprietary
database available in the cloud, right?
If you want Oracle or Microsoft SQL, typically that also is available on most of the cloud.
What you also see in this case, so there are a lot of property solutions in this case,
right, which exist, right?
And in many cases you'll find those either coming from your property vendor or you see
a lot of companies those days which are providing the property management service, right, around
open source databases.
So for example, you'll find Avian here, right, which is on like one extended provider management
services for a lot of open source databases, but I still put them as property vendor because
if you can say, hey, you know, is there this open source version of your kind of fancy
GUI, right?
So instead of paying you, can I take it and add it in my own data center?
Well, the answer would be no, right?
So, so, foundation, like its solution includes open source data components as a core database,
but as a whole it is, it is not, right?
And that applies to many vendors in those days.
Now if you look at the open source, there are actually a lot of databases available
both from like an old guard like MySQL, Postgres, MariaDB, right, as well as a new folks in
the book like Ugovyte, TIGB, Pircon also provides our own version for MySQL and Postgres, but
typically that is, requires more of, I would say like manual work to deploy, right, compared
to databases as a service which exists in a proprietary space.
Here are some choices in analytical spaces, right?
That is, I think, one of the big decisions for relational databases because of kind of
building a database which optimizes for transactional workload and analytical workload is kind of
quite different, right?
They are designed and shown very, very different, right?
And so there are typically different choices out there.
There is a little bit of overlap those days, right?
Some databases position themselves as hdap, hybrid transaction analytical databases, but
typically the databases are, you know, with one thing or for another.
Here are some relational and analytical databases property, right?
You can see number of very common solution here and then you also have a number of open
source solutions in this case as well, right?
I think what is very interesting is what, as you look at the analytical standpoint,
that they are, it's also like a very big focus, right, if a very large amount of needs, right?
So for example, if you look, some databases mentioned here like, you know, Preston, right,
and saying, hey, we want you to provide information so you can take data from all the different
data sources, right, and join and query wherever you'd like, right?
That's very valid use case, right?
Something like, you know, click house focus on saying, hey, we provide you sort of like
a real time analytics, right?
If you want to insert the data and then have it available for a query next second, well,
that's something what we focus on, right?
Or tigb, as I mentioned, they are the hdap database, okay?
Have some sign to speed up.
So the other class of databases, which is quite important, is the document store, right?
I think if you look at for many, you know, simple applications, some new developers,
right, you just say, hey, you know what, SQL, relational databases, yada yada, too complicated,
right?
You want just to stuff our JavaScript objects directly in database and work with that natively,
not trying to spread them on normalized schema and relational database.
All of the cloud vendors, major one, they're offering their property solution in this space,
as well as we do have number of property solutions in this case.
Like I would say MongoDB and Couchbase are probably the most popular in this regard,
which come in both cloud and enterprise space.
Now if you look at the open source, that is where I would have to say like both open source
and source available, right?
Because well, frankly, the most popular document database is MongoDB, which few years back
ditched open source license, right?
And well, so it is not open source solution anymore, right?
If you're looking for open source compatible, right, there is an early stage open source
MongoDB compatibility, there is early stage project ferret DB, which provides interface
for Postgres, right, which I mentioned.
One thing I would point out here is what relational databases, actually, the lot of work recently
is being much better for document store, right, specifically in JSON support, where you take
MySQL, Postgres, right, or even SQLite, all of them are also usable, right?
So in some cases when you say, well, you know what, I want to have some document store,
but I don't really completely hate open relational databases, that also can be a choice.
Key value stores, that is another important model.
In this case, I think it's interesting what they really can go into two different buckets,
right?
One is, hey, we are using that for caching, it's kind of in memory, transient, if you
lose it, we don't care, but we want that to be fast.
There is number of solution here.
For a property in all cloud solutions, I think Redis is a main leader.
In this case, we have both Redis Enterprise and the cloud.
If you look at the open source key value storage, solutions in my opinion, we also have a key
value, or I would say like a key value plus plus, because some of those solutions have
a much more powerful language than key value, would be DynamoDB, CosmosDB, Bigtable, right,
in a cloud space, Redis Cloud, and the enterprise versions of open source solutions, that's
what exists here.
Here are some examples of open source solutions, which have key value stores, and again, like
a key value store plus plus.
You would find, especially Iris Pike mentioned here, they are, well, do much more than a
key value store, Cassandra as well, but they, I would say, don't position themselves as,
I would say, powerful as document stores.
So, yes, we have also time series databases, that is another class I wanted to cover here.
Right, again, you can see solutions from a property, vendors, from a cloud vendors, property
vendors, and probably what they're most interested here is their open source.
It is also interesting what the time series database is also related in you, in technology
which has a lot more, I would say, choices those days.
Well, let me finish.
I would also mention maybe Percona's role, right, in all of this and what we are trying
to do, right?
What we try to do is to really see, to push the boundaries on what possible, specifically
open source databases.
Like, hey, you know what, if you want to have something which is totally open source, our
focus is on MySQL, MongoDB, and Postgres.
I mentioned MongoDB is not open source anymore.
Well, that's not our choice, right, but our choice, and we are having as much of our tooling
even for MongoDB open source as possible.
And what we build is 100% open source software around that, right?
If you look at our distributions for MySQL, MongoDB, and Postgres, right, generally include
a lot of features of enterprise companies need, like, you know, all you'd see in authentication,
whatever, but it is completely open source, and we focus both on your kind of conventional
or old deployments on Linux as well as we have operators for Kubernetes, right?
I think you have, like, some of the more advanced databases out there, and all that stuff, again,
besides MongoDB is open source.
We don't have any proprietary solution.
Plus, we do have a pure quantum monitoring management, which we position as a single
tooling where you can monitor and manage databases.
You know, you can get something similar to a database as a service experience with Kubernetes
back end, and again, that is all, you know, 100% open source, which you can play with
if you choose.
So to finish it up with our storage in the cloud, right, as you probably have seen me
going through that, right, some of you I see falling asleep, some of you rolling in your
eyes and that is totally appropriate reaction, right, because there's a lot of shit out there,
right?
It's like a lot of options out there.
So important to know here, hey, there is no one size fits all, right?
You guys can look with fits for your job for what your applications need.
But one thing I wanted you to come out with cases, like one last most of the takeaway is
what we could see in all, like, whatever slice and dice, all those areas, there have been
a choice of more than one open source solutions available in every single class of storage
you may need in the cloud.
So that's all I had.
Thank you.
We have a little time for questions.
Hello.
My question is about an interesting tool which used to exist and Percona used to have it
in the MySQL package.
Hand a socket.
Yes.
So I think it was kind of discontinued and I don't think it supports MySQL starting from
5.7.
So is there any movement in direction of supporting this kind of tool which enables you to access
your relational database both ways in a traditional SQL way and in a highly available, highly...
Well, that's right.
So the question is about the hand or socket interface for MySQL.
And yes, and there was this interface, right, gradually it's, I would say, came mostly out
of use, right, and we, you know, stopped supporting that.
If you're con as well, there's a couple of replacements, right?
One is which I think generally cover most of the use case of what hand or socket did.
One is MySQL supports memcache protocol, right?
So if you look at four key value store memcache comparabilities out there and then there is
also something called docstore, right?
That is MongoDB-like protocol, right, which allow you to store documents, like JSON documents
in the MySQL.
That is an other choice, right?
So I think within those two, well, it covers most of the hand or socket use case as well.
Okay.
Thank you, Peter.