So far, your stage is yours. I'm really looking forward to hearing about on-premise data centers
do not need to be a legacy. Thank you. So, hello everyone. And just to be clear, this is going to
be the topic that we are going to cover a little bit of history, some lesser-learned, and then
some technology bets that I think that would make sense in such conversation. So, about me, I have
been a Linux user for 20-ish years. I've been working with Linux for close to 20 years now,
and I currently work with Red Hat and do basically similar kind of conversation in my day-to-day job.
So, let's start with a little bit of history of the cloud. Let's call it this way. So,
Rackspace got founded in 1998 and I think was the first company that defined itself as cloud. In
2005, Softlayer was founded. They defined themselves as bare-meta cloud. And then in 2006,
we have the S3 launched by AWS, which was the first service of AWS. 2006 again, EC2. Sorry,
yeah. And then Google App Engine arrived, IBM bought Softlayer, creating it, IBM Cloud, now
called. And by 2021, AWS has more than 200 different services. So, what about the history
of the known cloud? Because what we have seen are old cloud environments, but those are nothing
new if you think about this. So, in 1964, which is probably older than anyone or most of the people
in this room, IBM introduced the CP40 and this machine had time-sharing technology, which was
very different from what we call today cloud, but still it was probably the initial point of the
history of the cloud. And in the late 60s, IBM released Simon, which is an hypervisor. By 1974,
the two kinds of hypervisor get defined as step one, the bare-meta virtualization, step two,
the hosted virtualization. And by 1998, VMware got founded and in 2000s, majority of companies
moved from bare-meta to VMware's VMs. 2001, ESX got released, which was type one kind of virtualization.
2003, we have the first type one open source virtualization, SAN. And in still 2003, VMware
introduces Vmotion, which allows you to basically move a machine from one host to the other without
rebooting it. And 2008, Microsoft arrives with Hyper-V. It previously had some other kind of
virtualization tool, but Hyper-V got launched in 2008. So what is the cloud? Why we are
distinguished the first group and the second one? Wikipedia says that cloud computing is the
on-demand availability of computing system resources, especially data storage and computing
power without direct active management by the user. I don't think this is a good definition.
I think that a better definition is a business model where one party runs to a second party
computer system resources, especially data storage, cloud storage and computing power,
with the smallest granularity possible. And my point is, cloud is not technical,
it's a business model. And if you think about, we move from renting machines like VPS on a
monthly basis, and then AWS introduced the concept of EC2 that was initially on an hourly
basis and then minute and then second, and now you can buy lambdas or similar kind of
things for milliseconds. And in a way, also, CPUs had the same shrinkage. So we move from
full CPUs or sockets to VCPUs, which basically is hyper-threaded threads, to fractional VCPUs
with lambdas or similar services. So my point being, the whole thing about cloud is not
technical, is only about the business side of it. So what can we learn from not only
the last 20 years of what we can define as cloud, but also the previous 50 of what we
can define as non-cloud, and more specifically, because we have seen that the cloud model
actually works. The non-cloud model was not very functional to the business, to the point
that very often those data centers got outsourced or in some different ways moved to the cloud
in the sense that moved to someone else. And the business started to expand constantly
those machines due to the basically OPEX model instead of the CAPEX model. So there is one
big aspect that we need to remember about this, which is the separation of concerns.
So standardize the interface between the infrastructure and the workload. If you go in legacy data
centers, very often you have 1,000 different kind of systems that the infra people have
to provide to the workload people. And this is because, oh, my system is different, my
software is different, whatever. In the end of the day, that is a huge load for the infrastructure
part of the business. Second, the scalability needs to be at workload level. So the infrastructure
also needs to be somehow reliable and within some SLAs. But if the system has to stay up,
if the application has to stay up, the application will have to take care about this.
And third, workload have an abstract concept of whatever is underneath it. So the physical
architecture. They don't need to know which data center they are in or in which rack,
what is the nearby server, and so on. The function, so we also need a functional business
model for a good managed IT system. And the first part is, as before, standardize the
interface between the workload and infrastructure so that it's easily countable and priceable.
Second, build back the infrastructure cost to the workload owners. We have seen, at least
in my definition of cloud, that we still have two parties. One that delivers a service and
the other one that consumes it and pays for it. So it's very important to create this
also internally in companies or organizations of any kind because this allows the infrastructure
side of the business to justify their expenses over some kind of at least recognition of
revenue or whatever, cost recovery, whatever. And third, keep the cost down. This is a key
point. AWS, Google, those companies will do everything they can to keep the cost down
because they need to be positive, cash flow positive. Obviously, if you are a department
in a company, it's slightly different, but it's very important to still be cash flow
positive because this will guarantee you that you will not have any issues over time with
this part of the financial model. And third, maintain control. We have seen the clouds
are obsessed about maintaining control and obtaining even more control on their hardware,
their system, whatever. And this is very important for your own cloud if you want to be able
to maintain it for 10, 20, 50 years. So the first one is, I would say do not use, but
be very cautious on using third-party properties software. Those companies can go away, can
change pricing model, can do whatever, be aware of this. Second, evaluate very strongly
the buy versus build decision because when you buy, obviously it's here now, but you
don't have the know-how about this. So probably you will want to build a lot of your systems,
not the core parts, but maybe the dashboard layer or that kind of thing so that you can
effectively manage it however you think better. And third, be very aware of lockings because
those will bite you over the course of the years. So, okay. How do I define the locking?
I define it as the product between the probability that a component will require substitution
during the solution lifetime and the total cost of the substitution. So for instance,
Linux, if you base all your architecture on Linux, it's going to be very expensive to
move out of Linux. But in the other hand, it's very improbable that you will be needed
to do it because very probably in 10, 20 years, Linux will be here. So a couple of points
on technologies. The first one is keep the complexity of your system at the lowest level
possible. Systems will get more complex and more absurd over time. So at least at the
beginning, start with the simple thing possible. Second, prefer build time complexity over
runtime complexity. It's way easier to automate a build thing than to automate something to
be run. And also when something breaks, it's better if it's simple because it's easier
to fix. If you have to compile yourself, compile it, but try to keep the complexity at the
runtime at the minimum possible. Third, minimize the amount of services that you deliver to
your business or your workloads owners so that effectively you can guarantee that those
services are exactly what they require and you are able to deliver them in a sensible
way. So I think that one big point is containers. Delivering a container-based solution at least,
it's probably the best option I think today. And use a Kubernetes distribution, whatever
you prefer and choose. That makes sense. It's fine. And we'll see later the Kubernetes
APIs are now fairly well-known, fairly abstract, and fairly used so that those can be a good
interface between the infra and the workload side. Also you can use a do-it-yourself community,
call it whatever, a distribution. You can buy a commercial distribution of Kubernetes.
If you do it, first, be sure that it's fully open source, what you're buying, so that you
decrease your lock-in because you are decreasing the cost that it will take you to move from
this to any other solution. Second, from a trustworthy company, hopefully that company
that you buy it from will not fail tomorrow because if it does, you will have a bigger
problem. And third, with a long track record of not screwing their customers because it's
not good. And if they are heavily involved into the open source community, it's even
better because that means that they are driving the development and they do have all the knowledge
needed to eventually fix issues as soon as they arise. So around automation, use an immutable
approach to your infrastructure. If you start to have different things and weird infrastructure
going on, it will be a dead sentence. Second, version your infrastructure, GitOps is an
option. There are many others. No matter what you do, try to have versions so that effectively
you can potentially roll back or at least see what changed from a version that is known
to be working to the current one and automate the whole process. If you have humans involved,
you will have issues. It will cost more and it will be effectively less resilient and
reliable. So putting all together what we have seen, I would suggest to first create
a multi-data center architecture so that effectively you have all that redundancy and that kind
of things, but hide them from your developers. Maybe they know the region concept or the
exact concept, but don't show the physical layout to your users, otherwise they will
start to do weird stuff. Second, use a tool to manage the clusters. Open cluster management
is an open source project that does it. There are other projects that do similar things.
It's very, very useful and it will help you over time because probably you will end up
running many clusters. Third, I would suggest personally to standardize on the Kubernetes
APIs as the only interface between the workload and the infrastructure because those are,
as seen, very known. Use a bare metal container platform so don't use virtualization or other
stuff into it. You will have hopefully enough workload to justify tons of physical servers
that don't add complexity with virtualization in between. Automate all the infrastructure
pieces and configurations, obviously, as seen. Start providing only a few interfaces to your
business and then eventually extend them when needed. An example would be an OCR registry,
object storage, and pods, deployments, those kind of basic things. Then if your business
comes out saying, oh, we really need that, then eventually you expand. The thing is,
only provide new services when you are sure that there is the requirement for it. For
instance, let's say that you want to do a database as a service. You already have onboarded
100 applications. 80 of those actually use MySQL. It would make sense to provide a MySQL
as a service, but it does not make sense to provide 50 different databases as a service
of which 48 will never be used. It's only complexity and cost for you. Then create a
simple UX for your users that completely obstruct everything that is below. It could be even,
you know, push your Kubernetes configuration here and we will manage it. Hopefully, then
you will be ensuring that all this stuff is versioned and so on so that even when the
workload fails for some reason, you can say, look, a version N minus one was working. You
did something. Now it's broken. It's not the infra. This was it. Thank you. I don't
know if we have a couple of minutes for questions. No, if there are. Thank you for your talk.
Could you expand a bit on the I didn't get why the what was the advantages of building
multiple data centers at first? Yeah, so that is usually a business requirement because
they will say, oh, we want to have everything that is a or at least this service needs to
be a and with one data center, it would be hard. Also, it really depends if you are a
small organization, maybe two data center, three data center could be okay. If you are
a big organization, maybe spread throughout five, 10 legally different regions, then you
will need OZ 3050 data center. That's a completely different scale. OZ all those are very generic
suggestions and then you have to apply them to your specific situation. And just a quick
follow up for that. How do you hide that from the workload developer? So the line just after
that one where you say they have to not know about the multiple clusters. How does that
work? Yeah, so if you pick AWS, for instance, they have the concept of region and a Z. Some
a Z. So it's are not that centers. Some are data centers. Other are parts of a data center,
but different availability zones within the data center are others are containers in the
sense of like 40 food containers full of servers. So the user does not know. They know that
there is region X, a Z one, two, three. What one, two, three means no one knows and no
one cares. And that's the thing. Thank you for the talk. And in your definition of lock-in,
you spoke about cost of portability and multiply by probability of portability, but doesn't
it like if you file to assess the probability of portability, wouldn't you fall in lock-in
without being aware of it? Sorry, what do you mean? Okay, I know I will always run my
cloud in Amazon Web Service. Why would I need portability? But then then I start using locked
in products. So I will never be able to leave. Yes. Well, you will be able to leave. It's
always possible to leave. You will simply re-write from scratch your whole application
and you leave. So what is the cost of that? A billion? Okay. So now it becomes a billion
of lock-in. That is my point. You can re-write tomorrow from scratch from the West up. It's
possible. How much it will cost you? A billion, five billion, a trillion? Okay, that is your
lock-in value. And that's the thing. Obviously, I would suggest you to keep the lock-in as
low as possible. So try not to re-write. To be in a situation where you have to re-write
everything. Yes, thank you. So we short-transmitted that one. Hello. One quick question. I'm going
to ask you a question. So if your organization has a traditional manual approach to operations,
which thing would you automate first? I would start from very simple processes just to ensure
that, you know, it works in the organization. The organizations start to understand it. Processes
like, you know, create VMs or create containers, whatever kind of thing you do. And then some
things such as patching and so on. But if you really want to go the automation way,
it's way easier to, after you have tested a little bit the thing, start to say, okay,
now we have the version two of the environment that is fully automated from day zero. Otherwise,
you will always be in a kind of automated but not completely automated situation. Thank
you. Thank you all. Thank you.