Okay.
Thank you for showing up in person and so many people.
So actually my first time at FOSTAEM and I think it's super excited to see so many people
and coming back to conferences but also such a crowded conference.
So I mean the talks previously were super full.
Now it's almost half full or half empty depending on how you look at it.
And even for such supposedly boring topics like a sovereign cloud, I mean that's immediately
sparked associations with state and GDPR.
I mean all the cookies that you have to click away.
So sounds boring at first but I think there's also some value in it and I think there's
a journey where open source can help to make a sovereign cloud come to life or like look
at some aspects of it.
This is me.
I go by the name Durandom on GitHub and on social media.
Three days ago I changed roads so now I'm in sales again.
Yikes.
I'm a manager as a managed open shift black belt so I'm still looking at the cloud topic.
Open shift is like a cloud on a cloud.
Before that I worked quite some time on AI, on AIOps in the office of the CTO and the
last thing that I did for two years now is imagining or revisiting open source now in
the age of cloud and seeing how open source principles can also apply to operations.
So we're going to look at the operate first community cloud.
Why do we need a community of practice around operations?
What does this community cloud look like?
And also where is it?
So I think this will be a, it's not really a hands on talk but you can take things away.
You can if Wi-Fi works for you, you can log into the cloud right now and I hope to see
you in some of the meetups or in the community after that because it's really open to anybody
who wants to learn something about operations or wants to teach something about operations.
So when I first heard the term sovereign cloud, like I said, it sparked the sovereign, the
king who has now also occupied the cloud and I put it into my favorite search engine and
it immediately came up with a lot of definitions on sovereign cloud.
There was one from VMware, some from Telecom and they all looked at different aspects and
these days in case you're not living under a rock, everybody's talking about jet GPT
so I thought maybe let's talk to this AI who already read all the definitions for me and
ask it about sovereign cloud.
And this is just the end of my conversation so I wanted to highlight the differences between
the noun and the adjective sovereign.
And the noun sovereign refers to a personal identity that holds supreme power and authority
while the adjective sovereign describes something that is supreme or superior in rank.
That still sounds not really friendly to me like do I really want something that is in
supreme power over me and why should I care about this then.
But this is also a notion of independence in that adjective because that's what I always
thought about when thinking about it a little bit.
And Jet GPT came up with this that there's a notion of independence in the adjective
to be described sovereign means to be independent not subject to control by any other person
or entity which if you think about it that also implements if you have supreme power
then you can also move away.
And having the highest degree of power and authority.
The term emphasizes the idea of self-governance and supreme power within a given context.
And the context seems to be cloud.
So when I look at sovereign cloud at least in my small world view it means I have the
power to move away.
I have the power to control stuff and I have that largest amount of independence.
And that seems at first contradictory to that business model that we saw in previous talks.
So somebody in a nice division of cloud is I'm running stuff on somebody else's computers.
So that doesn't seem to be like a lot of freedom because I have some some lock in.
But actually open source led a path away from lock in.
So I think it's important that we apply these open source principle also to operations.
And if you these days look at a cloud is it is it really open.
I mean it's built on open source software.
You get your RDS or some some other product and underneath.
Yes it's running my secret it's running elastic it's running all that open source stuff.
But you're still tied to that to that experience that the cloud provider imposes on you.
If you want to rebuild that with open source solutions.
You can do it it's it's looking pretty complicated.
So you need to master a lot of these technologies you need to stick them together.
And there's a reason for why people defer to the cloud because they are interested in the
workload.
They just want to swap that credit card and consumer build away the application.
But I think the last speaker put it really or the previous speaker put it really nice
that log in to be defined as a as a product of cost and the likelihood that something
is going away.
So you have to deal with that stuff.
But open source somehow if you go to this slide here as an open source actually showed
a way out of this and the last the left side of that funnel here is the traditional open
source as in as in software contributions funnel which we all know for decades and which
we all love.
So you find a project you use it.
There might be 100 users of it and at some point something breaks.
So you might file an issue.
You already contributed because you filed that issue and then maybe at the last time
even somebody fixes or maybe you fix that project.
So there's really a funnel of 100 users then 10 percent reporting issues and making up
that community and 1 percent actively contributing to that project.
If I'm using something as a service I'm essentially drowning this funnel.
So I'm stopping at the at the API layer.
I might contribute to the underlying open source software that might run this service.
But in terms of contribution I'm usually I'm stuck with maybe filing in the support case
and maybe the provider comes back to me but I have no possibility to actively contribute
to that and maybe fix that API outage.
But maybe I'm the only person having that problem and so the cloud provider doesn't
even care about this.
And this was the notion that our team thought about when thinking about open source in the
age of cloud where it's where there's more value apparently in running and providing
the software than the software code itself.
Or at least that's on equal scale.
And as we see with many enterprise distributions or business models you can get the source
code of that database or that service but you don't get the sometimes you don't even
get the built tools you don't get the tools that actually operate that service the SLIs
the metrics that you need to run there the runbooks etc.
So every deployment is either behind a paywall because that's the differentiating factor
for that company or you have to learn it yourself.
And it's actually quite hard to open up something also with legal constraints right.
So you might have might have proprietary and PII personally identifiable information in
in there you have logs so you need to make sure that you don't expose any of these secrets.
So that there's a tight balance and that's why most companies or most projects default
to close.
And even for even for communities that run their infrastructure like the Fedora infrastructure
that's somewhat open but you still need to be going through a lot of hoops to contribute
and to do something.
So it's not really open by default and it's also not meant to be as a blueprint for something.
Only 10 minutes left but I think I can go to the next part of this presentation.
So this is the this is the concept right.
So we need to shift left we need to open up operations and practice something so that
we build up a community so that we don't have to build our operational deployments from
scratch.
And while that was this is the concept of this operate first idea we also thought you
need to have something physical something hands on where people can actually contribute
because otherwise it would be just a talk show.
So somebody needs to lead the way and implement that stuff and we tried to build a hybrid
cloud with full visibility into the operation center and hybrid cloud these days is for
a lot of people Kubernetes.
So we have two bare metal Kubernetes classes running at the Boston University with 34 nodes
and 1200 cores so it's not a small setup.
Then there's one larger cluster running in AWS from the OS climate project which is also
managed with these operate first community cloud ideas and we also work with a German
super scaler.
That's what the layer below a hyperscaler means.
Jonas they donated some hardware and we deployed also some some classes there.
So my vision actually is to to have a really resilient distributed clouds set up operated
under these principles at as many hardware or cloud providers as possible.
Six hundred and twenty six individuals locked into these into these clusters about 200 namespaces
are there.
That's the so we do a lot of stuff on most of the stuff is happening on GitHub.
We have 150 people on the operate first in the operate first community.
There are like 1000 issues being filed.
Since it's a red hats bootstrap project it's like one third or half of the people are red
hat employees but there's also a lot of university contributions from American universities and
also a lot of open source projects already contributing them.
It's just a highlight of some some of the more noteworthy projects using this infrastructure
like OKD the upstream of open shift or OS climate or Janus IDP which is a project for
for some backstage plugins.
So backstage it's currently one of the one of the more hyped tools for a service developer
portal by by by Spotify.
These are some of the services that are running there like the usual stuff that you would
expect from a cloud set up.
We have our city for doing get jobs.
We have Grafana for monitoring stuff.
We have Tecton pipelines for building things.
There's a brow instance running for doing CI CD and a lot of other things.
So every and that's all deployed by the community in a GitHub repository where you can integrate
in into into these into these other services.
And I think that's where the actual value comes from.
So let's get real.
We love hands on keyboard and as I said it's all done via a really a get ops SRE no a get
ups get first approach.
The current entry points for you would be going to operate dash first dot clouds or
and that clicked through some hoops and you end up at the service dash catalog dot operate
first dot cloud which is an backstage instance where we for one showcase the services.
So you go to the catalog you see all these services with all their dependencies and you
see all the managed clusters there.
So you click on one of these clusters and you are presented with a single single sign
on logging screen.
And if you choose the second option operates dash first you can log in with your get up
account.
So it's authenticates against get up and without even signing up for an account you get a read
only view of the cluster which is pretty awesome.
So you see how these these services are being deployed and how other community services
are being deployed.
So you get a a a hello world example a live hello world example of a of of a fully production
cloud environment which you would see at your at at your site either at your for your project
or for your customer whatever.
And we documented the way and the why we came up to certain decisions.
So in this case it's application monitoring or there's also how to store credentials in
a cloud.
And these are the the questions that you will face if you're setting up a a your own local
cloud and we documented these for to bootstrap either other deployments or to contribute
back so that you don't have to really read through so many blog posts and documentations
and make your own choice.
There's some dashboards here and these are the dashboards that we use for troubleshooting
or the community uses for troubleshooting.
So you would see Kafka or open data hub and Prometheus live dashboards and here's one
dashboard for our for our clusters.
And that's the that's the GitHub org where you would start talking to us or talking to
the community.
The main entry repositories the support repository you can ask questions or you start with a
one of these templates and one of the coolest templates here or processes is onboarding
to a class as you get a form.
It looks like a form it's a it's a GitHub template.
You choose which cluster you want to be onboarded the team name and then we have some automation
in place that would automatically create a pull request to our get ops repository and
we only have to say looks good to me to it if you're for the person that's part of the
operating team and they are onboarded.
So that's also giving giving you some sense of how would I automate my local cloud's deployments.
You don't need to do that but it's it's it's a way to bootstrap you and there's a lot of
other issues going on and assets.
It's a community so things will eventually also break right now we have problems with
our object storage is broken if you are an expert in Nuba or in object storage and you
want to get your hands dirty and rebuilding some of that stuff.
This is the issue.
So to me though here which will give another awesome talk at the end of this track here.
Left some comments how to get started.
Nobody worked on it yet.
So it's up for grabs.
Thank you.
One question.
Hey you provided a good definition for sovereign cloud.
Who are the customers for sovereign cloud.
I don't know to be honest so I'm looking at it really from a technical perspective and
I think my key takeaway is everybody who wants to build their own clouds probably wants to
be sovereign in running their cloud and then you have to focus on stuff like minimizing
vendor lock in and being able to move to another cloud provider or move your data across clouds
to jump just on the question.
The transmission system operator is one of the customers that would like sovereign cloud
because of the resiliency that we need to have because we have critical infrastructure.
I think that was a statement not a question right.
All right take out your smartphone snap that QR codes and there's a biweekly community
meetup where you can meet all the wonderful people that are involved in this community
well.