So, hi everyone, welcome to my talk, welcome to Bearbox and first of all can all of you
raise your hands whoever heard of Bearbox or ok that is quite some and to use it actually
in some projects ok that is what I thought ok as I thought I am Marco, I am from Pentatonix,
I am an embedded software developer, my tasks are related to kernel, to bootloader, to BSP
stuff, graphics stuff and so on and so on. Most of the time I contribute my work to upstream
sometimes not, I live in the north of Germany and that is it and again there is just a brief
introduction to Bearbox who is not becoming familiar with and then let us add a new driver
so an example then add a new board so you can see how you can add your own board and
upstream it to Bearbox because we are always welcome new boards and then we make a short
hands on hopefully we have some time for it.
And yeah ok then welcome to Bearbox, Bearbox started in 2007 as a patchlet of U-Boot and
the patchlet was called U-Boot V2, this patchlet was retracted and then yeah Sasha renamed
it and yeah made an official fork of it in 2009. We have monthly releases, we have mainline
support in PDX test and we have mainline support in Biltwood and we want to have mainline support
in Yokto and Open Emmented Core. I sent patches just yesterday you can find the link below
or in the slides. Please any discussion is welcome and if it is not getting into Open
Embedded Core you can pull it from MetapdX or Metabearbox and ok yeah we have 330 contributors
around and yeah it sounds not that much but we are living, Bearbox is living, we have
around 1400 commits per year and ok the graph is not that optimal, it would be wise all
the time but yeah 1400 it's not that bad and we are live. So let's add a new driver
and what our design decisions in Bearbox. We are coming from Linux, we don't want to
re-render at the third time or the 10th time so we are taking the Linux device driver model
and stripping it down to bootloader use case. All the configuration is done via device tree
since day one, since we get forked and yeah device tree and K config, some of it, most
of it, device tree and we also since we re-use the Linux device driver model we also re-use
the driver frameworks. We just strip it down to met our requirements and then push it and
it's mostly just in copy and paste with small addictions. So then let's add a new driver.
As I said it's in copy and paste, copy it from the Linux source, copy it to the Bearbox
source and then adapt the code. So how does it look? In some example I took the clock
from some workshop and I made a diff, you can see the diff above, it's Linux 6.1 or
6.2 I thought, 6.2 RC blah blah and yeah just adapt the headers because of course Bearbox
does not have all those headers and replace them with some Bearbox headers and then replace
some functions we do not support. That's not very important, it's just replace some functions,
remove it or replace it, yeah. So we adapted the driver, we are finally done. So we have
ported our new clock driver for this workshop. So we have changed 50 lines of code for a
driver of about 171 lines of code, this makes about 1% or 2% of adapted code and we ported
the driver to Bearbox, to a bootloader. Most of the time when you port the driver, clock
drivers are a bit specific but some drivers do IRQ and Bearbox we don't have IRQs so you
need to port it to some polling mechanism but we have headers for that so we are welcome
you to port your driver or your driver of choice you need into a bootloader. So then
after we ported the driver we need to compile it. So let's add a K config in the make file
because we are a kernel related bootloader. So let's add a K config menu entry and at
the make file. It looks like a kernel. So then we are finally done. We need to enable
it, we need to compile it and we have everything. And of course we can test it with what with
the Linux device tree because we are device tree based and since we are using the complete
driver from Linux we also have the complete bindings from Linux so we can use the upstream
Linux device tree. You don't have to do anything just copy and paste. So yeah, feels like writing
a kernel driver isn't it? To me at least. So to sum up this a bit the Bearbox drivers
are just a stripped down Linux version driver and drivers can be ported with little effort.
There may be some more effort if you have more complex drivers or if you port frameworks
but by frameworks that really depends. There are some really easy frameworks and there
are some frameworks which are huge. So I added some examples which frameworks we already
support. A very decent one is the NetDSA. I think some of you know the DSA stuff. This
distributed architecture for switches. I think it's called distributed switch architecture.
And we support it in Bearbox because we are using the NetDSA framework from Linux. So
we can do NetDSA with my bootloader so you can speak with your switch like you do in
Linux. So that's very impressing for a bootloader. And yeah. Then let's move on. We have added
our driver. Let's move on and add a new board. Before we can add a new board I wanted to
explain you some stuff, some internals of Bearbox. I don't want to go into detail because
we don't have that much time. If we have more time at the end I will show some more examples.
And yeah of course you can raise your hand if you have questions in the end. Anyway.
We have a single binary in Bearbox which you flash to the target. But this is composed
of several components. One of it is the sock header. This is really, yeah. One of it is
the sock header. Then we have this pre-bootloader. Then we have some firmware blocks like device
tree like third party firmware blocks, TFA or ATF or DDR firmware. Depends. Depends on
your sock also. And then we have the actual bootloader. So as you can see there is a singleton
image but it is composed of different firmwares or different blocks. In Bearbox we do this
composing for the pre-bootloader and for the firmware and for the actual bootloader we
do link it together and the sock header is appended. So yeah also the sock header is
very sock specific and this appending mechanism depends on this image creation tool which
also sock specific. So then also some booting stuff need to be known before you can add
the board. Most modern socks are booting from a bootworm. So you plug in the check and then
the bootworm comes up, the bootworm loads some stuff from the boot medium you configured
via some TBIOs or some pins and then it is loading some kilobytes into some static RAM
and then it jumps to the static RAM and then executes the pre-bootloader and then the bootloader
and the bootloader finally decurnals. So now look into deeper and add a new bot. So as
I said the bootworm is loading this sock header. It is decoding this sock header, it is really
sock specific and it is executing the software which was loaded from the boot medium. Then
the pre-bootloader gets loaded by the bootworm and set up the DRAM and then it is loading
the real bootloader to the DRAM after it is set up to DRAM and then it jumps to the actual
bootloader or if you have some more decent socks like ARMv8 based socks then it is jumping
to the TFA and the TFA is jumping to the bootloader which we previously loaded to the DRAM. So
okay, now we know it and now we add the pre-bootloader stuff. This pre-bootloader stuff does not
have any support of device pre-orso. It is kind of low level stuff, it is kind of dirty
stuff. Anyway, in Barbox everything starts at the entry function. The entry function
is always the first point where it starts. Okay, let's add a iMIX 8MNEvk. With this entry
function we have some header functions after we load it into the DRAM and then we are calling
the NXP, this is some bot specific code which we get here and this set up the UART. So we
have pre-bootloader, low level debug stuff and then as the function calls startATF, this
function set up the DDR as I said. It loads the Barbox to the DRAM and starts the TFA and
the TFA is then jumping into the loaded image or into the given image, into the image which
we loaded previously at the specific address we told TFA. And after we loaded this we get
started by this last function and that's actually the Barbox entry function. And here you can
see the pre-bootloader is passing the device tree. So the pre-bootloader also loaded the
device tree and it's passing the device tree finally to Barbox. So Barbox is just running
with the device tree. So now let's come into the Barbox to the bootloader. This is the
stuff where all the metric happens, where all your bot specific fix ups does happen
like you have some overlays for some displays, you have different displays, do some detection
and then apply device tree overlays. So your device tree is finally finished, finally fixed
up for the kernel and the kernel don't have to do anything. This can, that stuff can happen
in the board code. And yeah, such a board code is also a driver in Barbox and after
the board code finished to load everything and do all the metric it jumps to the kernel.
So as you can see here, this is the entry function for a board code. Again, this looks
again for me to a kernel, like a kernel driver. You have some driver struct where you can
put all the functions and you have this compatible which is also checked and then depending on
the compatible which is given, the driver is loaded or executed or not. And then you
have the board function and the board function, you do this metric stuff I told. You do detect
where to come from, do some metric stuff and set up this is some kind of special in Barbox.
We have some Barbox update handler. This is some kind of, yeah, you know this metric in
the real submarine where you can have some scripts to load something from MMC to some
metric addresses and here are metric addresses and here are metric addresses and there are
five commands or so. In Barbox we have the Barbox update command and this is the handler
for it. We just forget the handler and in Barbox we can just call Barbox update and
finish. So there is just one command involved. And yeah, then finally the support code is
fixing up the file and then it finishes and starting the kernel. And the kernel is to
all the remaining stuff. So that's not part of my talk. And yeah, okay. So we have added
a driver, we have added a new board and everything apart, the pre-bootloader stuff feels like
a kernel to me. So I hope I can make you a bit excited about and you can visit the link.
This is Barbox hosted online on the tiny emo emulator. Yeah, just click on it and you can
try it out. Yeah, what else? Barbox says now it's coming to the improved part. Barbox has
a rich shell with autocompletion. The shell has history, the shell supports scripting
and so on. The shell is also called out. What you would see when you visit the link. What
do we have also? We do also have virtual file systems. This means no more commands and offsets
like you know from U-B
and you know how to mount from system D where you visit some directory and magic happens
and it gets mounted automatically. We also do have that in our bootloader. And we also
have memory mapped IO access so we can check the memory, we can manipulate the memory via
MD, via memory wide so MB. And yeah, as I said earlier, we have this Barbox update command
which is pretty amazing because it's hiding all the ugly stuff. It's just Barbox update
and you are done. And also pretty amazing in Barbox. We have multi-image support. It's
some language of Barbox. It's something you are compiling Barbox and then with one compile,
with one dev config, we can build 100 or more boards. And this is something I wanted to
show you right now with an hands-on. So now it's, I hope everything works as expected.
So yes. Is it readable or should I increase the size? Okay. So it's just a small script
I wrote. It does nothing. It applies make-dev config and it enters the dev config so I
can show you something about Barbox. So it's like, again, it's like a Linux kernel. And
here you can see system types and here you can see all the boards we have enabled. So
all the boards, not just one board. And okay. Exit. Everything is fine. And then it's calling
make compile. So okay. That's nothing fancy here about. The fancy stuff starts at the
end. Let that happen. And hopefully. So okay. Now we are at the end. We are finished compiling
all the stuff. And now we are building our images. And we are building around 100 images
right now with one command, with one dev config. And that's pretty amazing because I know how
some or I know BSPs where you have just two different U-boot configs to have one U-boot
for an SD card and one U-boot for an EMMC or one U-boot for an spy and one U-boot for
an SD. That's not the kind we are working. We are saying one image will order. And then
also you compile it and you can select as many boards as you want. As soon as. Yeah.
And test some limitations. The sock must be the same. So we. Or the architecture. So this
was at I mix seven. Sorry. I mixed four sevens. So all I mixed six and so on and so on. And
now we can see. So. No.
And then we have built. So we have built. 132 images just in one minute. And that's not
doable with U-boot. At least with my knowledge I can't do it with U-boot. And yeah. Of course.
And then as I said we have this. Or. If it would work. Yeah. We have this. Online mailbox.
And then we also have an editor. We have also VI but VI is not that good working within
the web. But we have also added and then we can edit some stuff like going here and hitting
blah blah or ha ha. Anyway. As you could have seen this script. And. It's nothing special.
It's just a script. Which checks some environment variable and then that's what. That's it.
I wanted just. Yeah. Half an hour ago. And then. We can handle. This. And see. OK. Global
first time. It's not that. And then we can say OK. Since we have history. We can move
up and I didn't edit. OK. Then it's a global. First time. Oh. Nope. Also all the completion.
So global. And. Food for them. And then we say hello for them. 20. Yeah. 23. And yeah.
That was a short head on. It's pretty amazing. There was a really. I really would like it
to see you if you have contributed to books if you send pictures if you bring your board
main line and. Let us enjoy.