Hello, I'm Frederick Denis, software engineer at Collabroix and I will present you the Bluetooth
test in wire plumber and perp wire and wire plumber.
Pypewire is a low latency, graph-based processing engine that attempts to handle the audio and
video streams.
It is intended to replace both pulse audio and jack audio systems.
Wire plumbers in charge of creating the audio and video nodes and the link between the nodes
according to the policies defined by the system or the users.
Most of them are designed for desktop, main distributions are switching to them or to
the embedded.
More specifically for Bluetooth, the Bluetooth classic audio profiles are divided in two
main categories.
The mono, the stereo and mostly unidirectional audio streaming called H2DP and the mono and
bidirectional profiles which is entry profile and it's a profile, the letter less and less
used.
For the Bluetooth classic audio profiles, H2DP stands for advanced audio distribution
profiles, it aims to manage audio streaming between media player and headset or speakers
and in this table you can see the supported codecs.
The first one is SBC codec which is low complexity fast and low C but is implemented on all
devices.
The H2DP specification allows other codecs like AAC which is optional and not implemented
on all devices and this specification allows also other codecs not defined in the specification.
Most of them have been implemented to improve the audio quality but are not supported by
all devices.
For example, the EPTX family of codecs can be found on Qualcomm devices or need licensing
from Qualcomm or the LDAC codec is found on Sony devices.
In
the LD3+, which is an enhanced version of the codec used in LED audio which we'll talk
later.
Some founders have the ability to do bidirectional audio on H2DP with the fast stream codec which
is an evolution of the SBC codec or the EPTX lossless codec which is one of the EPTX family.
Just one I was saying, last year we were able to pass the Bluetooth qualification using
both PIPEWIR and WYER PUBBLER on the Steam Deck.
HFP stands for hands-free profile, it is used for communication usage but unlike the H2DP1,
it also defines the commands to interact with telephony using a set of AT commands.
This can be done with external demands like HSP, HFPD or Ophono, Ophono adding a complete
support for the modem or with a native backhand which is only set, a limited set of AT commands
allowing to complete the connection with Bluetooth devices.
This can be used with configurating application.
Last year we had the native backhand, the support for modem manager allowing to have
a complete telephony usage from inside the Bluetooth, from inside PIPEWIR.
So with Ophono or modem manager, PIPEWIR adds a complete telephony support to the mobile
distribution device, device distribution.
HFP supports two codecs, the mountatory one which is CVSD which is an arabian audio connection.
In this case, yes for the CVSD the audio is sent directly to the Bluetooth chipset which
will anchor the data through the Bluetooth circuit and the second codec is MSBC which
is optionally a fixed configuration of SBC but it needs both support from kernel and
the chipset and it is automatically detected during runtime by PIPEWIR.
But on some hardware devices the chipset has a direct audio link connected to a nodial card
or to the modem.
To be able to support it we had a hardware score of 1.2 mode which allows PIPEWIR to
use the score socket to create and connect and configure the remote, the link to the
remote device.
While Wirepambert will create a pass-through node allowing the user to select the Bluetooth
remote device as an audio output and then the data are sent to the audio card which
plays them to the Bluetooth chipset which will at the end encode and send the data over
the year.
Now we'll do a quick overview of the new low energy audio specifications.
The idea is to unify the stereo and mono audio profile and replace both H2DP and HFP.
It has a better sound quality with the new ICTC codec and it has an ease-of-colluse
radio channel to guarantee bandwidth and minimal delay.
By default it is able to support bid bidirectional audio for every usage.
It supports multi-stream support replacing two wireless.
It also supports hearing aids and with the new hourcast mode you are able to broadcast
audio without interaction between the transmitter and the receivers.
This handles in a lot of new profiles and specifications.
The one in blue are already supported by BlueZ and Pipewire but there are not so many devices
on the market to test with.
They are still set as experimental in both BlueZ and Pipewire and in some configuration
to be set if you want to use them.
Regarding the broadcast support, it is already supported, the low level is already supported
in the kernel but there is still some work to do in BlueZ and Pipewire and mostly find
the correct euix to be able to share audio or to select the broadcast you want to listen
to.
Thank you.