Thanks for introducing me.
Hello and welcome also from my side to the embedded dev room.
We're going to hear something today about Delta-like streaming of encrypted over-the-air
updates for ROG.
So luckily I managed to put the entire abstract of the presentation already in the title.
So what we hear about is the changes and developments during the roughly two or three years that
happened in ROG, the ROG updating framework.
And so it's basically the development that happened since we've last met here, I guess.
So short notes about me.
My name is Sandrik G
I'm an embedded software developer.
I work at Pangotronics.
I'm the team lead of the integration team at Pangotronics and I'm the co-maintainer
of the update framework ROG that we will hear more about soon.
Pangotronics for those who don't know, it is a company based in Germany and we provide
professional embedded Linux consulting and support and work closely together with the
community and with since the beginning I think more than 7,000 patches in the Linux kernel.
So a short overview of what we hear today.
So the first thing is a short introduction into what ROG is for those who are not that
familiar with but very, very short.
Then we talk about the bundle format because this is crucial development for or the base
for all the further features that are listed here.
So the first thing I will talk about then is bundle streaming.
Then we will hear about adaptive or Delta like updates, how to encrypt our bundle, give
a short outlook on recent development about app updates and at the end we have a short
look into what is coming next on features and what is in the ecosystem.
So yeah, a typical over the air field update scenario could look like this.
We have here our server, the server, the image that we want to deploy to the target.
We create an update artifact from it, sign it, upload it to our deployment infrastructure
and then we have the individual targets, update targets here that download the update and
install it.
And there's also still this conventional not so over the air use case for example using
the USB stick.
So what ROG handles is basically two parts.
The first one is the creation of the update artifacts, the signing, verification and so
on and the actual installation, the phase safe installation of the updates on the target.
So yeah, basically ROG is an embedded Linux update framework so it handles the phase safe
and atomic update of AB systems, so redundant system where you have one partition where
you're running from an inactive partition and when you update you write your update
into the inactive partition.
Once you're done you switch in the boot loader to the inactive partition reboot and everything
is fine.
ROG is basically two parts on the target.
It's the service that handles the update that runs and installs here and it gets its view
on the system from the system configuration file.
And yeah, the artifact for updating we call in ROG a bundle.
A bundle consists of the images that should be installed.
It consists of additional hooks or something like this and a manifest that holds the description
what these images are for basically.
So it's written in C with some utility libraries to not reinvent the wheel for everything.
It's licensed on the LGPL and hosted on GitHub.
And it was started in 2015 and I think the first release was in 2017.
So yeah, as I already mentioned, the bundle format is quite essential for the next things
that we talk about here.
So let's first of all have a short look at the initial bundle formats because this was
a motivation for changing the bundle format then.
The initial bundle format was quite straightforward.
It was just all the artifacts and the manifest packed together in a squash file system.
We signed this squash file system and append the signature to the end of the bundle.
So the verification is also quite easy.
You just have to read the entire bundle and have to read the signature to be able to verify
the bundle.
So yeah, this is also the downside.
Even if we don't also just want to access the manifest, we have to always authenticate
or read the entire bundle.
So this is quite slow and if it comes to over the air updating, it requires us to always
download the full bundle before we can access any data in this.
So yeah, this is bad if we want to use it for streaming.
So this is why we have introduced in 2020 a new bundle format.
And this bundle format is basically called the Verity format and it uses the DM Verity.
So short intro, a device mapper system in Linux is a generic abstraction of manipulating
block devices.
So a device mapper has the same API as a block device has.
So for the upper layer, it looks like it's just talking to a block device.
But below it can manipulate the block device, authenticate data.
It can merge data together like we know from DM Lendier and there are several device mappers
in the kernel.
So the one that we talk about here is DM Verity.
It is basically an integrity protection method for read-only block devices.
So the rough concept is that you split the block image into several chunks and generate
a hash for each and of these you recursively do this again and again until you have a single
root hash and then you can verify each single block until the root hash recursively.
So yeah, you have a data protection or integrity protection for read-only files.
The Verity table is just appended to the image.
So let's see how we use this in the Rauch bundle.
So we take our images here and first create the Verity hash and the root hash.
The Verity hash is simply appended to the bundle and the root hash is now placed in
the manifest.
And then we just sign the manifest with an enveloping signature which means that the
manifest is the payload of the signature.
And what this gives us is now the verification of the manifest is quite easy.
We just have to verify the manifest or the signature and get the manifest content.
And inside the manifest there's also the root hash.
This is then automatically trusted if we have verified the authentication of the manifest.
And then we can set up the in Verity and use the hash tree appended to the manifest and
the authenticated root hash and then for each access to each chunk or block on the block
device this is authenticated to the Verity in the kernel and this allows you to have
fully authenticated random access to your bundle.
And you also you only need to verify by the time of using the data.
So the next logical consequence is to implement streaming.
So up to now Rauch was not so over the air.
So downloading means that we assume there is an external service like Hawgbit or an
application or an SCP that downloads the Rauch bundle to the target device and then with
Rauch we start installing it from the local storage.
Well the disadvantage of this is obvious.
We have to have some extra space on the target where we can store the bundle and the artifacts
can in a modern system become quite huge.
And so the approach is that we implement streaming or downloading in Rauch itself.
And if Rauch is able to do this and directly download it to the target device that we update
then no intermediate storage would be required.
So let's have a look how this is realized in Rauch.
So first of all what we do in Rauch is that we spawn or fork an unprivileged helper process
because Rauch runs as root as it has to update the system and you really don't want to use
a root service to download data from the Internet.
So it spawns an unprivileged helper and this helper acts as a translation.
It plays a block device on one side and talks to the update server via HTTPS range request
on the other side.
And HTTP range request should be supported by all common web service also like TTP support
this and it's also supported by many container delivery networks.
And if we combine this now with what we've seen with the access to a variety bundle then
we have fully authenticated random access to the remote bundle.
And yeah we can randomly access so no intermediate storage is required.
So the next need when we are able to download things is normally that we want to save download
bandwidth because bandwidth is limited, expansive or something and the normal approach for this
is to do conventional data updates.
It means you have two versions of your image on your host system, calculate a delta and
then you perform the update with this delta image on the target.
So if you have the exact version that you have to calculate the delta for on your target
this works very well, you can go here from version two to the target to version three.
But if you now have a system that is on a different version, yeah this fails because
it simply doesn't apply.
So it's an optimal diff, it allows very small updates but yeah you're required to have access
to the different image versions on the host and you only can update step by step.
So from version one to version two to version three.
So in Ralc we've chosen a different approach, a more generic approach for optimizing download,
this is called adaptive updates.
The concept behind this is that the bundle or the manifest itself provides a number of
optimization options.
So with each option there's normally an additional data connected that is stored in the device
for optimizing the download but since we are able to stream the bundle we don't have to
download these additional data that is stored in the manifest.
And then it's a responsibility of the Ralc service on the target to see okay which of
these capabilities do I support and which can I use and which is the best one.
And there's always the fallback to use a full bundle download so you're always able to download
the image you want to install.
One method, adaptive method, generic one is the hash index.
The idea behind this is that you split your image into several chunks and hash each chunk
and generate a hash list from this.
And for installation you just basically do the same on the target.
You take your target device, block device for example, you hash it with the same algorithm
and create the same hash index.
And then for the optimization you just download first of all the hash index that is stored
in the bundle and then you compare it line by line with the hashes that you've calculated
on the target.
And then you can download or just need to download the hashes that differ between what's
on your target and what's in the bundle.
And this works both for the intended target version but also if you come from a fully
different image then you just have to download a bit more because the diff or the hashes
that differ are a bit more.
For both devices this is already implemented in the current drought version and there are
also plans to support this for file based updates using Rsync and offline generated
Jackson files.
The next topic is bundle encryption.
So the motivation is I think quite clear, you will have some sensitive data in your
bundle and you want to protect it because you have it on an unsafe cloud storage or
an unsafe communication channel.
So in Rsync we have implemented this in two stage approach.
So the first one is a symmetric encryption of only the payload.
This is what normally already the build server does.
And this does not yet require access to the key material.
And the second part is the individual encryption.
Then you can take the symmetrically encrypted image and encrypted per recipient.
You can just take one key and encrypt it for all your devices by using a shared key or
if you really want to do security then you can also use per device or per recipient keys
and encrypt the bundle for many individual recipients, many thousands.
So this again uses a device mapper, a different device mapper.
Now we use DMCrypt.
It's also quite simple.
For the generation of the DMCrypt image or the image we use for DMCrypt we just split
up the original image into equal sized chunks, generate random symmetric key and encrypt
each block individual.
And the DMCrypt device mapper then just provides a transparent description of the images.
So if we access a chunk there then yeah, DMCrypt just decrypts this chunk we just selected
with the key, with the symmetric key which is the same used for encrypting.
And if we combine this now in the bundle, so we have here the image, encrypt it and
combine it with DMVarity then we have a blockwise authenticated decryption.
And since we have random access through the device mapper and the DMVarity format we also
have the possibility to stream an encrypted update.
So I'm short on time, a few notes about app updates.
So far in Ralq we assumed the application is normally the application.
We assumed a monotonic system where the application is the one thing that the device should do.
And so we said okay, the application is normally either part of the root file system or you
can have it in a separate slot.
But it actually anyway linked against the libraries that are contained in the root file
system.
So it's fine to install, it's always together with the updated root file system.
The reality is showed it's a bit different and there are more and more demands of having
the capability of doing container updates, doing app store like updates and with you
also have one vendor which provides a base system which is rarely updated and other vendors
provide the applications which are much more frequently updated and additional data should
be added there.
And up to now we had no solution for this in Ralq and said okay, then use Ralq for the
base system and use another update or update approach for this application or file updates.
What we are working on and this is in a quite premature state actually is Ralq artifact
update.
The basic concept behind this is that you have a slot for artifacts and inside the slot
we don't do image based updates but we do directory or file based updates.
And then we provide the same as we do for image based updates.
We ensure that the update is atomically and we also support both the case where we don't
have any dependency of the app of the container to the base system, this is what you see here,
but we also support the use case of having a dependency on the root file system but the
need to more frequently and independently from the root file system update your application.
So yeah, and together with our checks and files, the idea is that this again also supports
streaming and Delta like updates.
So just a very quick, I'll just show the other features and community things.
We've switched to mason build system recently, this is already merged.
It wasn't when I started the slides.
So a new feature we also have is adding custom metadata in the manifest that you can then
access via Ralq info or the deepest API for custom application.
And an ongoing development is also about providing more fine grained process because currently
we just have a slot, a pair slot progress and if you have a large tower then you wait
very long until the progress gets to the next step.
And a contribution that came or was started by the community as a real cockpit updater.
This is basically an interface between the hotbit deployment server and Ralq on the other
side.
It talks via deepest API with Ralq.
And this is a good example where the community started things and they moved them to the
Ralq organization and are now maintained by the Ralq community.
And with the latest version of the hotbit updater we are also compatible with using
streaming updates for hotbit.
And shout out to Leon who is sitting somewhere here in the room.
The middle Ralq community is a layer or layer collection started by Leon which provides
some example integration of Ralq into for example QEMO or Raspberry Pi.
And it's a very good starting point if you want to check out how to use Ralq, how to
use all the features in Ralq.
And I really recommend you to use this as a starting point.
And yeah.
A final slide for an open source project it's always hard to know which are the uses of
your project and where it's actually used.
So it's always interesting for us to know this.
One example where we came aware of that Ralq is used is a very famous one.
It's a wild steam deck that uses Ralq together with the ASIN.
Another example is the Home Assistant operating system that uses Ralq for updating the base
system and the O'Naru Eclipse project.
And one thing that I also find very interesting is that the information panels on the German
ICE trains have a custom distribution they call Linux for ICE and they also use Ralq
for updating their systems.
So this was very quick.
Thank you for attending.
I think we still have two questions.
Yeah.
I think we have time for one or two questions.
Hi there.
Thank you for that.
That's absolutely intriguing.
Really interesting.
So one of the questions was how do I plug this into BitBake.
And Yvonne said that.
That's great.
I know what to do when I get home.
In other words, what's the granularity of this?
I saw a sort of a 4K block size in there somewhere.
In terms of your hashes and then downloading blocks through the streaming process, is that
4K increments?
How does that change?
And what's the overhead in verifying those hashes as you download?
What's the impact on performance and have you looked at any figures for that?
Getting quite low.
So the question was if the 4K is fine grained enough for normal downloads.
So it's currently fixed but it could also be changed if that's not sufficient.
But in the current approach, the 4K is a fixed site there.
Okay.
So it's getting late.
So unfortunately we don't have time for any more questions.
But don't hesitate to ask them in matrix chat or try to catch our sticker in the corridor.
You can ask questions and we can discuss.
Thank you for a great talk.
Thank you very much.