Thank you.
Hello, everyone.
Silence.
I told my talk about building FPGA bit streams with open source tools.
The important part here is open source tools, because building bit streams for FPGAs was
quite a pain in the ass.
A while ago, you had vendor tools which were large.
You had to install them.
Some of them were working on Linux.
Some were working on specific distributions, if you have the right version.
It wasn't fun.
A few years ago, there were more developments on open source tool chains for FPGAs.
Since then, a colleague of mine, Stefan, and I, I'm fiddling around with these tools and
trying them out and doing stuff with FPGAs.
The experience of that I will be showing today.
About me, I'm Michel Trettar.
I work at Pangotronics as an embedded Linux developer in the graphics team.
Usually I'm doing software in Linux, sometimes user space, sometimes drivers.
That's my background.
Why am I doing FPGAs first?
Agenda first.
I will show you the open source FPGA tool chain.
Then I will show you an example FPGA-based system.
In the end, I will show you the insights and pain points we had when we were developing
the system and give you a conclusion and an outlook on the next steps that we are tackling.
Use cases for FPGAs.
You want to use them if you have real-time requirements and you need a high data throughput.
That's two things that you need in graphics as well.
You have high data throughput because you need to push all the image data from one point
to another.
You have real-time requirements because you have 30 FPS, 60 FPS that you have to address,
so you have a limited time span for each frame where the frame must be finished.
And another use case, or you would also use them for prototyping such systems because
you can fiddle around and start experimenting with different implementations.
The FPGA open source tool chain is basically these four steps.
You start with some HDL or description of your bit stream.
Usually it's very low or VHDL.
Then you have users which synthesizes the code into a netlist.
Next PNR routes and places the netlist for your specific FPGA implementation.
Next PNR needs to know about your FPGA architecture and which vendor you're using.
This is different for Xilinx, for Altera, which is Intel now, or Lattice.
You need to know something about your FPGA internal working for that.
In the end you have a packer which takes the router bit stream with the configuration and
writes an actual bit stream which consists of all the bits that configure the FPGA.
That was quick and I won't go deeper into this because as I said we were working on
this for a while and had several talks on that.
One by Stefan you find it on YouTube.
It's about the whose and what was of open source FPGA tools.
There he will go deeper into how these tools work and how you can interact with them, how
you can call them and how all of this stuff is working.
The second talk of building open hardware with open software by me as well on YouTube,
here I go into details how we automated this and put the FPGA toolchain into a Yocto-based
BSP so that we have reproducibility on the bit streams, the tools that I used, our configuration
and other providers of libraries that we are using so we can run a specific checkout of
the bit repository of our BSP and be sure that we get the same build as the last time.
This is also now in our SCI so we have some CI running that takes the status of the bit
stream and gives us working bit stream again from the previous day.
So what's in the bit stream?
Basically if you come as a Linux developer you want to run Linux on your bit stream.
That's where you take RISC-V, a soft core CPU.
Some of them are able to run Linux.
Most of them are able to synthesize for your FPGA so you have quite a few of these.
So BEX with 5 is one implemented in spinal HDL, BOOM implemented in chisel, ROCKET implemented
in chisel or CVA6 implemented in system very low.
I said previously you could take code for your FPGA in some hardware description language.
I said it's very low.
Here you can see that the four cores are implemented in three different languages.
So this is quite a few of different languages and each of these cores takes some periphery
to make it actually work, also implemented in the same language.
So once you decide for a core you more or less decide for which hardware description
language and tools you are using.
That's not something that's really flexible for us.
And this is a point where LITEX comes in.
LITEX is implemented in MEGAN, which is another hardware description language, which is based
on Python.
And it supports Linux on LITEX and gives various pre-configured FPGA bit streams that contain
a sumrisk 5 core and support various FPGA boards that you can just run.
So here you see an example from the LITEX Git repository.
It shows an ACON base board with a multiple Linux SOC.
You have some access to DDR.
You have some access to SATA and UART.
So this is basically an SOC that's able to run Linux with enough periphery to actually
make it work.
So there is an example for that available.
The question that arises was, okay, we have this example system, but we want to fiddle
around with the FPGA and want to run our own bit stream in there or at least be able to
customize it to some point.
So our starting question for this was, can we add our own custom cores that are written
in BERILOOK into the bit stream that falls out of LITEX?
For that, we decided to come up with a demo system.
So the requirements for that were we are using a lambda concept ECP IX5 board.
You saw it before with an ECP5 FPGA by LITES, which is supported by users and the entire
tool chain.
So support there is great.
We want to put VEXORUS 5 with Linux into the FPGA to run Linux.
And because it's already there, so the demo systems have it.
And we want to add to our system an LED ring because LEDs are flashy, LEDs attract people,
so it's something nice.
And we want to have interaction with the system.
That's why we put hand wheel there as well so you can, as a user, do it.
Do some inputs to the system and get some feedback from the system.
It didn't work probably because it didn't have power.
So starting with VEXORUS 5 with Linux, as said, LITEX already supports this.
You can go to the Linux on LITEX repository, look for this file, and you'll see an implementation
for VEXORUS 5 running on the LITES ECP IX5.
VEXORUS 5 is written in spinal HDL.
That's neither my gun nor very look.
In LITEX or in preparation for using it in LITEX, you generate the very look code for
this VEXORUS 5 core rapid in Python or my gun.
And after that, LITEX can just integrate the newly created core or generated core into
the SOC.
Here's an example target which supports light DRAM for memory access and light SD card for
using an SD card.
The LED ring supports the WS2812 protocol, which is a single wire protocol to control
LEDs or more than one LED.
It's usually used in other fruit LED stripes, but you can find various cheap clones on Alibaba
and forever.
There is already a core for controlling this protocol implemented in LITEX.
So it's there, coded in Megan.
It works as an IOM mapped bus slave.
So from Linux, you just write to the registers and LEDs flash and change the colors.
And on the bus, you have four bytes per LED, so that's the three colors plus whatever.
Code is done via hand wheel, which is from Amazon, which is usually used for CNC stuff,
so it has 100 steps and you just can turn it around and it gives you a rotary encoder
with two signals where you can find the direction of rotation.
We took some code of the Internet for that.
It's implemented in Verilog.
There are various examples for that.
We wrapped it in Python so that we can use it in LITEX.
And this one runs as a bus master and is able to control the LED core via this connection.
So it just sends right this color to this LED on the bus.
So if you put all of it together, in the middle we have the FPGA.
On the right side, we have the already existing system with the VEXRIS 5 running Linux, the
light SD card, which is connected to the SD card, the light DRAM, which is connected to
our memory.
All of these are put together via a bus, details are not important, it's a memory bus to communicate
between cores.
On the left-hand side, you see the encoder, which is implemented in Verilog, which is
connected to the hand wheel.
So this is one thing we added to the bit stream, and we have the LED.py, which is my gun for
the LED controller, which is also added to the bit stream and controls the LED ring.
So how this is integrated into LITEX?
We created a new LITEX target, LITEX distinguishes between targets and platforms.
Platforms are the actual boards, targets are the SOC that you synthesize into your FPGA.
So we took the existing platform and added a new target for our own SOC.
Because it's Python, we have inheritance.
We just inherited from the example base SOC with the LITEX core and the other, the VEXWIS5
core and the other stuff.
We configured it, instantiated it, reconfigured the pins so that we can actually connect our
own peripherals, so the hand wheel and the LEDs, to the connector of the board.
Add the LED core and add the rotary encoder, in our case it's a decoder for interacting
with the hand wheel, and we are done.
All of this customization is about 200 lines of Python code.
So what we encountered and fixed during this process, after we added our custom cores,
suddenly Linux was booting but it was not able to access the SD card anymore.
We were suspecting various problems in the end, like timing or that our bit stream generation
failed or something.
In the end, it turned out, due to adding our new custom cores, the memory map on the bus
has changed and the SD RAM controller has changed its base address.
And Linux didn't know about that, because we were using just the device tree that we
took from the example.
So we changed our Yacht build to take the configuration for the Litex core, generate
a device tree from that and give it to Linux, and that way Linux took the correct base address
and uses the correct base address and is able to use the SD card again.
So that's something that will come up later as well, because if you reconfigure your base
system and device tree changes, you have to make sure that your device tree matches your
system that you're using.
And one other thing is there is some boot loader in the FPGA or in the bit stream for
early bring up, which corresponds to the ROM code or the ROM boot loader that Marco mentioned
previously.
So it's in the bit stream.
And it usually requires, so we compiled the boot loader and then it started to re-synthesize
the bit stream, run place and route again.
So this is quite fast, but it's still, in our case, six to eight minutes.
That's not something you want to have if you're just compiling a really small binary.
So we changed our Yacht build to synthesize and keep enough space in the ROM, in the area
and compiled the ROM boot loader and just put it together afterwards.
So this works a lot faster if you're fiddling around there.
Pain points.
Megan is not really maintained anymore.
There is a successor for it.
It's Amaranth.
LightX is currently still using Megan, migrating it to Amaranth is not really feasible.
There are ideas to change it to a new hardware description language.
I'm not sure what's happening there, but we saw, especially for simulation, we saw that
Megan generates invalid Verilog code or code you wouldn't want to assimilate.
That's something.
Currently, we have to live with it.
Another observation was that the Yacht environment wasn't as reproducible as we expected.
We're not sure what's the cause for that.
If we are missing it somewhere, that there's some seed for compiling or for a place and
route which we haven't fixed.
So we saw that there's sometimes a failing bit stream falling out of the Yacht build
that should be actually reproducible.
And we wanted to use JTAG to debug the early boot of the VexRisk 5 and look into it.
We are already flashing our bit stream via JTAG on the FPGA.
So we have a JTAG connected to the board, but we were not able to connect it to the
VexRisk 5 JTAG connector so that we could add the VexRisk 5 core to our JTAG chain.
That's something we can work around.
We can just use different pins, but we have to use a second JTAG for that.
So that's something that's not that great and we haven't figured out yet.
According to the conclusion, adding and customizing LightX targets is really convenient.
It's something you have to figure out.
You have to work into it.
But once you're in there, I said it's 200 lines for configuring.
So that is nice.
The step from Blinky to just get an LED flashing to an SOC is really large.
It's not really surprising because it's much more.
But also from things that you have to configure, things where you've misconfigured something
and it's just not working, you have really many knobs that you can turn and your system
will surprise you.
And with all this tool chain, LightX, there are different modules in LightX.
All of them have to be in sync.
Sometimes it happens that if you just update one component, you will run into surprises.
So it's really important to make sure that you have something around this entire tool
chain that keeps all your tools fixed on a specific version that you know which version
you are using also for reporting bugs.
That's what Yopto is doing for us or is the plan to have.
So the next steps are maybe we want to run a kernel CI on the Linux on LightX system
so that we can just take Linux kernel and run it against the system.
Here comes the problem that kernel CI expects a device feed that's upstream which is kind
of a conflict with the generation of the device that has to match your target.
Then we see that Linux takes ages to boot on the Vexarisk 5, about two minutes.
Not sure if that's because the core is just slow or if there is something we are waiting
for in user space that just can be fixed.
The Vexarisk 5 actually supports multi-core systems.
We weren't able to boot this yet.
And maybe we want to look into using the same system on the concept with different Vexarisk
5 cores.
I said before there are four different cores in different languages.
All of them usually generate very low code so it should be possible to integrate it into
LightX.
Show me the source.
It's on GitHub.
This is Yopto meta layer where you can find the code for the LED ring or the entire SOC
configuration, the code for the handwheel and a few other fixes that we did.
So you can add this to a Yopto workspace and should be able to reproduce the bitstream
that we built.
So thank you for your attention.
That's me.
That's my colleague Stefan.
You can find us, send us an email if you have questions or just ask me and find me somewhere.
Thank you.
Okay.
We have time for literally one question.
And this person here was the first one.
Thank you for your talk.
I had one question about the address changing in the device tree.
In microcontroller world you can have a lot of microcontrollers with the same addresses
for the common devices like for SCM32.
All the SCM32 have the same base address for RAM.