All right, we'll get started with the next talk.
Julien Annon from ParaTools is going to talk about testing and validation.
Hello, everyone.
Thanks, Janet, for the introduction.
So, yes, I'm Julien Annon.
I'm going to talk to you about testing.
As you may notice, I'm a bit happy to have a mic today.
So please let me know if I'm becoming unreadable.
So first of all, a bit of background.
Back some years ago, we were actually, we still had a team developing an MPI runtime.
And while developing this runtime, we had the measure stake to develop a validation
system to assess our software quality, but also to be able to compare our implementation
to others.
So like everybody in each PC field at this time, we started to build our own ultra-specific
shell scripts to validate our implementation, because we were considering that our implementation
were too specific to be able to use some main screen tools.
So we started with search scripts, criteria.
The fact is that with the team growing, people working in separate place, working on multiple
heterogeneous machines, we had a huge issue to make people continue to validate, to use
this validation system, because it was slow, not really efficient, and hard to make it
go, especially about maintenance.
When we wanted to add anything from 2D validation process, it was just a nightmare.
It was really costly in term of time.
But also when our software was evolving, was growing, just adding just even a little test
into this non-recursion base was a nightmare.
So we started to consider why not creating a validation system able to take care of HPC
environments and what it implies, like, validation in multiple architectures, multiple machines
by multiple users with multiple benchmarks.
And we just thought about having a generic tool able to handle all of that at one point.
So what we want in that scenario, we are here in the case of validating an MPI implementation,
which means having a standard API.
So there is a lot of well-known MPI benchmarks already existing.
We don't have to rewrite a whole non-recursion.
We have benchmarks.
You have proxy applications and so on.
So how to scale these benchmarks to any runtime or any project using them to build a proper
validation process?
So what people want, I mean, what users of this validation system want, it's a simple
tool.
And we don't want to have really complex, cute, GTK, any kind of complex architecture
to deploy to this.
So what we want is just a command line interface, basically.
And really, really, really, really if you set up really, really, really few configuration
to deploy to have such test working, because a lot of people, maybe it's not a generality
here, but a lot of people, it tests, basically.
So we have to convince them that testing is good for software quality.
Something really simple, but also able to handle any really complex scenario we may
find in HPC running an MPI application.
It is not that hard, but it may become really, really complex.
And we don't want to have to rewrite this tool every two years because a new technology,
a new approach, a new paradigm is implemented, and the validation process should have to
be rewriting.
So from that state, we decided to write a tool to fit our needs, but to be able to be
used by people meeting the same requirements.
Before going further, I would like to tell you that testing is not a brand new field,
and some other projects are taking such kind of issue until now.
And so please take a look at them if you think that PCVS does not completely fit your needs.
They are really, really powerful tools in the field.
So today I'm here to talk to you about PCVS.
It's a tool maintained by the CEA.
It's written in Python.
Yes, everything is in Python now.
So we are based on Python.
It's a simple command line interface.
And with few configuration files, obviously in YAML, it's a trend.
The design of this framework is to bring simplicity when writing test logic to users.
So we want tests to be simple to write, easy to port, okay?
And these benchmarks, written by the user, we want to be able to be run in multiple environments,
so we don't want to bind a test suite to a given application.
Let's consider MPI runtime.
We don't want to have our LULash or our IMB benchmark bound to a specific MPI implementation
to be run on any kind of architecture.
So this is what we call in PCVS the retargeting approach.
The other approach we want to focus on is the fact that we have heterogeneous test environments.
We have benchmarks.
How to scale, automatically scale this benchmark to the actual test environment, consider,
for example, having users wanting to validate the IMB, but they are working on their workstation.
You don't want to launch up to, I don't know, 100 MPI processes on their workstation.
They are going to be not happy with the use question of their machine.
But once this validation system is run on a real HPC cluster, you want the test suite
to automatically scale to this supercomputer resources without having to rewrite 100 of
configuration files.
Or even one file is already too much, okay?
So this work is maintained by the CEA, which is a French research administration.
We are collaborating with them to make this tool more generic and more generic and attempt
to make as many users happy as possible.
So at a glance, some features provide the idea is to split the test effort into specific
fields.
The first one is the specification of test.
What a benchmark need to expose to build tests.
So this kind of information is carried by the benchmark, obviously, or to build, what
is the program, what are the parameters, and so on.
Even the environment, the testing environment here is carried by the people deploying or
providing the testing resources.
So most of the time it's just a team policy to schedule jobs or system needs, right?
All of this to pursue two goals, still the retargeting of tests automatically when the
user is calling the benchmark, depending on the compiler and runtime you want to target,
and autoscaling tests to test environment.
Obviously, as PCVS is a kind of test framework, we had to add some functionality around testing,
like in-place reporting, because most users are running their tests on HPC cluster where
the set of functionality can be restrained so they don't have access to all their GitLab,
GitHub, Jira, and so on and stuff.
So we had some basic tools to answer this need.
And beyond a single execution validation run, we added a way to make, to build the history
of the validation for a given application by storing results over time and allowing
the user to run simple analysis, still in Pton, to produce statistics over time.
So quickly, the architecture of PCVS is based on files, so by the CLI, so by the file system.
It's parsing some user inputs, and it's run through a dedicated connector to mainly SLURM
currently, mainly SLURM, but we are focusing on supporting the batch manager.
So the idea is that the benchmark express job descriptions and resource requirements
and the environment will provide resources.
Let's consider, for example, a basic component called number of MPI tasks the job is taking
the job will say, okay, my job is only running up to two processes, or it's only taking,
I don't know, cubic value of MPI processes.
People aware of users of the Lulash proxy application will know what I meant by cubic.
So it will describe constraint, and then we will have environment configuration files
called profile in PCVS where the system will say, okay, in that context, I will have up
to 100 nodes, so you will be able to spawn up to 100 MPI processes to run your application.
Based on that, PCVS will cost this information and we'll say, okay, I have MPI jobs, I can
run up to 1,000 MPI processes based on this specification.
By not running the user benchmark 100 times once for each combination.
PCVS has an opt-out approach, so it will consider that every combination provided by the environment
will be used to scale your tests.
So if your test is not able to run up to 1,000 jobs, it's up to you to specify that you can't
reach this limit.
So here is a quick example, I don't know if you can see up there, but we have a really,
really basic environment configuration where you can see that there is what we call an
iterator, this is a variadic component, and it can take up to four values for the NMPI
attributes, and when describing a simple job, we just say, okay, my job just consists in
running a program.
So PCVS will enroll up to four common lines to run four independent tests to execute.
So PCVS will automatically build your test scenarios based on your specification.
So how to basically write a test, but more specifically a compilation test, there is
a lot of fields to customize how you can build your tests, so it looks complicated, but as
you may see on the previous slide, all the keys in that TML are not more data-free.
At least the files, obviously, you have to specify which kind of application you want
to compile.
So the framework will try to auto-detect your language to select the proper compiler, obviously
you have a manually designed approach also.
If you are not based on compiling for files but already using a well-known build system,
we have also an interface to invoke directly build system to build your framework.
I'm thinking about, for example, Lulash, which is using a Mac file, DIMB using a Mac file,
or even the mPitch test suite using a configure-magnet style approach.
So you have many options, all of them are optional.
What I would like to highlight is a variant, it's a capability from PCVS to expose to benchmarks
a specificity, a requirement this job has to be run.
So in that case, the openMP keyword probably means something to everyone here, but it just
a token saying that to run this job, the component openMP is required to be scheduled, and in
the environment, the user will say, okay, what is my variant openMP?
In case of GCC, GCC-like compiler, it would be dash F openMP, if it's intact, it's not
the same option.
You see the ID.
I will add, PCVS will add flavor depending on what you have specified in your environment.
How to write a run test.
So this is where the components, the iterative components take place, we didn't put it yet
on compilation model because we have issues with the rate condition, reaching the same
file on the file system, but we are planning to capitalize, to encapsulate, to isolate
such model to be able to support also combination computation test, I'm sorry.
So what does a user have to do to integrate such tests in your workflow?
You can write a PCVS file, you put it anywhere you want in your benchmark pass, and it looks
like just a red node, and everything below is totally optional.
Here we can see that we restrict our add.out program to specific MPI value because as a
tester, I know that my test has this constraint.
You can even create this variable component for your own application if you want to programmatically
generate a list of scenario that PCVS should integrate to its own process to build multiple
scenarios.
So in that case, we this, sorry, why am I moving?
In the program node, you'll see that with this simple line, it will be able to build
three times the number of scenarios that you are expected to have initially.
And what a test without having a way to express or validate a test, obviously.
So for any test, not only for one, you have a YAML description to say, okay, so I want
my job to exit with this particular return code, having an execution time within this
range, matching or not matching this kind of pattern.
Even here is my script, give him the regular output of my test, and I will tell you if
it's okay or not.
Okay.
So I just write my test.
So to run them now, it's just cell-based, so you just have to call PCVS run.
But before running my benchmark, I just have to create a profile to express the resources
my environment has.
Obviously, in case of MPI, we provided some templates, some basic templates to initiate
the testing process.
So here we are just creating a profile named myMPI-based, just on MPI.
So by quickly running that, I will have a full profile-based MPI running tests for one,
two, three, and four MPI processes combination.
But from that, you can then expand the profile to feature needs.
The whole build of PCVS relies on a single directory, and in that directory, you will
find anything required to analyze the results and even rerun in the same condition the tests
for reproducibility.
You can see on the right, repository we provided alongside with PCVS, which is called PCVS
benchmarks, and we attempt to put in that repository many well-known MPI benchmarks,
PCVS enabled.
So here is a fancy view of PCVS.
Obviously, there is many options when running a validation.
You can have an interactive approach, non-interactive approach, slur-enable, I mean batch manager
enabled, running inside an allocation, outside an allocation.
And once the whole configuration has been generated, we have commands, especially a
database exec, to interact independently, uniquely with your benchmarks.
So for instance, what people are used to do is to run their validation, and after maybe
ten seconds, some failures appear, and they would like without interrupting the non-recursion
system.
Just rerun in an isolated environment their tests to see why it failed.
So we have some extra commands to rerun this special pattern.
Obviously, I'm going to just peel it up, obviously not everything is always perfect, and the
static approach of your MPI is not what you need.
You would like something more dynamic because you have some stuff to integrate to read to
process before knowing what you want to test, even within a benchmark.
So we have a dynamic approach.
Instead of providing a static ML5, you will provide an executable script, an executable
file, whatever it is, and it will produce by itself the actual ML5.
This way you can programmatically generate your benchmark suite without having to know
it in advance, without knowing in which environment your non-recursion base will be run.
Let's consider the NAS framework where within the name of the binary bit, you have the number
of MPI processes.
Cool.
Now we have run our tests, but we would like to see what it looks like.
We have a test framework, just a job runner.
So obviously we had some tools to report results to the user, spoiler, cannot be compared with
a real tool for that.
It is just to offer a way to the user to grab their results directly on their machine in
place.
And essentially it is just a way to look at tests at a glance to be able to rerun if necessary
in the process.
So as I said, we can isolate and rerun independently jobs, which is pretty convenient when some
failure wants to be explored right away.
And in Infinee, we are using a web server to report in a web browser directly offering
more interactivity for your results.
So what it looks like, for example, here gathered by Labelle, you can see that there is some
head, so some failures.
Let's dive into it.
You can see that, oh, some trouble with MPIIO, what a surprise.
And when clicking a job, you will see the complete log of this trial, so the command
line and the actual, so I truncated the actual error.
And you can directly dive into the error without leaving your actual SSH terminal.
So a quick overview of how to configure your site, so the test environment configuration
part.
This is also AML.
You define directly compilers, compiler and run times, and the special variadic components
here.
It's split in five different modules.
Why?
Because this whole profile can be split up to five blocks, independent blocks.
We can be distributed over a cluster because it's not always the same teams who are responsible
of this particular block.
Let's consider, for example, the variadic component.
It's in charge of the team to build this list, while for the compiler and runtime, it may
be in charge of the sys admins of the test environment machines.
And after running a single job, what I would like to see is to have a trend over multiple
runs, how my tests should behave, and in PCVES, we integrated a way of history to stack multiple
runs over time, and then run analysis on them to build stats, to build trends, to have more
things than just a test result, but a test result over time.
So here is an example of what you can do afterwards, running analysis directly on this historic
path, and this is enabled, I would like to call that a DSL, but actually just a Python
API to interact with that, and you can build such beautiful graphics to see over time,
the rates of success inside your test benchmark.
So finally, just a quick glance at Spark and PCVES.
We are not in Spark, but we are supporting Spark, especially to do such things, by specifying
a simple package, a simple spec package, we will be able to check any combination of building
this package to see if there is some curiosity into your package recipe.
For future work, we have many things scheduled, and the most interesting in the capturing
metrics, the capacity to PCVES to capture directly some metadata to be able to then run
analysis on them, and many other things, but I think I'm running out of time.
Thanks for your attention, and two questions.
I'm just going to run a quick demo.
So from your configuration file, I assume you already have control of the cluster, at
least you've allocated some nodes or something.
Do you have some step that then allocates and de-allocates these resources on the fly
for each one of the tests?
So actually, currently, most of our test scenarios have run through an MPI run with Slurman
Evel or Srun command hierarchy, so they are taking care of the resource allocations.
Some other users are just running the whole PCVES inside a given allocation, like resource
allocation, just a dialogue, for example, and then any test doing this Srun does not
pay the cost of waiting the...
Right, but if some tests need some type of CPU, the other tests need other type of CPU,
then you need to...
And if one of them is unavailable because an other user is using, you have to wait instead
of fail.
Yes, this is something we still haven't...
Have a solution for, would be to be able to put a job aside while we add the allocation.
Yes, something we are currently investigating, absolutely.
Thanks for the question.
Any other questions?
Yeah, so one thing that I wanted to ask was kind of, for your future work, you had mentioned
building out a graphical frontend using Textualize.
I was kind of wondering how much assessment have you done into that, because I've done
some work like trying to build GUIs with Textualize, and while I do think that it's very interesting
framework and it's great for making textual GUIs, I think that it still has a bit of a
way to come before it can really make a standalone or comprehensive or textual interface.
So I was just wondering what your thoughts were on that.
I'm not sure, and I understand the whole question, but you mean, why did we choose Textualize?
Yeah, why did you say Textualize?
Absolutely, just we discovered just recently, because we were using Rich to highlight the
output of PCVS within the console, and we are looking for a solution to present the
things graphically in a terminal, and we still are looking for the ideal framework, and as
Rich is already, as Textualize, I'm sorry, is based on that, we are considering Textualize,
but if you have any other offer to propose, I would be happy to discuss with you about
that.
Thank you.