So, hey everyone. My name is Mathieu Tasse. I'm a software engineer. This talk is about
retrospective of my last year when it comes to hardware development. So, my background
is that I do a lot of C programming. I've been doing so for the last ten years. Kernel
drivers, libraries, mostly on Linux. So, with Yocto, all of that mostly for profit because
you get to make a living. And I've also been hacking on more fun stuff like guide, do-geeks,
functional stuff for fun this time. And to me, up to last year, hardware was more or
less like a black box. I mean, I was familiar with the surface of the box, which are data
sheets, manuals, schematics. But what's inside of it wasn't that interesting to me. If I
had something harder than finding out a GPIO number or, yeah, any kind of trouble, I found
my hardware colleague drop the ball and move on. But last year, almost randomly, I discovered
the world of hardware repair and micro soldering on YouTube. And it's a fun world. There are
some really, really talented people which are repairing some stuff. They are finding
the one tiny capacitor that is failing, removing it, and just by buying some one zero zero
one cent capacitor, you are fixing a border. I found that quite interesting. I think that
the world would be really different maybe in 20, 30 years, and having this kind of subset
could be interesting. And at the same time, I had a project where I was involved in the
design of a motherboard for an Intel CPU. As the hardware guy was a bit busy, I was
somehow against my will involved in the hardware selection. And so I learned that it's more
or less picking out ICs, which means integrated circuits. It's like often a tiny black box
and you have to pick one. You have to pick one that is not out of stock and it's challenging
these times. And once you pick two or some that maybe will ship, then you need to draw
the wires between them. And it was quite a fun exercise. And it gave me the motivation
to acquire some tools because one of the difference between software and hardware is that with
software, well, you can have your laptop and work everywhere. With hardware, my experience
is that it's not only that you need some tools, it's that you need all the tools. Like if
you don't have everything, you will still have something missing and you'll be, oh no.
And so this is about how to turn your desk into a terrible mess. So first you need to
buy a microscope. You don't need a times 5,000 zoom. 540 is way than enough. You need some
LED lightening so that you're able to see what's your under that. And it's quite a fun
exercise to learn to solder under a microscope and it's nice to use. Then you need obviously
a soldering iron. Most of you are familiar with it. You need a hot station. It's maybe
even more important than the soldering iron. You use that to dissolve some ices, the tiny
black things. We soldered them. But it's difficult to manage because it's blowing 400 degrees
air so it's easy to mess everything. Burn your board. You need a generator to power
your board. You need a telescope to be able to see your signals. You need also a breadboard
so that you're able to experiment. Try out some things. You need some components, some
resistors, some capacitors, some indexes. As I said, it's nice to have all of those
so that when you are trying out something, you don't need to wait for two weeks, five
weeks to experiment. You need a multimeter. You don't need a fancy one. It's like a two
U
UOS multimeter. The main function is that when you connect the probes, it beeps. It sounds
funny, but with that, you can reverse engineer some tiny circuits. You can isolate some issues.
You can do a lot of stuff. You need some flux so that the solder is able to flow nicely.
It's probably very toxic and as healthy as eating lead for breakfast. Maybe you also
need some kind of human extractor. I need to improve mine because... You need also some
solder week or solder pump so that you're able to remove the solder when you have made
some mistakes. You need some tweezers. More than that, you need to learn how to use them
because when you are dealing with O4O2 components, they like to jump to the end of the room.
Quite a fun exercise. You need a perf board so that once you have a circuit on your breadboard,
you can make it more permanent. You need some wires to wire things, obviously. If you have
a two dollar multimeter, then you probably also need an RLC meter so that you're able
to find the values of your components. Last O, I felt like I needed... I have a software
engineer. I did some hardware at school, but not so much. I felt like I needed some kind
of reference book. When it comes to software, to me, it's like it's SICP, Structured and
Interpretation of Computer Programs. It feels to me like a novel. It's like a Stephen King
Moon novel. I can read it. I felt so entertaining. I asked, like, how can you use what's the reference
book for hardware? People tell me it's the art of electronics. I can just say that it's
a whole different deal here, to me at least. Reading more than two or three pages gives
me horrible headaches. It's a reference book. You will find some more in-depth explanations
on electronics like overflow. When I acquired all that equipment, I tried to design some
easy circuits. This one is a flash programming device on a perf board so that you are able
to put your IC on the socket on the left-hand corner and then able to flash it with flash
run. That was my third circuit. Then I managed to make a few repairs. I had a zero percent
success rate for like three months. Then I did hit two percent success rate by fixing
my coffee machine. Since then, I managed to fix quite a few things. I also managed to
hack a bias. It was a nice thing. I had a laptop with password protected bias. I tried
to remove the bias, which is the DIC there. I burnt it to ashes. I bought another one
that I still burnt to ashes, about the third one. I flashed it with the device you saw
with flash run, put a bias without the password, managed to solder it back on with the hottest
station I thought about. Then it wasn't working because I also managed to glue some couple
traces. Then I had to run some wires. At the end, the notebook booted. It's not much, but
it was quite a success to me. Then finally, I did try to get into PCB design. I have a
LED ribbon around my desk and I tried to make it remote controllable. I designed the PCB.
It's the worst use case you can even think of, but you get to start somewhere. I designed
a PCB on keycard with a CPU that was really fun to solder, a regulator, USB port, nothing
fancy. I found both software, I found keycard really fun to use. It was easy to draw the
schematics to make the routing even without any experience. Really nice software. I tried
to use the new keycard for my next design because the name sounds appealing. It was
quite an interesting process. That's it. The takeaway message is that even if you are 100
percent software engineer and you don't want to get into hardware, having a minimal set
of equipment and minimal set of knowledge allows you to do some fun stuff and tries
to connect you to your hardware colleagues, which is a good thing in my opinion. Thank
you.
riflesesc routine