Okay.
Welcome to the next session.
So I will be talking about Kooksaval and in-vehicle access to standardised VSS signals.
I will tell you what it is.
I hope I can convince you that it's a good thing and you want it, but let's see.
I'm Sebastian. I'm part of the Kooksa project and when I'm working, I'm working for Eaters
on vehicle software. So Eaters belongs to Bosch, if that is something that's more familiar
to you. So yeah, this is about automotive software.
So let's get started. We will start like very high, you know, like sky high and then I promise
we go down to code. So there should be something for everyone.
First thing is what Kooksa is an open source software project. So I'm not totally at the
wrong place here. First time for me, first time for Kooksa, I think.
Kooksa doesn't stand alone. Actually, it's part of the Eclipse software defined vehicle
working group. So Eclipse is one of those many happy homes that exist for open source
software. And the Eclipse STV working group, that's basically a bunch of companies and
people interested in automotive open source software and a couple of other interesting
projects beside Kooksa, but we're focusing on Kooksa.
You could say Eclipse STV, it shares the software defined vehicle mindset. So what is that?
I mean, later just Google it. You will see that's basically the latest and greatest type
in automotive. So whenever somebody tries to sell you automotive software these days,
they will probably put their STV stamp on it. So what does it mean? That's also, I can
only give you a very broad thing. So it's a little bit of a marketing thing.
But what it normally promises is faster updates. Like, I mean, today maybe you have a phone
and you get a stream of updates for two years and if it stops after two years, you're pissed.
If you have a vehicle, it's a bit different. Maybe if you're lucky, after two years, you
get an update with some emergency patches and you should feel pleasantly surprised about
that. And STV is a little bit about making this better in cars that you have more like
these apps and software functionalities added later and not so much big block of firmware
that we only update in emergencies. It's often you hear this term 10 times faster development,
not 10 times faster than you are maybe as IT guys, but 10 times faster than automotive
is currently. Because a lot of software there comes rightfully so from the mindset of like
deeply embedded stuff, you know, embedded for real men and women, engine controllers,
real time issues. And there, I mean, of course it is harder and it's lower process to develop
software. But somehow it has taken over also to the higher levels of your vehicle now.
So even your infotainment doesn't update as fast as maybe your Android phone. And that
is something STV promises to change. Many companies promising that so that will make
you as a user of vehicles more happy, developers more happy because finally they can write
software for vehicles or it gets cheaper, makes corporations happy. So that's STV is
awesome. Just Google it. Lots of press releases about it. So how do we do it? So I, well,
the point is in IT, we can already do it. So it's pretty easy. Actually, we take all our favorite
tech stacks. We know and laugh, which are super productive. We put a bunch of beefy
hardware. Okay. We need a little bit more hardware, but that is some understanding that's coming to
automotive. It might make sense to invest a little bit more on hardware to get cheaper and
more productive on the software side. And we put it all in a vehicle. Done. Problem is, I mean,
we do it. It's pretty cool, right? I mean, maybe you have your Kubernetes cluster in cars and I'm
not joking. People think about that and doing that so you can probably deploy WordPress easily.
Right. And if you put good enough hardware, I think your doom framework will be pretty acceptable.
Of course, there are challenges, right? I mean, it's a vehicle where you drive around yourself
with your family and things like that. So probably thinking about safety and security
is a good idea. And we come to that a little bit later in the talk. But the problem is,
if you put all these in your computer, if you don't have any access to the vehicle's hardware,
if you can't actually interact with the sensors and actuators in the vehicle,
yeah, then maybe it ends at deploying WordPress, right? You can't do all these fancy automotive
applications you have in mind. And that is sort of the challenge. It doesn't help you just putting
all these tech stacks on there. What does it, let's see, we are stuck here.
Okay. So what does it mean to access vehicle hardware? So mostly the most interesting part
on a vehicle is really signal based on a very low level. And you have maybe two kinds of interesting
things. Sensors, how fast am I? And simple actuators. Maybe you want to open the trunk, open the door,
engage the wipers. Now you might think, no problem. I read about Linux. It has CAN interface,
Automotive. I just enabled it and off I go. But of course, it should be pretty clear that it's
maybe not a clever way to just let anybody who deploy some software in my vehicle interact with
all the bus systems and all the hardware in the vehicle just for safety reasons alone. And of
course, you want your vehicle still to move. So that's probably not a good idea. Second challenge
is just the way how automotive software evolved in a vehicle. Let's say the serialization, the
data formats are very much not standardized. So even a simple concept like vehicle speed,
how it's represented in bits and what's the data type and what's the unit and things like that.
That is different from each manufacturer to each manufacturer from model to model, from model year
to model year. So that's a big pain if you want to write a piece of software that runs in more than
just one vehicle. Luckily, because we don't have so much time, challenge two, the second one is
solved or is in the process of being solved. There's something called the Covisa vehicle
signal specification link at the end of the talk. So yeah, there's some homework maybe for you.
The point is that's a very simple data model describing signals in a vehicle. It uses like
identifiers which are based on a tree. That's just an example. In fact, it's much more complex,
but you can already see the gist of it. Like here we have something like path like vehicle chassis
actually will tie up pressure. So you already have an idea of what it is, what it might be.
And the VSS defines then also like what would be the data type of this would be the unit,
maybe hectopascals. I don't know. Don't quote me on that. And if you have that and if your software
stack integrates it somehow, then interoperability and portability would get much easier.
But the question is, that's a data model. So it's actually a nice YAML based file format.
You convert it however you like, but it's not live software. So how do you bring it to life?
And that's a question where would you use these kinds of nice abstracted model?
And two things talk again about these real embedded layer, probably not. Because down there,
where you have the super small, you know, microcontrollers, few kilobytes of RAM, safety
critical stuff, maybe you can't or don't want to invest in this cost of abstraction. Because that
it costs. I mean, it's nice and neat, but it costs. Then I mean, all the other way,
somewhere in the cloud backend systems that the manufacturer might have or that a fleet operator
might have. There might be a good idea to have an abstracted data model. And that is also the place
where VSS is already in production today at several different companies. You can even go to AWS by a
generic service for that if you want. So there are solutions there because that is where at first
yeah, has taken root. And the question is like on the way between the sensors, which are very
deep in your vehicle up to the cloud, where would you do this transformation? Where would you move
from these proprietary signals and very different variants to the standardized thing? And I think
it's no surprise that an SDV, the answer is still in vehicle because you want to be better in vehicle.
But the point is do it not on a microcontroller, do it in a vehicle computer. I use the term very
broadly, but that will be any computing unit in your car that actually has a processor and has a
real, let's say POSIX style operating system. So Linux, for example, maybe the actual expense here
would also work, but not like not microcontrollers, but a microprocessor platform. And that actually
is exactly what Cook's
our values cooks about is an open source software component that can do just that sit on a vehicle
computer and provide access to the standardized signals. How does it look like in an architecture
kind of view? So basically you have something we call the Cook's our data broker. That's like,
you can see that like a small server, it can run on your computer. It provides a gRPC based
interface or network based interface you can connect to. You can get set, read, subscribe,
all these nice signals, these abstracted signals from the VSS tree. So it means the applications
on top, they would be portable. They work on standardized signals. Of course, you need to get
them in and out somehow because down there, I mean, we have the nonstandardized signals. So there we
have something we call it VSS provider or VSS feeder is a term you often see in our documentation.
And this is a software component that would transform basically the data from the proprietary
things in a given vehicle to the standardized form as required by Cook's our own as required by VSS
important some architecture decisions. So this data broker is it's written in rust, pretty
lightweight. It does not have many features. So no, no history or things like that. I mean,
currently it's like less than four megabytes. That's statically compiled, you know, everything
all in. And that's how we want to keep it so that it could really run on even the smallest one of
these vehicle computers. And there's also I'm not sure if we have old cooks or users there. There's a
version of cooks also in C++, but currently I'm focusing on the rust version for this talk.
But architecture is the same. So how would it look like, let's say, if you really want to write an
application that can basically open your trunk, pretty simple, right? User presses the button,
open the trunk, and you maybe also want to see whether the trunk is open or not. And VSS terms
is pretty simple. I mean, you talk to Cook's our data broker, you say, I want to subscribe to the
state of the trunk because then you can show this fancy graphic if it changes. You might have to use
a process that he wants to open the trunk in this app in or somewhere you want to set the target
position of the trunk. So you want to state the intent that you want the trunk to be opened. If
it ends there, nice. I mean, you talk to a database, nothing happens. So in the end, you need these two
VSS providers. We talk about feeder and control service. So feeder would be the component that
checks actually what is the state of the trunk, feeds this back to Cook's our vials so everybody
can get an updated state of subscribe. And the control service would run the other way around.
If the target value is set, the control service would be triggered. And then it can do basically
something. I mean, you can write a can frame or some IP that some of these standards which are
an automotive. I can make it a little bit more specific because for these toy examples,
because now it's just PowerPoint engineering. But I think people sitting here, they want to see code
or at least want to see if it exists. So the point is how would we make these feeder and how would we
make this provider? And I show you examples now in Python, two reasons. Python is compatible with
PowerPoint. I can fit every single one slide. And second, we have a very nice Python library on
Cook's that makes it easy. But as I said before, the interface is GRPC based and you can generate
in every language. If you want to write this in Rust or C++ or C or Go or whatever, you can just
generate it. So feeder example, pretty simple. So here in this example, because then you can run it
on your computer, we just simulate the vehicle access. Normally there you will need to have some
interface to can or some outer side API or something like this. So we just pretend whether
there's a file or not that states whether trunk is open or not. We just check for that. And if it
changes, we just set this vehicle body trunk as open data point to the current state. And that is
literally, I mean, this code, if you get the slide, you can copy it. It's a picture. You can type it,
you know, like in the magazines 20 years ago, you can type the code and run it. But this code will
run. So I didn't leave anything out for simplicity. Maybe error handling, but if you do everything
right, it will run. Control service is basically the same thing. The control service is now that
thing where we say we want to listen whether actually somebody wants to change the state of
the trunk. And if I see somebody wants to open it or close it, then we would enact the changes
in the architecture of the vehicle here. Again, we simulate it via the file. And let me check. I
think they're not so bad in time. So I think I can, I didn't dare to show it live. I'm not that
hard to say crazy here, but I can show you semi-live. Same code you have just seen.
So we start off by just starting data brokers. So this component that will always run,
then we use something called the data broker CLI. So we can just simulate what an app would do. I
mean, it's CLI for that. So you see, I will just query the state of the trunk. And it's not
surprising that it will say, I don't know, because we just started the cook survival book. How should
it know? We can now simulate feeding this value. I mean, it's again CLI. We just pretend that the
trunk might be open. So I said that. It says, okay, that's a good sign normally. And now if I
correct again, okay, the data is there. So yeah, hell yeah, we can make a database. Now let's look
again. That is exactly the code you saw before on the slide. We simulate whether the trunk is open
or not, depending on whether this file in the temp exists. And you see, there's no extra code. I'm
just running it now. It actually says trunk is not open anymore because we don't have this file. And
if we query again in the CLI, you see that it's reflected already. Now we can also, I mean, now
assume you have a user in a vehicle, right? I mean, he opens a trunk, he closes the trunk,
something like this. So again, we do this here with our mockup. And you see this is immediately
picked up. You can see from the logs of the feeder. And again, on the CLI, you see that
the state changes. And that would already be all you need if you want to have these fancy graphics
in there, right? Your car can just show you what is. I can do the same stuff now with the control
service. Also, same code as you saw on the PowerPoint. Basically it subscribes for state
changes. That's important. We always have the differentiation between current value and target
value because, yeah, that's important to see because some operations take longer and we
start it. Of course, first nothing happens because nobody requests anything. But now again, we are
back in the CLI. So now I can do a set call which basically is telling me I have the intent now to
open the trunk. I'm not good at slower typing. There it is. I type it, but now it's fast. Yeah,
don't blink. So you see the trunk control service immediately opens the trunk. You could see the
feeder also picked it up immediately because in this example it worked. And then, of course, we
can again get the state in CLI. Now we're closing the trunk. Our trunk is fancy. It can close by
itself. Again, pick it up. The feeder picked it up and you see it. So that's round trip. But,
yeah, that you can also do at home. So it's all the links you need in it.
Now I need to get my mouse back to set sec.
So that we just saw. So now I think one important thing I want to talk about is now, I mean,
that's fine and it works. And I mean, probably you believe me, it could also work if you know
the magic can commands or something like this. But the question is, would you want to run this
in your vehicle or should you do it? So the question of safety and security I think is very
important. So the thing is, no matter what your application is, at one point you need to think
about it. I mean, security is already the aspect that probably you don't even want to give all
applications access to all the data you might have. If you support the whole S3, I think it has like
700 to 1,000 signals already just in the standard thing. So maybe not every app should access it.
And the other thing is, again, like opening a trunk is maybe not a good idea if you're on
the highway and driving this 100 kilometers per hour. And so I'm very sorry to tell you that I
cannot magically solve it. I would love to tell you download Cook's
server and everything is fine. Of course not. But it's important to look at the architecture.
So the Cook's server, it's written that something in automotive, you call it the QM domain.
That's basically, yeah, maybe it's a well-tested software, but we don't trust it much for any
safety-related things. So what we do there is, okay, we can have authorization, right?
An application needs to prove that I am allowed to write this value or read this value of things
like that. That's a security aspect. Same like now these feeder and service we saw on the example.
Of course you could add some extra security there if you want. But the ones I showed you,
the Pysan things, they cannot give you any safety. At least not in the midterm.
I think now there are some, let's say, activities to try to make a safe Linux
kernel. And of course, I mean, the data broker is written. You could test a lot of it. You can wait
until you have certified Rust compilers. Maybe in the future that could also carry some safety
load. But for now, it's just hopefully well-tested Linux software. But the point is, once you go into,
let's say, now you write on the Canvas or something, right? Or you do a summary request.
So then you cross this boundary, and then there are several patterns that might happen.
So maybe you talk to some deeply embedded ECU that actually is controlling the trunk lock or
the door lock or something like this. Those things already have safety guard rails in them,
right? Even today when this is designed automotive, it's not that they will just blindly do whatever
you tell them. So there would already be something in it that will check,
I don't do it if I am on a highway with 100 kilometers per hour.
Of course, in line of this architecture, you might do rethink if it really captures all the things.
But anyway, on this layer, you have it. Another thing is, since the interface is GRPC, it's just
a network-based interface. So these feeder and the service, so the things that do the actual
conversion, instead of running them on the same Linux domain, the same Linux machine,
you could, of course, also run them on a more powerful vehicle computer that might be able
to carry safety loads. So like in automotive, we say that's maybe an SLB, SLC kind of thing.
So maybe something that run QNX and only certified software. So maybe if you implement your feeder
and services there, then they would be able to carry some safety loads. And of course, you can
always use underlying security concepts as you want. It's always a good idea for defense in depth.
So the thing is, as I said, we don't give you the magic bullet, but instead of now giving every
random application access to any kind of vehicle hardware, vehicle buses, one thing you have,
data broker, a single entry point, and basically you can do all the security you want there.
And then, since this is your control point, and you control what kind of feeders and services you
build, depending on your application, you can see where you need to put some safety loads and where
you need to deal with safety. Because there are issues where maybe you don't need to do,
because in automotive, we have lots of these gateway things everywhere we like them. So if
you have an application that's just doing telemetry and receives the data from some interface,
where you basically already have a data data that you can't even write,
right, maybe it's fine to do everything on the Linux one safety site. But the moment you want
to actuate something in a vehicle, you need to think about it. That's the most important thing,
but I think we give you all the knobs you need. So regarding to enabling STV, just to
repeat a little bit. So yeah, if you want any application to access vehicle buses,
that's probably a pretty stupid or insane thing to do. As we've just seen, at least with KUKSAR
you have the single control point where you can already solve the security issues due to
these architecture with the feeders and providers and these very generic interface, you can choose
where you put those and you can choose where you put them and the safety control points in.
So that enables you to really build a safe system depending on your application.
Other thing, what I said before, I mean, another big challenge is that the signals in your common
vehicle, they are all different. I mean, vehicle speed in five different vehicles is encoded in
five different ways. But as in KUKSAR, you can use the KOVISA VSS specification. You're
basically on the safe side there. You can use the standard signals, they're really standardized. You
can also describe your own ones if you want. That depends on how you want to apply it. But the point
is you have a common language for that and you can use this throughout your whole tech stack. So if
you really go to the cloud or things like that, you do the transformation already KUKSAR-wise site
on the vehicle. Everything else is just piping through and you don't need to deal with some
weird bits and bytes from Canvas up in your cloud level. So that is, I mean, as KUKSAR, we can't solve
everything in the software-defined vehicle because we want to leave something for other people. But
the interface problem that you have same safe and same interfaces in the secure and safe way,
I think that's a very good starting point. And the thing is in the vehicle, everything starts with
those low-level signals because the whole data fabric of the vehicle down there is built like this.
To learn more, yeah, I mean, you can ask me all you want now or grab me outside, otherwise a couple
of helpful links. So our GitHub, where the main KUKSAR data broker sits, if you don't find me here
or don't dare to approach me, you can also click the link and then you find my contract address.
I would invite you to check out Eclipse STV. As I said, there are other interesting projects in there.
Koveza VSS, which is gaining adoption throughout the industry as a data model. It's a super
interesting thing. And some advertising plugs to one of our sister projects in Eclipse STV,
Eclipse Velocitas. So I show you this very bare-bone Python examples if you want to have
something more fancy in regard to how you write vehicle applications, like a whole development
framework with generating deployable containers and things in CI, then Velocitas might be very
interesting. Why you make advertisement for this? Not only because it's cool people, but they also
integrate KUKSAR, so if you are a Velocitas app developer, you also get everything that KUKSAR can
do. Yeah, that's all I have to say. And if there are any questions, I'm still here for...
Three more minutes, I guess. Okay, so we have a question from the chat room.
I'm going to pick one. There's a couple. Are there available CAN or CAN FD data providers
for some cars in an open repository? Yes. So what we have is something called a CAN feeder or DBC
feeder. That's a very generic component to get CAN signals in. Basically what you need is something
called a DBC file. That's the industry standard how you describe CAN signals and do a mapping.
And it's always hard in the industry to get example traces out, but for the CAN feeder,
we have a trace from a Tesla Model 3, not because they give us, but because the community
reverse-engineated quite a lot. So basically you get a big trace of a Tesla and the mappings to
VSS, which you can try out directly. My question, and from OBD, it is open OBD has some definition
of something else from the pen, so can you move this? Could you repeat the question, please?
Okay. I think the question was with regard to OBD. So the answer to that is it is pretty
trivial to build an OBD feeder and you can do it at home with, let's say, the Python examples.
And if you're in a Python world, yeah, there's something called Python OBD, which is like a very
simple library for all the standard on signals. The challenge why we have not in our repositories
is we are all Apache 2 license on a Kips Foundation. And the Python OBD, just one example,
that's a GPL based code, so we can't put it in the repo, but you can, I mean, nothing stops you
basically to do that. Thank you for the presentation. It was quite inspiring. And actually,
my question is relating to this one. So let's say if I go home and would like to implement
something, then what hardware and software I would need and how much it would cost me to start
develop something. So if you start with your own vehicle, which is basically your own responsibility,
then what we just heard, like if you buy these OBD adapters, like from AliExpress for five bucks,
right, you can get them. And you can, with a few lines of code in several languages,
get already some interesting information about, let's say, your current vehicle speed, engine
loads, oil temperatures. Yeah. So that would be, I think, the coolest way if you just hack around,
and we actually have many people, also students who do that. Hardware vice, I mean, if you want
to go into real vehicle, I think you need to dare to cut some can lines and go deeper, but then you
go into, let's say, if you're not working with, if I would like to use your stack, so I would like
to use KUKSA. Basically, you can use, so hardware vice, I think there's also KUKSA, also has
hardware. I hadn't signed to present it yet, KUKSA hardware, which is a base module for a Raspberry
Pi compute module, and it includes two KANF-D interfaces and OBD. Currently, the challenge is,
we can't sell them to you yet, because we have the manufacturing files, like online. So if you
add electronics shops, you can do it, but yeah, they're not just, you cannot buy them.