We're going to start the next talk.
If you're going to stay in the room, please take a seat.
If you want to leave, please leave.
Okay, so the next speaker is Mikaeli, who's going to talk about a universal sparse blast
library.
So, yes.
At the core of many technical or scientific computing problems, we end up with reduced
the problem to solving a system of linear equations.
If the system of linear equations were a simple one, like a two by two one, the method of
solving would be pretty simple.
And in any case, it would involve representing the linear systems by the data structure of
a matrix, so a table of symbols, or usually numbers, and a few vectors of numbers.
So the matrix is the basic structure of scientific computing.
In the case of such toys problems or school problems, we have exact direct solutions at
our disposal, which works fine.
However, once we go into the problems involving simulation of larger domains, so engineering
problems, those linear systems to be solved become large, and also the methods that we
use for smaller systems are not applicable here anymore, because the numerical stability
of, let's say, toy problems or small problems, the stability is not here anymore.
Simply with those methods, numbers, results, diverge.
And the time to solution also increases more than exponentially.
So they're simply infeasible and don't make sense.
So it's a different, it was completely different techniques for large linear systems.
So furthermore, if the systems were not only large, but also full of zeros in the matrices,
so how do we call the systems, or how do we, what do we have to do it here?
We have to do perhaps with sparse systems or sparse problems.
This is the way we call it.
So in this acoustics matrix, or matrix coming from acoustics, we observe that less than
a half percent of each row on the average has a non-zero element.
So we would call this sparse system, perhaps, so the system coming from this matrix.
Indeed, usually we are happy with the definition of Jim Wilkinson, where we say a problem or
a matrix is sparse.
If we can, with our technology, which are technique, we can make use of the amount of
zeros there to our advantage.
So this is the definition.
It's not about numbers.
It's really about what we are able to do with the way the matrix looks like.
So among the different matrices we can encounter, we could have matrices from a circuit simulation
which look like this and have such clustered elements in them.
Sometimes the elements are more clustered around the diagonal, like in this quantum
chromodynamics matrix.
Computational flow dynamics matrices are a bit more regular, you could say.
So it means that you can exploit all of those matrices perhaps in different ways.
This is why I'm showing you this gallery.
This is another CFD, so computational flow dynamics matrix, a structural matrix, another
material problem matrix, structural, and so on.
This is also CFD1.
So this was just to tell you that sparsity really is related to the technology we use
to deal with it.
So usually we are happy using iterative methods with sparse systems.
Iterative methods because something is being iterated, so there is a loop, and with the
most common methods, Krilov methods, the loop usually has a bottleneck, has a core operation,
which is prominently multiplying the system matrix by one vector or many vectors.
Depends a bit on the technique.
There are several of them.
Some of them showing a new octave implementation of such one iterative method.
So there are two kernel operations or main operations.
Multiplication of the matrix by many vectors or let's say another dense matrix, or the
triangular solve, so the solving of matrices which are called preconditioner matrices,
but are sparse.
And these are the core operations which we are interested in, and I want to mention that
those operations for the sparse matrix vector or multi-vector operation can have many variants.
The variants can be on the matrix, which could be perhaps complex and hermitian and all symmetric.
It doesn't have always to be square.
It could be any rectangular, and perhaps it has already a unit diagonal, and we can exploit
this.
This is what I'm saying this.
Many things change if the matrix has a different, has a complex number, so long complex numbers
like a speaker before me spoke about.
So that changes the balances in the performance profile here.
And other things might change.
And all of this have influence on the specific kernels.
And if you think like Ludovic has spoken about the different variants that one might want
to build over different architectures, you see that this is, you end up with code bloat
if you really want to optimize each subcase.
Also the operands have their own variants.
So in the way the data are laid in the dense matrix.
Yeah.
And similarly for the triangular solve operation, there also you have different variants, which
leads to a multitude of different kernels or ways you wish to write them, kernels of
code.
So this leads to a committee of people, end of the 90s, to meet together, mostly US people,
but also with delegations from Europe, to standardize an API, which they called sparse
blast, sparse basic linear algebra subroutines, to somehow just give an API to the different
variations of the operations that I spoke about.
It's mostly, it's not like full blast, if you know the dense blast, it's mostly about
creating sparse matrices, destroying them, and doing a few operations, not only those
but these are really the core operations.
And they talked about C and Fortran because 20 years ago, 20 something years ago was the
final document which they finalized.
Now after 20 years we could say that, well, what they've wrote, especially in my opinion,
is perfectly portable, allows some parallelization even if it's not specified at all.
They didn't foresee extensions but it's possible.
If you look at the API, you see that you can have extensions, so they're not blocked somehow.
The namesake of sparse blast has been copied by every major vendor you can imagine.
The set thing that each major vendor has completely violated their API, so they changed something
in a slightly incompatible way, which is sad, it's simply sad.
And the original sparse blast didn't think about the GPUs but actually in my experience
looking at how people program codes, I see so much technical depth that I think you can
do compromises and with small adaptions you could adapt the sparse blast to the GPU computations
to some extent.
So I think you can save this API to a good extent.
And this is the reason why I'm here.
So I wrote a library which respects the original sparse blast.
So I see sparse blast program can look like this where you have annotation for the sparse
blast operations, which is logical if you know a bit, so you can understand it a bit.
And going in the direction of my library, it's centered around a data format, a sparse
matrix format which I came up with, it's called recursive sparse blocks, because there is
a recursive sub division, there are blocks which are sparse.
And the reason, the motivation for this data structure is to not exclude the sparse blast
operations.
So I have made compromises in order to allow sparse blast operations to be there.
I didn't want to preclude these operations.
So it's a compromise.
And the core idea here is to have, let's say, cache size blocks more or less, and a way
to give each multi-thread, multi-core, core something to work with.
So it's oriented towards multi-core.
It's not for GPUs, or not at the moment at least.
So the matrices which you have seen before with this data format, the data structure
works a bit like this.
The color is based on the population, on the amount of matrices are there.
Then there is another code with other information.
But this is just to tell you that the irregular aspect of those matrices is reflected also
here to some extent.
So the library itself wants to provide sparse blocks.
So building blocks for iterative solvers is pretty compatible at the library.
It works with C++, Fortune, Octave, and Python.
I say it's quite compatible.
So it uses, let's say, established technologies.
And it's quite compatible also in the sense with your software.
It doesn't require you to use too many.
The only data structure which is custom is the matrix.
You don't need extra data structures for vectors.
And the program you saw before written in the sparse blocks for using RSB uses just
one extra init and finalize function.
So I really respect the API.
But however, it's nice to write also the 15th standard.
Or I'm joking.
This is not the 15th standard, but just the internal API.
So if you want, perhaps you can exploit the internal API of LibreSB, or not internal,
but the native one.
Please tell me when I'm at 10 minutes.
Which is primarily in C. Then you have wrappers with C++.
And there's also the Fortune 1.
These are the native APIs.
And what is specific about RSB is that the blocking is not so clear which blocking is
best.
Because, yeah, depending on how you block, you could have better or worse performance.
And for this reason, there is an idea of using automated empirical optimization in this library.
There is a special call, a function which you call where you invest time to ask the
library to optimize a bit the data structure.
So you sacrifice a minute, perhaps, for optimizing the data structure a bit.
And you do this in the hope that the many hours which will be using this matrix afterwards
will be, will profit, will be decreased thanks to the optimization.
Because as I said, this is meant to be used for iterative methods.
So you will be running this for many hours.
And therefore, spending a few minutes in automated optimization, it's something that should pay
off.
No guarantee.
But that's the idea.
And that is usually how it's got.
To give an idea, this C++ API is what you would expect.
So there is a class templated on the type.
So there is type safety here.
What do you say?
This is my library.
Sorry, this is my matrix.
These are my non-zeros because this is what we are representing here.
We have flags, C-style flags for options like symmetry or asking for discarding zeros rather
than keeping the zeros because sometimes you want to keep structural zeros for modifying
them later, for instance.
So you have many such options here.
And this is why I'm showing this slide.
I'll tell you that there are many options which I'm not showing you here.
And the only data structure here is the RSB matrix.
No other custom stuff.
And you can enjoy the spam interface of C++ 20 that doesn't really force you to have any
weird custom vector type apart from the standard C++ ones.
If you want to use, for instance, GNU Octave and enjoy the multi-core speedup from LibreSB,
you can use the sparse RSB plugin which I wrote which uses LibreSB pretty efficiently.
So apart from a few conversions, it should have almost native performance.
Similarly for Python, the PyRSB plugin for standalone package has an interface which
is copied from CSR matrix.
So you use it mostly the same way, but underneath, LibreSB runs.
You don't see it.
Or you see it if you ask it to use the auto-tuning routine.
Because as I said, in all of those language implementations, you can also use all of the
functionality of LibreSB which includes the auto-tuning also here in Octave.
And I want to stress this.
GNU Octave doesn't have multi-threaded sparse operations.
With LibreSB, you can have them.
Same for SciPy sparse.
As far as I know, it's not multi-threaded.
With LibreSB, you get it.
LibreSB is by default is licensed as lesser GPL3, which means you can, as long as you
don't modify it, you can distribute it with your proprietary code.
If you modify it, well, it's more complicated.
You have to release the modified version.
The LibreSB library is if you want to learn to use it, it makes absolutely sense to use
a packaged version from Debian Ubuntu or most of Linux distributions.
Or if you use Windows and you can use Seguin.
Or once you want the performance, I mean, you can just compile it by yourself because
it's quite trivial.
Or enjoy what our colleagues here from Spark and EasyBuild have done and use the packaged
version from those distributions.
And some people have written wrappers for Rust and Julia.
I don't know these languages, so I didn't use them.
I think the last one is like the entire API.
I think Julia is more in Julia style, so it's just what is the core functionality is there,
I think.
Yeah.
That was everything.
I don't know how much time did I take.
Oh, 50 minutes.
Okay.