Happy? Hello, everyone. Thanks for attending. We were doing okay. Is that my device or theirs?
I don't know if that's me or... Okay. So today's talk is written by Jacobo
Mondy. Unfortunately, he couldn't attend today. He's his back, so I'm stepping in. So what
I'm talking about today is not work I've done. It's about his experiences working on the
PyCon Pro. I don't want to touch it now. Yeah. So my name's Kieran. Just like Jacobo, I'm
an embedded camera engineer with ideas on board. We've been working on VFRL2, kernel
drivers and for some time now LibCamera. We can be found on IRC, Matrix. Anyway, you want
to get a hold of us at GitHub if you need or after the chat. And today we want to talk
about how we perceive the Linux camera stack on both desktop and mobile environments. And
starting with the kernel, we see LibCamera as being a big part of that to support the
platform abstractions. And on top of LibCamera, we see lots of applications desiring to use
pipewire. So we're going to look through that. And the overall goal is that applications
shouldn't care what platform they're running on. They shouldn't care if they're running
on a PC, a desktop or a Liburn 5 or a PyCon Pro. And equally, any application you want
to run or framework, camera framework, they should all be able to say, hey, I want to
talk to the camera. Give me some pictures, please. And specifically today's talk is about
the PyCon Pro. Yakubo has spent some time over the last three months or so or more trying
to make sure that we can bring up the PyCon Pro with LibCamera and standard applications.
And the PyCon Pro is an interesting device because it's, I think it's promoted as like
a test ground. There's no official software, but it's a good device that people can play
with and develop their own software. Interestingly for us, it has an RK3399, which is a chip that
has an ISP. And it's actually a device that we have already been supporting for several
years now. It pretty much was one of the first devices we started supporting with LibCamera.
And part of why we created LibCamera is because cameras got complex. This is a slide I've
presented a few times. But on the left, we can see that beyond having just a single video
node where you might say, UVC, give me some pictures, cameras started getting more complicated.
They had multiple components and you want to configure them. And the one on the left
has now been removed from the kernel. And the N900, which already has a lot of different
nodes, that's 13 years ago. So if you can imagine, there's a lot of cameras out there
now that are even more complicated than all the components there, particularly lots of
Qualcomm phones. And with all those new components, it's very difficult for applications to know
what to do with each of those things. Suddenly every application has to be aware of every
platform. And that's going to lead to a lot of replication of code. Each camera application
is going to have to deal with media controller to configure the pipeline, has to talk to
V4L2 to get frames, has to talk to sub devices to configure parameters on the sensor itself.
And that changes for every platform. It's different on a Rockchip, it's different on
Raspberry Pi, it's different on an Intel. So LibCamera's goal really is to fill the
gap of that abstraction so that applications only have to look at one API again. And it
sits on top of V4L2. It's not a replacement for V4L2. But what we have is a pipeline handler
which deals with the platform abstraction. And we have a component called the IPA. And
that's crucial for devices like the PinePone Pro with an ISP and raw Bea sensors because
you need control algorithms. And the IPA in LibCamera provides a space to do that. On
top of LibCamera itself we have a native LibCamera API which is C++. We've got Python bindings,
there's people developing Rust bindings. The Rust bindings are actually giving us C bindings
I believe. Aside from that we've got Android HAL integration which is important and comes
up later. And integration into frameworks like GStreamer. And as I said, the Rockchip
LK3399 is one of the devices we started supporting when we started LibCamera, particularly on
the Chromebook, ChromeTab. But it's actually a really interesting platform because it's
in a lot of small-board computers as well. So it's readily available hardware. You can
plug in off-the-shelf cameras from Raspberry Pi and play with it. And what I actually really
like is recently we've been working on the IMAX8M+, which has the same ISP core in the
chip. So the same code that we've written for Rockchip also works on the IMAX8M+. So
I've mentioned that these cameras are now complex and we've got this thing called an
ISP which is kind of getting in the way of people getting images out of their cameras.
And the reason for that is the cameras themselves are now raw biosensors and that needs a lot
more processing and support to get good images from. Particularly the underlying format is
in a Bayer format which most applications don't want to process. So that data is fed
into the ISP but the ISP needs to be managed. It produces something called, well, it produces
statistics usually custom to each platform. And there has to be code or an algorithm to
process those statistics to then generate control parameters to configure the ISP for
the next frame. And ultimately then that will process in a loop and produce you some images
that the applications will expect either YUV or RGB. And we already have an implementation
of this. This is one of the things we started early. I believe a lot of this implementation
is derived from Raspberry Pi so it's quite compatible with the implementation that Raspberry
Pi have at the moment. But we've got various components like AGC to handle how bright the
image is automatically or set manually. White balance is important then lens shading of
the kind of three that you have to start with. But all that code is open and already existing
in libcamera. The kernel driver itself has been in the mainline kernel now since I believe
2020 and it was de-staged in 21. Helen from Calabra was working on that. And since then
it still had active development. There's fixes that go up and we've been working on it to
extend support for the IMX8 and plus. And so the kernel side and the libcamera side
is looking pretty good. We've got support for processing the images. We've got the kernel
drivers. But when we go back to the PineFoam Pro for quite a long time there's no driver
in the mainline kernel for the front camera, 8858. And even though there was a camera,
a driver for the back camera, it wasn't tuned and it wasn't supported very well. It wasn't
tuned really. So PineFoam Pro has been left behind from libcamera for quite some time because
no one was actively working on this and it just meant that you couldn't use libcamera
on a PineFoam Pro. And then Yakubo has been working on this in collaboration with others
who wanted to push this forward and make it work again. And Nicholas Roth started this
back in October, I think, where he wanted to get way droid running on a PineFoam Pro.
So he was trying to find out what are the missing pieces, what do we need to up-stream.
And this taught really drive from the work that he kick-started. So he submitted support
for the rear camera, front camera, to libcamera. And he based that on the kernel driver that
was in the PineFoam Pro self-hosted driver, not self-hosted, Meggie's tree. And interestingly,
the driver was, it hadn't been posted upstream, so it hadn't had any kind of review process.
And it exposed itself as a name with M00F underscore OV8858. So it was encoding properties
in the sensor name about where it is and its location. And that's not very good for libcamera
because it's not generic because then we can't have a handle that says only match the front
camera in location zero when we want it to support every device that has the sensor.
So the upstreaming process actually highlights where things need to be cleaned up. This has
gone through some iterations. And Yakubo, who would have been talking, has taken this
on to completion and will land in 6.3. It's accepted in the notes media tree now. So that's
getting in in March, I think. The support required for libcamera, we moved that and made
a release last week for 004. So now we've got a kernel with the ISP driver. We've got
the sensor drivers and the camera support all upstream and mainline. The other sensor
needs a lot of work still. Interestingly, it's supported by Raspberry Pi and the Raspberry
Pi kernel has a lot of downstream patches. So if anyone wants to get involved, this is
a really good opportunity to look at what is in the Raspberry Pi tree, take some of
those cleanups, get them suitable for mainline and post them up.
So if everything's there, what's next to make it good? There's lots of patches so upstream,
build for the 258. The next stages really are about camera tuning. And that's part of the
process that we're trying to provide in libcamera as a framework. We've got a camera tuning
tool. And that's really about helping the control loops know how to process the images.
So we have a camera tuning tool which is being developed and can be used already. You can
tune the cameras at home, simple things like taking pictures of white wall. Ideally you
want a color card that was on one of the earlier slides. But with very inexpensive tools you
can do some pretty basic, an initial start at camera tuning. So if you've got devices
and you want to investigate this, that's a great place to get started.
So that is not my work here is done, but it's Yakubo's. That's front and back cameras from
running on the device. This is using, captured using CAM, which is just a pure test tool
in the camera. We have CAM and QCAM. They're not meant for end users really. It's just
for helping us develop the framework. The images probably need more work on the lens
shading and white balance. But that's part of the tuning process that we mentioned. But
users don't want to stop using test tools. So what's also been going on and progressing
nicely is support for application layers on top. And Robert Mater, I met back in Prague,
and since then has been also working on this with his device, trying to get the desktop
environment to be suitable. The same experience you get on the desktop to work on mobile.
And that's building up the camera portal in pipe wire, extending support in G streamer
to handle controls and mapping that all through the camera portals. So from pipe wire's perspective,
this is what the media stack looks like for desktop environments or anything using pipe
wire, where pipe wire sits on top of lib camera, knows how to look at cameras that are V4L2
as well, but if it needs lib camera, it already has that integration. And then G streamer
and applications can sit on top of pipe wire. And Robert has been doing quite a lot of work
trying to clean up and finish that integration of that pipeline, application pipeline, particularly
in getting the known camera app to work all the way through. And I remember when I first
saw the known camera app, I saw it and thought, great, there's a standard design for a desktop.
I want this to work on the camera. So this has made me really happy seeing that people
have pushed this forward. The known camera is a design, I've forgotten which team was designing it,
but then James Westman took that design and created an application for it, which can be
part of the standard known environment, and also run on mobile devices, which is the key point.
If I could have put that in the slide. So,
he couldn't be here today, but he did manage to record on his PineFone Pro with a screen
grab and encode on the device, running known camera on the PineFone Pro, running through
pipe wire into lib camera, running lib camera algorithms and through the ISP. So this is
hardware accelerated camera. He's taking a picture. He, in a moment, will change the
camera to the front camera. There. And one of the things I like is, quite interestingly,
you can see the algorithms kick in. So you can see it starts out green and then it corrects
itself. So you can see that real time action from the algorithms that are in place in the
lib camera. In consumer devices, that still happens on a UVC web cam, but usually you
hide those frames. In the camera, with these up here, we're just not hiding them, so you
can see it. Excellent. So we can have real live demos instead of video ones. Can I get
a back? So, thank you. That demo was running known camera through the pipe wire camera
portal. And thanks to Robert, if you have a device running pipe wire, you can install
this flat pack, get that application and run it on your device. I believe that will just
all work. The instruction from Robert over there. Okay. I went with what I had. So that's
great. We can now run camera application that's exactly the same on desktop and mobile. But
there's more that we want to do on our phones or with communications nowadays. So getting
browser support is really important there. But now we've got pipe wire integration and
portals. Browsers, which will most of them use WebRTC, it would be really helpful if
we had integration of WebRTC that could talk to pipe wire. And Michael from Pangutronics
has been working on that. There we are. I want to see you later. Has been working on
that tirelessly for a year or more, I think. And I don't think I can point that far out.
But what was fantastic is last week it went green and that part has merged. There's still
a few more series to get in. But the core support is now there. So in some months, it's
a very wishy number. We should be able to see browsers able to handle this pipeline
and you could make a video call on your Python probe, which is fantastic. It's not me. It's
other people. I do talk a lot about other people's work. So I don't want to take credit.
Talking to some of the distros, I know that even once the code's ready, I believe we can
start getting early PPA-type packages available so that we don't have to wait for it to filter
through all the upstream processes. But that's up to the distros, not me. So there's actually
‑‑ it's quite exciting. There's a lot of development going on with LibCamera at the
moment. Lots of application-side development. And another one that's been being supported
lately since the last three or four months is Adam Piggs is working on Sailfish OS. And
he had an application called Harbor Camera that ran there. And he's ported that to run
on LibCamera. So he's been working on that on the PinePhone. And it's QT‑based. So I've
been running it on my desktop, my laptop, and an Intel device. But even though he's
developing it on the PinePhone, because it's based on LibCamera, the platform is abstracted.
So it will work on every platform that's supported by LibCamera. So the same application is now
going to run just the same as known camera will run on all the supported platforms. Unmodified,
which is brilliant. I've run it, as I said, on the Surface Go's and my desktop. He has
already started plumbing in manual controls so you can do things that you expect from
your mobile phone camera app to control the exposure and brightness that you might want
to play around with. And then autofocus and manual focus should be coming up soon.
That is a screen capture from Raphael, who is one of the other LibCamera community members
who is just testing Adam's work on the PinePhone. But that's actually running on MIMO-LEST, whereas
Adam's working directly on Cellfish. So, again, it's nice to see that the distribution doesn't
matter. It's all across the platform. The talk started ‑‑ a lot of this work
here started because Nicholas Roth was trying to get Waidroid support working. He wanted
to run Waidroid to get the Android applications running on his phone. And so that is a way
of running an Android environment in a contained ‑‑ in a containerized solution on your device,
on a regular Linux system such as we can now run on the phones. And I said earlier that
LibCamera already provides an Android camera help. So we've already got integration there
for telling Android how to talk to the camera, which is great, so that can be reused. There's
still a fair bit of work there, unfortunately. Nicholas has got it working in Waidroid. He
can capture frames. But due to the format that the buffers are captured in, he can't
display them. So that's going to need some more work in Mesa. And look at how the buffer
management is being handled. There may be some updates from ‑‑ excellent. So there's
recent developments that may improve this in the near future with pan frost driver development.
But might be an opportunity if anyone wants to get dug into those layers to work on.
Sorry, Millipixels is a fork from Dorota where she's been supporting the Libram 5. And the
interesting part there is she's working on a GPU‑based ISP. So on devices where we
don't have support for managing the ISP such as Qualcomm or devices that don't have one,
that work would be really interesting to see extend LibCamera to work on those devices.
And Pavel's talk earlier was about sharp photos on a mobile phone who's creating a software
CPU‑based implementation which will help get things started as well.
These are lessons Yakima wanted to highlight that he's learnt. But they do apply widely.
Fragmentation when it's all split with lots of different stacks from vendors, it's very
difficult to use that generically. So LibCamera's goal is to try and pull this all together.
And to do that, it needs mainlining. We have to have a single definition of what is true.
And mainlining is difficult. It takes a lot of effort. My friend that I travelled up on
the train with to FOSDEM, he was saying he posted patches to one of the Linux lists.
And after four or six weeks he had no reply and found that really demotivating. So it
is important that you consider mainlining from the start. You've got to get in so early.
It takes a lot of time. And it's always slower than when you've got control of your own repositories.
We've definitely learnt more lessons from developing LibCamera. A lot of us are derived
from kernel developers, we've been on the other side. And now we're seeing just how
important it is on the user space side that these controls and interfaces need to be standardised
and have a reference implementation. Since we've created LibCamera, we're finding that
the sensor drivers in Linux are improving rapidly, we hope. We've started saying that
controls have to be defined by the sensors. There's so many missing parts to the drivers
that are already upstream and they need more work to get them supported generically. But
doing so means it will all be more consistent and improve the experience for everyone. Thank
you. I think I might have two minutes. Excellent. So two minutes if you do have any questions.
It already does. I think there may be. Just to repeat the question, the question was will
LibCamera support the original PinePhone? So, Pavel is brilliant to answer that. Wait,
wait, wait. There's a mic coming. And there is kernel on original PinePhone doesn't have
required APIs for LibCamera. So you can either break the LibCamera to work anyway or you
can fix the kernel and people are doing both at the moment. It's in development. But Adam
Pigs who was doing the pinhole camera app, he is working on PinePhone. So, no, on PinePhone.
So it's one of the active platforms being used. So I believe so, yes. Any more questions?
After you talked about releasing 0.0.4, what's on your roadmap for an 0.1 release? What do
you want to get done? I'm sorry. I couldn't hear the question. For LibCamera 1.0. He's
ducking. He's getting out of the way. We want to. There's key features that we want to support
in LibCamera and it will break the API. So we already know exactly how we want to break
things. I started tagging releases so that we had defined points before Christmas. So
trying to do it every two months at the moment. It is in the plan. There's a big reconfiguration
API that wanted to try and get in first before we go for 1.0. But we need testing and app
to know how to get it right. Once we go 1.0, it feels like we're going to say that's it.
But I think some ways, some of it is more psychological. But that's versioning. So we're
working on it. I'm trying to make sure we handle API breakages automatically now so
we'll be able to improve on release management. We kind of always just said use the latest
because we were trying to iterate so fast. And that is hopefully improving. So we're
working on it. And I'm out of time. Thank you. Thank you for a great talk.