We are ready for the next talk by Courtney, who is going to talk about open source radio
astronomy.
Hi, everyone.
I work for Ostrone, which is the Dutch Institute for Radio Astronomy.
We are a government institute, so we are publicly funded.
Apart from being publicly funded, we have a lot of research grants, and that's basically
what pays my salary.
I'm going to talk about our biggest instrument that we have, which is called LOFAR, and we
actually utilize a lot of open source software there, almost exclusively.
There are some caveats.
My name is Courtney Luecker, by the way.
I am also into amateur radio.
My call sign is Papa Delta 3 Sierra Uniform.
This is going to be quite a relaxed talk.
We're going to give a high-level overview of all the different components that are there.
There's quite a lot of them, actually, so it's not possible to go into detail with the
time we have.
This is my first post-em talk ever, and also my first talk ever in a lecture hall, so that's
quite interesting.
Now, some background.
I mentioned that we are a government institute.
We firmly believe public money means public code, and we stand by that in almost everything
we do already.
We have an open source committee that also ensures that we do that, and we have basically
two very big telescopes.
One's called LOFAR, which stands for low frequency array, and the other is the Westerbork Synthetist
Telescope, also called WSRT.
There's some sister institutes that we work closely with or are related to us.
One is called COMRAS, which maintains a telescope that we've stopped using, and the others are
JIVE and EVN.
I'm not going to talk too much about those today.
What I want to show you is that there is this principle that our radio telescopes work on
that is called very long baseline interferometry, and this enables us to do radio astronomy
in a way that wasn't possible with traditional radio telescopes.
This is the whole map of LOFAR.
There's 54 stations in total.
Roughly 25 of those are located in the Netherlands.
I say it's around 2,000 kilometres in diameter, but that's no longer true because the one
in Rosen is new and we're now about 2,500 kilometres in diameter.
This diameter is also called the baseline, which is where the very long baseline interferometry
comes from.
If we then zoom into a station, you see all these tiles, and you see these little squares.
Those are the different types of antenna, and that is what makes this type of radio
astronomy so interesting, is that we don't have a single antenna to catch radio waves.
We have lots of them, about 20,000 in total, actually, which is quite substantial.
This centre is called the SuperTurb, and it's located in Ex-Lode, the Netherlands.
How can we actually combine this data?
I told you that traditional radio astronomy relies on a parabolic dish or a single antenna,
and we try to scale those up, make them bigger and bigger.
Of course, physics are at the limits at some point.
You can't make a structure from steel that's like 500 metres in diameter.
What we do instead is we combine smaller antennas to act as if they are a parabolic antenna.
The trick about a parabolic antenna is that all radio waves, no matter where they are
incoming from, they all have an equal distance to the receiver.
We need to emulate that with our antennas.
We do that in two ways.
There is an artificial delay, an analogue artificial delay, by just making the line
that it needs to travel across on the PCB or the coax cable longer, but we can also
do it digitally after the data is being sampled.
Then we can aim into the sky and create a very narrow beam that observes a very small
portion of the sky.
That allows us to zoom really deep into space and make very detailed images.
But what is this radio waves actually?
What are those?
What are we observing?
There are two types of radio waves that are being emitted by objects in space and the
galaxy.
We're only going to describe one phenomena today that's called synchrotron radiation.
Basically, if you have an ion, a charged particle, and you accelerate that, then it starts creating
radio wave emissions.
The frequency and the intensity at the frequency that is actually very dependent, that's all
details that are not very interesting for this talk.
But one of these entities that emit these types of charged particles are sometimes black
holes.
We'll see an example of that at the end.
I mentioned black holes.
There's other types of radio astronomy that are very interesting.
We can also model our own ionosphere, so there's more enlightening.
Stars are pretty interesting.
These are stars that are rotating at a periodic interval.
They have very strong radio waves coming from the poles of those stars.
What does Loewe actually look like?
It's a very small antenna, as I told you.
We can see on the left that there's wires attached to those poles.
Those are actually dipole antennas.
If you configure them like this, where they are like a V shape, they are called inverted
V's.
These are the low band antennas.
On the right side, you see the high band antennas.
They're like a clover shape, like a tie shape.
Then we combine all these low band antennas and 69 high band antennas in a station, and
we send the data at around 3 gigabits per second to our HPC clusters.
There's a two-phase cluster here.
The first is GPU processing, where we do correlation and beamforming.
The second is central processing, which is more like CPU based.
In the early days, our computing cluster looked something like this.
We had IBM BlueJeans machines, which were based on PowerPC, and they had a 3D Torus
interconnect, which is actually quite interesting interconnect.
This was problematic because utilizing the floating point vector extensions required
manually rewriting assembly, which wasn't that nice and was pretty hard to find developers
who were willing or capable to do that.
We moved to commodity hardware, two CPUs per socket, two sockets per server, two GPUs per
server, lots of networking.
That is really what you see here.
We had 32 gigabytes of 10 gigabit Ethernet, and then in 2018, when we upgraded, we had
24 times or 23 times of 100 gigabits in FiniBand, but you also see that there's a lot of 10
gigabit Ethernet per device.
I'm going to go into that while it is in a minute.
If you look at the data flow or more like a software site, then you see that the antennas
have ADC, so these convert the analog waves that are incoming to digital signals, and
then we do beamforming on the stations, and we send data to the correlator.
This correlator also does the correlation afterwards.
You can see that once the correlator is done with it, we store this to disk, and once it's
stored on disk, then it's made available to the central processing.
The correlator and our GPU cluster, Cobalt, are doing streaming, and the central processing
is more like your traditional HPC.
When we look at the data flow in Cobalt, there's all this incoming 10 gigabit Ethernet, and
this is why we have four or three 10 gigabit Ethernet links per Cobalt server.
They are streaming the data, and we configure a per station where it needs to send its data
to.
Then, once it's there, it's being transposed at roughly 240 gigabits, and once it's transposed,
we do have two pipelines that essentially run in parallel.
One is correlation, and one is additional beamforming.
We actually beamform twice in a sense.
It's a little bit more complicated than I'm sketching here, but I'm keeping things simple
because stations also have the capability to not beamform and send un-beamform data.
We have a special buffer that's called the transient buffer, where we dump raw samples
and can send those two clusters, but the general pipeline is what I'm sketching here.
If I zoom into these two pipelines, the correlator pipeline and the beamformer pipeline, I don't
want you to look at the details too much here because that's not interesting and I really
don't have time to explain it.
The trick is almost everything you see here is based on signal processing, digital signal
processing.
That's what we're doing.
We're using the fast Fourier transform, finite input response filters, and transforming the
data in the frequency domain, if you will.
Then it's put back into CPU memory at Cobalt.
Some final transformations are being placed, and then it's put into the disk so that CEP
can work on it.
At Ostrone, we do a lot with software, and I've showed you now how the data flows, but
I haven't told you what software components are making that data flow happen.
For Cobalt, it's actually one solid product that lives in the Loafer repository.
Please don't all now visit or get lab instance at once because it will die if you do that.
Try to spread that out a little bit over the day.
I'm sure I will upload the slides soon after, so you don't have to remember all this.
All these tools that are listed here, except for Cobalt with lives in the Loafer repo,
those are more like what you would find on the CEP side of things.
I'm going to explain, I want to address that this is just the tip of the iceberg.
On our GitHub repo, you can find a lot of more stuff that you can play with, and I would
encourage you to do so because it's quite interesting.
Then there's also CasaCore, which is heavily being developed at Ostrone as well, but it's
not actually just a product just by us.
A competitor or like a friend of CasaCore would be Ostropy.
Very widely known packages in the industry.
If you look at the radio astronomy toolkit, so the necessary things to go from antenna
to image, if you will, then these are your friends.
There's DP cubed, W clean, and IDG, and Rattler, AO flagger, and I'm not going to talk too
much about every beam.
What do these things do?
What are we looking at here?
DP cubed is where you define a complete pipeline.
You have the incoming data, you need to do some transformations on the data, maybe you
want to identify some noise sources that might be in your data, and eventually you want to
create an image, and for this imaging you need deconvolution as well.
You also need gridding and degridding.
AO flagger is where you identify noise sources.
This can be anything.
Radio instruments are very sensitive.
One noise source in particular would be electric fences, windmills, solar farms, bed quality
LED lighting.
Then we move to the imaging part with W clean, because when you have a radio telescope consisting
of many small antennas, in between your antennas there are holes, and that means that you're
not receiving the data as if you would have a very large parabolic dish.
There's some differences.
This creates some kind of fringing in the image that you need to filter out, and that's
what the W clean together with RATLAR and IDG are doing.
In IDG is your translation from the data domain to a domain that is useful for radio astronomical
imaging.
I talked a little bit about CasaCore, now it was industry widely used.
It's based on all the packages that have been around for a very long time, but we've actually
switched to the route now, so now CasaCore is built on top of these other packages rather
than CasaCore depending on these other packages.
There's several unique features here.
The UV domain is pretty interesting, so that's the domain about the plane that is filled,
so those holes in your surface area, if you will.
There's some Python bindings here, so these are all very nice tools that you can just
play with.
We also use a lot of open source tools, and we're doing quite well.
There's still some close source software, I'll get into that in a minute.
We use OpenMPI, OpenMP, SLURM, GitLab, Grafana, and actually the part that I work on is PyTangle,
which is a SCADA system.
With supervisory control and data acquisition, that's basically your interface that we have
on the individual stations.
Those stations then configure underlying hardware with the antennas and the ADCs, and they report
how they are configured to a higher level system.
We also use Prometheus, Docker, and a variety of interesting open source tools.
This is just the tip of the iceberg as well, there's much more.
Next to our SEP cluster is also pretty interesting, which is actually very useful, and we also
have a dust disk cluster, which is a cluster shared with many universities within the country.
Things where we can improve.
Well, we use CUDA, so that's not really open source compared to OpenCL or Falcon.
We're using WinCC for monitoring.
Maybe you've heard of that package, it's Windows-based, hence why it's called WinCC.
We're trying to face that out for Gervana and Prometheus.
That's going quite well, I'd say.
We have a lot of closed source SPEDA fender blocks, so if you have your Xilinx or your
Altera, then they, for instance, offer IP blocks to implement 100 gigabit internet interfaces,
and they're not too keen on you sharing those with the whole wide world.
Then InfiniBand firmware is pretty closed source.
I believe there's open source versions of that, but I don't think I know if they work
quite well.
Then the main area that we're actually struggling is with office management tools.
This is definitely the area that we can improve the most at Ostrone.
We use Office 365, Slack, and Zoom.
As you can see, Kupan, Omato, Moast, Jitsi, there's definitely open source alternatives
to this, so there's no real reason why we should be using this.
Of course, you need to host the infrastructure, and that also costs money, so there's some
little way there.
I'm not saying that it's definitely cheaper, but there's open source alternatives to this.
Now I want to show you, I told you about IDG that does the gridding and de-gridding.
I told you about VSWClean and the Dravata part that does the deconvolution now, and
I want to show you how those tools work in practice.
We have an ideal point source.
This is our most ideal radio source that can possibly exist.
It creates a very sharp point in the sky.
We put it toward the gridding, and we get a point function.
What this basically is, is this is the error of our telescope.
We now know, okay, this is the error it's going to generate in our images, because we
don't have complete filling of the UV plane.
There are holes in between our antennae, and then we can use the VSWClean image together
with Radler for deconvolution to create an iterative process in which we iteratively
remove the noise from the image.
Actually I'm going to see...
Oh yeah, that's nice.
Here you see these lines.
These lines are the fringes that I've told, and if you then perform these iterative cleaning
process on what are called calibrated visibilities, then we iteratively see that this image is
drastically improved.
Now, some example of this.
What is the science that we do with LoFAR?
How does this look like?
Well, this is a paper by Eric Timmerman, so you can look at it when you spare time.
What we're basically seeing here is we're seeing huge jets of these synchrotron radiation
emissions that are talked about.
You can see that they actually over millions of years, they vary in intensity.
At the center of this image is actually a black hole, but you can't see that because
it's a black hole.
And then on the background of this image, there is an overlay of what's the optical
domain, so not the radio domain, from the Hubble Space Telescope.
This is what we've been able to capture with LoFAR.
So we're doing groundbreaking science, and we're going to do a lot more.
We're in the middle of a big upgrade that's scheduled for the end of 2014.
WinCEC is going to be replaced with Kefana.
We're thinking about Olerta, but I've heard that Kefana has persistent alarms during actually
for STEM today, so we might not need Olerta.
And we're using Prometheus.
We had these low-band antennas, and the high-band antennas.
I briefly skimped over that because the details, yeah, you have to cut some corners somewhere.
But basically with LoFAR 2, we'll be able to use both of them in a single observation.
We'll also be able to use multiple beams, so I talked about the beam forming currently.
LoFAR is only able to have a single beam per observation.
And we will also be able to point at different points in the sky, change that during an observation.
And we call this Mega Mode.
Don't ask me why.
Yeah, we're completely refamping the SCADA system.
We're now using Patango.
We have sufficiently upgraded hardware, Unibore 2s.
We actually sell those to external institutes as well, so they're available.
And we're drastically improving the timing distribution, so we're currently GPS-based.
Everything is synchronized using GPS, all the stations across Europe.
And we're going to use the White Rabbit protocol that's made by CERN.
That's based on the Precision Time protocol.
Now very briefly, this Mega Mode, what would this schematically look like?
So this is basically what's running on Cobalt or GPU cluster, and we do imaging and beam
forming.
And now we have one beam and several pointings.
And they stay the same during observations.
Now we can have multiple beams, and we can re-point during the observation.
That's going to create a lot of flexibility for the astronomers, and I'm going to be very
excited with the science that is going to come from this.
I want to leave you with some links, as mentioned, our Ostrone repo, the Ostrone website.
There's a very interesting page about 10 years of LOFR, because we've actually existed,
LOFR has been in production since 2008, so that's been since quite some time.
There's this very nice map on which you can actually see all the physical locations of
all the stations, how many antennas are active or working or broken.
So this is all open data.
You can just look at this, and there's some history about all these presentations that
have done in the past.
So any questions?
Any questions for Poutet?
I see one.
We first a short comment.
The Chinese built a 500-meter dish, but that's just...
But what I really wanted to ask is whether you have collaboration with other astrophysical
observations like square kilometer array or something like that?
Well actually we collaborate on the square kilometer array, so there's definitely...
Can you repeat part of your question, because people were just leaving?
Well, whether there is shared development in software and stuff?
Yeah, for sure.
For instance on CasaCore, as I mentioned, but also WSClean, we see contributions from
external collaborators, and especially the part of Jive that I showed at the very beginning.
Let me see.
Shouldn't be too long.
So here I mentioned Jive and EPN.
This is a huge collaboration of parabolic dishes that are all connected, and all the
data centrally to Dringalo at the headquarters of Asturong.
And that's actually where the EPN network processes all this data.
But all these dishes that we use, those are not ours, right?
Those are from other parties.
Another question from the Jack and Ralph.
Someone's asking, since everything's processed digitally, can these telescopes focus on multiple
targets at once by processing the data multiple times?
That's an interesting question, and that depends.
As I said, you have to transient buffers, which dump raw samples.
But typically what we do is we already do beamforming on the station.
And if you do the beamforming on the station, you're already looking at some point in the
sky.
You're only sending the result data from that beamforming to this cobalt cluster, and you
can't beamform again then.
The data is lost.
It's reductive in nature.
But if you would send the raw sample data to cobalt, and it could somehow process all
the data, which I don't think it has the bandwidth to do so, then you could, at a later point
in time, point at any point in the sky again.
That's the job of the transient buffers.
Thanks.
Maybe a question here.
Would there be any ways or interests for amateur astronomers or radio astronomers, of course,
to help or work with astronomy?
Well, there's definitely job positions on our page all the time, I think.
I don't know if most are in the field of radio astronomy, but what typically happens, and
I can briefly explain, is we have a system called NordStar in which astronomers submit
their proposals and describe what they want to do with their instrument.
And then we have a community that looks at that, and that actually accepts these proposals,
and then they are scheduled.
This is actually a very good question, because I completely skipped this in the talk, but
I wanted to talk about this.
And then things are scheduled in a system called TMS, and that basically looks at, okay,
what part of these stations are required to do these observations and collect these data.
Then these data are collected and processed on cobalt and sap, and the data products are
made available to these individual astronomers who've done that, and they get exclusive access
for a period of time to do their research.
Okay, thanks.
I was more thinking about just if someone is like in Africa with a homemade dish, is
there any way to maybe capture something with an SDR and add a little bit to this data,
or the scale of things is so different that...
It's actually very important, or it's rather we need to model a lot of things and calibrate
a lot of things.
So that's why all the stations are roughly similar in shape, have similar hardware, so
it would be definitely possible to buy your own station, build your own station, and have
the same hardware, and then hook it up.
That happens all the time.
Different countries do that, buy stations, and then we add them.
But having very fastly different hardware and then hooking this up to this system would
be very difficult.
It's not designed to do that.
Okay, so if you would make a very cheap station that could be built by amateur astronomers,
you could deploy that a bit everywhere in the world, and then make your public radio
astronomy like that.
Interesting.
Thanks.
Any more questions?
Okay, we'll wrap it up.
Okay.
All right.