So, good morning everybody. I'm happy to see such a large crowd here. I hope I can stand
up for that. So, I will talk a little bit today about, a little bit about matter and
threat as a connectivity solution for embedded here. So, the agenda I have, I mean, giving
a little bit of a scope for the talk, then give you like an overview about matter. So,
I don't know how is time-love is set, how is time-love is open-thread and so on. So,
we'll start a little bit with that. And then how I'm using it or what we are doing using
it on Yocto as well as on ZFire. And then also how we are using matter on top of open-thread.
Talking about the more generic mesh capabilities that thread is offering you and the border
router that is needed to get it all hooked together. And then about one more detail that
is just have been introduced about like multicast DNS discovery proxy as well as service into
the service-re
the
power budget. So, having for example small sensor device that can run on a coin cell
battery for whatever six months, a year, maybe two years depending on the use cases and the
usage. And having mesh capabilities that don't have only like direct connections but we like
being able to extend the network over time by adding more devices and so on. And for
the situation with the power budget, sleepy end devices that really only wake up if they
are being interrupted for a specific use case or only waking up for a short amount of time
to querying the parent to get data that is also something I considered here. All the
stuff I'm talking about here are obviously open source solutions. Thread as well as matter
have found a consortium around them to like do products and do like testing and verification
as well as getting a certification and so on. This is definitely something different.
So, if you want to build a product you might need to pay for some specific parts but all
the software side or the engineering side that is open source here and that's what I'm
going to talk about. So, matter. Some people might have heard about it before. It was formerly
known as connected home or IP or ship in short. It is part of the now so-called CSI connected
with standard alliance. That on the other hand was called Zigbee alliance before. I
think that is something that rings the bell with more people than CSA. They have an open
source SDK for matter. It is an application layer so you are basically like not doing
any of these. It is built on top of IP version 6 and then does all the talk about like how
devices access, how the data is expressed and so on. What kind of device types are there.
It is more like they call it like the language for IoT. I don't know if I sign off on that
but that is like the basic idea we are having here. So, the 1.0 release for the spec as
well as the SDK was done in October last year. One of the interesting part why it got so
much hype was like the industry was that a lot of the big players are set together and
doing that here. So, getting like groups like Google, Apple, Amazon and so on in one room
and working together on this standard to actually try to get all the devices to talk together
even by keeping their own platforms. That is like a very interesting part and that could
be something that a lot of smaller companies could take as a leverage to get into these
kind of platforms to be supported instead of working with each and every platform individually
and get it enabled. So, you don't need to get your device worked with home kit and then
with Google Home or what Amazon has there and so on. So, you can just do it as a matter
device and then it should work in all of them. They also have a feature called multi-admin
which is something that would allow you to have like an, for example, you have an Android
device and your wife has an iPhone or whatever and both could control the same IoT devices
in the same network running the native platforms they are using. So, this is something you
can share the devices by using on different platforms as well. So, Meta and Yocto and
Open and Better. So, the Meta SDK, the way they are building that and so on, it's not
so, I'm not so familiar with that before I started it. So, they're using something called
Gen which is just generate Ninja. So, basically, it just does a whole run and then generate
all the Ninja files to get it all built and they have something called Pickweet that they,
it's like their abstraction how you get like all different kind of vendor SDK supported
and like different coscompile two chains and so on. This is like difficult to get that
into something like Yocto and Better which just focus on the coscompiling part here.
So, that was quite a bit of work. So, we had to do like a Gen base class to get it supported
and did a lot of like work around here. But anyway, we got that part working. So, we have
the core libraries building, we have the examples that are part of the SDK building, we have
that all in the in our own new layer. But there's also a different layer from an XP
Meta, MetaMeter which does it a little bit differently but in the end you're getting
the same result. You have like integration to run that on a Linux system. So, this is
a, that is all there. You can take that and then build on top of the library and take
the examples, the devices to like do whatever you want there. On the Meta, on the Z-Files
side. So, on here is a project that runs not only on Linux but we also run it on the Z-Files
side. So, we have like multiple kernels there. So, we also need to make sure that we want
to have the integration part there as well. I have been working on a proof of concept
to get Meta as a sub module or as a Z-Files module integrated. So, the build system would
inside the Meta SDK there is like a platform abstraction for Z-Files which is based on
two SDKs from Asignotic and T-Link. Their SDKs are based on Z-Files as well and they
have like a generic Z-Files abstraction now. And then we have the integration part where
we have a CMake file and so on to hook that into the Z-Files build system. We are an external
module and you have like a specific module, a JAML file that just tells where the CMake
file is, how is the setup, how the build setup is and so on. And then you're setting things
like Open
and we are going this approach. So, Meta devices. So, the device types that are available in
the SDK coming from the 1.0 release are very limited. I think they only have like five
device types specified right now. There are definitely a lot more coming and will come
in the next upcoming releases. So, Meta is doing like two releases per year in spring
and autumn. So, there should be a lot more going on there. They're using the ZigBeat cluster
library so in case you're familiar with that from all the projects or something, so they're
basing the device types and abstraction on that one, extending it a little bit and then
using it. But it should be a very good base for your own devices. It doesn't mean it cover
all the nitty details. It has to be on your product or something but it could be a good
entry point for cover the basic functionality and then for details you might leave that
out and have like an out of band situation. Or you go to the Meta working group and work
with them to extend that over time. As usual, like set up is the QR codes you might know
from other devices already like HomeKit and so on. You can also use have a pin and then
you have NFC that is upcoming that you can use it as well. So, in terms of connectivity
layers what they are supporting in the beginning, that is Ethernet and Wi-Fi, there's no much
need to like adapt it or anything. For Wi-Fi they're working on a better soft, so right
now it's a soft IP set up if you want to bring a device in but that means you would need,
for example, if you do the soft IP with your phone and then you leave the connectivity
to your normal data. So they're working with the Wi-Fi alliance to change that as a neighboring
service. So that is good. Brutus or energy is also available for device onboarding. It's
not a connectivity layer they're using on for data transmission but it's just only for
onboarding. And as I mentioned before, they have like these, if you're not, if your device
supports more than the device type expressions they are doing, you either need to work together
with them to extend that or you need to find a way to have that as an out of bound connectivity.
But here comes the beauty of being IP version 6. You have like end-to-end connectivity to
the device and if you, for example, have like a mobile application or something that would
control this, you could still do all the work with META to support the basic functionality
and then hand over to the IP, to the end device over IP version 6 and then control the device
for like an extended API you might offer on the device. But Ethernet and Wi-Fi are not
really the ones I was looking into when looking at the power budget and designing devices
that are really power budget friendly and can run for like a year or so on a battery.
So I was looking into threat for that. So OpenThread is the open source implementation
of the threat specification. Threat group is the governance body, again, membership.
You have to pay fee if you want to get certified in Seron, but you don't have to do that if
you're just going for the implementation of this OpenThread. It's BSD3 license, so that's
all easy for you to integrate in your products in Seron. It's mostly driven by Google and
formerly Nest and it's a very established code base already in products and running
in the millions of the world already. So threat is a mesh network. So what does it
cover here? So you have like different types of devices that are part of the mesh network.
You have full threat devices which are normally devices that have like a good amount of power
budget being either line powered or having like a big battery that they can operate on.
These are like often like routers that can like take the packet forward to another one
to make sure that everything, the whole data keeps flowing. And then you have like router
electrical devices which is something that will become a router if the mesh network needs
them later on to make sure that the data keeps flowing or if they are like in a corner of
the mesh network where they need to increase the quality for all the other nodes available.
Or there could be just a simple full end device which is just operating there not doing any
routing or something but still being a full end device. And then for the power constraint
devices you have like minimal threat devices which are minimal end devices and they can
be sleepy devices. So basically they would like spend most of their lifetime just being
asleep not drawing or drawing as little power as possible and only wake up if they are getting
an interrupt like when you open your window or something like that you want to send the
notification out for that or you just have a short poll to a parent and ask if there
is any data left for you. So they are using 15.4 as a base layer, a file layer and they
have a functionality where you send out a packet if there is any data available for you
and even in the act frame already you have like a bit set where it says there is data
waiting for you don't go asleep, poll me again and then you are getting all the data and
if not you can fall asleep already again. You can also have like in the newer specifications
you have something that is like synchronized schedules but that would mean you need a newer
type of like ships available not all of them do that so you would have to need like 15.4
yeah the 2015 release for that so you need to find like the silicon ships that actually
support that and then you can get that running as well.
I talked about the router things before you have router device, you have end devices and
then you have a leader of the threat network. This one is in charge of making sure that
all the key material for example is distributed to all the networks, all the keys are getting
wrote over if they are running out of frame counter and so on that really makes sure that
all the stuff is available and all the devices get the need information and then you obviously
have like a standby leader if the leader is like running out of battery or like someone
tripped over the power cable or something like that so you have all of that covered
in the mesh functionality as well. And the other important device that is available in
such a network is the border router because you want to have these kind of things obviously
connected to at least to your home network. Maybe even to the internet that's up to you
but you want to have like more devices than only within the threat network and that is
where the border router comes in. I will talk about that a little bit later because it's
also relevant to the meta part for the integration. In terms of addressing, there are like three
different types of addresses. We have like the link local, what you can reach directly
within your range, in your wireless receiving range or transmitting range and then you have
mesh local addressing which is like available in the whole mesh network and then you have
like the global addresses. It's all IP, one of six addresses and they have like allow
you to like individually target specific parts of the mesh. I'm rushing through that a little
bit because it's too much to go into all the details here in 20 minutes but it's a little
bit more in the slides. So in terms of the software they're having there available, there's
the OpenS
core library which is used for all of them. Then you have abstractions for like all the
different silicon vendors integrating with their SDKs and so on. So you can see them
all there listed. If you have a specific device for example running that you could, you would
bare metal on that as well or you could go and run it for example as an OpenStrand module
on Zifier being supported. On the link side they have like two basic services they're
running. There's the OT daemon which is like the basically only a full enterprise which
could operate as a normal enterprise in the network and then you have the OpenStrand border
router POSIX, how they call it, that is the full border router set up that you would run
on your Linux device if it's the border router and engaging there.
So talking about all the power constraints you are having, so there are two advancements
that have been happening driven by meta mostly but falling back to Shred to make it even
more power efficient. This is a multicast DNS discovery proxy and the service registration
protocol. So I talked before the border router is like the central part here to shield the
mesh network from the rest of the network or the other way around. And this is, so if
you look at a lot of the IT devices you have maybe in your home you know about, these are
often like vendors where you have like one specific hub for your specific device types
and so on. Then you have the next hub for the other types and so on. This is all crowded
and so on. And for the border router this is often more a software component that can
be updated in devices already available. So the 15.4 radius they are used for Shred that
are the same radius that are used for Zigbee. That means all the hubs that you might have
already have Zigbee support, it is up to the hardware vendor if they want to change that
over to a different firmware and then all the other software around it to make sure
they can also support Shred. It's also possible to run like both of them in parallel if you
do like multi-protocol on the firmware level where you have like Zigbee device support
as well as Shred device support. That's a bit more complicated but it is possible as
well. But nowadays one of the problems I saw when I worked with Shred the first time was
like everybody needs to get like another device being the hub and so on. But if you look around
now there's tons of devices already available that offer border router functionality. All
the Apple devices like the HomePod, the HomePod mini, Apple TV, or the Google Nest device,
Echo and so on. All these things are like the if you have them in your house already
or like people your target audience have them in the house already it's already sorted out.
And then there's a lot more hubs doing the support as well. The new IKEA hubs have support
for it. I think that the smart things hub is going to plan support for it and so on.
Then a lot of these smaller vendors as well are coming out hopefully over the year. So
that means if you bring home an Open Shred device or a Shred device you shouldn't be
worried to get it onboard as long as you have some of these. So it's not as easy support
as Wi-Fi for example right now but it's good to get traction there. But coming back to
the situation about the discovery proxy. So this kind of wireless networks they don't
have any multicast support. So whatever you send in as a multicast there will end up as
a broadcast in the whole mesh network. Which is obviously not a good thing if you want
to be like if you're constrained in power and need to listen in and wonder what's going
on. I mean the sleepy end device for them it's not too difficult because they would
sleep and the parents would just discard whatever they have for them if it's not targeted directly
for the specific device. But all the other ones would still like draw on the batteries
they're having to do that. So on the other hand multicast DNS discovery is something
that is very much used in the industry for all kind of service discovery in networks.
So we want to address that support as well. So there's a component now that has been specified
as an ITF of C draft. But just sitting there and doing basically the proxy what what's
the name suggests right on the one hand if you have like Wi-Fi or Ethernet you do multicast
DNS on the other hand you do a unicast DNS service discovery and so on. So that is like
basically proxying back and forth. That doesn't mean depending on the bottle where you're
using you don't you're not forced to that. So the end to end principle of IP version
still stands. But it's like an optimization you maybe don't want to miss out on. And on
the other hand so that is mostly covering the side where you have like Wi-Fi and Ethernet
flooding into in a threat network. But on the threat side you also want to make sure
that you announce the device that are available and so on. That is like the service registration
protocol where you go and say I have the service available as DNS. So this is like what I'm
offering here. And they can register on the border router service for that. So that would
mean and would distribute that again as multicast DNS on the Wi-Fi Ethernet side. Yeah. So transparent
gateway. So that is like how I knit all the things together. So we have a blueprint that
is like in a neuro hobby. We talk about like proof of concept demos we are doing and we
have a layer where we do all the integration parts here or the open threat stuff. I upstream
already they are in meta-o-e networking and the meta stuff that is still very much work
in progress going on as well as the ZIFI outside. But if you're interested in that I mean it's
not I'm not hiding anything here it's just not not ready to show. But if you're interested
we can talk about like where these things are. So this is like an old example I had
where I had like just a threat device being on border to it could like go ahead have like
secure our code for this specific device and then you have even have an Android application
to onboard on the network and so on and do all the stuff and then in the end this is
all the components together you have like IP version 6 connectivity and on top of that
this meta you would have like a real device abstraction and offering all kind of platform
integration and so on. And with that I'm done and I should have like a few minutes for questions.
Hi there thank you very much for that. We're currently looking at developing a meta cellular
gateway using some of the new ESP32 chips that are coming out. What I'm having trouble
getting my head around is the underlying physical layer in terms of 802.15.4 versus Wi-Fi 802.11.
And so what I'm trying to understand is if I buy a meta device it might be a meta device
that supports Wi-Fi or it might be a meta device that supports Fred over 802.15.4 which
to my mind feels like it's going to be really confusing for people. And I'm asking as we
go to develop this border router should we focus on supporting sensor like devices that
are Wi-Fi devices or 802.15.4 devices or is it not that simple?
I think it's sensible to make sure that you have at least a 1.5.4 radio in the device
because I think all the sensor devices you will see coming are most likely to use Fred
because just power budget wise I mean at least the feedback I saw in the working groups and
so the feedback I got in the working groups. Excuse me if you're moving in or out of the
room can you please do that quietly whilst we're doing the Q&A and try and keep the noise
down to a minimum because it's getting very difficult to be heard here. So please be considerate
to others.
Okay so I think you really need to make sure that you have that available because all the
companies that are looking into that they want to be conservative in power or something
they're definitely going for that. So and I mean if you do the hardware setup make sure
you have the radio available. If you enable that by default from the beginning it's up
to you right. I mean you can always have like the firmware available and then do ship the
device and then enable it later on that I've seen tons of devices doing that but having
it available for the hardware perspective I would not ditch that. It's like yes it's
like a few euro maybe depending on the volume and so on but I'm pretty sure that most of
the device will come with that.
Okay I've got a question from online here. I'm over here. Online we have a question.
What's the rationale for a non-router end device if it doesn't have any power management
requirements? What's the rationale for a non-router end device if it doesn't have any power management
requirements?
Okay I mean the thing is it could be a router. Normally in that case it would be like a read
like a router a leisure device but you maybe you don't need all the routers available in
your network right. I mean you have like if you have a mesh network and depending on how
the topology is and like maybe your house or your how the environment is basically you
have maybe enough routers available at that point. So all of the full end devices can
do that but you might don't choose for that so.
Okay any more questions?
Can you put your hand up?
Hi. So one of the most controversial parts from this back.
A little bit louder sorry very noisy.
So one of the most controversial parts of this back when it was released was they were
talking about authentication onto the network like onboarding via blockchain. Can you discuss
that a little bit?
Okay so what I think what you reference to is like the distributed ledger. So having
so one of the ideas that is like work around the in the meta-working group is like the
distributed ledger where you can authenticate the devices that are like so you're basically
not getting fake device in the network and so on. That's definitely something that could
be could be problematic for if you want to like do your own devices in your own home
for example and get them onboarded. I still have to see if that is really enforced or
not. That is really depending on the platform and so on how you're using that together.
Yeah but I need I need to hear some microphone or something.
Have you managed to get a DIY device onto an actual Google matter network yet?
Not on a Google network now. I was able to like get it all working together on my own
setup but I didn't work against the platform since around.
Yeah that sort of seems like one of the problems.
Well we have to see I wouldn't rule it out right now but I can I can confirm that it's
possible but it really depends on how you do it. But it's definitely the concern you're
right.
It's possible.
It's possible? Okay so yes someone said it's possible here. So okay. Okay thank you everybody.
Okay thank you very much.
Thank you.
Check the chat room. There's one more question on the chat room you can answer.
Okay.
Thank you.