Thank you for the opportunity to present our project, Namba NPI.
Let me first acknowledge the co-authors.
My name is Sylvester Arabas, and we are here with Alexi Bulenok and Kasper Derlatka from
Yagilonian University in Krakow, Poland, Machin Manna from the same university contributed
to this project, and we have also, we will be presenting some work from David Zwicker
from Max Planck Institute for Dynamics and Self-Organization in Göttingen.
So let's start with a maybe controversial provocative question, Python and HPC, and let's
try to look for answers to this question in a very respective, respected journal.
So maybe you have some guesses what's written there.
2019, in scripting languages such as Python, users type code into an interactive editor
line by line.
It doesn't sound like HPC.
Next year, level of computational performance that Python simply couldn't deliver.
Same year, same journal.
Numpy runs on machines ranging from embedded devices to the world's largest supercomputers
with performance approaching that of compiled languages.
Same year, nature astronomy.
Astronomers should avoid interpreted scripting languages such as Python.
In principle, Numpy and Numpy can lead to an enormous increase in speed, but please reconsider
teaching Python to university students.
Same year, nature methods.
Implementing new functionality into SciPy, Python is still the language of choice.
Full tests should pass with the PyPy Just-in-Time compiler as of 1.0 SciPy.
Are they talking about the same language?
No.
The left-hand side are papers about Rust and Julia.
The right-hand side are papers about Python.
Okay?
So maybe that's the reason.
So just to set the stage, let me present, I think, the way that is apt for thinking about
Python.
So Python as a language lacks any support for multidimensional arrays or number crunching
because it leaves it to packages to be handled.
Python also leaves it to implementations to actually interpret its syntax.
And SciPy, of course, the major domain implementation, but it's not the only one.
And actually, solutions exist that streamline, for example, Just-in-Time compilation of Python
code.
Moreover, Numpy, while de facto standard, is not the implementation of the Numpy API.
And alternatives are embedded in Just-in-Time frameworks, Just-in-Time compilation frameworks,
GPU frameworks for Python, and they leverage typing and concurrency.
So probably here the highlight is that Python lets you glue these technologies together
and package them together, leveraging some of the Python ecosystem and its popularity,
etc.
And probably, arguably, I would say that's an advantage.
I'm not saying that please use Python for HPC instead of Julia, probably vice versa,
actually.
But still, it's an interesting question to see how it can perform.
Okay, so let's check it.
I will present a brief benchmark, a very tiny one that we have come up with in relation
with this project.
And it uses Numba.
Numba is a Just-in-Time compiler that translates a subset of Python and Numpy into machine
code that is compiled at runtime using LLVM.
Okay, so here is the story about the super simple benchmark problem.
It's related to numerical weather prediction.
So you can imagine a grid of numbers representing weather here.
And numerical weather prediction, or part of numerical weather prediction, the integration
part involves solving equations for the hydrodynamics, that is the transport of such pattern in space
and time, and of course, thermodynamics that tell you what's happening in the atmosphere.
Super simplified picture.
I'm not saying that's the whole story about NWP.
But for benchmarking Numba, let's simplify it down to, in this case, two-dimensional
simple problem.
You have a grid, x, y, some signal.
And if we look at just the transport problem, a partial differential equation for transport,
we can see what happens if we move around such signal, which could be some humidity,
temperature, or whatever in the atmosphere.
Okay, so we have a sample problem.
Here I'm showing results from a three-dimensional version of what was just shown.
And let's start with the right-hand side plot.
X axis, the size of the grid.
So if it's eight, it means eight by eight.
Super tiny.
If it's 128, it's 128 by 128 by 128.
And wall time per time step on the y axis.
Green.
C++ implementation of one particular algorithm for this kind of problems.
Orange.
PiMP data.
The same algorithm numerically, but a Python implementation.
So here you see that actually Numba just compiled version outperformed C++, maintaining even
better scaling for the tiny matrices, but they are kind of irrelevant for the problem.
And please note that in both cases we have used multi-threading.
So here on the left-hand side, you can see actually on the x axis number of threads,
y axis wall time per time step.
And again, the green line is the C++ implementation.
These two are two variants of the Python one.
JIT compiled with Numba.
Almost an order of magnitude faster execution.
Five times faster.
And what's probably most interesting for now is that when you compare with just setting
the environment variable for Numba JIT to disabled, we jump more than two orders of
magnitude up in wall time.
So this is how Numba timing compares with plain Python timing.
But there are two important things to be mentioned here.
The Python package is written having Numba in mind.
That is, everything is loop based, which is the reason why plain CPython with Numba performs
badly.
And this line is kind of irrelevant, just as a curiosity.
On the other hand, the C++ version is kind of legacy based on Blitz++ library.
Back then when it was developed, Eigen didn't have support for multiple dimensions.
And it's object oriented processing which was reported and measured to be kind of five
times slower than for some 77 for these kind of small domains.
It's not the same for larger domains.
Anyhow, we can achieve high performance with Python.
But what if we need MPI?
We need message passing in our code.
How would we use it?
Let's say we divide in a domain that can position spirit our domain in two parts.
So the same problem, same setup, just half of the domain is computed by one process or
node or anything that has distributed, has different memory addressing than another worker.
So this is how we want to use it.
Why we want to use MPI?
Well, because despite expansion in parallel computation, both in the number of machines
and the number of cores, no other parallel programming paradigm has replaced MPI.
At least as of 2013.
And already in 2013, people were writing that this is even though it's universally acknowledged
that MPI is a crude way of programming these machines.
Anyhow, still let's try it.
And let's try it with Python.
So here is a seven line snippet of code where we try to import number to get the JIT compilation
of Python code.
And then we use MPI for Py which is Python interface to MPI.
What do we do?
We find some number crunching routine and we try to use MPI from it and then we try
to end JIT.
End JIT means the highest performance variant of number JIT compilation.
We try to JIT compile this function and straight ahead execute it.
What happens?
It doesn't work.
It doesn't compile because Numba cannot determine type of MPI for Py.MPI.intrachom.
Because it's a class.
Classes do not work with Numba.
At least not the ordinary Python classes.
So something doesn't work.
So the problem is that we have Numba which is one of the leading solutions to speed up
Python.
We have MPI which is clearly the standard for distributed memory parallelization.
We try to work with them together but it doesn't work.
So stack overflow.
Let's duck, duck, go it.
Nothing.
Let's quantit.
Wrong search engine, right?
Someone must have solved the problem.
Nothing.
Let's ask Numba guys and MPI for Py guys.
June 2020.
You will not be able to use MPI for Py's Python code.
It was not designed for such low level usage.
Okay.
It's a Python.
But I mean it must be doable, right?
We have two established packages.
The aim is kind of solid and makes sense.
So it must be doable.
And 30 months later, 120 comments later, 50 PRs later from five contributors on a totally
unplanned site project, we are introducing Numba MPI.
It's an open source kind of small Python project which allows you to let's jump here to the
hello world example which allows you to use the Numba and JIT decorator on a function
that involves rank, size or any other MPI API calls within the Python code.
So now we cover size, rank, send, receive, broadcast, the API for Numba MPI is based
on Numba.
We have auto generated documentation.
We are on PyPy and Conda Forge.
Few words about how it's implemented.
Essentially we start with C types built into Python to try to address the C API.
There are some things related with passing addresses, memories, void pointers, et cetera.
Not super interesting.
Probably the key message here is that we are offering the send function that is already
N JITed which means you can use it from other N JITed functions.
We handle non-continuous arrays from Numba MPI so we try to be user friendly.
We then call the underlying C function.
Kind of that's all.
Truly there is the key line number 30.
This one.
Well, that's nothing but in principle without it Numba optimizes out all our code.
Anyhow, these are kind of things that you see when trying to implement such things.
Unfortunately there are quite more of such hacks inside Numba MPI.
The next slide is kind of thing that you prefer to never see but they cannot be unseen in
a way if you work with it.
So please just think of it as a picture of some problems that we have challenged and
essentially wrote to Numba guys asking how can it be done and we got this kind of tools
for handling void pointers from C types in Numba with Python, NumPy, et cetera.
But well, that's you, Tilt Spy, and that's it.
And it kind of works.
And why do we know it works?
Because we test it.
And let me handle the mic to Alexey to tell you more about testing.
Here it is.
Thank you.
Okay.
This works.
So I'm going to tell you about the CI that we have set up for our project for Numba MPI.
So the CI was set up on a...
Sorry.
The wrong arrow.
The CI was set up at GitHub Actions, as I said.
This is the screen of the workflow.
We start from running the PDOC, pre-commit, and Pylint.
PDOC is for automatic documentation generation, Pylint for static content analysis, and pre-commit
for styling.
After that, if these steps were successfully moved into the main part where we run our
unit tests, this is the example...
Not example, but actually the workflow file that we run.
As you can see, when we run the CI against multiple systems, different Pylint versions
and different MPI implementations.
And here we should say a big thank you to MPI for PyTeam for providing setup MPI GitHub
Action, because this has saved us a lot of time.
Thank you MPI for Py.
And as of operation systems and MPI implementations, we are running...
In case of Linux, we are testing against OpenMPI, MPI-CH, and Intel-PI, Mac OS, MPI-MPI-NC,
MPI-CH, and in case of Windows, it's of course MSMPI implementation.
But when we are talking about MPI-CH, there is a problem that has recently occurred, namely
starting from version four of MPI-CH, it fails for on a Ubuntu, on our CI, for PyTeam version
less than 3.10.
So if anyone has ideas how to fix it, please contact us, we will appreciate any help.
Okay, so we are running the unit test on different systems and so on.
Let's see the sample unit test.
In this test, we are testing the logic of the wrapper, of the broadcast function of
MPI, and the main thing that you should remember from this slide is that we are testing this
function in plain Python implementation as well as JIT compiled by number.
We have also set up an integration test.
The integration test is in another project named by SuperDopplet-LES.
And this is just a scheme of this test, we are starting from providing the initial conditions
for the APDS solver, and these initial conditions are written to the HDF5 file.
After that, we are running three runs.
First one we run with only one process, the second one we have two processes, in the third
we run the three processes, and in each we divide, well, in the first we don't divide
the domain, but the other ones we divide the domain accordingly.
And in the assert state we just compare the results and we want the results to be the
same for different runs.
And also these results are also written to HDF5 file.
Interesting fact that everything works on Windows except installing HDF5.py package
for concurrent file access.
HD5.py package with enabled MPI.io.
We have troubles setting up on Windows, but everything else works fine.
And there is also an independent use case, the PyPD project that uses our library, our
package, and it's not developed by us, so the reader is a user.
And this is the Python package for solving partial differential equation, it focuses
on finite differencing and PDEs are defined by, are provided as strings.
And the solution strategy as follows, we start from partitioning the grid onto different
nodes using number MPI after that we pass expressions using the simpy and compile the
results using number and then we trade the PDE exchange in boundary information between
the nodes using number MPI.
Take home messages.
There is a common mismatch between the Python language and Python ecosystem.
We should remember that, okay, the language could be slow, but we also should consider
the ecosystem around this language, the libraries that are available, the libraries that are
available and probably different implementations.
And Python has a range of global HPC solutions such as just in time compilation, GPU programming,
multithreading and MPI.
In case of number MPI, this is the package to glue the MPI with Python code.
It is tested on CI, on GitHub actions.
We are aiming for 100% unit test coverage and also there is also already the project
that are dependent on this package.
Here we can find the links for number MPI, the GitHub links and also the links to the
packages at PyPy and Anaconda.
And we also welcome contributions.
The first two issues I have mentioned earlier and we also welcome encourage to provide the
logo for number MPI as well as adding support for the other functions or we are also aiming
for dropping dependency on MPI for Py in our project and also the plan is to benchmark
performance of this package.
And also we wanted to acknowledge funding.
The project was funded by National Science Centre of Poland.
Thank you for your attention.
We now have time for questions.
Thank you very much.
Any questions?
Question from an MPI expert.
Thank you.
Hello.
Thank you for the talk.
So the interface you are proposing is very close to the let's say C MPI interface.
Let's say when you do a send you work with a buffer or do you try to provide a bit higher
level interface for example serializing some Python object or it could be very useful.
Yeah, the interface is as slim thin as possible probably.
Very close to the C MPI.
One of the reasons being that within Numba and JIT code, things like serialization might
not be that easy to do.
There is no problem in combining MPI for Py and Numba MPI in one code base.
So when you are out of the JIT code you can use MPI for Py which has high level things
like serialization, et cetera.
So you can use it there but within LLVM compiled blocks you can use Numba MPI for simple send
receive already used.
Without higher level array functioning.
Having said that we for example handle transparently noncontiguous slices of arrays, we also yeah
there are some things that are higher level than C interface but in general we try to
provide a wrapper around the C routines.
Okay, thank you.
Any other questions?
Thanks for a great talk.
It seems really interesting what you are working on.
I have a couple of questions probably born out of ignorance but I just kind of wondered
if you could help me with them.
So firstly I was wondering why you went with making a separate package rather than sort
of trying to build this functionality on top of MPI for Py.
Would it have been possible to sort of add this feature of making things JIT compilable
into MPI for Py?
And secondly I was kind of wondering with the MPI I.O. thing that you were looking at
with Windows, if that requires kind of concurrent file access from separate processes in Windows,
is that just a complete no go for Windows?
Because I understand that's something that Windows kernel doesn't support.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Let me start from the second one.
So here our well, essentially it's a fun fact that everything else worked for Windows.
We do not really target Windows but it was nice to observe that all works.
It's kind of one of these advantages of Python that you code and you don't really need to
take too much care about the targeted platforms because the underlying packages are meant
to work on all of them.
And here everything works with Microsoft MPI.
The only thing that actually was a problem for us was to even install H5.py on Windows
with MPI support.
So we don't really know what's the true bottleneck but even the documentation of H5.py suggests
again trying.
For the first question, why do we create, why do we develop a separate package instead
of adding it on top of MPI 4.py?
So I think even on the slide with the story of the package, there was a link to MPI 4.py
issue, the bottom footnote, where we suggested would it be possible to add it?
And in relation with the first question, so probably the scope, the goal of MPI 4.py is
to provide very high level API for MPI in Python.
So with discussing with the developers there, we realized that it's probably not within
the scope of a very high level interface.
So we started off with just, well, small separate project.
But I mean, well, great idea.
It could be glued together.
We aim for dropping dependency on MPI 4.py which we now use just for some utility routine,
not for the communication or nothing that is used by Numba.
And probably that might be an advantage because you can eventually you should be able to install
Numba MPI with very little other dependencies.
And Numba MPI is written purely in Python.
So installing it, you do not need to have any site on related C compiled code and you
can do it quite easily.
Okay.
Thank you very much.