So, the next lightning talk is Victor, and this should be a really fun talk, I think,
about MLOps.
Yes.
So, hello.
This is probably going to be the least serious talk you have seen today.
So, I'm sorry about that.
We're going to be automating weight loss with AI.
It's a stupid project I made in a weekend, or like in a few weekends, but I want to talk
about it.
So, who am I?
Lightning talk version.
I'm Victor Sunk.
I work at ClearML.
Hi.
Let's make something.
So, that's the reason why I'm here.
The problem statement was I'm working at home, and I'm not working out enough, like probably
a lot of us are.
And so, the problem solution is why not lock my PC every hour and force myself to do push-ups,
and then it automatically opens again.
That was the main idea.
I want to do this with AI, obviously, because over-engineering.
And I'm a machine learning engineer, so if I am a hammer, everything looks like a nail.
This is going to be the diagram.
So, left top is an oak one.
It's an AI camera.
I'll talk about it in a second.
That will run one model, and then because one AI model is not enough, I have two.
So, there is a second model that runs on the Raspberry Pi that will lock my PC.
This is what it looks like.
So, you get like a notification, workout time, lazy bum, and you have to do push-ups.
It's in Raspberry Pi running in the corner of my room.
You can follow along with the diagram at the right top.
So, I'm going to do post-estimation with the oak one.
Now what is the oak one?
The oak one is a 150 bucks open source hardware AI camera, which is really cool.
I highly recommend it.
They run the Intel Mirrored X, so if you look at the speeds there, if you have the oak one,
because it does the AI, like the AI, on the chip itself, on the camera itself, it can
get a lot higher FPS on the Raspberry Pi because it doesn't have to go to the Raspberry Pi
to do anything.
Even when compared to another AI accelerator connected to the Raspberry Pi.
It also has excellent documentation, which is a unicorn these days, but yeah, it really
is a nice library.
So they have a bunch of cool examples that you can try, like there's DeepLop with segmentation,
there's other stuff.
But luckily for me, I didn't have to do any work because they also had post-estimation.
So thanks to GXGX for implementing this.
This is an awesome repository.
It's still being maintained.
If I remember correctly.
So definitely check that out.
That's really cool.
Now, what does this repository do?
It basically gives me post-estimation.
So it films me on that AI camera.
I have one with me, by the way, so after the lightning talks, I can actually give a demo
lightning talk.
I can't do it right now.
Basically it draws a skeleton on top of you in like seven, eight frames a second on the
Raspberry Pi, which is awesome.
And then it even positions them in 3D.
So that's nice.
This is stage one.
We want to go to a push-up detector.
This is stage two.
So we now basically have a skeleton.
If we just throw away the pixels, these are the only points that we actually care about.
And then now it just basically becomes a tabular problem.
So the second part of the machine learning, or like the simple machine learning, is going
to be really simple.
Now we just have a few points and we want to classify them.
Right.
For this second model, though, this is not pre-trained, so I actually have to label.
A few images, it's not a very complex model, but you have to do something.
So what we do, what do we want to do is we want to say, okay, this is a push-up, this
is a push-down, and then we can do some additional logic to actually count them while they're
happening.
Right.
But then the question becomes, how do I take a picture when I'm actually doing my push-ups?
Because like there is a camera there, do I need a button, but then it might overfit on
me pressing the button or like something else.
So if you're a machine learning engineer, the answer is throw more AI at it.
So basically over-engineering using an unnecessary amount of AI, I set up a microphone while
I was pushing up and pushing down.
There's a really cool open source package for Python that can do voice recognition.
It does send it to the proprietary API of Google, but at least the code is there.
And then you can just basically shout label me, and if label, the word label, is actually
found inside of what you said, it will take a picture.
So that's that.
Now we have a third AI model that's really useful.
And then I did a lot with ClearML.
So this is actually the MLOps part.
I now have two models.
I want to be able to train them.
I want to be able to maintain them.
So what did I do?
This is the labeling tool, so left top for you.
Right left top is the Oak one that will take a picture.
When I shout take a picture, it will send it to ClearML, which is actually an open source
MLOps tool, one that I work for.
And they have data versioning, for example.
So every single time I run the labeling tool, it will create a new version of my dataset,
which is very useful.
And then I can use this new version of the dataset.
I can pull it in.
I can use the experiment manager of ClearML to keep track of all my code.
Every single time I run a train, I will get all of my output, all of my plots.
And then you can actually build this into pipelines.
You can run this automatically on remote machines.
So I've already engineered a crap out of it, but I can't really tell everything in
Lightning Talk.
The main idea is you have a lot of different tools in ClearML that can help you with that
and automate a lot of that stuff.
Now training my own model.
So now we have all of those points.
We have for each of those sets of points, we have if it's a push up or a push down,
where do you go from here?
Training my own model, it's this, like it's super simple.
It's just three lines of code these days.
So this is just SK learn, it's an SVM, it's a simple classifier, it takes points in, gives
you one point out, push up, push down.
It's not ideal.
I should do a no class, but I was lazy.
No class basically meaning it's nothing, none of the two.
So now it will say when I walk to it, it will maybe register a push up, but it's not ideal.
So in order to combat that, I made a very simple, even simpler piece of code that basically
primes it.
So here on the plot on the left, you can see one is basically pushed down, two is pushed
up.
And so you can see it happen.
And I think, yeah, you can basically see it happen there in the beginning.
But when I run to my place to start to do the push ups, here you can see that there
is like a bit of jittering going on because it doesn't know the zero class.
So in order to catch that, what you can say is, okay, if the you can basically say if
the length is, yeah, if the length is 10, so if you're at least been doing detection
for some time, then you can check if the last 10 of them were pushed up.
So I'm basically ready in my position, only then prime it.
And then once it's primed, you can start counting.
So that's just a very simple, stupid way of doing it.
Two minutes left.
Excellent.
So I'm going to do one more thing.
Locking the computer.
So I use Linux, which allows you to do everything, which is awesome.
So locking the computer was easy, but unlocking was hard, as it probably should be.
You have to put in a password.
So there was no real way to get a custom password.
I tried thinking of like maybe I should like scramble my password and then fill in that
scrambled password, but never do that.
You will be locked out if your code is buggy and it happened.
So no way to get a custom password.
And there is one big problem.
I know my password.
So if I can't change it and I lock my computer and I really don't want to do pushups, I can
just fill it in and be done with it.
So the best and simple solution I can come up with is just to use Xdo tool and then spam
backspace.
So Xdo tool allows you to type automatically while your computer is locked so you can just
spam backspace, not allow you to fill it in because it's like backspace 20 times a second.
And then when you do the pushups, it just fills in your passwords.
And that's it.
So yeah, a lot of over engineering and I hope you find it interesting and you learned something.
So thank you so much for listening.
One last note before any questions.
There is a YouTube video about it on the channel MLMakin.