All right.
Good morning, everyone.
Welcome to the HPC Dev Room.
Thanks for being here so early in the morning, maybe not entirely sober.
We'll let Nicolas get started with opening the Dev Room with a talk on ParaV.
Thank you, Nicolas.
Thank you.
Hello, everyone.
Thanks to be here early in the morning to begin this HPC day.
Big thanks to everyone who organized this room.
That's really great to be here.
Thanks, Gennet, and all your team.
About me, I'm Nicolas.
I'm a developer and I have the chance to make my job about making first-code contributions.
I'm working at Keterware, Europe, and I work mainly on ParaV, so developing the software
but also interacting with the community.
So ParaV is an end-user application that works for scientific data analysis and visualizations.
We have an open community on the GitLab for the code and discourse for discussions.
It's supported by Keterware, which is behind a VTK for visualization toolkit and to make
you potentially already know about.
So what do we do with ParaV for displaying an analysis data set?
So it's mainly a 3D visualizer, but you've got some charts and spreadsheets and so on.
It's also an internet for data processing.
So we have a concept of filters to take an input and compute some stuff on it and get
your outputs.
So basically you can extract the data from the rest of your raw data.
We also have some other modules like realistic rendering, so you can do your communications
with directly your real data sets on that with just some kind of fake one.
So here is some basic screen shot of the applications.
Who is using ParaV?
We cover its generic applications, so we cover a large range of domains like fluid dynamics
so we can compute streamlines, particle tracking, and so on.
We have a volume rendering that is really nice for medical applications with you have
some 3D scan and you want to understand what happened inside.
So that's just an infinite list where a lot of domains that can be covered, but here is
the more well-known one.
We do use ParaV.
So as I said, that's an application, so basically the first way to learn is to use the GUI.
So you click on buttons, you do some stuff, and you're happy.
But you can also use the Python wrapping to write some scripts, and so you can run the
script on batch processing without having to be behind the computer.
It's also a framework because you can code your own extensions, your own derivated work
from ParaV in the native C++ language, but also some features can be done in Python code.
And it's all based on the visualization toolkit.
I mean, all the hard work of processing the data and doing the rendering come from VTK.
So as I say, that's also supported by Kitware, so I do work sometimes on VTK to have some
bug fix or some small new features.
Here we can run ParaV on which hardware is it possible to use it.
Basically on your small, classical desktop, we have some official binaries you can try
to download and just run.
It should be, it's cross-platform, I didn't say, but you can run it on ISO, on proprietary,
so it's like Mac or Windows, but it should be out of the box for Linux too.
You can also build it, we have a large selection of build options depending on what you want
to do exactly.
You can enable or disable it, so if you want to have pure Python data distribution, parallelizations,
or custom rendering.
A lot of stuff, we have some documentation about it, and we can help you on the discourse
if you are trying to achieve some specific build of it.
And which kind of usage do we have of ParaView?
So either research and industry are using it.
For instance, recently, well, the supercomputing conference in the US, and they organized a
service contest where people are asked to upload some nice videos made about their scientific
analysis, and most of them are using ParaView for just the data processing, but also sometimes
for the video generations and animate their data.
So why all those people are using ParaView?
Because ParaView does some stuff efficiently to process the data on their infrastructures,
so that's what I want to talk in the next part of my talk.
So what ParaView uses behind the hood to make it possible?
So first we have a client-server architecture.
So I already said that you can do it from GUI or from Python, but the GUI and Python
are just two clients, so you can do exactly the same stuff with one or the other.
There's no really limitation about choosing one or the second.
You can run with remote server, and you can run in a distributed environment to your server.
So, in that case, you can connect, you can either just run the server parts with a script
analysis, but you can either connect your local clients to your decent server, and again
using the graphical interface to do the stuff as if it was on your local machine, but instead
it's the supercomputer or the remote architecture.
At the bottom, two other modes that are available.
Typically, if you have some graphic nodes on your server, you can use them for just
the rendering part and stay the data management on the CPU nodes, and still you can connect
your client on it to see what happens and to control from a graphical interface.
And last mode, I will go back on it later.
We have an in situ infrastructure, so basically your simulation can call an API that's fluid
ParaView script analysis, and you can even connect with a graphical client to see time
step per time step what has happened on your simulation.
So, that's for the different mode of use for ParaView.
So first, to run on HPC infrastructure, we implement data distributions for the analysis.
So basically we rely on the MPI standards.
So our readers are MPI-aware, so they can distribute the data over the wrong early in
the process when you read your data on the disk.
Then most of the features are okay to run just with their sub parts of data, but some
other features need to know about the neighborhood to execute correctly.
So for that, we support the concept of ghost cells where each rank know a little bit about
the rank that is next to it.
In that case, mainly we split the data geometrically, so a subset is really a geometric subset of
your data, and different rank can know and communicate with the author for specific tasks.
At least we have some filters, so what I call a filter is really something that the user
can instantiate from the client and ask to process.
So we can ensure load balancing by redistributing the data during the process.
The visualizations can also be distributed over several ranks.
So for that, we use an inner library that's called ICT, that's based on the MPI process
to do that.
And probably you support a different kind of model of rendering, so if you are dedicating
on a node, you can, as I said, create a parallel tutorial just for the rendering part and connect
it to the data server.
You can have multiple GPUs per rank to do your rendering, but that's also possible locally
if you have just one machine that has multiple GPUs, you can ask to do rendering on both
symmetry and agility.
Concerning the performances now, so that distributions is not a bug performance, it's just about
running with too big data, so you cannot just run on your machine, that's a requirement
when you have huge data to be able to distribute it over your computer or your supercomputer.
Now we're talking a little bit about performance, because if you have big data, you also need
to be performant on how you analyze it and how you are proceed with it.
So for that, we have a thin layer for CPU parallelism, we call that a simple tool in
our code base, the goal is to do code parallelizations for many for loop, and main purpose is that
you can choose at build time and then at run time if you enable the OpenMP or TBB backends
and if you don't want external live, you can also use the C++5 to do that.
And so, as is just for instance, to parallelize a for loop or fill operations, it's really
widely used in a lot of our algorithm, and you have some environment variables that can
control the backend on some of the number of thread, the type of the thread pools or
if you allow nested pools or so on, depending on your resources and backend.
So it has some documentation on it, and we made some improvements last year about that.
Still about performances, we also use as an optional dependency the VTKM projects that
stand for somewhat some many core that is intended to be used on heterogeneous systems.
So basically, when you want to have performance on supercomputer or even, you still need to
be aware of the current technology and the state of the art, and as we saw in the past
decades, a lot of new architectures emerging.
We think about using a dedicated library to be able to use these new architectures.
So with VTKM, the goal inside VTKM library, the goal is to split all operations into really
atomic operations, and then at runtime, it can dispatch all that on the hardware you
find on the back ends that are available.
So with VTKM, you can use CUDA, OpenMP, GBB also to do the computation.
This time with VTKM is not just accelerating some specific loop inside an algorithm, it's
more about VTKM is reimplementing some whole algorithm like extracting ISO control also.
And then we embed this into ParaView with some kind of wrapper to communicate with all
VTKM works.
So that's optional, that's enabled by default in the binaries we provide.
Another point about performance, but that's really depending on the use case, on the data
you are using is the in-situ also.
Basically when you traditionally when you have your simulation, it dumps every time
step or every n time step some data on the disk, and then to analyze you have to load
back to data with post-processing tools.
But that's at a cost of writing and reading from your disk.
You should have the size on your disk, the whole side of the disk, so you should have
big disk, and then it has really a cost in terms of time when you should write a full
mesh of full data on disk and then read back with another process.
So basically the goal of in-situ is to make the simulation communicate directly with the
processing tools, and then the processing tools can wrap the memory in place and analyze
directly in the RAM without writing on the disk to save some IO time.
So in the context of ParaView, we have a standalone API that's called Catalysts that was recently
released, although we make big improvements into Catalysts past years.
And the goal of Catalysts is to have a really minimal API and a stable ABI, so you can choose
end-to-end time, the implementation you want.
And one other goal is to minimize the instrumentation you need to do in your simulation code directly,
so it's really easy for simulation developers to understand the few key places where they
have to put a new code to call our API.
So here is a really basic example from one of the tutorials we have.
You need to initialize, of course, and you need to call some method at each time step
where you want the processing to happen.
And finalizations.
Of course, you still have to do a little layer to describe your data.
For that, we do some sort of a party library to help us.
So Catalysts is a standalone, is an independent project, no, independent of ParaView, but
of course the first real implementation is an implementation for ParaView.
So we...
Sorry.
So, yes, we implement Catalysts, so the back end, so you can run ParaView pipeline directly
from your simulation each time step or when you call it.
So how does it work?
How do you...
You can...
The idea is that you are hard-cored the communication between your simulation and Catalysts through
the API, but then the actual script that is executed, the actual pipeline and visualization
you want to produce, it's all scriptable thanks to the Python wrapping of ParaView.
You can even load some representative data in the graphical interface of ParaView, do
some analysis, export this as a Python script and use this script to feed Catalysts and
then when you run your simulation with Catalysts enabled, it will reuse the script you produced
directly from the GUI.
So people that are not at all developers still can do some stuff with Catalysts.
And last point is that when you have a running simulation with the Catalysts pipeline on
your dedicated server, you also can use the GUI to connect to this ParaView server and
to see real time and get some screenshots of the visualization on the analysis that
is proceeding on the server.
So you can have a feedback, a time step per time step on what happened on the simulation.
So if you see that something is diverging or going wrong, you can stop your simulation
directly and you don't waste all the time before seeing that something went wrong and
that you should tweak the parameter and start again.
So yeah, I was quite faster than expected for me.
So in the conclusions of to be able to run efficiently on supercomputer with ParaView,
we implemented a client server mode.
The server is MPI-aware and can be run on distributed environments.
We are relying on old and well-known libraries such as implementation of MPI to do these
distributions, but we are also really looking toward new library that can help us.
We are able to integrate new library to do some performance analysis on new library that
is aware of a new architecture of a supercomputer or new technology.
That's okay, for instance, with VTKM or others.
And we have this API to do institute that can save a lot of time and disk space.
Just a slide to summarize the organize, so we have different kind of way to interact
with ParaView.
I dug with Python scripting, the catalyst in CT stuff.
You can also build some custom one.
We have some web example of clients.
At the bottom, we have a list, a non-finite list of library on which we would like to do
the effective work.
So basically open GLMPI, open MP.
Concerning roadmap, we have several improvements that are coming.
First I talk about in situ, induction implementation, you have each rank that does the simulation
does the co-processing work.
So that's not always what is intended.
You want to do the co-processing on other ranks, just because, for instance, you have
dedicated rank for visualization, so you want to do all the processing on the visualization
nodes.
That's not possible just with the in situ implementation, but we have an in-transit
implementation where the simulation can communicate with those different nodes, and the analysis
can happen on other ranks than the simulation, so the simulation can go forward directly.
We also use some new library, recently used a library called DIY that's here to do some
wrapper.
For us, we take it as a wrapper around the MPI, so DIY allows you to cut the data into
different blocks, and then the at runtime DIY itself is aware to do, okay, I should
put three blocks on each rank, or only one block, and it's just a new abstraction over
cutting your data for distribution.
We are also looking for better VTK on always better VTK integrations to be able to run
on a lot of hardware, and something very cool that is really new, it's just in the development
branch of VTK, so it's not in ParaView yet, that was merged, I think, one or two weeks
ago, it's what we call implicit arrays, and basically it's really good for memory point
of view, because it's some kind of use on memory.
For now, in the ParaView process, your data is really an array in the memory, in your
memory, so with the implicit array, we have some views, so you can implement an open pattern
on it, for instance, when you do an ISO control of your data, you know that the resulting
data will all have the same values, so if you want, if you, after the ISO control, you
will have one million points, you will know that all the points will share the same value,
for now it's one million times duplicate in your memory, so that's not efficient, with
implicit array, you can only one time the value and say, okay, this should be an array
of size one million, and the value you should return is this one, but you can imagine, as
though, have a compressed array in your memory, and have an on the fly, uncompressed algorithm,
just when you want to read your data, so it has a cost in terms of time of computations,
but if you run out of memory with too huge data, that can be really great.
Okay, I still can have a lot of things to say, but that was the end of what I put in
the slide, so thanks for attending, it sounds to be here early in the morning, and if you
have any questions, I think it will be the time, I put just a lot of resources at the
end of the slide, so you can get it from the website of the forum.
Thank you.
Thanks everyone.
Thank you very much, Nikolas.
Do we have any questions?
Thank you.
In our group, we are happy users of ParaView.
One thing that maybe I could add to a wish list, or some, well, maybe just for discussion,
is that we have quite some headache when using ParaView on GitHub actions for multiple platforms,
so like to set up environments for Linux, Mac and Windows with the same version of ParaView
coupling with Python, just to be ready to use it, it's a bit of a headache, especially
when you go to Windows and you need to download things, brew things, opt to get install things,
and then they not necessarily work altogether.
So wish list thing, GitHub actions, ParaView setup thing, unless it doesn't, it exists
already, but I haven't found it.
And the truth is, if there are no questions here.
The use of ParaView and GitHub actions, so in like a continuous integration, limited
environment I guess.
It's a wish list, I think.
Yeah, it's a wish list, yeah.
Well, we don't use GitHub directly, we have the GitLab where you can find a lot of stuff
where our CI and CD will produce nightly releases of ParaView through the GitLab.
I don't know if I answered part of the question.
So what kind of stuff are you doing with ParaView and GitHub actions?
Is it rendering?
Rendering with Python, yeah.
The fact is, I don't really know about GitHub actions because I don't use GitHub anymore,
so I don't see what you can do with that, that you should not able to do otherwise.
Any other questions?
There's a question on the chat.
Yeah, there's a question on the chat.
If I want to put catalyst in my simulation, what is the first step?
Oh, sorry, if you want to use catalyst?
What's the first step?
We have some, I think we have some tutorials, an example in the code base of ParaView, we
have some examples where there are some dummy simulations with just a main, so you can enter
it from it to see how it is organized, and yeah, one first thing is to be able to know
what do you want, which data do you want to send through catalyst, and where you can access
it in your code, and then so at this time you have located the entry points from your
simulation code, and then you will be able to start writing the small wrapper you need
to wrap your data on the need to the actual API of ParaView.
Thanks.
Okay.
Any other burning questions?
Maybe one last, yeah, last question.
Thank you for the talk.
Very naive question.
Awesome.
Is it working?
A very naive question, because I know almost nothing about ParaView.
You had many components there, one of them was the client that does the visualizations.
Would it be possible at some point in the future to be like a web client, where you
just log into the website and it just displays everything, or is it just, do you do the architecture
or is it like super complicated to do it that way?
So the question is, are we able to use a web client for ParaView?
Just for the part that does the visualization, if that could be like a web.
We have some web client for ParaView already, so we have a framework called Trame, that
in turn need to connect to ParaView server, and then you build your own front end for
these applications, so basically we don't have, you should build your own, but it can
be, okay, I have a server, I open always this data, and the front end is just a 3D render
view.
That's already possible quite easily, I think, with the Trame framework.
And Jupyter Notebooks also included, right?
Jupyter Notebooks, I think I saw it on the user interface line.
As we use intensively Python, we also make the step to be supported from a Jupyter Notebook,
and we also have a plugin that allow you to control a ParaView GUI, so you can do some
stuff in the Notebook, and if something goes wrong or you don't understand, you can launch
a magic command run ParaView, that's open the ParaView client with all the current pipeline,
and you can introspect in the GUI, and then you can go back to your Notebook.
Okay, thank you very much, Nicholas.
Thanks.
Thank you.