Okay, so last talk of the Dev Room, Paolo Bonsini is going to be talking about
reverse engineering a solar roof panel. Sorry, roof, whatever he said.
Here, yes. So as a quick introduction to myself and to set the expectations straight,
I'm not a hardware guy, I'm not a security guy, this is basically something I did for fun,
so I'm a beginner in these topics. On the other hand, I'm not a total idiot either. I know assembly
pretty well, I work with compilers, kernel stuff, so I know X-dumps enough to do this stuff. So
anyway, this all starts almost five years ago when I bought a solar roof for my family, and the
installer asked about having this optional data logging component, and I didn't really want to
have anything cloud related because IoT is short for Internet of Things That Shouldn't Be on the
Internet. So I didn't want it to be on the Internet, but it's entirely local, so I said,
sure, why not? And this is what I got from them. This is the normal solar roof setup, the stuff
that they want to touch with 10 football. This is the part that this talk will be about. And it was
already suspicious from the beginning. But I mean, who knows, maybe they bought it on sale, I don't
know. But the plot thickened when I, by chance, had wireshark running and I saw there was a raspberry
pi that I didn't know of. I have other raspberry pi, but none with this IP address. So in part,
actually, a few years later when I was not really preparing for this talk, but I noticed these on
their website. So these are the specifications for this. It has quad core and cortex. It even has a
microSD inside. So you know what kind of raspberry pi is going to be in there. But anyway, let's
take a step back and go back to 2018 and see what this thing does. So it's pretty nice. I mean, you
can only see this from outside, but actually there's extra things around. Here you can see that they
power it through the GPIO. In fact, the power brick, they actually cut out the USB part and they just
screwed the wires to the GPIO here. So what does it do? It basically locks data to the SD card every
five minutes. It lets you plot nice graphs. Unfortunately, I don't have any picture of the
graphs because I don't use the software anymore. But it also has five relays. You can see them
here. Like some of them have normally closed, normally open. Some of them only have normally
open. And it's based on five volt inputs, which is a bit weird because usually you use 12 volts or
24 volts DC for communication. Five volts is a bit weird. And it's not very useful also because you
have to actually put the wires on the wall and it was already hard to find a place for the whole
solar roof things retrofitted into a relatively old house. Another interesting thing is that it has
a built-in UPS because the inverter has like a 10 ampere line that stays up 24-7. If the grid goes
away, it's still battery power. So this is another incentive to actually reuse the Raspberry Pi for
something else. And also on a slightly lower level, what does it do? It has port 22 open.
Unfortunately, there's no way to upload keys. It has a remote update, but it triggered exactly once
when I plugged it in and then not anymore for four years. The web server is not Apache. It's not
Engine X. It's just an embedded web server with a vanilla server header in HTTP. But it has a nice
JSON API. It's easily discoverable with the Firefox developer tools and that's how I used this thing
for some time. So for example, there is the API login. There is API dash which is basically what
is used for the dashboard and it returns the instance data like one minute old at most with
some really cryptic names. Okay, var is not cryptic. Temp is not cryptic, but the other ones
are a bit weird. And it also has the possibility to get CSV data with similar headers for a particular
day or average across the whole year. The daily one is the most useful because if you have a lot
of data for the same header, it's easy to figure out what it might be. So for example, this one,
EMPH, okay, V is probably stands for voltage, W stands for what? But H you may not know of hand,
but if you look at the number, you can see that particularly that it's probably the frequency of
the grid or something like that because it's about 50. So you get lots of data. You get voltage,
current, power values. You get a few computed fields they are easy to recognize because the
name starts with X. So for example, X home is the current consumption of the home independent of
whether there is data coming from this. Sorry, there is power coming from the solar panels or
maybe instead it's coming from the battery. The actual data from the inverter are a bit not
suited for example to plotting useful graphs, but they have a few computed fields that put things
together. There's also a few dozen flags that are interesting. They are almost all zero and so they
will be a bit harder to reverse engineer. And also you can see the five volt inputs and the
relay outputs in the logs. I actually never use these so they are always zero, but they are named
like in one, in two, in three, in four, in five. So it's pretty easy to figure out. So what you can
do with this is already do simple minded hacks with curls. So for example, you can gather all the
yearly data and do your own plots. For example, you can see here is when I do laundry because the
weekend and Tuesday is where I consume more power. And another thing that I did very early on was
push data to QTT to get some nice widgets on my phone that could give me instant data without
opening the web interface. And also for home automation, at some point I was using this to
turn on and off some Zigbee smart plug box plugs. But this was not any reverse engineering at the
Raspberry Pi level. It was just looking at JSON stuff and doing just stuff with curl. But this
was already enough to find some interesting bugs. There are some weird stuff in the logs. So for
example, here you can see this is probably stands for day and hour and this stands for month and
seconds. But it's a value that has a decimal point in it so it makes no sense. And I will show later
what happens. Also there are some fields that end with L and H, but sometimes they are swapped. So
you can see that L is the one that stays always the same and H is the one that keeps going up and
down, up and down. And also with L and H, they didn't really care a lot about them because also
if you plot them, the plot looks like this. So this is the solar production from the total solar
production since the day that I installed it. And this is how much it had produced in January 2021.
This is in December. And it's really weird. What actually happened is that they put the low as
the signed value, but it should have been unsigned. So whenever it goes from 2 to the 15 minus 1 to
the 15, it actually flips back to minus 32,000 whatever. So you can see that this is exactly
655.36 kilowatt hours. And if you fix it, it's still wrong because there are some bugs. But I
mean, this was not supposed really to be used by the buyers of the appliance. People were just
supposed to look at the nice plots. Also this is way more worrisome because there are flags that
seem to be passing correctly. If you look at the logs, it keeps giving these weird names. They
keep going on and off like a few times every day. And the name is very scary. It's battery charge
over the current hard limit and same for this charge. And the weird thing is that you can see
this error in the web interface all the time, but you never see it on the inverter. The inverter
has a little panel with arrows and you cannot see that anytime. So that's weird and I didn't really
like that. I asked customer support, which were otherwise very nice, but they just said, yeah,
don't worry, it's fine. So all the time while I was doing these things for fun, I had the link
and thought that the microSD card would die over me because they say diamonds are forever. I don't
know if it's true, but certainly microSD cards are not forever. So even worse, I couldn't just go
and say, okay, it's 10 years, 10 years, won't you please send me another SD card because the newer
models have, they move the storage to cloud and they only have five years of free service, which
is especially close to the time before my own SD card died. So people want to pay for the cloud
service, you won't have to repair the data logger. Anyway, I never did anything about it until last
year. Last year I got the data logger to shut down on me twice in a week and I naively thought that
it was just a network problem and they said, okay, I will just take out the SD card and set up a
static address. Actually, the SD card was dying. I don't know why it really had all these problems
in general. It didn't have any problem until last November. In last November it really died in a
matter of a week. So I have no idea what happened, but I'm very thankful to the SD card gods for. So
when I open it, this is what it looks like and this is the behind of Raspberry Pi 3. It's potato
quality, but okay, the first impressions was that it's a standard Raspbian install. So I guess I
can forgive them for not obeying the GPL because they didn't do anything weird. I mean, it was just
Raspbian. And there were two statically linked binaries in MPI. One was running on TTY one. Nobody
ever noticed that it was running there because there's no room for an HDMI cable. So it was there
though. The main use of that home PI thing was that if you plug the keyboard through the USB and
you press there, it rebooted. So it probably was a quick way for them to do some testing. But it
had some nice ASCII art of the company logo. The other one is the one that we care more about. The
data is placed in the home PI storage. And the nice thing is that stress is installed. So I was
already thinking of ways to get some data from this because with stress it's so easy. Anyway,
there's basically again stock install. Some files are newer than the others. So that's an easy way
to see what's going on and what they changed. There's a couple system D units. There's an I2C
RTC. This is nice because at the time I hadn't even looked at the PCB or anything. So I didn't
know what was in there. And knowing that there is a real-time clock on the board is nice to know.
They disabled Bluetooth for no particular reason. Well, there is a reason but I will say it later.
So what I do is just I copy the binaries to my computer. I add my SSH and I turn it back on and
it works. So one thing that you need to consider before doing this kind of work is what about the
warranty, especially for something as expensive as the SolarGoof. The thing is the connection to
the inverter is to USB. It's not direct RS485. There is a screw term. This thing is away from
the board. So I didn't touch it. I just removed the screws to take a picture and that was it.
It's basically RS485 to USB adapter. So also the inverter has the about rate. You can customize it.
And the user menu has basically three choices. Date and time. What was the other one? It was
the total that it reports for the produced energy. So you can reset it to zero if you give it to
another person or for whatever reason you want to change it. And the board rate for RS5. So the
user is supposed to know that it is based on RS485 and is supposed to look at RS485 data. I don't
think this is any kind of lawyer analysis, but still I'm pretty sure I didn't break the warranty
on the inverter, which is the really expensive part. So anyway, I got the binaries. The first
thing I do is using strings. And just doing strings by plus is awesome source of information. And
what I noticed by doing quick search, for example, for the API endpoints and for DevTTY USB, is that
all the strings are together. And this means the program is unlikely to be written in C because in
C they will be terminated and they will be all one after another. So could we go? Because I mean,
there's not that many languages that you would use to write a web server in and that produce a large
binary. Certainly wouldn't be rushed because it was four years ago. So it wasn't as fancy as today.
And anyway, if you do a redelf, you can see some section headers that go-sim, tab, go, PCL, and tab
this is basically the go format for the debug information. So it's almost certainly go. Like
what? Certainly go. Another thing that you can do for strings is grab for GitHub because why
wouldn't people use RPIO libraries from GitHub? And also you can find some nice names and things.
And this is the name of the model of my inverter. So I know that what they call it in the source
code or in the files can be handy. So anyway, the thing is there is running this, I can
just I have SSH access. So what I can do is just trace it and see what happens. And one nice thing
is that the T2 opens and closes the HTTP every minute. So it's pretty easy to also get all not
just the board rate, but also the parity, the stop bits. Okay, that's very little, but okay,
I will go fast. So with the go, the thing is it has an event loop that can move a sub-item from
one thread to another. So you need to track the file descriptor numbers. So what you get here is
something that is basically you can realize recognize to be mod-boost. This is a write, sorry,
read the 16-bit registers request. This is read the one bit registers request. So what I did,
I basically took this from the logs and I put it in a small C program to the code what it was. I
could probably do something with Wireshark or whatever, but trace gave me already some C string,
so I put it in a C program. And this is enough, for example, to compare with the CSV files,
this is at least for the 16-bit registers. So for example, I can see now that these are probably low
and high. So this was the minutes and seconds, the hour, the day, the month, and the year. This is 21
in hexadecimal. And I can also see that some values are fixed points. So this one is the
version multiplied by 100, and this one is the temperature multiplied by 10. For the discrete
inputs, it's a lot more complicated. I could find in strings some nice names of the fields. So for
example, GRN was no voltage from the grid and so on. It's a bit weird that they put it on alert that
there was a blackout, but they didn't put as an alert that the fan broke, but whatever. And this
also doesn't make lots of sense to average the bulls, but whatever. So anyway, this is already
nice because I have the names corresponding to all the fields, but I don't have the mappings of the
discrete inputs. That's what Modbus calls the one-bit Boolean values to deflect. So I knew that this
was the part that was broken in the code. So this was probably not going to succeed, but actually it
was successful. I used the radar 2 for this, and I will super, super quickly go through radar 2.
This is what I learned about radar 2 because I had never used it before. So the commands are one
letter per word. So ADF means Analyze Data and Functions. There are some people here that are
old enough to remember Lotus 1-2-3. That's the way the menus worked in Lotus 1-2-3. Basically,
you had one letter per word in the command that you wanted to execute. And the main ones are seek,
print, and slash for search. And another interesting thing to know is that the state of your work is
saved in a project, which is actually a single file in a Git repository with thousands of commands
in it that say all the nice things about your binary. You can get some information from the
debug info that I showed earlier. There's a nice command to do all the analysis that is possible,
but it doesn't really work for a static-anally linked binary. So I use these ones instead. It
starts giving some nice information. So for example, in the project file after I do the
Analyze Strings commands, I can see that it has these CS commands. And now when I do the disassembly,
it actually prints this as a string and not as instructions. Likewise, when I do a XD,
I can see that it loads these. And it also says what is the data that is loaded from here. This
is pulling the constant pull. So for example, this instruction is the one that loads the address of
dev, TTY, USB0. One thing that you can do is also you can write your own commands and add them to the
file. So for example, here, I know that this location is a data operand for this instruction.
And I can tell that, too, for everything that is in here, make it dumped as bytes, not instructions.
So after I add all these things to the project file, it will not be dumped as a rubbish
ARM instruction. It will actually print the word. Then you can also search keys. For example, if I
search for the two flags that went up and down, I can see that they are here. And here they are
closed. So I decided to search for this address. You have to put it backwards because it's a little
Indian. So this is the first byte and this is the last one. But then I found that they were found
relatively close, like 68 bytes apart. So you dump them and it's very helpful that it even tells you
where the hits were from the previous searches. And here you can see some nice things. It seems
to repeat every 68 bytes and it's always pointed to the string followed by the length. And also,
there's these nice numbers which might be maybe the numbers of the discrete inputs, who knows.
And if you go back and back, you can see using the seek command, I can go back 68 bytes at a time.
And sooner or later, I get to a point where the format changes. 68 bytes before, there's nothing
like what was afterwards. So this was the beginning of the array. And now I know exactly which discrete
input was with which name and so on. I can also tell whether to print data. So for example, this
was a floating point number and if I print it, it's 0.1. So the guess is that this would also be
something related to the fixed point values. And now it's time to actually find the pointer to this.
I do, I search for this address here and I find it here. It's also the address followed by the
number of entries. So it's some kind of array descriptor for Go. And then I search for the
address of the descriptor. And then if I go here, I see that there is a reference from the query
function of my model of the inverter. So I guess we have a winner. And in fact, what I did then was
rewrite the software using Modbus. It outputs the logs in exactly the same format. So I still have
a continuous log from the date of the installation, except I didn't leave it exactly the same. I fixed
the bugs. So no averages of dates. The scary flags are not logged anymore. I can see now whether it's
using the battery or not. And I even got the grid non-flag during a blackout. So I guess that's full
confirmation that it works. It also does the same thing that I was doing before with curl. Now I do
it natively. So every minute I export it to MQTT with OMA system. I don't have the plot functionality,
but I can get it from OMA system. So that's fine. This is the source code. And sooner or later,
I will try to put an Ansible playbook so that if the SD card dies once more, I will just have a very
quick way to deploy it. As a bonus for the last minute of the talk, I have a picture of the PCB
because at some point I wanted to update to the Debian 11. The NIC name changed, so it didn't get
the network anymore. I had to really connect the Raspberry Pi to the keyboard and monitor. So here's
the PCB. It's a work of art. It's all two whole components. Don't ask me why. The inputs are a
voltage divider, so learning that the blue resistors are the more precise one finally paid off after
like 40 years of my life. Here's the battery backed RTC. There's a power LED and then alert LED connected
to the GPO. This is nice. This is a driver IC for the relays and also for the LEDs because these are
powered in 5 volts, not 3.3. And there's also, this is nice if somebody wanted to hack further on it.
These are test pins and they are connected to eight more GPOs on the Raspberry Pi, I think. But there's
something really weird here because this part, these two terminals are not exposed. They're
unused and this is a bias resistor. This is a terminator resistor. This is another RS485 transducers
because remember that it was connected through USB and it actually works. I have no idea why it's there,
but if you look at the website, there is probably an older version of the board where you can actually
read here common A and B. So at some point they wanted to use it and then they didn't saw on the
brochure picture. This is not used on the website picture. They still have the older version.
And that's it.