So, the next speaker is Todd Gamblin, and as I think a lot of people here know, I'm
very much involved in the EasyBuild project, which was actually the excuse we used to start
the HPC Dev Room, but we're also very open to other projects which are very similar to
what we work on every day.
So, in some sense, back as our mortal enemy, but we do allow them to give talks in the
Dev Room as well.
Yeah, thanks.
Okay, who's heard of SPAC?
Okay, cool.
People have heard of SPAC.
We don't need to do too many introductions for this talk.
This is less of a talk about SPAC and more of a talk about the CI that we've started
doing since introducing binary packages in SPAC.
I don't think I need to tell people why they need SPAC for HPC.
I think lots of folks have talked about that already today.
Someone said that, so I was supposed to talk a little bit about deployment.
To deploy SPAC, if you want to try it on a new system, just clone it from the Git repo
and run it.
Like, all you need is Python and a few other tools on your system to do that.
So you can just run it straight out of the repo if you want to play around with it and
build stuff right there.
SPAC is designed to install lots of different versions of things, like others have said.
This is sort of a snapshot of the syntax, some of the things that you can add.
You can install HDF5 at lots of different versions.
You can inject flags in the build.
You can pick a compiler.
You can do all that on the fly and it will build you a custom version of that software
and let you use it.
You can get it into your environment a lot of different ways.
What we're trying to do with SPAC is provide the ease of use of mainstream tools that people
are used to, but with the flexibility for HPC, whether we fully accomplish that is a
whole other question because there's a lot of complexity still in this because it is
intended for HPC.
Originally it was designed to build from source because it was trying to automate people's
common workflow.
Actually the Fermi lab and CERN folks added a first implementation of binary packaging
to SPAC and I talked about some of that in a past FOSM.
Since then we've actually started relying on the build caches a lot more.
SPAC has relocatable build caches that you can build in either a build farm or you can
make one right out of your SPAC build.
You may not want to do one yourself that way because then you won't have padding on the
path and like you said, patch off relocation is dangerous.
Generally if we build binaries for wide use we pad the paths pretty extensively so that
we can just poke values in instead of having to do all the patch off stuff.
But anyway you can install SPAC binaries from a build cache in S3 to your home directory.
You can make a common build cache in the file system.
You can use a build cache to accelerate SCI and it's very handy because it eliminates
the need to rebuild lots of stuff all the time.
So if you look at the SPAC project as a whole, I think people know most of this.
There's a community, we maintain the core tool, there's package recipes but the part
that you don't see is all the infrastructure behind the scenes that keeps the thing working.
And originally we did not have CI for SPAC or at least not for the package builds.
We've always had CI for the tool itself and we've done unit tests and checked a bunch
of things about concretization and so on.
But we weren't building all the packages and we're still not building all the packages
but we're building quite a few of them.
With the infrastructure that we have, we have a system where essentially you can build lots
of software stacks on top of SPAC.
You can write a YAML description of what you want in the software stack.
You can have E4S, AWS, Sysstack, Livermore, Mathstack.
There's a Viz SDK within the Exascale Computing Project and really every application is its
own software stack these days.
So our production codes have upwards of 100 dependencies that they are using for multiphysics
and so each of them is essentially maintaining their own little private software distribution
in some sense or another.
And so we'd like to be able to build all of this stuff and ensure that these things keep
working.
That's hard to do given that the GitHub for SPAC is a pretty busy place.
There's almost 7,000 packages in SPAC now.
Over the whole life of the project there's been over 1,100 contributors and you can see
down there this month there's been 122 people active on the GitHub repo and that's like
over 400 commits and 300 to 500 PRs per month that we have to merge.
And so ensuring that everything stays working with that many changes is pretty hard and
you'd be sort of nuts to do it without CI.
One of the problems that we have though is that CI for HPC is hard.
If you want to test in the HPC environments that you actually care about you can't just
take an HPC node and hook it up to random pull requests on GitHub.
They don't like that when the machine might have export controlled software on it because
you're effectively allowing someone, some random person in a pull request to run software
on your HPC machine.
And so this is the model for SPAC.
We have a bunch of external contributors on GitHub constantly contributing to this develop
branch.
We have sort of stable release branches where we freeze the packages to reduce the churn
that some people rely on.
Most users are actually on develop at least according to our surveys which is a little
surprising to me but that's where we are.
And then off of the release branches there is a software distribution within the XSEL
project in the US called E4S and there's a few others that sort of freeze a commit from
SPAC and do their own integration after that.
And that's really supposed to be the deployment mechanism for the 100 or so packages and it's
like 600 with dependencies that are in ECP.
And what happens with this is that that gets deployed to the facilities and the E4S team
goes and ensures that everything works but we're not able to run on these systems on
pull requests in CI and it's very frustrating.
And so essentially this is a bunch of downstream work that we would really like to get rid
of.
Moreover, like the applications are also doing downstream integration.
They may have their own CI which may be good.
They're essentially pulling from all these places.
They may pull a facility deployment.
They may pull from develop.
They may pull from a release.
They're essentially integrating from all these places and so there's a lot of downstream
importing there.
What we would ultimately like to do in SPAC is take all of that work that's going on downstream
and move it upstream so that we're actually doing CI testing on develop along with everything
else.
And so this is progress towards that but we're not doing that yet.
Essentially the main obstacle for us to build stuff that looks like the HPC environments
right now is a licensing issue which is that we can't take the create PE container and
run it in the cloud because that's just not something you can do with HPE's license.
We are pushing them real hard on this and trying to get an exception for us to build
things, in which case we would be able to do work upstream and ideally deploy it the
facilities from the binary cache which I think would be way more stable and less error prone
than what we do right now.
And so we set out to make this CI system to enable this with a bunch of different goals.
One of the goals is that we want to be sustainable.
We don't want to change the maintainer workflow and we already have a few enough maintainers
for the amount of work that there is.
We don't want to change what they have to do.
They're used to going out on GitHub and approving PRs, getting them merged, working with them,
checking if they build and so on.
And we don't want them to have to do something different.
So we don't want them to both have to maintain PRs and think about how the integration branch
is doing like some distros do.
We'd like that to just happen.
And so in that vein we want a rolling release where on develop we're constantly building
binaries for the develop branch and that we basically snapshot and develop for every release
that we do and say okay, it's stable.
Everything built.
We are ready to do the release.
We'll just cut one and then we will backport bug fixes to this back tool on that release
if we need to.
We want it to eventually support all 6900 packages.
It's not something we're doing now.
And we want source builds to still work with these binaries effectively once it's done.
So we want to make sure that the recipes are still versatile enough to do all those combinations
of builds that I showed on the first slide.
And then finally, and this is a big one, we wanted to ensure that the binaries that we
have in SPAC are just as trustworthy as the sources.
So if you feel like you can trust our maintainers and rely on the sources that are in SPAC packages
with checksums that you feel just as comfortable with the binaries that we're putting in the
build cache for you.
And so if you think about how this works, if you look at traditional package managers
like say APT or YUM, you have a recipe per package configuration that's getting thrown
into a build farm for each of those package configurations.
Think like easy configs if EasyBuild had binaries.
Throw that into a build farm and then you get these portable unoptimized binaries for
theoretical binary having EasyBuild where there's one of those per package configuration
or per spec file or whatever.
And then, and this is more like an APT or whatever, you're managing one software stack
that's meant to be upgraded over time and there's a consistent ABI across the distribution
so that you can sort of swap one package in for another.
And the solver in those distributions really operates on the binaries.
In SPAC you have parameterized package recipes that we are designing to be portable and we
want the maintainers to work on them together so that they remain portable so you can use
them in different environments.
Throw those into the build farm and effectively test the parameterized package recipe in lots
of different configurations and spit out different stacks.
Lots of different stacks optimized for different environments from the same portable recipes
for different systems, OSs, compilers and MPIs and so on.
And then we also want at any time for you to be able to choose to build something from
source along with that if you want to customize some aspect of the pipeline.
So to enable that we came up with this architecture.
We have a bunch of AWS resources because AWS has been nice enough to donate some cycles
to the project.
They are interested in using SPAC in their parallel cluster product and so that's the
motivation for them is they want binaries ready to go.
If someone spins up a cluster in the cloud they don't want to spin up a cluster and have
it sit there and build software for hours and then run after having charged a bunch
of money which is nice to them right because they would make a lot of money.
But then no one would use their service.
So they want binaries.
And in there we use S3 and CloudFront to distribute the binaries around the world.
And EC2 is really the main build resource.
RDS is in there but it's not that important.
We've got a Kubernetes cluster in there that we have auto scaling runners in and so we're
building mostly in containers inside of kube and there's a GitLab instance in there too.
So we have a high availability GitLab instance.
We chose GitLab because the HPC centers actually have GitLab CI themselves.
And so the same CI logic that you can run or that we run in the cloud, you could take
that and run it internally and have these pipelines generated for you at your own site
too.
You could slap another back end on this and have it generate buildgrass for some other
system but that's the one that we're using.
We're using runner pools with something called carpenter to basically get just in time instances
and allocate the containers on them efficiently.
And then we have some bare metal runners at the University of Oregon with some fairly
exotic architectures on them.
So if we need to build or if we need to specifically run on something that has an AMD GPU or A64
effects and so on, we can do that.
And we could add more runners to this eventually.
And there's a bot that sort of coordinates all this work.
So it's a lot of stuff.
It's actually, every time I look at this I am amazed at how complicated CI is and how
it's one of those things that seems like it should just work but there is a lot to maintaining
a reliable service for doing this many builds.
And I suspect other distro maintainers have realized that too and I'm just late to the
game.
The way that contributing a stack in SPAC works is we have this directory in the repo
that has all of the cloud pipelines in it.
And so you can see some of them are for AWS, some of them are different variations on E4S.
Each of those directories contains just a SPAC diagonal that defines the stuff that
is to be built.
And so if you look inside of there, it's basically just a list of packages.
So here's the ML CUDA one that has the build of I think PyTorch and TensorFlow, Keras,
Jax and Friends for CUDA.
It's just a list of packages plus there's a target up there, a target setting for all
the packages.
You could have a matrix of targets if you wanted.
And then there's disable Rockum and enable CUDA on everything except for LLVM because
there's that bug that's linked there.
And I'm not entirely sure about the specifics of that.
But this is the configuration part is up here and it's fairly minimal for the stack.
There's currently if you look at these a bunch of other boilerplate stuff for things like
mapping runners.
I'll get to that in a minute.
But this is, there's a PR that's going to go in where this is basically all that's going
to be in your stack.
And you might include some stuff from elsewhere.
But this is essentially a stack definition.
And we take that and this makes it very easy to change low level parameters in the stack.
So we had a working E4S stack with something like six or seven hundred packages building.
We wanted to get better testing for one API because that's what they're going to use on
Aurora.
And so we wanted to use the one API compilers.
We added some compiler config and we said everything should use one API.
And then at the very least we got a pipeline generated with some errors for one API.
And it made it really easy to iterate on this with Intel where we would basically say, okay,
this package is broken.
Here's the bug.
Go fix it.
And then they'd come back with another version of one API and we would iterate with them
until it was done.
I think this is probably more open source than anyone has recently run through a vendor
compiler.
And so just being able to do this I think is big because it might make those compilers
like actually viable things to use for real programs that have lots of dependencies.
At the moment you have to sort of piece your program together and build parts of it with
like, I don't know, PGI was the infamous one that broke on everything.
But I think this could help with the vendor compilers being a viable second option.
And maybe instill some competition among the vendors if they can do this frequently and
show benchmarks against these packages.
So this was I think a win.
Yeah, thank you.
Each of those stacks gets concretized.
And so people know in SPAC you take that abstract description of the things that you want to
install which is basically the requirements.
You run it through our dependency solver.
You get essentially a concrete description of what you're going to build which is the
whole concrete graph.
And then we generate a GitLab CI YAML from that that describes the jobs that need to
be run to build the whole thing.
This is the part that we could swap out for something else.
So like we've looked at like Tekton pipelines.
We've looked at other options.
I don't know, some people use Jenkins.
There's all sorts of things out there that you could potentially map the jobs to.
And I think we could generate a description like that from the representation that we
have.
For mapping those jobs, we have a section in the CI YAML right now or in the SPAC.YAML
that basically tells you how to generate the GitLab piece.
And so you see this mapping section here.
There's a match section.
If you match any of those specs there and the first three are just a couple, just some
names, then we have special tags that we put on the runners that say, you know, get me
a special resource for these things.
And so that first block is basically so that I don't run out of memory building LLVM, TensorFlow
or Torch.
Get me something with a lot of memory and a big CPU to build that one.
It has to run on a big instance.
Because those are sort of the long poles in our tent in CI.
And then down at the bottom, there's just a mapping from everything else gets something
that supports x86, x64, v4.
And it's a little smaller than the other one for builds.
And you could do this for lots of different architecture combinations and so on.
And you can ask for images and things like that.
I said that we needed to ensure that the source is as reliable, that the binaries are as reliable
as the source.
And so we sat down and we asked ourselves, you know, what is it that people trust about
the SPAC project?
And it's really the maintainers.
If you use any open source project, you're trusting the maintainers or you really shouldn't
be using that open source project.
And so I don't see where we can do better than that.
And so what we've done is we've said, you know, the place where bad things could get
into a build from, at least from SPAC is in the build environment.
And so if you give people control of the PR environment where they're submitting things
there, they could push a commit that puts something in a binary that gets cached.
And then, you know, somehow, I don't know, they could do bad things and end up caching
a binary.
And if we took that binary and stuck it out there for anyone to use, you know, there could
be bad things in it.
And so we have this separate set of untrusted S3 buckets where we only build PR things.
Each PR gets its own build cache.
That enables the maintainers to see if things work.
And then they come along and review the code.
And then once things are actually merged to develop, we don't trust any of the binaries
that we built on PRs.
And we go and rebuild everything and sign specifically from the, you know, the sources
that got approved.
Just, you know, so that we know that we didn't cache anything from that environment.
So that's where the develop and the release caches are coming from.
They're entirely separate from the PR environment.
And the signature here is, you know, it's ephemeral.
They have like a signing key locked up somewhere in a secret server.
And we generate, you know, we have subkeys and then we generate ephemeral keys for the
signing in the pipelines.
So whatever it is that you got signed with, it doesn't actually exist anymore by the time
the user consumes the binary.
We could look at SigStore for this.
It wasn't quite ready for arbitrary binary signing when we did this.
But that's an option to reduce some of the custom GPG stuff we had to do here.
So the pull request integration, I think, makes it easy for at least for most of the
contributors.
They get status updates on PRs.
And it's fairly easy for users because they can just add one of these binary mirrors and
then start using the build cache.
And I'm not going to get into the details here.
But in SPAC for a very long time, it was easy to get a lot of cache misses.
Like we would just look up hashes.
And I have another presentation about our reusing concretizer.
The summary is if you add one of these build caches and you have those binaries available,
SPAC will prefer to use them.
And so before it tries to rebuild something.
And so with the reusing concretizer, this is actually quite powerful.
And so, yeah, what could go wrong?
Well, there is a burden to doing this.
And a build cache distribution like SPAC nix or geeks is different from an RPM distribution
because every node has a hash.
And the deployment model is really that you have to deploy with what you built with.
And so you can't just swap in a new version of Zlib in a stack.
If something has a particular hash, that implies all of its dependencies has hashes.
And so you need to deploy the build cache with everything that it was built with.
So if, for example, you modify XZ, right?
And then you're going to need to rebuild all of these things too.
And you're going to need to do that all the way up to the roots of your environment every
once in a while so that there's a consistent build cache for people to deploy.
And that can be bad if your stack is this big.
This is E4S, right?
And someone comes in and submits a PR, which you can do, by the way, that, you know, modifies
package conf.
And then all of a sudden, you know, this is what happens to your CI system, right?
Your whole graph is rebuilding again.
And it can take a long time for develop to catch up with a change like this.
And right now we are rebuilding all that stuff on PRs.
So your pipelines can get long.
You dig in there and you see that, like, Visit is still building.
And you're like, this is the fifth time I've built Visit today.
I think Harmon once commented that he was worried that SPAC would eventually cause the
heat death of the universe because of ParaView builds.
Or no, the ParaView builds would eventually bring on climate change in the U.S.
So we worry about that.
We don't want to do that all the time.
The other thing that can happen is there's a delicate balance between redundant builds
and holding back PRs.
I didn't think about this before we really got into CI.
But it matters what commit you picked to merge with when you're doing a build cache build.
And so if you have a pipeline like this where you've built B and develop is now picked up
on D, and that one's building up there, and you get a PR like this, so PR1 comes in, you
can merge that with B and get a lot of reuse there and get a pretty good testing on PR1.
If instead you get a PR up here that is based beyond your last develop build and you try
to merge that with B or even C, I guess it's already based on C, so you can't really merge
that with C. But if you merge that with D, you're going to be duplicating the work that's
already being done on develop.
And so if you get a bunch of PRs like this at the same time, you can get a whole bunch
of builds at the same time that are effectively already being done on develop.
And so this is a difficulty of navigating these PR-based CI systems.
If you had a server that had served that one patch was built all the time once, then you
could get around this.
So you have to be picky about this hold up PR2 until the next thing is built and then
merge with that commit and send it to GitLab to be merged, or to be built.
And this can annoy contributors because they have to wait for that to happen for their
PR in order to keep the CI system sane.
We actually did bring down GitLab once with a bunch of PRs like this.
Essentially something got broken in develop, develop got held up, people started submitting
a bunch of PRs, they were all doing redundant builds and GitLab fell over.
So that was fun.
CI does keep things stable.
And so we have had, at least anecdotally, that our package maintainers at the lab are
much more happy with how reliable their builds are for packages on the machines since we've
had CI.
But like I said, the committers get frustrated.
And the other thing that happens here if you're doing so many builds on PRs is that if your
CI system has occasional system errors, if you're building a thousand things on a PR
pipeline, it's very likely that you're going to get a system error on there.
And so what ends up happening is that you end up having to babysit PRs a bit.
And that can be painful.
The other thing that happens is it's hard to stay correct.
So testing on PRs doesn't really ensure that you have a working develop branch.
If you have a setup like this with an initial package state, you get a pull request that
updates B. You get another pull request in there that updates C. You test both of those
configurations on your PRs and they work.
And you merge them.
The thing that you now have in develop is actually updated B and updated C. And you
never tested that.
And so keeping that state consistent is rather difficult.
And we're thinking we're going to – we didn't – you know, before we had CI, I think we
just didn't see these kinds of issues.
They would just get manifest on users, which is not great.
But now we run into them in CI because we can see that things are broken on develop.
So we're looking into using merge queues, which actually solved this problem, and a
couple others that we have pretty effectively.
So you can do faster iteration on PRs with merge queues because you're merging in sequence,
testing in parallel.
I'll describe what that looks like in a minute.
It's a good balance of CI versus responsiveness because you can do sort of sparse tests on
the PRs and queue them and then do the heavy tests.
And it actually does preserve the security model because anything queued in a merge queue
is actually approved by maintainers.
And you can take the builds and move them straight into develop.
And so what that looks like is this, where you might have the same initial package state.
You get two pull requests.
You do some small testing on the pull request.
And then you set up this merge queue where effectively you're doing heavy testing on
things that are basically staged exactly as they will be merged if they are successful.
So that gets committed.
That gets committed.
And now you've tested the final configuration on develop.
And you're not in an inconsistent state.
So we're going to stage the work that we do in CI.
On PRs, we're probably going to build just the package or just the package and its dependence,
which is similar to what Nix does.
On most merge queue pipelines, we may build a bit more than that.
And then every once in a while, we'll build everything on develop.
And we'll see how it goes.
We can probe what the balance is here.
So that's where we're at.
Thanks.
Okay.
I think we have time for one or two questions.
Any questions for Tom?
And off to the whole question, we have first MS software bill of materials, Devroom.
You mentioned export controlled software and also being able to trust binaries.
I work with classified customers who have isolated networks.
Probably be shot by MI6 if I told you who they were.
But could SPAC help with providing the offer, they're now asking for what software is running
on these systems?
I mean, what does that question mean, really?
Can you help with producing a report on exactly what software is?
We have a PR right now for so that every SPAC build would produce an S-bomb in some standard
format.
There's a whole Devroom on S-bombs today, which gets into that.
And so I think, yeah, we know everything in the graph and so do Nix and Geeks and the
other systems that do this.
We don't expose it in a standard format that auditing systems can scan right now, but that's
what we'd like to do.
So very briefly, Debian a while ago did something on reproducible builds, which were much more
difficult.
So if you haven't worked with it, that might be interesting for you.
Yeah, so we would like to have fully reproducible builds.
It's a lot of upstream patching, right?
And even Debian isn't fully reproducible right now.
I think that would be something we could consider after we get down to libc even, because at
the moment, because we have to run on things like craze where there's so much dependent
on the module environment, we have to include the external environment to get some of these
builds done.
But yeah, I would like to have a much more isolated build environment.
It's a good practice.
Okay, one more question here and then you need to switch.
Hi, so you were talking about Paddy, your head of files for relative pathing.
Yeah.
I'm wondering if you don't have a static path or a predefined destination as in FHS type
locations.
Are you in serious danger of running out of space in that header?
Well, we're not building in a static path.
We might be building in a home directory, right?
And so you can put padding in your install tree prefix, it's like the next store, and
you can say build with 256 long paths.
And you wouldn't want to have a user actually deploy in a path like that.
You can build that way, create the binary and then redeploy in a short path.
You've got potentially a space where there's, where you can have an arbitrary length path
as your...
A lot of stuff doesn't build with overly long paths.
So like if you get to 512, auto tools starts breaking down and not supporting that length
of a path.
And like the packages actually don't support it.
And so like the sweet spot seems to be like 256.
Seems to be.
Okay, thanks.