Okay, next talk is Pablo.
who was going to explain us how to set up
Slurm client environments more easily.
Good morning everybody, thanks for attending.
My name is Pablo, I'm representing
the Simplified Creation of Slurm Client Environment,
especially for containers.
Just a quick introduction about myself.
I first started working with Slurm professionally at CERN
for about five years.
I was running the HPC clusters at CERN.
That involved mostly Slurm, running Slurm.
That's when I came up with the idea for this tool.
Since about AOR nine months ago,
I started working at EPFL,
it's a university in Switzerland.
And there I also, I'm in a team that manages
the HPC clusters, and I'm also participating
in the SKA project, hence the free account,
where we do also things related to the HPC
and HPC infrastructure.
So just a brief introduction to Slurm
in case anybody is not familiar with it.
Slurm is basically both a resource manager
and a job scheduler, meaning Slurm will manage
your allocations, it will track which machines are used
and allocate to which jobs and which users own,
which CPUs and which nodes, et cetera.
And it's also the job scheduler,
meaning it will, when users submit jobs,
you have your happy users over there,
or hopefully people will be happy users.
And they will be one-on-one on your cluster,
so they make a job submission,
usually writing a script that launches some workloads.
And they will basically interact with Slurm,
and Slurm will manage all of these job submissions.
You won't just have one by one,
you will have hundreds or even thousands of jobs
that are scheduled to run on the infrastructure,
and Slurm will manage the fees and the priorities
and the accounting, et cetera.
So basically it's a batch manager,
but there's both resource managing
and the scheduling of the jobs.
Building a bit deeper into how Slurm works,
because this is relevant for this talk,
there's basically two main components,
two demons that are most relevant,
and those are the controller,
which is called the Slurm CTLD,
and then the demons that run on the worker nodes
at the bottom, which is the Slurm VDL.
And then you have other demons,
like the Slurm VPL, Slurm SD, Slurm VPL.
Those are not relevant for this talk,
but we mostly focus on the part on the left here.
So users and client tools,
they basically interact with the controller
over a Slurm protocol.
There's nowadays Slurm SD,
so you can also interact over the rest with some scripts,
but mostly the older user lab tools,
and mostly almost everything in the Slurm ecosystem
just talks to the Slurm CTLD,
and this controller handles the source of truth for Slurm,
so it knows which resources are allocated where,
it knows which jobs exist,
it knows who the users are, et cetera.
The controller talks to the Slurm demons,
and talking to the nodes in the Slurm units
are a charge of launching the jobs,
so you clean up, setting up the C-groups of the jobs,
whatever you have.
Now, what's important here is to know that
for all of this to work, you need at least two things.
You need the Slurm config files,
and they need to be in sync between the whole cluster,
so you may have some differences,
but mostly it should be the same.
There was no audio online?
Okay, oh.
So, as I was saying,
the Slurm CTLD handles the source of truth,
the Slurm demons are in charge of launching the jobs,
and the two important things are that
you need the Slurm configuration files,
it's mostly the Slurm comp file,
but there's other files as well.
Those need to be in sync in the whole cluster,
and they need to be basically the same,
they should have the same hash, ideally,
and then you should also have a shared secret,
so that nobody can, a rogue client,
cannot just add a worker node to the cluster
and start doing malicious things.
So you have, usually it's a munch secret,
it's called the demon called munch,
and you have a shared secret as well for the whole cluster.
And this fact is important,
it's very relevant for this talk.
Now, up to containers.
So containers are increasingly becoming
a super popular tool to run infrastructure
for reproducibility, for automating deployments,
and just in general, they're becoming super ubiquitous
in our industry, and I think for good reasons.
And they are, I think, very good use cases
for using containers with Slurm.
In this talk, I will focus on the use case
where you use containers for,
on the user and client side of things.
So those tools that will talk to Slurm,
to the controller mostly, to do things on the cluster.
So this could be some automation
that you have run to do whatever, for instance,
you could use it for monitoring purposes,
you could write a tool that does health checks
on the cluster for accounting,
where I've used it extensively for accounting as well,
but also integration with other services, right?
What if you want to connect the Jupyter Notebook with Slurm,
you will end up with some tools
that talk to the controller.
Now, there are basically two scenarios
in which you would use containers,
you can use containers with Slurm.
On the left, we have the local use case,
that means, imagine you have a front-end mode,
you have a machine that's configured where it uses SSH too,
and from there, they can run the Slurm commands
to launch jobs, to track their job usage, et cetera,
it's conventionally called the front-end mode
for the cluster.
So if you just add the Slurm client container on that node,
it's very simple, because you can just, as I said,
you need a secret with Munch,
and you need the config files,
and that scenario is very simple
because you can just do bind mounts,
and you can access the Munch socket to talk to Slurm,
and you bind mount the Slurm config directory,
and you're done, basically.
So that's sort of easy.
However, what if you have, for the use case on the right,
you have the distributed or remote use case,
and in that case, you may run your Slurm client container
in a different service, that's in a different network,
or you may run it on Kubernetes, or somewhere else.
In that case, you obviously can't just do the bind mounts,
because you need to give it all those things.
So you would have to give it all the Slurm config files,
and somehow the Munch shared key,
so that your external service can talk to your cluster,
right, specifically to the Slurm controller.
Now, this is an extraction from a Dockerfile,
this is the Naive approach,
this is how I started trying things, easy, right?
You just take the Slurmconf,
and you just copy it to the destination, right?
And this will absolutely work.
But I was not happy with this approach,
because then you end up managing two copies
of your Slurmconf, and I really like having
a single source of truth for,
when you do configuration management,
and automation of your infrastructure,
I really like having a single source of truth.
And managing this in this way with containers
is very fiddly, because it's very easy
that you will forget to update it,
or something that will fail to update it automatically,
it's, eh, it's just not ideal,
I didn't like this approach, but it will work, it will work.
And some of you who know Slurm may say,
oh, but Pablo, why wouldn't you just use
Slurm's config-less feature?
So Slurmconf-less is a new feature since Slurm 20 or so,
that will basically allow a client
to just pull the config files from Slurm.
So the Slurm-D demons that run on the worker nodes,
when they start, they will just grab the Slurm config files.
So you can just remove the needs,
so you can copy the Slurmconf file, right?
Well, it's a trick question.
Not necessarily, because then you need to run
a Slurm-D demon in your container,
and you also need the Munch demon.
And it sounds easy, but it's really not, trust me.
You will need to do a lot of hacks,
this is an instruction from a container that I was creating,
and you run in lots of awful, awful things.
Like Slurm-Demon, the Slurm-Demon expects
there's a release agent file to exist in the C group,
and the containers, they just don't create it.
If I tried it on Docker, I tried it on different
Kubernetes versions, it just doesn't exist.
I don't know why, I couldn't find out why,
if anybody knows, please tell me.
I googling around a font that could have been related
to some privileged escalation issues.
However, if you just remount the C groups,
the file appears, so I'm not sure what's going on there.
Another fun story is that, for instance,
if you're using Kubernetes, Kubernetes likes to
give a Simlink to your secrets,
and Munch refuses to take the secret from a Simlink
for security reasons, makes sense.
So there's no notworks, you will need to put in hacks,
and it's hacks on top of hacks on top of hacks
just to run these two demons.
And yeah, I was not very happy with this approach either.
So basically I was faced with two options.
When you're in rough with this situation,
you're faced with two options.
Either you basically do the first naive approach,
where you just copy all the stuff into your Slurm container,
you manage a copy of your Slurm config files,
but as I said, if you wanna consist a single source
of truth, this might not be ideal.
You also need, of course, in the case of use case,
unless you need Munch, and you need to supply
the Munch key, or you can try the conflictless approach,
but then you need to add Slurm D to your container,
so it can pull via conflictless to your conflict files,
but then anyway, you also need Munch,
and you need to add the Munch key to your container somehow
and managing secrets.
I mean, if you're running Kubernetes,
it might not be a big issue,
or some other container manager,
but you will still need to maintain all these extra demons
with nasty hacks, and we don't always like
all these having lots of hacks in our infrastructure.
There's a third option, by the way,
which is trying to go secretless.
It doesn't work in combination with conflictless,
where you try to use JSON web tokens,
but it gives a lot of issues, it doesn't really work,
I tried it, so I didn't include it here.
Just mentioning it in case somebody thought about it.
So Pablo, you talked about the bad and the ugly,
what about the good, is there any good part to this?
I'm glad you asked, yes.
What if we had a single shot CLI tool
that just a very simple tool that just was able
to authenticate to the controller,
either using Munch or JSON web tokens,
which Slurm also supports,
and just fetch the config files and then it's done.
That's all you really want to do, right?
Because then your tools, the Slurm tools can work
because they have the Slurm config files,
and just by having the JSON web token in your environment,
you can just talk to the Slurm controller.
And yeah, that's the tool that I wrote.
It's a very simple tool, it just does exactly
what I described there, and it's open source,
you can find it on GitHub, I uploaded it in the past month.
Fun story about this, as I said,
I had the idea for this when I was back at CERN,
I worked on this a year ago already,
but then I somehow lost the source.
I don't know what happened.
Just before I left CERN, the source was just lost.
I don't know why, I must have deleted it by accident,
I don't know what happened.
So after I left CERN, I kept in contact
with my ex-colleagues and they were telling me
that they wanted to do this integration
between the SWAN, which is the, who here knows SWAN, anybody?
Okay, one, two, three.
Yeah, so it's the Jupyter notebook service for CERN,
which also does analytics, and we wanted to connect it
to SLURM, and we run into all these issues
because this is a service that's exposed
to the whole internet, so we didn't want to have
the munch key for the SLURM cluster in the container,
et cetera.
Anyway, so then I left CERN and then, yeah,
my colleagues were telling me, oh, it would have been
so useful to have this, what a pity.
And then a few months ago, I just, yeah,
I just didn't like the fact that I had lost the source
and all these days, I spent a couple days
reverse engineering the SLURM protocol,
and I just didn't like losing it, so I just rewrote it
more properly in Python and just made it public.
So if you're interested in making client containers
like this, feel free to give it a try.
It looks a bit like this.
It's very simple, you can choose between munch
or JWT, JSON Web Tokens Authentication.
If you choose JWT, which is the most simple one,
you just need an environment variable with a token,
and you can tell it where you want to store
the config files, and then you have verbosity as an option.
So it's very simple, it has very little dependencies.
So the tool talks several SLURM protocol versions,
because with every major release,
SLURM changes the protocol versions.
So you can list them with minus L,
and it will show you basically all the versions
that it supports.
And then, yeah, so imagine you have a SLURM Web Token
in this variable, you can just tell it to do
JSON Web Token Authentication with the server.
It supports multiple controllers in case you have
high availability set up in your SLURM clusters,
so you can specify a list of servers that it will retry
until it succeeds, and then you tell it the protocol version
of the SLURM CTLD, because it needs to know
what protocol it should talk.
The protocol version negotiation, I think it doesn't exist
in the SLURM protocol, so you have to tell it
which version you want it to talk.
And that's it, and then it will just download
the SLURM config files and happy days for your containers.
Conclusions, I think I'm ahead of time.
So this tool called straw, it can simplify the cost
of creating and maintaining your SLURM client containers.
It can also increase the security because you don't need
to put the munch key everywhere where you're running
your client containers, JSON Web Tokens, Sophist.
Caveats, caveats, I think this tool should not exist.
Because ideally this would be supported upstream.
So if anybody has any influence on SkedMD SLURM development,
yeah, I think it would be nice if we had this
built in into SLURM.
And then the second caveat is that the JSON Web Tokens,
they need to build, the token needs to be associated
with either, with a SLURM user, basically.
So ideally, you would be able to just generate
a JSON Web Token for a user that's gonna run
on the SLURM cluster, and then if the secret
for some reason is exposed, you've only exposed
the JSON Web Token of a single user.
However, this is a limitation built into the SLURM,
into SLURM, basically.
You cannot pull over the protocol of the SLURM config file
unless the token belongs to the SLURM user or to root.
Still, I think it's an improvement over having
your munch key available everywhere.
And yeah, feel free to try it out.
That was it, I'm happy to answer any questions you might have.
Thank you very much, Pablo.
Time for questions.
So what kind of clients do need the config file?
Could you do everything over REST nowadays?
Like, is it still necessary to use the config file?
Yes, so anything that wants to run S run, S batch,
S queue, S info, for instance, if you have the Jupyter
notebook plugins, they will run just on those commands.
Or if you wanna run a client that uses PySLURM, for instance,
or any library, really, anything that uses libslurm
underneath will automatically read the config files, right?
So of course, you can write your own client,
handwritten from scratch, that just interacts
with the SLURM RESTD to do stuff.
Yes, but you cannot leverage all the existing
user client tools, and the libslurm, PySLURM, et cetera.
So if you wanna create a Python tool, for instance,
that leverages PySLURM, this would be,
I think, a good solution.
I think SLURM does have a REST API,
but it's considered very insecure.
So even the documentation tells you don't use this.
Maybe, I just didn't understand, like, for a long time now,
why you, everyone needs the config file, right?
I mean, why does it need to be in sync?
Like, couldn't they just exchange the information
over the protocols, and just say, like,
this is your SLURM server?
Yeah, that's the config-less feature,
that's the config-less feature, essentially.
Yeah, but the config-less feature just downloads
the config, look next, like, config-less, okay.
Yes.
Download the config, don't need the config beforehand.
It's like serverless, there's always a server somewhere.
Yes, yeah, exactly.
So, that's just how SLURM works.
Yeah.
Yep.
So, I'm still a little confused
about the SLURM client container.
So the container is an application
on the actual SLURM client,
because you have to document, in the SLURM Conf,
you have to sort of say what your clients are,
so that the scheduler can intelligently
decide how to schedule jobs, right?
I'm missing something.
No, you don't really need to declare
all the clients for SLURM.
You just need to declare the worker nodes
that are part of it, but you can have any,
I mean, it depends on how you've configured it.
You can limit it, you can limit in SLURM
which clients are allowed to connect,
but you don't have to.
So you could just, but even if you do,
you will need this, because you will,
even if you authorize a host name to connect as a client,
it will need to have the munch key
and the SLURM Conf files, et cetera.
Does this answer your question, or are you?
Well, no, so when you, in the SLURM.conf,
you sort of detail what your positions are,
and you have to kind of tell it what the capabilities are
of your clients, of your SLURM clients, right?
So that SLURM can decide how to schedule jobs.
I'm missing something cool about it.
Well, I think you're thinking about the compute nodes.
Yeah, I am.
Yeah, the node names, part of the SLURM Conf.
Right, so the containers run on the compute nodes.
No, the containers would be,
let me go back to one of the slides where,
so you're thinking maybe about the compute nodes,
each of which runs a SLURM D daemon,
and those you have to declare.
Yes, I think in 2023, by the way,
you will be able to dynamically spawn compute nodes,
but that's future.
What I'm talking about is all the users and client tools
that connect to the controller to run SQS info,
like when you use SLURM, and you,
so if you had some tooling that you automated
to gather metrics from SLURM, or yeah,
a Jupyter Notebook service, for instance,
that connects to your cluster that wants to launch jobs,
that wants to run as batch SQ, whatever,
that's in that domain.
Yeah, I mean, the newest version of Werewolf runs containers
on my back for the stream.
Sorry.
I think the newest version of Werewolf
is set up to run containers on the SLURM clients, right?
It's sort of, you're actually launching containers
as applications, so that was kind of.
That's on the compute nodes.
On the compute nodes, yes.
Yeah, yeah, that's the compute nodes.
Thank you for your talk.
So I have a question.
You are telling that you can pull the configuration
with your tool, but there are many, fine,
you can't pull with configless, for example,
all the Spunk plugins, or I think,
to apologize, you can pull it, but various,
like I said, Spunk plugins and so on.
So how do you manage this kind of config file
that are not ended by default by SLURM?
Right, that's correct.
So when you use the configless feature,
it will download the Serm Conf, the Cgroup Conf,
a lot of config files, but it will not download
your plugin files.
But I think those are usually not needed
if you're running a client, because those are just,
usually just needed for the Slurm D-demons,
for the worker nodes.
Like the epilogue, the prologue,
you mean all of those plugins, scripts, right?
The authentication plugins.
Those are usually needed by the Slurm D-demon,
but if you're just writing a client,
but say you're automating something with PySlurm
to interact with it, you don't need those files.
And Slurm will happily, you can happily run,
Sinfo is run as batch, or SQ.
You can happily run all of those commands
without those files.
Yeah, okay, so if I just summarize,
the ID is just to create some front-end nodes,
but not to really work nodes.
That's right.
So,
so if you wanna use configless to set up a front-end node,
you might need those files from somewhere else.
But if you're just creating a container
to just interact with Slurm and send Slurm commands,
you don't need them, basically.
Because the plugin files are usually the,
yeah, the epilogue prologue for the Slurm D
or the Slurm CTLD,
and that's not what these Slurm client containers are about.
So short answer, you usually don't need them.
Hello, thank you for the talk.
I'm wondering, in huge institutions like InCERN or EPFL,
would you run your own forked or patched Slurm
so you could fix maybe the authentication privileges?
Yes.
Or is it just not done because it's a...
I've never carried any Slurm patches, to be honest.
I've always, both at Slurm and EPFL,
we just use Slurm out of the box.
It works well enough for our use cases.
It is true that you could, for instance,
do a patch to enable finer,
good on the similarity for the permissions.
For instance, you could enable any user
to pull the config file.
That would be a nice patch.
We don't do it.
Okay, thank you.
Okay.
We have time for one short question.
Hi, thanks.
We actually are very interested in this
because we are applying,
we have a Jupyter hub frontend
that actually talks to Slurm cluster through SSH
because we don't want to install all that stuff
like the Mange and the full Slurm deployment
into the Jupyter hub host.
And I'm wondering, how does it talk, actually,
to Slurm control?
Is Slurm control always listening to any,
any of hosts that will talk to it?
Or is there any restrictions to who is connecting
to the Slurm control daemon?
So there's an alloc nodes setting in the Slurmconf,
I believe, which will allow you to restrict
from which nodes you can allocate resources.
So you can limit it.
However, if you don't have that,
I think Slurm will happily accept anything
because if you have the shared secret,
it's considered good enough.
Okay.
Or a valid JSON web token.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Thank you very much, Pablo.
Thanks.
Okay, thanks everybody very much.