All right, we'll get started.
We have another talk on MPI, but I think a very different one, running MPI applications
on the Toro Uni kernel.
Exactly, yeah.
So hello everyone, I'm Matias.
I'm going to talk about running MPI applications on Toro Uni kernel.
In this speaking, a Uni kernel is a way to deploy user applications in a way that is
closer to the hardware by trying to reuse the operating system interferences.
So in the overall, it should perform better than just deploying a user application by
using a general proposed operating system.
First I would like to introduce myself.
While I am passionate about operating system development and virtualization technologies,
I had worked at Citrix to take Huawei and I'm currently at Bathes.
And here I have my email and my GitHub profile if you want to know more about what I'm doing.
So I'm going to start to present what is exactly a Uni kernel and then I'm going to go to the
details of what just makes Toro special.
And then I will show current implementation of the MPI standard on top of Toro and I will
finish with a benchmark I'm trying to do to see if the current implementation is working
I expected of things that could be improved.
So maybe you are already familiar with this picture.
This is more or less how a user application is deployed either using a virtual machine
or bare metal.
So what we have is the operating system, the user application and the two different modes,
the different modes in the X86 processor.
So in general what we have is that when a user application requires someone to open
a file and a packet or whatever it's going to trigger a syscall and then it's going to
be a switch in which the processor is running from which is user space to kernel space so
it's going to be processing a kernel space and going back, right?
And in general when we see what we have inside the kernel is we have different components,
right?
For example, the scheduler, the file system, different drivers and so on.
So in particular, scheduler is going to choose what is the next process that is going to
be executed.
One of these processes is going to be your MPI application for example.
So if you deploy your MPI application by using a general purpose of the system, your application
is going to compete with other processes in the system for sure.
And also what you have in the scheduler is some policy which is going to decide which
is the next process to be deployed.
Also we have a component like a file system and since we have a general purpose of the
system we're going to have several drivers for different file systems and different drivers
and so on.
So what some people observed was that there was too much generality in using a general
purpose of the system for a single purpose application like can be MPI.
So some people come up with a new architecture.
They propose what they call uni kernel.
You have some projects there like OSV, MiraShoS, UniCrash or NanoVMs.
What they do is just take the user application and compile it within the kernel itself.
So at the end what you have is a single binary that is going to be deployed either by using
a virtual machine or a bare metal.
So instead of for example having syscalls that we have in the case that we have a general
purpose of the system and different modes of execution, in the case of a uni kernel
we have simply calls which are cheaper than using syscalls for example.
In general the project that I presented before all come forward to the epoxy standard so
means that if you have any application writing in C that can forward epoxy you can theoretically
compile with a uni kernel without any modification of the user application.
In reality this does not happen and most of the time the epoxy that the uni kernel implement
is not complete so you have to do something somewhere to just, you cannot just take your
application and compile it and generate something.
It doesn't work out of the box in most of the cases.
So in this context what is total is also a uni kernel.
It's an application oriented uni kernel.
The idea of total is to offer an API which is dedicated to efficiently deploy parallel
application.
In the case of total it is not a proxy complaint.
It means that even if the function like this opens and closes and so on it's more or less
the same name.
The semantic of this function is slightly different.
So I will not say that it's a proxy complaint in that sense.
I will explain that later.
So let's say that the three building blocks of the total uni kernel are the memory per
core, cooperatively scheduler and core to core communication based on vue.io.
Here I'm talking about the architecture of the uni kernel.
I'm not talking about yet the application of how we're going to build an application
to conform to total.
And I'm going to explain three points.
So first what happened in the total uni kernel is that we have memory dedicated per core.
So at the beginning what we does is just allocate, I mean, to split the whole memory in rations
and we assign the expressions per core.
And for the moment the size of the expressions is just proportional with the number of calls
that we have.
That makes that, for example, the memory allocator is quite simple.
It doesn't require any communication because we have chunks of data.
I mean, yeah, the allocator is, we have one allocator per core which means that we don't
require any synchronization in the kernel to allocate for one core.
It's quite, we call it per CPU data, let's say.
So for example, if you have a thread in a core one and we want to locate memory, we're
going always to get it from same ration and that happens also if we run the core two,
we are going to use from ration two.
And the idea is that by doing this we can then leverage technologies like Iber Transport
or Int
and we have mainly one API to create thread which is called a big int thread and it's
the parameter have to say in which core each thread is going to run.
The scheduler scalability which means that it is the thread that's going to call the
scheduler to then choose another thread.
And this is by relying on the API called a systrath switch and most of the time this is
just in bucket because we are going to be idle for a while so we just call the scheduler
or for example we're going to do some I.O.
So the scheduler is also very simple.
We have again per CPU data so we have one queue per core and the scheduler is simple
going to choose the next thread that is ready and then the scheduler and this means that
also we don't require any synchronization at the level of the kernel to a scheduler
thread so it's like each core run independently one from another.
Finally I am going to talk a bit about how we communicate cores and basically what we
have is one dedicated reception queue per core for any other core in the system so we
have one to one communication.
It's basically relies in two primitives which is send and receive front, send to and receive
front and it's just by using the destination core and from where we want to get a packet
for example.
These two primitives are the ingradias to then build more complicated APIs like MPI
gatner, MPI because and MPI scatter.
So these are the building blocks for those API for example.
To implement this core to core communication I was using butyl so I was just following
the specification.
I will talk a little bit about this.
I don't want to go too much into detail just to understand roughly how communication between
core is done.
As I said before we have one reception queue for each core for any other core in the system
so it means that for example if core one want to get packets from core two we have a reception
queue and also if core one want to send a packet to core two it's going to have a transition
queue and the number of queues is going to be for sure different if you have three core
for example because the build queues are dedicated.
So basically how a build queue works is made of three rings buffers.
So the first ring buffer is a buffer which only contains descriptors to chunks of memory.
The second buffer is the aviable ring and the three ring buffer is the user ring.
Basically what happens is the aviable ring is the buffers that the core one are exposed
into core two.
So the core two, if the core two want to send a packet to core one it's going to get a buffer
from aviable ring, put the data and then put it again in the user ring.
This is basically how build.io works.
Just that if you are familiar with from build.io, in this case for example the consumer of aviable
ring is the core two but if for example if you are in a hypervisor and you are implementing
some build.io device the consumer is not going to be the core two but it's going to be the
device model, key.mu for example.
I don't know if you are familiar with that but it's the same scheme.
This allows that for example since we have one producer and one consumer we can access
to the build queue without any synchronization.
At least if we have only one consumer.
So you don't require any luck for example to access to the build queue.
So yeah I already talked too much.
I don't know how much time I have left but I wanted to show some examples about the implementation.
It's more fun than all the slides I should show.
So what happened?
How we deploy an application by using toil away.
We have the MPI application.
It's a C application for the moment and you compile it with a unit that's going just to
link the application with some functions that are the implementation of the MPI.
For example MPI because Gator and so on is implemented in this level in the MPI interface
and this unit is going to use some MPI from the unique kernel.
So at the end what you're going to get is an ELF and binary that could be used to deploy
your application here as a beauty machine or a better model.
So you don't have any operating system in the middle here.
You have only your application, the threads and so on but you don't have nothing else.
So if you want to see how it is deployed, if you get the MPI application that's going
to happen, we're going to get the main and then instantiate it one for every core in
the system as a thread.
So to benchmark the query implementation, I'm not very familiar with the MPI where I
just come in from another domain so I'm not really familiar how I had to benchmark such
implementation and so I choose the also microbenchmark.
Maybe you know them.
I just pick up one of them, like for example MPI barrier and I try to implement which
is quite simple.
The benchmark is quite simple so I decide to re-implement it.
I could not take the benchmark as it is.
I have to do some rework to make it work and then my idea was to see how this behaved when
I was deploying this as a single VM which many cores.
The hardware that I use is this one.
Since I'm not familiar with the high performance computing work, I'm not really sure if this
is hardware that you often use.
It's quite a new Intel.
You can get it in Equinix.
The price is four euros per hour.
I launched the test and I tried to measure things so I was just measuring the latency
of this and I was taking into account the max latency through over 48, 16, and 32 cores.
I'm getting values in the order of the microseconds and then I found this paper which was also
using this benchmark to measure their platform.
I was saying in this paper they were reporting around 20 nanoseconds and 30 nanoseconds.
Sorry, this is nanoseconds.
Not nanoseconds, sorry.
In this platform, in any case, I will be very cautious about this graph because I was getting
a lot of variation in the numbers.
Most of the time, for example, I was trying a machine with 32 cores and the VM has already
32 BCPUs so you should not test in that sort of machine because one of the threads is going
to compete with the others with the main one of the host.
You should always test with less cores, less CPU cores, physical cores.
The idea is to continue doing this.
Improving the way I'm measuring this and also trying different hardware.
At the same time, I found a lot of bugs in the unique corner by doing this.
For example, at the beginning, I only support more or less four cores so I went from four
to 32, well, it was a number in a constant but anyway, I found many bugs when I was doing
this so it is all, this is just a proof of concept and I worked in progress.
You don't take it too serious, I'm trying to say.
I don't want to jump into any conclusion from this.
It was fun to do anyway.
That's all.
I don't know if you have any questions.
I'm going to turn it over to you.
You said this runs on bare metal.
The unicurnal runs on bare metal.
How do you even install it?
Operating systems are kind of complicated.
How do you even install it on bare metal?
How do you install it on bare metal?
How you install it?
If I had this, how would I install it on bare metal?
Is there an installer?
Installer, you mean?
You can just use some device to boot from, for example.
It's bootable?
Yeah, that's it.
Well, yeah.
You have many ways to do that.
You don't have to start it, for example.
You can do it from the device that is removable, for example.
You don't need to start it, I mean, whatever.
Any questions?
No?
Thank you.