Okay, the next talk is a perfect fit after the previous talk.
So Olivier and Axel are going to talk about Troika, a system to easily manage, submit
your jobs to any HPC system.
Yeah, thanks for inviting me and thanks for letting me talk.
So yeah, Troika, as Ken has said, is a system so that we can interact with job submission
systems with one given interface.
So just before I start, a bit of context where I work.
So I work for the European Centre for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts, which is a European-based
international organisation, and we run an operational weather forecasting service four
times a day that we send out to national meteorological services and private customers.
So we also operate quite a variety of services, like we have our own in-house research to
improve the models, to do climate analysis, refocus.
We operate services linked to climate change, for instance, as part of the EU Copernicus
service, and we've just started a new project called Destination Earth.
So I'll talk a bit more about that because it's a nice entry to what I will present.
So it's a EU programme for weather and climate.
It's a large collaboration that we drive with ESA, the European Space Agency and the European
Meteorological Satellite Organisation.
And the goal is to run simulations of the Earth at one kilometre resolution.
So for those who are wondering, that's about 256 million points per vertical level.
So this project is quite big, and it will run on multiple HPC systems across Europe.
So for instance, I think Barcelona with BSC and Lumine Finland, just to name two.
And that means we will require some level of flexibility to run our workflows.
So you noticed I didn't say job because in weather forecasting and also for these projects,
we have lots of different tasks that we run together.
So here you can see an overview of what we run operationally.
But in practice, that's a few thousand tasks that run every time we want to run one of
these pipelines.
And we have multiple types of workflows in-house.
So the main one is the operational one, of course, but then researchers have their own
workflows.
We have support workflows like CICD, deploying software, or just fetching data and using
data and things like that.
And that amounts to about half a million tasks per day on our HPC cluster.
And so sometimes we run parallel jobs, but most of those tasks are just small, like one
CPU or a few CPU tasks just to do some processing.
So for that, we use a workflow manager that we developed called ETflow, which basically
manages a task graph as a tree with additional dependencies.
So you can have dependencies on dates, loops, and things like that.
And that runs a script for every task.
So a task being one leaf in the tree I show here.
It stores variables for preprocessing if needed, keeps track of the task status, fetches log
files on demand.
What it doesn't do to keep it simple is connect to remote systems and talk to specific queuing
systems.
So ETflow just runs commands on the server host, which is usually VM, and provides three
entry points, which are submit, monitor, and kill for every task.
And so if you want to run an actual job on an HPC system, that means you have to have
some kind of interface.
So first you can start by just saying, oh, yeah, the command is SSH to my cluster and
submit a job.
And that's it, which works.
But when you change cluster, or even like there is an option to put, you're in trouble
because you have to change that variable, and it can be a bit painful, especially if
you have thousands of tasks, or you don't want to regenerate the whole workflow.
So next possible thing, you write a shell script.
So you could do multiple actions in your script.
You have a bit more flexibility.
But I don't know if you tried handling configuration in your shell script.
Usually it ends up quite easily into a nightmare.
It's very hard to maintain.
If you deal with several people, everyone has their own.
So we try to have something a bit cleaner.
And so we want to delegate it to a submitter interface that can be made generic, gives
you lots of flexibility.
And you can also maintain it as a proper piece of software.
That means versioning, testing, and some level, at least, of reproducibility.
So, we call our software Torica because it runs mainly those three actions, submit, monitor,
and kill.
It's able to handle remote connection to a remote system, mostly using SSH.
It's also able to prepare the JavaScript for submission, interact with the QE system, and
optionally you can run hooks at diverse points.
So it's written in Python.
We put a strong emphasis in making it configurable so everything can be driven by configuration.
I'll show how this works afterwards.
And we want it to be extensible.
So you can add new connection methods if running locally on your server node or running over
SSH isn't enough.
You could just add a plug-in.
If you want to support another QE system, same.
And if you want to add some hooks, for instance, to create directories before you jump runs
or copy files over before or after submitting a job, et cetera, you can also do it.
So as an example, that's how you would run Troika.
So it has quite a simple command line interface where you can control most of the flags you
will need in your day-to-day life.
So you choose the action you want to do, submit, monitor, or kill.
You give it a machine name which is defined in configuration.
Some options like the user, you tell it where to write the output file because that will
stay on the server.
And it serves as a reference if you want to copy some other files that would be put alongside
this one.
And so here you can see the log below that shows the commands that would be actually
executed when doing that.
So as I said, everything of that is configurable.
So each site has a name to identify it on the command line.
And then you define the connection type, local, SSH, whatever you want to add, a type.
So for now we support direct execution, SLURM, and PBS.
And then you can add some hooks, for instance.
Oh yeah, before I start doing anything, check the connection just to see whether it will
actually work.
Or, oh yeah, before submitting the script, just make sure the directory containing the
output file exists.
Or once the job is submitted, copy the log file to the server so that we can see everything
in the same place rather than having files scattered around every system.
And so that's all good, but just having an alias to sbatch that does it remotely is
not really helpful.
So we need also to modify the JavaScript to add some options that are understandable by
the submission system.
So for that we decided to have a new language, because obviously the directives are not interoperable
across submission systems.
And so we need some kind of translation.
We input some generic directives, and we can add some in the configuration as well.
And then we translate them.
So either for things very simple, like, oh yeah, the output file in PBS is minus O, in
SLURM is minus minus output.
So this kind of translation, you could have also plugins that compute resources, like,
if someone gives you the number of nodes and the number of tasks per node, and you need
the total number of tasks, things like that.
So you could add plugins, or if you have some specific resource management in your HPC,
you can add that as well.
And then on the output side, we have a generator that's site-specific, again, because we need
to adapt the directives to the system.
It can make the last few translations, for instance, the actual syntax of some options
like mail options.
Most submission systems allow you to specify an email address to which send an email for
some of your tasks.
Only the syntax is slightly different for everyone, so it does that translation.
And it's able to add code if you need, for instance, to define environment variables
in your software.
So the main components that are extensible in Troika are, as I said, the interaction
with the queuing system.
So you have a parser that reads the native directives so that you can use them if you
need them for your processing.
It generates the JavaScript.
It runs the appropriate commands, so either using qsub as batch or whatever.
It could use APIs if you have another system.
And it can also keep track of the submission, so most of the time just keeping a job ID
so that if you want to monitor the task, you just say, oh, yeah, the script was this.
And Troika will know, oh, yeah, I put the job ID in that file next to the script.
I don't need you to tell me where it is.
And so you can interact.
You can choose how you want to interact and define new interfaces if you want.
Same for the connection.
So the connection mostly does the running of commands on the remote system.
It's able to copy files over if needed both ways.
Then you can have some hooks at various points.
So at startup, just before submitting, just after killing a job, for instance, if you
want to tell a workflow manager that, oh, this task doesn't exist anymore, I just killed
it.
Or at exit if you want to move your log files around, for instance.
And that allows you to perform extra actions.
And then the last thing you can customize is the translation.
So if you want to generate more directives than the user provided, you can also do it.
And basically, you just pass a function that takes the input set of directives and updates
that set to whatever you need.
So a bit of a success story for us.
So we've just switched to a new HPC with a new set of ECflow server VMs, new location,
new everything.
So it's much simpler to actually be able to just change a config file rather than rewrite
a whole shell script that does all the submissions for us.
And also, since we have lots of different users, they have different needs, they have
different ways of working.
And what we managed to do with Troika is that we managed to bring them all together to use
a single tool which runs the operational workflows where they need to have a tight control over
what they actually submit and all the options.
Research workflows which need to be very flexible because every researcher might have their
own specific needs, but in the end they run mostly the same kind of code.
So we need to have an interface that allows that.
And then we run also general purpose servers.
If someone has a data processing pipeline, for instance, they can just spawn a server
and do their work.
And that needs to have an easy to use interface because we don't want to teach people, oh,
yeah, you also need to know that to run your job.
So now what we do is we provide them with VMs where Troika has pre-installed and many
of them just don't even notice that it's there.
And as a summary, so I said at the beginning that we handle about half a million jobs per
day and most of them now pass through Troika and it hasn't failed yet, so hopefully it
works well enough.
What it will help us with also going forward is supporting our software development.
So it's not necessarily tied to a workflow manager.
We want to control our CICD pipeline also using that because some of the elements of
the pipeline have to run on our HPC system.
So basically what we could do is from a GitHub runner, we could use Troika to connect to
our HPC run jobs there to do testing, deployment and everything.
We as I said run our in-house workflows and we will continue to do that for the foreseeable
future.
It will help us to adapt to new HPC systems because every time we make a tender, any provider
could answer and we don't control which submission system we will end up with and even which
site specific variants there will be in the set of options.
And then for Destination Earth, as I mentioned before, we want to support multiple HPC with
minimal changes to the code.
And so just to tell a bit more where do you want to go from here.
So we want to support more queueing systems because I mean we support two and one of them
quite well because we use it, the other one a bit less maybe.
We want also to add functionality to inquire about the submission system.
So for instance which are the queues available, the partitions, things like that so that the
user doesn't need to go to the server, check before running, like you could just run a
command that fetches all the information in a useful way and gives it to you without abstracting
basically the specifics.
We also want to add some generic resource computation routines so we have some in-house
but they are very tied to the way we function and so there will be some work to make it
more generic and then integrate it in the main source code rather than in a plugin.
And for improvements to the code we want to improve script generation, for now it's a
bit clunky but it works.
We want to widen desk coverage because you never test enough and provide packages to
install it on Debian based machines for instance or RPMs for Red Hat systems etc.
And if you want to contribute feel free to talk to me or go to our GitHub page and I'll
stop here for now and take questions.
Hello, thanks for the presentation.
So basically I've done something quite similar for my employer sadly cannot be open sourced
but the problem that we have is we have legacy clusters with legacy job submission systems.
How did you manage to get the traction to migrate to Torica and to convince the user
to port their job developments to this new system?
So what we did first is that we made it as seamless as possible so if you want to interact
with your job submission system without using our directives you can, they will just pass
through but you lose on the generosity.
And then what helped us is that we changed our HPC system and that means we did basically
start afresh and everyone had to make changes so we just pushed that onto them and I must
say many of them have been happy because that meant we can do that for them rather than
them having to figure out the details of how do they submit jobs on that new system and
everything that we can just tell them oh yeah it's reinstalled it works and so yeah that
has been really helpful.
I actually have a follow-up question to that so one thing we have been doing we switched
recently well four or five years ago from Torque to Slurm and we didn't want to let
all our users retrain themselves and learn the Slurm commands because in our experience
Slurm is a bit less user-friendly than Torque is so what we did is we rolled a wrapper that
people can still use Qsub but they're actually submitting to Slurm and it just it auto-translates
the script in the background.
Troika doesn't do that now right you have to use the Troika command but it knows about
the Slurm header.
Yeah so you could technically do it we didn't want to encourage that but technically you
could like add I think you could write it in three lines a plugin that just takes the
directives you would probably need to support all the directives you need but all the options
like we have a built-in parser that is able to read like Slurm commands for instance and
so you just need to tell Troika oh yeah use those on top of whatever is specified in configuration.
Is that something you would take pull requests on?
Yeah if you want to.
We have another question.
Hi thank you for the presentation very interesting so I'm an early programmer myself and so my
question for you is how does it fail like how you studied or provoked you know intentional
failures of the system and have you encountered funny behaviors like plenty hilarious faults
of the system.
Yeah we had I mean getting a new system has its lot of failures so I don't know if Axel
you want to take over for that because you probably have handled some of the failures.
In example of the command line provided you can see that we wrote on redirect the output
for each submission and this is a chance to analyze the submission and to decide what's
the best approach to deal with erroneous submission meaning that some of them have to be reflected
the hard way to make it clearly visible this is a problem and some others can be handled
in an either way or not so visible way in still deterministic way and so it may be hidden
and still automatically under the problems when they occur and this is what we expect
with so many job to submit to focus on the critical essential for the human side and
to teach the to have a chance to teach the machines who the hook system to manage with
those specificities we have identified as problematic but we want to keep ignore the
or manage automatically until a fix is coming from the system for example if it is related
to the system problem or identified issue that may come with the next release so this
is the way to deal with the failures that can occur at job submission.
Thank you.
Did I understand correctly that when you're monitoring a job the reference is the script?
Yes.
So that correct so that means everyone has to make sure their scripts are uniquely named
each time otherwise or is it the script and where it is in the file system?
It's where it is in the file system so you are correct if someone deletes or renames their
script then it can cause a problem or submits with the same script so it's not a problem
for us because our work for manager basically does some preprocessing meaning that the script
has some additional things like oh, yes, it's your second try at that submission so I will
add the job to at the end and so that's how we circumvent this issue but you are definitely
correct and that's something we will need to improve at some point but we didn't want
to have to link to a database or something so that we can keep it simple.
Thanks.
You could just copy the script on submission.
We could copy it.
That's what Slope does, half a million scripts.
We need to think about clean up.
Other questions?
Hello.
Users like things to be as simple as possible.
In order to do that, they would probably be nice to have some sort of central location
where recipes of various clusters would be sort of combined accessible for people to
be able to get access to.
Is that in your plan?
What do you mean on the configuration side?
So I could imagine a user turning up going I'm going to download Troika and I'm going
to talk to this cluster that I have access to.
How do I get the configuration?
Oh, okay.
I see.
So we don't have that but if Troika gets the traction, I think we could come up with
a website where you can host your configuration files or have some kind of index where you
can list them.
I think, I mean, we would have all that's needed to do that pretty easily.
I think hopefully the configuration is easy enough so that you don't need to do much on
top of what's actually provided as examples.
But, yeah, you are correct.
We could, if it gets popular, just provide configuration files for several systems or,
I mean, HPC system providers could also just give a configuration file with the system
so we can have it where Troika is installed and then the user doesn't even need to bother
about it.
Very small second one.
Given you've just done all this stuff, have you heard of a project called DRMAA, the Distributed
Resource Manager Application API?
It might make the insights of this slightly nicer for your EC flow stuff.
Maybe it might take some inspiration for that.
Thank you.
A question but also an observation.
A long time ago there was a standard code DRMAA.
Just mentioned.
It seems not to be used.
Maybe I'm wrong.
Very quickly, your system, if you had cloud-based resources on AWS, you've got an SSH connector.
Could you in the future maybe run up some machines on AWS?
Yeah, that could be an option.
As long as you can write Python code to spawn up an image, a container somewhere.
Yeah, sure.
I think there are APIs for that.
There just needs to be a plugin that does the connection and that's it.
Cool.
We're out of time.
Just a comment.
I don't think you have any people using Troika outside of ECMEF.
No, that's the first time we actually present it outside.
All right.
Good.
So you're trying to get people to start using it?
Yes.
You're building a community, you're getting yourself into trouble.
You're going to get public requests and bug reports.
Okay.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Nice.
Please come forward, please