Yeah, so let's start with this talk.
My name is Marek Wachud and this talk is about U-Boot as a BSCI provider.
Now BSCI stands for a Power State Coordination Interface.
It's a standard drafted by ARM and it is used on ARM system.
It defines a software interface that's used by things like bootloader as operating system.
To bring up CPU cores, stop the CPU cores, do a system suspend, resume, perform, reboot and power off.
The presence of the BSCI interface is mandatory on ARMv8.
It is optional on ARMv7 although you can find ARMv7 systems which do also provide BSCI.
There is a related interface which is called an SCMI and this is used for clock management,
power domain management of devices.
You may sometimes see that there are systems which misuse BSCI for this kind of functionality
like power domain on and off and this is wrong.
So that all goes into SCMI.
We will not talk about SCMI however right now.
The reason why BSCI exists is multiple fault.
One of them is convenience.
The thing is doing these things like CPU core on, off, suspend, resume, this is a really
horribly complex process and hardware is full of bugs so implementing it correctly so that
your system doesn't randomly crash during suspend for example, the code is very complex.
If you want to run multiple OSs on an ARM machine, there is a balancing act in place.
Basically what ARM decided was to implement this once, implement it properly and then
expose to the operating system an interface which allows it to say okay, well, now suspend
or now bring up a CPU core.
And all this horrible complexity and all the work arounds for the hardware bugs, they are
hidden in this sort of an interface which is implemented once.
So it pretty much covers the convenience, the complexity.
The other thing is the thing which brings up CPU cores may interact with say regulators
and this could potentially damage the hardware if you do it wrong.
So if the hardware is very fragile, it may also be a good idea to hide this from the
operating system which may crash and do something wrong and then potentially damage the hardware.
That's why it's hidden in the firmware.
However, what you may argue is that if we put this functionality in the firmware, what
happens if the firmware is buggy?
Then you have to update the firmware which essentially means updating your bootloader
which is dangerous operation unless you are very well prepared for that.
So it can break your machine if you do it wrong.
So all of this is really a balancing act.
Why not put it into the OS or into the bootloader?
One completely separate reason for existence of this API is virtualization.
So in a virtualized setup on ARM, the secure monitor firmware which is running in the highest
privilege level provides a PSCI interface to the OS running in lower privilege mode
which is like the EL2.
And that OS itself can provide the same looking PSCI interface to the OS running in virtualization
so in EL1.
And to the OS this looks very much identical whether it's running in virtualization or
whether it's running on bare metal.
So for that purpose also there is the PSCI interface which allows you to bring up CPU
cores which in one case may be virtual and in the other case they are the actual real
CPU cores hardware ones.
Now the way PSCI is implemented is by means of SMCCC which stands for SMCCole convention
which is another standard drafted by ARM and it basically tells you that on ARM64 there
are two instructions, one of them SMCC the other HVC instruction and they both trigger
a synchronous exception.
In case of the SMCC instruction the synchronous exception lands in exception level 3 in case
of the HVC the synchronous exception lands in EL2 and the SMCCC also tells you which
CPU registers to set up before you call the SMCC and which CPU registers are then used
as a return value from the SMCC or HVC instruction.
As for the exception levels there is four of them on ARM64 EL3 to EL0, the EL3 is the
most privileged one.
This is where the secure monitor firmware runs and this is also where the code which
brings up the CPU cores and does the suspender zoom and all this is running.
EL2 is the less privileged and this is where operating system is running, the one which
is running on bare metal.
You can use SMCC from the EL2 into the EL3 to request services from the secure monitor.
EL1 is used for virtualized OS so an OS which is running in virtualization can do HVC which
would trigger a synchronous exception in EL2 in the OS which is running on the bare metal
and the OS running on the bare metal may provide some services to the virtualized OS this way.
You can read all about these exception levels in the ARM specification.
If you download the slides which are in Penta you can use all these links which will redirect
you to all the specifications so we can just read all about that.
Suffice to say there are these four exception levels on ARM for now.
The way the SMCC actually works is that if you want to do an SMCC request you're supposed
to set up CPU register zero with a function ID which basically says what kind of request
you want performed by the secure monitor or by the OS.
And then you're supposed to set up six additional parameters, X1 all the way to X6 which are
parameters for this function which you want to trigger.
With this set up you have to do the SMCC or HVC instruction.
This instruction triggers synchronous exception.
This synchronous exception then makes the CPU elevate its exception level to the higher
one and trigger the exception handler which validates that the function ID is even okay
for you to call, that the parameters for the function are okay at all.
If all of this is correct then the request which is represented by this function ID is
then performed by the secure monitor firmware or by the OS.
Once the request is performed the secure monitor firmware or the OS will set up four additional
registers X0 to X3 with the return values and will return just past the SMCC or HVC
instruction into the calling software and resume execution at the exception level of
the calling software.
And then the calling software can collect the result of this call in the register of
X0 to X3 and do something about this.
This is roughly how it works.
About these function IDs.
These function IDs are the requests you can do to the secure monitor firmware or to the
OS running in the bare metal.
You can actually not find them in the SMCC specification because the SMCC specification
just says there are function IDs but the blocks of these function IDs are distributed across
various specifications like the BSCI specification which has two blocks carved out of the function
IDs or the SCMI specification which has its own set of function IDs.
The BSCI specification has two sets of function IDs, one is for 32-bit BSCI calls, the other
is for 64-bit BSCI calls.
The only reason for this is that 64-bit BSCI calls just take 64-bit parameters so the function
signature is slightly different.
But beyond that it's very much compatible with 32-bit and 64-bit BSCI functions and
function implementations.
So you can look up the function IDs obviously in the BSCI specification.
You can also look them up in the U-Boot sources, you can look them up in the Linux kernel sources.
This stuff here is coming from the U-Boot sources.
Hello.
So what you can see here is for example CPU on BSCI function which is actually a macro
which is expanded to like E4 or C4 I'm sorry C4 plus 3.
So this would actually go into the SMC register X0 before you call the SMC instruction.
Now there are multiple callers of the SMC instruction as well as multiple handlers.
There are callers in U-Boot.
This is all built around this as we call it the SMC call and HVC call implementation.
In Linux the BSCI implementation lives in driver's firmware BSCI, BSCI.C.
The handlers are either in ATF or in U-Boot itself.
The U-Boot SMC callers are all built around this SMC call function.
So like anything in U-Boot which does BSCI interaction is essentially SMC call, BSCI
function name and then some parameters for the BSCI function.
If you look at the SMC call in U-Boot actually it very much copies what's in the SMC C-C.
So that means set up register X0 with function ID, set up a couple of parameter registers
X1 to X6 then trigger the SMC instruction, once the SMC instruction request is done the
execution will return past the SMC instruction and continue here where the U-Boot code will
collect the registers which were set up by the secure monitor firmware as the written
values from the SMC instruction and then you can use them in the U-Boot code.
There is a matching HVC call a little bit further in this FVC call.C in U-Boot if you
want to look it up which is used for the EL2 HVC call.
U-Boot has the bonus thing that it actually has a command which is called an SMC.
So in the U-Boot command line you can experiment with the SMC calls and it's a command which
takes seven parameters up to seven parameters.
The first parameter is the SMC function ID and then the six additional parameters are
the parameters for the SMC function.
So if you want to do like a PSCI call I think this one is like PSCI version here you can
do it like from the U-Boot command line and you can experiment with this all you want.
The return value from the SMC command is four values which is the X0, X1, X2 and X3 CPU registers.
So you can then analyze what you got out of the SMC call if it didn't fail obviously.
As for the Linux kernel there is this additional thing in Linux than when the PSCI firmware
driver is probing Linux has to figure out whether it is running on bare metal or in
virtualization.
So if Linux is running on bare metal then it uses the SMC instruction to communicate
with the secure monitor firmware otherwise it's using the HVC instruction if it's running
in virtualization to communicate with the OS that's running on the bare metal.
But beyond that the PSCI firmware driver in Linux just exposes the PSCI functions as a
wrapper around SMC calls and the actual SMC instruction call and the setup of the X0 all
the way to X6 registers.
This is implemented in SMCC call.s in R64.
So it's very much yet again a wrapper around the SMC instruction no matter whether it's
U-Boot, whether it's Linux.
But now let's talk about the more interesting part which are the handlers.
And for one to be an SMC handler the CPU core has to fulfill a couple of requirements.
The main requirement to handle SMC exceptions is to be able to even receive the exceptions.
So the CPU core basically has to be able to receive exception in EL3 if it wants to handle
SMC.
If you are on an SMP system you also have to be able to receive IPIs, interprocessor
interrupts because in order to bring up secondary cores it is necessary for the secondary cores
to be able to receive IPIs to break them out of a loop in the PSCI provider firmware because
the OS is not immediately ready for the secondary cores.
I'll explain that in a bit.
In U-Boot most of this PSCI and synchronous exception handling code is actually in place
already and it's all generic code.
So the U-Boot entry point is very much here in the stub.s and the PSCI synchronous exception
handling code is here in PSCI.s.
It's there both for ARM32 and ARM64, it's just in different subdirectories.
All you as a user actually have to implement is the PSCI.c which are the C callbacks of
the actual PSCI functions functionality which perform the stuff which the PSCI function
are supposed to do with the hardware like start the CPU core, stop the CPU core.
So all this stuff is generic, all this stuff is SOAK specific and if you decide to implement
PSCI provider in U-Boot you have to fill that in.
Now if a U-Boot is configured as a PSCI provider then U-Boot is running in EL3, that means
in the highest execution level, exception level.
That means U-Boot is not able to perform any SMC calls so you have to make sure there are
none because otherwise the system would just hang on boot.
The OS will be running in EL2 and it will be able to do SMC calls into the U-Boot synchronous
exception handler.
So this is something to keep in mind.
Beyond that if U-Boot is configured to be a PSCI provider there is only really a little
bit of additional setup when the U-Boot starts up in this MV8 setup PSCI and this code does
basically that it takes parts of U-Boot which are marked with attribute secure which is
essentially the PSCI handling code.
It copies it into an SRAM, then it set up some M-U tables and flags this SRAM with a
secure bit.
That means no code running in not EL3, that means anything lower than EL3 will be able
to modify this secure handling code.
And finally the U-Boot sets up an exception vector so that when the synchronous exception
happens it will land in the U-Boot synchronous exception handler and then enter the PSCI code.
So when such a synchronous exception happens the U-Boot synchronous exception handler is
entered.
So when like an OS does SMC call it will land here in the MV8-PSCI.S handle thing and at
that point the synchronous exception can be anything.
So first we have to figure out whether this is even an SMC at all or it could be a hardware
fault, it could be an unknown SMC exception which we cannot even handle.
If it is an SMC exception we need to figure out whether it's a 32-bit one or 64-bit one.
Assuming it's an SMC64 on MV8 we still need to figure out whether this is even a PSCI
exception or it could be another type of an SMC.
If it is a PSCI then U-Boot looks up the callback function which implements the PSCI function
ID if it even exists in U-Boot and if it does then it sets up a C runtime environment and
jumps onto the C function which then looks very much like this and in this C function
you can just do like a write into a register and for example in this case power of the
system and like you don't have to care about the assembler before that all you have to
care about whether the PSCI provider is very much this because this is so specific and
this is something you have to implement.
Now on S&P there is this additional problem in that when the operating system running
in EL2 requests from the PSCI provider that it wants to bring up secondary core the operating
system will pass through the PSCI pointer for the OS entry point but you cannot just
turn on the secondary core which will start up in EL3 and point it into the OS entry point
because this would be a security violation.
You would essentially start the CPU core which is running at the highest privilege level
and make it enter the operating system in some sort of a highest privilege level state
even though the OS is running in lower privilege state.
So what happens there is the CPU core actually has to enter U-Boot.
In the U-Boot init code the CPU core gets configured, gets set in a defined state so
that it can enter the OS.
The CPU core GIC the interrupt controller registers are configured so that it can receive
an IPI then the CPU core drops into EL2 and then the CPU core starts spinning and waiting
for an IPI so that when the operating system is actually ready to receive the CPU core
it can ping it with an IPI and the CPU core will then be released to the operating system
and it jumps to the operating system entry point and then the operating system runs on
two cores.
So this is the detail with an SMP.
Finally here is a summary of what to do in case you want to use U-Boot as a PSCI provider.
So you have to look up the GIC distributor and redistributor base.
This is something which you find out in your SOC data sheet or if there is a Linux device
today it's already there and define these two macros GIC debase and GIGR base.
Then you have to make sure that your Drem is marked as non-secure because sometimes
it is marked as secure and if it is marked as secure in the MMU tables then your OS will
not be able to access Drem and it will crash.
You potentially have to configure other security related registers of the CPU.
This is again SOC specific.
You have to look it up in your SOC data sheet.
Then finally the main part of the implementation is fill in your PSCI.C callback implementation
again SOC specific and then remove the previews PL31 PSCI implementation block which potentially
was ATF.
Enable these U-Boot config options give or take in the U-Boot port config and compile
and then it should basically work.
And in case it doesn't work U-Boot has the debug UART functionality.
So if you have two UARTs on your machine you can point the debug UART into the other UART
not the console UART and use this dedicated lightweight printing mechanism to essentially
print some sort of debug output from the U-Boot PSCI provider the secure part even while the
Linux kernel is running it is possible to get some debug UART prints out of this.
Here are the config options which you used for that.
And now since I'm through my slides I promised an example.
So this will be very boring.
Here is U-Boot and if you are familiar with U-Boot this is how it looks and it just looks
all the same except if you are familiar with U-Boot on iamix 8M plus or iamix 8M in general
you may notice that there is no notice here.
The notice comes from the ATF PL31 blob and the blob is not there because the U-Boot is
the provider of that functionality now.
But beyond that I can boot the Linux kernel the same.
The Linux kernel detects that there is a PSCI interface in the firmware which is now provided
by the U-Boot.
The Linux kernel brings up the CPU cores.
The CPU cores show up in pro CPU info and the CPU cores just work.
And that's actually all there is to show.
It's exactly the same as it was with the blob except now you have one less entry in the
S-Boot.
So you no longer need the ATF PL31 blob which is bundled with U-Boot because U-Boot can
do it now for you.
And by the way this stuff is now upstream since two days ago.
In case you enable a debug UART you will see some sort of a debug print out of the secure
part of U-Boot.
For example here is a PSCI CPU164.
This is the Linux kernel sending the PSCI request to U-Boot and you would just bring
up the CPU core down for the Linux kernel.
And that's it.
Thank you for your attention.
Questions?
Yeah.
So, if you have an existing ATF implementing PSCI and you want to move to U-Boot you have
to convert everything at once.
There's no way to like step by step move functionality over.
So you see the functionality is actually super simple.
I mean all you have to do is like turn on CPU core, turn off CPU core and suspend and
power off and reset.
And this is like 200 lines of code.
So it's like super simple really.
And it's actually all now upstream for iMix ADAM plus.
So we can actually just use that as an inspiration.