Okay, let's start off then.
Okay.
So,
Now it's working.
Okay.
So, we're going to talk first about what is WAM.
WAM stands for Web Application Manager.
It's the LG WebOS web runtime.
It's built on top of Chromium nowadays.
WebOS, it's the operating system for embedded products.
It's web-centric.
So, the idea is that web applications are first-class citizens to the same level of native applications or even more prominent in WebOS.
The components is built on top of Jockto.
It uses Wayland for graphics with QML for the Wayland compositing and Malit for vtokibos.
It has a unified media server.
And for IPC, between applications, it has a JSON protocol that is named Luna.
So, yeah, WAM is the centerpiece of the web experience in WebOS.
So, places where it was used, HP touch path a long time ago, some platforms, when WebOS was part of the palm offering.
Nowadays, it's the key part of the WebOS, the LG Smart TVs.
From 2013, that's the main WebOS to use for those TVs.
So, we have hundreds of millions of users using this.
Other products we have implemented in the WebOS and RoS integration.
So, we have some robot experiments, digital signage, some appliances like this fridge, and web hours like this clock.
It is used from 2018 in the WebOS open source edition.
So, basically, it's a party distribution with open source basing all these components.
It is used nowadays also on the ADL, on the automated Linux.
It's the web runtime for ADL.
So, there was support of the LG WebOS web runtime to the ADL that is not WebOS.
How it works.
So, this is the architecture.
The reddish areas have what is implemented by Chrome.
Orange part is the, nowadays it's also part of Chrome, but it's the integration with Wayland.
There's the blue parts that are provided by WebOS that are the Wayland Compostor and the IPC.
And one is the green part.
So, it's built on top of Chromium that handles the running web applications in the system in an efficient way.
So, the thing, why we want to put one in, is basically the ADL is having high support for the web platform nowadays.
Web platform moves fast, so if you want to get up to date to the latest standards, you need something that provides the web standards
and moves as the Chrome baseline moves, get the latest web standards.
It controls the application like
ICON, so basically when you run a web application, one takes care of running it, of closing it, of reducing the saving memory resources,
CPU resources, GPU resources, so they are properly distributed on the system, saving CPU and battery when applications are not visible to the user.
So, yeah, that's one of the great advantages is this single-world runtime gives some performance improvements because we are sharing as much possible resources for running web content.
Thus, the last one, launch time optimization, it's also quite critical because running a web stack is quite heavy thing nowadays.
So, being able to have things pre-launched, pre-worked, is quite important for having a seamless web experience where application launching is very fast and applications switching is also fast.
Our security, well, it has all the web standards about how to run remote content and also local content through security origins. Security origins basically is the sum of a scheme, the port, and the host part of the URL.
We have some permissions declaring an application manifest so we can determine which parts of the system web application can use.
And about developer tools, we have basically the same we will have on a Chrome browser, so we have the web inspector on developer tools, and we have the chromium tracer for having performance analysis in the system.
I think that one of the important things is that it's been running for a long time in millions of LG TVs on all the devices, so 10 years of experience, it's proven, it's running, it's stable, and it's used for a long time.
And now it's also adopted in the AGL reference platform too.
So we have here some links for open source, the open source flavor of WebOS, and all the components are the same we have in smart TVs, we have one WebOS service.
So basically you use WebOS service, you can try all these components in your own devices.
Okay, so let's move to the retrospective part.
As I said, it's been 10 years.
The main caveat here is that I joined the WebOS project in October 2012.
The history of one WebOS start before 2008, but I will mostly focus on what I lived and not what happened before.
Anyway, it's just lesson learned.
I hope some of them may be useful or insightful for you.
Okay, so a bit of history.
WebOS was developed by Palm that was acquired by HP in 2010, and then on 2011, HP decides that they don't want to develop any other WebOS product anymore.
So the last device is a tablet that is HP.com.
But in 2012, there's a start of a partnership between HP and LG for pouring WebOS for the LG Smart TV boards.
The idea was that WebOS could be the basis for the future Smart TV offered by LG.
They had something that was named Netcast before, and it was hard to maintain, and it was hard to keep moving with what was required for the future Smart TV OS,
whether you have model one Web application running at the same time, that switch, that WebOS were already providing at that time.
So in 2013, basically what happened was that LG acquired the business unit that was Palm before.
So basically the business unit that owns WebOS.
That business unit was renamed to the LG Silicon Valley Labs at that time.
I'm from 2014. LG WebOS-based TV is introduced in computer entertainment show in Las Vegas, and then the TV were released a few months later.
I think it's April 2014, the first LG Smart TV based on WebOS.
Okay, more about open source.
As I said, HP Palm decided to scrap all the WebOS new products, so they stopped doing new products, and they published most of the source calls open WebOS.
With the idea, I think, well, the feeling at the right time, at that time, that nowadays is the same, and they opened it to attract interesting WebOS, to attract investors.
Basically, they were already considering selling the business unit. But when LG acquired the Palm business unit, they stopped maintaining open WebOS.
So they came back to the no open source developing model. That was kind of a strong problem, but it was very, very hard.
They worked to put WebOS for mass TVs and released into products.
That is something that sometimes it's not very clear, but when you have something like an open source product, some upstreaming, some public products,
but then you want to get to release quality for a product for millions of users, it's not easy.
That's how to work, to stabilize, to mature things, to even pass controls by authorities about quality. It's not very easy.
So we all decided to focus on first having the smart TVs run WebOS, and then open sourcing again would be an afterthought after that.
Usually, that doesn't happen in the end. This kind of afterthought never happened, but in this case, it happens.
So in 2018, like six years after open WebOS was stopped, basically, this is WebOS open source edition.
The focus was in this case allowing people to take this, to prototype ideas, do experiments, make things around WebOS,
because basically you would have UI, just to experience a way to integrate this in Web components.
The idea is students, independent developers, would have a way to prototype and do things with that.
So again, the idea is creating a community around it.
So OSC is acting nowadays. After five years, it's still there, so it's not something that is going away.
The Hermitage, that's very high, and nowadays it's a high four model.
My view, it simplifies testing new ideas.
It allows to start things like integrating one WebOS part in ROSH for robotics and in EDL for automotive.
So it was quite a success in that regard, but there are tons of experiments that have been happening that are quite useful for prototyping product ideas.
So if you want to integrate WebUI in your experimental product, OSC can help.
It's very easy to integrate Web applications, Web contents, both are even running locally.
Okay, so how it happens, we have WebOS, we have open source edition.
There was an idea at the SBL that it would be interesting to part of Chromium,
the work runtime we have in WebOS to put it to EDL, so it would have a runtime with all the advantages we talked about.
So it has been a collaboration between EDL and IGALIA, and then presented to the Linux Foundation.
So in the end, a collaboration among the three.
Before 2018, GALIA was assisting in putting Chrome browser adaptation to Wayland on the Chrome browser, so it was running in EDL.
But in May, in 2018, my team in LG Silicon Valley Labs did this experiment to port one to EDL.
It was actually one month, but it was mostly working in two weeks, and then we started maintaining it from 2019 to present.
Okay, the thing is that the experiment proved it was possible, and now the focus is always moving to be able to run EDL with only WebUI.
So basically, the main UI at that time in EDL was using KIUT, and the idea was that if you didn't want to run on top of it,
you could run on top of one and half of the system UI and don't ask for applications.
It also allowed to integrate with other applications, add with the system services as per EDL item,
and that's part of the continuous adaptation as EDL evolves with different system protocols and system services.
We need to evolve to catch up with that.
So that was what happened in the last four years.
We did one adaptation to EDL.
Okay, another evolution.
In 2012, we were using KIUT WebKit.
We moved to KIUT WebKit 2 in the first two years, and the first mobile HDVs were using KIUT WebKit 2.
Then we moved to use KIUT Web Engine.
The idea was that everybody was moving to Blink, and it was not much more than that.
It is that we had the feeling that Chromium and Blink were moving faster while doing more for the web platform,
so it would save costs for maintenance to use an engine based on Blink and Chromium.
So yeah, we used KIUT Web Engine, KIUT already has a part that would save us time for doing that part.
But from 2015, we moved to create our own binding layer and drop KIUT Web Engine.
So this WebWiz Review is a new component that replaces KIUT Web Engine, and one is built now on top of that.
Why?
The main reason, there are a few reasons, but there was a concern about the licensing model on KIUT Web Engine at that time.
It was one of the first components that moved to LGPL v3.
So the way they're content about the pattern clauses and for a TB vendor, that was kind of a problem.
And not only a TB vendor, we found several others that would have some concerns on that.
So there was no other KIUT Web Engine use at that time.
So in the end, we did this, we removed that dependency, at least in the Web Engine integration side.
It also allowed to simplify the continuous algorithm to track upstream Chromium at that time,
because at least the media stack in WebWiz is way different.
So maintaining a different Web Stack on top of KIUT Web Engine on top of Chromium,
and tried to keep that baseline, tried to keep upstream, it started to become quite hard.
Then we did something different, and that's more recent.
One was based on KIUT for a long time, but there was concern from some stakeholders, not LG,
that has a partnership with KIUT that is strong, so it was not a problem.
But for other stakeholders, the ECPL dependency was kind of a problem.
And the other reason for using KIUT diminishes a bit, because basically C++ and STL grow a lot,
improved a lot, and simplified things.
So it was not that important to have all the pieces that KIUT was providing for free as part of the bundle.
So last year, two years ago, we moved to not depend on KIUT anymore,
and now it's based on STL, and other C++ libraries for JSON passing,
and Avital G-Live for the main loop.
And we moved from QMake to CMake.
Okay, but the thing is about stability.
One didn't change a lot in the last 10 years, so the main ideas that we had running 10 years ago
are still there, the way we handled the way running web applications, etc.
It has been useful, the architecture has been flexible enough to adapt to the web engine changes we explained,
dependency changes, new products, and even always changes.
So we've been able to port one to different devices, different web engines, and it adapts very well.
So first, about the future, WorldWash is still here to stay.
It's just spending lots of money on making it the main part for the WorldWash TV offering,
and they've been even allowing it to be used for third-party TV vendors through the WorldWash app.
And there are some future discussions.
We are now using GCC for building.
We may move in the future to reduce clang, basically because it's the toolchain that Kermit supports,
so maintaining a bottle change is kind of problematic.
And we want to improve the upgrade cycles.
We want to be closer to apps in Chromium, so there are many refactoring that's happening nowadays to improve this also.
So these are the final remarks.
Yeah, 10 years of the project, more to come.
It's in millions of products.
It proved to be useful, and it allows to create products offering.
I mean, don't put this in Arduino.
It's not going to work.
But for products with 512 MB, even 250 cc
Thank you.
We have a few questions, starting with the online questions.
The question online was, if I have an LG TV and they want to rebuild the firmware from sources, is that possible?
I don't think you're going to know the answer to that one.
No, LG's TV is proprietary OS.
I say that maybe around 10% of the software is proprietary, but you cannot be the firmware.
And actually, the TV industry is quite bad in that regard,
because of DRM and of the requirements of the TV content providers like Netflix,
Disney+, all these kind of things.
They want to have a strong hold on how the contents are delivered
and when the contents are possible to be delivered and paid and whatever.
So it's not all a thing about LG.
Samsung has the same problem, other vendors have the same problem.
It's that the industry that will deliver contents to the TV are quite problematic in that regard.
That's something that I would like to see it improve.
Google has done a lot for a little reducing the path that is related to the DRM,
but that's a problem of the TV industry that we need to deal with it.
So we manufacture OEM boards and over the years I've found it really difficult to know what kind of platforms.
I find it really difficult to recommend UX platforms to our clients.
So nowadays we're starting to look at Flutter.
That seems to be something people are talking about.
I'm really not a UX person.
So when would you say we should be recommending this and WebOS as opposed to other alternatives?
What are the sort of pros and cons, as it were?
Actually, there are different lines.
For system UI, you can choose whatever you want.
Flutter is quite efficient.
Qt is quite good.
Web is possible.
If that's not a job decision, the main thing is that do you need web applications on top of the web?
You need applications on top of that because you may want to play separate contents like Twitter application that is web,
like YouTube, silly that.
If you need separate contents, you may also want to have a run time.
So you already have the needs.
You may want to still use web also for the system UI.
It's your choice.
The tooling is a great advantage of Web Content because there are tons of ways to do UI in web,
and it's pretty much a common standard for that.
But yeah, it's a choice.
Thanks, everybody.
Thank you.