Yes, hi, I'm Johannes Bechberger.
I was already introduced.
I work at the sub-machine.
It's another great distribution of the OpenJDK.
So I worked since the beginning of last year on my new project on Async get set trace.
It's essentially an improved version of the Async get call trace API.
And I think many of you probably don't know this API.
I didn't know it before I started this project.
But essentially, it's related to profiling.
So how does profiling work?
Some of you might have always seen FlameCrafts.
If not, there are some other talks on profiling in the Mozilla room that you can look it up.
But essentially, what profiling is, you want to see which parts of your applications are
possible.
For example, here, I can see that some JDK stuff is probably a thing that takes time.
But essentially, how it works under the hood is that we have a selection of threads, like
for example here, five threads.
Then we randomly select three threads because we cannot usually sample all threads because
it would be too costly.
Then we pre-allocate some traces.
This is just a data structure where we store the stack frame information in.
And then we ping the first thread.
And with ping, I mean we send it a signal.
And then in the signal handle, we walk the stack because in the single handler, the thread
is stopped.
So it can walk the stack.
We do this with the thread two, with the thread five, and we have the traces.
And then we store it.
And then we do some post-processing.
That's essentially how Async profile works, but just in a loop.
In a loop, we always do this.
And so we need an API because we need an API.
It's called Async at call trace because we could use JVMTR libraries.
They are safe from bias.
So they let the threads wait till they're ready, till they're at a safe point, but we
want to have the call trace at a certain point where we want it.
And so Async at call trace is quite a cool API.
So how it works, here we have the stack, how it's on your system.
We have at the bottom the pthread start.
It's on the Unix system.
And on top, we have some Java frames.
And then it goes up to the top to write byte method because it writes to a buffered output
stream.
It's essentially print, hello world, it just prints some strings.
And in the single handler, we get the top frame.
That's where the u context from the single handler points to.
Then we do some stack blocking and Async at call trace does it for us.
And essentially, it returns us in a pre-allocated data structure, the frames, and the number
of frames that we got.
And it also stores a number of frames in error code if there was an error.
And so what we get for every frame is the line number.
So it's called line number, but it's essentially the bytecode index.
I don't know, it's historically this way because this API is from 2003 around and we get a
method ID.
But we only get this information on Java frames.
So what are these problems?
So don't get me started.
I worked on it for long enough time.
So it's unofficial.
So it's there in 2003, like for three months, and then Oracle put it out, Sun at the time
put it away.
It's now just lying around as an exported symbol but doesn't have its own header.
It's unsupported.
So if there's a change in another part of the JVM that potentially breaks it, nobody
notices it because there's only one single test that doesn't test that much.
So there's also missing information.
So it only gives us information on the stack frames of the Java frames but not on anything
else.
And it misses information like inlining, which isn't that great.
And so in the beginning of last year, I started to work on a new API because this, I think,
a call trace is the best we have.
And maybe we could do something better.
So I started to work on Async at Stack Trades.
It's now a CHAP candidate.
It's 435.
So if you want to see the CHAP in its entirety, just go on the Opti SDK website or read the
blog post for this talk and you get a picture of what it does.
And so the idea was to create a better API that gives us more information and is far
more supported, so with lots of tests with its own header.
And so again, we have the stack, our stack, but we then get more information.
For example, we get at its most basic level, we also get the kind of the thread that we're
running on.
So is this thread like in Java mode or is this in GC mode or what is this thread, which
is quite neat.
And we got more information.
For example, we get the BCI.
It's no-call BCI because, yeah, it's the byte code index.
We get a method ID.
We get also the type.
Is it inline?
Is it native?
With native, I mean not C, C++, but these boundary methods that are defined in Java,
but like which code is implemented in C, C++.
And we also get the compilation level.
So is it C1, C2 compiled or don't compile at all?
So this is quite neat because we get more information.
But the cool thing is we have options now.
We can, with this API, we can set in an integer, hey, we want to have non-Java frames and
we also want to walk non-Java threads, which leads us to this situation where we get information
also on the thread on these C, C++ frames, which is quite nice because for these frames
we get also the type.
So it's a C, C++ and we also get a program counter.
So we can then go back, do some of our own analysis and use DLSim to get the methods
of the DL family and get the method name.
And we can also walk with these options non-Java threads.
So we see more information.
It essentially makes the life of a profile developer far easier because we can now just
use this API.
It will be supported.
If it gets in, it will be supported.
I'm working on lots and lots of tests.
And yeah, that's, I hope it gets in.
And as a bonus, what I also introduced is new methods for OpenJDK developers to walk
stacks because currently the code is spread between a few different places.
Some of them are copies of others.
So it's quite hard when you change some port.
You have to change other parts too.
So it's essentially technical depth.
There were good reasons in the years before, but still I want to make stack walking easier.
So the new API that I used in the implementation of my chat proposal allows us to just give
a stack walker some options like, hey, I want to walk stacks.
I want to skip, I want to walk also non-Java frames.
And I can just go over and say, oh, give me the next frame.
And on this next frame, we can ask all the information.
Is this a Java frame?
Is this a native frame?
Which is this compilation level?
And this makes it far easier to walk stacks.
And hopefully makes it easier to combine all the stack walking from some ever-related stack
traces from async get call trace from JFR using one API.
And so when you make an improvement in one of these APIs and implementations, you get
an improvement on all.
So what I've done is that I improved async get call trace with the help of my colleagues
to be much safer, so I wrote testing code that used safe set so that it kind of checks
the pointer before it exists.
So it's far safer than I did here for async get stack trace.
Lots of testing, for example, I did some fuzzing.
So I called async get stack trace with random u-context, so with randomized frame pointers
and stack pointers, and it doesn't crash like for hours on a large machine, which is quite
cool.
And so this covers async get async profile when it modifies the frame and stack pointer
to alleviate some concerns when the VM is in undefined state.
It needs a lot of convincing, so I'm still in the process where I have to talk with all
the people from Oracle, all the JFR people.
It's a long, drawn-out process, but I hope I can convince them, because clearly the people
on the profiler side are really happy to have this because it has many advantages for them.
And of course, again, testing, because the whole point of this API is that you get more
information but also that it's a better tested API.
Currently, I have six tests, and I'm working on more.
So I hope that it gets in.
Till then, you can see on GitHub there's a draft PR on the strap.
Just search in the PRs for draft PR with R-SkiST in the name.
And then you can follow me on Twitter and our team at SpeedSubmachine, and that's all.
Oh, yes, yes, yes.
And I'm also blogging mostly in others, and all the blog posts are also put on FUJ.
But you can follow me there and read on all the topics that they talked today.
So thanks.
Question, yes.
So SafeHatch, I think it uses signal handlers, so it cannot be called from a signal handler,
so what do you do there?
Wally.
Oh, yes.
The question was, can SafeHatch be called from signal handlers because it uses signals?
I think it uses different signals because I didn't have any problems using it from signal
handlers.
So I have tests.
To use us and get stack-dressed, you have to use signal handlers, so I didn't see any
problems so far.
I think that's possible.
It's even weird because from signal handlers, you cannot do any mallocs, so you have to
preallocate, but you can call fork.
So it's quite interesting.
Any other questions?
Does it handle invoke dynamics, especially?
Because within that stack, you'll get the whole stacker deciding how to dispatch the
call.
So the question was, does it handle invoke dynamics specifically?
Now it just uses, it just is based on the frame stack-walking and the internal mechanism
of stack-walking.
So it doesn't handle it differently than, for example, I think, get call trace and
trace R.
That's all Java frames.
Yeah, that's all Java frames, so that's probably fine.
You have to change the negative parts?
Or does it work on all platforms?
So the question was, does it work on all platforms?
It's known that it doesn't really work on Windows just because Windows hasn't really
a concept of signals.
If you have any ideas on getting something like this to work on Windows, feel free to
drop me a message.
So no, I didn't have to change any native parts.
I had to create some native parts for testing to modify the U-context, because this is highly
operating system specific.
So the changes to the whole OpenJDK are fairly minimal, so they aren't that large besides
passing through some bullet to configure stuff.
And the code itself is just a few couple hundred lines, so it's quite simple also to understand,
and there's a blog post that describes the reasoning behind it.
Any other questions?
Yes?
Is it already a sub-machine?
No, it's not yet on the sub-machine, because I'm still in the process of testing it.
So there's, of course, a podcast.
You can already use the JVM when you compile it yourself.
I'm in the process to updating my demo repository, which contains a modified sync profile that
uses it, so you can try it out yourself.
I'll try it out in the next few weeks, it still has some bugs.
Anything else?
Thank you very much.