Let's write in. We don't have much time. My name is Paul Mazurel. I go by the name of
Phil Micoton, on Mastonon, on Twitter. I've been a REST developer since 2016. I spent
most of my career as a third developer, so it was only natural for me as my first project
to develop a library to build search engines. So if you're familiar with Lucene, that's
kind of like Lucene, but for the rest of the world. That was my first pet project. It grew.
And two years ago, I co-founded a startup called QuickQuit that is about building a
search engine that is specialized for logs. But just a word about QuickQuit. I'm not here
to do an advertisement. It's not a commercial, but it's related to the talk, so I need to
explain to you what's the problem, which is the problem that we are trying to solve.
QuickQuit is a REST project. It's under the AGPL license. It's open source. You can find
the source code on GitHub. And so we specialize on log search. So what's specific about log
search compared to, let's say, an e-commerce search engine is that the data that we get
is more or less immutable. So we assume that people will want to ingest documents into
our search engine and won't modify it too much. So after ingestion, the document stays
there until it goes out of its retention period, at which point we will delete it. Or maybe
you might want to delete it if you have a request to comply to GDPR with hundreds of
kind of stuff, but you cannot modify it like you would do for an e-commerce website.
And so one of the big differences in terms of efficiency is that when you deal with log
search, the volume that you have to deal with has no limits. The scale is the limit. The
largest amount that we've seen so far is people indexing 100 terabytes a day. So that's the
volume of data. Imagine if it was actually generated not by machine, but by humans. You
will have to have a lot of people typing grief as to deal with that kind of volume. So that's
something that you will only get if you're doing log search. And compared to an e-commerce
website, most of the CPU is actually spent indexing and not searching because you have
comparatively way less search and way more documents. So indexing is actually crucial
to our problems, and that's very different from usual search engines.
Indexing, what does it look like? That's the point that we are trying to solve. Super oversimplified.
We get, as I input, a stream of documents. It's interesting to have another idea. For
one pipeline of indexing, we have to deal with around 40 megabytes per second. And as
an output, every 30 seconds we write a file. We put it somewhere. And usually we register
it on some metadata back end. And at this point, the file is searchable.
And the rules of the game here is we want to have the highest possible throughput. And
we want to keep what we call time to search as low as possible. So time to search is at
the moment when JSON file is entering the system, we start the clock and we measure
how long it takes for it to go out of the system in the form of one of those files at
which point it is searchable. We need that to be as low as possible. And we need, it's
very important to keep it very stable. We don't want to have like a period of time
where it goes through the roof. So that's the whole game.
And in that black box, we do a lot of stuff. It was very simple. I won't go through all
of the stuff that we do. But the important part here is every single of the steps is
using different resources. The time is spent on different stuff. So for instance, when
we index things, when we build our in-memory index, we are spending CPU. When we are writing
the file, we use IO. When we upload, we use network. And sometimes we are waiting for
something that is outside of the system. We spend no resource at all except we wait.
So you might think that, let me tell you, it's obvious. We have one function for all
of those steps and we call them sequentially. But if you do that, you are wasting the resources
of our system, of course. For instance, when you are uploading, you are spending your network
resource. But your CPU is not doing anything. So you're wasting money.
The solution to this problem is relatively simple. But it's not that simple to implement.
You want to streamline your pipeline. What I mean by streamlining in a very concrete
way is you might have two steps, like indexing, spending CPU, upload, spending network. They
go sequentially. But what you want is you want indexing to work on building the first
file. And when it has finished, you start uploading, of course. But as you upload, you
want to stop working on the second file so that you are spending CPU while you are doing
your network stuff. That's the kind of behavior that we want.
And of course, this example is a little bit too simple because the second step here is
shorter than the first one. It's a nice case. But if you don't see the other way around,
we would have to have some kind of mechanism to deal with, to have back pressure. And in
my experience, a lot of very good engineers are not familiar with the concept of back
pressure. So let me explain what it is about. If you already know what it is, bear with
me and enjoy the fine artworks that we have here.
So the idea of back pressure is imagine you are cleaning dishes with a friend. One of
you is cleaning the plates and the other one is wiping them dry. And the person wiping
the dishes dry is a little bit too slow compared to the person cleaning the dishes. What's
going to happen is that your plates will accumulate like forever. And in the computer system,
it's a very common problem. And that's how you get out of memory hours.
So the solution is rather simple. You need back pressure, which means you need some way
to signal the person who is cleaning too fast that they should slow down. And the simplest
mechanism to do this is you need to have some kind of limit on your stack of plates or your
work queue or whatever you are using in your system. And then they stop once they reach
the limit. So there's a simplest way you could have back pressure.
So with all this said, the game here is how would you implement that? What would be your
goal? Go to implementation if you had to have such a system in one hour. And ping Rust developers,
I think that most of the people in this room will come with the following solution. So
the upload part, it's not CPU, it's just dealing with networks. So it's very natural to think,
okay, I'm going to do that in a Tokyo task. And back pressure, let's see. I already know
what I'm going to use. I feel that a good solution is I'm going to have a channel with
some capacity. And once it reaches capacity, of course, people sending work to my task,
they will have to wait. And it's going to be very nice and natural.
And then on the indexing part, we will have the same mechanism. Only right now, we will
have to actually do a lot of CPU heavy work. So maybe we won't run that in a Tokyo task.
And we will spawn our own thread or maybe we will use a thread pool to do that work.
It would be better, right? And we use the same mechanism. We will have a channel to
receive the work. The capacity here is much larger because the type of stuff that we put
in the channel is very different. For the uploader, we are getting files. They can be
large like 100 megabytes. So it makes sense to have it as small as possible. Here it's
documents. So it's for many documents, you will emit one file. You won't probably get
a series that is larger than three. And yeah, everything is fine and dandy. It's quite natural.
And we just reinvented actors. That's basically what actors are. So actors is a programming
paradigm that has been invented in the 70s by a researcher called Karli Witt that has
been popularized more recently with Erlang. And the actual formal definition is here.
It's from Karli Witt himself. And I'm going to read it. Even if it's a bit weird to read
slides out loud, this one is important. So an actor is a computational entity that in
response to a message it receives can concurrently, A, send a finite number of messages to the
actors. We've done that. B, create a finite number of new actors. We haven't been spawning
any actors in our example yet, but we do that in quick reads. That's something that we do,
especially for supervision or spawning a pipeline or stuff like that. So we do that. C, designate
behavior to be used for the next message it receives. That one is a little bit fuzzy.
Do we do this? No, we definitely don't. But if you water it down and you squint a little,
the fact that the actor has actually a state and the whole point of having this actor running
on a specific thread is that it will be possible to handle message and mutate our state. And
mutating our state is a bit like designating the behavior that will be able to use for
the next message. So we ended up building our own actor framework. So to be honest, I'm not
trying to advertise for this framework. It's another ADPL license, so you can use it. You're
free to use it. If you want to take over it for kids and make it better, I'd be happy for us to
use it. If you want to use it as is and you would like to have it as a MIT license, I'm perfectly
happy to put it under MIT license as well, actually. But right now it's not designed to be
reused by other people. But I think I might be able to tell you about our journey and maybe
could inspire other people to write our framework. There are actually a lot of actor frameworks in
Rust. The most famous one is Actix. So under our actor framework, what does an actor look like
compared to our original snippets? Yeah, it looks like this. So I implemented the uploader there. So
you have to implement first a trait called actor where you will define a bunch of small property
about your actor, especially the capacity that we have seen before. So it would be like the
capacity of the channels that we described before. And then you will have to implement a
handler trait for each type of message that you deal with. So contrary to our example, now we can
deal with several types of messages. Same actor can receive different kind of requests, if you will.
Another difference is most of the time you want to communicate with an actor in an asynchronous
way. That's how the actor pattern is working usually. But sometimes it's handy to actually
have some kind of reply when you do a request. It's a bummer because if you really want a reply,
that means that you will be waiting for the actor to process its entire queue and execute your
command and then return the result. But you don't have to use it. Most of our messages don't
choose it, but when we need it, it's handy. And our indexer, it's about the same. The one thing that
I want to point out is this thing on the actor trait where we specialized what should be returned
on the method runtime handler. So you remember that in our example, we said that an indexer spends
a lot of CPU. We wanted to run it on a dedicated thread. We don't do that here. What we do is we
target a specific Tokyo runtime, which is weird. So that's an implementation shortcut that we used
instead of running stuff on a thread pool. What we do is that we have several Tokyo runtime and we
have a Tokyo runtime that is dedicated to act as a thread pool. The benefit of this is this
implementation shortcut gives us a possibility to write exactly the same code for an async actor
or async actor, which is neat. And by the way, we're not the only one to use that trick. In
fact, the bear actually wrote a blog post about this a little bit of time ago. Now that we have a
framework, you might have noticed that the code was not even shorter. We have seen a couple of
features that we got from the framework, but what can we get like more? And within QuickWit, we have
25 different actors. What's cool when you have a framework is that you code stuff once and the
benefit is multiplied by 25. What could be the benefit? So hopefully, we get better structure
and code that is a little bit more readable. People open a file and they know what to expect. I want
to know what is the capacity. I set up the queue of this actor. Where should I look? That's something
that you get from having a framework. But also, we will talk a little bit about that, but we get
supervision from the framework. We get a neat solution to deal with time, which is probably the
main reason why we don't use tactics today. And then we have a bunch of recipes to write
unique tests, which is very important. We also have some stuff to be able to see what our actors
are doing and we have a solution for discovery. But we won't talk about this in this talk.
Supervision. Of course, I would like to tell you our code is perfect and perfect code is especially
for tenure-rasp. It never fails. In a sense, we don't expand spannics or stuff like that,
but we have to run our code, so party code, user-defined code. User, they can write a VR script to
transform their documents in the pipeline and that's running on our indexing pipeline. We have
to do IO. We have to interact with different systems. For instance, we get our documents from
a source. It's running in the pipeline. We send them to a storage. We have different storage that
are implemented. There's a lot of components and any one of them can fail and we want a very large
runtime. So one solution to this, it's not super-burly. It's not like it works all of the time, but just
try to turn it off and on again. It feels a little bit stupid, but you just restart everything from a
blank state or blank slate and sometimes things work that way. So the supervision works as follows.
We have an actor that is in charge of supervising all of the actors that are in the pipeline. What
it's doing is that it's pulling actors and when it detects that they failed, it will kill everyone
and restart everyone. The definition of failure is a little bit sophisticated in our case. It could be
an actor that has returned an error from a handler or it panicked or we have some system to detect if
an actor has not been progressing for three seconds. We have a notion of progression in our framework
that's an original way to do stuff. And we use one-fold supervision which means that if one actor
failed, we restart everyone. Okay, that was for supervision. Now we're about handling time which is
probably the most interesting part of our framework. So we need to be able to deal with the idea that
for instance in our indexer, we want to emit a file after 30 seconds has passed. So we have a
condition like this. 30 seconds after the first document was added in that batch. And we cannot
do like a time.sleep in the handler because it will block the entire processing of documents.
So the solution for this is rather simple. We have a method so that actors can ask the framework to
send back a message to themselves after a given amount of time. So 30 seconds here. And it seems
like a very simple solution but it has a problem. So here I showed how it worked. So actor is sending
a message to the scheduler. It says what is happening under the hood. It's sending a message
to actually an actor that is run by the framework called the scheduler actor. And 30 seconds later,
the scheduler will stack a message into the queue of the actor. The trouble there is imagine that
you already had a lot of messages in the queue of the actor. Then where are your 30 seconds? Maybe
we have one minute worth of messages in the queue. And then our entire contract of I want to emit a
file every 30 seconds, it's broken. We cannot do that. So the solution we went for is actually
mailbox are a tiny bit more complicated. They have two queues. One is a low priority queue,
the usual one. And we have a high priority queue. And the scheduler will put that in the high
priority queue. So as soon as the actor has finished dealing with a message that it was processing at
the time, it will jump on this scheduled message. And we will get our nice 30 seconds callback.
Testability, we let me check the time to know if I'm good or not. 20 minutes, perfect.
Testability, we have a bunch of solutions to write tests. Let's go through code to see
actual elastic codes, see how we can implement complicated real-life stuff and unit tests it.
So the code that we look at is a batch builder that is mimicking pretty much what we're doing
in indexing. So we have two possible conditions. We emit a file either because we have enough data
and it's enough to get a file. So let's say if you have 100 messages, it's not 100 in reality,
but if you have 100 messages, you emit a file. Or if 30 seconds has elapsed in the reception of the
first document of the batch. So it starts slow and easy. So we have our actor here.
So this is the state of the actor, but this is the actor as well. So something that is obvious
is it will have to have some mailbox to push the speed that it produced to. It will have a
document batch which will be a vector string. So the document will be just string. It will happen,
document to that. When it's big enough, it's going to flush it and send it to the mailbox of the
consumer. And one thing that is new here is we added some counters and we will be able in the
unit test to do some assets on this internal state. I didn't talk about it, but the actor trait
actually has an associated type which is called observer state. Of course, the whole idea of
actors is to encapsulate your state into your thread or your toker task and you're not supposed
to be able to mutate it or even read it from the external world. But we have some things that
makes it possible to ask from outside the actor, what is your observable state? And it will send
a message to the actor and the actor will send back the result of the observable state method here,
which is nifty for observability and for unit test. And then here is our handler. So we will have two
messages. One message will be receiving a document. Here, it was just a string as I told you. I wanted
to keep stuff simple. And we will do several things. So the first thing that we do is if this
was the first document in the batch, we need to register our callback message using the schedule
self message. We will append this document to our batch and then we check for the condition. We have
enough documents in the batch that we emit a batch using our second batch emission condition.
And in that case, we call emit batch. I didn't put the code of emit batch because it was too easy.
Not very interesting. And then
and then I didn't put the handler of the timeout message, but you can guess it basically is
emitting the batch. And then when we want to unit that stuff, we write things like this.
So we have a universe in our unit tests. It's a very important thing. We want to isolate our
unit tests, one from each other. The universe is in charge of this. So all of the actors of your
program have to belong to the same universe. Otherwise, they're not supposed to communicate
together. And we will see that this isolation will make it possible to do something really
cool in the next slide. And so this universe makes it possible to make a fake mailbox.
But we create the consumer side of things. We can create our batch builder and it's alone.
And you can send a message to it. That's what we do there. So I usually like to jump and point at
the screen, but I've been told that I cannot cross a white line. So yeah. And then what we do
when we want to create an asset is that we call this function called process pending and observe,
which just means that we wait for all of the messages that are currently in the queue of the
actor. We have all of those processed and then we call observe and we get a snapshot of what is
the observable state of the actor. And here's the observable state with a counter, which is equal to
the number of documents that we wanted. And then we check that the consumer mailbox does contain
our two batch, because 250 is 100 and 100 two batch. And we also want to be able to check the
time out that the time out counter is working well. So here, what is interesting is we created
our universe, but with a method with accelerated time and we will be marking time at this point.
So you won't have to wait 30 seconds to have your unit test run for 30 seconds. It will do magics
and the result will be exactly the same as if you were not accelerating time, but it will just be
faster and I will explain a little bit how it works. And so to further unit test, obviously we
have to call some way to wait and we call universe.sleep to do that. And it's important to
use the universe.sleep and time.sleep because we are mocking stuff, obviously.
So we cannot choose the mocking facilities that we are in Tokyo because we use several runtimes.
And also what we do is similar in semantics as pose and auto advance if you're familiar with it,
except we never freeze time. We keep time flowing, but what we do is tiny bit different. So you can
imagine that if you are not accelerating time, your outer execution would look like this. So
actors are processing stuff and sometimes you don't have any message in any queue or actors
either. And the only thing that will resume the processing is some time out to happen and the
scheduler saying, okay, I have a message for you. You asked for a self-scheduled message.
It's happening now. So our framework detects that we are in a phase where no one is working
and waiting for the scheduler. And in that case, and only in that case, we accelerate time. And
that's why we get a result that is exactly the same as if we didn't accelerate time,
but just faster. So we compress our execution before, after. That's how it works.
So that's, I wanted to show you the actual indexing pipeline in full complexity. I said
25 actors, it's not 25 actors here, but we have other actors in other parts of the code because
the pattern got quite popular. It's quite complex, but it makes me extremely good. It makes me feel
good to be able to show that when we have to explain like a new developer what the indexing is.
Thank you. What the indexing is doing. We can point at things. Everything on one of these
box is doing one very simple thing. It has its own file. It has its own unit test. It makes me happy
to have this very simple figure that we can discuss around. One thing that I need to talk
to you about is one problem with actors is if you have cycles in your actor network,
you might experience deadlock. And it's a pretty terrible thing that kind of deadlock because
it can happen at any time in production. Like it can work for one week and then you
experience the deadlock. It's a scary thing. There's a sufficient condition to overlooks
if you don't have any cycles. Usually, that's the case when you are writing a pipeline.
In the graph before, there was actually a cycle. We will have a look at it in a second.
There is a nicer condition to overlooks. It's if the graph of your actors where you removed
all of the Q where you had an infinite capacity. If that one is a tag, then you won't have deadlocks.
And that's what we are doing here. So the loop, the cycle that we had was due to the fact that
we have an auxiliary pipeline that is merging the file together. And there is an arrow over there.
I'm going to cross the line. I did it. I apologize. If you remove this arrow, then it's a tag. And
that's sufficient condition to never experience deadlock. It helps me sleep at night. And we have
a bunch of other features. The most important one I think I want to tell you about is we measure
back pressure. So the framework is automatically measuring back pressure and expose it as a
primitive counter. That's very neat. Very useful for us. And let's use the rest of the time for question.
So are there any questions in the room? Yes. The last slide of the previous slide was you didn't need
parallel actors. What do you need like Fanny and Kanna out for heavy parallel work?
Oh yes. So there is something that I didn't read, but she's going to read really fast.
And notice that we don't have anything to be able to have several actors work on the same queue or
like work concurrently to process the faster. So yes, we haven't needed that strongly enough to
actually implement it. I wrote an implementation and never merged it because we didn't really need
it. So indexing, we just put several pipelines on the same machine, not too much. So that part,
it's unpal. But yeah, we just never need, we haven't needed it yet. I can't read the way.
Parallel behavior happens at the pipeline level and the actor level, right? Yes, exactly. So the parallel
behavior... Sorry, you want me to repeat. Okay. So the, we use more than one core,
just because within the pipeline we do the streamlining thing. So we may have different actors
that are consuming the CPU at the same time, but we don't have one actor going, oh,
I, so it's actually five instance objector and we are doing the work five times faster.
We didn't need that. Any more questions? Yes. Do you have the fairness system so that one actor
doesn't keep on processing the system, allow others to be processed?
Yes. So no, we don't have that. So one thing that we have, actually we don't want, we have the
opposite problem. We don't want fairness. So there is one, so if you look at our pipeline,
the stuff that is taking a lot of CPU would be the indexer, it takes, the server would take a lot of
IO and we want to give it priority because it's the thing that we want it to use as much as CPU
as it can. So we want to give it one core and we want it to use as much IO as it needs.
And we would like to give it priority. So the way we do that is that we run it on a specific
runtime and over there it has its dedicated core. For IO, the framework is actually not really
helping. So what we do is that we have some IO struggling that makes it so that those actors
are not able to actually write on disk faster than, and you can configure that. And there is some
corner of the table computation to compute what you should do. But
yeah, other actors will not be able to write on disk faster than let's say 80 megabytes per
someone or such other. And the merge that you have below, it's okay if it lags a little bit.
So that's the part that we want to be low priority and the part on the top we want to be high priority.
So we don't have any fairness and we don't want any fairness.
Yes? So I guess your supervisor actually has a higher priority than anything because otherwise
those timeouts may also be delayed. So the supervisor is running on, it's very fast,
it doesn't do much. So it's running on a Tokyo runtime that has a dedicated core and those runs
one bazillion actors, but they're all very light so it doesn't matter at all.
Yeah, absolutely. You're absolutely right. But the thing is it's running on its specific
runtime and it's not CPU AV so there's plenty of core to work with. Yes? When you accelerate time
in the testing universe, do you have to specify the steps in time you take? You mean the number of times?
I assume that when you accelerate time basically when nothing is happening, you take a time step
and then see if something would have happened at that time point. Does that mean that you have to
specify we take steps of 100 milliseconds and then test every time if something would be happening now?
No, it's not. We don't need to say how many steps we take, we don't need to say
what is the resolution of the steps that we take. The only thing that we do is that the scheduler,
when it detects, it needs to accelerate time. It has some kind of heap that says, okay,
the next event is actually in 70 milliseconds. So it has jumped 70 milliseconds in the future
and it triggers that event and then the execution of the actor that was supposed to receive this
message will go and if no actor is working anymore, then we re-accelerate them again.
So it's no steps, no resolution, no nothing.
Yes?
How about reliability if you want to be sure that the log line will make it to the index?
Do you count them or how do you know they made it through?
So, yeah, it should be the subject of another talk because now that's a super interesting question.
So the pipeline, you want to know, to have an idea of what kind of semantics,
deliver a semantics that you want to have. We actually offer exactly one semantics
and the way we deal with that is, so we didn't talk about that, but we have the
documents that are coming from a source actor and the source actor when we spun it with
tell it, okay, you need to stream messages from this specific checkpoint and when we publish stuff
like downstream, we publish stuff by running a transaction on our metadata store backend
and that transaction updates the checkpoint of the stuff that we have published and it publishes
speed as well. So that's when we restart everything, we can check in the metadata store
what is the last checkpoint and it starts from there. And if there is an error, the metadata store
will just yell at us and return an error. It will say, okay, no, something weird has been happening,
maybe we all had two pipelines working at the same time and your checkpoints are overlapping
and you have a problem. That's the way we work with this problem. Yes? At universe, is that a
special grade or is it in the standard library? No, it's the universe thing is something within
our framework and that's what we use to be able to isolate typically different programs or different
unit tests or different systems. Yeah, it's within our framework.
Okay. It is.
Do we still have time or? I think we have one more question or one more minute.
I think there was a, yeah. I understand that this dropped the numbers on the numbers indicate
the capacity of the computer, right? The capacity of the channel between the actors, right?
The numbers, yes. Yes. So we have a lot of tuning points in the system, right? Yes.
So the question is, from your experience, how sensitive the performance of the system
is to the tuning of the pressure on the channels? And maybe you have some kind of advice or a rule
of thumb for what you choose for best performance as the third guest for the channel. Yes, so the
question was on this slide, all of the little numbers that we have on the arrow is the capacity
of the different cues between actors. That's a lot of parameters to tune. They probably have
an impact on performance. Is there a cool recipe to that? So the first question was how much do
they impact performance? And the second one is do we have a nice recipe to be able to tune them
maybe automatically? I'll go first because there is no more time. So they don't impact
performance all that much as long as you got them a little bit correct.
So usually, you need to identify the stuff that should be at one, and then you put it at one,
and where you want a little bit of capacity. It should be quite obvious if you know your system.
I'm sure that there is a nice recipe to auto-detect that. I haven't found it, so if you have ideas,
I'd love to. Usually, that kind of question is someone was thinking about something.
So please come to me. I'll tell you the truth. I'd love to hear your thoughts.
Thank you everyone. Time is up. I send the webinars.