So, before we go on with the next security related topic, we're going to talk about something
completely different.
And that is about elastic surge internals by Martin from the Bulgaria JAG.
And maybe also about security in this context.
So, we're going to put this side and this side.
Test, test, test.
Thank you.
There's lots of people coming in.
Please move to the middle of your row so that there's space on the sides so people can sit
and sit.
We're working in Sisko together.
A lot of people coming.
So, we can start.
All right.
If you're standing along the side, please take a seat.
Hello, everyone.
My name is Martin and I'm a consulting architect at European Patient Office.
I've been also doing a lot of consultancy on elastic surge in the past two to three years.
So, just before we start with this session, how many of you are using or have used elastic
surge in a project?
Okay.
More than half of the people.
So, why this talk has forced them?
So, multiple reasons, in fact.
When I've worked with elastic surge, I realized that even though it has quite a good documentation,
in many cases, you need to go into the public code base and see what's in there and to understand
how it works.
I've had questions from many people how this functionality works or how can I achieve something
with elastic surge.
And not always it's clear from documentation or blocks over the internet what we can achieve
So, in this short session, I'll try to show you how this elastic surge work internally
and I'll talk about the elastic surge architecture.
So, first of all, we'll do a 360 degrees overview of the elastic surge stack, which I believe
most of you are familiar with.
Then I'll go into the elastic surge architecture and at the end of this short session, I'll
show you how you can write a very simple elastic surge plugin.
In most cases, you won't need to write an elastic surge plugin because there is quite
a rich ecosystem of elastic surge plugins that you can use.
But many companies find that that's not always the case.
So, sometimes you need to either customize something in elastic surge or write your own
plugin to achieve something.
All right.
So, let's talk briefly about the elastic surge stack.
In the middle, we have elastic surge, which is a Java application.
It's being updated quite often.
There are a lot of features being implemented in elastic surge, especially in the latest
few releases.
And around the elastic surge server application, there are different applications that are
being built to allow it to work more easily with elastic surge, such as Kibana.
Kibana is a user-rich user interface for elastic surge that allows you to achieve multiple
things.
So, not only querying elastic surge, but Kibana allows you to also visualize data that's already
in elastic surge or build different dashboards that are quite nice, especially for management.
Also, if you want to put different data from a variety of sources in elastic surge, you
can use lock stash.
So, originally lock stash was implemented to provide a way to aggregate locks into elastic
surge.
But over time, lock stash evolves to an application that is used to integrate data in elastic
surge, not only lock data, but any kind of data.
So, you can think of lock stash as a log aggregation pipeline that allows you to put data in elastic
surge.
And on top of that, we also have a different set of so-called bits applications that are
lightweight lock shippers that allow you to collect data and put it either directly into
elastic surge or through lock stash into elastic surge or different other data sources.
The specific thing about the bit applications is that they are lightweight in nature, so
they are supposed to not consume a lot of resources, such as CPU and memory.
And in that reason, they allow you to collect lock data or other data and put it into elastic
surge.
Now, you can think of elastic surge as a web server built on top of the Apache Lucine Library.
So, the Apache Lucine Library is an actively developed Java library that is used by different
applications that want to implement some kind of search functionality.
And elastic surge is one of them.
So, I'll show you briefly in a few slides how elastic surge interacts with the Apache
Lucine Library.
And another way to describe elastic surge is a document-oriented database.
So, elastic surge is used by different projects, not only for searching, but also as a NoSQL
database.
So, I had a few projects where elastic surge was used purely as a NoSQL database, not as
a search engine.
And one can think, okay, elastic surge is a Java application.
Why?
I cannot use Apache Lucine directly.
And the reason is that elastic surge provides a number of features that are missing in the
Apache Lucine Library that allow you to implement search in your project way more easily than
using directly Apache Lucine.
Some of these features are, for example, JSON-based REST API, which is quite easy to use, quite
easy to write search queries to index data into elastic surge, and so on.
There is also a really nice clustering mechanism implemented in elastic surge that allows you
to bring and scale your elastic surge cluster quite easily, something that's not possible
if you use directly Apache Lucine in your project directly.
And also, it has a number of other features, such as, for example, caching, that allow you
to improve the performance of your search queries, and so on.
Now, the basic data structure used by elastic surge is the so-called inverted index, and
indexes are stored on disk in separate files or Lucine segments.
Search can be performed on multiple indexes at a time.
That's one of the capabilities of elastic surge.
And in earlier versions of elastic surge, documents were logically grouped by types.
That was effectively deprecated as a version 7 of elastic surge, and it's expected to be
dropped.
In order to ensure score relevance when you search for some data in elastic surge, elastic
surge uses a set of different algorithms to score results relevance.
In the later versions of elastic surge, this algorithm is BM25.
In earlier versions of elastic surge, this was a simpler algorithm, which is called TFIDF.
At the base of those algorithms is the fact how many times does a term occur in a document,
and how many times does this term occur across all documents that are currently indexed in
elastic surge.
Based on that, by default, elastic surge scores every result that gets returned by your search
query, and by default, it returns results sorted by relevance score.
Now, why would you use elastic surge in favor, for example, of a relational database?
Well, it provides faster retrieval for documents in way more scenarios than a traditional relational
database can do.
So, as you know, traditional relational databases provide faster searches through indexes.
However, indexes in relational databases have many limitations based on the type of SQL
queries that you write.
In an elastic surge, the inverted index data structure provides you with the capability
to cover way more scenarios for searching using more complex queries.
For that reason, many projects choose to use elastic surge as a search engine.
Now, documents also in elastic surge might not have an explicit schema, as you have in
a relational database, and that's typical for many NoSQL databases.
An explicit schema, however, can be defined on the fields, and certain fields can even
have different types mapped to them.
This is needed because sometimes you need to use different kinds of search queries based
on the field type, and some field types pose limitations.
So, that's why you might need to have multiple types on a single field in elastic surge.
Now, this was brief about what is elastic surge and how it works.
Now, let's see what the architecture of elastic surge.
Elastic surge, as I mentioned to you, is designed with clustering in mind.
By default, in later versions of elastic surge, if you create an index, it has one primary
chart and one replica chart.
So, what is a chart?
Now, an elastic surge index contains one or more primary charts that distribute the data
in the elastic surge cluster.
Below that, an elastic surge chart is in fact a Lucene index, and a Lucene index is, in
fact, the data structure that stores the data on disk in terms of Lucene segments.
Lucene segments are the physical files that store data on the disk.
Now, when you index data in elastic surge, you might have also replica charts.
Replica charts provide you with the possibility to enable high availability and data replication
at the level of the elastic surge cluster.
So, two types of charts, primary and replica charts.
The more nodes you add to the elastic surge cluster, the more data gets distributed among
charts.
Now, it's very important that upfront you plan the number of primary charts based on
the data growth that you have.
It's very difficult to change later in your project life cycle the number of primary charts.
You need to re-index data.
However, if you want to change the number of replica charts, that's more easy to do
later in time.
So, it's very important that you plan upfront what's the number of primary charts on an
index that you create.
Now, by default, elastic surge tries to balance the number of charts across the nodes that
you have.
And one of the other capabilities that elastic surge provides you is that if a node fails,
you still can get search results, or so-called partial results can be returned, even if some
of the nodes in the cluster are not available.
Now, by default, elastic surge determines the chart where a document is indexed based
on a relatively simple formula.
You get the hash key of the routing, key of the document.
This is the document ID, which can be generated in different ways.
You can generate it from elastic surge.
If you don't specify it, your application can supply the document ID, so on and so forth.
And you'll take the modules, the number of primary charts that you have defined on the
index where you index the document.
Now, as I mentioned, by default, the routing key is the document ID, but you can also use
a different routing key.
And one interesting technique that some people use to enable distribution of data in the
elastic surge cluster is by specifying a custom routing key that allows you to enable
so-called chart routing.
This is a technique that allows you to specify at which particular chart you want to send
the document to be indexed.
But that's a case that's used in some specific scenarios.
In most cases, people rely on the default mechanism that elastic surge uses to distribute
data in the cluster.
Now, by default, new nodes are discovered via multicast.
If a cluster is discovered, a new node joins the cluster if it has the same cluster name.
If a node on the same instance already runs on a specified port, and if you try to run
another node on that instance, elastic surge automatically gives you the next available port.
Now, however, in some cases, in some companies, multicast addresses are disabled for security
reasons.
And that's why the preferred mechanism to join new nodes in an elastic surge cluster
is by using unicast addresses.
In the Elasticsearch YAML configuration, you just need to specify one or more existing
nodes from the elastic surge cluster so that they can join that existing cluster.
And in that list of unicast nodes, you don't need to specify all the nodes in the elastic
surge cluster.
You just need to specify at least one node that has already joined the cluster.
Now, when you bring up an elastic surge cluster, there are some considerations that you need
to take.
First of all, as I mentioned, sharding is very important for you to consider what should
be the number of primary shards that you define on the elastic surge index, and the number
of replica shards which is more easy to change over time.
You also need to consider how much data you store in an elastic surge index.
Indexes with too small amount of data are not good, because that implies a lot of major
overhead, and the same is for indexes with too many amounts of data.
I've seen some cases where people store, let's say, more than 2, 300 gigabytes of data in
an elastic surge index, and that really slows down search operations and other operations
of that index.
And people start wondering, okay, why is my indexing slow?
Why are my search queries slow?
And in many cases, the reason is that because data is not distributed properly in the elastic
surge index, the preferred amount of data that you should keep in an elastic surge shard
is between 5 and 10 gigabytes, roughly speaking.
So if you have more data that you want to put on a shard, you should consider splitting
that data.
So you either use more shards in the cluster, or you split the data into so-called sequential
indexes.
So for example, you might have daily, weekly, or monthly indexes.
Yeah.
Now, this is what I mentioned.
So you should avoid putting too less data in the elastic surge cluster.
Also, if you have too many shards defined on an index that also introduces performance
and management overhead.
So you should consider rather splitting the data in the index rather than bringing too
many shards on a single index, and determining the number of shards should be a matter of
a prompt planning.
Now apart from putting the fact that you need to avoid putting large amounts of data in
a single index, the main strategy that people use is to use, for example, prefix when they
split data into indexes.
For example, you can put prefix for daily, weekly, or yearly indexes.
And if you do that, it's a good practice that also use aliases to reference data, not directly
reference a particular index in your application, but rather use aliases.
In terms of concurrency control, elastic search does not provide pessimistic locking, like,
for example, you have in relational databases.
If you want to establish some form of concurrency control in elastic search in order to make
sure that you don't have unexpected race conditions, so elastic search uses optimistic
locking for concurrency control.
The way this works is when you index a document, there is a version attribute that can be specified.
And if there is already a document indexed with that version, then the operation is rejected
from elastic search.
Concurrency control can also be achieved with the two fields that can be specified when
you index a document.
If sequence number and if primary term parameters, if they already match the document that's
indexed, then this operation gets rejected.
So if you want to establish some form of concurrency control in elastic search, you can use this
optimistic locking provided by elastic search.
In terms of high availability, you can create one or more copies or so-called replicas of
an existing index.
The number of primary charts is specified when you define the index mapping, or you
can change it later.
Once an index request is sent to a particular chart, determined based on the hash of the
root ID, the document is also sent to the chart replicas.
And one interesting property in elastic search is that the replicas are not used only for
high availability, but also used for searching purposes to improve performance.
So when you have replica charts, they also participate in the search request that you
have for elastic search.
Now this mechanism for improving performance is really nice, but this doesn't mean that
you need to supply to increase the number of replicas because, of course, that increases
management overhead.
So it's also a matter of determining how many replicas up front you would need.
And later on, if you plan to scale your cluster, you can also increase the amount of replicas.
So you should not put a lot of replica charts also at the beginning when you define your
indexes.
Now how is a chart request processed?
Now if we want to index a document in elastic search, what happens?
We send the request to a coordinating node.
This is one of the nodes in the elastic search cluster.
And this coordinating node sends the request to the chart, to the node in the cluster where
the document needs to be indexed and stored in loose in segments.
When the document reaches the elastic search node in the cluster, the particular chart,
it gets sent not directly to the disk, but to two in memory areas.
This is the memory buffer and the transaction lock.
Now the memory buffer gets flushed every second to the disk.
So when you index a document in elastic search, you cannot expect it to be available right
away for searching purposes.
But there is also a parameter that you can use to enforce it to be written to disk right
away before waiting for this one second to be flushed on disk.
There is also another area, which is called the transaction lock, where it gets flushed
not so often.
It gets flushed every 30 minutes or when it gets full.
So the important take over from this is that when you index a document, you should not
expect it to be available right away for searching.
But you can force it too.
What happens if you send a search query to elastic search?
First the search request gets sent to one of the nodes in the elastic search cluster,
the so-called coordinating node.
Then we have two phases.
First is the query phase.
The query phase asks all the shots, primary and replica shots, hey, do you contain some
data for that search query?
And this information gets returned to the coordinating node.
Based on that information, the coordinating node determines which nodes it needs to query.
And on the second fetch phase, it sends the request to the shots that have some data for
that search query and return it back to the client.
Now in terms of how is the elastic search code-based structured, this is a snapshot
from the GitHub code base of Elasticsearch from the public code base.
Now what I'm speaking about in this presentation applies for the public code base in Elasticsearch
because of version 7.16, there was a licensing change.
And there is a lot of controversy in the open source communities whether Elasticsearch is
still open source or not.
So we can have a discussion about that after the session.
I'm not going to go into the details.
But the main thing about this licensing change is to protect Elasticsearch from other vendors
willing to provide Elasticsearch as a service, not from people willing to customize Elasticsearch
or to use it for their in-house projects and so on.
So this is the structure of the Elasticsearch code base that has been like this since the
Apache license code base.
So Elasticsearch gets built with GitHub actions.
You can see what's the definition in the.github folder.
The main server application is in the server folder.
The documentation that gets generated on the official Elasticsearch website is in the
docs folder.
We have the main modules for the Elasticsearch server application in the modules folder and
the internal plugins in the plugins folder.
An implementation of the REST-based Java client for Elasticsearch, the high level and
the low level REST plans are in the client folder.
And the distribution folder, you can find the Gradle scripts that allow you to build
different distributions of Elasticsearch for Linux, Windows, and so on.
Now I would say the structure of the code repository is very logical.
It's easy to navigate.
So you can just go into GitHub and if you need to see, for example, how is a particular
plugin or module implemented, you can just go to GitHub and check it out.
Now internal Elasticsearch is comprised of different modules.
And in earlier versions Elasticsearch used a modified version of Google GIS for module
binding.
They are slowly shifting away from Google GIS in favor of their own internal module
system.
So modules are loaded on startup when the Elasticsearch server starts up.
And in this simple example I've shown an example of how modules were bound internally when
the node starts up.
So we use a module binder.
The earlier versions B was a Google GIS binder.
And then we bind particular module classes to their implementation.
And then whenever you need them, you can reference them in the Elasticsearch code base.
It's a very simple dependency injection mechanism.
Now when Elasticsearch starts up, you can imagine it's a simple Java application.
The main class is Oracle Elasticsearch, Boost.App Elasticsearch.
It boils down to calling the start method of the node class.
And the start method, in fact, loads up all the modules of the Elasticsearch node.
Now some of these core modules are, for example, modules that provide the REST API for Elasticsearch,
module that allows you to establish clustering in Elasticsearch, or so-called transport module.
There is a module that allows you to build plugins for Elasticsearch, and so on and
so forth.
Now how does Elasticsearch internally interact with Lucene?
When you start up the node, the node also exposes, provides different services that
are used by the modules of Elasticsearch.
And for example, if you want to, when you start up a node, there is a createShart method
that gets called indexService createShart to create and initialize the chart that is part
of this Elasticsearch node.
Then if you want to index a new document, it boils down to calling indexShart apply
indexOperation on primary.
Then this boils down to calling the index method on the indexShart class.
And the indexShart class goes down to an internal engine class that calls indexIntoLucene, then
that calls internalEngine.addocs.
And at the end, we just call indexWriter, which is a class from the Apache Lucene library,
add documents.
So it boils down to calling different methods from the Lucene API.
And on top of that, we have a lot of initialization and services happening.
So in a way, you can think that apart from all the functionality that Elasticsearch provides,
the integration with the Apache Lucene library just boils down to calling the different APIs
that Apache Lucene provides.
And last but not least, I'll show how you can build a very simple Elasticsearch plugin.
Now if you see the Elasticsearch code base, it already has some built-in plugins that
you can use.
And there is a very nice Elasticsearch plugin utility that you can use to manage plugins,
to install them, remove them, and so on and so forth.
If you build your own plugin, you can use the same utility to install the plugin, and
it gets placed in a folder in your node installation.
So if you install a plugin, you need to make sure that it's installed on all the nodes
in your cluster.
Because many plugins are cluster aware, and it needs to be installed on every node in
the cluster.
Elasticsearch plugins are bundled in zip archives, along with their dependencies, and all of
them must have a class that implements Oracle Elasticsearch plugins plugin class.
There is a plugin service which is responsible to load the plugins in Elasticsearch.
Now let's see how we can create a very simple ingest plugin that allows you to filter words
from a field of an index document.
So if you index a document, you can specify from which field which words you want to filter
out.
This is a very common scenario, for example, if you want, for example, to implement that
allows you to clear contents from documents, and so on and so forth.
It's probably one of the simplest plugins you might have.
So first we have a filter ingest plugin class that extends the plugin class and implements
ingest plugin.
We have different interfaces for the different types of plugins you might have for Elasticsearch,
and ingest plugin is one of these types of interfaces.
Then you specify, you implement the get processors method because an ingest plugin needs to have
processors that you can define that do something on the documents before they are indexed.
And the get processors method, what we do, we get a filter word from the parameters that
we supply on the ingest processor that we define in Elasticsearch.
And then we get the filter field.
So we have two parameters, the word that we want to filter out and from which field of
the document we want to filter it out.
Then we create a map of processors.
And in that map, we put the filter word processor that we create from this class and return
it.
You can also have multiple processors defined in that plugin.
Now what does the filter word processor look like?
The filter word processor extends abstract processor from Elasticsearch.
It again comes from the core class of Elasticsearch.
And we have an execute method.
In the execute method, we get the document that we want to index.
This is the ingest document.
We get the value from the particular field that we want to filter out.
And then we replace that value with the empty string.
And then we set back the value on top of that field and return the document.
This when you index a document and you specify that ingest processor applies the filtering
on that document before it gets indexed into Elasticsearch.
Now those two classes, if you want to build a plugin, you also need to supply some simple
plugin metadata.
Then build it, for example, with Maven or with Gradle.
And then you can install it with the Elasticsearch plugin utility.
And in that manner, you can build any plugin you would like for Elasticsearch.
And since we are running out of time, I'm not sure if we have some time for one or two
questions maybe.
Okay.
Do you have time for?
Yes, of course.
Okay.
So if anybody, yeah.
Hey, actually, in size, you saw how too many charts can go out of the form of the new.
Yes.
I was curious how did one know how many charts are too many charts?
Well, I would say it depends on upfront estimation of how much data do you expect to put in that
index.
So we need to do an upfront planning.
Okay.
In the first phase of my project, how many, let's say, gigabytes of data I would have?
And based on that, you determine how many initial set of charts do you put.
And if those charts still have a lot of data, then you consider partitioning the index.
So it's a matter of upfront planning to determine that.
Okay.
Yeah.
What structure is used for indexes and data?
It's inverted index.
This is data structure.
Yeah.
Inverted index.
It's just called an inverted index because it's an upper between terms.
And for each term, you have a pointer to the document that contains that term.
So it's called inverted index.
Yeah.
Okay.