So, hi, I will start right away because my talk is quite packed.
So, I'm focusy monies working for Amazon in the Amazon Coreto team.
My slides and the examples are on GitHub.
I will show this link one more time at the end of the talk so you don't have to take
a copy.
I am principal engineer and Amazon Coreto team working the OpenGDK since more than 15
years.
I have been with SAP before that for also more than 15 years and have various duties
in the OpenGDK and JCP.
So, let's get started about firecrackers.
A firecracker is a minimalistic virtual machine monitor.
It's KVM backed.
It only supports a limited set of devices, basically block and network devices which
are virtualized through VITIO and a V-SOC and a serial device.
It makes it very fast and also very secure because it doesn't support any exotic devices
like for example QMO.
It has a REST based configuration.
It's completely written in Rust which also makes it kind of safe.
It's based on, it was from Google's cross VM and it's nowadays based on a Rust VM library
which is like a base library for virtual machine monitors and I think that's also used by cross
VM meanwhile.
It supports a micro VM metadata service which is basically a JSON storage where you can
share data between guest and host because with full virtualization it's not easy to
exchange data between guest and host because all the guest applications run on their own
kernel and with this data service for example you don't need a network connection between
host and guest.
And then the firecracker process itself supports in addition to the security provided by KVM
unboxing so a jailer utility which basically places the firecracker process on the host
into additional C group change root and second environment and it's all open source, Apache
2 licensed and it's the technology behind AWS Lambda.
So every Lambda runs in its own firecracker virtualized container.
So here's just a picture of what I've just told you.
So we have the kernel with KVM on the downside and then we have the firecracker process which
has a thread for each vCPU which you configure in your guest and then it has a special thread
to handle IO and an API thread which is low priority to handle the rest requests and then
it boots the guest kernel which has the VOTIO devices and the VM thread handles this, VOTIO
issues and maps them for network to tap devices on the host and for the block devices either
on a native block device on the host or on a file system which is exported as block device
to the guest.
And then you can run a bit of application on the guest and you can run as many guests
as you want.
It's only limited by your amount of memory basically.
The overhead by firecracker is just about 50 megabytes so, no it's less.
We will see, it's very small.
So let's go to a demo.
So I have to truncate the file.
So here we just start firecracker.
We specify the API socket where we communicate within.
We have a log file and log info and the boot timer to see the boot timer.
And now from another terminal we start to config this with JSON data as I told you before.
So we configure two vCPUs and 512 megabytes of memory.
I have here a root file system, extended x4 root file system and a freshly compiled Linux
kernel.
So I will now use another REST command to configure the Linux image which will be booted
and I pass quite a lot of kernel arguments.
It's mostly to switch off devices which you don't need anyway and which are unsupported.
And we define as init script to just run bash.
So init script will be just a shell.
And then we finally have to define a root file system.
That's our x4 file which I showed you before.
And now that we've configured everything we can just start the virtual machine again with
a JSON request.
And when you go back into our window we see that now the virtual machine has been started
and it took about 200 milliseconds to start bash.
And it's fully configured.
Linux the image was assembled from a Ubuntu 22 image and the kernel I've compiled it myself.
You see we have two CPUs and about 512 megabytes of memory.
So if we exit the shell it will be just reboot because it was our init process.
From this 200 milliseconds we just take to boot the serial device alone took about 100
milliseconds.
So if you take that away usually in production you don't need the serial device it puts in
100 milliseconds.
And that's on my laptop.
So very quick comparison of Firecracker and Docker.
So Firecracker is fully KVM virtualized.
Docker has only C group namespace isolation.
The good thing about C group namespace isolation only is that Docker images run on the same
kernel so they can do copy and write page cache memory sharing.
So if you run many of them they are dancer.
Whereas for if you run several Firecracker images they cannot directly share memory.
So you have to use ballooning devices for example in the gas to give back memory to
the host.
On the other side that's much more secure because every container has its own memory,
its own kernel.
And Firecracker has snapshot support to checkpoint the whole container like with the kernel everything
together and Docker can use Creo checkpoint restore and user space to do the same thing
basically serialize Docker container with all processes to a file.
I will see examples for that now.
So now what is crack and Creo?
So as was mentioned before crack is called in native restore and checkpoint.
It's a new project in the open JDK.
It has basically three points which are important.
First one is to create the standard checkpoint restore notification API because many applications
are not aware of being cloned and there is state, security, time, all this kind of stuff
which an application might want to react upon especially not only when cloning but not only
when checkpointing and restoring but especially when cloning the application.
Think for example of an application which logs to a file and then you would checkpoint
it and we start to clones and they both write to the same file.
They will corrupt the file usually.
So you have to take some measures if you run many things in parallel and the application
is not prepared for that.
So if you want to, crack is currently not part of an official open JDK release.
It's still mostly a research project in the open JDK but you can already now make your
application ready for crack by using the org crack API that's available on Maven Central
and that basically wraps JDK crack namespace which is currently in the crack repository
in open JDK but if it finds JavaX.crack once it should become available it will switch
to that and it also offers the possibility to pass the custom implementations to a system
property and then finally what makes crack interesting for many people to experiment
with is that it basically integrates with Creo so it has a copy of Creo packed with
the crack distribution so you can easily checkpoint your Java process and restart it.
And then as I mentioned before Creo is checkpoint restore and user space.
It's an old Java functionality which allows to serialize a single process to the file
system.
It uses kernel free cgroup freezer to freeze the processes or process tree and then writes
all the memory to the disk and so on.
Still Creo has some issues because it has to take a look at all the open file descriptors,
shared memory segments, stuff like that which might not be available again when you restore
the image whereas Firecracker as I said before it restores the whole kernel with all the
file system everything in place so it's much simpler from that perspective.
So let's take a quick demo on Firecrack.
So I have here open JDK build 17 with crack extensions and then you simply pass the option
checkpoint two that's a file and this is just a pet clinic, a Spring Boot pet clinic example
application and I modified it to register with the org crack callbacks as I said.
You can see here it's registered to org crack and now that I've started it I can use J command
to checkpoint it so I send it a checkpoint command and when you see just out of the box
it didn't work it shows some exception because it found for example that the port 88 is open
and this uses a vanilla version of Tomcat which isn't implementing the crack callbacks
so that's not that bad.
It has a developer option which has to ignore exceptions so for this simple case it will
probably work so let's try it.
Start it one more time.
Prepare the checkpoint here so let's wait until it becomes ready.
So now checkpoint it and you see we also locked the resources so you see there were about
10 file descriptors and most of them were okay because like the crack modified VM already
knows a lot of the file descriptors the VM is using for example for the jar files it
has opened or for the module files and it closes them by themselves without need to
register anything.
And the checkpoint it worked and what's interesting is here that before checkpointing it caused
the listener, the handler I installed in my pet cleaning application so I could do additional
stuff before checkpointing and now we can just restore this frozen process and you see
it starts instantly it caused after restore a hook I have registered and we can send a
CURL request on 8080 and it basically still works.
So that's nice.
Let's go further.
So now firecracker so that's basically a combination of initial firecracker and crack.
I found it somehow funny that words are so similar so it's a play with words and in my
opinion it's the best of two worlds to combine these two.
Currently as I said a crack project is based on Creo but I think it might be interesting
to add support for firecracker as well and I'm currently working on that.
So with firecracker you can basically checkpoint a plain JDK even if it's not modified by crack
because as I said no need to worry about file descriptors so on.
One issue with firecracker as I said before you cannot trigger the checkpoint from Java
so the crack implementation in open JDK can checkpoint itself because Creo is running
on the same kernel like the Java application so Java just so JNI calls Creo and checkpoint
itself that's obviously not possible in firecracker because you cannot escape from the gas that's
the whole thing about running it in a fully virtualized gas so we need another means of
communication but that's not that complicated.
It offers maximum security and speed and as said before no copy on write memory sharing
but you can use ballooning same page merging kind of features which are also have their
plus and their drawbacks but things to investigate.
So let's do a firecracker demo with Java now.
To not bore you more with all this JSON request I've written a shell script which basically
does all that in one script and instead of calling bash it just starts Java as init process
and we can now submit the request and you see it's working it's here here is the request.
I have still registered these callbacks although I'm running on a vanilla JDK by using the
ORCRACK library so they are empty they won't do anything and I can now snapshot firecracker
and you see that's also quite quick.
Firecracker is not is resumed automatically so I have to kill it manually and now if I
restart from snapshot you will see it also it takes just a few milliseconds to restart
the whole image and again I can see where I enter it it works you see there is no the
hooks are not being called because there is no real crack implementation in the back in
this case but like checkpointing for Java itself works and it's also easy to run a second
clone now obviously we cannot run it in the same namespace because it will use the same
IP address like the first version so we started in a network namespace so minus and zero
is just to create a new namespace for the clone and you see it uses IP netns netnamespace
exec to execute firecracker but it restores quite as quickly and the initial IP address
of the process has now in this namespace it's now mapped on a different IP address on the
host but you see it's still working so in the guest the guest still has the same IP
address it has in the first place it's just running in its own namespace and inside the
guest again the the tomcat is running on the same port or no problem so we just kill the
first instance and we kill the second instance how much time do I have oh okay okay so just
a few words I I realized that talks which are rated the highest are usually saw some
animation so I decided to do animation because usually I only saw consoler console demos
so quick introduction user for demon is a is a possibility to handle page faults from
the user space and firecracker offers the possibility instead of mapping the image file
right into firecrackers memory to to use an external user for demon and if we write the
user for demon ourselves we have the possibility to follow page by page which addresses get
loaded at the restore and I found it interesting so I created that kind of thing so to an animation
for that and for that we we restart our our firecracker service native memory enabled
native memory tracking and from the guest we do now SSH into into our firecracker guest
where Tomcat is running and just call J command native memory details and and put that into
a file and we do the same thing with the PMAP information this is just a shell script inside
the guest which basically prints all the virtual to physical mappings for all processes into
a file and now we can start the visualizer and it takes the logs of the user for demon
and the native mapping so what you see here is basically the physical memory line of the
guest so it's memory page zero and in the end it's memory page one gigabyte and every
square is for kilobyte page and if you go and it's on the Java process for example you
see the dark these are the pages the RSS of the Java process blue ones are occupied by
the Java process but they are also in the page cache so that's probably a file for example
or something or class share class for example when you when you look at the NMT output we
see that for example for the classes we use about 66 I probably cannot read it it says
virtual is 69 megabytes RSS is 60 megabytes and user for demon loaded about 10 megabytes
of it and here's the animation I promised you so this is how the pages got loaded when
we did the first call request on a resumed image and like the yellow ones are all the
pages which is loaded and orange one no no yes some are orange belong to the to the to
the virtual memory region I have selected here so for example all the orange pages are
the parts of the class space which got loaded for the first request so this is a lot of
space for more investigation would be nice to to compact this more like physically because
you want to prefetch the things which get loaded especially if you download your images
from from network for example and but the problem is that all the physical address space
is continuous like the virtual the physical pages are not and try to look into a possibility
to do that so that that's it thank you
yes yeah
yes I unfortunately there is no time in 20 minutes to show that but you can obviously
use the current crack implementation inside firecracker use J command and instead of crew
there is a back end called the pause handler that's just a small program which instead
of calling crew just dispense the whole process and then you can send in the signal to restore
it so with firecracker you basically checkpoint with the pause engine then do the firecracker
snapshot then restore firecracker and then just do an SSH with the kill signal on the
process and it will will start it's one possibility another one is I wrote the JVMTI agent which
basically does the same thing even without Creole it it's a spence or so as it calls
system GC and then waits on a on a port so just ping it with telnet or whatsoever and
it even calls the the hooks by implementing this custom possibility to with the property
so I say or crack to use my crack implementation to call the hooks so that all works it's in
the in the repository which is I had a resource slide which I didn't show it has all the links
may