Just two classical optimizations that will help modern but mature virtual machine where
we have that powers native images.
Why is it important?
And who I am?
My name is Mitre Chukov.
I work with a company named Bellsoft which actively participates in open JDK community
and we release our own JDK distribution which you probably met if you have ever built a
Spring Boot container with default build pack.
So it's in there.
And now Spring Boot, since version 3, supports containers with native images.
It can be built as a native image and if you do that the compiler being used is the Barricot
native image kit which is a Bellsoft distribution of GraalVM.
So that's another project that we participate and GraalVM itself can be seen as different
things at least two major modes that we can observe.
It can run as a JIT where compiler is Graal or we can build a native image with a static
compilation and it will utilize a special chief virtual machine substrate VM.
And here it's different from the traditional Java, traditional way of how we run it.
Well another interesting and peculiar point here is that it is written in Java.
So it is a complex project but most of the code is Java and this is beautiful.
So you have a virtual machine and a compiler for JVM languages and Java in particular written
in Java.
So if you look at Java itself, why is it so beautiful?
Well not so beautiful compared to Kotlin as we know, right?
But still both Java and Kotlin they share those concepts.
So from the very beginning there is a way to write correct parallel programs.
So then to write parallel programs we need some means of synchronization or to orchestrate
our threads if we share data.
But most typically we do that.
And also it's a managed runtime where we don't have to worry that much about pre-memory because
we have garbage collection and garbage is collected for us and our programs just, they
can have memory but you have to work hard to get one.
And having that native image implementation makes our final binaries very sometimes, makes
them very performant.
Of course we have an instant startup.
It was mentioned today several times.
But we can also have a very good peak performance.
In certain cases that's not a rule but it can happen.
Like it happens here on this plot, that's just a simple Spring Boot application and
we just ping the same endpoint.
And here the native image works better and also it warms up instantly and it has very
good latency.
So for this small amount of memory that it takes, so this is a small service, it takes
small amount of memory, very small heap.
And it also has low latency.
And under the hood it uses serial GC and we'll talk about that later.
What about relationship between Graal VM and OpenJDK?
Well we're here in the Friends of OpenJDK room and Graal has been integrated as an additional
experimental compiler in JDK 9.
But well, it has been removed from recent JDKs.
But what's the left over?
It's an interface to plug it in.
So now it's going to be a second attempt to do that.
So here on slides it's mentioned that there is a discussion about project, new project
they all had.
But last week it was already called for votes in OpenJDK to start the project of bringing
the most sweet parts of this technology into OpenJDK, back into OpenJDK.
It's something that happens right now.
So that default garbage collector that sometimes shows very good latency even compared to parallel
GC or G1 in hotspot.
Well on small heaps.
Well it's a kind of garbage collector we can easily understand.
And it's a generational stop the world collection.
So here only one survivor space but actually it's 16 by default.
But anyway, so we stop all our application threads and we collect garbage in a single
thread.
So this is kind of a basic garbage collector right.
From the other hand it's reliable and it's very effective especially if we have only
a single core available.
So you see the problem.
We have some CPU which may be enough to run many threads but we run only one of them.
At least for garbage collection.
Garbage collection can take significant time during our application execution.
Well that's obvious.
Well what would we do?
Of course we would like to do exactly the same thing but in parallel.
To decrease the time garbage collection takes to reduce the garbage collection pause.
Because it still stops the world pause but we reduce it because we process data with
multiple threads.
So that's the idea of parallel garbage collection.
The idea is not new but surprisingly this modern runtime doesn't have it yet.
Well we decided to implement it and it's still being under review and some implementation
details well they change.
But the idea is very simple.
You just say pass the garbage collection selection during the creation of your native image.
For instance if you use some main or gradual configuration for your Spring Boot container
you also can do that.
And then you have some grips in runtime which you also can twist when you run your application.
And well you enable that implementation.
I'll show some performance results later.
But basically the implementation itself well it can be analyzed as a change in a big Java
program which Braavium is.
And there are now two GC interfaces and implementations.
And this functionality just reuse existing things in a very I would say smart way.
Just to keep what is all about the parallelization as a code.
So everything else is reused from serial GC.
Basically there's a problem of how do we synchronize and share the work because parallel threads
for garbage collection they also have the same problem because they work on the same
data so they have contention or may have contention.
So we need to share in some smart manner.
Well it's implemented with a work divided in its volume.
So every thread operates its local memory and it's a chunk of memory of one megabyte.
So if we need an extra memory like we scan objects and we fulfill some set of data that
we operate on.
And then we have an extra chunk we can just put it aside so someone else can pick it.
So that's the stack that contains the chunks of work.
And then the work is finished the thread just takes next chunk of work.
There may be a situation when threads similar several threads try to copy to promote the same object.
And this is actually solved very simply.
They just reserve some space for the object and then tries to install forward pointer
using an atomic operation.
And as this is an atomic operation only one thread succeeds so others just roll back and
this is lightweight operation.
Again this is Java this is not a strict email sorry but still all existing places that manage
memory were reused without changing the architecture of Gralys so.
There are already possibility to add garbage collectors so if you want to implement one
it's not that complex.
The major problem is to be correct then you deal with memory then you deal with concurrency
and then you inject your code into this virtual machine because it's all declarative magic
that requires you to be careful.
Well some performance results with relatively large heaps with serial GC you can have pauses
of several seconds which is long of course.
And there's a big difference if you have a two or three or four second pause or if you
decrease it by one second.
So that's possible that this implementation already.
So that's the order of this improvement.
With another benchmark is Hyper-Alog you see that latency here latency of pauses can be
decreased like two times.
Those pauses are not that big and we have frequent collections here so X axis is apple
so each point is a garbage collection and Y axis is time in I believe milliseconds.
Well that's parallel GC.
So we can obviously improve many applications and many installations where we have an option
to use several CPUs.
If you use one CPU of course we won't see much difference.
There is some increase in memory used for service needs but that's kind of moderate.
So other parts of this complex system.
I mentioned synchronization and well synchronization is useful but it has trade-offs because if
we implement the non-synchronization we need to save our CPU resources to put aside threads
that won't get the resource.
We need to stop them to queue them to manage that queues to wake them up to involve operating
system in that process.
So that's not cheap.
But there are situations that that's another queue right and that even influences the design
of standard library because like we all know string buffer and string builder right.
One class appeared because well another one wasn't very pleasant in terms of performance.
Yeah we need it sometimes but in many cases we need a non-synchronized implementation
saying like hash table and hash map whoever uses hash table right.
But it's very good synchronized.
But not all classes that have any synchronization in them have their twins without synchronization.
That makes no sense right.
So there's a well-known technology how to deal with the case where accesses to our data
structures to our classes are mostly sequential than at any point in time only a single thread
owns and operates with an object.
Let's call bias logging or thin logging.
Well why is it simpler and more lightweight?
Because we don't want to manage all the complex cases.
We know that we are in a good situation and if not yes we can fall back and it's called
inflate our monitor.
Well it existed in OpenJDK for ages and it has been removed from OpenJDK.
First deprecated then no one noticed I believe because still are there too many people using
something newer than JDK11.
Well some consequences were noticed probably too late.
Well what are the reasons first of all what are the reasons to remove bias logging from
OpenJDK from hotspot JVM?
Well to ease the implementation of virtual threads to deliver project loom to decrease
the amount of work there.
So some consequences here an issue is discovered.
In certain cases things like input streams can be slowed down like here it's 8x or something
that's enormously slow.
And for growl VM there is a mode that you say during static compilation.
Okay this native image doesn't try to work with many cores it's a single threaded program.
So it's simple and it works really better in these circumstances.
So there is an optimization for that.
But you have to know it in advance then you compile your program.
Well and there is of course a runtime option that supports all kinds of situations and
it's complex.
So the missing part is in the left lower corner well to dynamically be able to process the
situation of sequential access pattern.
So we implemented quite a classical approach to this problem that helps to that brings
that thin locking to growl VM.
The initial idea was operating with object header so where it already contains a pointer
to a fat monitor object.
But it can be treated as well as some words we can atomically access and put some information
there.
Probably close to final implementation that we have right now still or again uses a point
or because it turned to be not so easy to keep correctness across the whole VM with
some memory that you treat as a point or as a word depending on the situation.
Well anyway inside that part of header or inside that special object we can have 64
bits of information.
And we can mark it as a thin lock this is a flag right then we can do it atomically.
We can keep the ID of an owner thread which we can obtain then the work the threads and
a count of recursive locks that we currently hold.
That by the way means that after a certain amount of recursive locks we have to inflate
monitor because we can store more information in that part of this work.
So again it's a pure Java implementation where we work with some atomic magic and we update
this information.
But what we've got and the most recent numbers are even better.
So we see that effect on exactly that example the streams.
We can speed them up and even in a very kind of nano benchmark kind of measurement you
also see the improvement and even in multi-threaded case there is no difference with the original.