Hello, everyone. Good afternoon. I am Thanos from the University of Manchester. And today
I have the pleasure to present you Tornado VM, what is the state of Tornado VM at this
moment. And in fact, I want to focus also on a slogan that's very known to everyone.
The right ones run anywhere for Java. So we'll start with that. So this is a known slogan
derived since the 90s from microsystems in a way to advertise that Java language and
the JVM in particular, it is a platform that can ensure portability across different CPU
structures and architectures. So the idea is that programmers can run their code, they
can compile it once, and it can run transparently on different hardware architectures. However,
hardware has changed in the last years. It is evolving. And perhaps this is not sufficient
for the new types of hardware resources that are coming. So lately we have GPUs and FPGAs
which are coming to complement the power of the CPUs in a way to maximize performance
and reduce the energy consumption. These are good, but there is some challenges that are
deriving and these are mainly posed in programmability. So how programmers can harness this power
from these resources. I don't know if you have experience with OpenCL and CUDA, but
mainly these programming models that have been designed for these hardware types to
get access to these hardware types, they are mainly focused on the C and C++ world. So
there are different programming models from different companies like SQL, OneAPI, NVIDIA
CUDA, OpenCL, which is a standard that can run on all the devices. And if you have FPGA
expertise, then perhaps you can write RTL and Verilog, which is a hardware description
language. But this is very low level. And here we are talking about Java, so we want
to go high level. So if you are a Java developer, then you use the JVM and you go to the CPU.
If you want to have access to these devices, then you need to write your own native interfaces
in the JNI and then tap into the C and C++ world. But still, you need to be aware of
how these programming models are written. So you need to be familiar with this. And
this is exactly the problem that Tornado VM has been designed to solve. So Tornado VM,
it is a plugin to existing OpenJDK distributions like Amazon, and others. And the way that
it is built, it is to enable hardware acceleration in an easy manner. So it offers a Java API.
And it has inside a JIT compiler for the hardware devices that I saw in this figure. Our compiler
inside, it can automatically translate the Java bytecodes to run on CPUs, multi code
CPUs, GPUs integrated or discrete GPUs and FPGAs. And the compiler in the backend, it
has three different backend types. It can emit OpenCLC, PTX, which is assembly for the
CUDA for the NVIDIA GPUs. And it has recently also the SPIRV backend, which enables to utilize
the level zero dispatcher from the one API. So Tornado VM, it is a technology that can
be used as a JVM plugin to enable hardware acceleration for JVMs. And some of the key
features is that it has a lightweight Java API. It is coded in a platform agnostic manner.
So one command can be the same no matter which device it will be executed to program. And
it can transparently at the compile time specialize the code. Because the code that is generated
for the GPU, it is completely different from a code that is generated for an FPGA. So regarding
the compiler, we have different phases that will be enabled for GPUs and different phases
that will be enabled to specialize the code for an FPGA. Our code is available in GitHub.
So we encourage everyone who wants to have a look to fork it, download, play with examples,
or even create their own examples. And also to come back to us, I mean, to feel free to
use the discussions to trigger the discussion if you have questions or to open issues if
something is broken in order to fix it. And we have also available Docker images for NVIDIA
GPUs and Intel integrated GPUs. Now the next part that I want to talk is regarding the
API. Two weeks ago, we released a new version of Tornado VM, the version 0.15. And this
comes with many new changes in the API level. So our goal was to make the API easier for
Java programmers in order to use it in a comprehensive manner. So to know how to use and how to express
parallelism from Java. But first, I have to make you familiar with the programming model
of Tornado VM. And this programming model comes, it is inspired from the heterogeneous
programming models like OpenCL and CUDA, the way that these programming models are operating.
And in this sense, a Java program can be composed of two parts. The first part is the host code
where it is the actual core of the Java application. And the second part, it is the accelerated
code which actually it is the method or the set of methods that will be offloaded for
execution on a GPU. Once we have made this clear, then we can move with the execution
model which it requires first because the processing will take place on a device, it
will have first to move the data from the host code from the CPU to the actual device.
Then perform the processing. And once the processing is finished, then the data, the
result will have to be transferred back to the host code. Now in Tornado VM, in the API
of Tornado VM, we have exposed the set of objects and annotations for each of these
two parts, the host code and the accelerated code. In the host code, we have the task graph
object and the Tornado execution plan. The task graph corresponds to what to run on a
GPU. And the Tornado execution plan, it is how to run on the GPU. And for the accelerated
code, we have a set of annotations and objects that I will show you later. So let's start
with the task graph. What to run? Assuming that you are a Java programmer, then you want
to offload the execution of a method. In this example, method A to the GPU. This method
has some input and some output. Now this method corresponds to what in the Tornado VM terminology
call a task. So each method that will be offloaded for execution on hardware acceleration, it
is a task. And it has the input data and the output data. And then we have a group of tasks
which is the task graph. Now task graph can be a group of tasks that may have dependency
or may not have dependency. And the programmers, they want to offload them all for hardware
acceleration. In this particular example, I have put one task in this task graph. Once
we have defined what to run, one question that comes, it is how often to transfer the
data between the host, CPU and the device. And this can have a tremendous impact because
it can affect the data transfer time. So it can have a long execution time. So it can
affect performance. But can also affect energy. The power consumption. So how to transfer
data, it matters. It depends on the pattern of the application. So one application may
need to copy only the first execution if the data are read only. Then always or only in
the last execution, for example, for the output, for the result. And here is a code snippet
of how the task graph can be used to define this functionality in the Tornado API. So
we create a new object, the task graph. We assign a name, which is a string. In this
particular example, it is TG. And then we utilize the exposed methods of the API in
order to fulfill the execution model. At first, we use the transfer to device which has two
inputs. The first argument that we put, it is a data transfer mode which will be used
to trigger how often the data will be moved. In this particular example, it is first execution
shown in the first execution, the data will be moved. And then we'll have the parameter
which is the input, which is the input array. The second method, it is the task and it defines
which method will be used for hardware acceleration. The first parameter, it is a name, a string
actually of the method. It could be any name. And this is associated for the dynamic configuration
which I will show you later. The second parameter, it is the method reference. So the reference
to the method that will be offloaded to the GPU for acceleration. And then it is the list
of parameters of this method that corresponds to the method signature. And the last method,
it is the transfer to host. And this, again, this method, it is configured the first argument
to be the data transfer mode. In this example, we will copy the data, the output in every
execution. Okay. And once we have defined the task through the task graph, this task
can be appended, can be updated. We can add a new task, a second task. We can change the
way that the data transfer will be triggered in every execution only in the first execution.
Then the next step, it is to define the immutable state of the task graph. So how to preserve
the shape of a task graph. And this is done by taking a snapshot of the task graph, by
using the snapshot method in the task graph object. Then we retrieve back an immutable
task graph. And this means that this can be used for JIT compilation and execution on
the hardware. And this ensures that the Java programmers, they can create different versions
of their task graph. They can update it. And then the code that will have Internet of VM,
it can store all these versions. It doesn't need to recompile and override the generated
code. And this is the final step before we move to the actual execution plan. We have
the mutable state of the task graph that can be modified and the immutable task graph that
it cannot be modified anymore. So if the users, they want to do a change, they can still change
the task graph and get a new snapshot for a second version of their code. And now we
move to how to run, how to execute the task graph. And this is done through the execution
plan. Here is a snippet of a tornado execution plan. We create a new object that accepts
as input the mutable task graph. That doesn't change anymore. And then we can either directly
execute it in the default execution mode by invoking the execution plan.execute method
or we can configure it with some various optimizations. In this particular example, I have enabled
the configuration to run with dynamic reconfiguration, which is a feature in tornado VM that will
launch a Java thread to get compiled and execute the application per device that is available
on the system. So we can have a CPU, a GPU, an FPGA. Java thread will run for all the
devices. And then it is triggered with a policy of performance, which means that the first
device that will finish the execution, it will be the best. And the rest, Java threads
will be killed. Now I have concluded the part of the host code. We can briefly go to the
accelerated code, which is the way to express parallelism within the kernel, within the
method or the tornado VM task, as we call it. We have two ways, two APIs. The first
one is called loop parallel API. And in a sense, we expose the add parallel annotations
that can be used by programmers to as a hint to the tornado VM compiler that these loops
can run in parallel. And the second one is the kernel API, which is an API exposed to
the users through the kernel context object. And in a sense, the meaning of this API, it
is meant for open CL and programmers or Java programmers who know open CL in a way to get
more freedom on how to code things so they can get access to local memory, which is equivalent
to the memory of the CPU for GPUs. So they have more freedom on what to express. And
in fact, I have used this API to port existing kernels written in open CL and CUDA to Java.
For more information, you can use this link, which is the actual documentation of tornado
VM and describes some examples. I will briefly go to one example of a matrix multiplication,
which I presented last year in force them. So in this example, we have the accelerated
code and the host code. The matrix multiplication method implements matrix multiplication over
a flattened arrays in two dimensions. And the way to annotate and express parallelism
using the add parallel annotation, it would be to add the add parallel annotation inside
the four loops. That means that we indicate that these loops could be executed in parallel.
And now regarding the second API, the kernel API, we would use the kernel context object.
And in particular, we would use the global ID, X and Y, which correspond to the two dimensions
that we have. So in a sense, it is like having the thread ID that will execute on the GPU.
Here are some use cases that we used tornado VM. And concluding this talk, I would like
to focus on a feature that we implemented in a project that we are working. It is called
Elegant and the idea is to create a software stack that unifies development for big data
and IOT deployment. And there, tornado VM is used as a technology to enable acceleration
as a service. So we have implemented the REST API. It is still a prototype. But the programmers,
they can write a method, they can specify a method, they can specify the characteristics
of the targeted device. And then the service will return back open CL code that it is meant
to run parallel this function. The interesting part is that this code, the open CL code,
it is generated to be portable across different programming languages. So it doesn't only
bind to Java, it can run also through C++, Python, because it is open CL. And this means
that in this particular example, we have Java, we use OpenJDK, we take the byte code and
we pass the byte code to tornado VM. And tornado VM is running on an experimental feature which
is called code interoperability mode. And in this mode, it converts this byte code to
open CL that can run from any programming language and run time. Therefore, it is like
prototyping in Java for parallel programming. Wrapping up, we would like to receive feedback
and we are looking also for collaborations if we can help to port and use cases or for
any other issues. And summarizing this talk, I briefly went through the right ones run
anywhere in the context of heterogeneous hardware acceleration. I have familiarized you with
tornado VM, which is an open source project. And the code base is available in GitHub.
And familiarize you with the programming model of tornado VM and the new API, how to use
it. And more are about to come in the FUJ blog with a new blog. So, finally, just to
acknowledge the projects that they have supported our research in the University of Manchester
and I'm ready for questions.