Okay, continuing with the migration topic. There is a relatively new tool called Open
Rewrite and you're going to hear all about it from Tim.
Yeah, hi. So it's been mentioned a few times before so I hope I can live up to the hype.
My name is Tim Tobeyk and I'm a staff software engineer at Moderna. But I recently started,
just the start of this month. And before that I was a migration engineer as a consultant
for five years. So what that means is I would walk into organizations familiarize myself
with all the old technologies that they were still using and then hack away at lifting
all those services up to the latest versions of Java and Spring. I would frequently find
versions that have five to ten year old versions of Java or JUnit or Spring which is not ideal
from either a security perspective or even a developer experience point of view.
Initially I would migrate these services by hand. I would gradually introduce more and
more forced automations. But then at the end of last year of the early last year I discovered
OpenRewrite. And OpenRewrite is a tool that promises to make life work of all such migrations.
I got so excited by this technology that I started to contribute and even present about
this on conferences and then eventually quit my job to work on OpenRewrite full time. So
after a nice sabbatical that brings us here today. Perhaps you faced some of the same
challenges that I did at a conference like this. You will hear all about new framework
and language features. Yeah, back at work you are stuck using Java 8 and JUnit 4. And
migrating all of that by hand can seem daunting if it ever gets priority. I want to show you
how easy it can be to perform major migrations. That way you too can adopt all the latest
language and framework features. And it can be fun to adopt new language features such
as records and text blocks. But you don't want to adopt these features manually or only
on a single project. Instead we will look into automation to make all projects feel
like new again. So you can benefit from JGM language and framework improvements.
Here is a very brief overview of the types of migrations I will be talking about. Likely
you already performed some of these migrations in the past. And other migrations are always
just around the corner. If you look back over time there is a near constant stream of worthwhile
improvements to percolate. And I like the challenge. I still get excited whenever a
new version comes out. I just don't like the repetitive elements that come with upgrading.
And if you try to keep up my hand you will hardly get anything else done. Especially
as microservices these days mean you are not just upgrading once but dozens of times. Automation
may then be the only option. Especially for companies using thousands of services.
To open rewrite you can now migrate between versions of Java and Spring with a simple
command. You can even migrate between frameworks such as from JUnit to the search A and from
Java EE to Spring. In this talk I will tell you all about OpenRear, how it came about,
how it works and what you can do with it. And finally we will briefly look at who is
developing these recipes and how to apply them to open source projects.
OpenRear was developed at Netflix initially to aid in the migration of an internal login
framework to SLF4J. You can probably imagine that any login framework is going to be pervasive
throughout an organization. To even consider migrating you need perfectly accurate automation.
So they, especially when usage is spread across hundreds of services, so they develop a parser
to accurately read Java and turn the source code into a lossless semantic tree. This model
can then be modified to replace the old learning statements with calls to SLF4J.
Next the migrated model is written out as close as possible to the original source code.
That way the applied changes are minimal, leaving surrounding codes untouched.
Later the same developers moved on to work on Spinnaker and while trying to onboard teams
and organizations there, they found that teams often struggled with the same outdated languages
and frameworks. To help teams adopt the latest versions, they applied a different set of
migration recipes through the same lossless semantic tree parser. This allowed them to
quickly reduce this technical depth and bring teams from Springb
one to Springb two and from JU4 to JU5. The project has since been open source with the
company behind it committed to making all recipes available on the Apache license for
open source software. The initial focus for open rewrite is on the Java virtual machine
languages and surrounding technologies. There are parses for instance for Java, Groovy,
Gummel and XML and these in turn unlock support for built-in such as Maven and Gradle and
libraries such as JUnit, AssurJ and Guava. Ultimately refactoring entire frameworks and
platforms is supported with recipes available for application frames such as Micronaut,
Barkis and Springb. Open rewrite is not the only parser capable of understanding and manipulating
Java. However, three features set open rewrite apart from the competition. The first is to
focus on exact type attribution. By having the exact type available on any tree element,
we can be sure to only manipulate exact matches. The second characteristics that sets open
rewrite apart is the form of precipitation. The parser not only takes into account the
functional code but also the surrounding code style and implementation. This allows us to
accurately reproduce your source code regardless of further changes. Changes made through open
rewrite look just like a colleague worked on your code. And finally, the stabilization
format ensures you're able to query and refactor your code faster and at scale. Together these
features make open rewrite exceptionally good at safe code transformations especially as
the changes are minimally invasive and guaranteed to work in farther than due to the do-no-harm
mentality. By manipulating the full lossless semantic tree, open rewrite can far exceed
simple search and replace operations. With the full lossless semantic tree built, we
need to instruct open rewrite what operations to apply and where in your code. Recipes are
how you define such a group of search and refactoring operations. Together they accomplish
a higher level task such as framework migration. Recipes can persist of a single standalone
operation or be linked together with other recipes. Open rewrite comes with a large collection
of fine-grained recipes out of the box that can be combined for common migration steps.
You can think of these as LEGO building blocks ready to be applied with the proper parameters.
There are hundreds of these building blocks to, for instance, change types, change methods,
change arguments, manipulate properties and alter dependencies and plug-ins. Individual
recipes are implemented as Java visitors that first match and then modify elements of the
lossless semantic tree. There are plenty of examples available but notice that you only
need a dedicated Java visitor but none of the existing recipes can already achieve your
goals. Typically you can get very far, only combining, configuring, combining, applying
existing recipes through a YAML description form. Modules then group together these fine-grained
recipes into more coarse-grained application-specific recipes. There are modules, for example, for
loading frameworks, testing frameworks and application frameworks such as Spring. Think
of these as LEGO sets with built plans for common migrations ready to be applied. In
my opinion, the lossless semantic tree combined with a large collection of fine-grained recipes
is what sets OpenRide apart from other similar tools such as error problems we fastened.
I want to show you how migration recipes are configured in OpenRide. Let's briefly look
at a migration from JUnit 4 to JUnit 5. I want you to imagine the steps of what we needed
to such a migration. You've likely applied some of those steps already in the path. Among
others you'd have to update the test annotations. But you would also have to update the assertions
and sometimes the argument order. You'd have to update all imports and update any test
rules and that's just getting started. Notice how each of these steps is reflected as a
separate recipe in this JAML configuration form. Some refer to and configure the NERIC
step, such as the change type recipe. Others are implemented as an imperative step, a dedicated
Java visitor that changes the lossless semantic tree. All these steps combine to achieve a
typical key JUnit 5 migration. This is a common pattern with OpenRide. Large migrations are
broken up into small, reusable steps. When we run this recipe we get predictable results.
Our imports are replaced as we would expect and our Makito runner is replaced into using
the extension. Lifecycle annotations such as that before are correctly replaced. But
interestingly we can see how OpenRide shines through when it comes to converting expected
exceptions. Having the full power of a lossless semantic tree combined with a Java visitor
allows us to adopt a search phrase. It's these types of changes that would not be possible
with a regular expression approach. Running migration recipes is fairly straightforward.
First you apply a build tool plugin for OpenRide. I've used Maven in my example but Gradle works
just as well. Then depending on the changes you want to make you add a dependency on the
respective OpenRide module. Lastly you run the OpenRide plugin with the migration recipe
that you want to execute. The command scene here will migrate an application from Spring Boot
1.5 to the latest Spring Boot 2.7 branch. And we're also working on a 3.0 migration.
And this migration works all the way back to Spring Boot 1.5. It will update dependencies,
properties and deprecations from any older versions. And it includes the JUnit 5 migration
we've seen before. As well as any Spring specific test constructs.
So now that we've seen how OpenRide works, let's have a look at what you can do with
it. Obviously by now we've seen it is well suited to migrations. You've mostly seen migrations
from one version to another. But you can also migrate from one framework to another. If
you want to switch from LagerJ to Ocelot4J you can. And the same thing if you want to
switch between JUnit and AssertJ. And even larger migrations are in development.
Another application is fixing static analysis findings. A large collection of check style,
sonar and security findings are supported to allow you to reduce your technical debt
in minutes. And finally there's a whole class of recipes to enforce a code style. And rather
than merely apply a formatter, these style recipes go a step further to actually change
your code. And this ensures your code style is consistently from project to project. And
in addition to what's already available, it's fairly easy to add custom migration recipes
specific to your project. So now that we've seen how it works and what
you can do with it, let's briefly look ahead at what is still to come. As you've seen,
Kotlin remote has dedicated parses for multiple languages already. But we have some catching
up to do still. We are working on a parser for both Java 18 and up and Kotlin. But note
that you're perfectly able to run on Java 17. But you cannot yet migrate to some of
the new language features. The interesting thing about Kotlin is going to be that the
Java migration recipes that we have will also just work even though the languages look very
different. Another subject we're working on is data flow analysis. And this not only takes
into account the individual code statements, but also how data flows throughout your application.
This will allow recipes to, for instance, add immutability or dedicate to security fixes.
Another interesting development is the Spring Boot Margarit project from VMware. It builds
upon OpenVRide to migrate projects towards Spring for mother frameworks. It takes a slightly
different, more interactive approach, which will be a coming handy one when it comes to
the Spring Boot 3 migration. All these features are in active development. It's not yet clear
when you can use this in a production setting, but it's interesting developments nonetheless.
As a last subject, I want to tell you a bit about the content behind OpenVRide. As I said
before, Moderna has committed to making all recipes available open source. Our focus is
on applying recipes at scale. Through Moderna, clients can discover code patterns across
an entire organization and target these for transformation. And even if you're not a paying
customer, you can still use the web interface to browse available recipes and even apply
them to open source projects. This can be a great way to start contributing back to open
source software. And if you find any of the migration steps are missing, OpenVRide itself
is very accepting of new contributions. The community plays a large role in the development
of new recipes. Now, as you could probably tell from my email address, we're not exactly
a big company, but we're pretty well connected in the broader Java community. Through collaborations,
other companies contribute migration recipes for their own works. And this ensures their
users are able to migrate easily and timely between the releases. And if you maintain
or merely enjoy a particular library or framework, you can help other users by providing migration
recipes. So with that, we are getting near the end of my presentation. Before I think
I can join away, I want to recommend a few resources where you can learn more. There's
extensive documentation available on OpenVRide. Development is all on GitHub with new suggestions
typically picked up with surprising speed. And as you've already seen, it's quite easy
to contribute minor migration steps. If you want to try some recipes quickly on open source
software, have a look at public.moderno.io. And if you have any questions, you can reach
out on our public slide or via email. And finally, if you would like to play around
with the commands you've seen before, I've written a blog post to accompany this presentation.
This blog post migrates an old Spring path clinic branch from Spring Boot 1.5 to Spring
Boot 2.8 to Spring Boot 2.x on Java 17. That way you can play around with the commands
and see the changes made every step. For your own projects, I recommend you start with the
testing framework migration. They're an easy way to gain confidence in the tool and see
what it can do for your projects. And with that, I'd like to thank you for your attention.
It's also really great about Tim's story is that he was enthusiastic about a project.
He started contributing to it and now he was offered a job and he's working at the company
behind this project. It's really the textbook story of starting, contributing, and then
getting paid to do that and joining the company behind the project. So thank you very much.