Thanks to be here. Thanks for missing your lunch.
And let me rant about Kotlin. I'm Nicolas Frankel.
I've been a developer for like now more than 20 years.
Perhaps I'm not a developer anymore.
I'm a developer advocate, but I still see myself as a developer.
I love developing. Right now I work on the Apache
API 6 gateway. It has nothing to do with Java.
It's just an infrastructure component.
But since they allow me to be here, here is the slide.
Anyway, why am I talking about Kotlin in a Java room?
Well, they didn't want me to talk about Kotlin in the Kotlin room.
So that might be one of the reasons.
And also I've mentioned I have like two decades of coding experience.
And those two decades were spent in Java.
So I started with Java 1.3, perhaps.
And well, there were like big wins and small losses.
And I tried Scala. And I didn't like it at all.
I still have the certificates saying, hey, you are like Scala certified.
I didn't like it for multiple reasons.
Then I went to a couple of conferences.
I had a friend. And she made also talks about Kotlin.
And I said, we don't need Kotlin. We have Java. It's enough.
Then I wanted to teach myself Android development.
And Android development at the time was only in Java.
And the API was super low level.
And I said, no, I cannot write such like code that it brings me back 15 years ago
when I was writing Java on the server side.
And I looked for solutions and I found Kotlin.
And I thought, wow, that's cool.
And I stopped learning Android. And now I write Kotlin on the backend.
So just a disclaimer.
If Java is the best language in the world for you, just leave the room.
I'm not trying to bash Java. But depending on your culture,
I'm pretty straightforward. You might feel offended.
So better leave now. It's up to you.
Okay. Let's start slow.
Immutable references. I'm telling you, hey, it's better in Kotlin.
And you can tell me, hey, Java has it. Right?
Immutable references.
Okay. Let's try to check how it works.
Immutable references in Java. Oh, fun stuff.
Immutable references in Java.
So here, this is my immutable reference class.
So I have to put final here.
I have to put final here. And I have to put final here.
Now I have immutable references.
Who puts final everywhere?
A couple of people.
No, really.
We had this idea 15 years ago.
And then we decided, no, it just makes the reading so much harder.
So perhaps not.
Even worse, if you don't put final on the parameter,
you can actually relocate stuff,
which I believe is one of the worst things you can do.
Like, really, really, really bad.
So I'm not saying that Java doesn't have it,
but I'm saying that in Kotlin, it's from the beginning,
you need to decide whether it's a var,
which means it cannot be reassigned,
or it's a var, which means it can be reassigned.
If you are using IntelliJ, I don't know about Eclipse or NetBeans.
The good thing is that if I say it's a var,
so it can be reassigned, it tells me, hey, like,
there is something fishy.
It's not an error per se, but at least it's visually pleasing.
And, of course, by default,
for who don't know, any is the equivalent of object,
so it's not very important.
I could write object.
By default, you cannot reassign parameters.
Any language that allows you to reassign parameters
should be taken with, like, utmost caution.
It's actually not a great design ID.
So, of course, Java was designed a long time ago,
doesn't have it, but Kotlin takes the lesson.
And if you think that vol and var are coming from Scala
because you are a Scala fanboy,
that's completely true.
Kotlin has stolen every good ID.
So don't pretend otherwise.
That's fine.
Okay.
Second, immutable classes.
Well, that's fine. Now we have Java records.
We've got them.
That's fine.
Let's continue.
Null safety.
Null safety in Java is not that fun, right?
How many ways do you have to implement null safeties in Java?
That's a good thing.
Ah, yeah, that's a good thing.
Diversity is a good thing because we work in IT.
And if you want to really, like, have fun,
you might check, like, nullable, nullable, nullable,
nullable, nullable, nullable, nullable, nullable,
oh, not null, no, no, no, no, no.
Well, I'm sorry, sorry?
Not capitalized under the first node.
Yeah, exactly.
I'm not sure it's an error.
I think I just copy-pasted, so I'm not sure.
Yeah, that's really fun stuff.
And, of course, they won't work with one another.
So you need to have the preprocessor.
Sorry, you need to have the compile-time processor,
and you need to choose which library you will be using.
And then you hope that somehow it will work.
Dukes, in Kotlin, what do we have?
Well, it's baked into language.
So basically, here I was too lazy to write it in Java,
but basically, if you write something in Kotlin,
you have additional types.
So basically, for every, like, normal type,
this is a nullable type, and this says
it's a nullable type.
It means that if you are calling something
on a non-nullable type, you can call whatever you want,
plus whatever.
And if you call something on a nullable type,
Kotlin will say, oh, it was saying something,
and now it doesn't say it.
Yes, because plus is smart.
Plus knows how to operate on nullable types.
But let's do something that is not safe,
which is, it's also very smart.
The library is too smart for me.
Yeah, empty.
Reversed?
Yeah, finally, thanks.
And it tells you, hey, you know, this might be nullable,
so please don't call it like this,
because there is a chance you might encounter a null pointer
at runtime, and yeah, you should take care.
And well, afterwards it's quite easy.
You can do this stuff.
I mean, if you have been doing Groovy,
or I think Scala does it too, but the compiler tells you,
you should be careful about this.
And again, it's backed into the language,
so for every type, there are two real types,
one that might be nullable, the other might not be nullable.
The good thing with, I will show you
after where a section function, you can write extension function
that work on nullable type, which is really, really crazy.
Good.
So second stuff, better.
The utils classes.
Who has not written a single unit utils classes in their life?
Nobody.
So even people younger than 30 have written them.
In general, there might be a divide,
because all the developers have written them,
the younger ones, they are smart enough to use the library,
but the thing is, well, at our age there was no library.
So basically, we say that Java is an object-oriented language,
and then we put everything in a class,
we put static methods in the class,
and we pretend that it's object-oriented.
Right?
Yes.
Well, let's not pretend it's object-oriented.
If it's no object, a static class with static methods
is not object-oriented.
So here, I have created my amazing string utils class,
and of course, I need to remember,
because the users of my class, well, they might instantiate it,
so I will just remove the constructor,
make it private, again, very object-oriented,
and then I create this capitalize stuff,
and I do whatever I want,
and then I can call the capitalize method.
Good.
Scala and Kotlin have, I think, like, similar stuff.
Let's not pretend we are an object-oriented language.
We can just add methods, end states,
but mostly methods, on existing classes.
That's crazy.
Yeah.
Of course, at the bytecode level,
it boils down to a static method.
That's not the problem.
The problem is the user experience,
is the developer experience.
We can see now that we are really doing here,
we actually are doing object-oriented development.
So through this functional stuff,
because here we create a function
that is at the root level,
we are able to write better object-oriented code,
which is mind-blowing.
Even better, as I mentioned,
we can say, hey, this only applies,
so here we can have var f of type string might be null,
so this is a nullable type,
and here we cannot say f dot capitalize,
because it's null, right?
It's a nullable type.
Here it only applies to real strings,
but we can do something like this.
We can say, hey, it might be a nullable type,
and we can check if this equals null,
then we return the default, which might be an empty string.
Yeah, I see like, what the hell?
Static, yeah.
And in the end, that's a static method,
but how you call it is like object-oriented,
which, in my opinion, makes like Kotlin
much more object-oriented than Java will ever be.
Well, will ever be, no, I'm not sure.
Let's see what we have in the future.
So that's already good stuff.
And then, oof, ray fight generics, right?
Who has been bitten by the lack of ray fight generics already?
Yeah, yeah.
So I have a collection of thingy and a collection of foo,
and, well, at runtime you have nothing.
So here, the trick when you do Java is to pass the class.
So here is taken from Spring.
And when you get a bin, you say, hey, I want a bin of class
whatever, and then you will get the whatever.
OK?
How can we do it in Kotlin?
Kotlin has this ray fight.
So when you call a get bin, you can pass the type that you want,
and it will get you, but it's a string.
If we are a bit like tricky, we can do this,
and it's a list of string.
And if you tell it, because it's all about compiling,
because in the end, of course, the byte code is still the same.
The byte code must be compatible with Java byte code.
There is no ray fight generic in the byte code.
So it's just about compiling.
And here we can say, either we set it here in the signature
when we call it, or we tell that S is of type string,
and we will get a string.
And I think that's pretty amazing.
The only thing that we need to do is do this.
We need to tell it's ray fight.
Sorry.
Again, we need to tell it's ray fight,
and for ray fight, you need to have inline.
Why?
Because as I mentioned, there is no trick.
At compile time, it will actually replace the code.
It won't be a code.
It will be just copy-pasted.
And so it knows which type you are.
And in the end, so I still have a bit of time,
we can do like really, really fun stuff.
I will.
Yes.
Yes, fun stuff.
OK, I will create a function beans,
and for the moment, I will return any.
OK?
So some syntactic sugar, I don't think it's really important.
I don't think it makes me want to use Kotlin.
It's just easier to use it.
Like either you return the type like this,
or here any idiot can understand it returns any.
So the Kotlin compiler is not an idiot,
but Java compiler is.
On one liner, it doesn't make any sense to specify the type
explicitly every time, but still the Java compiler
requires you to do it.
Makes no sense.
OK.
But you're still allowed to.
You can still.
Sure, sure.
If for whatever reason, if for whatever reason,
you want to specify what it is, because it might be complex,
but then if it's complex, perhaps it doesn't belong to one
liner, then you can still add a lot of code.
And if it's a liner, then you can still load too.
Especially if you return a concrete implementation,
and you want your signature to be an interface.
That's perfect.
OK.
And now I will have a class, which I will call,
let's say, binsDSL.
OK.
Here I want this to return binsDSL.
So now I can write something like this.
I can have a main function.
Main.
OK.
private static void main.
And I can call the bins function.
Bins function.
Great.
Nothing mind-blowing.
Now what I can do is I want to write something like this.
OK.
So I want to write something like this.
I will just use the compiler.
OK.
So I create, here I accept a parameter that takes nothing
and returns unit.
Here what I can do is normally I would write something
like this, but in Kotlin, if the last argument is a lambda,
you can move it outside the parenthesis.
So that's what I did before.
And then here, if there is no arguments and there is a lambda,
I can remove the parenthesis.
Good.
Now I can add the bin method inside.
And I can say that I can actually call the bin method on
the bin DSL.
So here I can do something like this.
And what is it telling me in resolve method bins?
So I still have an issue.
Yes.
Up.
Little trick.
Yeah.
Sorry.
That's life coding completely.
I thought I would be less fast.
OK.
And now we can say that the bin method is generic.
Right?
So we can say it accepts a type T.
And I don't remember how it's written,
so I will be doing my stupid stuff.
Inline function.
So here, inline fun.
Reify T.
Here, and it returns a T.
And if you continue like this, you can have this kind of stuff.
So here, this is the spring boots, Kotlin DSL.
So you say this will create bins.
Each bin you can define either through a lambda or directly.
And through the reified stuff, here,
you see the product handler actually requires two dependencies.
And at compile time, it knows that it requires,
I don't know, a foo and a bar.
So because those ref methods are reified for generics,
it knows it needs to call the ref method calling,
getting a foo and a bar.
And it will inject them.
So here, you have the magic at compile time,
and at runtime, it's the usual spring boots stuff.
And I believe it makes my code much easier to read.
Of course, you need to understand the trick.
It's like every time.
You need to be very explicit in the beginning,
because you like a lot of context.
When you have the context, then it
makes your stuff much, much easier.
And that's all.
I don't want to bore you with more details.
You can follow me on Twitter.
You can follow me on Masterdom, because, well, you
don't know what will happen to Twitter.
And although the talk was not about Apache API 6,
you can check Apache API 6, which makes my job so much easier.
And I can come back here to talk about unrelated stuff.
Is there any time for questions?
There is.
Thank you.