Thanks for joining during your lunch.
I have some pie for you, some raspberry pies with a little bit of Java coffee.
So let's jump in.
Normally there was a session planned now about Kotlin, so I have a little piece of Kotlin
in this presentation.
I'm not a Kotlin developer myself.
What is the raspberry pie if you don't know it?
This amazing small board.
It's really small.
This is the raspberry pie zero.
And yes, indeed, that's 15 euros.
This is a full PC, a full Linux PC where you can run on Java, Java, VIX, anything that
you do as a Java developer, you can also do on this small device.
Of course, it's not so powerful, but it still allows you to do a lot of experiments.
And what is special about raspberry pie is those pins where you can connect electronic
components and that's what I'm going to talk to you about.
I see I have some missing images.
That's a good start.
There was also raspberry pie picco launched a few years ago.
That's actually a microcontroller.
So if you see a raspberry pie picco, if you ever played with Arduino, it's more comparable
to that, so we cannot run Java on that one.
So what is raspberry pie?
It's a single board computer.
You can run a lot of different Linux distributions on them.
I mostly start with the raspberry pie operating system, which is the official one.
But you also have gaming operating systems, a NAS system, any kind of thing that you can
think of does exist.
There is a website, awesome raspberry pie, where you will find all these.
There are many versions which are also 32 or 64 bits, which can be interesting if you
want to do some specific experiments.
And they make 400,000 raspberry pies a month.
And still you cannot find them.
Because of the ship shortage, this 400,000 is not enough.
They do reserve a lot of them for industrial use.
So as a consumer, a maker, you have to find them.
rpilocator.com is a website which polls a lot of websites who sell raspberry pies and
they list them.
If you follow them on Twitter or on Mastodon, you will get an alert if a certain type becomes
available.
I have been speaking at FOSDAM virtually, thanks to Fujie in the last two years.
And in 2001, I spoke about how I got into Java on raspberry pie.
I started doing some personal projects.
I wanted to have a touch screen control for the drum boot of my son.
I wanted to use Java VIX and I was missing a lot of documentation.
So I wrote about that.
And I end up even before building that thing for my son.
I have written a book.
And then afterwards, finally, he got his controller.
In the book I explained and also in the FOSDAM talk how you get started with this, how you
can use Py4j.
Py4j is a library.
More about that later to help you as a Java developer.
And I also gave some examples of running Java VIX on raspberry pie.
So 2001 was my explanation how I got started with Java and raspberry pie and has been my
niche pet project ever since.
And last year I was here again because there were new raspberry pie boards launched and
we had to do some changes in Py4j because they were not compatible anymore.
So in 2021 we launched version 2 of Py4j which is more compatible with the newer ports which
uses Java 11 under the hood and allows you to do a lot of fun stuff and I give you some
examples.
I also gave an example of a crow pie OS.
Crow pie OS is an operating system based on the official raspberry pie operating system.
But FHNW is a university in Switzerland.
They have a lot of courses where they use both Java, raspberry pie, electronics, all
kinds of stuff and they contribute a lot back to the Py4j project.
And they made an operating system with some additional tools for Java developers like
the latest Java VIX is there, the latest Java is there.
On the background screen of your desktop you see the IP number of your computer which is
very handy if you have a lot of raspberry pies and you never find back the connection
to them.
Also some experiments with FHGL.
Who has used FHGL or know what it is?
No.
Definitely take a look at it.
It's by Almas.
He's a professor at an English university and he created an amazing library for creating
games.
If you ever want to do some fun stuff and create a game with Java and Java VIX, FHGL
is the project and you will also find a lot of info about that on FHGL.
And I also had some demos with HiveMQ.
That's also something that's very easy to do is messaging from raspberry pie towards
a cloud provider.
HiveMQ is a messaging platform but they have a free cloud solution for up to 100 devices.
Every maker with more than 100 devices can now raise his hands.
Nope.
Okay.
That's the place to be where you can find those things.
Now Py4j.
Py4j is a Java library.
That means it's a dependency.
You add it to your Java project.
Inside the library is native code.
Native code that will call the different protocols that you can use to interact with the pins
on your raspberry pie.
So the simplest thing, you connect the let and you can make the let blink but you can
go a lot further, read temperatures, control, let displays, all that kind of stuff.
Now with the launch of Py4j version 2, we also launched a new website.
And actually that's my role in the project.
I didn't contribute a lot to the sources of the Py4j library but I focused on the documentation
part.
Just like Fujai wants to be the source of truth for all Java developers to find information
about Java, Py4j wants to be that for the Raspberry Pi where you have information about
how you run Java Avix on the Raspberry Pi.
One of the nice use cases of Java Avix is a kiosk mode so that a user interacting with
your Raspberry Pi through a touch screen cannot do anything else than your application.
They cannot go to reboot or format in Linux terms.
Now let's look back at what happened last year.
For me personally my biggest change is I joined Azul.
Azul is one of the distributors of OpenJDK.
I'm part of the documentation team and because of that I can also focus a bit on writing
documentation for Fujai and articles and other stuff like that.
But it was meant to be because Azul has a lot of distributions of it's called Zulu.
That's the core product of Azul is a distribution of OpenJDK like you have so many.
What is the main advantage of Azul Zulu is that it is available for a lot of platforms.
More platforms than most other distributors.
Oh, yeah, all the distributors.
That's the nice thing that I found out after joining Azul.
They are even the only one which supports all the oldest Raspberry Pi models.
Now what I also found out is who knows SD-Kaman.
Yes?
Okay, look it up.
SD-Kaman allows you to switch between Java versions with one command.
It didn't run on the Raspberry Pi.
And of course that hurt.
So Fujai, the website for friends of OpenJDK, behind the scenes there is the disco API.
The disco API is an API to search for Java distributions.
Now the same disco API is used by SD-Kaman.
And SD-Kaman is a tool for Linux and Mac where you can do it's a one line installation script.
Then you do SD-Kaman list Java and you will get a list of all the available Java distributions
for your platform.
Now because of the disco API and small changes done by Gerrit Grunwald, who is also an Azul
colleague who is maintaining that, and by changes in SD-Kaman and I did very few very
small commits to that, we were able to get to this.
So if you have this Raspberry Pi Zero from the first generation which has an ARMv6 processor,
is a different architecture than the newer ones, you will get four versions of Java that
you can install.
Unfortunately it's only Zulu, as Azul I say, it's only Zulu who will work.
There is still a problem with the architecture of the processor that has some issues there.
But so you can install with SD-Kaman Java on any type of Raspberry Pi because, I have
something else here, if you run the same command on a newer Raspberry Pi with a 64 bit operating
system, Raspberry Pi always has that now since recently officially, 45 extra lines.
So there are more than 50 Java distributions and this screenshot I think it dates from,
it's from a Fuji article in last February.
So Java 19 is not on this list, so there are now more than 60, I guess, Java versions that
you can install, distributions that you can install on a Raspberry Pi.
Another article I wrote for Fuji is G-Bang.
Who used G-Bang?
No.
Since Java 11 I think you can run Java files without compiling them.
If you have a single Java file which does some simple things, you can just run it, you
don't need to compile it.
What SD-Kaman adds, sorry, what G-Bang adds, is you can define your dependencies in that
one single file.
So if you install G-Bang on a Raspberry Pi or on any computer where you didn't run Java
yet, it will install Java for you.
Then you can just create a text file and then with this Gradle style definition of dependencies
inside your Java file, G-Bang has everything it needs to run your codes.
So this example is based on the minimal code example that we have on the Pi 4J website,
is just to control a lit.
Let me see if the video works here.
If it doesn't show you, I will just forward you to fuj.io where you can find the full
video.
We didn't try this before.
These sessions here will go very fast.
Another fun project I love is Vadin.
Vadin allows you to build user interfaces with pure Java.
If you have played with Java fix, it's a bit the same feeling, but then for web applications.
So you have button elements and table views and all that kind of stuff.
I also wanted to create an example using Vadin on the Raspberry Pi and that's exactly what
I have done and this video will play.
So this is the web interface without any modification that you get from a default Vadin project.
There you have custom set up with just a lit and a small button and then you have the Vadin
application running.
So this is a spring application, combination of spring Vadin, Pi 4J and that's running
on the Raspberry Pi.
So it's running on the Raspberry Pi you see also on the top.
I'm not going to show you any rocket science experiments.
It's just pure basics.
It's blinking a lit, the hello world of programming electronics.
And you see after the button has been touched that the info changes there.
So that's all what is documented.
Five minutes.
I promised you some Kotlin.
I'm not a Kotlin developer myself, but Pi 4J, the project, it's a community project.
It's an open source project so we welcome anyone who wants to contribute.
And Mohammed Hashim who once as a student I think developed a Kotlin implementation
of the first version of Pi 4J said I can do that again.
So he created a Kotlin implementation on top of Pi 4J.
So if you are a Kotlin developer and want to do Kotlin on the Raspberry Pi, you can
do so and even control electronics.
I'm not a Kotlin developer.
These are just some example codes that I took from his examples.
Now what the fun thing is that he also went back to the documentation part of the Pi
4J website and added four pages or five pages with documentation about how to do this with
Kotlin.
So if you're interested in Kotlin on the Raspberry Pi, go to pi4j.com.
Now a few things I can tell you about this year and what we're going to do.
Just as an experiment again, I wanted to create a library.
I got very worried about how I have to maintain libraries and the legal part.
So I don't know if this was a good idea.
I wanted to create a library containing a database of all the Raspberry Pis, the history,
and what pins they have and what you can do with these pins.
We needed for another project so I wanted to create this library.
Now on top of this library we actually created API.py4j.com.
And again I used Vaden.
I know it.
I've used it before.
So this application, API.py4j.com, it's public.
It's using a library containing a database with Raspberry Pi information and it's visualizing
it here.
And because it's a Spring application we can of course have Swagger and all that kind of
stuff.
But the fun thing is of course it runs on the Raspberry Pi.
It runs on the Raspberry Pi that we got from this company, finaltech.com, in check.
So somewhere in Prague in a data center, Raspberry Pi is hosting this pi4j.com.
I don't know how performant this is so if you all visit it at the same time we will
know it.
And then something unexpected happened a few weeks ago.
I was asked by Daniel Frey how about Spring Boot and pi4j.
Does that exist?
No.
But now it does because he created it.
So Daniel Frey and Ashaun Carter are two guys from the Spring team and they just developed
this.
And I joined them in a Twitch.
It was a bit chaotic but yeah it was a Twitch.
And we didn't finish it yet but we're working on it.
So you'll have a Spring Boot starter that will help you to detect which Raspberry Pi
you are running it on, how it should be configured.
It will create the context for you.
The context is that it loads all the plugins to control the GPIOs and that you will be
able to also, how is it called?
The info controller, the Prometheus list of all the data that you get from Spring and
what?
Grafana?
Yeah, that you can use it for Grafana.
So you will have all this data available.
What IOPN is toggled, what is active, what is the signal that is arriving at this pin.
So that kind of info, it's not finished.
We're working on it so maybe if I'm back here next year I can show you.
So what is next?
You can visit me on Twitter.
I'm also on Masterdome on the Fuji social account.
Of course with Fuji we also started the Masterdome service.
And I write a lot about all this kind of stuff and you can find it either on Fuji or on Pi
Fuji.
And that's all I want to do.
Thank you.