Hello, everyone.
Welcome to our talk.
Thank you so much for staying for this long.
This is the second last session of the day.
Really appreciate you being here.
Today we're going to be talking about modernizing legacy messaging system with Apache Pulsar.
Here we have Enrico and myself too.
We're from Datastax.
Before we start, if you like a copy of our slide deck, here is the QR code and also the
short link if you want.
I'll let you take a moment.
Even if you missed, don't worry.
We'll be sharing with you our connection info.
When you can connect with us, we can always be there to answer your questions too.
With that, let me start.
First just a quick introduction.
Who is Mary?
I'm a streaming developer advocate at Datastax.
Datastax is a company based in California.
Specializing in Apache Cassandra, managed cloud.
Now we also have the managed cloud for streaming, which is Apache Pulsar.
I was also a developer advocate before joining Datastax last year.
I'm based in Chicago.
I'm also the president of the Chicago Java users group and I'm also a Java champion.
Before this, I was spending over 20 years or so being a developer myself too.
That's me.
This is Enrico.
Enrico.
Oh, yes.
Sure.
I'm Enrico.
I work with Mary.
I really enjoy working with open source communities.
I'm involved in a few Apache projects like Pulsar, but all the big Datastax, so DoKeeper.
Also I collaborate with Maven and Curator.
I'm participating also in some CNCF project like Pravega that is still about messaging
and distributed streaming and also contributed to RDB that is a distributed embeddable Java
database.
Cool.
Okay.
Great.
Enrico.
I'm really happy today to be here with Enrico because we were just working remotely, finally
get to meet here in Belgium when he lives in Italy and I'm in Chicago.
Okay.
Without further ado, this is the agenda within 20 minutes.
It's going to be a little bit quick, but we'll end up having Enrico also doing a quick demo
as well.
First, let's give an introduction to what is JMS, assuming not everybody is familiar
with that.
Let's give an introduction and then we'll talk about Apache Pulsar and why Pulsar and
also just quickly describe the Pulsar architecture and how do you do the mapping between JMS
and Pulsar and then how to use JMS API with Pulsar.
Enrico will show that and then that's how we're going to be doing.
First of all, just some core concepts too of JMS.
As such, JMS is all about also messaging, but it's very much a Java-centric technology
and it's here, as you can see, it's also a publish, subscribe kind of model, making
use of destinations that it supports cues and topics.
Messages, producers, consumers, these are typical like PubSub producer, consumer type
of pattern.
Such is a pattern, but this has its own implementation.
Basically, too, it makes use of the JMS context and that will help you with the connections
and sessions.
Okay.
About destinations.
Essentially, too, it supports both cueing and the topic too.
It acts as a broker in the topic case, but for cues, each message is basically, as such,
message cue is you drop the message there and then it gets picked up and then it's kind
of done by the consumer like that.
It's browsable, this cue, first out kind of approach.
Then with topic, it allows for multiple subscriptions too and message dispatch according to the
subscription type as well.
As far as consumer styles go, you can have blocking, which is blocking receive methods
and that's all application driven.
Also...
Go, go, go.
Okay.
Then there's also making use of the message listener method, which is a JMS to driver
driven in that case.
As far as producer styles go, the blocking will be send method or there's also a async
send too and that will be like with completion listener.
That's real quickly.
As far as administrative operations go, as we know, JMS does not cover administrative
operations.
How do you manage the destinations and doing connection properties, all of these things,
the defining security models, our resource limits, all of these things and configure
all of these, JMS itself doesn't have to do it.
How do you manage it?
It usually relies on your vendor.
How do you do all of the management too through some vendor way of allowing you to do that?
Basically too, there's also API also to let you work with administrative objects too.
Basically they're supposed to be also provided by the system as well.
As far as destinations go, there are queue and topic references and connection factory
basically is essentially too using connection factory as the client that allows you to connect
to the system in that case.
There's also JMS, the API essentially allows you to interact with Java EE, or now it's
Jakarta EE, but back then there's Java EE.
In that case you can basically make use of EJP components.
There's Stateful Stateless EJP that's used in web surflets or the JAXRS, JAXWS endpoints
and allows you to also do background, like doing scheduling kind of way of doing things.
There's also message driven beans.
These are essentially too, it's basically their JMS specific kind of beans to handle
messages in there.
It's basically managed by the container, the JEE container.
When you receive messages from a container then it will essentially be activated in that
case.
The Java EE container provides support for all of the lifecycle management pulling of
these context dependency injection of these things.
It supports security standard API of these tools, basically relying on the container
to do that for you.
There's also too, what about external resources?
A lot of times that's how it relies on resource adapters.
It allows you to essentially extend the Java EE container in that case.
Some key points basically to use it is you need to have the resource archive file, so
the.RAR file that will contain the code and you have to then configure the resource adapter
and everything.
It allows you to essentially create administer objects, right?
These objects will conform to the standard API and it's implemented by the core inside
the resource adapter too.
These are the different packages, like basically Java X.GMS in this case is I think in the
new version would be Jakarta, but we're still talking about Java, the older JMS in this
case and will be connection factory, queue and topic.
Usually each object is bound to a JNDI, naming and directory interface registry provided
by the container.
It's specific to the container as to how you do deployment too and that's how it usually
works.
Now, then let's get introduced.
Now we talk about JMS stuff as a bit more legacy stuff.
What are some of the options to leverage on today's more modern world that allows you to
work in a cloud native environment better?
We want to introduce to you Apache Pulsar is an open source platform and it's cloud native
and it supports distributed messaging and streaming too.
As such, this is the link where you can find out more information or this is actually more
of the GitHub repo.
Wanting to highlight it, not too much time, but basically it's very cloud native in nature.
It's born with the cloud native DNA.
It's basically the key point of it is why do you want Pulsar?
I think at least one of the key points.
It separates out the compute and the storage.
Basically Pulsar can focus more on working with the messages, delivery, dealing with
all the messages coming in, delivering all of these things.
You have the whole laundry basket of all the log messages.
What do you do with it?
Rather than dealing with it, Pulsar said, let me get Bookkeeper to handle it for me.
That way Pulsar can focus on that, just the messaging part and coordinate with the Bookkeeper.
That's what it does.
It also supports multi-tenancy and that's a very nice way of helping you to organize
all of your messages.
As well as some features that are more ready for enterprise level, geo-replication is also
a major thing in that.
And also it has what is called tiered offset.
Basically if your messages get code, in Bookkeeper you don't want it to take up too much room.
Then you want to move it to, or actually I should say, it gets in the warm storage and
you want to move it off to cold storage.
So all these Pulsar has built in and it knows it.
So native Kubernetes support all of these things, schema, it has a Pulsar schema, connectors,
and you can use basically a Pulsar IO framework to build different connectors.
And currently we're supporting almost 100 different kind of connectors in there.
Message processing, you can use the Pulsar functions framework so you don't need to use
anything outside to do message transformation as you're building your data pipeline.
And also the nice thing too is that it doesn't restrict you to only using Java as your client.
You can use other things like C++, Python, Go, and other community contributions to such
a cloud.
There's also Node.js, also.NET, C sharp client too.
So that's really flexible and really functioning real well in Pulsar.
So let's kind of really quickly take a look.
I already mentioned some of it.
Essentially too it's a blazing performance, that's what we all want, provides you with
true real-time type of processing.
That's why we want it.
It's basically millions of JMS messages can be handled if you have JMS leveraging on such
a platform.
So it's all good.
Horizontal scalability.
If you expand your infrastructure, adding more servers and nodes and all of these to it,
Pulsar will handle that for you.
You don't need to rebalance all of your topics and you don't need to deal with offsets, such
as in maybe Kafka, things like that.
It has its own way so then you don't have to worry as a developer worrying about all
of these infrastructural things.
So all of these things are just listed here.
I know there's a lot of words in here but it allows you to kind of get a bit more into
detail and we can share with you this thing.
So let me pass this on to...
Actually let me see.
Oh, let me kind of quickly.
I thought this was...
Okay, so just a really quick basic architecture.
This kind of pictorially described to you what I just talked about.
We only had so little time.
So this is just describing to you producers, consumers can be written in many different
languages not just with Java and it gets managing by BookKeeper that deals with all of the storage
side of things and very dynamic.
As you can see, this kind of quickly summarized in picture what Pulsar can do for you.
Okay, and then here, just quick summary Apache Pulsar.
Again take mixtures of a PubSub type of architecture, right?
And that's what it is and supports like multi-tenants, namespaces.
Some subscription modes do that, you can also leverage on that essentially turn Pulsar into
a queuing kind of capability if you use an exclusive type of mode to do subscription.
And one other thing.
Yeah, so there are different modes.
It's just highly flexible is what we're trying to tell you about this story.
So here we have a...
Sure.
A little bit sorry about that.
We can talk more about it later.
So I just want to map Pulsar concept to JMS.
JMS is pretty straightforward.
So the model is quite flexible because it deals with queuing but also PubSub.
And in Pulsar, the mapping is really natural because you can map a JMS topic to a Pulsar
topic, whatever it is, a standard topic, partitioned topic, virtual topics.
So a JMS queue is like a Pulsar shared subscription.
And the JMS is like a Pulsar message with an envelope and with the body.
So in JMS, we have several consumer types.
So I'm not going to enter the details, but there is a subscription type that matches
the JMS requirements.
One important thing is that if you want to use JMS with Pulsar, you don't need to install
any additional plugin because the JMS API is built over the standard native Java client
because the Pulsar features are a super set of JMS.
So it's only about implementing an API.
You know, as in JDBC, you have an API that allow you to connect to every database.
In JMS, you just have to implement the API and follow the specs.
If you want, you can deploy a server side component just to push some of the component
computations.
So, for instance, in JMS, you have filters.
You can filter the messages.
So if you want, you can filter them on the broker.
Otherwise, you can simply filter them on the client side.
I'm just showing some examples of how to use Pulsar with JMS.
Maybe if you are already familiar with JMS, that's pretty simple.
So in JMS, you start with a connection factory.
So we have Pulsar connection factory.
And this is JMS 2.0.
And you can get a JMS context.
You get a reference to a destination.
This is create queue.
Create queue is not creating a queue.
It's creating a reference to queue because JMS doesn't deal with administrative operations,
as Mary said.
You create a producer.
You can send as many messages as you want.
And if you want to consume, you create a consumer.
And you can use receive or set a message listener.
This is from standard Java.
If you're using Jocate or Java Enterprise, actually, yes, I've been helping a few companies
to migrate from Java Enterprise to Pulsar.
So I know much more cases about Java Enterprise more than Jakarta.
But that's it.
So for instance, if you want to write and you have an enterprise Java bin, then you
can ask for the container to inject the connection to Pulsar.
And this is a standard Java Enterprise code.
So this code runs with active and queue, with the tip code, with whatever you want, whatever
you are running.
And the container injects the connection factory and the destination.
And you can, as in the standard Java code, you can get a reference to the JMS context.
And then you send.
We will see later how the administrator, for instance, with Apache Tomy, connects all the
parts.
The consumer, usually in Java Enterprise, you use message driven bins to consume from
destinations.
So yes, this is a simple message driven bin.
You configure all the relevant things that you want.
For instance, usually you configure the destination.
That is still a logical name.
And subscription type or the parallelism or the kind of things.
In many containers, you can configure the things on other descriptors.
Usually in XML files.
You implement a callback, on message.
Every time a message is dispatched to the application, the code runs.
And if everything goes well, the message is acknowledged to the Pulsar broker.
It won't be delivered anymore.
If there is any exception that is thrown, Pulsar will deliver again the message.
In Tomy, there is a very simple way to deploy the resource adapter for Pulsar.
So Pulsar, you configure the connection to Pulsar.
Now in the demo, I'm using localhost.
And this is the most interesting part.
I create a logical queue.
So foo queue, this is a queue.
And I bind it to a physical destination.
So the container will connect the, create a Pulsar connection factory and also the Pulsar
queue.
The demo is on my GitHub space.
So yes, you can run it by yourself.
I'm going to use Apache Tomy 8.
Starlight for GMS.
I'll talk about that later.
That is basically the GMS implementation.
I create the administered object with the same file that we saw and Apache Pulsar to
.11.
So we have one application that consumes one that produces and Pulsar will run locally.
So let me switch to the console.
Oh no, yes, the code.
The code is really simple.
This is on GitHub.
So you can check it out later.
So this is the producer, I'm not writing the code that instantiates or assigns some value
to the factory or to the queue.
I'm scheduling the execution of this method every two seconds.
And that's it.
Very easy.
On the GMS list, these are two separate applications.
Usually in a real world application, you have some application that produce the data.
And you have a pipeline that transforms your data and something else that consumes the
data.
This is pretty common.
So here on message, depending on the type of message, I'm printing the content and message.
Here I'm just declaring the reference to the logical queue that I want.
And in this case, openHB that is still Tomy will resolve the binding with the physical
queue via JNDI.
We are running out of time.
So I have a script to run all the demo.
The script simply installs two instances of Tomy, Pulsar, copies the configuration file,
employs the resource archives, changes some ports because I'm running multiple services
on my machine.
So there will be conflicts.
Copy the consumer application to Tomy 1, copy the producer application to Tomy 2, then start
the Pulsar standalone.
That is a quick way to start Pulsar locally with all the services, but only in one JVM
process.
So Tomy 1, to be 2, and then we will see the logs.
So there is some noise initially because it is installing everything.
This is Pulsar.
This is starting.
These are the two Tomy.
And actually, we don't see.
Oh, yes.
This is good.
So Tomy 2 is sending the messages.
Tomy 1 is receiving the messages.
So it works.
It's a very straightforward setup and very common way to develop with the Java enterprise.
Let's wrap up.
Two minutes, probably.
Yes.
Okay, good.
So JMS is very useful and it allows you to switch very easily to another vendor.
Usually with JMS, you don't use very specific features.
Usually in my experience with JMS, maybe you're using TIP code, you're using active MQ.
You configure on the container some special flags, but the code usually is pretty standard.
So switching to Pulsar is usually easy.
Pulsar is cloud native.
It's scalable horizontally.
So like Mary said, really, it looks like a promise, but this is real.
You can add machines, remove machines and the service automatically adapts.
Actually at Datastax, we are running it as a service on the cloud.
And so this is very powerful because you can automatically adapt the resource consumption.
And also you can move the data that is not actually consumed to tier storage.
And this allows you to really lower the cost.
It's open source.
And vibrant community, if you want, you can reach out to me on the community.
And there are many people, very enthusiastic.
Pulsar is young.
It is only five years old, something like that.
But in the past two years, it grew very fast because it is really the next generation.
Maybe someone working with the active MQ, then I did it in my previous jobs, active
MQ and then Kafka and then Pulsar.
Now it's time for Pulsar.
If you want to use Pulsar, you can use Stalep for GMS.
I'm the initial author and main maintainer for Stalep for GMS.
So yes, feel free to ask me any questions.
It's open source.
It's on GitHub.
Pulsar connection factory.
If you're using standard Java, there is a resource adapter that works well with many containers
and it's already tested and running on production.
Just real quick, if you like, get this copy of the slide deck.
But otherwise there are resources in here, community info, references to all the Pulsar
information on GitHub and also in Pulsar site.
And also then just additional information too with data stacks.
If you're interested, we offer the $25 credit per month for personal projects.
So wanting to share with you.
I know it's not true, open source in that sense, but we do have estra.datastacks.com
and all of the estra streaming is our companies supporting this in our cloud.
So where did it go?
Sorry.
You tried to subscribe to us.
Oh, that's right.
Okay.
So how do you contact us?
This is the slide containing information about Twitter handles and LinkedIn, all of these
things.
So please do consider staying in touch with us.
We'll be very happy to answer more questions that you may have and all you want to share
with us your project idea.
We'll be happy to.
And also on Fujai's luck.
Yes, that's right.
So thank you.
Thank you so much.
And I think then that's, that's all right.
We'll make sure.
Okay.
Thank you.
Any questions?
Are there any questions?
I'm so sorry.
Yes.
Sure.
First one.
All right.
So, uh, the functions, uh, uh, uh, addition to the messaging part, doesn't it make it
an enterprise server for us?
What?
The, the post-op functions.
Yeah.
Or post-op function is a lightweight, uh, processing framework that, uh, usually, uh,
it's very easy to enrich the data that you are ever on your topics.
So, uh, it's for very lightweight processing.
Uh, so if, if you have to do more complicated processing, you usually move to something
like fling or other things, but post-op function is very useful when you have to really process
your data.
And also it is the, um, base for post-RIO that is the connector, uh, framework.
So basically in post-RIO you can deploy on, on the post-RIO cluster your code that transforms
your data on your topics.
Um, yes.
It, it starts from a, a message on post-RIO and usually it ends with another message on
post-RIO.
So it's really useful for transforming the data that is on post-R or to, uh, push your
data outside of post-R.
I don't know if these answers.
We need to continue.
Oh yes.
There is a question over here.
If you want to have a discussion and also on Fujislak you can have discussions with
the panelists, but, um, at the top there, um, Mary.