All right, welcome.
How do you like our little Duke rock stars here?
So there's stickers going around somewhere so you can get some of these stickers.
I think we have four different rock stars or something.
Anyway, so stock is about Quarkus, obviously.
Who am I?
I'm a developer advocate at Red Hat.
My name is Kevin Dubois.
You can find me on Twitter or Macedon.
So I know we've already talked in a few sessions today about traditional Java and the startup
time and all that stuff, so I'll do that some more.
So we'll talk about traditional Java.
So traditional Java is, let me see the little hand.
Traditional Java is designed for, let's say, different times, not designed for cloud-native
workloads necessarily.
It's designed for running kind of long time.
And what's important in traditional Java is throughput at the expense of footprint.
So footprint can be quite large, right?
You typically have traditional Java applications running on pretty beefy servers.
And they're designed to be long running, and you have dynamic loading and all that stuff
with mutable systems.
But in the cloud-native world, your throughput, you get that mostly through scaling.
Your workloads are ephemeral, which means that if you think of containers, when you
scale up a container, when you start up a new application, those containers are going
to start up, and then maybe they're going to get rescheduled on a different node.
And so containers kind of come and go.
They're not going to be around.
And if you change something in a container, that change is not going to last, right?
Because that container, whatever you change inside, that's going to be gone when that
container gets removed.
So in that sense, we have to think of Java in a different way.
We need to think about the footprint of it, because we want smaller containers that we
can schedule across different servers.
If you are familiar with Kubernetes and clusters, there's usually multiple servers on which
it schedules containers.
So we need to be able to handle that.
And so that's where Quarkus started was kind of invented, I guess, because it's a framework
that uses Java, but we call it supersonic because it starts up very fast subatomic because
it's very small, like subatomic smaller than an atom.
And it's still Java.
So if we look at Quarkus in terms of startup time and in terms of memory usage, you can
see here, this is a test that they did with a relatively small application running on
a traditional cloud native stack.
It took 136 megs of memory running the same application.
With Quarkus, you already got pretty good gain in memory, right?
And that's running on the JVM.
So it's the exact same application running on the JVM.
And then compiled down to a native, with GraalVM, you get, of course, even less memory usage.
And you can see here, too, Quarkus starts up quite a bit faster than a traditional cloud
native stack, which is ideal when we're talking about cloud native, when we're talking about
containers, talking about serverless, where we need to start up really fast so we can
react quickly to changing loads.
So startup time is one thing.
There's also the warm up issue.
I don't know if issue is the right word.
Actually when an application starts up, it takes a while with Java before you get your
maximum throughput as well.
So here we can see that, you know, like a traditional Java application, this is actually
the points, and I think this is like 13 seconds or something, before it's actually able to
be working at maximum throughput, which, you know, for this particular use case, it needed
a certain amount of throughput to be able to handle load enough.
And then you can see here with Quarkus, it goes quite a bit faster.
Now Quarkus isn't just about fast startup time.
It's not just about memory.
But it is kind of a nice feature of Quarkus.
So if we think of containers and Kubernetes nodes, traditional Java applications running
on EAP or WebSphere or whatever, running on a Kubernetes node, you can see they take up
quite a bit of space.
Let's say that in this case, only four instances of the application can run, which isn't so
ideal because if one of the pods, one of the containers goes down, that means you lose
25% of your workload, right?
If you look at Quarkus, on the JVM, you already have quite a bit more density, which means
that if one of these guys goes down or needs to be rescheduled or whatever, you still have,
you know, what is it, maybe 70% or something?
That's still up.
And we can compare that to Node.js or Go or something where Go has quite a smaller footprint
and with Quarkus Native, we can actually be very comparable with Go, which is nice because
that means that we can use our Java skills and not have to change languages and reinvent
the wheel and still get all the benefits in the cloud-native world of having fast startup
and everything.
So how does that work?
So a traditional Java application, basically build time is when you do your packaging and
then as it starts up, it loads, config files, and then does class-pass scanning and build
kind of its model of the world and everything.
But this is when it starts up.
So if you think of containers, again, that means that this all happens when the container
starts up.
And that takes a while.
And then so with Quarkus, what we try to do is instead of doing all that, you know, at
runtime at startup time, we're trying to do all of this or as much as we can during build
time before the application actually gets packaged, which means that during runtime
we have a lot less to do, right?
So it starts up quite a bit faster.
So that's kind of the cool thing about Quarkus.
And then so you can use Quarkus on the JVM or you can compile it down to native, of course,
just like most other frameworks.
But there's some cool things about native compilation with Quarkus as well that we'll
get into in just a second.
So this is my favorite part about Quarkus.
It's not necessarily, I mean, yes, it's nice that it starts up fast.
It's nice that it has a small memory footprint.
But what's really cool about Quarkus is that it has a bunch of different ways of making
the experience of working with Java and Quarkus a lot more fun.
So one of them is, you know, so of course it's based on standards.
So Quarkus uses, you know, your Java EE standards, your Java standards, uses, you know, Vertex
and all that good stuff.
So if you're used to that, hey, great.
You basically already know Quarkus for 99%.
What's really cool with Quarkus is that there's this dev mode.
Basically you can start Quarkus on your local machine in dev mode.
It's going to start up and it's going to just keep checking to see if you make changes in
the class path.
And so every time you make a change, it's going to automatically reload when you, you
know, let's say go into your browser, whatever, you make a new request.
It's going to automatically reload your application so you don't need to recompile, redeploy
every time you want to test something.
Quarkus does that automatically.
So you can just go to your browser, hit refresh, and it's there.
So make a code change, refresh, it's there.
Which you know, if you're a developer of a couple, you know, of some other language where
that just happens, then that's not so cool, but in Java that's pretty cool, right?
So you've got our little guy here that says wait, so you just save it and your code is
running and it's Java.
And the guy says, I know, right, supersonic Java.
So that's pretty cool.
Another cool thing with Quarkus is that it has this concept of developer services.
So who knows test containers?
So basically it uses test containers built into Quarkus.
So let's say that I'm developing an application and I'm adding an extension to use Postgres
database or a Kafka topic or something.
Actually, well, of course you have to have a Docker or Podman or something running on
your local machine.
But Quarkus will look and see, hey, you've got this dependency on a database.
Do you have something configured on your local machine?
Do you have a database running on your local machine?
Is that configured in your application properties?
If not, no worries.
I'm just going to start up a container with that dependency, for example, a Postgres database
and wire that up.
So it's going to set the configuration so that it connects to that database automatically.
And then you can even go and see what exactly that configuration is and then copy it down.
Anyway, so that's the developer services.
So Kafka or, yeah, there's a whole bunch of different developer services that you can
use just out of the box, which is pretty nice because otherwise having to configure a database
on your local machine or, Lord forbid, a Kafka instance with all your zookeepers and all
that stuff, that's not so easy.
So you have live coding.
You also have continuous testing.
So kind of the same concept.
So if you have unit tests, you start your continuous testing.
So every time you make a code change, it knows, hey, this class is related to this unit test.
So I'm going to rerun this unit test every time I make a change here or vice versa.
If you're making a change in a unit test, it knows this is what I need to rerun.
So it gives you quick and immediate feedback every time as you're developing, which, yeah,
again, it's pretty handy.
It also has a dev UI.
So it has a UI in your browser where you can go and look at all these different developer
services that are running, what Quark is doing.
So again, I was talking at the start about Quark is doing some optimization, right?
So during the compilation time.
So in the dev UI, you can actually see what it's doing, how it's optimizing, and what
it's going to remove from the class path.
Because Quark is does some introspection to make sure that, hey, this is used or this
actually isn't used by your code.
So I'm going to remove all that from the compilation.
Here's a Quark is CLI, which again, it's not super crazy.
So you can either use Quark is with Gradle or Maven, or you can just use the Quark is
CLI, which means that you can do like Quark is dev or Quark is build or whatever.
You can even use, you can say Quark is image build or image push, and it's going to build
your application.
So build your application, build a container, and you can even push it automatically all
from one command, which is kind of handy, right?
And then one of the last but not least is unification of imperative and reactive programming.
So Quark is has a lot of reactive programming kind of built in underneath.
Now me, for example, I'm not a super deep expert in reactive programming.
But what's nice with Quark is too is that I can write imperative code, right?
So just every statement gets handled one at a time, and it blocks every time.
Whereas with reactive, you've got these event loops.
But you can use both at the same time in the same, even in the same code in the same class.
So for those who are familiar with reactive, usually you kind of have to decide, hey, if
I'm going to build a reactive application, that means I have to decide before I start
writing this code, you know, that this framework that I'm going to use is reactive, and I can't
combine the both.
But with Quark is you can, which is nice.
And best of all, it's still Java, right?
So you get all these kind of features.
And at the end of the day, if you're familiar with Java, this is really not reinventing
the wheel at all.
So it uses microprofile, Vertex, RestEasy, you know, like, and if you want to add extensions,
you can interact directly with Kubernetes.
So you can push your code directly to Kubernetes.
You can create config maps or secrets directly from Quarkus.
You can work really easily with Kafka and OpenShift, of course, Apache, Camel and all
that.
So in terms of native compilation, I think we've already had a few sessions about that.
So I'm not going to go too deep into that other than, you know, if you can run Quarkus
on the JVM and probably for 70 to 80% of the use cases, that's probably a good way to go.
If you really want to have the fastest startup time and the smallest footprint, then you
can do a native build of your Quarkus application with Quarkus, by the way, that's really easy,
because if you create a new Quarkus application, it already automatically has a native profile
built in.
So you can decide, you know, as you're doing your compilation, whether you want to do a
native build or not.
But yeah, so Red Hat is on the GraalVM advisory board.
And then there's the Mandrel project, which is a downstream distribution of GraalVM specifically
for building Java native builds.
And that's what Quarkus uses to, for example, if I do a native build and I don't have GraalVM
installed on my local machine, Quarkus will, again, pull down a container.
It's really good at pulling down containers to do a native build inside a container on
your local machine.
So again, then you don't need to have GraalVM installed and configured on your local machine.
So it really tries to make your life as easy as possible and kind of have the benefits
of a lot of the things.
So if you're thinking of, should I do a native build or just run on the JVM, this is kind
of an opinionated scoring.
But if you want the maximum developer joy, the best and easiest monitoring, peak throughput
and reduced max latency, then you want to run it on the JVM.
If for you it's important to have the lowest memory footprint, a small packaging, and a
very fast startup time, then a native build is probably the way to go.
So what do you want to use?
What can you use Quarkus for?
Probably anything.
So there are Quarkus-based Kubernetes operators.
So there's an operator framework where you can create these automatic components in Kubernetes
that manage resources in Kubernetes.
You can create GitHub actions with Quarkus.
You can create just regular jobs.
Yes, you can build traditional Java applications, even monoliths with it.
But this is, of course, a sweet spot of Quarkus's cloud-native application, so event-driven
applications, reactive systems, microservices, and serverless and functions.
So that's about it for my session.
So if you want to check out Quarkus more, developers.redhat.com has a ton of resources
on Quarkus, on a lot of developer stuff.
This dn.dev slash Quarkus tutorial is just a nice, lightweight introduction to Quarkus,
where you can create an application from scratch and then add some components as you go.
You add a database and then check out the live dev mode and all that stuff.
So it's a pretty nice thing.
Like I said, if you want to keep up to date, you can follow me on Twitter or Macedon.
I try to post interesting stuff, but I don't know if that's really true, but we'll see.
All right.
That's it for me.
Thank you.
Any questions?
Yes.
One of the first slides you compared startup time and peak performance and like the probably
the image was only about 50% of peak performance of OpenJDK.
So is that really true?
Like I knew that it's lower peak performance, but just a few percent seems.
I don't remember exactly the numbers on there.
Yeah.
So that yeah.
So the warm up.
Yeah.
Like the.
Yeah, definitely.
So the peak throughput time, there was a slide about the three graphs.
So yeah, I think with the native compilation, you're not going to have necessarily more
throughput than on the JVM, but you do get the startup time.
You know, like the time it takes to get to the maximum throughput is faster when you're
when you're native.
I get it.
But if I end up at just 50%, that's just not acceptable.
Like if it's like 80, 90% okay, that's fine.
Yeah.
We can look at it later.
Yes.
Yeah, that's it.
Yeah.
So the question was how easy is it to migrate to Quarkus from, for example, spring boots.
So Quarkus has spring compatibility extensions.
And so that makes it relatively easy because basically you're for the most part, you won't
have to change your code.
You just have to add the, you know, add the spring extensions.
Of course, in your palm, you're going to need to make some changes.
But it's fairly straightforward.
And my colleague, Eric D'Andrea, he wrote a book on spring, let's say, Quarkus for spring
developers.
And he does talks too.
But if you want on that developers.redhat.com, you can find, you know, there's a section
about books and you can find that book.
But it's, yeah, overall pretty straightforward.
So like I said, there are extensions so that you can keep using your spring annotations.
Now would I recommend you just migrating your application and keeping all your spring dependencies?
Probably not.
But it's kind of a nice way to migrate without too much work and then afterwards maybe migrate
further.
Any more questions?
Yes?
What are the advantages of the packages that you've produced and why don't you use what
you've produced on everything instead of Quarkus on the computer?
It's so faster than on the one.
So the question, if I understand correctly, right?
So the question is, why should you use native?
Yes.
Compilation?
On the graph, native is way faster and less smaller.
So why don't we always use native on the JVM?
Because on the JVM, you have all the kind of capabilities that the JVM brings, right?
So in terms of garbage collection, in terms of throughput and everything, JVM is very
optimized to do that.
When you do a native build, the GraalVM compiler is going to do kind of an opinionated approach
of how to do your native build.
But then that's also it.
It's not going to be able to optimize afterwards like the JVM does.
Kind of depends.
I think we're out of time.
If anybody has any more questions.
Yeah.
Thank you so much.