Hello, everyone. I'm happy to share some experience of mine with building Rust libraries. There's
a lot that I went over to come up with the lessons that I actually feel like are worth
sharing and much more than can fit into a talk. So I tried to sort of get it down to
the things that are most important to me. But if we have some space at the end, we can
dive deeper into some of the things that I will only cover very briefly.
So who am I? My name is Amin Roneha and I have been creating open source libraries for
quite a while. I have originally written a lot of Python code. I wrote the Flask micro
framework for Python. And I have been doing open source libraries probably since I'm 17
or something. So this is many years of experience in some sense. And I started using Rust in
one form or another almost exactly ten years ago. So I have played with this language for
really long at this point. And so I went through some iterations of what works and what doesn't
work. Commercially, now I work for a company called Sentry. We're doing application monitoring
and crash reporting. And so we use Rust there. And so I'm going to share the learnings of
this in sort of two ways. One is open source libraries that are there for other people
to use. And the other one is libraries that are to be used within the context of one specific
company. Because some of the things that we create, the only users really are ourselves.
And so in terms of open source libraries that sort of feed some into this talk, I'm taking
a little bit of code from my instant snapshot in testing library, my mini change template
engine and a few others like my console library. Okay. So this is a quote that I read a couple
of months ago. And it's not so important, but it really bothered me. It was a comment
to an open source library written in Rust that more or less made the statement that
defaults shouldn't exist and people should think really, really hard to spend the mental
capacity of understanding what it should be doing, picking defaults blindly is a mistake.
And I don't subscribe to this at all. Because I believe that it's the responsibility of
a library author to make sure that the defaults are the best that you can possibly take. And
the way I would think of this is you can think of creating a library or an API as if you're
building a business. You have some sort of success criteria and you can measure yourself
against this success criteria. And I don't think the success criteria should ever be
to confuse the user as much as possible. It should be that you measure how successful
your customers are in using the API as you designed it. So if they do something that
is not ideal, there's something you can fix. And the second thing is then they will typically
use your API to build a product themselves, to solve a problem themselves. And the quality
of the output that the user then produces in some way is also something that you have
an impact on. So you can kind of think of it like the percentage of users that are making
the wrong or right choices is the dial that you can sort of try to dial. The problem obviously
is how the hell do you measure this? And it's really, really hard. Because most of the things
that you can actually measure, they don't really show up in useful things. So you can
define the success criteria. And I think a lot of people do this in some way subconsciously.
But they actually have no way to measure it. I don't have a way to measure most of those
things. So the only thing you can do in the beginning is measure yourself. So you treat
yourself as the first user, horrible sample size. But you can sort of figure out as you
are using your own stuff, does it do what you think it does? And then every time you
sort of hate the experience, at least write down it like they didn't like this. So it's
a good start. But the problem is you are really flying blind. There's no good way to measure
this. And this is not unique to Rust. This is the fact most of the time it works like
this. But in terms of API design, I think we have learned in other environments that
there's actually a lot of stuff to measure. So if you were to create an HTTP library,
a lot of companies are trying to figure out how often do the users that hit the APIs do
the things that they don't want them to do. For instance, because they create bad load
patterns or because they just generally hit the API in ways that is not efficient. And
I tried to figure out how do you optimize so that the user actually does the thing that
you want. And this works if you run a service because you can see what everybody is doing.
You can't really see anything that a developer is doing in your Rust library. The only numbers
that we have are download statistics, which are really pointless because they are heavily
skewed towards libraries that are used by other libraries. So you can build the most
amazing library ever to build an application. But if there's only ever application developers
that are going to download this library, you're never going to accumulate a lot of download
statistics because most of the standard statistics come from either CI. And very few people actually
download the codes to run on a desktop. So if you have 100 developers, they're going
to pull this once each usually. And then it's cached on their machine. The download numbers
come from CI. So it's only this dependencies of dependencies that actually end up driving
those numbers. And so they can be demotivating in some sense. And they're definitely not
that useful. So you can't really track anything sensible in terms of adoption just by the download
numbers. So the first feedback you're probably going to get is some form of frustration.
So it's usually bug reports or it's someone internally telling you that this thing is
really inconvenient to use. In some ways you have to prompt them to actually tell you that.
But you can kind of do it like user service and interviews to figure out like do people
like this. And you kind of usually don't get people to reply to service. So one other way
to sort of solicit feedback out of people is you take this issue request, ignore it
entirely almost, and go back to like why did they submit this in the first place. And they
try to ask that question. Because quite often when they submit a bug report, they're already
down a really weird path anyways. And maybe you can take them on a higher level and figure
out like why did they even try to do this. I mean like when they do a feature request.
Bug report is less so. OK. So as mentioned, it's really hard to measure. And so because
it's really hard to measure, a second thing that you can sort of use is trying to figure
out like OK, if you think this is worth measuring, what is it that this number actually represent?
This is to be some sort of values. And so these are the ones that I find are important
to me. They're probably not necessarily important for everybody else. But I felt like over the
years I can get behind those. So the first one is I think the hello world of your library
should be relatively concise. So it should be easy enough to get started. To some degree
this is simplifying onboarding. But to another one it's also that the less stuff there is,
the easier it is to maintain the whole thing overall. I got into this a little bit. This
also leads towards good defaults. Ideally you don't have to copy paste five lines of
code in if a single line of code does. The smaller the surface area of a library actually
is at the end of the day, the easier you have in terms of maintenance and also in the ability
to do modifications over time. Because the more API you expose, the higher the chance
that you're going to break something. And I don't like breaking things. I think backwards
compatibility is really important. I hate the idea of unnecessary churn. I've been part
of the Python 2 to Python 3 migration thing. And it was horrible. And it was particularly
horrible because a lot of people that really liked the language, myself included, got stuck
on Python 2 for a really long time. Because we used it in a commercial context. We used
it for large projects. And those were the ones that moved the slowest. And so you had
a lot of, let's say, power users stuck on an old version that actually used it in a
quite extensive context. And it took us a couple of years to move. And while we couldn't
move or we could only play with it in small experiments, the language kept innovating.
And all those innovations were unable to be used by the people that previously were really
engaged in their thing. And so this I don't like the idea of letting people behind. So
the easier the migration path is for it, the fewer people are going to leave behind than
all the versions. And in a way, my goal is to keep people on the golden path. So what's
the golden path? It's the idea that you have an idea of how people should be building stuff.
Typically this is a thing that you're doing in system design. You have and you plot an
idea for someone to execute along. And this is like the blessed way to doing things. And
you try to get as many people as possible on this golden path. But libraries have the
same thing. If you want to build a security library, for instance, like an encryption
standard library, there are many ways to build a wrong one where you give people so many
choices that they have no sensible way to being sure that they're on the one that actually
does the right thing. But the problem with the golden path is that it will change over
time. What is correct today might not necessarily be correct in two years. To go back to the
security thing, at one point we recommended everybody MD5. And then that was not a good
idea anymore. At the very least it should be SHA-1 hashes. And now obviously we don't
want that anymore. And the problem with this is that a lot of things change over time.
And so if you create, for instance, a library that wants to make a choice for a user but
is designed in a way that the choice can never be changed on the fear of breaking code to
some degree, then you did something wrong in the sign originality. Some change requires
adjustment by users. And that's really hard to do. So if you have some sort of golden
path, you can figure out how many people are on that versus the thing that you don't want
them to do anymore. And again, measuring is almost impossible. But one way you can do
that is if you are building a library where you think other libraries are going to use
that, you can use something like GitHub code search to figure out how many people still
use the deprecated pattern. You can also leverage depend-about quite a bit to figure out how
many people that actually are getting a depend-about update are going through with the update versus
not. Okay. So defaults matter. As mentioned earlier, I'm a strong believer in there should
be good defaults. And I think defaults really come in two choices. One default is the absolute
default. You're never going to change the default of a U32 integer to be anything other
than zero in Rust. There wouldn't even be a discussion about it to change it to one.
There's an obvious default and it's so dependent on that you just will never be able to change
it. But then there are sort of defaults that are intentionally designed so that it can
change over time. And so for me, a good example here is the hash table in Rust or any hashing
function in Rust doesn't say what hashing algorithm uses. It defines some sort of properties
around it within the boundaries of which it probably doesn't change. But the Rust developers
could come in from one way to another and switch from zip hash to FX hash and most of
us wouldn't notice. Right? So to enable these sort of defaults, you have to design the system
around it so that these can be changed and you have to communicate to the user how you're
going to change them. There have to be some rules and expectations around what the stability
here means. But you should try to aim that you can actually enable this change. Because
otherwise you end up in a situation where you have created an API and now you need to
make a second one because the old one just doesn't work anymore and you either have to
take it away, it's going to be frustrating for a user, or you have to lie about what
it does. There are a lot of libraries out there that say, hey, my function does zip
hash and in reality it doesn't do that anymore because they wanted people to move up. But
they were afraid of breaking it. So why does this work in Rust, for instance, with the
hasher? Because they said, okay, this is never going to be portable. And I think this is
a really interesting part because it also kind of enforces without saying what it is
how good it is. So what I mean with this is that the hasher in Rust randomizes all the
time. So if you even try to use it in a portable way, you're going to quickly figure out that
every time you rerun your program the hash is different. So you cannot even get into
this mood of trying to use it for something that's portable. And there's a really good
analog of something like this which is every once in a while people build programming languages
and I think Go went down this same path where they said we're going to build a garbage collector
and it doesn't compact right away but it's eventually going to be a compacting garbage
collector. And the problem is if you don't start out with actually writing a compacting
garbage collector, a compacting garbage collector takes a pointer and moves it somewhere else.
So to compress down the heap space. But if you never compact to begin with, people get
used to this idea that the pointer is really stable and they will stash the pointer somewhere
and they rely on the fact that it never moves. And so at a later point, three years in, someone
says like, oh, now we built this awesome compacting garbage collector, but they can never turn
it on because people took advantage of the fact that there was actually a conveyance
in the API that they used that wasn't supposed to be there but it wasn't enforced. And so
what the Rust hasher does in this sense is it always randomizes. So it already makes
it so uncomfortable to use for the wrong thing that you wouldn't use it. And so if you were,
for instance, to build another language with the desire to eventually build a compacting
garbage collector into it, you would probably try to make it so uncomfortable to use these
pointers for stashing away that it already wouldn't work in the absence of one. So I
think it's a really important part to make sure that if you want to be able to create
this, change the defaults, that it start from the beginning thinking, okay, how do I build
it so that I actually keep this freedom? And so why do I even want to change this? Well,
because you have this problem of cargo-culting. I have created things in the past myself where
I discovered that people copy-paste the first example from a documentation over and over
and over again. And then you have this first example from a documentation in millions of
repositories. And for me, the weirdest one is that one of my frameworks that I built
actually ended up in a university course as a programming 101. And universities are sort
of an amazing catalyst for this because you end up with all of these students putting
their GitHub repositories of their first courses on GitHub. And then you see the madness
you have created multiplied through every single student that on boards. And it's a
real lesson. So I really respond really negatively to this idea of this code example, which I
know it's hard to read, but it basically sort of the, this would be the equivalent of not
picking a default hash. It would be like, well, we think that Rust is a hard programming
language. It's like, supposed to be like C++, you should think. So you pick the hasher yourself
and then you just put it in there. And then I swear to you, this would be the first code
example, even if the documentation says like, you should pick FX hasher for this type of
hash map and you should use zip hasher for this other hash map. Nobody would read it.
They take the first code example and copy-paste it in. But now we discover maybe zip hasher
actually is better than FX hasher, but we cannot change everybody's code all at once
because everybody has copy-pasted the wrong thing over there. And what I know happens
is that every once in a while someone comes in like, okay, we know that FX hasher is really
popular. So we're going behind the scenes, change it to actually be a different hasher
because everybody copy-pasted this thing everywhere. It's incredibly common that you find an API
that says like, I'm named really misleadingly because this used to be my implementation,
but now I'm something else entirely. Right? So it doesn't like this cargo call thing I
hate and I don't think it's good, but I understand it's really appealing because it's flexibility.
This I think I actually made the wrong code example here on the slides, but I was too
lazy to change it afterwards. But just imagine for a second that this code example wouldn't
return a string, but actually returns an enum with a variant called sha256. But the idea
here is more or less this. If you do create a library that does something of which in
the future there might be different implementation coming along, what you probably want to do
is not just return the output, but you want to annotate the output with what kind of thing
it is. So if you create a, if you have a library that sort of is supposed to validate files
on the file system and it does it by calculating a checksum, it's much better for that library
not to return the bytes of the checksum, but to return the bytes of the checksum and the
information by the way, sha256. Why? Mostly because it forces the developer to recognize
that this thing might change. It might not be sha256 forever. And this sort of explicit,
like even if you never plan on actually changing this at all, it still forces something in
the mind of the developer to recognize that this is probably going to change. And I know
of a version control system that very famously clicked one sha hash and is completely incapable
of changing it now. Not because it's technically impossible. They've changed everything. But
because there's an ecosystem of stuff that assumes that it will never change, this change
cannot be pushed through. They have the one version, the other version, the incompatible
of each other as an example of this. I know this is very security heavy right now, but
the idea is the same. Every once in a while there's a reason for you to move up to a different
algorithm or something of that nature. And if you haven't created an API in the beginning
that sort of hammers down this point that it might change, people will not necessarily
think about this. Less is more. I think it's pretty obvious. The larger the API surface,
the more stuff you will have to make sure doesn't break if you change internals. Particularly
internal APIs are incredibly leaky accidentally or intentionally. And whenever you want to
change it, you have to ask yourself the question if someone is actually using this. A lot of
people start out building libraries where every single module, every single function
is just pop. And every version breaks everything ever because you just don't have the time
and at least you don't have the time usually and the capabilities to figure out if someone
actually uses all of those functions, you just break them all. Or you just spend all
this extra time making sure they never break because it's impossible. So the goal is small
API surface. But then if you go to a small API surface, there's some tricks in Rust you
can use to reduce API surface but not really. For instance, we have some really common abstractions
like intot or sref t which can be used to be generic over something. It saves you the
necessity to build a function four times. You might want to open a file by string or
you might want to open a file by path. Just write one function. You can do sref path and
it's possible to pass any of those compatible types. It's kind of cheating because it's
really still four different APIs but they're hidden behind a standard construct that the
developer understands. So this is an example from Mini Chinsha. Both name and value are
generic. One is converting into copy and write string thing. So you can either pass it an
own string or you can pass a static string reference. Both will be fine. It behaves as
you would expect. The first thing is a string argument. You cannot get it wrong. The second
thing is whatever converts into my internal value type of which there are a bunch of conversions.
I could also have made seven different whatever functions for every single data type that
exists but this is a simpler way to do it. And I could also have said, like, okay, you're
going to pass the value directly already but since I already need to provide a way for
the user anyways to convert it into this value type, might as well use this. It's very consistently
throughout the API now using into value. There's only one function and it hides all of those
different variations of actual API that still exists behind this into thing. Sref is sort
of the same. I actually hate Sref because it makes it really unreadable. So instead
of your function taking a path by reference, it takes a P and then the P is hidden behind
Sref path and then before to use it, very often I use Sref.toPath. Which is just weird but
this is a really common pattern. So I don't like it but it's so standardized in the ecosystem
that people get to expect it. And so because we all have been willing to live with it,
I guess this is sort of enough of a reason to keep doing it. If you have this sort of
APIs that use a lot of generics to do type conversions, you will immediately blow up
your compile times. This is the standard trick to not do that which is you keep the generic
part into tiny, tiny function and then call it the non-generic part. So in this case,
the conversion goes to this value type. I know it's really hard to see in this projector
but basically the function render takes an object that can serialize with 30 and then
it calls value from serializable which takes this value conversion into value type which
is the non-generic which I use all over the thing and then all the function underscore
render underscore eval, they will not be generic and so they have one instance whereas the
other one will be one instance per type actually passed. What does it mean? If you don't do
this, if this was all one function, last time I checked this, the mini changer compile times
are exploding to more than double or three times just because of this one function. Why?
Because it's very common that you pass different types of it and the Rust compiler thinks that
inlining is awesome and it inlines this VM eval function there which is I think like
15 kilobytes or something and so it makes a duplication of this 16 kilobytes for every
single type that you put in. In this case, I only have 16 kilobytes once. It's serious
amount of code that you save with this and it's probably the best way to save compile
times for a lot of code. There are actually some tools that you can use these days to
figure out why these functions blow up that much but if you use generics, particularly
with S-ref and int2, worth looking for. I mentioned earlier I like to keep the API
layers as small as possible. That doesn't mean that I don't build actually an onion
of API behind the scenes. I like this onion concept like APIs are layered but the user
only gets the outermost layer, the inner layers are here for own enjoyment and then you keep
these inner layers and you have this flexibility of change remaining but it's still kind of
clean and then over time if that library becomes like the most stable thing ever, you can actually
start exposing the next layers of the onion. A good example for this is Rust compiler plugins.
Rust compiler like many other systems want you to be able to write a custom plugin for
it like the proc macros. The problem is that exposes a lot of the internal machinery of
the compiler which the compiler authors don't want to be stable. What they did is they actually
took the internals of that thing, they exposed it through a secondary library which I think
was soon. I think soon as they were on top but maybe it was proc macro tool but in any
case it was exposed as a secondary library. They actually used the same code but they
had different stability guarantees and then they used a conversion system which was basically
serialized a string and deserialized from string to bridge between the two. If you do
feel like okay I actually want to eventually expose this other library and I want this
innermost functionality to be available for customer, you can think of exposing it as
a completely independent library for experimentation and then eventually when it stabilizes you
can give it another onion layer to the customer. But again, once you have exposed that your
stability guarantees are going to be much harder to uphold. Just a simple example internally
in my templating engine I have a lot of abstractions like compile template which is something that
I know would be awesome to use externally but I don't want to give it to you and then
the code generator and the parser that have already been people asking how to get access
to it, you're not going to get it for now. But I keep the abstraction internally because
it's much more fun this way. As I mentioned, I like to have as little API service as possible.
By the way, I fail at this. You will notice that when I start a library usually it has
way more API than after three iterations want to take it away. But I basically try to keep
it flat so I expose all of the things I want you to use to the top level and then all of
my internal structure is whatever. However, I feel like to actually lay out those things.
If I do have so much code in the library that I feel like there need to be sub modules,
make them up on the spot. So in the instant snapshot testing library that I wrote, I have
a lot of internal types that you actually want to use as a user every once in a while.
And they come from all different locations in the code base. In my librs, I have a pubmod
internals which is documented. Those are internals you're allowed to use. But I just pull them
from wherever they're defined. This module doesn't exist as an internals.rs file. It's
purely a thing that sits in my librs to organize the structure. And that way I have the freedom
to move these things around as I want. Related, every once in a while you have to export an
API that has to be public for reasons that mostly sit in the restrictions of the language.
But I really don't want it to use it. So just hide it. So doc hidden, you will find a lot
of Rust libraries which have a lot more public API. But you're not supposed to use it. It's
usually hidden behind underscore, underscore. And it's just hidden. Why does it exist? On
the one hand, because macros often need to access functionality. The other reason is
also that you might have to create dependencies. So Insta, for instance, has to expose internals
out of itself into the test runner called cargo Insta. And the way I do this, I have
a hidden feature flag which says if you're cargo Insta, you can use this feature flag.
Everybody else, please don't. But if you do still use that feature flag, you're still
not going to see all of this API because it's kind of hidden away. This also helps when
you use, for instance, docsRS is an awesome tool to document your crates. A lot of people
run docsRS with all feature flags so that it's fully documented everything. If I wouldn't
hide all of those things, then this internal feature flag that would turn on this API would
accidentally document it. I don't want that. So even the APIs that sort of are there for
me, I will still hide from documentation. Cool. Traits. I have a really complicated
relationship with them because I think they're awesome, but I also kind of don't want them
to be in APIs. I think they fall into two categories. Some of them are, well, maybe
the other way around, open traits are most common one. As ref into, everybody can implement
them. And then there are a lot of cases where you might have traits that only exist as an
internal abstraction. Let's call them sealed traits. They come from a crate and they're
only implemented in the crate and nobody ever should implement those. Why do they exist?
Because you want to box something up or because you want to have really nice documentation
where you can select my crate except these types of things. I wrote a Rust library a
couple of years ago where I made the conversion trait so that you can pass any Rust type that
is compatible with Redis in all of those functions. And I didn't seal it off. And now it's public
interface and people have been sealing off their own types, have been implementing for
their own types. And so now it's just there. You can't take it away anymore, which is fine
for that library, but I didn't want to do it in other cases because to me that trait
actually mostly only existed so that it's there for documentation purposes. So you can
seal them in two ways. One is sort of the soft seal, which is just hide the functions
that you're supposed to implement. And then it's unclear how you're actually going to
implement it. In this case it's soft seal so you can actually call it still and you
can actually implement it. I'm not sure if I like it or not, but there are actually some
use cases of why you might want to do this. Mostly you have to do with code generation.
But there's also the way of doing a full seal where you put a private zero size type into
an argument and because it cannot name the type because it's never exposed, you can absolutely
not call this ever. And the funny thing is Rust actually depends in the standard library
of this pattern a lot. If you use any type and the generated groundcasting feature, it
uses an internal system called type ID to return a unique number for a type. If you
were to be able to override this and lie about your own type, you could cause unsafe memory
access. And so they have a seal marker in there that you can't implement and only the
default implementation is only the valid only implementation. So it's a pattern. It's just
not a pattern that has syntax support. It's just used that way. For now maybe it will
eventually get one. So why do I not like traits that much? Because I find them incredibly
hard to discover. It's very annoying if you import a type from your library and then you
want to call a method on it and the method is not there until you bring the trait into
scope. And I know that a lot of people write this awesome pre-ludes where like import this
from my library and now by the way you have 20 types sitting around in your scope. It
works but it has a whole bunch of problems. One of which is that it makes your error messages
a lot more confusing because there are traits in a standard library that if they are in
scope, types with the inherent implementations will no longer function the same. There's
a type called borrow, a trait called borrow. If you bring borrow into your scope you can
no longer borrow from I think a ref cell. It will error because the trait overrides
the inherent implementation. So that's not great and there's a bug report from like seven
years ago I think of this already. But how do you change it now? That's the behavior.
But that's the problem that you have with pre-ludes because they are just based by name
and it will say there's no implementation by that name or it doesn't help you that there's
an inherent method on this thing. I'm not going to let you call it. You have to disambugate
your call. There's some problem coming with the trait stuff and they're really useful
but you shouldn't maybe overdo them to some degree. It's really nice if the type out of
the box already has a neat little behavior. And if you want to abstract to a multiple
stuff you can add the traits later anyways. There are however traits you should probably
implement all the time. My favorite one is debug. It should be on all your public types
if you feel like it's blowing up your code generation times too much. You can hide it
behind an extra flag you can turn on demand. I give you a very good reason why debug should
be on all your types. Every once in a while you have to be generic over something and
then you will usually say I'm generic over serialize or I'm generic over my really cool
thing that you should be calling. The problem is when you're generic over serialize only
and you're deep down in nested generic over serialize type and you want to debug print
you can no longer do that because serialize does not imply debug. Even if a type is capable
of debug serializing because it's not a trait bound on the thing you cannot call it there.
Which is very very annoying in a lot of code setups. What I do these days I will make debug
and imply bound on a lot of a super trait on a lot of the things that I actually expect
to be very deep in code calls so that I can actually debug the whole thing. The problem
is that that requires that the ecosystem embraces the idea that almost everything is debuggable.
Just make it debug. If you really think it's blowing up a compile time just put a sectioned
flag in that it can turn on when you need it but not being able to debug very deep down
in generic code land is just an unnecessary frustration you can avoid. This trait is almost
like debug. It just converts this thing to string. It's obviously useful for a bunch
of cases but I can definitely overdo it. I much rather have the compiler yell at me
that I should be telling it how to format rather than the type in itself just being
formatable. But there are obviously a lot of types for which it's necessary. Like if
you would expect that it stringifies if you have an error. Errors have to be stringified
so you can't really opt out of it anyways. But I feel like that a lot of types actual
weight converted into a string is the debug thing is really hard to discover API. Yes,
of course, then I get two string methods appears but you don't know if this is a thing that
you're supposed to look at or if it's just a debug format with a different output. I've
seen both. There's some types where you can call two string on it but it's not the real
string form. You have to pick a different one. And it's just an alias for debug print
and sometimes it's the real deal. So this is a very confusing trade, I think. Copy and
clone are obviously the most common traits that you have to deal with. Once granted,
impossible to take away, I would say, because people start expecting that they can clone
it. And so copy is a really tricky one because you can only uphold it for as long as it looks
like a certain type of structure. Once you put something in there that's not copied,
there's no way to fake the copy. And so if you make your type copy and then you've later
discovered that was a mistake, you now need to hold an arc. It's a breaking change. And
I don't like breaking changes. So about copy you have to think, like, will you uphold this
forever? Clone, I think, is actually relatively fine to back port. If you discover over time
that you really can't clone the thing anymore, you just put an arc over it. So a very common
reason in the past I've noticed that I have a type, it has clone, and now it can no longer
be cloned because it holds a box function. Doesn't actually matter. Instead of a box function,
make an arc function and it works again. So a lot of these sort of classic cases of hey,
I can't clone this anymore because of a reason. You just arc it. It's fine. And then the problem
with copy is also with the inverse. You don't put copy on something and then people get
really angry because they expect it to copy. Classic case is the range type in Rust. It
doesn't copy. Everybody is like, it doesn't understand why does it not copy. There's a
good reason why it doesn't copy, but it's really annoying and I think it's one of the
most common frustrations in Rust that the range type is not copy and that you have to
clone it all the time. Like this by response on GitHub, I think. This one I will only briefly
cover but I don't have recommendations on if something should be sent or synced, but
I do think that it's actually totally fine not to have objects that are thread safe.
And the reason for that is that you can often just tell a user, you can create an API where
the user doesn't really have to do this. They can just put this locally and they're done.
Why? Because, for instance, one of the things that I love to do is create this sort of session
abstraction. Session abstraction is I want to deal with a bunch of objects for the scope
of one function only. So I load everything into some sort of environment where I do some
stuff with it. I have an object called session. It tracks a whole bunch of data modifications.
It gives me access to something. It's the only thing that ever needs to hold this thing.
And then when I'm done with him, I tear down the session and my lifetime problem goes away.
So for as long as you don't have to pass this over really complicated boundaries, just have
this thing, make a session abstraction, hold all the data in there that bores temporarily
and then disregard it. So this is from our symbolication library. It holds when you want
to deal with a debug file, you open up this debug session, you do a bunch of stuff, you
tear it down. And we have never, I think, had a case where we need to hold on to this
where the lifetime was actually a problem. But you will notice here there's a self-sell
in there, which I think is probably one of the best things you can have. Often you create
an API and then you discover I need to borrow into myself. And Russ doesn't do that. But
self-sell lets you do that. So there are a lot of crates that have been created over
the years so you can borrow into yourself. This is my favorite. It basically gives you
almost like a, it gives you a type that says here I hold some data and by the way I also
hold a reference into myself. And it doesn't really convenient way. So if you have created
yourself into a hole where you feel like lifetimes are your enemy, this might dig you out of
this. Yeah. Last part. Errors, I think they're important. They're talked by themselves. You
have to consider if you panic or error. My strong recommendation is not panic, but if
you do panic, use track caller. You probably know what this is, but it basically removes
this one function. Hello. So it removes the one function from the call stack and hello.
So it removes this one function from the call stack and then the panic message says, hey,
your problem was where you called in this case pop on an empty stack and not the completely
pointless unwrap in there. Right? Because like you want to know where you're fucked
up and not here, obviously. Errors are really important. Again, there would be a talk by
themselves. But my ask to everybody is please implement the error on those thingies because
then you can sort of compose them. A lot of people still don't do. It's very, very annoying
if they don't. Thank you. Do we have time for questions? Yes. So maybe we have some
time for questions. We have three minutes of questions. So otherwise we can also do
in the hallway, but might have one or two questions. Any questions? Hands up. Thank
you very much.