Hey, everyone, and welcome to my talk, keeping history in sync with turtles and magic or
the same shell history everywhere. I'm going to be talking to you today about a project
I've been building on and off for the last two years or so. To get started, who am I?
My name is Ellie and I'm the lead infrastructure engineer at a company called PostHog. When
I'm not writing software for work, I try and maintain a couple of side projects in my free
time. When I don't have the energy for that, I'm normally exploring outdoors, which, as
you can probably see, is usually on a motorbike for me. To dive into a tune, first of all,
I'm going to start with the name. Originally, it was called shink for shell and sync, but
I couldn't really say that out loud without cringing. I looked at something new. I've
been a fan of terry pratchett's disc world books for a really long time. For those who
are unfamiliar, the premise there is that the world is a disc and it rests on the shoulders
of four giant elephants stood on the shell of a space turtle called the great attun,
which I'm probably mispronouncing. I thought it would be a bit pretentious to include the
words the great in my project name and putting an apostrophe in a binary is probably not
a good idea. I ended up with the name attun. A little bit more specifically, attun was
made to synchronize shell history between multiple computers. I had the problem that
I would be switching between a whole bunch of laptops, I would be remoting into various
different boxes and trying to find one command that I ran a few days previously on whichever
computer it was was pretty difficult. So I wanted it all in the same place. The first
thing I did was replace the normal ZSH history, bash history or whatever fish uses, I don't
really remember, with a SQLite database. We could then have some functions to import your
normal text history into the database. Because databases are a little bit more flexible than
flat text files, we could also include some additional context. In the case of attun,
this is context such as how long a command took to run, whether or not it was successful,
which directory it was ran in, as well as the shell session. So the way we do this is
we plug into your shell. If your shell supports it, it's via the normal shell hooks, pre-command
or pre-exact and post-command, I think they're called. But in the case of bash, which I do
not have positive feelings towards, we do a really horrible pack with the prompt. So,
hopefully you can see the GIF on the right. On top of this database, we also built a search
TUI. This is bound by default to control R and the up arrow, which is a little bit contentious
for some people, so you can remap that, too. Search UI has three different search modes.
By default, one is a fuzzy search inspired by FZF, the other is a prefix search, which
is pretty self-explanatory and a substring search, which same thing, you should know
what that means. We also have several different filter modes. So, attun allows you to search
your shell history for the current session, for the current directory, for the current
machine or just all of your shell history for every machine ever. That you've connected,
anyway. It would be cool if it could have otherwise. A little bit more on that extra
context. Attun has a stats command which kind of analyzes all of your history and will show
you things like the most used command, which for me is LS. I didn't realise I ran that
so much. How many commands you have ran, as well as how many unique commands you've ran.
We're definitely not making the most of all the data available, and there's a lot more
sort of cool analysis we could do. You can also get the stats for a specific day or week
or month or whatever. A little bit more on the search. You don't have to use the search
UI. We also have a command line search interface. This is kind of useful if you have a specific
command in mind. Maybe you know roughly when it was or roughly what it looks like. It's
also useful to integrate with other tools. Someone on the Discord told me that apparently
they've used this to integrate directly with FZF instead, which is pretty cool. You can
see here that I'm searching for all successfully ran commands after yesterday at 3pm that start
with Git. Obviously, I did not make these slides today. The time specifier supports
like a human way of expressing time, and the command search supports regular expressions.
A little bit more about the Syncs ever. It's a kind of pretty boring HTTP API that shares
blobs. It has no idea what the blobs actually contain. It was originally written with warp,
which I found to be very fun. Kind of nice mental exercise, I guess. We ended up rewriting
with Axum because while warp was fun, it was difficult for contributors to figure out how
to use, and it also contributed pretty massively to a high compile time. And Axum has just
served the problem. The server is completely self-hostable. Anyone with it installed can
just run a 2N server and have a running server. We also have docker images and Kubernetes
manifests for anyone that wants to get a little bit more fancy. A little bit more on the Sync
is that it's not quite realtime yet. While I would love it if it was, it currently syncs
an interval of 15 minutes, and you can reduce this down to zero, which basically means it
will sync after every single command. If you know fancy running your own infrastructure,
there's a public deployment of a 2N that I ran. Currently, it's got about 11 million
lines of shell history on it. There's about 300 active users. It's all running on one
dedicated Hetzena box, and it handles way more requests than I thought it ever would.
I'd also like to thank the GitHub sponsors I got, which I didn't really expect anyone
to contribute, but they cover the server bills entirely now, which is a really nice feeling.
A little bit more about privacy. I imagine people here probably feel more strongly about
that than others. Everything is fully end-to-end encrypted in the Sync, because I really don't
want the responsibility of people accidentally pasted into a shell API keys on my machine.
We use libsodium secret box, because I'm not at all a cryptographer, and it's more difficult
to mess up than most other things. Finding a reliably maintained library for that was
a bit tricky. The original bindings we used were not maintained beyond security patches.
We recently switched to Rust crypto, if I remember rightly. All of the encryption keys
get automatically generated when you log in, and you have to keep track of them yourself.
If you lose your keys, there's nothing I can do. Your data is gone.
So why Rust? This is the Rust dev room, after all. A token runs twice for every shell command
you run. It runs just before and just afterwards. It lets us get the timing data and everything
else. If we had latency there for an interpreter to start up or a run time to do whatever it
does, the experience would not be great. If you added 50 to 100 milliseconds to every
command you ran, people would rightfully complain. So Rust fits the bill very nicely there. It
also has to be reliable, because if we're dropping shell history randomly, then it's
not at all serving the purpose it was written for. Having a static binary to deploy is also
really nice. No one has to make sure they have Rust 3.7, not pointing any languages in
particular, installed on their system with the right versions of various libraries installed
or anything like that. And it's also safe. So, you know, I don't have to worry about
any memory issues or anything like that. The other factor which I think for a side project
is especially important is that Rust is fun. When I started this project, I was also considering
using Go, and I was also writing Go for my day job. I didn't really fancy the idea of
getting home after work, writing Go all day, and then writing some more Go. So Rust solved
that very nicely, and I think the main reason I actually got around to finishing this is
because I was enjoying writing it. Additionally, the Rust community is fantastic. Every time
I've asked for help, people have been really helpful. Everything I wanted has been available,
and they're just generally very welcoming and accepting, especially compared to some
other tech communities. So I actually have one other service, and I'm glad most of the
previous talks have discussed Python, because now I don't feel as weird for mentioning it
in my presentation too. I have another service called rinse wind, a bit of a naming pattern
there, if anyone is familiar with it. What this basically does is it picks into the database
and generates graphs like this, which are heavily inspired by the GitHub commit activity
chart but for your shell history. It's currently closed source for no real reason other than
it's a really horrible hack that I don't want to package nicely for anyone. It mostly uses
NumPy and OpenCV and a few other things. It's also completely opt-in, so you don't get this
by default. If you don't want any proprietary code touching your data, you don't have to.
It's cool. Just with one command, you enable this. On the open source side of things, this
is the first open source project I've released that people have actually been interested
in. I made it just for myself and stuck it on my GitHub, and it ended up being quite
well received by a whole bunch of people. We ended up in a lot of package repositories.
I think off the top of my head, it's the Arch Linux community repo, Homebrew, Alpine Linux,
and some Nix. I'm not entirely sure how Nix works, but one of the Nix repositories. There's
probably a whole bunch more that I'm not aware of. We've actually got 63 contributors as
of today. Some of them are returning regular contributors, which is very nice that people
want to regularly give time to my project. Some of them are just sort of drive-by. They
found something that annoyed them or a bug they wanted to fix or something like that.
They contributed, which was lovely. I'd also like to especially thank Conrad. He's much
more involved in the Rust community than I am and also a very long-term friend of mine.
He helps me maintain a 2in, and when I was first starting and not so good at Rust, he
did a great job of tidying things up a bit. In terms of the future, right now, a 2in has
a bit of a flaw in that you can't actually delete history once it's been synced. This
is mostly because the sync is pretty consistent, and every machine you have is a potential
writer, so ensuring that you delete something and it stays deleted is actually really difficult.
I've currently got a solution to it which works on my laptop. I just need to make sure
it works on everyone else's too. I'd also like to sort out Bash, because pretty much
all the complaints we get about shell integrations are from people running Bash, and it's very
frustrating. I don't actually use Bash, and I hate having a setup on my machine just for
that. I'd also like to show some more information in the TUI. I don't know if you saw very much
on the GIF earlier, but it basically just shows what's useful for search results. I
would love it if there was another tab where you could also see sort of statistics about
a command that's run, maybe how often it succeeds versus fails. You could get some nice stats
about make-build that way, and that sort of thing. I'd like to improve the search a little
bit too, because right now it's good enough, and I think it could always be improved. I've
been meaning to explore some of the full-text search modules that SQLite has, or maybe something
like TanTV or one of the other search libraries in Rust. Otherwise, I'd really like to improve
the sorting. Right now, we sort chronologically, which is a pretty safe default. I'm not going
to turn this into a horrible Twitter timeline type thing, but it would be nice if we could
sort based on the context we have. Maybe every day at 9am, you CD into your repo and you
run Git pull. By default, it would be nice if you press Ctrl-R and Git pull was already
there at the time that you frequently run it. We've got all the data for that. It just
needs to be plugged together. In the even further future, the number of people that have spoken
to me about the fact that they have development API keys in their shell history, it would
be nice if we could do something to get that out of the shell history and sync that alongside
the data. Being able to bookmark commands is also something I would quite like to be
able to do, because there's some longer commands I run frequently and search for frequently,
having some sort of hotkey or alias would be really nice. Otherwise, I realised that
a subset of a to-ends history could also be used as a runbook if you had a begin and an
end marker to it and you could just replay some commands from your past. That's actually
it. I went a bit faster than I was expecting, but if there are any questions, I'd be very
happy to answer them.
Can you search for things which have come after your most recent command frequently?
I'm not sure what you mean, sorry. To take what you've just typed and see what you typically
do next. So actually returning the command after the one you've searched for.
That's one of the things I'd love to be able to do with the smarter ordering is know a
sequence of commands that's commonly run and predict the next one based on history. If
that's...
So, I tried to install your tool, but I'm using Bash and I was wondering how far are
you with fixing Bash?
Bash generally works fine. It's usually the people that have a whole bunch of Bash plugins
installed or have a weird Bash prompt that start to have some issues, but generally it's
okay for most people.
Does it handle having different cells in different computers? For example, if I'm using one computer
Fizz and another CSA, does the thing work between those two?
Yes. So we translate from whatever your shell uses natively into the format we use. So whichever
shell you use on each machine doesn't matter.
Okay. Thanks.
I have a couple of questions. First, I didn't quite get how do you authenticate with the
server by having a key?
So the sort of user authentication is just a username and password, but then your actual
data is encrypted by a key that's only held locally.
All right. And second question, do you have a home AZSH plugin or have you considered
one?
So we have a ZSH plugin. You can use normal ZSH plugin managers to install and use it.
All right. Thank you.
Getting some exercise in.
Is it possible to disable the history for a few commands and then re-enable it?
Not currently. We have spoken about the idea of an incognito mode. If you prefix a command
with a space, it won't be saved. It's kind of annoying if you have to run a lot of them
in a way.
We have some questions from the matrix. So Olivier says how would it interact with something
like Starship?
I actually use Starship and it doesn't interact with it at all in that it works completely
fine.
Awesome. And, yeah, that was the only question.
Cool. Thank you.
There's one at the front too.
Two short questions. The first one is, since Besh is so probably, I'm using Besh. What's
your favorite, Cheryl?
I like ZSH, I think purely because I started using it maybe 10 years ago and have it so
hard to break. I think if I was going to start again, I'd probably try fish a bit more.
And a question about the time stamps. Are you using the client-side time stamps from the
machines or server-side?
We store client-side, the time stamp will be whatever your client is, but we use two
time stamps to sync to work. We have the server local time stamp, which is only used for syncing,
and the actual data is all encrypted and hidden, so it's whatever your client stores.
Sometimes the local time stamp is important if you want to sync with the system, but sometimes
also the whole time.
The computers are out of sync. I had a bunch of issues of time stamps when I was first
writing it, but we got it all sorted out in the end.
Is there a limit to the length of command? For example, imagine a huge pipeline with
the SQLs and JQ queries in there.
Currently it's eight megabytes of whatever it is once it's been encrypted. It's only
a server-side limit, and it's pretty arbitrary.
Another question. Any plans for special handling for similar commands? Maybe fix syntax if
you run similar commands in a row?
I hadn't really thought of that before, but it might be worth considering.
Sorry, I did have a few more questions from Matrix. I think my device is not synchronizing
properly, but Andy sent me a screenshot.
Does it integrate with regular history mechanisms provided by the shell, for example, excluding
certain commands automatically like CDNLS, skipping storing in history by prefixing with
white space for sensitive commands, etc.?
The prefixing with white space is included. The default ignoring is not, but it doesn't
actually replace the text file history either. You will still write to that if you ever decide
you want to stop using it.
Where would context-aware recommendations come from?
If we have a history of your shell, we know the directories you're in, we know what commands
you've been running at what times, so if we're predicting the next command that you want
to run, we can use your own history.
The question follows up with, it's end-to-end encrypted.
It would all be from the client. The server's just a dumb blob store. It doesn't really
know much of anything.
Any more questions? I think that's it.
Awesome. Thank you.
Thank you.
That was really well.