So now we have Orson, he's going to be talking about GlideSort.
Very beautiful opening slide.
So yeah, take it away.
Thank you.
Can everyone hear me?
All right, good.
Thanks for coming.
So my name is Orson, and I'm here to present GlideSort.
I did this research at the CBI Database Architecture Group.
GlideSort, what is it?
It's a general purpose stable comparison sort here.
Does everyone here understand what that means?
No.
Oh, okay.
Well, good luck.
So stable means that it does not reorder equal elements.
They stay in the original order.
So essentially it makes sorting deterministic.
GlideSort is a hybrid.
It's a hybrid of merge sort, quick sort, and block insertion sort, which is a very
variant of insertion sort.
And it is robustly adaptive to pre-sorted and low cardinality inputs.
Don't worry, I'll talk about what that means.
I made a reference implementation in partially unsafe Rust.
And you can think of it, if you're programming Rust, as a drop-in for the slice stable sort
algorithm.
So you might wonder, stable quick sort?
The answer is yes.
A guy named Igor Fondenhove made very, I don't know, he did very good work on FluxSort,
where he showed that indeed you can do stable quick sort efficiently.
Wikipedia will tell you that quick sort is in place, that it is done using element exchanges,
and that it will literally tell you efficient implementations of quick sort are not a stable
sort.
So Wikipedia tells you, no, you cannot do it.
Stable sort uses extra memory to do its sorting.
And if you tell people, hey, you can do the same with stable quick sort, they completely
lose their minds.
Like, no, quick sort is in place, you cannot do that.
That's not true.
You can.
And you probably should.
So earlier I mentioned adaptive sorting.
What do I mean by that?
To adapt is to change your behavior to deal with new information or a new situation.
And there are two ways that you can be adaptive, in my opinion, major ways you can be adaptive
in sorting.
And they correspond to two schools of sorting.
There is the bottom up school of sorting.
Those are your merge sorts or your merge sorts variants.
And they are bottom up.
They construct larger and larger sorted sequences from smaller sorted sequences.
They are often presented in a schoolbook way top down, but really fundamentally they are
bottom up.
And that way they can be adaptive to pre sorted runs.
If there's already pre sorted running your input, you can just take that as is and continue
merging up.
There's also the partition school of sorts.
Those are your quick sorts, your sample sorts, your radix sorts.
They partition out or distribute data.
They are fundamentally top down.
You start at the higher and you partition to smaller, smaller, smaller.
Subpartitions and that way they can be adaptive to low cardinality inputs.
So what are low cardinality inputs?
Essentially you have a lot of data and you're sorting it by a subset of the data.
So you're sorting your customers, but you're sorting them by which city they live in.
Or you're sorting your cars, but you're sorting by the brand of the car.
And even though you might have hundreds of thousands of cars, you might only have 100
brands.
So you have a lot of essentially duplicates, at least from the perspective of a comparison
operator.
So how does adaptive quick sort deal with that?
The idea is that during partitioning we can detect buckets of elements that are all equal
to each other.
And there's a challenge with doing that.
You don't want to do extra unnecessary comparisons.
And we actually want to avoid three way comparisons.
That's a bit funny because Rust's basic or trade uses three way comparisons.
But that's a lie.
Under the hood we turned that back into a two way comparison because computers aren't
very good at ternary logic.
They really love binary logic.
They love ifs and else.
So we still turn that back into two way comparisons.
And there's been a long history on adaptive quick sorts in this way.
With Dykstra and Hauer.
I still don't know how to pronounce that.
Working on it.
And already time flies.
Eight years ago I showed that in pattern defeating quick sort that you can detect this and handle
this very efficiently.
So how does that work?
I had an entire earlier talk on PDQ sort that you can watch if you're interested in this.
But essentially we have two different partition strategies.
A partition left and a partition right.
The partition left puts elements equal to the pivot on the left.
And the partition right puts equal elements on the right.
And what you do is when you select a pivot you check if that pivot is equal to a pivot
we used previously.
And you can do this efficiently using a single extra comparison during partitioning.
Or at least pivot selection.
And the default is that you put the equal elements on the right.
But if you detect hey this pivot is equal to a previous pivot you put equal elements
on the left.
And this way you implicitly do a three way partition using two way comparisons.
And you can prove that on average this means that your sort is O and log K where K is the
number of distinct values.
If every value is distinct that becomes O and log N we're used to that.
But if you have a lot of duplicate values O and log K goes a lot faster than N log N.
There's also adaptive merge sort.
These as I said earlier these merge pre-existing runs in the input.
The problem with solving this is that you want to minimize the amount of unbalanced
mergers that you do.
So you don't want to merge a very large array with a very small array because that's quite
inefficient.
And you also want to somehow store during your algorithm where the runs are in memory.
And if you do this in an illogical way you have to potentially store a lot of data about
where all the runs are.
And Van Neumann invented merge sort very early.
And Knuth described also quite early a natural merge sort that takes advantage of pre-existing
runs in the input.
And then in particular Tim Peters popularized Tim sort which became the default sorting
algorithm in Python that really showed the first sort of clever way to keep track of
your run information and minimizing unbalanced mergers.
More recent work is power sort which extends on Tim sort essentially or has the same logic
but more clever logic and actually has mathematical proofs that it creates balanced merge sequences.
And in fact Python I believe now uses power sort logic as well.
So I'm not going to go into detail on how power sort works.
I don't have enough time for that.
But essentially the core loop of it is that you create a run and that can either be by
finding the run in the input or doing a small sorting algorithm to create a small run.
You compute the power of a run.
That's the heuristics I'm not going to get into.
And then you keep a stack of runs and then use the power heuristic that we computed to
decide when to merge two runs.
And you can prove that the stack then becomes logarithmic in size and that your merge sequences
are going to be very good.
And the idea is that create a run can take advantage of existing runs in the input.
So a problem merges.
We want to be adaptive to low cardinality inputs and we want to be adaptive to pre-existing
rather than input.
But one is fundamentally bottom up and the other one is fundamentally top down.
And that's why I call this glide sort.
We glide.
What do I mean by that?
The idea is that a soaring bird only flaps its wings when necessary.
Glide sort only sorts when necessary.
So during this create run process, sorry, before that, I changed the concept of a run
to a logical run.
And a logical run can be one of three things.
It can be just as before, it can just be a sorted range of elements in your array.
And can also be an unsorted range of elements in your array or two sorted ranges that are
right next to each other in your array.
We change the create run function.
We do, in fact, if there's a run in the input, detect that and return that as a sorted run.
But if we don't detect a sorted run, we just return an unsorted run.
We don't eagerly sort anything.
And how you do that is very simple.
You just scan through the array and if you find a run that we consider big enough, we
return it and otherwise we just skip some elements and return an unsorted run.
And then you add quite a bit of code for merging two runs.
But it's actually relatively simple.
As long as two unsorted runs concatenated fit in our scratch base, which is essentially
this extra memory that blows people's minds, as long as it fits in that, we just concatenate
our unsorted runs.
And otherwise we actively physically sort the elements using quicksort and then create
one of these two sorted concatenated run cases.
If we have two sorted runs, we concatenate them.
If we have an unsorted run and something else, we actually sort this unsorted run and then
recurse.
And finally, we have our actual physical mergers.
So when we can no longer be lazy, we can no longer glide, we have to actually merge elements.
So that is essentially the main loop of glidesort.
So it's an extension of power sort, but you can apply the same logic to any natural stable
mergers sort.
We don't eagerly sort small runs.
We keep them as unsorted runs as long as possible.
And this way we transform the sorting problem into a sequence of quicksort calls and triple
slash quad mergers.
And doing this we are adaptive to pre sorted runs and low cardinality inputs at the same
time.
So why triple and quad mergers?
And there are three main reasons.
There's ping pong merging, bidirectional merging.
Oh, sorry, before I want to quite clearly mention something, glidesort is not the first algorithm
that is adaptive to both of these categories at the same time.
But to my knowledge, at least it is the first algorithm that is robustly adaptive.
So it does not hard code anything.
It does not use heuristics to decide when to switch to which algorithm it detects is
completely naturally based on the input.
So why triple slash quad mergers?
There are three main reasons.
Ping pong merging, bidirectional merging and parallel merging.
Ping pong merging is not my idea.
It's found in two earlier projects, once again by Igor van der Hove and an earlier paper.
Ping she says virtue.
And the idea is that in a traditional merge, you copy out part of the data someplace else
and then merge back into the original array.
That's an extra memcap.
With a triple slash quad or a quad merge, you can merge both into your scratch base
and on the way back.
Because essentially when you do an out of place merge, you get a mem copy for free because
you're moving to some other place.
So I think that's best described visually.
If you have four, so in this case a quad merge, you have four sorted runs, you merge two
into your scratch base, you merge two more into your scratch base, and you merge two
back.
And now we eliminated three mem copies.
So don't have to do that.
That's one advantage of being lazy with merging.
We can also do bidirectional merging.
To my knowledge, it was first done again by Igor van der Hove in quadsward where he described
a parity merge where he showed a very clever technique to merge two equal length arrays
without any branch checks.
But then I thought by merging from both ends at the same time.
But then I thought looked really into why that was fast and how can we extend that and
use that further.
So the idea behind a bidirectional merge is that if your destination and your source arrays
are disjoint, you can merge from both ends at the same time.
And then the pointer that's going from right to left does not interfere with the pointer
going from left to right.
These two logics are independent, essentially.
And it essentially looks like that.
Why?
Why do we want to do that?
Modern processors are quite different than what maybe your traditional processor with
your mental image are.
They are superscalar.
That means they don't execute one instruction per cycle.
No, they can execute many instructions per cycle.
They are out of order.
The processor will internally reorder your instructions based on your assembly, based
on the data paths and when memory is available.
And they are deeply pipelined.
That means that they don't like it when the next instruction depends immediately on the
result of the previous instruction because it has to go through the entire pipeline of
the processor.
So to study that in a bit more detail, we look at a branchless merge, which was first
described in branch mispredictions don't affect merge sort.
This is not the code that they used in this paper.
This is from roughly translated from Glide Sort.
But you don't have to get into it how it works.
The main important part is that you analyze where is the result used in the next slide.
You find that generally all the data that's computed is needed immediately.
The worst part of it all is that the next iteration cannot start until the previous
iteration is finished.
You don't know if you're merging two arrays.
You need to know am I continuing with the left array or the right array.
There's a lot of data dependencies.
So that is my main takeaway from Glide Sort and my main low level design principle is
to interleave independent branchless loops.
So branch is important.
The processor isn't jumping around and canceling your pipeline.
And by interleaving, we can hide some of these data dependencies.
The processor can execute multiple instructions at once.
It can essentially reduce the impact of having to constantly wait for the previous result.
You can also consider parallel merging.
In this case, we had one merge where we did it in parallel from the left and parallel
from the right.
But we also noticed that the first step in our quad merge has two independent merges.
These are essentially parallel.
But we're not using threads.
But we can interleave their loops.
So once I discovered that, I thought let's create more parallelism.
By doing a binary search, you can identify a split point where you can turn one merge
into two smaller merges by swapping the right blocks in the middle.
I won't go into the exact logic of proof about that.
But you can.
And in fact, if you are doing an out of place merge, you can do this swap implicitly by
just reassigning pointers.
So there's no actual physical mem copy going on.
However, if you're doing an in place merge, you can actually do the physical swap.
And now you have for free a fallback for low memory merging.
So even if you don't have a large buffer available to merge with, you can use this algorithm
to do it in a low amount of memory.
Then I also optimized the quick sort portion of it with the same principle.
I came up with what I call bidirectional stable partitioning.
Again, I don't have time to get into it.
But the idea is that we do, again, partition like in quick sort.
So this one set of elements goes to that are less than the pivot, go somewhere else.
Go go here.
And some that are greater or equal, go somewhere else.
But we do it from both the left hand side to the right and from the right hand side
to the left.
And these two loops are independent from each other so we can interleave them.
Same principle.
When you recurse, it gets a bit more involved because now your data is in multiple different
locations.
I can tell you this is not fun to program.
But I did it.
And here it is.
So I do have some experiments to show you very briefly.
The next round is set up.
So this is a lot of text that basically says a 2021 Apple MacBook.
And these are the numbers you would get on an Apple 2021 MacBook.
So at the top I have two variants of Glide Sword.
One is the default variant that you would get if you were to download it.
Glide Sword 1024 is a variant that uses a fixed amount of memory.
So 1024 elements of memory.
Then we have the Rust Stable Sword, the C++ Stable Sword, an implementation of Tim Sword,
a PDQ Sword, an older algorithm of mine, which is also the stable Rust sorting algorithm
and the whatever shipped as the standard sort in C++.
And you can read the slides yourself.
Glide Sword is quite a bit faster than the Rust Stable Sword right now.
What isn't shown on this page are some more competitive algorithms like Flux Sword and
Quad Sword.
They trade blows for blows on different data sets.
But those are written in C. And they don't have to deal with some of the problems that
we deal with that I'll get to later in my talk on sorting in Rust.
If you actually change your comparison operator, so we're only sorting by the last byte of
the integer.
Fun fact, if you do this, stability becomes even observable for integers.
Glide Sword again speeds up even more compared to the Rust Stable sorting algorithm.
So now we're over an order of magnitude faster for these data sets.
If you want to use it, good news, it's released.
It took me a while.
But it's finally out.
You can just cargo add Glide Sword and you can replace your sort, call to Slide Sword.
With Glide Sword, if there are any standards library people in the audience, come talk
to me after the talk.
I would love to see it integrated so you don't have to call Glide Sword and it would just
be done by default.
But this is a Rust dev room.
Some of you at least probably are interested in Rust.
So I will also talk about some Rust specifics.
So what it takes to implement a sorting algorithm in Rust.
First I'm just going to rant.
Unwinding panics, I think a Rust billion dollar mistake.
They are a complete nightmare.
If you are writing unsafe code and you've ever had to deal with panics, some people
in the audience are laughing, they're horrible.
Because essentially since you can catch them and we have to be sound and safe during a
panic, they're essentially the same as C++ exceptions.
In C++ all these functions say if you throw an exception, tough shit.
Like your vector is invalid now.
Too bad.
Doesn't matter.
You don't have that choice in Rust.
You have to always be safe and sound in Rust.
Ensuring that is a nightmare.
Especially when you're dealing with generic code in unsafe code.
So if you're calling foreign code, anything you do, any call can panic which causes an
unwind.
So whenever you call a foreign function, you have to make sure that you are in a sound
and safe state.
The problem is every single trait is foreign code.
That clone call, that's foreign code.
This comparison operator, that's foreign code.
Implementing Glideswear was a complete nightmare.
Every time I compare two elements, that could cause a panic, that could cause an unwind,
and you saw all this stuff that I'm doing with arrays all over the place, all of that
has to be restored to the original location because it's a mud slice.
You cannot leave a mud slice in an unsound or you can't leave holes in it.
Everything has to be returned to the original.
It's a nightmare.
I really wish we would just instead of panicking, we would just write out a stack trace and
abort and be done with it.
I hate it.
That's my rant.
Oh, yeah.
And in fact, Glideswear has an actual real performance penalty because panics are a thing.
I can't just write a, like if you're writing an insertion sort, for example, in C++ or
in Python, you would just have a loop with a loop variable and you would put the items
in the correct place.
If you're implementing a thing like this in Rust and you're leaving gaps, so you're moving
the element out during the insertion sort, you have to have a drop handler that puts
this element back during a panic because this ORD implementation, this foreign code, can
cause a panic and can cause an unwind.
Even when I'm sorting something like integers which cannot panic, if I don't want to duplicate
my entire code base, I still have to pay this penalty for dealing with the potential for
panics by storing all my data in structs and all this algorithm state.
So yeah, that's a problem.
But I also want to praise Rust where it is pleasurable.
I love that moves are mem copies.
There's no move constructor.
If you want to move a type somewhere else, you essentially just copy it and you ignore
wherever it came from.
This also makes optimizations possible that aren't possible in C++ because of move constructor.
At least not if you don't want to use templates, metaprogramming.
For example, instead of copying an element, this is an example actually from Glide Sort,
not written like this, but where you place an element in one of two places and if it's
going to the wrong place, it doesn't matter because it will just be ignored or overwritten
in the next iteration.
If it's a small type, just place it in both.
Don't do a branch.
So essentially, this is the opposite of unwinding panics.
There are no surprises.
A mem copy is always what you get.
This is not necessarily.
This part, brace, part, complaining, split at mutt.
Splitting a slice in two or more.
It's a one-way street.
You cannot go back.
Once you split, it's split unless you go back to the original object, but that's not always
an option.
In Glide Sort, when I concatenate these arrays, I need actual concatenation.
My options were raw pointers.
That was the option.
More store an array with indices, but now you're storing an extra pointer everywhere
and passing an extra pointer everywhere and that's overhead that I didn't want to pay.
So I came up with a thing I call branded slices.
You could hold an entire talk on this, but it's essentially applying the idea of Go-Sell,
some of you might have heard from this, where you essentially brand a type with a unique
lifetime that you cannot create.
You can only create this lifetime once and it's not interchangeable with any other lifetime.
With that, you can make safe concatenation.
You could just check is the end pointer equal to the begin pointer of the other array?
If yes, we can concatenate.
That would work, except that could also just be happening by chance because of the local
array layout on the stack and you could create unsound behavior.
If you know that they came from the same allocation, then it's safe to concatenate them after checking
end equals begin.
That's what I did with what I call mod slice, which in Glice
is a mod slice type, which has a brand, so you can do the safe concatenation.
And it has a state, which is one of five things.
It's weak on init, maybe init, always init, always init, essentially immutable slice.
So you always have to return it to initialization state.
The maybe init init are a bit more specialized than just maybe on init where the type doesn't
really encode what it actually contains.
And weak is essentially a pair of pointers.
And the code becomes a lot more readable and a lot more verifiable by explicitly encoding
your assumptions about your slice type using the type and then calling functions like upgrades
to say, hey, this now becomes an exclusive mutably slice.
I'm only going to access this here.
Or hey, I'm now going to temporarily invalidate this initialization state of this slice.
That was essentially my talk.
I'm leaving academia.
So if you have an interesting potentially rough job, my contact details are on the slides
or come talk to me after the talk.
I'm not interested in cryptocurrency web 3 or similar endeavors.
I love cryptography, but I don't know.
Some of this stuff gets rather sketchy.
No offense.
That was essentially my talk.
I'm going to leave this on this slide.
Are there any questions?
I have a question.
Did you test GlideSort on, let's say, less modern CPUs like embedded CPUs that don't
have autofodder execution, et cetera?
Yes.
Can you repeat the question, please?
Oh.
So the question was, did you test the algorithm on any older CPUs that might not have as much
instruction level parallelism and that kind of stuff?
The answer is yes.
And yes, it is slower than other state of the art that don't do these tricks.
This is really aimed towards essentially the future of modern processors.
From older CPUs, it is slower than, for example, FluxSort, which doesn't do this aggressive
interleaving.
But if you compare it to the current Rust stable sort that's currently in the standard
library, it still completely dumps us all over that.
Okay.
So sorry.
Can you hear me?
Barely.
Can you speak loudly?
Okay.
When you take two sorted sequences and you take the bottom half of one and the top half
of another and create a third sorted sequence out of that, I thought that was an interesting
observation.
But what do you use it for?
So it's not the top half and the bottom half.
That's just a simplification.
You're talking about the splitting of merges into smaller merges, right?
Yes.
Yeah.
So it is not the top half and the bottom half.
It involves a binary search to find the unique split point that allows you to do this swap.
It could be bottom half, top half, but it's not necessarily the case.
What do I use this for?
It creates two independent merges.
After doing the swap, this merge no longer depends on this merge at all.
And by doing that, I can have two independent loops that merge these and then interleave
the bodies of these loops.
So it executes one instruction from this merge, one instruction from this merge, one instruction
from this merge, one instruction from this merge, et cetera.
And that way these instructions don't depend on each other and you can hide these data
dependencies and such.
On top of that, I use it as a fallback for the low memory case where you don't need
– so Glideword can use less auxiliary memory.
We have a last question.
Thanks for the talk.
I would like to know if you have a bench.
I'm sorry, I cannot hear.
Can you speak a bit louder, please?
Did you bench when the array is already sorted?
Did I bench when the array is already sorted?
Yes.
Yes, it's on the slides.
Is it on the slides?
Yes, it's the ascending column on the slides and on this slide as well.
It's the one percent.
Sorry?
It's the one percent column.
No, ascending.
Ascent, okay.
That means sorted in this case and descending means reverse of sorted.
Okay, thank you.
All right.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
The next question is for Fluzo Spas.