So now we've got Tommaso, he's going to tell us how to build a snake game.
Are we going to build it together?
Hopefully.
Hi all.
Today we are here to talk about snake, obviously, rust and wasm.
In particular we will see how to build a snake game written in rust and shiphead has a wasm
module.
Before doing that, I would like to introduce myself.
Hi, I'm Tommaso, I have two cats.
And commonly I used to be a software architect in web application environment.
So probably the games is not my best stuff I can do build, but I try.
So let's start to talk about what wasm is.
Nevertheless, is a stack based virtual machine that allows to be portable.
So we can build the application and bring where you want mostly.
And the main target is web, but not linked to the web only.
We will see later.
So we have four concepts, efficient and fast.
Memory safety, open the bug able and part of the web platform.
For this reason we have four parts.
The core one, JavaScript API that allow us to interact with JavaScript worlds like browser
nodes and so on.
Web API that allow us to interact with DOM events and so on.
And Wazi, this is a code for WebAssembly system integration if I remember correctly.
That allow us to interact with file system, networking and so on.
Obviously Wazi is not allowed in browser context for some reason.
So how we can write a wasm module?
But wasm actually supports two kinds of format, text and binary.
But probably you don't want to write directly into wasm.
For example, assembly probably in this year no one writes in assembly directly.
But if you want you can do that.
But probably you want leverage on different languages.
For example, C, C++, Rust, Go and so on.
But if you remember the previous slide we talked about the memory safe of the WebAssembly
and which is the other language that remember has a similar capability.
Rust because Rust guarantee memory safety.
And this is why we are here to talk about Rust plus WebAssembly.
So which is the constraint we have for building wasm in Rust?
Unfortunately we are not so free to use what we want.
We need to put an attribute wasm in gen in all type of export.
So structure and so on, but not linked to that.
Also the implementation block we need to treat like that.
So put the same attribute on top of the implementation block.
And unfortunately wasm doesn't understand all the types available in Rust.
So by our integer but not all the integer supported 14 points and vector.
We have some limitation about that.
Has consequence, for example, enumeration need to be treated as a use 80.
And all the values from methods need to be casted to some wasm types or it was in gen
structure.
So we are here to talk about snake.
Who play at least one snake?
At least one.
Okay.
Phew.
For the other snake is a simplest game.
Two grid.
There is a two dimension grid.
Your aim is to win for winning, avoiding the go through a wall and eat yourself.
You are able to eat foods that give you scores and so on.
Your aim is to drive the snake through walls and try to eat the food more or less.
Anyway we will see you later.
So our code is here.
Is a cargo workspace with three members.
The first one is just plain Rust implementation of game logic without wasm stuff, without
any other part.
The second one is handmade snake that is just a wrapper on the previous one in order to
let a JavaScript world to import it and use it.
So we implement the web interface manually through JavaScript and DOMS.
And the last is a plugin that allows us to create a proficiency, more proficiency than
manual ones.
A game.
The last two members use the first one.
And we will see how.
So conceptually we have a bunch of stuff.
A direction that allows us to describe which is the direction the snake have.
The point because we live inside a grid.
So we have to somehow describe the point.
The game itself, private stuff, but mainly we have two members.
Tick and get the last snapshot.
Tick allows us to move the snake in the direction specified there.
And the last snapshot allows us to know what happened in the last tick.
For example, I eat a food, I go through the wall, which is my score, which is the position,
and last but not least, the period duration.
Because you know in the game the interval between the ticks change accordingly with
your score.
So the game more go on than the period decrease.
So how we can use hopefully you read the code.
Cross the finger.
Anyway, I describe it.
We have a level.
Describe it has a simple way through a string.
We can parse it creating a game.
We invoke a tick method on the game describing which is the direction we want to use.
Get the last snapshot, check status.
For example, in this case I eat a food because the age goes on the food.
We are not yet on the wall and the game over is none.
Instead the code below goes through the wall.
So on the wall is true and the game over is some with the reason.
And finally we have two public levels.
Snake one is the two.
The difference probably you know but for repeating the difference is the frame.
So in snake one we have a frame with all the walls.
Instead snake two is more like a toroid.
So you can go left and appear on the right and appear on the ground.
So how we can use this.
We have snake core.
Again, without any dependency.
We need to repeat because we already seen.
We have some deficit about that.
We have some custom JavaScript code that interact with DOM in order to update the UI.
Which is more like what happened.
And at compilation time after the compilation actually we have a process for compilation.
The last code into a wasm and this compilation generates two artifacts actually.
The wasm itself and the auto generated JavaScript module that allows us to simplify the interaction
with the wasm module.
Remember that the same JavaScript code in the same DOM.
So more or less what we have is wasm and auto generated JavaScript that allows us a lot.
So shortly we need to wrap all the stuff.
All the stuff.
So the direction, the point, the game, the snapshot and so on.
So definitely we are not able to do that for a large project.
Obviously this works for a little once like snake but if you want to build a bigger one
probably is not the best solution.
But if you want instead create a cartographic library, hashing library, something like that,
this is really amazing.
It's sufficient.
But for the gaming probably not so much.
So before seeing which is our alternative we have a demo that you can find in the code.
So let's see if it works properly.
Obviously yes.
Here.
Because I haven't the framework that helped me to build a better UI, I choose this one
sorry, I'm not a UI expert.
So for our purpose is sufficient.
As you can see here there is some bootstrap webpack blah blah blah, we don't care at all.
But at the third point we download wasm.
Wasm is a few kilobytes, so not so big.
And the user is able to choose which the game he would like to play, click on here and move
with the arrow key.
Not whoa but why not whoa.
Thanks.
Okay.
Obviously when I go through the wall the game is put on wall.
And not the best user experience we have but sorry.
So we will see the code together in the final Q&A session.
So sorry.
Time to strain it.
So which is our alternative?
Our alternative there are many alternatives obviously.
I chose Bevy engine because I like it.
I didn't find again I web developer so for gaming stuff I don't understand nothing.
But Bevy engine allow me to put something in short time so good stuff guys, good stuff
team.
And support across platform as well.
Windows Mac, Windows and obviously web.
The pattern used is a CS, entity component system.
Entity is just an ID that you can put on the wall.
And the component is a tag, something you can attach to an entity like image, like a
position, like something like that.
And system is a function that work on those stuff.
Can add the entity remove the component, remove a component, move existing component and so
on.
So more or less how Bevy works, each frame invokes Bevy runs our function called system.
Let change add remove components and entities.
That allow us to change our worlds.
And finally Bevy render some of them obviously on the screen.
So conceptually this is what I understand in two years at night obviously is not my
job again.
So it is almost simplest to understand.
Last stuff to introduce of Bevy, we have another concept I need to introduce.
Event is a plain object that allow us to be fired and to be listened.
So we can inform other function, other systems that something happens.
And the resources is just a global instance because system is allowed to access only on
the world, not our custom objects.
So you need to put your resources on the world and fetch it inside the system.
And a nice feature, Bevy tracks when a resource changes.
We will see later.
So how can you them?
A system for example firing events that is listened by system two that on that event
change accordingly a resource A and the system three more or less react on that change.
For example moving the snake.
So let's have a look to a more detailed example on the code skipping the arguments because
it is not important to understand better what I would like to show.
Mostly because systems runs every frame, we don't want to tick on every frame.
We want to wait a time here.
So you know also for test proposing, this is nice.
So we need to wait the tick event.
So only when the tick event is fired, we call tick method on game.
Game is on the third argument that the game resources obviously is the game we saw before.
After that we get the snapshot to check if the game over is we are in game over.
If yes, we send, we fire a game over event.
After that we update the snake position, update the resource score, update the food and duration
of the timer because you know the period can change.
Nice stuff to be focused on is the if because we don't want to change if the real value
is changed.
Maybe leverage on the refmute.
So it is important to not refmute before the real change.
So have a look at a quick demo.
After the demo we can see the code.
I promise.
So again, the demo, I propose you to show the native part.
So this is our windows that is created natively.
Again I can choose next one with button this time.
And again, it is not my job but this is what I implemented.
So as you can see under the hood there is some locks and in front of you should be at
least the snake that runs through the table.
And this is the way I handled the game over.
And obviously quit closed the windows.
So we have three different states in our game and in our code I treat these in three different
packages, sub-packages.
Choose game, play game and game over.
And as you probably understand we can leverage on event system to bring the user from one
state to another one.
Also because it is written there.
So let's focus on the play state because probably the most important one.
So what we need to do in the play state?
Probably we need to surely when we enter in that state we create the resource, the dedicated
resource and make the initial draw.
After that we already saw we need to wait the key event called game methods.
Update the position, update the foot position and the square number.
And surely we do not forget them handling the press key and the file the game tick.
So this is the last slides.
After that we can run in we will see the output and the code.
So the graphical representation we have in red the system so the function.
Handle keyboard input that update the direction resource.
We will see it before when I press the key the direction resource change.
And game tick is the function that wait six seconds.
So after six seconds since game tick event, listen by tick system, that update after calling
tick on the game all the resources.
Because the resource change I can update accordingly the score of the snake and the food.
Why I started like that because the last three systems I mentioned the score of the snake
up the foods can be paralyzed by bevy, bevy has a system that allow you to automatically
paralyze the system.
If he understood that is paralyzable.
For example, doesn't access immutable way on the same stuff.
So show me the code but probably show me the result also.
If you want.
You want.
Okay.
So I built it in release mode.
And this is important.
Refresh the page.
Okay.
As you can see here we have 60 megabytes not kilo.
But not in release mode this heavy up to 70 mega if I remember correctly.
So crazy.
Snake one.
Obviously the same user experience, the same go.
Yes.
Sorry.
The same user experience.
And as you can see here there is the logs also.
Nice feature is that he also link to the particular lines.
And it is amazing at least from my point of view.
So let's dig into the code.
So we have time.
Apparently, yes.
So here we have the handmade snake.
I remember that this is just a wrapper around our core implementation.
As you can see here there is a JavaScript API from the WebAssembly package we described
before.
The other part is just the tracing, for example, a different allocation.
The second dependency allows us to print a message on panic, for example.
And the first is the was being done.
So because I don't lie, not now, at least, here we have all the being done attributes
with all the enumeration, the structures, and so on.
And here under this folder we have the classic webpack frontend stuff.
I really don't know what is this.
So for building it, I use waspack that allows us to translate in wasm and used in the handmade
package.
Instead, the snake is built using track that allows us to somehow transform all the rest
plus index.html into a web application directly.
And if you are question how it works, why we made handmade snake and the baby snake,
which is the main difference under the hood, the answer is this.
Sorry.
I can't.
Okay.
This is the public repository on GitHub.
And here, as you can see, there is a web system, another API that allows us to interact with
the DOM world.
So at the last side, we can change the canvas because under the hood there is the canvas.
So more or less, I have done.
Thank you.
If there is any questions, I will be happy.
Be kind.
So we have about five minutes for questions.
Can we have a show of hands for questions?
Have you ever played around with much more entities than maybe like 100,000 or 1 million
entities?
Good question.
No, I didn't.
I know that the limitation here is the thread number.
We have in JavaScript, we have in browser.
If you don't use WebWorker, for example, you don't able to scale on this part.
Bevy is not using WebWorker, at least for the time being.
So he is not able to parallelize.
And for this reason, probably you can find a limitation.
There is no Internet, but in the Bevy engine website, there is a dedicated example.
Also, ship has Wasm, so you can find it and give me the answer, please.
Thanks.
Thank you very much.
How are you feeling?
Seems to be good.