Hello, everyone.
Yeah, my name is Michel Senna.
So I work for Microsoft and I'm mostly the main of Landlark,
which is a new schedule Linux feature.
It's about soundbusing.
So this talk is about Rose Library.
We wrote for Landlark.
And well, we kind of had some changes about compatibility.
So yeah, just quick introduction context
to understand the pro-oriented here.
So yeah, why care about security?
So here, well, it might be abuse for some.
But like every application can be compromised.
Every operation can be trusted at first.
And during the lifetime of a process,
it can become malicious.
So yeah, as developers, there's multiple problems.
So we don't want to participate to malicious actions
performed by attackers through our software.
And we kind of have a responsibility for users,
especially to protect their personal data.
And yeah, there might be some issues about third party code.
So security soundboxing is a security approach
to isolate software and mainly to isolate them
by dropping ambient access rights.
So in Intel, when you launch an application in a common
system, this application can access a lot of files,
including some which are kind of private, like.ecc for example.
So sound mixing should not be confused
with namespaces and containers, which
is a way to create kind of a virtualized environment.
And second is also something which
is really interesting for security purposes.
But it's not about access control.
It's about protecting the current.
That was initially the initial goal of second.
So Landmark is really dedicated from the ground
to bring sound making features to Linux
to bring some security features to the kernel.
So it is an access control system
available to every processes.
You don't need to be a root or whatever.
And it is designed to be embedded in applications,
so to create built-in soundboxing.
It's a way to create one or even multiple layers
of new securities.
So it comes kind of after all system-wide access
control, which are already in place.
And so it's available on most distros nowadays.
And if it is not the case, well, I
want you to open an issue in your favorite distro.
So about sandboxing here, what's the interesting point
about sandboxing and built-in application security?
If, well, that we can create tailored security policies
and embedded them in the application.
So there's interesting things about that.
And that might help to make it security invisible, which
is kind of the main purpose here.
We want to not bother users, but secure them anywhere.
So because this security policy can be
embedded in the application, well, it
can use the application semantic.
It can use the application configuration transparently,
so you don't need to add another configuration stuff.
It's not another layer of execution.
It's embedded in the application.
And of course, well, if the confusion
depends on user interaction, well,
it can adapt to this change of behavior.
And one really interesting point is, well, as a developer,
you want to test what you do.
And you want to kind of get guarantees
that whatever you're developing is still working.
And being able to embed the security policies
in your application, make it possible to test them
the same way that you can test every other features.
So that's really interesting.
You don't rely on, let's say, a Linux
being installed on your test machine and so on.
And it adapts to the application over time.
So if you have a TI, which is well configured,
you can test it and make sure that, well, you
can add new features, adjust the security policy,
and make sure that everything works as expected.
So speaking about the library and the Rust library,
so the idea was to create something which is rusty,
so I don't want it to rust.
And for this, well, we wanted to leverage strong typing,
so to get some developing guarantees,
and also to follow some common patterns.
So many here, the builder pattern.
So it's still working for us.
It's working.
But we're working on improving the API
and make it easier and more easy to use
for competitive reasons.
So this talk about this kind of compatibility requirements.
And so I'll talk about that.
Some examples of early public users are listed here.
But it's still in kind of beta, for now.
So let's start with some code example.
So just as a warning, this kind of simplified code,
it's working.
But yeah, for the demo, well, it's not demo,
but for these examples, the idea is
to make it simple to make it easier to understand.
So you can see at the left, there's a C code.
And at the right, the exact same semantic, but in Rust.
So I will mostly talk about the Rust code.
But yeah, you can take a look at the C code
to kind of see the difference between them
and how Rust can be useful there.
So as I said, it is based on the builder pattern.
So you create a rule set object here with the rules and you.
And from there, you kind of call different methods
to build the object here.
In this case, a rule set.
So rule set will contain a set of rules.
And yeah, at first, you define what you want to enforce,
what do we want to restrict, what
do we want to deny by default. So in this case,
these are two actions.
They are shown to execute files and they
are shown to write on files.
So obviously, it's not enough.
But in this case, it's easy to understand
for a simple use case.
And then once you define the rule set
and what the rule set can handle, well, you can create it.
And the rule set creation translates to,
you can see at the left, there's a landmark trade rule set.
And this function is, in fact, a syscall.
So in the rough part, when you call the create method,
it creates a new rule set, which is backed underneath
by a new file descriptor dedicated to landmark.
And that is a wrap in the rule set object.
Then if you want to add rules to allow some directory to be,
for example, executable, which is the case here,
so you append the slash user directory,
and you make it executable, so elo access, xfs execute.
And then you can add other rule you want.
For all the exceptions, that should
be legitimate for the legitimate use case.
And then you restrict the current process.
Well, in fact, the current thread.
And from this point, the current thread
can only execute files which are in slash user.
And it cannot write anything at all, actually.
So that was a tradition, quick introduction to the library.
And the thing is, another key is not a full feature access
control yet, because, well, it is complex.
And well, to reach this goal, well,
we need to spend much more years to increment,
well, to add new features to the link scale.
And the thing is, well, sometimes you
might add new features that enable to restrict more.
And sometimes we might add some features to restrict less.
So let's see what this means.
So the first version of Landlok, which
was released with 5.13 kernel, basically allowed
to read, write, and do a lot of common stuff
to restrict a lot of common file-stem actions.
But there was, like you can see here, there's three categories.
The first one, always denied, was
for the first version of Landlok,
the actions that were always denied whenever
you sandboxed a thread.
So that was for, well, complexity in the development,
but also security reasons.
So for example, you are not able to execute set to AD binaries,
because it will be kind of a way to bypass the sandbox.
And there was some restriction on ptrace,
so you're not allowed to debug an application process, which
is outside the sandbox.
Obviously, it will be a way to get out a sandbox.
That's not what we want.
So the second version of Landlok had its new way,
a new access write, which was a way to repound files.
So at first, it was denied to change the parent victory
of a file for security reasons, because Landlok is based
on Fy-Arkey's identification.
And that was kind of complex.
But with the second version, we implemented that.
And then it became configurable.
So one item last in the always denied box.
In the third version of Landlok, all these versions
are new kernel releases.
And in the third version, we added a new way
to restrict Fy congregation.
So congregation in Landlok is to change the size of a file.
And this was always allowed before,
because it wasn't end up.
It was a bit complex to implement this
in the kernel at the time.
But now it is possible.
So you can see that we can move items from the always
denied box to the configurable, and from the always
allowed box to the configurable list.
So application compatibility.
There's two main things in compatibility.
There's forward compatibility in a way that when you update
your kernel, you still can use the old kernel features.
So that's kind of common.
And the backward compatibility in this case
is when you're using a kernel feature,
well, you might need a specification of the kernel
that supports this feature.
And if your application is launched on an old kernel,
well, that feature might be missing.
And the thing is, when you're developing an application,
well, you don't know on which kernel your application will
run, because, well, it's a user choice and a disk choice.
What comes with Landlok is the ability
to get the Landlok what we call the ADI version.
So it's really just a number.
That increment is started at one,
and then increment for each new set
of features which is added to the kernel.
So to give you an idea, it's really
simple to get this ID, this version.
It's with Landlok rate rules at Cisco with a specific flag.
So yeah, it's a T code, but it's really simple.
So what we want to do at first was these four main properties.
The first one is to be able to make it easy to use
for developers, of course.
So we want something which is generic, which
kind of follows the build-up pattern, because, well,
it's kind of common and easy to use.
We want developers to focus on what they want to restrict,
not the implementation in the kernel.
And we want them to gradually go from a coarse-grained access
restriction to a fine-grained one.
So we don't want them to need to implement a fine-grained at
first.
It might be difficult to difficult.
So yeah, it's the same way that we can incrementally
add new set of features.
We can also incrementally restrict more and more
over time.
No need to be super strict at first.
And yeah, it should be simpler to write for the common cases.
OK, at first, the first improvement was to create group
access writes.
So let's say you know which landlord version is supported
by the running kernel.
Let's say it's the second version.
Then you can create a new rule set, which will get all the
access writes which are supported by this specific
kernel.
So you just call the handle access with the access from
all and then ABI2.
And then you can do kind of the same when you're adding a
new rule.
And this time, well, you want to add an exception on the
slash result to make it readable.
So in this case, there's two main groups, the from read
and the from writes.
And for example, the from read includes reading a file, but
also reading a directory.
Listing a directory.
OK, second property that we would like to have is being
able to enforce a strict restriction.
So even if we don't know on which kernel the
eviction will run, on some cases, we might want to be sure
that all features are enforced and restricted.
There's two use cases here.
The first one is to test it.
If you want to sandbox some applications, you want to make
sure that even if you're using all the
standard scheme features, well, your application will
work as expected.
So that's really important.
And you don't want to run your application in an old kernel
and kind of be fooled by the fact that your
application is running because there's no, well, not all
security features are enabled.
So you want to cut these kind of issues in your CI.
And also for security software, well, you want to
have some security guarantees.
So you want to have a way to fold the whole sandboxing with
all security features that we embedded in our application.
The third property is to be able to enforce the best
security with some minimal requirements.
So that's kind of the opposite.
And this use case is mainly for end users because end user,
well, you don't know which kernel to be used.
And so you want to be able to enforce an
opportunistic sandboxing.
So if they have a new kernel, well, they will be more
protected.
If they have an old kernel, they might not be protected
at all, but that's not your choice.
That's their choice.
And at the end, they want to run your application anywhere.
So another requirement is to be able to disable the whole
sandboxing.
If some features which are required may not be met.
And this approach should be easier to write than others
because it is the most common thing to do.
And the last property is being able to run, well, to
configure at runtime the sandboxing, but to make it in
a way that you're running most of the codes.
So the idea is to be able to have kind of the same code
running everywhere almost, even if they don't
have a recent kernel.
Why that?
Because you want to kind of identify early kind of some
issues which might be linked to the sandboxing code.
And that's if you have, let's say, two users using a
recent kernel and four users using an old kernel, well, you
might want to test as much as possible with all your users,
even if they don't have a newer kernel.
So the first approach we took was, so I'll go quickly here.
There's three approaches.
The first one was to add a new meter to the
rule set builder pattern.
So it was a simple method to set the best for approach.
So if it was false, it was required to add these features.
So in the example, an application that need to move
files from one degree to another needed to add the
accessFS refer access rights to allow this access.
And if it wasn't the case, well, the thumb making should
not be enforced.
Otherwise, it will break the application.
So that is a requirement.
And in this case, that was a way to change the state of
the builder over time.
So this is flexible, easy to understand, but in some
current cases.
And it makes the code not really clean.
Another approach was to do the same, but this time, instead
of two shifts, enable or disable, there were three ways
to change it.
The best effort way, the soft requirement, and the hard
requirement.
So a way to make it best effort, a way to make it
error if there is any unsupported feature, and a way
to disable the sandbox without error if some
feature were not supported.
So that wasn't ideal, neither.
And the last approach, which is currently working for us, is
kind of a new one.
So the idea is to make it still configurable and to follow
all these properties, but to make it a bit simpler and
still flexible.
So here in actual, well, you can make a new rule set that
will error out if there's any unsupported features.
But at the same time, you can specify which feature is
required to enable the sandbox or not.
So that's kind of specific, but yeah, it should be better.
So going forward, there's a lot going on in this first
library, a lot to improve.
You have a new helper, you get a recommendation.
And I encourage you to send back your
addiction or others.
And well, there's some tips if you want to get some
motivation here.
It's a rewards program.
So thank you for attention.
There's some interesting link here.
This talk was kind of a dance, but I hope you enjoyed.
Thank you.