So, we have Samuel here to talk about Pydantic 2 and how it leverages Rust superpowers.
Thank you very much.
Can you hear me at the back?
Great.
So, a bit about me.
I'm Samuel.
I've been a software developer for 10 years, among other things.
I've been doing open source quite a lot for the last five years.
Mostly Python projects, but moving a bit into Rust over the last few years.
The most high profile Python project that I maintain is Pydantic, which I started back
in 2017 and has subsequently kind of taken over my life.
I've been working on it full time for the last year.
So, what I'm going to talk about today.
I'm going to give you an introduction to Pydantic, some hype numbers for vanity, but also for
some context of why making Pydantic better is worthwhile.
I'm going to explain why I decided to rebuild Pydantic completely.
I'm going to talk about how I've done that with Rust and I guess most importantly why
doing it in Rust is the right choice.
I guess I'm preaching to the converted, but hey.
What I'm not going to do is hello world, this is how you would build a Python extension
in Rust.
There were lots of other talks on that.
They're great.
And also the PYO3 documentation is amazing.
So I think it's more interesting to go into a bit of depth on the challenges, the advantages,
than just to do the hello world example again.
What is it?
Well, Pydantic is a data validation library in Python.
It's not the first.
It's definitely not the last.
It started off as a side project like so many open source projects.
Nothing special.
I maintained it in my spare time.
People came along occasionally.
Said nice things, reported bugs.
Occasionally said not very nice things.
And then something weird happened.
And its usage went crazy.
So the first thing that happened, which you can't really see on this graph in 2018, my
friend Sebastian Ramirez started the fast API project, which is a web framework in Python
which uses Pydantic and has now got, I don't know, how many thousand stars, 60,000 stars
or something.
It's got a lot of attention.
You can see fast API's growth there.
That got a lot of people, I think, to first find out about Pydantic.
But something else happened at the beginning of 2021 to cause Pydantic's download numbers
to go crazy.
Now, I'm well aware that Aaron Armin's speech talk earlier kind of pre-trolled me before
I even made my talk saying that download numbers are a terrible metric.
But they are the only metric.
So that's what we have to use.
It's also worth saying that I have actually looked at Pydantic's downloads in terms of
as a dependency and as a direct download.
It's not that easy to do with PyPI, but it looks like about 15 million downloads a month
are from as a dependency of another package.
And the remaining 25 or so million are people installing Pydantic directly.
So it seems like people are using it not just as a dependency of another library.
I've included Django on there as the middle line because it's the most high profile, most
well-known web framework in Python.
Not to be critical of it.
It's amazing.
It's like changed my life.
I mean, no disrespect by saying we've overtaken it, but just that Pydantic's usage has gone
mad.
In terms of how it's used, it's used by lots of organizations you would expect.
All the fan companies, something like 19 out of the top 25 companies in NASDAQ, but also
by organizations which you wouldn't expect like JP Morgan.
Use it quite a lot.
I don't know in what regard.
But it's quite interesting.
If you have an open source project, if you look in analytics at the referrers, lots of
those big, very security-centric companies forget to turn off the referrer header from
their internal systems.
And they name their internal systems things like github.jpmorgan.net.
So you can see which companies are using your dependencies by looking at those referrers.
So, for example, Apple have no public demonstration of using Pydantic at all, but six different
enterprise instances of GitHub within Apple use Pydantic, and you can even see which ones
they are.
They're like maps.github.maps.apple.com, github.siri.apple.com, et cetera.
It's also used by some cool organizations, used by NASA for processing imagery from James
Webb and used by the International Panel on Climate Change for processing the data they
give to the UN on climate change every month, which is the stuff I'm most proud of and why
I want to make Pydantic better.
So what's so great about Pydantic?
Why are so many people using it?
The short answer is I don't know.
Because you can't go and ask those people.
You can look at a graph, but it can't really tell you.
But we can look at Pydantic and what people say, and we can guess at what's made it popular.
So this is, I know we're in the Rust room.
We've got some Python code.
Don't worry.
We'll get to Rust later.
This is some Python code that demonstrates what Pydantic does.
So we have a model which represents a talk which has four fields in this case.
Obviously, title is a string.
Attendance is an integer.
Number of people who came when, which is a date time or none and has a default value
of none.
And then the mistakes I make, which is a list of tuples with the time they were made at
and a description.
And then lastly, last line, we instantiate an instance of talk using that data.
And if there was a mistake, we would get an error.
If there wasn't a mistake, we'd obviously get the instance.
The first thing that makes Pydantic special and the reason that people like it is because
we use Python type hints to define the types.
That's become reasonably commonplace now.
There are a whole suite of different libraries that do the same thing.
Either because it's obvious or because they're copying Pydantic.
But Pydantic was the first to do that because type hints were kind of new in 2017.
And obviously, the main advantage is it's easy to learn.
You don't need to learn a new kind of DSL to define stuff.
But it's also compatible with static type checking with all the rest of your code, with
your IDE.
Once you defined your model, and if Pydantic's worked correctly, then you know you've got
a proper instance of talk.
So the frustration that caused me to create Pydantic was that type annotations existed.
They sat there in the code.
You could read them, but they did nothing at runtime.
And so effectively, could we try and make them work?
The second and slightly more controversial thing that Pydantic does, which I think is
one of the reasons that people find it easy to use, is because we default to coercion.
So you can see a tendency there, although it needs to be an integer.
It's defined as a string.
Pydantic will automatically coerce from, for example, a valid string to an integer.
But it'll also do other coersions that are a bit more commonplace, like coercing a string
as an ISO date format into a date time object.
And same for the durations.
Some people hate that.
Some people complain about it a lot.
I suspect lots of people who don't even realize they're using it.
They process environment variables, or JSON, or URL arguments, and they're always strings.
And Pydantic just works, and they don't even see it.
A few other reasons I think were quite popular.
We're fast-ish.
We're friendly-ish on the bug tracker.
I don't promise not to ever be cross of people.
And we're reasonably feature complete.
So that was Pydantic.
It's great.
Lots of people are using it.
What's the problem?
Well, it started off as a side project for me.
It wasn't designed to be successful, and the internals stink.
I'm very proud of what Pydantic is doing in terms of how it's being used.
I'm not proud of what's under the hood.
And so I've been keen for a long time to fix the internals.
Also second way in which Armin kind of trolled me before my talk was talking about API compatibility.
We're going to have to break a lot of things in Pydantic v2 to get it right.
But that's the right thing to do, I think, to get the future API to be correct and stable
and not break again.
And while we're building v2, why don't we do some other stuff?
So make it even faster.
It's already quite fast.
But if you think about that number of downloads, you think about the number of CPU cycles globally
every day devoted to doing validation with Python.
That's currently in with Pydantic.
That's currently all in Python.
That's probably quite a lot of carbon dioxide that's being released effectively unnecessarily
because we could make Pydantic significantly faster.
Strict mode I already talked about because, well, often you don't need it.
There are legitimate cases where you want strict mode.
We have functional validators which is effectively running some Python code to validate a field.
They're useful, but they would be more useful if they could operate like an onion.
So like middleware where you take both a value and a handler and call the handler if you
want to.
Once you've done some processing of the value, that would be super valuable.
Another thing we could add, composability.
So Pydantic, as I showed you earlier, is based on a Pydantic model.
Often your root type doesn't need to be a Pydantic model or shouldn't be a Pydantic model.
It might be a list, might be a tuple, it might be a list of models, it might be a type dict
which is a common new type in Python.
And then lastly, maintainability.
Since I maintain Pydantic, I want maintaining it to be fun.
So about a year ago last March, I started as a kind of experiment, could I rebuild some
of it in Rust a year later?
I'm still working on it full time and we're nearly there.
So what does it mean to do some validation, to validate Python data in Rust?
What's the process?
Well, phase one, we need to take a Pydantic model and convert it to a Rust structure.
So unlike libraries like Curd, we're not compiling models in Rust.
The compiled Rust code doesn't know anything about the models it's going to receive because
obviously Python developers don't want to be compiling Rust code to get their model
to work.
So we have to have a, in Rust terms, dynamic definition of our schema which we could then
use for validation.
The way we build that is effectively these validators which are structs that contain
both characteristics of what they're going to validate but also other validators recursively
such that you can define complex structures.
So in this case, our outermost validator is a model validator which effectively just instantiates
an instance of talk and sets its attributes from a dictionary.
It contains another validator which is a typedict validator which contains the definition of
all the fields which have effectively the key that they're going to look for and then
a validator that they're going to run.
The first two are reasonably obvious.
I've added a few constraints to show how you would manage those constraints.
And then the third one, the when field is obviously a union which in turn contains a
vec of validators to run effectively in turn to try and find the value.
And then the last one which is the kind of more complex type contains this list validator
which contains two-pool validator which contains two more validators.
And we can build up effectively infinitely complex schemas from a relatively simple,
I say relatively simple, principle at the outset which is we have a validator, it's
going to contain some other stuff.
So what does that look like in code?
I said I was going to show you some Rust code.
I'm going to show you some Rust code because I think this is the most clear way of explaining
what it is that we do.
So the root of everything is this trait validator which contains effectively three things.
It contains a const, a static string which is used for defining, as I'll show you later,
which validator we're going to use for a given bit of data build which is a simple function
to construct an instance of itself in the generic sense.
And then the validate function that goes off and does the validation.
We then take all of those, well, we then implement that trait for all of the common types that
we want.
So I think we have 58, 48 or so different validators.
And then we bang all of them into one massive enum.
Then the magic bit which is provided by enum dispatch which is a Rust crate that effectively
implements a trait on an enum if every member of that enum implements that trait.
Effectively it goes and does a big procedural macro to create an implementation of the function
which is just a big match choosing which function to call.
But it's significantly faster than DINE.
And in fact in some cases it can abstract away everything and be as fast as just calling
the implementation directly.
So I said earlier that we needed to use this constant, the expected type.
We use that in another effectively big enum to go through and we take the type attribute
out of this schema which is a Python dictionary and we use that to effectively look up which
validator we're going to go and build.
And again, I've shown a few here but there's obviously a bunch more.
This in real life is not implemented as a big match statement like this.
It's a macro that builds this function but it's clearer here if you get the idea.
So I showed you earlier this validate function and I kind of skipped over the input argument.
So the input argument is just an implementation of a trait.
That trait input is like the beginnings of which are defined here.
And it effectively gives you all the things that the validation functions are going to
need on a value.
So is none, strict string, lack string, int, float, et cetera, et cetera, but also more
complex types like date, date time, dictionary, et cetera, et cetera.
And then we implement that trait on both a Python value and on a JSON value which means
that we can parse Rust directly without having to go via Python.
That's super valuable for two reasons.
One for performance reasons.
So if our input is a string and if we were to then parse it into Python objects and then
take that into our validator and run all of that, that would be much lower than parsing
in Rust and then running the validator in Rust straight away.
The other big advantage is to do with strict mode.
So I said earlier that people want strict mode but they say they want strict mode but
often they don't.
So what people will say is I want totally strict Python, why isn't it strict?
And then you'll say do you want to load data from JSON and they say of course I do.
And you say how are you going to define a date?
And they'll say I use a standard date format.
That's not strict then.
You're parsing a string.
And they're like oh, that's fine because it should know in that case it's coming from
JSON.
Well, obviously, how are we going to do that?
By parsing JSON directly and in future potentially other types, we can implement our strict date
method both on that JSON input, we can say well, we're in JSON, we don't have a date
type so we're going to have to do something so we're going to parse a string.
And the strict date implementation for JSON will parse a string.
And therefore we can have a strict mode that's actually useful which we wouldn't have had
if we couldn't have had in Python where the validation logic doesn't know anything about
where the data is coming from.
Even if we have a parse JSON function, all it's doing is parsing JSON to Python and then
doing validation.
So then that's all very well.
That defines effectively how we do our validation.
What's the interface to Python?
So that's where we have this schema validator Rust struct which using the PyClass decorator
is also available as a Python class.
And all it really contains is a validator which of course can in turn contain other
validators as I said earlier.
And it's implementation which are all then exposed as Python methods are new which just
construct it so we call the build validator and get back an instance of our validator
which we then store and return the type.
Actually this is much more complicated.
One of the cleverest and most infuriating bits of Python core is that we, as you can
imagine this schema for defining validation becomes quite complex.
It's very easy to make a mistake.
So we validate it using Python core itself.
Which when it works is magic and when it doesn't work leads to impossible errors because obviously
all of the things that you're looking at as members of dictionaries are in turn the names
of bits of validation.
So it's complete hell but it works and it makes it very hard to build an invalid or
not build the validator that you want.
And then we have these two implementations, two functions which do validate Python object
as I said earlier which core validate and same with JSON where we pass a JSON using
Serd to a JSON value and then call validate again with that input.
This code is obviously heavily simplified so that it fits.
It doesn't fit on the page but nearly fits on the page.
So not everything is exactly as it really is but I think that kind of gives you an idea
of how we build up these validators.
The other thing missed here, we also do the whole thing again for serialization.
So the serialization from both a Python model to a Python dictionary and from a Python model
straight to JSON is all written in Rust and it does useful things like filtering out elements
as you go along and it's effectively the same structure, uses the same schema but it's just
dedicated to serialization rather than rather than validation.
So what does the Python interface then look like?
So this is so what I didn't explain earlier is that Python v2 which is going to be released
fingers crossed in Q1 this year is made up of two packages.
We have Python itself which is a pure Python package and then we have Python core which
is almost all Rust code.
We have a little bit of a shim of Python to explain what's going on but it's really just
the Rust code I've been showing you.
So what Pydantic now does, all that Pydantic effectively takes care of is converting those
type annotations I showed you earlier into a Pydantic core schema and then building a
validator.
So looking at an example here, we obviously import schema validator which I just showed
you from, that's come up at the wrong time, from Pydantic core and then we, the base level,
the base validator which in turn, the schema for the base validator is model and it contains
as I said earlier a class which is the Python class to instantiate and another schema which
in turn defines the fields and that inner validator is then defined by a typedict validator
as I said earlier.
So this is completely valid Python code, this will run now.
So yeah, we have a typedict validator which contains fields which in turn are those fields
which I showed you earlier.
So title attendance is of type int.
The most interesting thing here is if you look at the when validator, it gets a bit
confusing.
It is, its schema is of type default which in turn contains another schema which is of
type nullable which is a kind of the simplest union, either a value or none.
The default validator contains another member which is the default value, in this case none.
The inner schema is then nullable which in turn contains another inner schema which is
then the date time.
So that's how we define effectively default values and null or nullable.
So one of the other mistakes in PyLantic in the past was that we kind of conflate, effectively
Python made a mistake about ten years ago where they used, they had a alias for union
of something and none that they called optional which then meant that I didn't want to have
a thing that was called optional but was not optional.
So we conflated nullable with optional in PyLantic and rightly it confused everyone.
So the solution from Python was to start using the pipe operator for unions and to basically
ignore optional.
They can't really get rid of it but they just pretend it didn't really happen.
My solution is to define default and nullable as completely separate things and we're not
going to use the optional type anywhere in our docs, we're just going to use union of
thing and none to avoid that confusion.
And then I think mistakes, I hope it kind of makes sense to you.
Again, it's this like schema within schema within schema which become validator within
validator.
And we take our code as I showed you earlier, run validation, in this case we call validate
Python because we've got some Python code but we could just as well have a JSON string
and call validate JSON and then we have a talk instance which lets us access the members
of it as you normally would.
So where does Rust excel in these applications?
Why build this in Rust?
There are a bunch of obvious reasons to use Rust, performance being the number one, multi-threading
and not having the global interpreter lock in Python is another one.
The third is using high quality existing Rust libraries to build libraries in Python instead
of implementing it yourself.
So I maintain two other Python libraries written in Rust watch files which uses the notify
crate to do file watching and then rtoml which as you can guess is a Toml parser using the
Toml library from Rust.
And the rtoml library is the fastest Python, well Python, Toml parser out there.
And actually watch files is becoming more and more popular, it's the default now with
uvehicle which is one of the web servers.
But perhaps less obviously in terms of where Rust fits in best.
Deeply recursive code as I've just showed you with these validators within validators,
there's no stack and so we don't have a penalty for recursion.
We do have to be very, very careful because as I'm sure you will know if you have recursion
in Rust and you don't catch it, you just get a segfault.
And that would be very, very upsetting to Python developers who have never seen one
before.
So there's an enormous amount of code in Python dedicated to catching recursion.
We have to have two or three different sorts of guard to protect against recursion in all
possible different situations because it's effectively the worst thing that we can have
is that there is some data structure that you can pass to Python which causes your entire
Python process to segfault and you wouldn't know where to even start looking.
So that's a blessing, the lack of a stack is a blessing and a curse.
And then the second big advantage I think of where Rust excels is in these small modular
components.
So where I was showing you before these relatively small in terms of code footprint validators
which in turn hold other ones, there's no performance penalty for having these functions
in Rust.
I say almost because we actually have to use box around validators because they hold themselves
so there is a bit of an overhead of going into the heap but it's relatively small particularly
compared to Python.
And then the lastly, complex error handling.
Obviously in Python you don't know what's going to error and what exceptions you're
going to get in Rust.
Putting to one side the comment about panic earlier, you can in general know what errors
you're going to get and catch them and construct validation errors in the case of pedantic
which is a great deal easier than it would ever have been to write that code in Python.
So the way I want to think about the future development of Python is not as Python versus
Rust but as Python as the user interface for Rust or the application developer interface
for Rust.
So I'd love to see more and more libraries do what we've done with pedantic core and
effectively implement their low level components in Rust.
So I kind of my dream is a world in which thinking about the life cycle of a HTTP request
but you could think the same about some NL pipeline or many other applications, we effectively
the vast majority of the execution is Rust or C but then all of the application logic
can be in Python.
So effectively we get to a point where we have 100% of developer time spent in high
level languages but only 1% of CPU dedicated to actually running Python code which is slower
and is always going to be slower.
I don't think there's ever a world in which someone's going to come up with a language
that is as fast and as safe as Rust but also as quick to write as Python.
So I don't think it should be one versus the other.
It should be building the low level, building the rails, perhaps a bad term but the rails
in Rust and building the train in Python.
It doesn't work but you get where I'm coming from.
On that note, thank you very much.
A few links there, particularly thanks to the PyO3 team who built the bindings for Rust
in Python which is amazing and if you want a laugh there's a very, very funny issue on
GitHub where a very angry man says why we should never use Rust.
So if you want to read that.
I then took some time to take them to pieces which was quite satisfying although a waste
of time.
So have a look at that.
Questions?
First, especially for the sanitation, are you thinking to publish a library of Rust?
The job is already done and you could have a public API in a library already to validate
Rust data.
I'm sorry, I don't understand quite what...
Sorry.
So you wrote the library in Rust so could you publish just an API to validate JSON for
example from Rust instead of through Python?
Absolutely you could and it would be useful if you wanted to somehow construct the schema
at runtime fast but it's never going to be anywhere near as performant as because you
were not compiling...
We can't do anything at compile time.
Secondly, it's currently all completely intertwined with the PyO3 library and the Python types.
So there is a future nascent possible project, Tydantic, which is Pydantic for TypeScript
where we take the PyO3 types, we effectively replace them with a new library which has
a compile time switch between the Python bindings and the JavaScript bindings or the Wasm bindings
and then we can build Tydantic.
That's a future plan but a long way off.
Right now it wouldn't really be worth it because you would get lots to slow down from Python
and from compile time.
So we really need a completely different library just for Rust like you're saying.
Yeah, CERT is amazing.
I don't think I'm going to go and try and compete with that.
At least it's great for that application.
Hi, thanks for the talk.
Personally I think the Python library cryptography introduced Rust and had some complaints from
people using obscure build processes where Rust didn't work.
Are you expecting anything from that?
So I will actually bring up now...
Now I'm going to get into how to...
Effectively go and read that issue where among other things I...
Oh, how do I get out of this mode?
So rant, rant, rant, rant from him, effectively I went through the just over a quarter of
a billion downloads over the last 12 months of Pydantic and I worked out looking at the
distribution of the different operating systems and libc implementations etcetera that 99.9859%
of people would have got a binary if they'd installed Pydantic core then.
That number will be higher now because there will be fewer esoteric operating systems.
Most of the failed ones if you look are actually installing, say they're installing Python
onto iOS.
I don't know what that means or whether it could ever work but...
The other thing I would say is Pydantic core is already compiled to WebAssembly so you
can already run it in the browser.
So I understand why people complained but I think it's not a concern.
It's a straw man for most people.
It's like satisfying slap down.
But again if there's another distribution that we don't, we currently release 60 different
binaries, if there's another one we'll try and compile for it and release the binary.
There's a question right at the back.
I'll get back to the talk rather than...
Is there a way to use the Django models as Pydantic models?
Say again?
To use the Django to have binding or to translate the Django model directly into a Pydantic model?
There's no way at the moment.
There's a number of different ORMs, six I know of, built on top of Pydantic which effectively
allow that.
If you were wanting specifically Django there's a project called Django Ninja that makes extensive
use of Pydantic.
I don't know that much about it.
But if you actually wanted Pydantic models you'd probably want some kind of code reformatter
to convert them.
So I look at Django Ninja, I'm sure what they're doing is the best of what's possible right
now.
If you had additional time, say after finishing Pydantic, are there any other projects where
you'd like to follow this vision of a Rust core with Python user space or API?
There are a number of ones.
There's already OR JSON which is a very, very fast if unsafe in the sense of listed with
unsafe JSON parser which is very, very fast.
There are the obvious one is a web framework where you do like I kind of showed here the
HTTP parsing, the routing all in Rust.
That's not very easy using ASGI.
There are already a few projects doing that.
So that would be the obvious one but there's no winner yet.
Currently the best low level web framework is Starlet which FastAPI is built on which
I think it does use Rust for, it uses a Rust library for HTTP parsing or a C library.
So some of it's already happening but no obvious candidate right now.
What I would say though is libraries like rich, no criticism of will but rich is incredibly
complicated, it's for terminal output, it's not so much performance critical but it's
really quite involved in complex logic.
I would much prefer to write that logic in Rust than Python.
I think there are lots of candidates.
Yeah, what do you mean by Python as the application layer?
I guess I could have added some example code here but you can imagine a Python function
which is a viewpoint in a web framework which takes in some validated arguments done by
Python.
You then decide in Python to make a query to the database to get back the user's name
from the ID and then you return the JSON object containing data about the user.
If you think about that, all of the code outside the Python functions could be written in a
faster language whether it be the database query accessing the database, TSL termination,
HTTP parsing, routing, validation but effectively using Python to define as a way to effectively
configure Rust code or configure compile code.
Yes hello.
I have a question, just a pedantic one.
Is there any support or are you planning any support for alternative schema types like
protobuf or gRPC or Avro?
In the future, what I have a plan for is I don't want to build them into pedantic.
Pedantic is already big but you can parse them to Python now and validate them as a
Python object.
There is a plan effectively to take the this value which you would then construct in Rust,
parse as a Python value into pedantic core which would then extract the raw underlying
Rust instance and then validate that and that would allow you to get basically zero Python
validation effectively.
But without having to us having to either have compile time dependencies or build it
all into pedantic core.
I think that's our last question that we have time for.
One comment we did get from matrix was that this code is a bit small on the display so
if you upload the.
I will do.
Yeah perfect.
So if you're watching the stream, slides will be uploaded and you can read the code.
Oh I'll put them on Twitter as well but yeah definitely I'll upload them as well.
Awesome.
Thank you very much.