So, my talk is about modifying the Rust compiler to support Cherry's hardware capabilities.
I'm going to start off with a brief introduction.
My name is Lewis Revel and I work for a company called Ember Cosm.
I work on many things, but I'd say I specialize in developing LLVM backends for constrained
or unusual architectures.
Ember Cosm itself is a software services company.
We operate in the boundary between hardware and software, particularly in the embedded
space where you can find many unusual, difficult and interesting problems like writing compilers.
So what is Cherry?
It's an acronym capability hardware enhanced Rust instructions.
It's best described as an instruction set extension which can be adapted and applied
to different architectures.
The main feature of Cherry is that you can encode access constraints on memory addresses
using things called capabilities.
Capabilities essentially have metadata alongside memory addresses that allow you to specify
these access constraints.
These can only be operated on using capability operations which replace the normal pointer
operations.
These operations utilize the metadata to enforce those access constraints.
It's worth pointing out there are two modes of operation for Cherry.
There's pure cap mode where all pointers are capabilities.
In hybrid mode, you have pointers by default on normal pointers, but capabilities are annotated
as such in the source code.
So capabilities together with capability operations allow you to enforce spatial, referential
and temporal safety in the hardware at run time.
Spatial safety is to do with disallowing accesses out of bounds of an original allocation.
Referential safety is disallowing accesses without valid provenance.
Temporal safety means that if the lifetime of an object is over, you can no longer access
it through a capability.
What about integrating Cherry and Rust?
We're working on this as part of a project led by our customer, CyberHive.
They're funded in turn by Digital Security by Design, which is a UK government initiative.
CyberHive wants to use Cherry hardware to enhance secure network protocols that are
written in Rust.
The goal for us is to produce a Rust compiler that's capable of targeting Cherry-based
architectures.
With the long-term goal of a stable compiler that can produce production-ready code for
security purposes.
We know that we're initially going to be targeting Arm's Morello platform.
Rather than being able to compile existing Rust code for Cherry, what's the motivation
between integrating Cherry and Rust?
Essentially it boils down to another layer of protection.
We know that Rust is good at identifying and enforcing access constraints at compile time.
With Cherry you can identify constraints at compile time and enforce them in hardware
at run time.
A good example is that Rust code annotated with unsafe is often a necessity in many real
world projects, which means that it could behave badly but we don't know until run time.
With Cherry you can prevent this bad behavior in hardware when it occurs at run time.
There's some other small side benefits such as replacing slow software bounds checks with
hardware bounds checking and replacing pointer plus length types with Cherry capabilities.
To make things more clear I have a motivating example.
Say we want to add a dynamic offset to a pointer and then load from that pointer.
This needs to be done in an unsafe block because we don't know until run time if it's going
to do something bad.
Without Cherry you could end up accessing out of range of your original allocated array.
With Cherry that access will not occur at run time and the hardware will either panic
or give you something, a default value.
Now that we know that we want these benefits, how do we go about modifying Rust to get them?
The main problem is that we need to account for capability sizes correctly.
That is we need to stop assuming that pointer type size is equal to the addressable range
of the pointer.
Because capabilities have metadata this isn't the case.
Also in LLVM, in the Cherry LLVM fork, capabilities are pointers in address space 200 whereas
in Rust we assume that all pointers to data are in address space zero.
Also if we want to support hybrid mode we need to be able to specify different pointer
type sizes for different address spaces.
So address space zero will have different sizes from address space 200.
One thing I hope doesn't require many changes is that we need provenance and bounds to be
propagated through the compiler because they need to be attached to capabilities.
And of course if we want the optional bonus stuff we need to implement that as well.
Progress so far.
So the data layout changes are completed which means that we can correctly specify capability
sizes, both the type size and the addressable range for both pure cap and hybrid mode.
I have modified APIs which produce pointer types to get rid of the assumption that pointers
are in address space zero and now these APIs require an explicit address space parameter.
And the biggest change is that for APIs where we have a where we report a size for a type
this is replaced with a total type size and a size of the value that you can represent.
And yeah, this means that like I said before we can support cherry capabilities.
There's also in the strict provenance API there is an explicit unsafe method of producing
pointers with no provenance from a U size.
And for cherry we need to use cherry operations to set the address of a null capability to
achieve the same result.
What I'm currently working through is trawling through assertion failures that come up when
building the core libraries with this modified compiler.
What still needs to be done?
Well there's almost definitely going to be modifications to the libraries to remove any
assumptions that break for cherry.
There's also the question of how do we specify capability types in hybrid mode?
And because I don't think that Rust annotations are the right tool to specify a specific pointer
as being a capability I think this requires a library solution.
For APIs where I have replaced a size with a type size and added a size of the value
that you can represent we need to go through all of those uses of the type size and see
if they should really be using the size of the value that you can represent.
Because this is the main cause of the errors that I'm seeing in building the libraries.
And of course a lot of testing and polishing is going to be required.
Before I finish the talk I do need to mention that there's ongoing and past work that is
in this same area.
There was a master's thesis from the University of Cambridge and there's another government
funded project from the University of Kent.
And thank you for listening.
Please feel free to check out the code on GitHub or ask me any questions outside.
Thank you.