Hello everyone, I'm Mehdi Bessa, CTO of Metrally Security and today I'm going to present to
you Bastion Lab a secure data privacy friendly framework written in Rust.
Is it working?
Yeah.
It's better this way.
So when making this project we came across one big problem.
Let's say for example you are one hospital and you want to share critical data such as
ECG data, earth rate, respiration rate and so on, for example a startup that is working
on, that has deep learning algorithm to detect anomaly in those data.
The most usual way today is to use a Jupyter notebook that you can isolate from network
and all but unfortunately this is not the appropriate way because Jupyter notebooks
allow arbitrary code execution and with some way you can extract the data without even
the data owner seeing that you did that, which is a big problem mostly with sensitive data.
Earth solution, try to fix this issue.
For example you will not have direct access to data.
You will only have limited operation allowed.
So really what you need to, for example, aggregate the data, only extract what you need, only
do for example some average and calculation on a microsite of data but most importantly
you can only have sanitize and authorize output allowed.
Meaning for example if I don't want the startup or any other actor that work on my dataset
to see the name of my patients or some critical data such as if they have hypertension or
so on, I can just set up in the policy and they will not be able to access that unless
I explicitly authorize it and yet nothing's forced me to accept it.
I'm going to present you very quickly an API.
Don't get mad with me.
The API is in Python because the API is in Python where the server ingress.
So don't get mad yet.
Okay.
Doesn't look as bad as I thought.
Actually it does.
Sorry about that.
Does that work?
No, I think the resolution is not there.
That's okay.
I will go on with just explanation.
That's fine.
No, that's fine.
Ah, thanks.
Sorry about that.
So no Pythons.
They're good for doing away.
But thanks.
All experience with Rust in Berlin Bastion Lab.
We had several reasons to make a project which is the biggest reason memory safety.
I think you know all very well what I'm talking about here.
The very parallel way Rust has to end link multi-trading.
No mutable static unless you use lazy static and not any other technique.
That was a pain to bypass but we did manage.
And the medium-based size thanks to what is being a low-level programming language.
Ideal for trusted execution environments as we are working with such as for example AMD,
ACV, IntelliGX and so on.
The less code base, the less big the code base, the easier it is to audit.
Now for the performance reason.
As I said Rust is a low-level programming language.
Very close to seen term of execution speed.
But the biggest reason is polars because our API relies on it.
Except that we implemented a network stack to never allow anyone to access to the data
directly.
Polar as well offer one of the best performance in working with data sets and so on.
Join, aggregation and so on.
It was the easiest way to do it.
Plus it's in for Rust.
There is no bindings and so on.
Thanks for that.
So you can see here the performance, the benchmark we made.
We use Panda as a reference that is as you can see here more than terrible compared to
polars.
We compare to polars lazy.
All solution that is lazy by default.
Lazy means I'm only executing a query when I strictly need it.
We do it all the time.
That makes a big difference.
Plus I'm working on only the data that I need and not the world data set if I don't need
to.
That's another benchmark on a bigger set.
You can see that Panda is still off the roof and never compared to the other one.
Now though, how did we do that?
We thought to use the best create that are available for doing that.
We wanted to use Tonic and Tokyo because Tonic offered GRPC which will allow us to make
a cloud that is not in Python if we need to.
Thanks to the protobuf that is implemented in many languages and the GRPC protocol as
well.
Polar, as I mentioned it already, rings because in addition of setting up a policy, for example,
if I don't want people to access to a specific two names or whatever, there's that.
But rings, we always ring implementation directly to verify and I need to provide my public key
to access to the server.
We use ring implementation to do that directly and to check if the key match and if the key
is real.
And Tokyo because we are using like EVI like MUD, the multi-threading, the un-synchronous
move and so on.
For example, when you need to accept a dataset, we spawn a new thread that will send a request
to the data owner saying do you want to accept this request that is about to leak sensitive
data?
It's not written this way but it is this yes and can come with now.
Instead of blocking the whole process, I will have a thread that will time out after a while
if I don't access it means I reject it but I can say yes or no and other requests such
as a simple one or not sensitive one will be accepted.
Plus the NSEC move plus Tony, that makes very well together and allow many connections as
we want.
This is the best we could dream of.
As I was about to show, that was supposed to be in the Google collab but it's an easier
representation here, we have for simplistic reason, sorry Python code but only a few lines,
the data owner part that uploads the dataset, set up a policy and for example I can reject
my dataset but I can allow sensitive requests but I want it to log it.
Oh, shit.
Thanks everyone.
Thank you.