Fernando, he's going to talk about using Rust for your network management tools.
Take it away.
All right.
Thank you.
So welcome everyone.
My name is Fernando.
I'm a senior software engineer at Dreyhat.
I work for the networking services team mainly in focus on network management tools.
And today we're going to talk what was our journey building a Rust tool for network management.
So okay.
We did not start with Rust.
We started with Python.
But after some time we decided we wanted to shift to Rust.
So this is two talks in one.
One is how we did build the project in Rust and what we learned when moving from Python
to Rust.
Okay.
So network management.
What's network management?
Basically it's all the operations that you do to configure your networking.
Roots, interfaces, DNS, firewalling, whatever you do, it's network management.
So it's a process that is quite complex because it requires a lot of coordination between
user space and kernel space.
We need to check when we get notification for kernel space because all the tools would
modify the network status.
We also need to communicate with kernel in order to configure stuff.
So it's a quite complex task.
And this is already a tool which is network manager.
It's by default the tool that is in almost all situations used for managing your Linux
network configuration.
And we were willing to use it and we were willing to build in top of network manager
because implementing everything was really, really complex.
So we created NMSstate.
And NMSstate is a tool that communicates with network manager and it's a library with a
command line tool and allows us to configure the network using declarative states.
So you can define what do you want and you don't need to care about how is network manager
or how is the kernel doing.
And what's going to do or what are the dependencies.
You don't need to care about any of that.
NMSstate is going to manage it.
So it makes everything easier.
So as I say, we started to build NMSstate in Python.
And one day we noticed that a lot of our users were willing to chip a binary and not Python
and don't use the Python environment.
And well, there were also some performance issues because we needed to do a lot of operations.
So we decided to give you a try to Rust.
And we have a problem is that we have a library and a binary and we needed to move both of
them to Rust.
And also we already have a big base of users.
So we could not break them and we need to do it in a way that we are going to support
all the features that we already did in Python.
So well, we created our own NMSstate library in Rust.
I will tell you how.
And also the NMSstate CTL tool, which is the command line tool.
All right.
So the first thing is that we are using JAML files and JSON files and we are parsing them.
So in Python this was quite trivial with any schema and we needed to find a way to do it.
In Python we were using dictionaries so that user could create a dictionary and using a
JAML library it was quite trivial to convert that JAML into a dictionary.
We needed something in Rust to do this.
So we end up looking at CTL.
CTL is a framework for serializing, idealizing Rust attack structure efficiently and generally
we use it for JAML adjacent but it supports other formats.
This allows us to keep our declarative state, keep our API.
So that was pretty good.
And we noticed that CTL allows us to implement our own serializers and deserializers.
So that was also a big plus because we could do validation steps and simplify the validation
work when getting the configuration file from the user.
And then there were a lot of decorators on server so it was quite good for creating early
access for creating multiple helper functions and also some conditional deserialization
and serializations.
So here is an example.
For example this is an interface state for a kernel bond and we basically define it is
up, it has an IPv4 address with this address with this prefix length and it is enabled
and then we define the link aggregation options.
So we have the mode options and the ports.
One really good thing that we have is that we have partial editing.
So you can define what you want to change and we are going to merge it with what you
already have configured on the system.
And about the decorators as you can see there we were able to use the decorator for, for
example, accepting numbers, accepting strings, accepting only the number, custom strings,
creating alias, renaming, all of that.
And it was quite good.
So okay.
We communicate with network manager and we communicate with network manager to configure
the network state.
And we have a problem is that before we were using the Libenham bindings, Python bindings,
and they were not available in Rust.
And we tried to create a Rust bindings but it was quite complex because they used g object
and we didn't have g object and it was a big mess.
But we noticed that network manager is providing a Dvas API.
So we say okay, let's use Dvas then.
And we noticed that there is a create which is ZitaVAS and with ZitaVAS we were able to
communicate with network manager using the Dvas API and with the ZitaVAD and we were
able to encode the data structures that we were using to communicate with network manager
and configure the settings that we wanted.
So using this we solved one of the problem which is telling network manager what we want
to do and also fetching what already network manager have which is also important because
all right, there are some options that maybe we do not want to override because the user
configured it that way and for patch LED team that is important.
We need to know what the user configured and what the user want to modify.
So okay, one problem solved.
Then we have another problem.
So network manager does not provide at all real time information from kernel and we needed
that because we also do verification.
So when you configure something, you in a state do a verification step which what it
does is compare what the user defined which what is configured on the system.
And we have a problem because network manager was not providing real time information and
sometimes it took quite sometimes to get the information that we wanted and we were having
some problems on the verification.
So we were looking for a library and we did not find any library that certified our requirements
but we noticed that there is already a Rust-Ned-Link library and Ned-Link is the kernel API for communication
between user page and also I think between kind of components and it was perfect.
We could use Rust-Ned-Link which is an existing library to build another tool which is Nisport.
So Nisport only queries information from kernel and show you in a JAML file or basically proper
data structures.
It was quite good because we had started to contribute to Rust-Ned-Link because Rust-Ned-Link
was an independent project and they didn't support everything so we were able to help
there and currently a lot of people use Rust-Ned-Link and it's a quite big project and probably
the one that most of the people use when need to work with Ned-Link and Rust.
So we have one more problem.
Now we have network manager working, we have verification working, validation working,
we can read the configuration, we can do a lot of stuff but then networking is complex
and there is one thing that is called OBS or OBSDB and they will manager configure OBS
but they do not configure global OBSDB settings and that was a problem because we wanted to
do that.
So how we did?
We basically started to use sockets and using the Rust-SDD library for stream sockets we
were able to communicate with OBSDB, send petitions, read what they already have stored
on the OBSDB and configure whatever OBSDB settings the user want to configure.
So we created our own server JSON, using server JSON libraries we created our own JSON RPC
to communicate with OBSDB.
This is internal of NMS state, we have considered to put it on a separate crate but we did not
yet.
Then we had another problem.
I promise this will end, we are going to have a solution, it will stop at some point.
So we had users, the users were using our Python library and some of them were willing
to move to Rust, some of them were willing to move to Golan but we were already developing
a resolution.
And some of them didn't want to move from the Python code to Rust so what we did is
create bindings and we create plenty of them.
First of all we created C bindings, so C users could use the Rust library, then from the
C bindings we created the Python and Golan bindings.
Finally one of the other problems that we had is that we got a huge integration test
base and we wanted to reuse them.
So with the Python bindings we were able to integrate the Python integration test that
we had into our Rust library.
It was quite cool because we were able to start building the new Rust NMS state but
at the same time using the Python integration test.
And this way we were sure that we were not breaking any existing use case that we already
support.
So that's it.
It was a success.
We are quite proud because most of the people that were using it liked the idea and even
the ones that did not care about if you use Python or Rust were happy because the change
was completely transparent for the final user.
If you were using Python nothing will change for you.
The code is the same.
You don't need to do anything different.
So it will be a transparent update.
And if you are using Python and are willing to use Rust, okay, you need to change your
code but basically the API is the same.
So well, you were able to use the same JAML files and the same JSON files and everything
will work.
So we got a lot of adoptions and right now the user base of NMS state is still growing
and we are quite happy.
Also it was we created goal and bindings because OpenShift people and Kubernetes people were
willing to use it and it's written in goal and so we provided them with goal and bindings
and they really like it.
So yeah, it was a success story.
So basically that was our journey.
I would like to hear, I think we have time for questions.
So please ask whatever you want.
I promise you that I don't know dumb questions.
So thank you very much.
All right, any questions?
Okay.
I had wondered what your experience was in terms of time to implement in Rust versus
Python from a developer point of view.
I think it took us around two years to develop mainly work on it.
It was full time.
It was a long journey but it helped us a lot having the Python integration tests working
with a new library because we were sure that we were not breaking the existing cases and
speed up the things a little bit.
Absolutely.
Do you have a feeling for how long it would have taken you if you had re-implemented it
in Python?
I know that's not really a thing but roughly how long if you had said...
Going back to Python.
No, if you had said, we've got it in Python but for no good reason, we're going to rewrite
it from scratch in Python to make it cleaner, let's say.
Just as how long does it take to write something in Python versus Rust or maybe it's not possible
to guess.
Well, I think it depends.
In my opinion, this is a personal opinion, writing Python is much easier but then you
have more bugs.
This is what's my experience.
When I implement something in Python, I do it in 30 minutes, one hour, two hours but
then I go back.
When I do it in Rust, it took me more longer, a lot of compiler errors, a lot of unsafe
stuff everywhere so we need to avoid that.
But then it's quite stable.
I can say that nowadays the Rust version, it is younger that the Python one is more
stable.
We got less back reports and we have more users.
Thank you.
Did you run into any problems in terms of compatibility when you created C bindings
from the Rust code?
No, not at all, to be honest.
We did not have any problem.
It was quite straightforward.
I must say that the NMSD library is, well, we spoke to the users, it's quite simple.
That makes it simple for us.
We did not have any problem.
That's it.
Okay, thanks.
The problem.
You mentioned that it was a long journey when you implemented this in Rust.
Could you compare what you have expected in the beginning of this journey and with the
reality?
Okay, I must say that I'm not the only one person working on this.
There is my teammate, Chris.
Chris was the lead here.
I must say that I did not trust very much that we were able to do it in two years.
We were like, yeah, in two years we are going to have Rust.
I didn't think so.
But he was right.
So I think my expectation is that it would take much longer, but it was much simpler
than what I thought.
Also, I thought that we could have more problems with finding the libraries that we need to
do all the operations that we needed.
But I must say that Rust has a great ecosystem.
The libraries that we are using are really, really well maintained.
That's great.
Let's work for us.
We have a question from The Matrix.
Sure.
Sounds a bit weird.
Tanya is asking, how long did it take your team to learn Rust or did they know Rust already?
No.
We did not know Rust.
I mean, well, we didn't know what Rust was and we did some work on Rust.
But we did one thing here.
We started with Nispor instead with NmState.
So when we noticed what are the missing pieces, we first started with Nispor, which is much
simpler than NmState, and we learned on the way.
I must say that I am also surprised with all the Rust resources that it was quite easy
to learn.
But we learned on the way.
When we needed something, we started learning it.
And then we revisit the code and we change things.
For example, initially we did not understand correctly how to use traits.
So we did not use them.
And then we noticed, right, traits are really useful.
We are not using them.
And then we started to implement traits everywhere and make it more flexible.
Thank you.
Great.
There's no more questions.
Thank you for your talk.
Thank you for listening.
Thank you.