I'll just yell.
But yeah, so this is effectively my talk.
It started out as a really big thing and then I realised 40 minutes wasn't actually that
much time and so we sort of had to compress it down into a bit of a slightly smaller talk
but hopefully covering the most interesting points in my opinion.
So a bit about me.
I'm Harrison.
I come from London.
I live in London and I work for QuickWit where, as Paul has said, we build basically a distributed
search engine for logs.
I am the creator of LNX which is a slightly different design of search engine, probably
more akin to something like Elasticsearch or Algolia for all your lovely e-commerce
websites.
And you can contact me at Harrison at QuickWit.io.
A little bit about LNX since this is basically the origin story of this talk really.
It's a search engine built on top of TantrV.
It's akin to Elasticsearch or Algolia as I've said.
It's aimed at user-facing search.
That's things like your e-commerce websites, your Netflix streaming platforms, things like
that.
It's not aimed to be your cost-effective log search engine.
It doesn't really handle those hundreds of terabytes a day type workloads but it will
handle thousands of queries a second per core.
It's very easily configurable.
It's designed to be really fast out of the box because it uses TantrV and it has an indexing
throughput of about 30 to 60 megabytes a second on reasonable hardware with high availability
coming soon which is the presence of this talk.
So what is user-facing search?
I've stolen Crunchyroll's website and I've typed some bad spelling in there and you see
that a lot of the top results actually account for the fact that I can't spell.
That's basically the biggest principle with these user-facing search engines is you have
this concept of typo tolerance.
This is a really good thing for users because users can't spell.
The downside of this is that it has a lot of CPU time when we're checking those additional
words and it makes things a lot more complicated and often documents are mutable and a lot
of other things but also when you have these nice search experiences and you want low latency,
something called search as you type has become more popular now and that means your amount
of search as you're doing for a single user is increasing several times over because now
every key stroke you press is a search versus typing it all in one go, hitting enter, user
gets a bunch of results back goes, oh no, I've spelled something wrong or I can't see
what I want on here so I'm going to type it again.
That is effectively the principle of these search engines.
We have Algolia at the bottom which is a very common one which I think most people know,
very popular for document searching.
We decided, hey, we don't want to use one of these pre-built systems, we don't want
to use Elasticsearch, that's big, that's scary, I don't like it.
We don't want to use Algolia because I don't have that much money.
I'm just a lowly paid software developer, I can't be spending thousands of pounds on
that.
We look at some of the others but we go, no, we're just going to write it ourselves and
then that's where we have a little look because we hear something about Tantavy, we hear something
about Rust and it being blazingly fast as all things must be and so we go, okay, I like
this, I like what it says.
It says Apache Lucene, I think I've heard that before somewhere, written in Rust, I
think I've definitely heard that before.
We take a little look at what it is and it is effectively akin to Lucene which if you
don't know what that is, it's a full text search engine as it's called.
Tantavy in particular supports things like BM25 scoring which is just a fancy way of
saying what words are relevant to this query.
It supports something called incremental indexing which basically just means you don't have
to re-index all of your documents every time you change one thing.
You have fasted search, you have range queries and we have things like JSON fields which
allow for a schema-less indexing as such.
You can do aggregations which have some limitations in particular around JSON fields being a little
bit limited but the biggest thing is it has a cheesy logo with a horse which I believe
Paul drew himself so I think that needs a clap on its own but there are other features
which I just haven't.
Yes.
But there are more features which I can fit on this slide in time of the essence.
So you might be wondering what the basic implementation of Tantavy looks like and because it's a
library it's actually really quite simple to do.
So we have a couple of core things starting at the top as we define what's called that
schema.
Since Tantavy was originally a schema-based system, we need some way of telling Tantavy
what the structure of our documents are and defining what properties they have.
We can use something like a JSON field to give the impression of a schema-less index
but schemas are good, we should use them.
They come with lots of nice bells and whistles so in this case we've created a schema with
the title field and you can see there we've added the text and stored flag which all that
really says is I'm going to tokenize this field and then I'm going to store it so we
can retrieve it later on once we've done the search.
The second thing we do once we've done that is we create our index writer and in this
case we're just letting Tantavy select the number of threads so by default, when you
create this index writer and we give it a memory buffer, in this case about 50 megabytes,
we will allocate n number of threads, I think up to eight threads depending on what your
system is using so you don't really have to put much thought into the multi-threaded indexing.
Then we're just adding a document really so we've created our document, we've added the
text field, we've given it in this case the old man of the sea and we're going to put
it to our indexer which is essentially just adding it to a queue for the threads to pull
off, process, spare our disk.
If we want to actually have that be visible to our users for searching and things like
that, we need to commit the index so in Tantavy you can either commit or you can roll back
and if you have a power failure midway through indexing, when you reload from disk it will
be at the point of that last commit which is very, very useful so you don't leave with
partial state and all that nasty things.
And then once we've done that, we can actually search and in this case you can either build
queries using traits which are very nice and you can mash them all together with lots of
boxing and things or you can use the query parser which basically parses a nice little
query language, in this case we've got a very simple phrase query as it's called, trouble
that up and it spits out a query for us.
We then pass that into our search executor which in this case we're executing the query
and then we're passing what are called collectors and they are effectively just a simple thing
to process the documents which have matched.
So in this case I believe we've got the count collector and the top docs collector and the
count collector does what it counts, a big surprise there and we have the top docs which
collects the top K documents up to a given limit so in this case we've selected 10.
We only have one document to match so this doesn't matter that much but if you have more
you can limit your results, you can adjust how things are scored etc.
Now that's all well and good in this example but this doesn't actually really account for
spelling and as we discussed earlier users aren't very good at spelling or at least I'm
not so we maybe we want a bit of type intolerance and in this case Tanh Tui does provide us
with some additional way of doing this in the form of the fuzzy term query.
It uses something called lem
swapping a word around, removing it, adding new words, a bit of magic there really.
And as you can see at the bottom this is effectively if we use just the regular full text search
well if we enter the term hello will only match with the word hello but if we go with
the term hell will only match with the word hell.
If we use some fuzzy term query here we can actually match hell and hello which is very
useful especially for the prefix search.
This is built upon Tanh Tui's inverted index which uses something called a FST which is
effectively a fancy word for saying we threw state machines at it and then made them return
results.
That's as much as I can describe how they work, the person who originally wrote the
FST library in Rust burnt sushi, he has a blog on this, goes into a lot of depth, really
really useful for that sort of thing but I can't elaborate any more on that.
But all of this additional walking through our index and matching these additional words
does come at the cost of some additional CPU.
And once we've sort of got that what we're left with is this nice block of data on our
disks really.
So we have some metadata files here in particular meta.json that contains your schema along
with a couple other things and we have our sort of core files which look very similar,
if they look very similar to these things that's because they are.
In particular we have our field norms, our terms, our store which is effectively a row
level store log file, our positions, our IDs and our fast fields.
And fast fields are effectively fast because we cut somewhat simple and equally vague name.
But now that we've got all this stuff on disk, if we wrap it up in an API, we've got everything.
In this case we've got a demo of NNX working here and we've got about I think 27 million
documents and we're searching it with about millisecond latency.
I think in total it's about 20 gigabytes on disk compressed.
Which is pretty nice but there's sort of a bit of an issue here which is if we deploy
this production and our site is very nice, we get lots of traffic, things increase, we
go, hmm, well, search traffic's increased, our server's not coping, let's just scale
up the server.
And we can repeat this for quite a lot and in fact things like AWS allow you a stupid
amount of cores and things like that which you can scale up very easily.
But you keep going along with this and eventually something happens and in this case your data
center's burnt down.
If anyone remembers this, this happened in 2021, OVH basically caught fire and that was
an end of I think a lot of sleeping people.
And so yeah, your data center's on fire, search isn't able to do anything, you're losing money,
no one's buying anything, management's breathing down your neck for a fix, you're having to
load from a backup, what are you gonna do?
And well, you think, ah, I should have made some replicas, I should have done something
called high availability.
And in this case what this means is we have, instead of having one node on one server ready
to burn down, we have three nodes available to burn down at any point in time.
And in this case we hope that we've put them in different what are called availability
zones which mean, hey, if one data center burns down there's a very small likelihood
or at least is it possible for another data center to burn down in the meantime.
And this allows us to effectively operate even though one server is currently on fire
or lost to the ether or I don't know, network has torn itself to pieces.
And this does also mean we can upgrade.
If we want to tear a server down and we want to restart it with some newer hardware, we
can do that without interrupting our existing system.
But this is sort of a hard thing to do because now we've got to work out a way of getting
the same documents across all of our nodes.
In this case it's sort of a share nothing architecture.
This is done by Elasticsearch and basically most systems.
So we're just replicating the documents.
We're not replicating all of that process data we've just done.
We need to apply them to each node and doing this approach makes it a bit simpler.
In reality LNX and QuickWit do something a little bit different but this is easier.
I say this is easier because the initial solution would be just spin up more nodes.
Add some RPC in there, what can go wrong?
And then deep down you can work out, it's like oh, do you mean networks aren't reliable?
What's a raft and things like that?
And so at that point you go, okay, this is harder than I thought.
And you realize the world is in fact a scary place outside your happy little data center.
And you need some way of organizing states independent on things catching on fire.
And this is a hard problem to solve.
And so you have a little look around and you go, well, Rust is quite a new system, it's
quite a young ecosystem, we're quite limited so we can't necessarily pick a Paxos implementation
off the shelf.
We maybe have something called raft, so that's a leader-based approach and that means we
elect a leader and we say, okay, leader, tell us what to do.
And it will say, okay, you handle these documents, go do things with them.
It's a very well-known algorithm, very easy to understand.
It's probably the only algorithm which is really implemented widely in Rust.
So there's two implementations, one of them by the Pincap group called RaftRS and the
other by DataFuse Labs called Open Raft.
Varying levels of completion or pre-made.
So in this case you think, okay, I don't really know what I'm doing here, so maybe I shouldn't
be managing my own raft cluster.
And you hear something about eventual consistency and you hear, oh, it's leaderless, any node
can handle the writes and then ship it off to the other nodes.
As long as the operations are idempotent and that's a very key point which means you can
basically ship the same document over and over and over again and they're not going
to duplicate themselves or at least they don't act like they duplicate.
And this gives us realistically a bit more freedom.
If we want to change, we can change.
And so we decide, let's go with eventual consistency because, yeah, I like it an easy life and
it seemed easier.
Yes.
People laughing will agree that, yes, things that seem easier probably aren't.
And so our diagram sort of looks something like this.
And I'm scared to cross the white line so I'll try and point, but we have step one.
A client sends the documents to any node that doesn't really care which one.
That client then goes, okay, I'm going to send it to some of my peers and then wait
for them to tell me that they've got the document.
It's safe.
And then once we've got the majority, which is a very common approach in these systems,
we can tell the client, okay, your document is safe.
Even if OHV burns down again, we're probably going to be okay.
It doesn't need to wait for all of the nodes to respond because otherwise you're not really
highly available because if one node goes down, you can't progress.
And so this system is pretty good.
There's just one small problem which is how in God's name do you do this?
Many questions need to be answered.
Many things, how do you test this or who's going to have the time to do this?
And well, luckily, someone, aka me, spent the better part of six months of their free
time dealing with this.
And so I made a library.
And in this case, it's called Data Cape.
Woo, yes.
In this case, this is called Data Cape.
I originally was going to call it Data Lake, but unfortunately that already exists.
So we added cake at the end and called it a day.
It is effectively a tooling to create your own distributed systems.
It doesn't have to be eventually consistent, but it just is designed to make your life
a lot easier.
And it only took about six rewrites to get it to the stage that it is.
Because yeah, things are hard.
And trying to work out what you want to do with something like that is awkward.
But some of the features it includes is it includes the zero copy RPC framework.
And this is built upon the popular archive framework, which is really, really useful
if you're shipping a lot of data because you don't actually have to deserialize and allocate
everything all over again.
You can just treat an initial buffer as if it's the data, which if that sounds wildly
and safe, it is.
But there's a lot of tests and I didn't write it, so you're safe.
We also add the membership and failure detection.
And this is done using chit chat, which is a library we made at QuickWit.
It uses the same algorithm as something like Cassandra or DynamoDB.
And this allows the system to essentially work out what nodes are actually its friends
and what it can do.
And in this case, we've also implemented an eventually consistent store in the form of
a key value system, which only requires one trait to implement.
And the reason why I went with this is because if you implement anything more than one trait,
people seem to turn off.
And frankly, I did when I looked at the raft implementations.
So we went with one storage trait.
That's all you need to get this to work.
We also have some pre-built implementations.
I particularly like abusing SQLite.
So there is an SQLite implementation and a memory version.
And it also gives you some CRDTs, which are conflict-free replicated data types, I should
say.
And also something called a hybrid logical clock, which means it's a clock which you
can have across your cluster where the nodes will stabilize themselves and prevent you
from effectively having to deal with this concept of causality.
And causality is definitely the biggest issue you will ever run into with distributed systems
because time is suddenly not reliable.
And so we go back to our original thing of, well, first we actually need a cluster.
And in this case, it's really simple to do.
All we need to do is we just create our node builder.
We tell Data Cake, OK, we've got your addresses this, your peers are this, or you can start
with one peer and they'll discover themselves, who their neighbors are.
And you give them a node ID.
They're integers.
They're not strings.
And the reason for that is because there's a lot of bit packing of certain data types
going on and strings do not do well.
And here we can also effectively wait for nodes to come onto the system so our cluster
is stable and ready to go before we actually do anything else.
And by the time we get to this point, our RPC systems are working.
Nodes are communicating.
Your clocks have synchronized themselves, mostly.
And you can actually start adding something called extensions.
Now extensions essentially allow you to extend your existing cluster.
You can do this at runtime.
They can be added and they can be unloaded all at runtime with state cleanup and everything
else, which makes life a lot easier, especially for testing.
They have access to the running node on this local system, which allows you to access things
like the cluster clock, the RPC network, as it's called, which is the preestablished RPC
connections.
And you can essentially make this as simple or as complex as possible, which is essentially
what I've done here.
So I've created this nice little extension, which is absolutely nothing other than print
what the current time is, which realistically I could do without.
But nonetheless, I went with it.
And this is what the eventual consistency store actually does under the hood, is it's
just an extension.
And here we can see that we're passing in a, I can't point that far, but we can, we
pass in a memstore, which is our storage trait.
We pass in our eventual consistency extension using this and we pass it to the data cake
node and say, okay, go add this extension, give me the result back when you're ready.
And in this case, our eventual consistency cluster actually returns us a storage handle,
which allows us to do basically all of our lovely key value operations, should we wish,
including delete, put, get, that's about all there is on the key value store.
But there are also some bulk operations which allow for much more efficient replication
of data.
The only problem with this approach is it's not suitable for billion scale databases.
So if you're trying to make the next Cassandra or Cilla, don't use this particular extension
because it keeps the key value or the keys, sorry, in memory, which it uses to work out
what keys have and have not been processed.
And the reason for this is effectively because I didn't really trust users implementing this
on the storage side correctly, which turned out to be a good choice because the amount
of unit tests that this failed initially was a lot.
And so now we've sort of got this ability to replicate our key values.
Our life is a lot easier.
In particular, we can actually go as far as essentially saying, okay, we've established
our data connection, our key values, let's just use Tanteri as our persistent store.
And this is effectively the simplest way to do it.
And I've made a little demo here, which you can go to that link.
I basically abused and slightly ignored certain things in particular correctness, but this
will replicate your data.
You may end up with duplicate documents because I didn't handle deduping.
But in this case, we can fetch, we can delete, and we can index documents with Tanteri, and
that's our persistent store.
And here you can see we're doing about 20,000 documents in 400 milliseconds in the local
cluster.
Yes.
And that is effectively the end.
Great, so are there any questions?
How long do we have left?
Oh, how long do we have left?
15 minutes.
15.
Nice.
Wow.
Excellent timing.
Do we have a question down here in the front?
Yes.
So, I actually kind of saw in there.
Do you have a way to provide from outside to the Tentivity transaction or Lynx transaction
an external ID that I can use to integrate with the standard storage?
Change the question would be an easier way.
Do you have a way to say which level of data has been indexed?
Yes, so in this case, I've sort of glossed over it a little bit because in reality, it's
a little bit more complicated when you implement it.
So in reality, when you actually implement this, you would probably have a, essentially,
use the replication to replicate the initial documents, and then you would have a check
mark to essentially work out what documents have and have not been indexed yet.
Or you would add an additional step like a write-ahead log so that way you know that
as long as the documents are there, you can make sure that your check, your commit point
is always updated to the latest thing.
In LNX, it's actually a little bit different again because the way it creates indexes is
they are per checkpoint, so a new index has created every commit effectively.
But you don't have to do that, and in this method, I didn't.
So yeah, it doesn't do it here, but you can add a write-ahead log and you can basically
do anything as long as the trait is implemented.
Hello?
Hi.
Anymore?
Okay, okay, okay.
All right, so congratulations for the presentation.
I think I can see you.
Thank you.
Yes, hello.
So congratulations on the top.
I'm just having a question regarding the matching that's happening beyond the search engine.
Are there any plans to support something beyond the N20 class, such as vector space modeling
or vector search, or is this something that's in the coming time?
So let me see if I got that question right.
So was that about extending Tan to V, so if you want to go beyond something like BM25
or Lievenstein's distance and things like that?
Yeah.
What is the support apart from BM25 that are plans to support the other kind of searches,
such as distance searches?
I think things like vector search or word embedding search is still something which
is quite far away and would need quite a big push to do with Tan to V specifically.
If you want to add additional queries or additional functionality, it's quite easy to add with
Tan to V, so it's actually just a query trait.
So one of the things that NNX does, it actually has another query made called fast fuzzy,
which actually uses another algorithm for pre-computing dictionaries in order to do
the edit distance lookup.
And that basically just involves creating another query.
And you can customize effectively all of your query logic, all of your collecting logic,
and things like that.
So providing you're within the scope of the API, Tan to V will allow you to implement
it yourself.
Otherwise, things like the word embeddings, which are a little bit more complicated and
require a bit more on the storage side, would need to.
An issue and a very motivated individual to probably implement that, which currently we
don't really have.
So it's pretty little question.
On all your sketches, the network, the subject network was fully connected.
Is that important?
Let me see if I can find which one that was.
Was it this one or was it this one?
Well on this one, it does not look fully connected, but I'm not sure if this diagram depicts connectivity,
connectome, or just which messages has actually been dispatched.
I'm going to cross the forbidden white line here because we're doing questions.
And effectively, these are just indicating sending responses and getting things back.
So these nodes don't actually, in a real system, you could have a network petition here, and
your node one can no longer talk to node three.
It's effectively lost to the ether.
And maybe node two can also not do it.
And in this case, it doesn't actually really care.
All that you need to do is you need to achieve what's called a consistency level.
Which means that if you want to progress, you have to reach that level, otherwise things
are counted as not happening.
And so in this case, if node three is down or can't be contacted, as long as node one
can contact node two, and node two acknowledges the messages, things can still progress.
This is the same with raft as well.
So raft operates on what's called a quorum.
But effectively, any one node can go down in a three node group, and the other two nodes
can still progress, providing they have what's the majority.
So we understand full connection of the network is not an important factor here.
Well, it's nice to know.
Thank you.
Thank you for your talk.
I see here that there is basically a consistency mechanism for indexing.
Do you check as well if it had an over nodes when there is a search request as well?
Say that again.
Sorry, I didn't quite pick that up.
Do you check if it had an over node when there is a search request?
Not an indexing request?
In this case, we have relaxed reads essentially.
So we don't do, we're not searching across several nodes and getting the most updated
version from that, which is part of the trade-off you make with the eventual consistency.
You will have that with raft as well effectively, unless you contact the leader, you won't have
the most update data when searching.
But one of the things you do have to do if you go with the eventual consistency approach
like we do here is you would need to effectively handle the idea that maybe you will have duplicate
documents because something's been resent in the meantime, and so you'll need to be
able to deduplicate that when you're searching or have some other method of handling it and
deleting it from the index.
So that means that effectively every node must have a copy of the data.
I cannot have five nodes like a free repeat guard system or something like that?
Yeah.
So as long as if you've got a five node cluster and three nodes respond, you can immediately
search from, if those three nodes have got the data, they can immediately be searched
from effectively if you want.
But the other nodes may take a little bit of time to catch up, which is the principle
with eventual consistency.
They'll eventually align themselves, but they're not all immediately able to reflect changes.
One question down here.
Hello.
Just a simple one.
In hindsight, would you take the raft part?
In hindsight, probably not still.
And the reason for that is because the current state of the Rust ecosystem with it means
that there's a lot of black holes effectively around it.
And so you're either going with an implementation which is very, very stripped down in just
the state machine part, or going with an implementation which is very, very trait heavy and is a little
bit opaque around what you need to test, what you don't need to test, and how it behaves
under failure.
So in this case, I like this approach more because it allowed me to implement things
like network simulation, which the RPC framework supports.
So we can actually simulate networks failing locally in tests and things like that, which
makes me feel a little bit more confident than trying to just have the state machine
and implement everything and all the handling correctly.
But I think in future, yeah, you could use it, but it's just not quite at that state.
Great.
If that's all the questions, then...
Should I stand up?
Yeah, for sure.
Actually no.
What was I going to ask?
So I'm not sure I quite got how... if the engine actually does any data sharding or
there's a hash ring or...
Yeah, so in this approach, for the simplicity of time really, we're not actually doing any
data sharding.
Servers are really quite big nowadays, so even for your e-commerce website, you can
get a pretty huge server and the biggest issue tends to be replication and high availability.
The data sharding is something that...
QuickWit is something that would be concerned about because you've got so much data, you
need to spread it across machines and things like that when you're searching.
But in e-commerce, at the point in which you're searching across multiple machines, you're
probably going to be looking at the higher latencies.
So you would be better off dedicating one machine per search rather than several machines
per search, really.
Awesome.
So I think that's all of our questions.
Thank you.