Check, one, two, hello.
Hello.
Hi, where's Malte?
Hi, nice to meet you.
Okay, sorry, just like one of my hacker friends has been working with me on the project.
I've actually never met him in person, so nice to meet you.
Anyway, today we're going to be talking about Aura or Aude, however you want to pronounce it, is fine,
which we're temporarily calling a distributed systems runtime,
and that's the name that has caused the least amount of friction over the past few months.
Okay, so my least favorite slide, my slide about me.
So I'm an engineer, I work at GitHub, I help keep GitHub.com online.
Sorry about the Shaw thing last week.
Yeah, so I keep a lot of systems online.
Some of you may or may not use them, all of you hopefully have good opinions of them.
And then if you want to follow me on the Fetaverse, there's where you can follow me.
So I'll do overview and context.
So if you want to go to the GitHub repo, you can grab a photo of this or just remember it.
The link to the slides are there right now, I just forced push to main like two seconds ago.
So you can go and you can see the slides and there's like links to everything there that I'll be going over today.
So if you want to grab that, go ahead and grab that.
Okay, so we're going to start off, I'll do a little bit of context.
I'll answer the question, what is Aura, what does it do?
And then we'll spend the last two thirds of the presentation talking about Rust
and why we decided to use Rust for the project and some reports about how it's going so far
and some of my experience as well.
Okay, so just show of hands, who here has heard of Aura before?
Oh, God, okay.
Well, thank you for following my project.
That makes me very happy but also a little terrified.
So anyway, Aura, it's an open source Rust project and it's aimed at simplifying node management at scale.
And so when I talk about it, I usually say it's basically a generic execution engine for containers, VMs and processes.
The really quick pitch that I'll give on Aura is all of these things, containers, VMs,
hypervisors and basic process management is all that I do at GitHub
and all that I have done in my career for the past 10 years.
And I have used a plethora of tools to do this and I was tired of learning and managing all these different tools
and so I hope that this will be the last tool I ever have to work on in my career.
So I wrote a thesis about the project and I'm trying hard to continually reevaluate this thesis
and basically it says that by bringing some deliberate runtime controls to a node,
we can unlock a new generation of higher order distributed systems.
And what I mean by that is in my experience, a lot of the things we do on a node are organic
and grew over the past 30 years or so.
And this is more of a deliberate set of what do we need in the enterprise
and what do we need at a bare minimum on the node and I think that if we get that right,
we're actually going to have a much more interesting conversations in the coming decades.
So I also believe that simplifying the execution stack will foster and secure observable systems
while reducing complexity and risk.
And complexity, if you have ever ran Kubernetes, is the name of the game.
Cool, so I'll be talking about these things called nodes today.
So node is a keyword and when I say node pretty much always in life,
but very specifically in this talk, what I mean is a single compute unit in a set.
So this would be one or more computers that we're trying to group together and manage as a set of computers.
So when we do one thing to a node, the sort of assumption here is you want to go and do this twice
or three times or 10,000 times sometimes or so on.
So when we say node, I want you to think of a set of computers or an array of computers.
OK, so what does Aura do?
So the thesis here is this is going to be a central control for every runtime process on a node.
So whether you're running PID1 or a container or a virtual machine,
the hope is that all of this can be funneled through the Aura binary at runtime
and Aura will have the ability to not only manage it but also observe it and control it and start it and stop it.
And who knows, maybe even one day debug it if I'm very lucky.
It runs as a minimal init system. So this is important.
A lot of folks want to compare Aura to systemd and the more I think about it,
the more I think that I really believe Aura and systemd have different goals.
Aura doesn't really want to become a desktop manager.
In fact, it kind of wants to be the opposite of that. It wants to be as lightweight and as minimal as possible.
In a perfect world, there would be no user space on an Aura system
because we wouldn't actually want users touching a single computer.
Remember, we're managing sets of computers.
And so the hope here is that we can make this as lightweight as possible.
Additionally, we want this thing to have a remote API.
So the idea of a single person sitting at a desk and operating on a single node is kind of irrelevant here.
So everything that we do on the node, whether it's scheduling another process like a bash shell
or it's scheduling a container, should all come through this remote API.
And we're going to learn more about this API in Rust specifically later on in the talk.
Also, it runs on Linux. It right now is tightly coupled to the Linux kernel.
So what doesn't it do? So it doesn't do generic desktop support.
So that's just completely out of scope. I don't want to deal with your Bluetooth drivers.
I don't want to deal with your sound drivers. I don't want to manage your desktop interface.
I don't care. In a perfect world, this hooks up to the network,
and that's about the most advanced user interface we're going to have to one of these nodes in a set.
Additionally, higher order scheduling is out of scope.
So when we talk about enterprise management, whether it's some sort of orchestration system like Kubernetes or not,
a lot of those discussions very quickly go into the scheduling discussion.
There was a really good article, I think it was yesterday or the day before, on Hacker News
that came out of fly.io about their orchestrator experience with Nomad.
I see somebody shaking their head. Yeah, you read the article.
It was a great article, and maybe we can find a link to it and put it in the video or something for folks.
But that conversation was very much about how do we make scheduling decisions with available resources today.
And that is pretty much all I do at my day job at GitHub,
and that's all I've been doing managing Kubernetes for the past five or six years.
And so while I'm very interested in having that conversation,
my hope is that by simplifying the node, we can make those scheduling conversations easier in the future.
And what I mean by that is that we will have less to say about what we actually do on a node,
and we can effectively make nodes boring.
So it doesn't run on Darwin, it doesn't run on Windows.
Like I said, we're tightly coupled to the Linux kernel,
which if you haven't pieced it together yet is why Rust is very exciting for the project.
Okay, so again in summary, where did ORIT come from?
It came with challenges with complexity at scale, so we just want the node to be boring.
And it became, there was this desire to simplify and secure the stack.
So I do deeply believe that with simple systems come secure systems.
Every hack that I've been a part of in the industry has usually started with some sort of disparate
and un-node fragmented attack surface that somebody's been able to exploit
and do some sort of lateral movement once they're into the system.
So if we can simplify that and we can just make the conversation involve less moving pieces,
my hope is that we can actually secure the stack.
I also want there to be a stronger node API.
So who here has ever debugged the kublet API before?
Who here even knows what this is?
Okay, so we have a handful of people.
So the kublet is Kubernetes version of we're going to go run an agent on a node.
It does have an API.
Last I checked it was undocumented and it was tightly coupled with the Kubernetes control plane.
We hope to break that.
We hope to just have a generic API that you could use to run a single process remotely
or you could schedule millions of processes remotely.
And we want that to be a very strong and thoughtful API.
One of the big lessons of running large distributed systems at scale is that
the bigger you get, the less trust that you can have in the people working on your systems.
So as I've grown either like my small mastodon server that's grown into a medium-sized mastodon server
or even dealing with thousands of nodes at scale,
one of the lessons that I've noticed is that all workloads tend to this untrusted banality.
So the bigger you get, the less you can trust a single workload.
And even if these workloads are on the same team as you,
you really want to start looking at them as an isolation zone
that you don't want to trust too much from the centralized control plane perspective.
So we started off Aura with a few guiding principles.
Number one, I wanted to be boring.
So we're targeting a single binary.
We want this binary to be polymorphic in nature.
Who here is familiar with Busybox?
Great. Yeah, Busybox.
It's a good binary in my opinion.
I really like what it does.
There's a switch on arg zero and it basically behaves like however you call it.
So we're trying to get some similar functionality into the Aura binary as well.
And we also want this thing to be lightweight
and have a very strong scope and be as low risk as possible.
Additionally, we wanted this thing to be attainable.
We wanted to play nice with others.
So I knew that I wanted this to fit in neatly with Kubernetes.
I knew I wanted this to fit in neatly with Linux.
And I knew I wanted pretty much everyone in this room to feel realistically
like they could be running this thing on their laptops one day as the project grows.
And so in order to do that, the API was going to be the majority of what we were talking about
as we began developing the project.
And ultimately, I wanted to be functional.
I don't want it to subserve the needs of a corporation.
I don't want it to serve the needs of a higher order control plane.
I literally just want a standard library for executing processes in containers and VMs at scale.
What we do with that is out of scope.
I just want it to work first and foremost.
So ultimately, I want boring systems.
And if you see in the background here, there's all of these subtle distributed system propaganda
notes that you can go look at if you want to look at the slides later.
So ultimately, I wanted the thing to be safe.
So when we're looking at tenant security, one of the questions I ask is,
how do we make it easy to do the right thing?
And I think that comes from the underlying infrastructure.
And in our case, Aura is the underlying infrastructure.
And we intended to build a very strong project here that would unlock this sort of safe paradigm
that we could give a team a binary, and they would be able to run their applications on top of it.
And we wouldn't really have to worry about anybody sneaking out of their container
or accessing any parts of the system so we didn't want them to access.
So tenant security is a strong motivator for this as well.
OK, so about six months ago on Twitch, which I do a Twitch stream,
you should maybe follow me if you want to learn more about the project.
But I started to write this paper.
And it was mostly as some bro in chat was like, yo, why don't you just go rebuild system D?
And I was just like, maybe I will.
And so anyway, I ended up writing this paper.
And so, well, here we are.
And so the paper really grew.
And it started to answer a bunch of questions about like, why should we should go write it and go?
No, no, no, we should go write it in C, because C is going to be the most common language
that will interface neatly with the kernel.
And we can do EVPF probes and so on.
No, no, no, no, we should go write it in Rust.
And you can go look.
There's a Google Doc.
And it's just got all these comments of people from all over the internet and all over the industry
arguing about what we should do.
And eventually we settled on we want a lightweight node daemon and thus became the Aura runtime project.
Okay.
So this is where we shift from the conceptual what is Aura, how did we get here, what problems does it solve.
And we start to get a little deeper into the code.
So when we originally started the project, we started writing it in Go, the Go programming language.
And there's two kind of predecessor projects that later turned into Aura, which is written in Rust.
This first one that we call Aura Legacy, which up until about five, well, I guess 15 minutes ago now,
but right before I walked into the room, this was a private GitHub repo.
And I've gone ahead and actually opened it up.
So if you want to go see the original code in Go, there's some really interesting things in there.
We did some libp2p bit torrent style routing between nodes where you can build a mesh of nodes and things.
But you can really see where this runtime daemon started and some of the original concepts that we were tinkering around with.
Ultimately, though, we ran into a lot of the same problems that I ran into in Kubernetes,
which was I needed to start recreating these objects and I needed to start reading some config,
whether that be YAML or JSON or something similar, and then marshal that onto a struct in memory
and then go and do arbitrary things with that, in our case, schedule a pod.
And one of the things that was kind of outstanding in the back of my mind was what about access to libc?
I knew as soon as we started scheduling containers and DMs, we absolutely were going to need native access to libc.
Additionally, there's this project called NAML, which is basically Turing Complete Kubernetes Config.
It's written in Go and it just uses the Go SDK.
And that was yet another way of sort of validating this idea of we need to start making our system stronger
and building stronger interfaces for teams to manage different parts of the stack.
So those are the two sort of precursors to the Aura runtime as it exists today.
But of course, writing in Go came with some challenges.
The big one here is obviously native access to libc.
We were going to be creating C groups against the Linux kernel.
We definitely wanted to use the clone3 system call.
And the container run times of today had some assumptions about how we were going to be executing the clone3 system call
that, of course, I had to disagree with because, hi, have you met me?
I have to disagree with everything.
And we also wanted to implement some P trace functionality as well.
So obviously, Go was going to give us some challenges here when it came to using C Go.
So Rust became very exciting and definitely got a lot of attention very quickly as we were writing the Go side of things.
We also wanted EVPF for networking.
I personally want it for security and maybe for some other interesting service mesh ideas.
But I do think that having EVPF for networking as a non-negotiable,
we're definitely going to want to simplify what Kubernetes refers to as kubeproxy,
that we can now invent our own name and hopefully simplify that later.
But I digress.
We also wanted some access to native virtualization library.
So all the KVM stuff is written in C.
And if you go look at the Firecracker code base, that is also written in Rust that vendors the KVM bindings.
And so we knew we would want to access these three components and all three of these were going to be problematic with Go.
Update as of about an hour ago, I went to the state of the Go room across the hall here.
Did anybody else go to the Go talk this morning?
Yeah, we got three or four hands up here.
So this kind of pissed me off.
Go has unwrap now as of 1.2.0.
And they also freaking have.clone.
And I was just like, bro, get off our keywords.
This is totally like, this is our thing.
So anyway, it's really exciting to see Go taking these concepts a little more seriously.
And if you've ever written Rust before, who here has written unwrap in Rust?
Put your hand.
No, no, put your hands down.
We're not supposed to do that.
We're supposed to use other things.
I don't know what we're supposed to use now.
I just get so much shit on my Twitch stream every time I write unwrap.
But yes, we do have unwrap and clone in Go now,
which is just a strong indicator that we're likely doing something right with Rust.
So anyway, I made the decision to move to Rust.
And I didn't know very much about Rust when I made the decision.
And I literally just started at the main function and said, we'll figure it out as we go.
And I ordered the Rust book and just jumped in and started to write code with the hope
of accessing kernel constructs and C groups and EBPF probes.
So what could possibly go wrong here?
OK, so how are we doing on time, by the way?
We're 15 minutes in.
OK, cool.
So Rust, to help us solve the YAML problem,
I suspect we're all familiar with feeding YAML to machines.
We've all done this before at some point in our lifetime.
OK, so this is a thing I do a lot working in large distributed systems.
And I work with people who do this a lot.
And we do it so much, we've tried to get really good at doing it.
And that, I think, that's an interesting discussion.
So in my opinion, so warning, Chris Nova opinions here,
in my opinion, all config ultimately is going to drift towards Turing completion.
So I see this C++ templates.
Anybody?
Anybody C++ templates?
OK.
Helm charts, customizing Kubernetes, any of the templating rendering languages
that you see in web dev and front-end work,
there's all kinds of interesting Python libraries that will allow you
to interpolate your config and so on.
In my opinion, a good balance is kind of something like Bash that is Turing complete,
but it just comes with some strong guarantees.
And so I knew very quickly that I didn't want to be feeding YAML to Aura.
I definitely didn't want to recreate this idea of, like,
we're going to have to manage 1,000 pieces of YAML
because we have 1,000 different nodes.
So I wanted to explore more about what are some options that we have here,
so we're not just feeding YAML to machines anymore.
So thus became this really interesting project of mine.
We'll see if this pans out, which is this binary called AuraScript.
So AuraScript is a Rust binary.
We have it compiling with muzzle today,
and it embeds all of the connection logic for a single machine.
And so we'll talk more about the semantics of AuraScript in a second.
But ultimately, what you need to understand to kind of get the initial motivation here
is that this aims to be an alternative to managing YAML at scale.
So I found this really fascinating TypeScript runtime called Dino.
Have folks heard of Dino before?
Can I swear in here?
I effin love Dino.
I'm sorry. I really like this project.
If you want a good example of, like,
hey, I just want to see a really successful Rust project
that has a really strong community,
I would encourage you to just go look at the Dino project.
I think their code is beautiful.
I think what it does is beautiful.
I think the way that they manage the project is beautiful.
It's just a really good quality project,
and it solves a problem for us with Aura.
And so Dino is basically, it's a runtime for TypeScript,
and it's written in Rust.
And the way the project is set up,
that you can go and you can add your own custom interpretive logic,
and you can build fancy things into the binary,
and you can do things with the TypeScript interpretation at runtime,
which is precisely what we needed to do with Aura.
So here is the model now.
So instead of feeding YAML to a single node,
we now have this higher order set of libraries
that we can statically compile into a binary,
and we can interpret it directly on a machine.
So in order for you to interface with an Aura node or a set of nodes,
all you need is one binary,
mtlsconfig, and then whatever TypeScript you want to write.
And this is an alternative to, like, any of the Nomad command line tools,
or the Mesos command line tools,
or the Kubernetes kubectl kubectl command line tool.
And now you can just write it all directly in TypeScript.
So this is actually a concrete example of what would be,
what systemd would call a unit file,
what Kubernetes would call a manifest,
and what Aura just calls a freaking TypeScript file,
because we don't have fancy names for our stuff yet.
So you can see here at the top,
we basically contact the Aura standard library,
we get a new client,
and then we can allocate this thing called a cell.
A cell is basically an abstraction for a C group.
We cordon off a section of the system,
and we say, like, we want to use a certain percentage
of the available CPUs on a node,
and I want it to only let processes run,
in this case, for 0.4 seconds,
and then we'll use the kernel to just kill the process
if it runs longer than that.
And so the first thing we would do is we would allocate that,
which is an improvement over Kubernetes as it exists today,
because we can allocate resources before we actually
start anything in that area,
and then we can go ahead and actually start whatever we want.
And so you can see I simplified the example just for today,
but it's just, it's remote command injection as a service.
So this whole talk was just basically like how to go
and run a bash command on a server.
And so now you can express your commands and similar primitives
that you would see in other run times directly in TypeScript.
The interesting thing here is TypeScript is just natively
more expressive than a lot of the AML things that we see today.
In this case, we can actually do math,
but I'm sure you can imagine you can do other things as well.
You can access logic, loops, if statements,
there's if branching, and so on.
And so we were able to actually solve some of these like
templatey, rendery style problems by just doing things
natively in a well-known and easy to understand language
such as TypeScript.
So patterns started to emerge.
So Rust gave us the ability to generate the TypeScript binary
with all of the magic behind the scenes
MTLS security config that we wanted.
And so now the conversation was a little more like this,
which is how do I manage a small set of TypeScript,
and it's much more flexible, and you can start to actually
express things the way that we used to and just express
things statically, and then you can have all of your Turing
complete logical components below, and you can mix
and match these however you want.
Okay, so in addition to addressing the YAML problem
with DNO and TypeScript, Rust also helped us to solve
the Sidecar problem, and by us I mean this is our hope
as we operate our Mastodon servers and our various other
ridiculous side projects that we operate,
both in my basement and in a colo in Germany.
So talking about Sidecars, who here knows what a Sidecar is?
Show of hands. Okay, most folks do.
Okay, so a Sidecar that is always available with the same
features as a host. So this is going to sound a little bit
weird, and this slide's going to look a little bit weird,
but just bear with me as we kind of like unpack what's
actually going on here.
What we want, that I don't think we're talking about,
is that sentence. I actually think what we want is we want
a Sidecar to sit along our applications that does literally
the exact same things we have to do on a given host whenever
we're managing these workloads at scale.
As I began looking into writing Sidecars at the host level,
I began drilling deeper and deeper into the C programming
language as I was writing this in Rust and just made the
connection that memory safety was going to be key because
we're going to be running these demons right alongside of
your workload. And so unpacking the need to do this really
helps you understand why we shifted over to Rust.
So again, another Chris Nova opinion. Any sufficiently
mature infrastructure service will evolve into a Sidecar.
So if you have done any sort of structured logging, in my
opinion, if you will continue to build structured logging
and you will continue to ship logs, that will eventually
turn into a Sidecar that you're going to want to go run
beside your app so you have this transparent logging
experience. You can rinse and repeat that paradigm for
pretty much anything, secrets, authentication data, and so
on. And so I started to see these patterns kind of surface.
And very specifically, I started to look at how would I
solve these with Rust. And as it turns out, the Rust
ecosystem had a plethora of pleasant surprises for me as I
started to explore what putting some of these features into
a binary would look like. Logging was boring because we
could just use Tokyo streams. Auth N and Auth Z was boring
because all I had to do was just use the Rust derived
primitives to just start applying Auth Z to each of our
units in the source code. Identity was boring because I
didn't even get to fight with open SSL anymore. We just had
to use Rust TLS and that was easy. And so the network was
also easy because we had native access to Linux and libc so
we could just very boringly schedule a Linux device and we
got a Linux device and it was pretty straightforward. So we
were able to create this at the node and now my question was
how do we bring this into the workload level at scale and I
think this is where most of the conversations you start
talking about things like Istio and service meshes and
structured logging and so forth. And I actually think that
we can simplify that conversation too. And so what we
were able to do with Aura is we just spawned the root daemon
and used that as the new PID one in any of our nested
isolation zones. And when I say spawn I very directly mean
like we literally read the byte code from the kernel and
we build an image at runtime with the byte for byte, the
same byte code that's running on the host and then we can
just go and execute whatever we want against the same API
as the original host runs and all of this is memory safe.
So I can put this right next to your application in the same
name spaces running in a container or running in a
virtual machine and there's a relatively low risk of any
sort of binary exploitation at scale. So here's a model of
what that looks like. So on the left big side here we have
the Aura host daemon and on the right we have the three
types of isolation zones that you can run with a daemon.
You have a cell sandbox which is effectively a C group, a
pod sandbox which is a group of containers running in
unique Linux name spaces and a virtual machine which is
effectively a container with a kernel and some virtualization
technology. All of this is possible with Rust natively
and all of this was made possible by spawning the binary
and creating these nested isolation zones at run time.
Additionally, Rust was able to help solve the untrusted
workload problem because of the memory safety and that Rust
offers and because of this really interesting model that
we have right here. So this is a zoomed in model that might
look familiar if you've ever done any container escapes
before and in this model basically what we're saying is
we're replacing any sort of like pause or initialization
sequence in an isolation zone with the same daemon we run
on the host. So I think the Rust binary for Aura right now
is about 40 megabytes and we can just copy that into a
container and run that alongside your application. So it's
a relatively small application run time that will sit right
alongside of your app. So managing memory from
MTLS and AuraD. So as I'm writing Rust, one of the things
I notice is I start paying attention to memory management
more. Every time I try to clone something or the freakin'
borrow checker yells at me that kind of like is a small like
grim reminder of my roots as a C developer. This is an
interesting takeaway. The only memory that we need to share
that multiple parts of the system have access to in this
entire model whether we're creating containers or VMs is
the shared MTLS config. So this is the only bit of shared
memory that we really have to manage and Rust very clearly
called that out and to be candid I don't think I would be
able to be as comfortable with this model if I was doing
this in something like Go. So Rust was able to help us
solve the maintainability problem. So did somebody say
Rust macros? So we have a really brilliant guy, Future
Highway, who helps us work on the project and Future Highway
is our resident macro guy. Does everybody here have a
macro guy on your team? Because you should. He has made
things a lot simpler for us. So one of the things we
struggled with with Go and Kubernetes specifically was like
how do we generate objects with unique logic? Rust macros
were a solution to this for us. So if you've ever looked at
the Kubernetes code base you can see we've created these
things called CRDs that started out as third party resources
and we've built this entire bespoke API machinery system
that basically is a glorified macro system that allows us
to generate Go in the project. So we're allowed to use Rust
macros now and it's a very simple model in the code base.
We basically have a combinatorics problem where we're
able to map the different primitives to the different
logical systems that are unique to us and we can generate
our source code as needed. And so our source code ends up
looking like this, which I think we've successfully achieved
boring for a low level runtime. This is a fairly straightforward
call and then we can be confident that the code it generates
is unique to the project and encapsulates all of our
concerns as maintainers. So really the whole conversation
now is just the proto conversation. Everything can be
generated by Rust macros. The whole project really is
pretty much on auto-gen at this point. You can just go
introduce a new field in the API and then you can spit out
a new client. It'll plumb itself into the runtime. It'll
plumb itself into the Aura Script library and everything
is given to us for free just because of macros in Rust.
And so this is our code path and the way that we're able
to take advantage of macros. We do a lot of manual work.
We fight with the borrow checker. We make some improvements.
And then we get done and we encapsulate it into a macro.
And we can simplify our code path by just replacing all of
that with a macro after we've been done. And so this is
the Aura project as it exists today, which again I'm very
stoked to say that this is a very boring exercise.
So a quick update and then I'll be done with my talk here.
There's a few components, all of which are written in Rust
here. Number one, the Aura D daemon is the main static
binary that's written in Rust and compiled with muzzle.
So we can ship that without any of the shared objects on
the host directly into an isolation zone. AER is
completely generated from proto client. So this is exciting.
We can actually call a GRPC API directly from the client.
We don't have to do any of the runtime plumbing. So if
we add a bool to the proto file, we get dash dash bool
directly in the client compiled for free without typing
a single line of code. So this is a very exciting primitive
for us. So we can just begin to have API conversations and
not necessarily care about the internals of the program
anymore. Aura script is completely generated and we
have this exciting project down here, which is AE, which is
an alternative command line client written in Go.
So ultimately the lesson here is Rust was able to help us
solve the boring problem. We have a very complicated, very
obscure piece of technology that is you don't really have
to do much to work on it anymore. Most of it's on autopilot
at this point and most of the conversations are very
philosophical in nature and not necessarily about how to
implement things in the software.
So takeaways about the project. Aura is completely
stateless. So you can restart a node and it's basically
empty until you push config to it, which means all of our
systems are declarative like NixOS now and you can just
pass things like TypeScript or JSON to them and it makes it
easy to manage things like containers.
Next we have some to-dos for the project and I would
encourage you all to get involved. And if you want to
see a demo of all this, I'll be out here in the hallway
after the talk and you can come and you can track me
down and I'm happy to give you a demo. So anyway, I think
we have a few minutes for questions and five minutes for
questions. So I'll take questions and if you want to
get involved, here's how to get involved and I'm Chris
Nova. Please clap.
You mentioned the size of the binary being 40 megabytes.
Is that with size optimization or no?
Sorry, say that again.
Is the size of the binary at 40 megabytes with size
optimization applied already or not?
No, that's completely unoptimized. That is just straight
out of the compiler without any aftermarket tuning.
Amazing talk. Quick question. So if I want to have just
enough Linux to like pixie boot into this thing, do you guys
have any templates because it feels like a shame to run it
on something like Crel. I just need like enough of Linux to
just pixie boot into that.
Yeah, so the question is basically can we pixie boot this
and then you mentioned Crel. Where we're going we don't
need Red Hat. So I guess what I would say is in theory all
you need to run is a static Linux kernel and Aura and a
network connection and some NTLS config. And so everything
else at that point, all of your packages, your services,
your commands are passed to it via the API.
Hi. You mentioned that you use a lot of macros. I've also
run into problems where you have a combinatorial explosion
of templates in C++ speak or something like that.
What are your thoughts on generics for generating some of
this rather than macros in order to be a bit more type safe
I suppose?
Personally I got a little drunk with generics, I'm not going
to lie. When I first moved over from Go because I was just
so excited about it, the reason I like macros is because we
can add logic to them. So we have like, to give you an
example, we have containers and we have VMs. So we'll have a
section of the macro dedicated just to VMs that manages the
kernel. And that's irrelevant to the container systems in
the project because containers run on the host kernel. And so
we can embed those small branches directly into the
macro code so that macros generate slightly different
outputs based off of the inputs that are given to them. So
for Aura, when you're dealing with similar systems of code
that have small nuances like we are, macros really, in my
opinion, are the way to go. Did I answer your question?
Looks like?
Simple question. So can I actually give the configuration
instead of our script or type of script just in Rust?
Yeah, of course. So we have this Rust client here. It's
basically a Rust SDK. And then we have a tool called AER
which takes it a step further and is actually automatically
generated with macros. And it's a compiled binary that you
can just use from the command line. So you can just type
commands directly into it and it will run against the server
on the back end.
Yeah, there's also an SDK. So you could write your own Rust
code. And it's gRPC. So you could generate, you could write
it in Go, and we do, and you could write it in Python or Ruby
or realistically anything, any client you want.
Hi. I was wondering when you talk about the remote API, have
you considered a future direction to make this a unique
kernel?
A unique kernel. I have a slide for this. So I added a bunch
of FAQ slides to the end because I knew that we were going to
get all these good questions. The answer is it depends. Hold
on. Let's see if I can't find it. You guys get to see. There
it is. It depends. What does unique kernel mean to you? I
think the most minimal system we could do would be a Linux
kernel as it exists today, like good old-fashioned stock Linux
giant make file to hold nine yards, and then the or a D
daemon. And that would be the minimal system. Everything else
you would need to pass to it at run time.
I think we have time for about one more question.
So you said it doesn't do any higher order scheduling. I
guess I'm kind of curious what, if you want to do things like
resilience or steering or, you know, if the job dies, bring
up what are people typically using with ora?
So ora is still very new. I think that my hope for the
project is kind of like the same hope I had with my book,
like solve the lower layer first and then that is going to
open the door for higher order conversations in the future.
My hope is that there's a whole ecosystem of schedulers,
right? You change your scheduler, you change your
socks. Well, maybe not that often, but the point would be
that that's very specific to the needs of the current
organization that's working on it. And I would hope that we
can still use the Kubernetes scheduler or the Nomad
scheduler to schedule jobs on ora.
I know there's also some machine learning folks who have
some data resiliency problems that are interested in ora
right now and plan on using some weird global mesh that
will do a peer-to-peer network around the world, kind of
bit torrent, and then they intend to use ora for that.
So I think there's some opportunities there. The project
itself won't ever have an opinion on a scheduler. Maybe I
personally will start another project to do that in the
future or something, but this is the scope for now.
So that's all the time we have.
Okay.
Can we hear it again?