So let's get started.
So this section is about why and how to upgrade to Java 17.
And Simon already talked about the great new stuff that's being developed in the last couple
of years.
But I was wondering, like, what version of Java are you currently using at your projects
for your company?
So who's already using Java 21?
Please raise your hand.
Of course, that was a quick question because that's already access.
I guess you don't use that on a production machine.
But who's using Java 17 already?
Quite a few.
So basically you can tell the rest how to do it now.
Who's still using Java 11?
Okay.
Why it goes wrong?
Java 8?
Okay.
Older than Java 8?
That's not too bad.
So the interesting thing is, well, I mean, Simon talked about Java almost existing for
30 years.
I've heard of old features coming in the last couple of years.
Still a lot of people are on 8, which is almost like 10 years old, which is quite interesting,
of course.
You miss all the cool new stuff.
And that's basically what this session is a bit about.
So if you have any questions, it's a short session.
So please ask me afterwards on Twitter, LinkedIn, or somewhere else.
This session is based on a GitHub repository I created.
So I collected all kinds of examples from projects where I did the upgrades to newer
versions of Java, starting with Java 8 and opening to Java 17, a little bit about 21
as well.
So it basically gives examples, shows you error messages that you see when you upgrade,
things like that.
So you can use that when you do the upgrade yourself.
So why actually this session?
I think a lot of people see it as challenging to upgrade to a newer version of Java.
And a lot of people also estimate it at really large amounts.
To give a concrete example, one of the companies I worked at, one of the teams estimated that
to just upgrade their application, which was like a one team effort, which was a couple
of years old, they said it would take them a quarter with a couple of persons to upgrade
from Java 8 to Java 11.
And you can guess what management done said.
They said no, basically.
So they put an upgrade.
They already stayed with it for a couple of years.
And why I am not basically trying to convince people to change their estimates, but that
estimate was really high.
In the end, I didn't want to have all the discussions.
And I was lucky that my manager simply said, you do whatever you think is right.
So I upgraded it myself in like two weeks.
Of course, I had some previous experience.
So maybe it takes a bit more if you haven't done many Java upgrades in the past.
But still, I did it next to my normal job.
Most of the time, you're waiting for the build to finish anyway and all the tests to run.
So it's not like that much of work.
And what I found interesting is we always bring management that we cannot upgrade our
applications.
But in the end, it's us who benefit most.
Because then we can use all those cool new features.
So before I had the Relax Manager who said do whatever you want, I often did it on like
a Friday afternoon.
I upgraded to a new version of Java, tried to compile stuff, tried to tweak it a little
bit.
And then I got a better idea like, hey, we need to fix only the test or maybe stuff that
doesn't compile, we need to fix it.
And then I could say to management like, hey, give me two days or give me a week.
And then they often are like, oh, OK, you're already working on it.
We can give you a week and you can upgrade.
And that's often beneficial to yourself as well.
But there was also a good reason that you should do it for the company.
Because the new versions of Java, they also offer you free performance improvements, security
updates, things like that.
So there are a lot of good reasons why you should upgrade to a new version.
And I'm watching you actually upgrade.
So something changed in Java.
And you built your application on top of it.
Most applications have some dependencies.
I only know a few who basically built everything themselves.
But in general, you have some dependencies.
And if something changes in Java, those dependencies might break.
Or your application code might break, or both of them.
And then, as they sometimes say, a lazy developer is a good developer.
If you wait, those dependencies will automatically update their code to make sure that it compiles
on the latest version of Java.
Often already before the new version is released, sometimes shortly afterwards.
And then what will actually be removed from Java?
It's basically anything from tools like Java Mission Control, to methods, to all kinds of things.
If you go to my GitHub, you can get some references where you can see in detail, for instance,
on the Fujii website, you can see what methods are deprecated, removed, et cetera.
You can get a lot of those details, which is quite interesting.
But you can also simply try it out.
And then upgrade to a new version, and you get those compile errors for free.
Then in order to upgrade your dependencies, because I noticed that if you keep your dependencies
up to date, then it's relatively easy to update your Java version.
If you have really old dependencies, it might be tricky, but then first you need to upgrade them
before you can go to a newer version of Java.
And there are some interesting tools to help you there.
For instance, the Renovate project automatically creates pull requests for all your dependencies
in your Git repository.
So then you only have to merge it.
You don't have to search for the version or anything like that.
There are also maybe ungrable versions plugins that can show you the latest versions
or can automatically update those versions for you.
One thing to keep in mind with that is sometimes your artifacts, they change their name.
For instance, first we have Java EE, as was explained before, and then we have the JHPC API package
inside the Java X page.
Now it's Jakarta, so it basically changed.
So make sure not only to use the latest version, but also to see if an artifact basically has a fork
or some other name or whatever.
And actually there are also some nice plugins for that.
All group IDs alert for plugins, names, and gradle.
They basically alert you that, hey, you're using some older project,
there's a newer project available, you should change your dependencies.
So again, most of it you can automate.
If you don't look completely at what changed in different versions of Java,
which you will probably encounter when you upgrade to a newer version,
when we started Java 11, one of the bigger changes was that Java FX was being removed.
However, there are still separate builds for Java FX, like the one from Gloom.
You can use a main dependency.
And what a lot of people are unaware of is that there are different versions of the JDK.
So you have the OpenJDK, there's Oracle JDK, there's an Amazon JDK, there's a Microsoft JDK.
Some vendors, they offer more than basically the standard JDK.
They offer extra tools, like for instance Java Vax included.
So for instance, the Liberica JDK, they offer a build with Java Vax still included.
I see OJDK built, it's mentioned here still.
I forgot to remove that one because that project basically stopped.
So they don't release any new updates nowadays.
Another interesting thing that was changed was that in the past,
Java contained a few fonts, just a real small set of fonts.
Basically those fonts wouldn't be found.
And now they are removed.
If you do that on a normal operating system, it doesn't matter,
because then they will use the operating systems fonts.
But if you use a really small operating system, like Alpyn Linux, that also doesn't have any fonts.
So then Java has no fonts, the operating system has no fonts,
and you get some really weird errors about missing fonts.
For instance, if you use tools like Apache Poi, which you can use to operate on office documents,
that apparently use some fonts under the hood, and a colleague of mine got this issue,
and then the solution is basically to install some Java packages with fonts.
Some other stuff that's been removed is the Java Mission Control.
You can now download that basically separately.
If you want to do some profiling or monitoring of your application,
I highly recommend having a look at this one, it's really interesting.
But it's no longer part of the JDK itself, it's like a separate tool that you can download.
And I think one of the bigger changes was that the Java EE and Corba modules have been removed.
I hope Corba isn't used that way anymore in your projects,
but Java EE modules are often used.
If you look at a concrete example, for instance, Jog B.
As mentioned before, it was Java X, and now it's Jakarta.
So basically you need to change the imports of your application,
and you need to add to the dependencies explicitly, as it's no longer part of the JDK.
And that goes basically for all the ones.
If you see here all the different modules on the left,
you can see the replacement artifacts on the right.
For Java EE and Java W.S., you need two dependencies, one for the API and one for the implementation.
Let's see if you make the switch to Jakarta, you need to make these changes.
Also, some people that didn't switch to Jakarta,
they simply added the Java EE dependencies explicitly.
That's also possible, but I mean those no longer receive any upgrades.
So if you want to receive upgrades, you should move to the Jakarta versions.
Java 15. Who's using Nashor in here?
I see a few hands.
In the past I only saw that conferences always founded a really cool tool,
but never encountered it in projects.
And then I worked at a company and upgraded a lot of projects from various teams,
and suddenly I got a Nashor exception.
So there are some places where it's being used,
and in those cases you can simply add this dependency,
and then you can keep on using them.
Java 16.
It's a very interesting one.
They basically strongly encapsulated JDK in journals.
So what does that mean?
In the past there was some internal logic of Java basically,
like reflection APIs and things like that.
And they were never meant to be used by end users.
They were only meant to be used by the guys who built Java itself.
But they couldn't hide it away.
A couple of years ago we got modules in everything,
and now they can hide away that logic.
But if they would have done that immediately,
a lot of applications would break because they would use these internals.
But gradually they are making it a bit harder to use those internals.
So what happens now if you use some of those internals?
You get exceptions like this.
For instance, Lumbok uses lower level Java logic,
and it's also something like that.
A module compiler does not export some stuff to any module.
Basically means Lumbok doesn't have access to that anymore.
So what's the solution?
Again, a lazy developer is a good developer.
You read it a little while, and then Lumbok creates a new version,
which you add as your dependency, and then you can simply continue.
If that isn't the case, maybe you use some obscure older framework or library
which is no longer maintained, and they won't update it,
then there is still a workaround available.
And that's basically by giving some compiler arguments.
So, princessfire, the maybe compiler plugin, you can get these arguments,
which of course is a little bit dirty, like someone puts a lock on their door,
you remove the lock, and then you leave the home open,
so everyone can again access it.
So it's not really a nice solution.
So please just update your dependencies whenever possible.
And there is an even dirtier hack,
that is you can start the Java process with minus minus illegal access,
and then everything is open anyway.
So that's like to really smash in the door with a hammer.
How long is that option going to stay?
Sorry?
That's a good one.
Thank you for, that's a hop to the next version,
because now we have another strongly encapsulated JDK internal.
So Java 17, so it stayed for six months basically.
So with Java 17, the launcher option minus minus illegal access no longer works.
So you had six months to fix your issue.
So then you get an exception like this if you try.
So again, by now I think you know what to do to resolve this,
make sure you have greater dependencies.
Those lower level JDKs, JDK options, those methods and things,
they have replacements that are higher level.
So if you use those methods in your own code,
make use of those higher level methods instead of those lower level methods.
Unfortunately, there is still the last resort.
You can still use that minus minus add opens to still open up stuff.
As far as I know, there are still no plans on stopping that.
So yeah, that might stay for a bit longer.
It's like a workaround to make this work.
Then when you look at the newer Java versions, so Java 18, 19, 20 and 21,
they didn't announce any major removals,
although the full time for 21 is still a thing under debate.
I tried with another repository that I have that a lot of,
for another presentation, I explained a lot of libraries and tools for Java.
I tried upgrading all of those in Java 21 and then I still got a few issues.
So not everything was there, but that's mainly because the compiler doesn't support it yet
by those frameworks, as we will see in a second as well.
But no major things are being removed so far,
so it should be a relatively easy upgrade.
Then one thing that I encountered a couple of times
in the puzzle team in the beginning was that I often got the exception
unsupported cross-file major version 61.
Does someone know what that means?
So basically, cross-file major version 61 is used to describe Java 17,
so it basically means your stop doesn't run on Java 17.
But then with the number 61.
If you see the same with the number 65, that means it doesn't run on Java 21.
So if you get these kinds of weird errors,
again, upgrade your dependency and often it's fixed.
So I tried running some examples on Java 21
and then Spring, for instance, they don't support the cross-file format 65 yet,
so you get this issue.
Often that's resolved after a while by the people maintaining those dependencies.
So in the past, basically upgrading was a matter of find, replace, import,
compile it and then see what breaks and fix that.
Nowadays, there are basically more and more tools available to help you with that.
So there is the more generic open rewrite project,
which I think you can use for changing almost anything.
It's really a VONs, find and replace engine, so to say.
And there's a session about that topic a little bit later.
Yeah, and a session later by Tim.
So if you want to know more of that, stay seated here.
There is the Spring Boot Migrator project,
which is more focused on upgrading Spring applications to newer versions.
And quite recently, they introduced Eclipse migration toolkit from Java,
which is again a bit more generic toolkit to also upgrade your Java versions.
I have to be honest, I tried some of them in simple projects to play around,
but the upgrades I did in the past I mostly did it by hand.
Because mostly, like I explained, it was a matter of upgrading dependencies
and then see what code changed.
And maybe I was lucky, but in most cases that was relatively easy.
So after you've done this work, you upgrade your dependencies,
fix the code that's breaking in your own code base.
Then basically, you're happy again, you can finally use those cool new features
from the last 10 years that nobody has said or a lot of people aren't using yet.
So you can make use of records, new classes, all those cool nice features.
And I think that's really helpful.
So to summarize, if you look at the amount of work,
I think if you upgrade from 8 to 11 and you switch from Java EE to Jakarta,
it's relatively a bigger task.
It takes you a bit of time to upgrade everything,
get the right packages that are compatible with each other,
and get that to work.
Still, it's not like a quarter with a lot of people.
It's still a matter of, I would say, depending on your application days or maybe weeks.
If you go from 11 to 17, that's a lot easier.
For me, it was mainly updating a lumbock and some test dependencies.
Because tests like mocking frameworks, they always use those internals of the JDK.
So they tend to break when you upgrade to Java 17.
So if you upgrade those, then most of it already works.
So I did, I think, like six or seven projects from 11 to 17.
And for all of them, that was basically all I had to do.
Only one that used some reflection logic in one of the unit tests,
so I had to rewrite it, but I could quite easily rewrite the same test case
with higher level logic and test the same cases.
So all in all, I would say from 11 to 17 is easier than from 8 to 11.
And from what I see now, from 17 to 21 is maybe even easier
unless they introduce any big changes in Java 21.
My advice is always to take incremental steps.
So don't try to do everything at once.
First try to make everything compile.
And you can also tell your teammates, your manager, like, okay, now it compiles.
So I'm one step further, now I do my tests,
and then we're basically, we can deploy it and run it.
Instead of saying, add 80% done, because we all know how much 80% done means.
It means 80% of the work didn't need to be done.
So that really helps, make those small steps.
Also for yourself, then you know what the progress is.
And as I mentioned before, I mean, we can make management
for not giving us the time to upgrade Java,
but in the end, I think for us it's most beneficial
because then we can finally make use of those cool new features.
Nowadays also Spring requires, for instance, Java 17,
if you want to upgrade to the latest version.
So I think that's one more reason to make sure that you're up to date.
So that was it.
I think I have five minutes left.
So if someone has a question.
Coming back to this problem with class version, is it because we are trying to run classes
which were compiled against JDK 19, for instance,
at least under JDK 17 or stuff like that?
This is because the bytecode is too new and the features are dropped.
Yeah, I think that's a little bit of a problem.
It doesn't support the newer bytecode.
So basically you need to update your JDK.
Now you need to update the dependency
so that it is compatible with the bytecode of that new version of Java.
So this happens when you run an older dependency
on a newer version of Java basically.
Yeah.
Would you recommend gig to help defend the posture?
So the question is, would you recommend to get out the Panda bot?
I think it's quite similar to Renovate, which I used.
I quite like it, but it depends a bit on what kind of dependencies you use.
Because some dependencies release really often, then you get a lot of those updates.
But I think it's a lot better because if you look at traditionally,
a lot of projects is done by hand.
It's not like a funny task to do to find out the latest versions
by going to the main repository or something like that.
So it's often neglected.
And if you use tools like the Panda bot or Renovate,
you basically get the issue smashed into your face like you have to merge it.
And it's more or less automated.
Unless of course, often you merge it to build fills, then you have to fix it.
But at least I think it helps to stay more up to date with your dependencies.
Because else, I've seen it in so many projects,
most developers don't care about it,
and they only upgrade once a security issue is being found or something like that.
Then they upgrade it, and else it stays the same old version.
Well, if you keep it up to date continuously,
sometimes you have to do some minor fixes,
but then you don't have to do those big fixes
when your friends just want to migrate to a newer version of Java.
And also there's a session on this topic,
the one after the next one about dependencies specifically.
Okay.
Regarding the at-opens fact,
is there a way for a Java 11 compile time
to report issues that will grow in Java 17 runtime?
This unnamed class opens, you know.
Because we are compiling in Java 11,
but when we run in Java 17,
then we see that we need these at-opens, but we try to read it.
There was a flag there that could warn you,
but I'm not sure from which point.
Oh, sorry, yes.
The question was, the gentleman compiled in Java 11
and run it on Java 17, the code,
and then it breaks because some at-opens were missing.
Basically they're using some internals of Java,
and he asked, is there some way to find out on Java 11
if I'm missing those things?
Because then I can fix it there already.
So I know there was some flag,
something like give a warning or something,
but I don't know in which version of Java that was introduced.
So what would be the solution to compile in Java 17?
Yes, I would compile in Java 17
and using the desktop release option for a project
to be able to run in 11.
In that shift, we call these things as part of the code.
Yes, then you can run it on 17.
That's of course the easiest way.
But let me compile it on the 11th.
Yes, sorry.
We should compile for it on 17 and then it will go as part of the code.
Yes, then you get the warning immediately.
Or you can see if that flag already exists in Java 11.
I'm not sure.
I know it was introduced sometime, but I don't know which version.
Thank you.
And thank you all.
Thank you very much.