So, that was a blast.
And we are finally back in person.
And also I'm going to take a picture because we are finally in person.
Once again, if you leave, please be quiet because it is extremely loud up here.
And no, you're not special enough that you should keep talking.
Thank you very much.
So it's a wrap.
Random stats because stats are fun and easy to make.
Sometimes it was a little bit of a rush.
Our peak this time was 1.5 gigs in concurrent outgoing streams.
Once again, please quiet if you decide to leave.
Last year we had 1.65 gigabits peak and that was fully online.
So that gives you a rough idea of how many people still chose to consume offsite even
though we have a relatively full foster but not as packed as 2020 we think, we estimate.
35 rooms, 800 concurrent viewers and roughly 20K unique viewers on the streams.
We have a total of almost 400 hours of scheduled video for the ones tracking the numbers over
the years that is less than the last two years because physical ULB has less space and less
staff rooms than fully virtual but still we managed to fit quite some stuff in.
We already have 53 released videos online and 21 are currently being reviewed and or
transcoding for a total of almost one full day of video.
Speaking of video, if you are a speaker or if you are a deaf room manager, please, please,
please, please, please with sugar on top.
You get those emails and you do what is in those emails and please help us review them
because if you don't do it as a speaker, it falls on the deaf room managers to do it and
if the deaf room managers don't do it, it falls on staff to do it and it's a lot of
work and a lot of video because 400 hours of video is a lot.
So please, if you are a speaker, if you are a deaf room manager, those emails are important.
Do not ignore them.
If you have any issues, email video at Fosdomorg and they come from no reply at Fosdomorg.
Matrix also dropped because obviously a lot of people are in person but still we had quite
some online participation slash online synchronisation while people were rocking the hallway track
and attending talks and such.
We sold out of Schwag.
We weren't fully certain.
We didn't know what we have a fully packed UOB, what we have almost nothing, anything
in between but we managed to sell out so that's good.
And we also had 130 advance orders.
For those who don't know, we will continue to give you the ability to order Schwag beforehand
which means you just get a voucher and you get a password and you get to front desk and
you get it immediately.
We don't have to do the payment, dance, everything.
And also maybe depending on how the timeline works out, maybe we even can start ordering
specifically for you as you do advance orders.
There was a lot of food consumed.
There's actually two slides.
It's a lot.
And it's not even a full number because this is as of 1530 local.
Once again, thank you, it's really loud.
Network we stopped checking Mac addresses for various reasons.
Network was a little bit of a mess this year because a lot of things broke which we thought
remotely were fine but the Macs concurrent we saw for IPv6 addresses being assigned was
over 30K and the total amount which we gave out was 53K.
People switched from one network to the other, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
So it's not a fully scientific method and also privacy extensions which keep basically
messing up all our stats but it's at least not a little.
Also UAB has some traffic analysis on their controllers we don't for obvious privacy reasons.
So you can guess what for the first time since they installed that stuff was the top website
or the top site accessed by total volume of data going to and back.
Any guesses?
Obviously.
We also had some stats.
Initially we kept them at 2.5 but we switched from one gig to 10 gig over the weekend because
that's how we rock.
And we actually managed to consume more than the one gigabit which we had before.
Going forward hopefully next year we will maybe even have two times 10 gig.
We'll see.
If you are and I keep telling people this every year if you are still using 2.4 gigahertz
please don't.
Get hardware which does 5G, 5 gigahertz, well 5G, no, 5 gigahertz, of course you will have
less contention.
You won't have zero contention but you will have less contention if you have hardware
with 5 gigahertz.
It's generally nicer so if you buy your next laptop your next would ever consider spending
a little bit more money on 5 gigahertz.
We come to thank yous.
First of all the matrix and element people.
Who asked to not be named just like so listed.
Also Libera chat staff.
And also sponsors without whose this wouldn't be possible.
As per usual as I call out the next groups if you wear a colored T-shirt of the appropriate
color, please come up front and take your applause.
I'm not crying again.
I'll see.
All the volunteers.
Come.
I also see at least one green and one orange shirt which is not up front which is a big
mistake.
If you don't have the shirt on but you did volunteering,
and whatever, please come up front.
We have a few staff who are also supposed to come up front now.
And thank you.
As per always, please send feedback.
We really rely on this feedback and we actually take it to heart.
So please send any and all feedback which you have.
We cannot always accommodate it but we read everything and we really do take it to heart.
Thank you.
That should be helping, not feedback, whatever.
If you see trash, here, anywhere else.
Congratulations, this is your trash now.
And I'm being serious.
It is an immense amount of work to build up in basically half a day on Friday and also
to tear down within two to four hours on Sunday.
So anything you see, please just take it with you, throw it in the trash, whatever, but
please help us clean.
Also speaking of cleaning, if you have some time, we would highly appreciate it if you
just stayed around a little bit, helped us clean up.
If you gather here, we will tell you what to do and it will take a little bit until
we have all you segmented.
But we can use every single hand for the network cabling which you tear out under guidance.
You can keep the network cable.
And also for the ones who stay until the very end and help until the very end, we will feed
you in cabling at the end.
So please consider just coming up front to help.
Yes, after the thing, obviously.
And that's it.
So see you next year.
And as is tradition.
So A, I forgot all the speakers who are in here.
They also are supposed to be on stage if they so choose.
So now is the time to come on stage if you want to.
And as is tradition, we are ending Fostom with the Fostom dance.
My knee is kind of broken.
So I'm not going to lead the dance.
Wouter is going to lead the dance.
And with that, thank you.
See you next year.
I don't know who among you has done the Fostom dance before.
It's actually quite difficult.
But not really.
We start like this.
And it's difficult because you have to balance on one leg.
But I'm sure you can all do that, right?
So bear with me, and then we lift the one leg.
And then we start moving.
Everybody move.
And we go faster.
And there we go.
We're dancing.
Thank you.
That was the official Fostom dance.