First of all, thank you for coming here to this session.
I think it's fantastic to have an audience who is potentially interested with regulation
and compliance.
This is something that impacts all of us as a community, as our users, consumers, and
also from a work perspective.
So I think it's really important to be able to understand what are the impacts of regulations,
compliance, certifications, when we are developing software, when we are sharing our work from
a, I would say, a community perspective, but also when that work goes into production on
systems, critical systems.
So thank you for being here for that.
Today we have the unique opportunity to have some of the folks who wrote, or at least
review wrote, some of the legislation directives, like the Cyber Resilience Act.
And we will go through a couple of lightning talks, because I think it's really important
to set the scene.
So we could start discussing about having a panel, but if we don't understand the overall
construct of those regulations, that's going to be hard.
So I would like to have a warm welcome from Benjamin here.
If you can give him a bit of love.
Thank you.
So we are really honored to have the European Commission here to help us with this.
So thank you.
Benjamin, up to you.
Thank you very much.
Thank you so much for having me and also for showing interest in our work.
That will maybe affect some of you, but most of you probably won't be affected by it.
I mean, as a commission, we are always trying very hard to reach out to all the people that
could potentially be affected by our regulation, but it's sometimes a bit difficult.
I mean, it's often mostly large companies that have the resources to actually engage
with us.
So I'm really happy to be here, and I'm so glad that so many of you decided also to stay
for this panel.
So the Cyber Resilience Act is a new proposal of the European Commission.
It intends to improve the cybersecurity of hardware and software products.
It's intended to complete a puzzle.
So there's already other legislation at union level on cybersecurity.
Most notably, there is the NIS directive, which has recently been reformed.
The NIS directive focuses more on the users of hardware and software.
So it ensures that large companies, critical infrastructure providers and so forth take
security seriously, do their patches regularly and all that.
But the Cyber Resilience Act now focuses on the other side, on the manufacturers of these
products.
And, I mean, I know that many of you are probably not dealing with policy every day, and it's
particular not with European Union policy.
So I've just added one slide at the very beginning to quickly explain to you what the commission
is and where we are in this process and who the other players are.
So yeah, this is highly simplified.
It's much more complicated than that, unfortunately.
So I work for the European Commission for the director general connect.
It's like the director generals, they are like departments within the commission.
So we mostly deal with telecommunications, internet, emerging technologies and so forth.
And it is the European Commission that makes legislative proposals in the European Union.
So we write the draft, and then we propose this draft to the so-called co-legislators.
That's European Parliament and where you have the members of European Parliament, so parliamentarians,
and the council that represents the 27 member states.
And these two institutions, they analyze the commission's proposal, they come up with their
own positions, and once they've done that, they negotiate with one another.
And at the very end, once they agree on a common line, a common position, they adopt
the text and it enters into force.
It becomes a law.
So this is basically how it works.
It's very simplified.
So our proposal came out on 15 September 2022, so in autumn.
And it's now with parliament and council.
Parliament has not yet started discussing it.
They're still sorting out which committees will be in charge of it.
But council is already at full speed.
There are regular meetings every second Wednesday.
The council is meeting to discuss the text proposed by the commission.
So that's just for your background.
And now we'll talk about the substance of the proposal.
So what are we trying to achieve?
So we want to reduce the number of vulnerabilities in hardware and software products.
Of course we know that it's an unrealistic goal to aim for zero vulnerabilities in products.
And this is what this slide represents.
So the cheese represents a hardware software product filled with holes.
I mean, I know not all are filled with holes, but many are.
And I mean, we attempt to reduce the number of such security holes in hardware and software
products through legislation.
And yeah, I will just get right into the main elements of the proposal to give you an overview
and then I will provide some more details.
So it's all about providing cybersecurity rules for hardware and software products when
they're placed on the market.
So placing on the market entails that we're talking about commercial activities here.
So companies that make money with hardware and software products, they will have to follow
these rules.
We're using a well-established framework.
It's called the new legislative framework.
It's been used in the past by the European Union to regulate other products such as toys
or machinery or electrical equipment.
And you may not know it, but you're all actually very familiar with it.
So whenever you see a product that has the CE marking on it, CE, I will show it later,
like you have it, for example, on laptops or iPhone chargers and such things.
So this is all new legislative framework regulation then.
What we do in the proposal is we establish obligations for three types of economic operators
for the manufacturers.
I mean, that's the core element, of course, of the proposal.
But then there are also the distributors.
These are brick and mortar stores, online shops, and also importers that place products
on the European market that have been developed in third countries.
And the importers and the distributors, they don't have to, I mean, they don't do secure
coding, of course.
They're just selling products, but they have to ensure that the products that they are
selling are, like, in line, I mean, that they comply with the Cyber Resilience Act.
One of the core novelties of our proposal is that it does not just cover rules for the
placing on the market, so what the product should look like, but it also covers the period
after that, the entire life cycle.
So I mean, you all know that for cybersecurity.
It's extremely important that you keep tracking your products, that you ensure that when you
discover new vulnerabilities, that you fix them, you mitigate them, you provide patches
and so forth.
And this is part of our proposal that for a period of five years after the placing on
the market of a product, you do that.
You provide security updates.
One essential element of any new legislative framework regulation is harmonized standards.
So the rules that we propose in the Cyber Resilience Act, they are very high level, technology
neutral, objective oriented.
I mean, if you go through the proposal, you will see they are really high level.
It's more like on the level of provide a secure by default configuration, take care of access
management, make sure data is handled confidentially and so forth.
So really high level, but then we have the standards that will be developed by the European
Standardization Organizations.
You may have heard of them.
They are called SANS-ANILAC and ETSI.
And they are voluntary.
You don't need to use these standards, but they will help you write secure products.
And then there is also the conformity assessment.
So manufacturers, they will have to demonstrate that their products are actually compliant,
but I will explain that in more detail later.
And finally, there is the market surveillance.
So in all the member states, you will have authorities that can check out the products
and approach manufacturers, ask them to remediate vulnerabilities, eliminate risks, and if they
don't comply, even hand out fines.
So the scope of the proposal, it's hardware and software products, products, not services.
So when I say hardware products and software products, I mean final products such as laptops
or operating systems, but also components such as CPUs, hard drives, software libraries,
and so forth.
We don't regulate services.
So software as a service is outside the scope of this proposal.
That's already regulated by the NIS directive, which I mentioned earlier.
But we do regulate something that we call remote data processing solutions.
So often today, products, they actually come with some cloud or other elements such as
many mobile applications.
They usually they access data in the cloud, and these are essential functionalities of
the program.
And then you would also have to ensure the security of these remote data processing solutions.
As I already explained, we only regulate commercial products.
So anything that is non-commercial is outside the scope, including open source when it's
non-commercial.
But on the other hand, open source that is commercial, I mean there are a lot of large
commercial projects, I'm sure you're aware of them, they would be covered.
And then we exclude certain products that are already regulated by other regulations
such as cars or medical devices.
Yeah, I mean why did we choose to exclude non-commercial open source software from the
scope?
Well, there are a few reasons, and first of all, this is standard practice for any new
legislative framework product regulation at union level.
We only focus on commercial activities.
But also in the case of open source, there are some more special considerations that
we took.
So first of all, would it be fair to regulate someone that does not make a profit with a
product, right?
I mean, and we think it would not.
And wouldn't we be setting the wrong incentives to regulate someone who doesn't make money
with it, right?
Would you keep developing something if you're asked to like follow regulation and you're
not even earning money with it?
So we would be setting the wrong incentives, that's why we decided to exclude them.
And then of course we also know that open source, I mean, it's critical often from a
cybersecurity perspective, but it's just as critical from an innovation and growth perspective.
I mean, there are so many small companies, medium-sized companies that use your components,
your products, free of charge to develop on top other products and services.
And for them it's crucial that they have access to this resource.
And that's, I mean, we are fully aware of that.
And my colleague, Rice, he will, I mean, he will later on the panel also explain to you
in how many other ways we support open source as the European Commission.
So here in a nutshell, the obligations that manufacturers of commercial products would
have to comply with.
I mean, first you do a risk assessment of your product during the design phase.
Then you comply with the essential requirements that are in the regulation.
I explained earlier what they look like, these high-level objective-oriented requirements.
Then you establish vulnerability handling processes such as a coordinated vulnerability
disclosure policy.
And yeah, of course, I mean, with any legislation you will have to document in which way you
comply.
This would be called a technical file.
And once you've done all that, once you've done the conformity assessment, you can affix
the CE marking to your product.
And then for a period of five years, you will be required to handle the vulnerabilities
that arise in your products.
On top of that, there's also an obligation to report critical vulnerabilities to our
cybersecurity agency.
We are talking about vulnerabilities that are already exploited in the wild by criminal
actors, but that have not been necessarily fixed.
And this is for the purpose of helping national authorities mitigate risks in critical infrastructure
and so forth.
Here's one example of how we are also trying to help the community.
So in the Article 11, which is about the reporting requirements for manufacturers, we require
them whenever they integrate a component and they discover a vulnerability in it, and this
could be an open source component, that they notify the entity or the person that maintains
this component.
I mean, so people like you often, for example.
So for example, when you go from GitHub, when you source a component and then you discover
a vulnerability, at least you should reach out to the maintainer and inform them of the
vulnerability.
Ideally do more.
Maybe even provide code to fix it.
So here is how it works as regards components.
This is an example of a smartphone manufacturer that builds a smartphone.
So there will be some components.
Here you see them on the left-hand side in blue.
These are components that the manufacturer develops themselves.
So they would not be placed on the market separately, but as part of the final product.
And then for these components, you would not need to do a separate conformity assessment,
but it would be part of the final product.
But then there are other components.
You see them on the right-hand side, such as the ones that are developed by upstream
manufacturers.
So here you see the RAM or the CPU.
In that example, it would be manufactured by someone else.
So these are placed on the market separately, and it would be the upstream manufacturer
who would need to ensure the security of these components and to fix the CE marking.
And of course, the manufacturer of the smartphone is responsible for the entire product, right?
Just because you integrate a component of someone else doesn't mean you don't take
any responsibility for it, but you would need to do due diligence when you integrate those
components.
Yeah, so these are the categories for the conformity assessment that we propose.
For the vast majority of products, the default category, you would do the conformity assessment
yourself as a manufacturer.
You do not need to interact with any third party.
But then there is a smaller list of critical products, which you can find in the annex
of our proposal.
That's roughly 10% of the scope.
And there we require more stringent conformity assessment and sometimes even independent
third party assessment.
Examples of these more critical products are firewalls, CPUs, or operating systems.
And then there is also a possibility for highly critical products.
We are not making use of that now, but we are proposing that in the future we can add
highly critical products to a list for which it would be necessary to undergo a mandatory
certification.
We do not have any products in mind.
This is really just to future-proof the legislation because we all know that digital products
permeate society more and more and we become more and more dependent on them.
And there may be a point at which we will rely on such crucial products that we need
even a higher level of assurance.
I don't know, think human brain interfaces or something like that.
I mean, yeah.
Okay.
This is the CE marking that you're all very familiar with.
We are also trying to facilitate compliance for the manufacturers as much as possible.
So we would be providing after the entry into force of the proposal compliance on how to
– sorry – guidance on compliance in general, as well as examples how to do things in practice,
for example, on how to delineate what is a commercial product, what is a non-commercial
product.
We will also, I mean, as I said, develop these harmonized standards.
We are looking into providing funding through the Digital Europe Program – that's a European
funding initiative – for national market surveillance authorities, but also for manufacturers
to help them comply.
But then, frankly, we are also counting on you, on the community, on software developers,
on the market also, to come up with tools that can help facilitate compliance.
I mean, many of these tools already exist, of course, such as static and dynamic code
analysis tools, S-bomb generators, but, I mean, you name it, there can be any number
of tools that could help facilitate compliance, maybe to generate some of the documentation
automatically and, I mean, also be extremely open to ideas how to facilitate this, so feel
free to approach me after the panel and we can discuss it.
Here, this is the timeline, just for you to better understand, and this is also my last
slide.
So, as I said, we made the proposal on 15 September.
We are now undergoing this legislative process.
We are hoping to conclude it before the European elections in May 2024.
And then, once it's done and enters into force, we will launch a request for standardisation
with the European standardisation bodies.
And then, 24 months later, it would enter into application, so that's when manufacturers
would need to comply with the rules and also when the harmonised standards would become
available.
Yeah, so there's still plenty of time for you to help within the process, to reach out
to members of Parliament if you have concern or to the member state authorities and get
involved.
We are, of course, also extremely interested in your views, so you can also reach out to
us.
I mean, I also brought some business parts, so later, if you're interested, you can have
some.
And, yeah, I mean, I'm extremely looking forward to the discussion now.
Thanks.
Sorry for being so fast, but I only have 15 minutes.
Thank you, Benjamin.
So, I don't know if you saw me moving around during the talk, but we were discussing cyber
resilience and also potential software defect.
I just escorted a bug outside how convenient it was, so saving a bug.
So now we're transitioning to Martin from NLNet Labs and he's going to give us his point
of view of the CRA based on from an NGO, so a non-government agency or office, organisation,
sorry.
So this is a different approach.
And, yeah, they are dealing with DNS, so that might be an important infrastructure element
to consider in this topic.
One more come from Martin, please.
Good morning, everyone.
So, I'm really grateful that Benjamin just did the hard work of explaining the legislation
and for me the, I suppose, easier part of reacting to it.
So my name is Martin Arzter.
I work for NLNet Labs, which is a non-profit R&D organisation.
We make open source software for the internet.
I stole this terminology from a great report from quite a while ago.
And what we do is we develop internet standards or we contribute to the development of internet
standards and we make implementations.
And the specific area of focus that we have...
The mic closer to you.
I will...
So the specific work that we do is we develop, we contribute to the development of internet
standards and we make implementations in software that are open source.
And we've been doing this for two decades.
We make software in the areas of DNS and we make software in the area of routing, specifically
routing safety.
And what we also do is we try to bring that knowledge to policymakers and that's what
I'm doing hopefully today.
So Benjamin just talked about the scoping and he mentioned that most of us would be
out of scope.
And when I read the proposal in September, October, I wasn't so sure.
And I think that's something we should discuss.
So there is a recital in the text that basically reads free and open source software should
not be covered by this regulation, which is I think we should be very happy that the Commission
is aware of open source and has taken concern to actually address this in new legislation
that they come up with.
I think that is something we should celebrate much like the fact that open source has been
here for 25 years.
So maybe a little warm round of applause just to acknowledge that we've been heard.
And what I want to talk about today is the fact that there's a clause here and it says
outside the course of a commercial activity.
And what is a commercial activity?
There are some examples.
It's not a defined term.
And one of the examples that is relevant to my organization, to Nellet Labs, is specifically
that what is called out is that if you charge a price for technical support services, then
you are considered commercial.
So the organization I work for is a registered charity.
We make software, we develop standards, we give it away for free, we give away updates
for free.
And yet we employ people with mortgages.
So the question is how are we supposed to make money?
And we found a way, namely the network operators that use our software want it to be available
long term.
And they want there to be different implementations available.
So they've chosen to pay us to provide support.
And so this makes our work a commercial activity, at least in the way we read this text.
I would be glad to be wrong about most of the slides I'm showing you today.
And please tell me if I am.
But that's why we got interested in this legislation.
And there are some risks if you look at this exception, because if you have an expansive
interpretation of the word commercial, then the exception is narrow.
It's this balance, right, depending on how you interpret commercial.
And if it's a narrow scope of exception, then what you create is a disincentive for open
source developers who start working on something in their free time to professionalize.
Because at some point when you hit this commercial qualifier, then you come into scope of regulation.
And there's nothing bad about regulation per se, but we have to acknowledge that the step
from not being regulated to be regulated is a change, right?
And what we don't want to happen is for charities like an elite labs and others who make this
kind of software to realize that the way they've been able to sustain their development is
now disappearing.
So what we don't want is for there to be an incentive to move to closed source software.
And finally, especially in the area of DNS, what we want is product diversity.
So it's not a good outcome if we go to a place where there's less organizations working on
these projects, because with what we want is different implementations that do not share
code for stability.
So it's not just me.
The OSI reacted to the response, and they said, and I like this quote a lot, the problem
is not the lack of taxonomy of commercial.
So the solution is not explaining what commercial is supposed to be.
It is the very act of making commercial the qualification rather than deployment for trade.
And what is relevant about this quote is that there's a very different, the act of maintaining
and creating software, and the cost of that is very distinct from the act of profiting
from its deployment.
And if you confuse these two steps, then you and commercial may help you confuse those
steps, then we get into this place.
So that's about general scoping issues.
I'd like now to move to specific concerns we have from an elite labs.
And why do we have concerns?
Because we have products, we make unbound the resolver, we make some other product.
At least we believe it's not an unreasonable interpretation to consider the stuff we release,
including binaries, to be products.
And maybe we're wrong.
I'd love to hear that.
So if we are product, and if what we do is considered commercial, then there are some
unintended consequences by being covered by this legislation.
Because currently we are an outfit with 15 people, 14 of whom are either software engineers
or developers.
Every effort we put into proving that we're doing the right thing, the compliance bit,
which is a logical part of any legislation, every effort that we spend on compliance will
not be spent on securing our software.
And the only reason why a charity like ours exists is making secure software, resilient
software for internet infrastructure.
And if you look at the annex three list of critical products, it doesn't take too much
imagination to frame most of what we do as critical products in terms of this legislation.
And I think Benjamin explained about the way to avoid having to call in third party auditors.
But it depends on the availability of European standards that are applicable to our work.
And in general, I think most of us are not engaged in the European policy process.
And even less of us are involved at the European standards institutions.
Because basically we have no need to be there at this point in time.
And we have not had a need in the past.
So at an outlet we work quite a lot on standardization.
But it's at multi stakeholder forms, accessible to any party without payment, et cetera.
And that's not how these European standardization institutions work, unfortunately.
So the escape hatch, if you are a critical product, to not have to call in third party
auditors may not actually be available in practice.
And that means we will have a costly burden checking our processes, which does not actually
contribute to the quality of code.
And that's why I think this is a concern for us, or at least an unintended consequence.
There's also text in there which requires you to fix all known vulnerabilities.
And this does not have a regard for severity.
And what this does is if you have to fix all known vulnerabilities, then this skews your
engineering effort from practices that protect you against unknown vulnerabilities.
So this is this I think this is not what it was actually intended.
I'm just flagging it.
Because we I think we want there to be good laws.
And we want to help in a democracy to achieve those good laws.
I mean, why if you live in a democracy and you like that, why not contribute, I suppose.
Otherwise, there's not a lot of points.
So there's also more detailed concerns.
So for example, we currently have the opportunity to provide security updates to providers we
know are extremely critical to the functioning of the Internet.
So if we are about to release a patch and give full information about what it fixes,
we can choose to provide a update just ahead of time to a, for example, root server operator
or some other entity which is not equal in terms of importance to all of society.
And the current text takes away our ability to do so because it requires us to do everything
at the same time, which may not actually benefit security, which is the goal.
There's also obligations to report incidents that actually relate to third party use of
our software.
So we don't do any operations.
We just develop software.
But if we are obliged to report incidents that relate to the use of our software, this
gets into a conflict of our role of remediating vulnerabilities.
And this is the case because these third parties may have some reason not to go public with
an incident at first.
If you create a conflict of interest in talking to us, then we may need longer to fix the
vulnerability if there is such a thing.
What we don't know, and this is more of an uncertainty, we don't know what constitutes
substantial modification.
So the whole idea that you trigger reassessment of your product for the CE marking, it hinges
on the fact that when substantial modification is made, you need to do it again.
And we currently don't know if that's a major release, minor release, patch release.
We do quite a lot of releases.
And depending on how this pans out, we may spend a lot of work doing compliance and less
work of doing release engineering.
Finally, there is some clause about time limited availability of software for testing purposes.
I think that's fundamentally incompatible with how open source is done.
Much of the points I've made today, we worked on together with ISE, the authors of Bind,
among others.
And on their website, you can download about 30 years of binaries, of all versions of Bind
ever made, which is really helpful if you're trying to find issues, vulnerabilities, whatever
you try to.
But the...
So what we don't want is for them to have to get this stuff offline, because I don't
think it actually helps us reduce vulnerabilities.
So if you are interested in this stuff, I recommend you to read further, because this
was just my perspective, and Elnett Labs as a charity employing people that are getting
paid full time to develop open source software is not very common, and I realize that.
But you don't have to take it from me.
You can also read about other responses.
So there's the work of OSI, there's work by Open Forum Europe, Brussels-based think tank
which collects voices from other organizations relating to open source, including commercial
ones.
And Simon, who's in the front here, maybe he can raise his hand, actually compiled a
list of responses by other...
So you can take a look yourself and have a...
And give it some thought.
I wanted also to quickly give a shout out to a blog written by Thomas DePierre.
I'm hoping I'm not butchering your name.
And it relates to supply chain thinking, how that's currently quite dominant in thinking
about security for open source.
And his point is basically supply chain thinking doesn't work if someone in this supply chain
is not actually considering themselves to be a supplier.
So that's it with respect to what I had to say.
In summary, we believe that these goals that the Commission is trying to achieve are worthy
goals.
And as a consumer, I would like them to succeed.
However, there's also some unintended consequences in their current proposal.
And I think we should aim as a society to fix those.
I'm very interested to hear your perspective.
And for now, I'd like to thank you for your attention.
And I'm looking forward to the panel.
Thank you.
Thank you, Martin.
We hit 30 minutes with two different opinions and views.
Is there some questions in the audience?
Not yet?
Oh, one, two.
Two questions.
I'm from the UK.
So how does that affect other European countries that may be?
Okay.
How does it affect the UK and the UK working with Europe?
We're still part of Europe after Brexit.
And secondly, how does it affect what's happening in the US in terms of all the stuff that NIST
is doing, particularly on, you know, from the executive order that happened in 2021?
I couldn't hear the second question.
The second question was how does this affect the US?
So thanks a lot for that question.
So for the cyber resilience act, we are applying the same principle as for any other union
legislation that is about services or products.
So whenever you provide a service or a product in the European Union, you have to comply
with the rules of the European Union.
So that means for the cyber resilience act, if you provide a hardware or software manufactured
outside the European Union to consumers or other users within the Union, you would have
to comply with the cyber resilience act.
So there's absolutely no difference.
It doesn't matter where you're located.
If you want to sell your products here, then you have to comply.
So there's also no risk that there would be an advantage for maybe manufacturers from
America or so forth that they would not have to comply and therefore have lower costs.
No, it's an elite level playing field.
Everyone who wants to sell their products here would have to comply with the same rules.
I hope that answers your question.
Hi, why is policy the right place to put these measures into effect rather than a standardization's
body like ISO, which already does a lot of the same things and provides people who want
the guarantees associated with this reliability testing to select products that comply with
the ISO requirements?
Okay, if I understood the question, the question is why we think that a mandatory approach
is necessary, right?
Right.
Why is the mandatory approach necessary instead of a voluntary approach that could be selected
by consumers who want it?
Yeah, I mean, the voluntary approach is the approach that we took basically for the last
20 years, right?
And it hasn't worked.
I mean, we are not eager to regulate new sectors.
I mean, especially when it comes to such innovation and growth fostering sectors such as hardware
and software.
So, I mean, that's one of the reasons why the Commission of the European Union for a
long time decided not to regulate.
But we see that, you know, despite of new standards coming out, development of lots
of secure development, lifecycle, guidance, new programming languages that are memory
safe, I mean, all this is coming.
We see that.
But nonetheless, I mean, the vulnerabilities, they are not going down.
And we see actually more cybersecurity incidents than ever before.
And this is why we chose to regulate.
I mean, in our view, there is simply not sufficient incentive for the market to take cybersecurity
as seriously as it should.
I mean, you all know this.
I mean, you have so many specific features in this market such as time to market.
I mean, first mover advantage, who is the first one to build a platform wins basically
the whole market.
Yeah.
So, under all these constraints, manufacturers do not have an incentive to prioritize cybersecurity.
And we feel that this can only be fixed through regulation.
Thank you.
So, there is more questions to come, but we have a panel after.
So you will be keep your question and ask your question after so that we can proceed
with the last presentation.
I was also thinking about the same thing as you, sir, about the ISO part.
Working with customers and partners at Red Hat, I can tell you that they need a directive
or a compliance based on the law.
Otherwise, they will never apply the things.
The next speaker, Omar, is going to introduce us to the other part, which is more like the
defective product and what it means in terms of liability.
So please welcome Omar with a round of applause.
Thank you.
You okay with that?
Yeah, we can see you, right?
I think Martin will show you how to use that.
Yeah, I think it's...
Yeah, perfect.
Thank you.
Thank you for the invitation.
Thank you to be here.
I'm going to try to not use too much legal terms because I think now we're going to enter
a zone that if you're not a lawyer, you will not really understand what we're talking about.
So I will kind of try to use more simple situations.
I think the name of the proposal speaks by itself, Product Liability Directive.
The PLD, as we call it, is about the liability.
So I'm going to tell you, give you some examples.
Boeing 737 Max, two of them crashed some years ago.
An autonomous vehicle that crashed and killed a person.
In South Korea, a lawnmower that went into a person, your mobile phone that overheats.
All of these situations are what we call the liability.
And all of them include softwares.
So what Benjamin explained to you are the obligation that when you want to place your
product in the union on the market, but when something goes wrong, someone has to pay the
bill.
This is how every system works in all countries.
And what the product liability does tells you who is the liable person and what the
victim has to show to claim the compensation.
So the regime of the PLD exists since 1985.
But as you know, the product of 1985 were not the one that we have today, including
software, AI systems, IoT, et cetera.
So what we have done is to redraft and re-clarify the regime that existed by including all softwares
in it.
Because as you know, and with the example that I gave to you, software can in some situation
cause harm and cause a damage.
So what the PLD does, and it says that the manufacturer is liable for damage caused by
defect in their product.
And the injured person, so in a tribunal or in a court, has to prove the damage, the existence
of the damage, the defect in the product, and the link, what we in legal terms call
the cause of relationship between the defect and the damage itself.
If this is proved, the manufacturer has to compensate the victim or the family of the
victim in case of death.
So the manufacturer is defined.
This is a definition that appears in all legislation, product legislation in the union.
The damage, what damages are we talking about?
Death, personal injury, damage to property.
Think about an IoT boiler system in your house.
Over hits, the house explodes, someone has to pay for that.
That's a simple situation, but at least you see exactly what we're talking about.
Data loss, data corruption, this is a new addition.
So obviously the liability that you had until now covered any physical things, but as you
know, you own stuff, even in the material world.
When you talk about NFTs, why would you be covered if your painting burns because of
your house, the explosion, let's say, or whatever, but you cannot get compensation if actually
you lose your NFT?
So all of this has been re-adapted and included in the regime.
So these are the damages for which the manufacturer has to pay compensation in case there was
a defect that caused the damage to one of them.
So the entire notion of defect, and I'm going to try to explain a bit also what was the
part of the revision, the entire idea of defect is that the product did not, let's say, had
a lack of safety that a general person is expected to have.
So your fire alarm does not detect the smoke.
You are expecting that it would actually do it.
If you have a computer and actually the software has so many vulnerabilities that you lose
any of your data, you might expect that actually should not do it.
So all of these are normally explained in quotes, and if you establish that there was
a defect and that there was damage, then you get compensation.
Defect does not mean that we're talking about a zero absence of bugs in a software, for
instance.
That's not what it means.
Zero, it's impossible.
You cannot have it.
But you can have vulnerabilities that as a developer you should have expected or you
should have foreseen.
So all of these elements are taken into account to establish the liability of the manufacturer
or manufacturer developer depends on which type of product we are talking about.
So as I said, the liability has been revised, there are different adaptations of the regime
for liability, the digital age, circular economy, this is about the substantial modification
that we're talking about.
The global value chains, this is a concept that we talk mostly in trade where a product
comes from outside of the union, the manufacturer is established outside of the union and brings
the product in the union.
So you need to know who is the liable one.
And then a better protection for victims.
So basically what the new proposal or the new product liability directive proposed is
to say that any software is a product, no matter how it's supplied or provided.
So this obviously also includes any AI systems.
No matter if it's a software as a service or anything that will be concerned as a service,
all of them are software and all of them are products and all of them will be covered by
the liability.
But at the same time you also know that software do not work independently.
You have what we call the digital service, the flow of data that feeds the your AI system
for the training.
All of them will be covered and all of the providers of those data, for instance, will
be also covered by the liability in case something goes wrong.
As we talk about already, there is the exception of open source software outside of a commercial
activity.
To be clear, outside of a commercial activity is the exception for any product.
If a product is outside of a commercial activity, it's out.
But what is a commercial activity?
Well, if your software is sold, this is a commercial activity.
If you provide services to the company that takes your open source software, this is a
commercial activity.
Those are examples of commercial activity.
This is how it has been interpreted by the court.
This is part of the court judgments and case law.
You will have different situations, but these are some examples that I gave to you.
The damages to data loss and corruption.
The software updates and upgrades.
Obviously your software or any type of product that are digital evolved during their lifetime.
This has also to be taken into account.
If you do not provide a software update or upgrade that was necessary to avoid the damage,
you can be held liable.
These are the different elements, but obviously I will not go into absolute details.
Addressing the cyber vulnerabilities might also open a claim for damages.
The evolution of an AI system through machine learning could also open a claim if the machine
creates any damage.
So that's a bit of the adaptation.
The circular economy is the general concept of substantial modification.
So obviously if someone substantially modifies a product, in this case a software, it should
be the one who should be held liable if something happens, has a manufacturer or the developer
of this software after he has done the substantial modification.
The value chain is more related to the traders that imports the product in the union.
As a victim you should not be blocked just because you do not know who is the manufacturer
of the product.
So anyone who is part of the value chain that brought the product in the union can be held
liable.
So through an importer, if you buy through an online marketplace, those entities could
be held liable instead of the manufacturer.
And then obviously if they have contract with the manufacturer itself, they can have recourse
against him.
The better protection, it's more for technical points, but it's how it's going to work in
courts.
You have situations that are so complicated.
Let's take an AI system, explaining where the defect is in an AI system might be complex
as a victim to show.
So we created what we called in legal terms legal presumptions.
If you have one of the, if the victim can prove one of those elements, you have what
we call the presumption.
So we presume that the product is defective and it has caused the damage.
And if it's the case, then it is to the manufacturer to explain that actually it is not the case.
So that is a legal tool that exists in every system, but we have adapted it to ensure that
if something goes wrong, someone at least has a possibility to have a claim.
It does not mean that you're liable.
It just means that you can bring a claim to a court and make your case and explain why
the product was defective and why you have a damage and why the manufacturer should be
held liable.
This is not an automatic situation.
It's not because we have included software, for instance, in the scope of the legislation,
that it means that you will be held liable.
You need to have a damage.
You need to have a plane that crashes because of the software that obliged the pilot to
go down instead, to go up.
The autonomous vehicle that goes into a wall, why there was nothing on the road.
Those kinds of situations are the ones that at least allow a victim to make the claim
and go in court and try to get the compensation.
If the product was not defective, well, then there is no problem.
And again, when we talk about software, this is not a zero bug that we're talking about.
We are talking about expectation that you have about the software, the fact that your
software should not overheat your boiler, the fact that the pilot, the software pilot
in your plane should not push down while you're trying to go up.
Those kinds of things, these are the situations that we're talking about.
So these are a bit of technical situations.
But we have what we call a disclosure of information.
Only the manufacturer of the product itself knows the product.
So as a victim, you need to have access to some sort of information, like the data used,
any kind of evidences that could be of an help to create the claim.
Obviously those information are protected by trade secrets.
This is not a way of giving away your secrets.
They are protected through courts.
They are systems.
We have years and years of practice in national system, in tribunal, to know exactly what
can be showed, how can it be showed, and what to protect.
But there should be an access to the necessary information for that.
And finally, this is a bit of the small details that have been changed.
There was a ceiling before for claims, before you could not get more than 70 million.
I mean, we're not talking about every claim will be 70 million.
Let's put it like this.
But there was a ceiling cap.
This has been removed.
Nothing explained that you should limit it in number of money.
There was a threshold.
If your damage was less than 500 euros, you could not have any claim for liability.
And then the liability as a time period, you're not liable for 300 years.
You're liable for 10 years after putting on the market your product.
After that, you cannot be held liable under these rules.
But there is a time limitation.
This allows to predict and to ensure the risk of your business, if it's a business, or of
your product.
And there has been a small adaptation for personal injuries.
This is typical for some specific product like pharmaceutical products where the damage
appears after.
I mean, I didn't go into all the details, but the product liability does not apply only
to software.
It's one of the products.
We're talking about cars, cars, pharmaceutical products, all of them.
So any damage that any of those products will cause, you would have a claim for compensation.
So that's it from me.
Thank you very much.
I hope there was not too technical.
Thank you, Omar.
We're going to go now to the panel.
And I will introduce James Lovegrove from Red Hat, our policy director.
Who will be the moderator?
So I'm giving the mic to James.
Very good.
Welcome, everyone.
I appreciate that we're halfway through the session.
So if you want to stand up and then sit down and stretch your arms, that's fine.
So in terms of the first time we came, yesterday we had the policy summit brought together
a couple hundred people in person and hundreds more online, I understand.
But what's interesting is only five, six years ago when we started it in earnest, as the
OFEs in the crowd, there was literally, I see Talo was there, there were sort of 14,
15 people in the room.
So I mean, that massive scaling is interesting in the sense of response to the growth of
EU policy impacting digital ecosystems, open source included, but also the intent and realization
that as a community of open source practitioners, further collaboration and coordination is
absolutely essential.
I think today is a good example where the Commission sees that as well.
We're joined today by three members of the European Commission, from Digit, from Grow,
from Connect.
And frankly, I think they're worth a shout out and a round of applause.
It's a big deal having them here.
Thank you.
All right.
So I mean, music to our ears, Benjamin made it really clear up there, he mentioned rationale
to exclude non-commercial open source.
So the door is open, the ears are open, but this is a complex process.
Yesterday we were talking about the analogy of trains leaving stations and so forth, and
yeah, it's now en route.
That's going through quite a complex co-regulatory process.
And as a community, we don't have the resources in many cases to actually keep up with that.
So again, this kind of collaboration is absolutely critical if we're going to reflect that rationale
of best practices when it comes to open source, but also best practice in terms of the tools
that we're talking about into the law, into the practice.
Otherwise, there will be unintended consequences, and I think nobody wants to hear that.
I think the final point I want to make just before I hand over to our first panelist is
that even if we get the open source exclusion and some of the clarity into the text and
the articles around open source, it's still kind of half of the journey.
And I think that's important just to underscore.
There are still elements which need further discussion, how they practically impact this
extraordinary ecosystem.
And I think without further ado, I'm going to hand over to Zoe, who is the senior policy
manager from Digital Europe.
I'll let her introduce what the organization does and who it represents, but it's a big
deal when it comes to engaging with EU policymakers, both here in Brussels but across the union,
and it's great to have her here to let us know what Digital Europe thinks about this.
Thanks.
Thank you, James.
Thanks a lot, everyone, and indeed, many thanks to the organizers of the panel, but also to
the Commission.
We also do really appreciate that you always take the time, and I know how much effort
you are putting on this legislation.
So Digital Europe is an industry trade association.
For those that don't know, we represent the tech industry that is active in Europe, but
we also obviously represent both global actors from across all regions that they are doing
business in the tech industry in Europe.
And we have two chambers of members.
We have the corporate ones, and we also have the national trade associations.
This gives us an outlook on both the global scale of things, but also on the national
level.
We also represent trade associations, including SMEs, for example.
So why are we here?
That's because we think that the Cyber Resilience Act is one of the most pivotal legislation
that we are going to have.
Well, now we're this funded, but in general, it's a trendsetter.
It's a very, very important legislation.
At Digital Europe, we do sort of internal search to see what is important for our members
to make sure that our resources are allocated accordingly, and AI, data, and the Cyber Resilience
Act have been ranked as the three highest priorities for the digital industry.
So I just want to emphasize again how important this legislation is, and thank again the organizers
for really taking the time to highlight this.
Now I think it's probably one of the first times that the industry and NGOs really agree.
So Martin's presentation was very interesting, and I noted down many of the points that we
also highlight in our position.
I also want to take a moment to say that you probably wonder, especially the open source
community, you wonder why the industry, the big tech or multinationals, why do they care
about the open source community?
So actually, I just wanted to clarify that for us, it's very, very important to make
sure that the open source community is not overburdened by this legislation.
For many of our members, even up to 100% of their commercial products have relied on open
source components, and just like James said, there are many priorities, many things that
we can improve at the CRA, but not overburdening the open source community is one of our top
priorities as well.
So it is also important to note that it's a bit of a stereotype to think that the big
tech companies, for example, they only rely on closed source and they don't care about
the open source community, but I want to highlight that for us, it is very, very high important
to make this a key priority for the CRA to have clarity on what this means for the open
source community.
So I'm not going to repeat too much myself because you already said it, Recital10 excludes
open source, and we very much welcome this.
And in general, we welcome the legislation.
It's a very good draft.
It's something we can really work with, and we need it.
We can start from that.
We all agree, also the private sector, that we absolutely need these type of requirements.
So we are very willing to find a way together that makes it work, but we really need to
get it right.
Including too much, too soon, can also be very damaging.
So for open source, there is the conundrum of it's excluded, but not really.
So the text says that it's not in, but then when you look at the commercial element of
it, and if you look at the definition of what commercial is under the blue guide of the
new legislative framework, it says that commercial is understood as providing goods in a business-related
context.
So what does this mean for the open source community?
What does a business context mean?
Because like I said before, many of the commercial products rely on open source components.
So we need clarity.
Right now, if you look at the document, there are 85 pages.
Commercial is mentioned only twice, and there is no definition.
But this brings me to the bigger element, the issue of the proposal that we really see.
One, we really welcome the fact that the NLF is the approach that is chosen.
Benjamin did a great job explaining the NLF and the C marking and everything related tangible
products.
That is now, the big quest right now is how to move a regime that has been so working
very well, we think, for tangible products.
But now, the biggest challenge is the CRA wants to transform this regime into something
that is workable for software, which is, again, very welcome, because NLF has proven to be
the right way to do things.
But we really need to work more on the definitions.
So commercial is just one way, one example.
Then there are other examples, like components.
In Article 11, when it comes to reporting, it says that manufacturers have to also report
on vulnerabilities, including soft open source components in paragraph 7.
So the question there is, what does a component mean in the context of the software as well?
So this is a general comment on how we really need to work together to transform NLF into
something that makes sense for software.
This is why at Digital Europe, we have been really advocating for a clear provision asking
the Commission to develop guidelines that are specifically, that they adapt to the specificities
of software, and specifically, standalone software, with the inclusion of the industry.
Because what we see here is that the people that are going to actually have to abide by
the new compliance rules, the industry players, are not really included in the draft in the
sense that we really want to be part of an expert group, that we are going to help the
Commission that we know has the appetite to do this right.
But we bring the experience, and we bring the questions also.
What does this mean?
What does placement of the market for software, for example, mean?
What does substantial modification mean?
Modification, sorry.
So all these things, we, I think the important thing is that we all see the, we have the
appetite, but it still needs to be clarified in the text.
And maybe just as a final point, all these things need time.
And I really welcome the question before on standardization.
We appreciate that 90% of the products rely on self-assessment and when existing harmonized
standards are there.
But we also need to look at what does this 10% mean for critical products?
Have we actually made an assessment of how much of the burden is for third party conformity,
for example, are notified, but is ready?
So this all means that we need time to get it right.
The current proposal says 24 months for implementation for the development of harmonized standards,
sorry, and for the development process is just too little.
And I think this is probably something we are more or less aligned on, that we need
more time.
And for us, the proposal is 48 months, but I know this is something we will discuss further
with the Commission and with the collaborators.
Okay.
So I don't want to go into more.
There's way more there.
Just as a final comment, even if, as James said, even if we get the open source exclusion
right, there are several things that need to work in the whole context of software,
including reporting obligations.
The right timelines right now, it says 24 hours for initial notification, but we want
it to be aligned fully with a needs directive because we think it's just introducing too
many processes, it's just too much.
And yeah, I mean, I don't want to go too much into more details because James is giving
me a smile that says that I've talked too much.
Thank you very much.
Thank you, Zoe.
Well done.
So I'm going to now turn to Rom, a colleague of mine.
As you know, Red Hat is an upstream first pure play open source software company.
And therefore Rom spends a lot of his time, maybe a lot of, most of his time upstream
as a volunteer, as a developer, as a contributor.
So I'd be interested in hearing your perspective.
As Martin was mentioning, he has a particular perspective on it from DNS and now the sort
of wider, larger ecosystems that are involved in the kinds of products and projects that
Red Hat's involved in.
And to Omar's point earlier about just getting real on zero bugs being impossible in the
context of PLD, I think that's an important point to underscore and something which, you
know, the no known vulnerabilities implications for open source or even for proprietary, not
so much proprietary, but nonetheless, it is important to have that, recognize that the
commission understands that, but it needs reflecting, as I say, in the text to make
sure that clarity is clear.
So Rom, I'm going to come over to you and give you the microphone.
Thank you.
Yeah, so we are in a unique position at Red Hat of being a large contributor for the open
source and if you look at the portfolio of product that we have, I think we're depending
and contributing to about more than a million different open source projects.
That's the level of contribution.
One particular example that James was mentioning is the look at critical systems, but also
critical products like credentials and the zero bug.
We all know that zero bug policy is impossible to achieve and I'm really glad that Omar
underlined this.
But the reality is that if we don't have clear definition about this, it's going to slow
down so much contribution, so much innovation that we have.
We already see that through the lens of our internal folks and myself for some project
that I'm working on from communities, maybe you know communities, with the Special Interest
Group for authentication and key management system.
There's a lot of people scared there.
Because we're looking into putting into, I would say into the product, new features that
we deem interesting and we truly believe that it will be a game changer for the community
and putting a product in production.
But in the meantime, we are really scared because we are not able to make a full interrupt
compatibility assessment with all the different projects.
As I said, one million projects.
Can you imagine if you start having the need to go through the full cycle of integration
and testing for this?
We try to do it at Red Hat.
And that's sometimes the reason why when you look at the difference between what you find
in the community with Fedora, or doing a bit of marketing now, about Fedora or SenseOS or
I would say OKD, you will see that there's a major gap between what we have there, which
is like top edge cutting edge solution versus what we have in the product because we have
that we're scared about it.
Not scared in the sense that we don't want to give innovation, but we are scared about
what would be the end goal, the end results if we are becoming responsible also for some
breaches.
With credentials and the work I'm doing on contributing actually because we are about
112% working on this.
We look into this perspective, this lens of compliance and regulation and no later than
yesterday I was in one of our company events where we had 1200 techy people, we were interested
in technology and we were discussing a group of 60 there about this.
And that's the moment some people were like oh I'm not going to touch this, I don't want
to be responsible for this.
So we need more clarity, we need more understanding, so when we see the law and that's what I would
really love to have, it's to have more like a framework where we can share this with the
community and make sure that we can put straight upstream those perspective, those regulation
compliance perspective so that you guys are not afraid of contributing to any top notch
cutting edge solutions.
Credential is one of them.
If you know a bit of communities, you know that it's nothing related to password managers,
but as soon as you're using secrets with communities then it becomes a password manager and it's
a critical class one product then.
So it's those kind of things that nobody can think about but we need to get that into perspective
so we understand what needs to happen then in the product.
So there's specific elements to take care and there's a cycle of work that is really,
I was going to say burden but we all know that when we do software we need to go through
a secure supply chain.
This is the buzzword of 2022 and 2023 but it's a reality and I like to comment about
the ISO part.
There's so many different ways to standardize this.
There's so many ways, there's the best practices from an industry standpoint.
There's guide, I think the EU has the blue guide also where you can have some guidelines.
So there's different ways to approach this but it's an ethical responsibility to apply
it and sometimes, well, we are so carry on with our innovation that we forget about it.
We're like, oh, we should do it like this.
And so that's the other side.
I'm really worried about the regulation but in the meantime I'm really happy that there's
something there to enforce us straight from the beginning to have this secure supply chain
in perspective.
That's for me actually.
Great thanks, Rom.
I think one of the things I took from that is, and I think this penny is dropping not
just in this room but elsewhere, is that software is fungible and I think some of the terms
in the draft regulation around intended purpose around calling from my son, probably not a
good time by Sam, in terms of intended purpose, reasonably foreseeable, any known or foreseeable
circumstances, I think that's something which gives open source reports for concern.
And I think one of the reasons is, coming from an open source licensing perspective,
is that bringing that community together is not just a question of passion to solve problems
and build out open innovation in Europe but also to be shielded so developers do not incur
liability nor offer warranties.
And I think that's something which is clearly important.
And actually it's a good segue to Ghes because in his capacity at Digit in the open source
program office, the EUPL is one of such license which again is important to open source contributors
and collaborators.
So I'd be interested to hear more from your perspective, and understand from your thoughts
on this particular topic.
Thanks.
Thank you, and it's very good to be back at Fosten, people.
I think we all agree.
This legislation of course also impacts the Commission open source projects.
So we're looking forward to figuring out how to work on this.
To give you a bit of perspective, so I talk on behalf of the European Commission's open
source program office, and going to quote the words from Deborah Bryant yesterday, where
basically for you an easy to find, easy to access way to find out who to talk to amongst
our colleagues.
We will do the leg work.
We'll find out who we should put you in touch with.
We'll find out who to talk to.
And we will liaise when necessary between the Commission policymakers and the open source
community.
So that's one thing I can promise you, we'll try and make this happen.
A little bit about the OSPO, James.
Is that okay as context?
So we started in 2020 thanks to a communication from the Commission to itself about an open
source strategy that recognized that if the Commission wants to reach its political goals,
it needs to basically take into account that in everything there is software and in all
the major political goals, open source is a critical component.
To be an industry, to be a European market, to be active in innovation, to be active in
competition, open source is there and it can't be taken out.
One of the first things we did as OSPO is make it super easy for the Commission to disseminate
its open source process.
So far, previously it was a paperwork process that would take six months.
Now it is basically up to the project to decide we want to go open and we have a code repository,
code.europa.tu, which now has some 200 projects, some 700 users.
This is from the Commission, from IESMA, from DG Connect, from JRC, from the European Central
Bank, from the EDPS.
So you should check that out and maybe start working on some of these solutions.
This also shows that we will be impacted because we're pulling in an enormous amount of open
source to build these components.
Another thing that I think is good for you to realize is that we're, as a Commission
OSPO, in touch with OSPOs in the member states.
Some of them are here.
I have my colleagues from Germany on the right for you on the left and the colleagues from
the Czech Republic on the left for me, so on the right for you.
And we're in touch with these specifically for this kind of reasons.
We need to network as OSPOs, we need to avoid making mistakes that others have made before
us and work as a group.
I think I'll stop here.
It's a good introduction.
Very good.
Thanks, Gace.
So I am conscious we have, if I'm right, another half an hour, 25 minutes.
Is that right?
10 till 10.
So I would like to give Benjamin the floor just to capture some of the thoughts I see
you scribbling down.
I hope I don't put you on the spot.
But I'm sure some of them are familiar and it would be really good to hear from you on
those.
Thanks.
Great.
Thank you so much.
Yeah, I mean, actually all the points are familiar to me.
We are, of course, engaging a lot with stakeholders.
And yeah, so I mean, as the Commission, we are now in a bit in a tricky position because
we made the proposal.
And it's, of course, the Commission's view that our own proposal is perfect the way it
is.
That being said, it's the beginning of the journey.
And I mean, it goes without saying that the Parliament and Council were closely looked
at the text and they're, of course, also consulting us a lot.
And many of the things that have been mentioned here, they are being discussed by the Co-Legislator.
So for example, this question of providing products with no known vulnerability.
I mean, I can say that this is being discussed already by the Co-Legislators.
And also, I mean, we've heard quite often already this concern that maybe the transition
period is too short.
I mean, we believe that 24 months is sufficient.
But we hear this a lot from other stakeholders.
So I mean, you can be sure that this is being all taken very seriously from us.
Wonderful.
Now, folks, it's really important that this community here in this room take this opportunity.
It's not a speak now or forever, hold your peace.
But it is a good opportunity.
So if there are any who want to chime in a question, comment, that would be great.
And then we're going to move back to the panel.
Who's first?
I think you're first.
I already stole your mic.
Sorry.
Okay, go for it.
Can I borrow one?
Please.
Go for it.
Okay.
Sorry.
So I'll try to be brief, but there's a lot to say.
So first I have to apologize because I feel about this.
So I will be carried away.
Sorry.
Nothing I'm going to say is meant to be offensive to the Commission.
Actually I think that many of the recent attacks are very good for the internet industry, for
the internet, like the digital market side.
So the criticism will not be meant as a rejection of regulation.
So my perspective, I'm a software developer and the head of policy for OpenExchange, which
is a German open source software maker of around 270 people.
So I'd say that we are small compared to the big tech industries globally.
But we are still one of the biggest.
So we are also one of the companies that I mean, we make stuff that is in every Linux
distribution like Davco.
And so we care about security.
We are ISO certified, ISO 27.1.
We do this.
So we are among those that could afford to follow everything that's in the CRI and would
do that.
But we are part of an ecosystem.
And so we feel the need to, I mean, also bring the perspective of others, including some
smaller projects that we use in our own projects.
And the problem with this regulation is, well, there are multiple problems.
Let's start from the non-commercial exemption.
So there isn't really no way that you can tell commercial projects from non-commercial
projects because each and every project, except maybe like my hobby project, which I only
do for myself and publish somewhere, has some economic result, creates value.
And there will be people using it to create further value.
And so it is basically very hard to write a non-ambiguous way to tell commercial from
non-commercial.
And all projects, including like, I mean, search centers like in the net universities
need some money to get at least donations.
So there is no way you can tell this.
And on the other hand, I would also be against in saying that all open source software is
exempt from this regulation because I'm sure that the proprietary software makers would
come and say, you know, as they have been saying for 20 years, open source is just a
toy, it's just a hobby project, so you should use proprietary software which is secure.
So don't do that.
The problem is really that this law doesn't seem to understand how software works.
I mean, software, pure software, material products have a nature which is significantly
different than any physical product with software in it.
So this regulation seems to be designed with cars in demand, with toys, with IoT devices,
but not for pure software.
Pure software is more similar to literature in a way.
It's something that is the result of collective development.
And if you have a look at open source projects, yes, we are the manufacturers of Davco.
But if you look at the code, it's written by people everywhere on the planet.
So yes, but the real authors are maybe like a thousand people which are in Europe, outside
of Europe, everywhere.
And so your law seems to put the burden of putting a CE mark on every line of code which
is imported into Europe.
I don't even know what that means.
We have repositories.
Maybe they are in Europe, they are mirrored in the US.
There are people from Australia and from China putting code into it.
And this code is traveling all over the world throughout the borders of the European Union
several times per second.
So should I every time I check some code, I mean, someone should stop the code at the
border and put the CE mark.
This doesn't really make any sense.
It's simply impossible.
And it is to say, I mean, all the people here, I mean, your law is designed for the traditional
20th century way of making things in which there's a manufacturer and there's a distributor
and someone that sells them in a shop and then there's the use of the consumer.
I mean, like if we were still buying, sorry, I'm trying to be sure, but I know you want
to stop me, but I have to say this.
And so it seems designed for the time when we went to the shop to media markets and bought
Windows 95 in a box on a CD.
And this is not how it works.
Everyone here is at the same time a manufacturer, a distributor, an importer and a user of code.
And there's no way you can distinguish these roles.
So you have to find something.
You have to find somewhere.
So I know I can cut it short.
So I don't understand the problem you're trying to solve.
Show me one case in which a European piece of open source software had a problem that,
I mean, created issues with the entire world and how this could be solved by this regulation.
Because if you just maybe funded some security audits for projects that cannot afford them,
this would make a much bigger effect.
So let's start again discussing from software for something specific from software, because
this really is not working.
Thank you.
So I submitted the open form Europe document that Martin referenced.
I probably have a dozen questions, but I picked one.
So to publish software in the EU or to import software into the EU, the publisher must perform
CRA certification and accept CRA obligations.
This means that software from outside the EU will no longer be available in the EU if
those developers do not perform CRA certification or accept CRA obligations.
How is that not a massive problem?
Yeah.
But really, really quick.
There's always...
Yeah, okay.
Yeah.
I think my understanding is one of the goals of the CRA...
Close.
Hi.
I think my understanding is one of the goals of the CRA is to avoid log4j or open SSL type
of incidents.
But they are non-commercial open source software.
And when we exclude them from CRA, we are technically not addressing these cases.
So what do you think about this?
As a solution, what do you think about expanding the proposal to set up necessary operational,
financial assistance dedicated to the critical open source initiatives?
Maybe especially the EU ones, maybe European OSPO.
Is that feasible?
Thank you, Alex.
Thanks.
Thanks for the insights and thanks for the panel.
I mean, I have two questions.
We have a lot of problems.
But I'm interested in solutions.
So first, what's your proposal to fix this commercial term?
So do we have one?
Could you let us know?
And the second one, to the Commission.
So do you see the issue like NLnet?
So would you consider charities to be affected by this definition or not?
So what's the Commission take on the NLnet position?
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
And finally, we've known for a long time since David Wheeler wrote his paper stating that
all open source software is commercial.
The word commercial is a bad word to use if you want to exclude open source.
And so I recognize that it arises from the courts in Europe and from the Blue Book.
But have you considered using different terminology to solve the conflict that exists here because
of the nature of the community you're addressing rather than because of the context of the
existing legislation?
And secondly, which community organizations did you consult in working on both the PLD
and the CLA?
The panel is comprised purely of commercial organizations or commission members.
And all of the questions you've received are from community charity representatives who
are in the audience and on the panel.
I wonder what you're going to do to fix this problem so that you don't get it with every
subsequent bill.
Thank you.
Can I?
Okay.
Yeah.
Thanks a lot for all these questions.
I mean, maybe first this one on who we consulted.
So as a run-up to any commission proposal, there is a public consultation which runs
for three months.
It's a period of three months where we ask a set of questions to the public and everyone
can respond to these questions, including you.
I mean, maybe you didn't know.
It's possible.
I understand that.
Of course, we know, of course, very well that these public consultations, I mean, that big
players, commercial players, they are more paying attention to this because they have
the resources to do, though.
And that's clear to us.
But that's also, of course, one of the reasons why I'm here, right?
Because I know that this community, maybe the voice is not heard as much as the voice
of other communities.
And as I said, we can, of course, keep engaging.
You can come later.
I can give you a card.
And we can discuss.
We can even do maybe another small event and discuss further, right?
I mean, it's all possible.
On this concept of commercial, so first, I mean, I think it would be very difficult for
us to replace it by another concept because it's well grounded in this new legislative
framework.
And all the industry players that we've been speaking to so far, they all say they want
us to use the new legislative framework because they are familiar with it from other product
types, right?
So we want to ensure that all stakeholders can use the same framework.
If we now invent a different framework, it will lead to a lot of fragmentation.
It will make compliance more difficult for companies.
So that would be difficult.
Of course, I mean, there's this crucial question of where to draw the line of commercial.
I think we are open to all your points.
We understand them.
I think what would, from our perspective, be very difficult, I mean, this is how I understood
your intervention, would be to say we just exclude all open source because it's all somewhat
commercial and it all needs to be excluded.
I think this would not work simply for the fact because it would create an incentive
for proprietary manufacturers to switch over to open source, right?
Not everyone can do that.
You want that?
Okay.
I see.
No, but it would create an incentive to get out of the scope and to not have to comply,
right?
I don't think this is what you want.
Then there was also a point from you on all the many small players and how it would be
maybe difficult for them to comply.
So the cyber resilience act is, I mean, the requirements are risk-based.
That means that, I mean, when you're a very small player, there's also a chance that maybe
your project faces smaller risks and is maybe less critical.
And you can take that into account when you comply with the requirements of the regulation.
On top of that, for the vast majority of products, we only require self-attestation by the manufacturers,
which means you will not have to reach out to any third parties or interact with any
authorities.
You can do it all by yourself.
And this should be absolutely feasible.
What other questions did we have?
Yeah, there was this question of how the CRA would improve the ecosystem for components
that are vulnerable, such as log4j, where you said, I mean, this is a non-commercial
component.
So, I mean, we have this due diligence obligation in our proposal.
That means that in the future, when a commercial manufacturer integrates a product, for instance,
a logging utility that is free of charge available, they will have to make bigger effort than
today looking at these components.
I mean, that, again, of course, depends on the risk.
I mean, if your project is low risk, you will only maybe check the change log if there are
regular security updates or not, and you're done with this assessment.
But of course, if you integrate this component into something much more critical, you will
have to take a much more closer look at these components.
So what we're trying to do is we're trying to make manufacturers of commercial products
proprietary or open source or whatever assume more responsibility for the open source components
that they're integrating.
And we believe that this will help raise the level of security on these components as well.
Yeah, there was this question on whether charities would be considered as a commercial activity.
So I cannot just give you a straight answer on that.
I think it always depends on the individual case, right?
I mean, what we've learned is that there are so many different types of open source projects,
so many different types of funding models.
So you really need to look at each and every case to see if it's a commercial activity
or not.
What I already said, I mean, as the commission, we are absolutely willing to provide more
clarity.
This could be done, for instance, already in the legislative process that we single
out important examples and we provide clarity directly in the legal text.
But for all these other niche cases that will come up, this will not be possible in the
text because we cannot, you know, a legal text needs to be short and concise and we
cannot take into account every single example.
But we're absolutely prepared to provide examples once it has come into force so that you have
the certainty that you need to know whether you are in the scope or not with your project.
I think I took them all.
I think, yeah, of course.
So for, I mean, I'm going to speak for the PLD, but for my proposal, we had expert groups
consultation in 2019, 18, 20, 21, consultation also through the contractor where they were
questioned through different kind of stakeholders.
We had the consultation for when the proposal was adopted by the commission in September
2022 with the half-year C-POTO.
This is where you find all the proposals and where you can give your comments on it.
And it was for more than three months for ours.
So we always tried, obviously, to reach as much as possible.
The thing is, obviously, there are sometimes channels.
It's not that we avoid having talks with the people that can criticise the legislation.
We need critics to also make the legislation better.
This is how it works.
So obviously, as you said, that, yeah, there might be some players that are more voiceable.
This is the reality.
I think it's also part of how the field or the ecosystem organised between itself.
You need to have one speaker, someone that can represent also the community, because
obviously if we have someone that comes for the open source community that says that he's
speaking for the community, then he would bind everyone.
So you know, those companies that have those trade associations, et cetera, this also gives
a framework for us to really say, okay, this is a voice of this sector, this sector, this
sector.
If we do not have this, it's a bit complicated for us to take it as just being the voice
of the entire community, because you can have an opinion and someone else can have another
one, but then which one do I have to consider as being the one of this community?
That's a bit of the complexity also for us, just to be honest.
On the charity one, there are definitions.
Commercial activity is whatever against for money or for free.
It does not matter the economic value in that sense.
It's a concept that goes much more broader than this.
So I understand that there is this need of clarification.
This is where the definitions are there.
But they are also the basics of any legislation that we have in the union.
It's not that simple to change just one definition that is common to all of them in one single
piece of legislation.
This is also the reality of how the proposal works.
You need coherence.
You can have some exclusions.
But we talk about why, I mean, it's not just the need of excluding open source software.
It's also the need of ensuring that it does not have an impact on innovation, but you
also need to take into account the reality of it.
So that's a bit of the...
Thanks, Omar.
Benjamin?
Yeah, sorry.
I just want to be thorough.
I forgot to answer one of the questions I just realised.
So there was a question on whether we think we... whether there could be a risk that products
developed in third countries would simply not be made available anymore on the European
Union market.
So no, we don't see this risk, to be honest.
I mean, the European Union, depending on the figures that you look at, is probably the
biggest economy in the world.
I think everyone has a very strong interest in bringing their products on our market.
It has also not been the case with other regulation.
If you think of the GDPR, yeah, I mean, the list of companies that choose not to provide
services in the European Union because of GDPR is very short, yeah.
So we don't see this risk.
Thanks, Benjamin.
I know, Martin, you're dying to say something.
So Hannah, go to you.
Thank you, James.
So I will answer the question for Alexander of how to fix this.
But first, I would like to respond to some of the comments made.
So I think you hit the nail on the head by saying that the consultation, that it's complex
within the existing way of how Brussels operate, at least that's my perspective now as a newcomer
here.
And I think if we are not addressing that bit, like how to talk to communities like
this, then we will be in this situation again and again and again and again.
And I want to point out specifically that the discussion about commercial just now,
I've read both your proposals, and you are not using the same examples of what constitutes
a commercial activity.
So if you're saying that they originated from the legal jurisprudence, then one of you seems
to have a different view on the jurisprudence than the other one.
And I was wondering, have you considered talking to the open source program office when considering
the definition?
And I'm sorry if this is a bit confrontational, but I was just actually curious.
So before you answer, I'm going to try to answer Alex Alexander's question.
I think he was asking how to fix this.
I'm not jealous of your jobs because I think this is extremely complicated and I don't
have the full answers.
I have one sub-answer and it relates to critical products.
I believe that there should be an escape hatch for class one and class two critical products
that if they are completely open source, then there should be the ability to do self-assessment
regardless of any other factors.
Because I think the value of having critical products that are open source is tremendous
in terms of security too.
So we should be considering that aspect in addition to whether or not there is an EU
standard that it can conform to, for example.
I hope I touched somewhat on the ask again in maybe a couple of weeks because I think
they are in a hurry, so we should be too.
And then maybe back to the question I just asked about talking to Gheis.
The power of the moderator.
What's it worth?
Cold beer?
Maybe just to add one question to make your debate a little harder.
First I think that we also need to recognize that you guys are also here on a Saturday
and everything, so I think the appetite to interact with many groups is also there.
So I think that's important to acknowledge as well.
But I'm mostly wondering about the part on technical support because we are focusing
a lot on the definition of commercial, but the text itself says also especially when
technical support is provided, then the open source software is not excluded anymore.
And I guess this is more of a general question because I'm not myself an open source developer,
but I'm just wondering to what extent this is demotivating then for developers because
I understand a big part of the maintenance after, for example, is a motivating factor
for people to develop because then they are also involved later on on the maintenance.
And I'm wondering also to what extent this is counterproductive for the objectives that
the CRA sets, having the people that are involved in the development but also they're involved
in the later stages of making sure that the product remains secure, then actually this
I think I would assume that it helps the security of the product.
So it's more of a question on whether you have discussed this part.
I'm sure you have if you put it there, but just if you could elaborate a bit further
and an open question also to the audience just because I think it's important for the
audience to sort of educate us as well.
Thank you.
Yes.
Okay.
We've got five minutes left.
So Roman, Omar, and then we close.
So I'm just going to continue what you just said.
I think one of the tremendous beauty of the open source community is giving support to
each other.
And I think technical support, as defined, is very dangerous.
And I'm going to give an example.
If you are having a if you maintain a project and you use one of these service like GitHub
and you start helping someone to make the solution work.
So it's technical support, right?
So you open an issue, you start helping the person and so on.
If the person who received the help decide to sponsor somehow the developers giving money,
giving contributions in terms of money, then from the definition it becomes a commercial
activity.
This is not the intent.
It's a donation.
So I think it's really important to get that into perspective.
So we are not reducing the level of contribution both in terms of software development, documentation,
but also money to run some testing infrastructure that is required to do security.
So that's my point.
Just it.
Wonderful.
There's an applause.
There we are.
Good.
So Omar, I'm going to hand it to you.
I know you wanted to answer a point from Martin.
So for the internal cuisine of how the Commission works, proposal don't come out from one own
service.
So we have three different director generals.
So connect for the telecommunication.
Digi-Grow is for the industry and the JIT.
Each proposal before going out is assessed by all the dedicated services of the Commission.
So everyone is consulted and everyone makes the legislation readapted where it needed
because obviously the expertise of each one of the director generals helps to make the
proposal.
So you need – it's an internal mandatory step.
And on the small definition, it's not that we have different concepts.
It's the – how it has been interpreted until now and we're talking about almost 40 years
of case law.
It's elements of what the commercial activity can be and cannot be.
It's never a proper situation.
It does never draw a specific line.
I know it does not reply to your question, but we have elements of what is or what is
not a commercial activity and all of them take into account at the end to create the
commercial activity.
But they are not – it's not just if you are in room A, it's commercial activity and
in room B, it's a commercial activity.
It's different element that can constitute the commercial activity or not.
That's a bit of a situation.
If you are developing your open source software from your couch on a Sunday, this is not covered.
If you're – if a big company takes it out from a website, whatever, you are not making
the commercial activity, but the company is doing the commercial activity.
So you're not – you know, these are a bit of the differences.
These are the elements.
But if you make it – if you make yourself money out of it, this is a commercial activity
in a way or another.
If you also make it, you are the commercial activity.
If a big company takes the software and puts it in its product, he's doing the commercial
activity but not you.
So you will be the one to cover it, not yourself.
It's a bit of – this is how the commercial activity works.
I know it's complex, but yeah.
I don't know.
We have two minutes left, so 60 seconds.
Yeah, I mean, on this technical support, I mean, it's of course a tricky one, right?
The idea behind the Commission Proposal of the Site Resilience Act is to say that when
you're making money with a product, it's a commercial activity and then you should
comply with the rules because there are so many different ways in which you can monetize
a project.
It's not always just charging a price, yeah.
It could also be placing ads in your mobile app or, I mean, charging a lot of money for
technical support.
I mean, technical support does not necessarily mean that it's a non-commercial activity.
So of course it's different if you just recover your costs, yeah.
That's maybe something else.
But if you're truly making money with a project, we are convinced that it's only fair
that you are covered by the subresilience act.
So that end device compatibility check, compliance check, I think is important.
I think we've run out of time.
We could have gone into the whole notion of components, which you mentioned on 11.7, and
where we see that posing some workability issues.
Unfortunately, we've run out of time.
But I would like to ask you all to show your...