Okay, there's next talk.
Please be silent.
Okay, this will get an interesting thing.
Normally I'm used to move my arms a lot while I'm talking, so I try to get the microphone
always close to my body now.
I will give you some information about the ELISA project.
ELISA stands for Enabling Linux and Safety Applications.
Maybe a quick question up front, who is aware of safety-critical software?
So shall we raise the hand?
Hi, that's good, maybe 25-30%.
I hope you will also learn something new then.
See before we start fully, I just give you a short view on which project context I'm
working.
So as you can see, my project is mainly focusing on embedded IoT Linux at Bosch.
And what you try to do is utilizing a lot of open source projects, see how they fit
into a landscape, and can be of value for very, very different device classes because
normally you don't believe it, but in all of these kind of products you will find Linux
in there are also embedded real-time OS and so on.
So that's all about this part, shortly about myself.
Who am I?
I'm a technical business development manager.
I'm focusing on embedded open source mainly, doing this for the Bosch.
And in parallel, that's also why I'm speaking here.
I'm the technical steering committee chair and working group lead for the Linux Foundation
ELISA project.
I bring a past history of 15 years plus, I guess I started in, we'll see, Ubuntu 6.
10 more or less to set it up on old PCs sharing it to exchange students, so like a distributed
hub of PCs.
And since 10 years I'm more or less in the automotive space with Linux.
We had our first product with 2.6 kernel out.
And yeah, I guess now we can start on the real things.
So if we talk about Linux in safety critical systems, we first need to get an understanding
what a system really means.
And a critical system maybe, first you say assessing whether the system is safe requires
understanding sufficiently.
And you can see here's nothing about Linux in there because a system always goes beyond
the scope of a pure operating system, beyond maybe a single component.
And in this one you have a system context in which Linux plays a role.
And you need to understand the system context and how this is used because if you don't
get the understanding how Linux operates, you cannot see in which components you're
interested and which features you may need or which not.
And then you can evaluate what kind of these features are really relevant for safety.
And while you're doing so, we'll most likely identify gaps that exist and you'll definitely
need more and more work to get this done.
So if you look into the Linux ecosystem, which we have already, there's a good reason also
to take Linux because there is a large variety of devices.
The ecosystem is strong.
You have good tools around this, an incredible amount of hardware support.
It runs on many, many devices.
And also very important, you have a broad set of experts in there.
If you see what's sometimes taken as the benefit of a certified safety critical OS, often it
comes with hard real-time requirements and capabilities.
We know that the pre-empt RT patches are in good shape and in the kernel.
But hard real-time maybe goes even further down the road and then there is a development
process.
And if you see these two sites, if you come and want to address very complex products
like in the automotive field or maybe you can even call your robot vacuum cleaner a
more complex product, then you come from two perspectives.
On the one side, you could go with a traditional small component driven RTOS and you have to
handle all the complexity so you need to have more hardware involved, you have more multi-core
support, not everything works out there.
Or you go the other way around and you come with a Linux where you all have these kind
of things but you need to improve and see what do you do about the development process,
what do you do about the real-time capabilities and so on.
So anyway, when you build a more complex product, you need to find a way to tackle these kind
of challenges.
And also bring the difference closer to each other.
While we were looking at Linux, I'll take the part in the beginning, it's a little bit
like a disclaimer in a little more text.
In this collaboration of Elisa, we said we cannot engineer your system to be safe.
We're talking about functional safety, not about cyber security, but if we just take
this example, there's always a strong risk also that you have security breaches in your
system.
So it's similar here also with safety.
If you build a system, it's still your responsibility for it and just because we provide a little
bit of guidance or engineering principles and so on, it's still in your responsibility
as someone producing a product to make things safe.
And also that way to make sure you really have the prescribed processes in use, use
the methodologies and one of the core questions which typically could come is like, oh, so
you're from Elisa, you make a safe Linux, will you certify a kernel version?
And that's not what will work because we all know you have to move forward.
There's continuous improvement there, sync and vulnerabilities fixed so you need to go
on and this gives an additional challenge which is continuous certification.
So we will definitely not have a version and we will also not certify Linux in this project.
We just give the tools and other elements in there.
So here are the last part of it.
There's still responsibility, legal obligations, liability and so on which is also in your
role.
Nevertheless, we find a good set of partners already which are willing to support this
mission and they subscribe and say we would like to bring the whole thing forward and
seeing this there is the mission statement which we have drawn.
It's lengthy.
Basically you can read that there's set of elements, processes, tools.
It should be amenable to safety certification.
We look into software and documentation development and in the end that we aid the development,
deployment, operation or the adoption of a project into another project.
If you look at this mission, you see basically four key parts which we will also talk later
about.
You have elements and software which is concrete implementation of what we're doing and you
also have the processes.
A development process always falls into safety critical, into security system wherever you
look at.
And if you start to automate things, if you would like to analyze, there's always a strong
involvement of tools in there.
And the last thing is when you do all this kind of work, you need to document it.
And actually there's a lot of documentation work needed in any place.
So how we do all this kind of things?
We take it in our ELISA working groups.
We split this depending on different topics, on different contexts, they're growing depending
on demands of certain sizes reached.
We're extending this.
And if we take a first look, we have a safety architecture work group.
This is a group which actively looks inside the kernel and takes, for example, a watchdog
subsystem because watchdog is one of the crucial elements which we have in use.
It looks what are potential safety related functionality.
Is there something in the kernel which is non-safety related?
How would these kind of things interfere?
And by this, the safety architecture work group does a lot of analysis, try to improve
documentation in the kernel, provide new tools.
So that's a strong set in there.
Basically driven by use cases and demands of products.
And a little more broader approach is brought in by the Linux features.
And actually the full name is Linux features for safety critical systems.
So it's not about generic features, it's about the safety criticality part in there.
You can imagine this a little bit like if you're familiar with security measures like
namespaces or other parts, that we're looking for elements in here which could improve safety.
So which means if you take this special kernel configuration, a feature, turn it off on whatever
you do and say, okay, this will come up as a blueprint, this is something how you better
work with memory, how you not work with memory, all these kind of things are tackled in the
Linux features.
And then it's a nice group because with the results which are in there, if you're already
in a process of enhancing Linux and don't want to wait for all the results of the use
work group and so on, you can have incremental steps here, just take some part of it and
make your system more robust, more dependable and you can also judge it against how does
it compare to security things which you're doing.
And so here, that's the big value of this group.
It's more on a direct use base and serving a long-term safety argumentation, but not
that it's something which develops for years or so.
It's basically assess what's there.
This also the improvement of code quality is very important.
We have tools investigation code improvement work group.
The code improvements could be, for example, done with doing fuzzy testing on the kernel
using tools like CodeChecker or Syscaller and then bring them also into a set up where
we have a server kind of a CI which runs on Linux Next or whatever kernel configuration
to identify issues to get the kernel more robust, more dependable, reliable and serve
also the argumentation about the quality of the kernel.
And what was also on the right side in some of the challenges part was on the engineering
process and as you know, there are rigorous methods within the kernel development.
So there are a lot of reviews, patches are rejected and you see that there's strong demand
from traditional project management when it comes to safety products and not every process
complies with it directly.
So we need to find an argumentation how is there an equivalence to the open source development
process compared to what, for example, an ISO 26262 requests for automotive products.
On top, what is very interesting to understand here is also that if we look into open source,
you basically cannot easily buy a maintainer or developer there.
So you cannot buy features directly or so you get more an unbiased view or maybe a personal
view but a maintainer who is really committed for the component for this power subsystem
of the kernel and so on.
And with this strong commitment, for example, you already fulfilled a little bit of independent
view because in safety systems, whenever it comes later on, the developer needs to commit
to what has been done but of course it's not written down.
It's not written down.
The maintainer fully commits to whatever it does.
So this is some part, for example, where you can start argumenting on it.
And as the different elements need to get somewhere and need to be visible, we figured
this out because we were running quite in parallel with different streams on this but
never brought this forward, we came up with the systems work group and the system work
group actually should take all these different elements, bring them together, works cross-functional
and maybe even cross-project and combine the elements.
In order to tailor the system properly, we have vertical use cases.
A newly created one, so there's not much information in this presentation about the aerospace work
group yet.
The overall idea is it should address everything which flies and you know that in aerospace
there are many safety standards, safety integrity standards, various levels in there.
What you may not know and that's at least what we have heard so far was there is already
Linux in use and also in certified product there's Linux use but it's only on a very
low safety level so it's not on a very higher upper level of safety certification.
What's an obvious thing if you see the member there is like 50 to 60 percent is from the
field of automotive and therefore we have an automotive use case in there.
If you drive a car, if you have a scooter or whatever you may see sometimes that there
is an oil pressure sign, oil temperature sign, check engine, whatever basically when you
put on the ignition you can see all these little LEDs and this is also the use case
which we are using in the automotive work group.
Basically what we said digital or cluster, instrument cluster, the speedometer, everything
becomes digital, everyone has a display in your cars and that gives a good chance because
there are more complex system in there, a lot of rendering, graphics rendering involved
and this is actually safety critical function.
Even if you are in driving or in rear gear mode this has to be properly displayed and
it has a safety criticality assigned.
Because showing the check engine part is a safety criticality.
The third group which we have is from the medical devices and here this is something
from a completely different perspective while automotive has the commercial element in mind
maybe want to have cost savings driving topics forward with the open APS, APS the artificial
pancreas system.
It's driven by open source so there were open standards, chances to interact with your insulin
pump and you see that this can become very uncomfortable.
There's a nice TED talk from Dan M. Lewis, I recommend this, I put the link also in the
slide that you can download them and check it.
You can see that you basically need to track your glucose level and certain dose of your
insulin depending on your glucose level and this is also with warnings and so on and it's
very basically event triggered so you see the blood pressure goes up so you set the
dose it has a certain delay until it reacts and what came in here was to add the raspberry
pie in the middle writing some scripting around it getting it stabilized and create a product
out of it.
And why I want to stress this is this is not to any IEC ISO certification done, it was
done by an open source engineer, started this project and if you download this, if you use
it, you use it on your own risk and therefore the work of Elisa was basically also the first
use case we put directly in the beginning of the workshop to say let's take a deeper
look let's analyze what's in there.
It's running for thousands of people, it has never been certified, they are very happy
and you see it's increasing quality of their life but it's not certified.
This is safety critical product not certified and we are not targeting to do the direct
certification of it.
In the first step we are looking into the different levels of the analysis, see what
is involved, what workloads are in there, is there something which could make this fail,
is there a risk in there, what potentially could go wrong here and this is basically
the completion of the use cases and I've drawn this basically together as you can see an
inner part which is very common for almost all the different projects which get fed then
by the use cases feeding and say this is how you need to configure, how you need to specialize
because you cannot create a full safety critical item completely out of the context, you cannot
have this generic safety argumentation, you always need to judge it towards assumed context
and this then turns into Elisa deliverables.
A little bit on another view here you can see also an exemplary system architecture
mainly how we triggered it in the systems work group.
It's not only Linux involved in these latest products so if you come and you of course
in the medical devices open APS system it's a pure raspberry on it.
There is not the direct archers involved if you don't treat the sensor or the insulin
pump as the archers next to it but if you come to more complex products you always need
to face that there are archers involved, there are microcontroller, microprocesses, container
technology come into picture, everybody talks about containers and embedded these days and
also virtualization technologies like Big Zen or the KVM so this is something which
gets in there easily and for this part if you see on the working group site this Linux
features, architecture, code improvement this directly go into the Linux work.
So the main outcome of this is for the Linux ecosystem, the Linux kernel and a lot of this
work is also not directly related to the hypervisor or the archers but there are things also
which going a little bit further like the tools and the engineering process things which
are coming out there may also have a good value for other products which you build on
so if you have a Yachta involved in there you can build a file also with a meter layer
and then it may be good to have this tooling parts in there or also code improvements
can come into picture there, certain tools which we make use of in your CI for testing,
QA system or others this is an element to be considered here and lastly the use cases
to further completeness they basically tailor down this system to whatever you need so for
example in the automotive work we for now tailor the system down for getting a better
Linux kernel understanding and we get rid of the endear originally from the container
the virtualization the archers but we know once we have solved some parts of our work
we need to get the system context and the system context involve all these kind of things
right and saying this we also do a certain outreach to other projects so I put in the
Zephyr community we have the automotive Linux which is already in there there could be other
Linux versions and also strong involvement of the Yachta project and said I didn't know
where to put the SPDX properly on this picture but we see it later on how we interact so
far we already are in discussions with Zephyr and Xen we have weekly meetings also where
Xen members pop up where Zephyr is present with some representative and we saw that these
are safety critical open source projects so they basically save the share the same burden
they need to show how the development process is done how do we guarantee certain quality
levels where is the testing done where are the requirements management and the trace
abilities to everything this is something which pops in there quite good if we take
this architecture and as I'm coming from the automotive part we have different projects
which share these architectural sorts and there is a large group on the Eclipse SDV
project there is a SOF initiative from ARM basically having similar members like the
SDV and then we have a large automotive grade Linux which also is so nice to provide us
with the reference implementation for the automotive use case so they share very similar
architectures lastly not directly related to safety but having safety considerations
in there and being part of the system is the Yachta project for some building part to get
this into a CI reproducible here for example the S-bomb generation suddenly plays into
the game which you can do with the Yachta project and while we were discussing we figured
out that there is also like data needed into system S-bomb and for this we reached out
to the SPDX and there is actually SPDX special interest group on FUSA meeting weekly to extend
this scope there is also later on talk where parts of it get presented why do we do all
this I like this statement from George Bernard Shaw he said if I have an apple and you have
an apple if we exchange the apple we have still one apple but if I have an idea and
you have an idea and we exchange these ideas and we have two ideas and that is basically
where it goes about we need to get a good understanding we need to bring the things
together and by this we of course need to look into certain activities so now we come
into the part what the different work groups do and if we check for example the elements
process tools documentation not every work group acts in the same amount as the others
do so just put some bubbles in here to see where our mainly our work is going so we have
a lot of things of course on the software part that people are interested in the Linux
kernel and the process part is maybe not so strong because it needs to be centralized
and the usage of this process goes into the other work groups so the OSAP the medical
part architecture a little bit also they work on these kind of processes and bring this
into the other work groups tools seem to be pop out on multiple work groups because here
tools are handy tools pop up we bring it into the into repo you might tell about it get
it used and if we want to go into continuous certification at some point of time there
will be a need of having a lot of tool support in there and basically every work group does
documentation I want to give you some examples on this from the process perspective there
is a system theoretic process analysis that the first topic I will tell a little bit more
about so it's the dry stuff about the systems architecture it's not the code level on this
but we figured out when you do this kind of STPA analysis at some point of time you reach
also a level where you need to understand more about the kernel so I'll tell you something
a little bit about the workload tracing which we have done and also here supporting from
the another work group here of a call tree tool that's self not in basically utilizing
tools and approving things but writing something also from scratch and this all then later
on fits into the meta ELISA which is basically the Yachtel layer for the automotive use case
enhancing the automotive grade Linux demo alright we also did something without modification
like the code checker implementation syscall I will not tell that much about it but just
to give some examples of our work on and all our information is public so we are quite
spread it up to GitHub part there's some parts on G drive we do regular blog posts and have
some white papers published so it always depends on whom do you want to have as audience or
readers so we share this is also YouTube channel but I don't judge this as documentation okay
as at first we look into STPA so STPA stands for system theoretic process analysis what's
interesting to see is if you're coming from safety criticality maybe automotive you know
hazard analysis risk assessment FMAs you may grow with watch spreadsheets drawing cases
checking your API interfaces and all these kind of things and the nice thing about the
STPA is you go a little more in a graphical approach like on the left part of the picture
some basics here it's still relatively new I say this because the old analysis part come
from microcontroller worlds up down to the 60 70 I guess 70s is more or less so there
was a long time where a lot of these analysis techniques came in and they haven't been much
improved but the systems which have been a lot of analyzed have increased complexity
and this is something which need to be considered and this system theoretic process on STPA is
able to handle very complex systems the reason for this is that you can start from a quite
broad view and maybe you don't know all the elements so you have something you just get
a name for it you don't know how it really looks like and you have another blob where
you have more details so you can connect all these different blocks and these analysis
will still survive even if you know not the whole block of some specific part yet and
then you will go in a very iterative approach and just go there step by step you figure
something out you go to one level down going deeper into the system figure out that your
assumption didn't hold true so you do these kind of things for the analysis and what's
also good if you have certain analysis it basically looks on an API level it looks under
definitions or so but this one explicitly goes on the system context and it includes
human interaction the human operation and this is also what's not there for other parts
in parallel you directly get a good while you do the analysis you already improve your
documentation you get a good standard standing of the system and you can even if you are
in a QA department so you can even integrate it properly with existing systems model based
approaches the principles of it to get the very very high level it's quite easy there
are four key elements there is the controller on top this one sends a control action to
a controlled process and this provides typically a feedback well that's not enough in the end
there's also important to know that the controlled process as such may also control something
else so that's how things get more grown up and the question now in the end is what could
go wrong what are unsafe control actions you can use these methodology for maybe understanding
how your water pipes flow in a building or how people walk through certain so you can
always attach this to whatever use case you like you always the same approach but for
our case and the main idea of it was for safety criticality for risk assessments and that's
why we say let's look under unsafe control action a little bit of warning and the next
slide is in a way that you will not read it's level one analysis of this open APS use case
and well yeah that's how it looks like in the middle there's the open APS system you
have a view from the top level so it's a developer view it's not the full user view here so you
have infrastructure people if algorithm developer you release the software then they come to
human operator who uses the software installs it further on this goes in the system we don't
know yet what the system is this is what I mean with the very first level you don't care if
it's the Linux system or whatever is an easy just so this is my open APS system and when you
have understood what is your critical part in there how the system context looks like you
may go into the next level and now we zoom in into this open APS system and go on the next level
and in this you see there is an actually a Raspberry Pi involved we know this from the
hardware part and the OS and there's a Raspbian you have an open APS toolkit involved the
actual algorithm this may control the insulin pump the night scout part is also an edge
external command you see all these kind of things and the work group has been on this
level for some time and then try to write down the next level going deeper and then
actually needed support so that's where workload tracing came into picture we used the
mentorship project here and had support so someone fully concentrating on the activity
of workload tracing that's another little table which you can only read therefore the
main things to be known is we use S trace and C scope as the main tools for the analysis
but there are stressors in there like stress and G, Paks, TES and other parts this may depend
on your workload which you use once you are challenged with the system and in this one
the information which is coming in there now our system calls how often are these system
calls coming in the frequency of it which subsystem does they belong to that you know
okay where is my critical parts where is the system call entry point and by this you can
more deep dive into the different system and this causes a lot of refinement into the upper
layers again because now you have iteration and see maybe you have a wrong assumption
but still before everything was correct as you understood now you just improve it related
to this cause of the call tree tool that's something basically rewritten and own part
so the idea was to see here is a system call what else of course what are the ways how
to interact there how to visualize things because if you just see something and grow
through the code you cannot really grab the complexity and this was just the first shots
also here it's not worth the reason but you can see there is a file system part and the
very interesting part is this is quite a static thing so you will see all the potential options
while in the previous view if you have a call if you have the workload tracing you basically
see where has the pass gone but you don't directly uncover the untraced passes and here
you see all the passes but you have the part chance that you meet something completely
irrelevant because you're not on this with your workload and this is a compromise or
complementing element of this and well you get a good insights on the kernel construction
and it can help you to analyze more workload in there right we bring all these things together
in the meta-aliasing instrument cluster it looks like the AGL instrument cluster we saw
this picture before I highlighted the change which we did we write danger in there and
this made us the whole thing safe which well is of course not the full story the full story
is that we just needed a use case to which we can analyze which has safety relevance and
it was a good QT based demo so we could make use of it it was running on QM0.
The kernel has a little drawbacks on this I'll come to this very soon but with this
you can start analysis tracing workloads and also add a watchtruck mechanism yeah watchtruck
would be the next part of it basically what we like use of in a lot of concept is an external
watchtruck even if you don't see it directly in the open APS system for example there's
still an external monitoring involved which gives emergency data if the Raspberry Pi would
do something wrong in the one or the other direction not that it happens but there is
a monitor there which controls which will give a beep or so and inform the user similar
you do it in the automotive case where you have this telltale environment and you want
to have something which is traced in your workload so yeah this challenge response watchtruck
challenge response make basically it's not simply looking for something but it gives
a little challenge to the workload while the workload process process other parts and it
gets a response in there so that you know okay yeah that's really alive and it's not
just replying and it's the demand here comes basically that we for a lot of use cases cannot
fully guarantee that the workload comes in the proper time that a process doesn't hang
and this release a lot of responsibility from you by checking this was an external
workouts and it's mainly looking into the safety critical workload I know there are
ideas to say well let's put this watchtruck thing and let's watch everything in there
this typically doesn't work out so you really concentrate on the things and say this is
safety critical and all the other parts are related to user experience so if you're drawing
rendering engine it and God's lucky and you see a lot of delay and touch screen or whatever
that's nothing which you want to experience from a user perspective but as long as the
warning signs come in time and improper from safety perspective this is all fine so it's
good to split up here between what is the intended functionality what is the safety
criticality of it what do I need to monitor and what not and for this this is just the
safety net in there here I said this is used widely in automotive there are other industries
basically always have your safety net somewhere around which monitor sinks and what we try
to do is we want to get more responsibility to Linux and by this you can start where with
a lot of elements in this safety critical part and yeah so that's the main thing on
this part and the last message is very important for me it's not that you consider your watchtruck
in this design as being there or need to be there you basically start creating your system
that you never need to trigger the watchtruck because you don't want this this is just your
system functionality and it has to work and in best case this gets not triggered into
a safe state for a total use case for example this could mean that the screen is turned
off or that you do a restart basically you would maybe make a black screen or so that
people directly recognize the driver oh it's not going right here that could be also be
be a warning message or what else but depending on what's your safety passes you need to make
sure that this is really also triggered so their safety criticality comes in picture
again I prepared a one minute video but I never know how these kind of things properly
work if you do a demonstration so I just put the YouTube link on the material and if you
are brave enough or even not I guess it's nice a straightforward thing we have a good
documentation how to experience this demo because when we started with the Elisa work
we saw that we basically start building our topics from scratch we documented everything
right good as best on our standing and then someone came and said well but I'm not using
Ubuntu I'm using an open sousa tumbleweed and we figure oh we need a little bit more
maybe that we have more environment set up that people can reproduce things so we came
up with a docker container which basically gets the things packages installed which you
need the right version of it to make it easier for people then the next thing we observed
was oh okay the people do a yukto build yukto consumes a lot of space and a lot of compilation
maybe the cache binaries would be a good option and so we also enabled the estate in there
so that you cannot can now build like in the parts which are still buildable or needed
to be built in a roughly 40 minutes on a poor laptop it's basically depends on your download
speed also right it's quite amount of download which you typically have with the yukto build
on long one we also see if we can extend the two other systems that we are maybe also Debian
version of it or so but for now it's the yukto star the last thing which we figured out there
are also use cases maybe where you want to deep dive into the system and this would be
the complementing part to this demo if you don't want to see the video and you want to
just try it out directly if you have qm on your system installed just download the binaries
directly they get built nightly so really nightly so every night you get a new one it
always goes to the latest version of the AGL with a little bit of problems last week but
it's up and running again does a build check does a boot check so that you can really experience
it and it basically uses the instructions which are written down in the github readme
markdown file right yeah this is about this some next steps the stpa is continued so we're
getting into deeper levels of it we need to see that we get the workload tracing properly
reflected in the different diagrams this was heavily driven by the medical devices work
with the automotive has not used the workload tracing that much but we bring this in there
the call tree also got extended with another tool which was uh ks called ks naf does certain
kernel static navigation tool so to get a better analysis on better view on this um
therefore the meta eliza as i was talking about qm where everybody wants to see real
hardware so we also are on a pass on bringing this on an arm based hardware for now so we
have the x86 in qm with simulation and an arm underneath is mainly driven by systems
work group and what is very important so far this display checking in there so we are not
normally you would check what the rendering of a telltale but there's so many different
kind of implementation so that we mock a lot of things there and we want to improve this
so that we have proper display checks and also a lot of monitoring this is basically
on the four topics which we have seen uh additionally we work on the system as bomb we enabled the
s bomb part for generating material in the demo we want to improve kernel configuration
trimmed on the size of the image then uh have the rt documentation updated have more complex
cluster demo involved and that's mainly it so summarizing what you have seen uh we talked
about the challenges in the beginning basically what a difference between the traditional
safety critical arthas and the new one what's this is what the collaboration can and what
cannot achieve you heard about the goals and the way of the strategy which tools we analyzed
or which which elements we looked into and also then uh you could see how the different
work groups interacted how they put into a system how we outreach to wider community
parts i talk about the contributions of the different work groups what is shared with
the community also in form of usable use case downloadable then you could see methodologies
of our stpa workload tracing and lastly uh we got a little bit of view on what's coming
next and i guess we're good from the time from the questioning part
does anyone have a question there's one above coming down you have a question okay
thanks for the interesting talk uh you mentioned certification uh as one big problem so uh
where uh can we improve things so that certification processes become more open source friendly
and open source software becomes more certification friendly so what has to be done or can be
done there yeah i i guess some part from the certificate so you're asking how can uh open
source and certification come closer to each other from both sides right and um one thing
could be for example done in the documentation in improving tracing down having tools supporting
how do certain features get from the mailing list into the system if there's a test around
it so this gives a lot of confidence and trust in what it's doing um from another perspective
there's not much in the safety integrity standards which allow the usage of pre-existing software
and so for this there's also an iso pass currently which allows more usage i mean depends on
the safety standard which you're in if you're some relaxed medical standards it's less requirements
on this but for automotive it's very strong and prohibitive on this um so i would say
doing careful work and explaining design decisions and so on making this visible and more structured
having maybe centralized bug tracking and so on this this can help a lot from this perspective
it will be good for the certification authorities and we do a lot of clearance also yeah if i
heard you correctly said from supporting the um assessments and authorities in there we
also have uh company support where we really are in the working groups and get from certification
authorities input in the continuous work which we are doing so they are directly working
within the work groups as well yeah chin as well thank you very much for your talk um
i had a i had a just uh quick question i want to get a feel for what your opinion on on
this is um do you think there's space as um a certification for for something like linux
improves can you move the mic a little closer because it's for me i hear the people louder
leaving so just a little sorry yeah oh oh wow yeah see the difference um as as um as
uh process for certification and for validation of uh linux kind of improve and and change
over time do you think there's ever going to be space for for linux to be used in in
kind of a critical component on vehicles or do you think that space is completely reserved
for for something that's actually using real time uh the main part which i heard was if
there's i got the real time part in the end yeah like do you think there is it's already
there fair thank you okay was there someone else have a question you have a question yeah
so what is the place for linux itself in um let's say what does safety integrate and to
integrate the level of linux itself in this model because if i take let's say i saw two
six two six two um there's a v model requirements for development this but linux already has
source code there are no you know there is no coverage this test with all these memcdc
coverage etc etc so what's the place of linux and how to keep it maintain it without forking
yeah so um you say where's the space and the place of linux if you see the v model for
example the iso two six two six two where does things fit in there a lot of demands
like uh car coverage parts tracing and so on so what you can see is that um first of
all speaking about a level you will not directly go to an azl d level which puts much more
requirement on the tools that's for sure so you should start on the lower azl ab level
that's also what we did uh we relaxed some part also for automotive cases let's don't
start with two complex parts maybe get a real-time criticality out there because then you have
to review much more parts and um so the space which i see is that you should argue equivalence
for certain things that you are in close collaboration with successors and explain how things are
done because when the iso was originally prepared it was not considering a complex system as
linux being in use and the large amount of pre-existing software so from this if you
are in an assessment if you are there if you can show and show the credibility by requirements
work by good concepts you may in the first and come up which to system which is arguably
safe but not directly certifiable to your iso two six two part but uh this already showed
you the perfect discussion room also right because then you see well you cannot tell
me this is not working but you still say it's not certifiable and then you see also the
glitch of the standard and if you reach this point you have a lot of good support when
you go with certification authorities early if you have internal assessments and you can
judge it and in the end it's also your responsibility where you say oh i argue foreign equivalence
because it's not saying in this book you have to it says recommended highly recommended
leaving you also trace for showing equivalence to this model i'm using this and on top i'm
adding this and by this you can get an iron and of course getting feedback from your developers
that the work which you're doing also into kernel mainline and so on so maybe also it's
possible to somehow affect how iso two six two six two is developed because it's a bit
outdated in some way some of the members in elisa have people in these iso committees
that are basically taking it back into that direction for the future revs of the standards
i we don't have visibility at least i don't because i'm not in those committees but we
do know that um some of those member companies you saw up there um are there and they are
advocating for things to work a little bit better in future revs okay is there anyone
else who has a question um okay well thank you for your talk
uh