Hello, everyone. I'm Marco Castelluccio. Thank you for being here to listen to my talk.
I'm an engineer manager at Mozilla. I've been at Mozilla for almost 10 years now. I've been
I started as a contributor, then an intern, then I was hired, and I've been here for almost
10 years. I started working on some funny projects like writing a Java VM in JavaScript,
and then more recently I started focusing on using machine learning and data mining
techniques to improve developer efficiency, which has also been the subject of my PhD.
During this talk, I will show you how we will all be out of our job in a few years. Joking.
I will just take you through our journey of how we incrementally built features based
on machine learning for improving software engineering, one on top of each other.
I'm the father of two, Luna and Nika. And before we start with the presentation, I wanted
to explain a little why we need to do all these complex machine learning things on top
of bugs, CI, patches, et cetera, et cetera. Firefox is a very complex software. It's a
browser. We have hundreds of bug reports and feature requests open per day. We have 108
million bug reports at this time, which is almost the price of a one bedroom apartment
in London. We release every four weeks with thousands of changes. And during 2022, we
had 13 major releases and 45 million minor releases. As you can see, we even sometimes
party when we reach a certain number of bugs. As I said, Firefox is one of the biggest software
in the world. We have a lot of legacy. Netscape was open sourced 25 years ago. A few days
ago we celebrated the 25th birthday. Over time we had 800,000 commits made by 9,000 unique
contributors representing 25 million lines of code. We had 37,000 commits only last year
by 1,000 unique contributors. Not all of them are paid. Many of them are volunteers.
And this is a list of the languages that we use. As you can see, we use many of them.
We have C, C++, and Rust for low level things. Rust is gaining ground and is probably going
to overcome C soon. We use JavaScript for front end and for tests. And we use Python
for CI and build system. But we have many more. So if anybody is interested in contributing,
you have many options to choose from. But let's see. So as I said, the complexity is
really large. We have thousands and thousands of bugs. And we need some way to control the
quality, to increase the visibility into the quality of the software. And we cannot do
that if the bugs are left uncontrolled. One of the first problems that we had was that
there is no way to differentiate between defects and feature requests. We call them bugs on
Bugzilla. But they are actually just reports. Many of them are defects. Many of them are
actually just feature requests. And so at the time we had no way to measure quality.
We had no way to tell in this release we have 100 bugs. In this other release we had 50.
So this release is better than the previous. And so we need a way to make this differentiation
in order to measure the quality. And it was also hard to improve workflows if we had no
way to differentiate between them. So we thought of introducing a new type field. This might
seem simple. It's just choice between defect, enhancement, and task. But in practice when
you have 9,000 unique contributors, some of them not paid, it's not easy to enforce a
change like this. And we also had another problem. We have 100 million bugs. How if
we just introduced this type, it's not going to help us at all until we reach a mass of
bugs that we change. So if we just introduced it at this time, it will only start to be
useful six months from now. So we thought how do we set the field for existing bugs
so that this actually becomes useful from day one. And we thought of using machine learning.
So we collected a large data set. I'm not sure it can be considered large nowadays.
With 2,000 manually labeled bugs, a few of us labeled independently. And then we shared
the labeling so that we were consistent. And we had 9,000 labeled with some heuristics
based on fields that were already present in Baxilla. Then we, using the fields from
Baxilla and the title and comment through an NLP pipeline, we trained an XGB boost model.
And we achieved accuracy that we deemed good enough to be used on production. And this
is how the bug bug project started. It was just a way to differentiate between defects
and non-defects on Baxilla. We saw it worked. And then we decided, we thought, what if we
extend this to something else? What is the next big problem that we have on Baxilla?
And it was assigning components. Again, we have lots of bugs, millions of, 100,000s of
bugs. We need a way to split them in groups so that the right team sees them, so that
the right people see them. And the faster we do it, the faster we can fix them. At the
time it was manually done by volunteers and developers. So you can see a screenshot here,
a product and component, PDF viewer. In this case, we didn't need to manually create a
dataset because all of the 1 million bugs were already manually split into groups by
volunteers and developers in the past. So we had, in this case, a very large dataset,
two decades worth of bugs. The problem here was that we had to roll back the bug to the
initial state because otherwise, by training the model on the final state of the bug, we
would have used future data to predict the past. And it was not possible, of course.
So we rolled back the history of the bug to the beginning. We also reduced the number
of components because, again, with the Firefox scale, we have 100,000s of components. Many
of them are no longer actually maintained and no longer relevant. So we reduced them
to a smaller subset. And, again, we had the same kind of architecture to train the model.
With a small tweak, we didn't have perfect accuracy, and so we needed a way to choose
confidence and recall. So pay the price of lower quality but catching more bugs or catching
fewer bugs but be precise more time. So we can control this easily with a confidence
level that is output by the model, which allows us to sometime be more aggressive, sometime
be less aggressive. But at least we can have a minimum level of quality that we enforce.
The average time to assign a bug then went from one week to a few seconds. Over time,
we auto classified 20,000 bugs. And since it worked, we also extended it to webcompat.com,
which is another yet another bug reporting system that we have at Mozilla, which if you
find the web compatibility bugs, please go there and file them because it's pretty important.
And you can see here an action of the bot moving the bug to, again, the Firefox PDF
viewer component. Maybe I should have used another example just for fun.
Now we had something working, and it was starting to become promising. But we needed to make
it better. We needed to have a better architecture for the machine learning side of things. We
needed to retrain the models. We needed to collect new data. We needed to make sure that
whenever a new component comes in, we retrain the model with the new components. If a component
stops being used, we need to remove it from the data set and things like that.
So we built over time a very complex architecture. I won't go into too many details because it
will take too long. But maybe if somebody has questions later, we can go into that.
And then with the architecture now, it was easier to build new models. So we even had
contributors building models just all by themselves. In particular, there was a contributor, Aayush,
which helped us build a model to root out spam from Bugzilla.
So it seems weird, but yes, we do have spam on Bugzilla as well. People are trying to
get links to their websites into Bugzilla because they think the search engine will
index them. It's not actually the case. We tell them all the time, but they keep doing
it anyway. We have university students. Bugzilla is probably the most studied bug tracking
system in research. And we have many university students from many countries that use Bugzilla
as a playing field. Many times we even contact the universities and professors asking them
if we can help them give more relevant topics to students, et cetera. But they keep filing
bugs. And this contributor maybe was from one of these schools, was tired of it and
helped us build a model. And the results were pretty good. I'll show you a few examples
of bugs that were caught by the model. So this one was, if you look just at the first
comment of the bug, it looks like a legit bug. But then the person created a second
comment with a link to their website. And it was pretty clear that it was spam. This
one is another example. This is actually a legit bug. It's not spam. Maybe it's not so
usable as a bug report, but it was not spam. And then somebody else, a spammer, took exactly
the same contents, created a new bug, injecting the link to their website in the bug report.
And somehow, I don't know how the model was able to detect that it was spam. It's funny
because you can see that when you file a bug on Bugzilla, Bugzilla will automatically insert
the user agent so that we have more information as possible to fix bug. But in this case,
he was copying the contents of the other bug. So we have two user agents. And they're even
on different platforms, one on Mac and one on... Ah, he was using Chrome, actually.
Okay. So we were done with bugs. Well, we are not done with the bugs. We will have plenty
of things to do in the future forever. But we were happy enough with bugs. And we thought,
what can we improve next? One of the topics that we were focusing on at the time was testing
and the cost associated to testing. We were experimenting with code coverage, trying to
collect code coverage to select relevant tests to run on a given patch. But it was pretty
complex for various reasons. So we thought maybe we can apply machine learning here as
well. But before we go into that, let me explain a bit about RCI because it's a little complex.
So we have three branches, three repositories, which all kind of share the same code, Firefox.
We have Tri, which is on-demand CI. We have Autoland, which is the repository where patches
land after they've been reviewed and approved. And we have Mozilla Central, which is the
actual repository where Firefox source code lives and from which we build Firefox nightly.
On Tri, we run whatever the user wants. On Autoland, we run a subset of tests. At the
time, it was kind of random, what we decided to run. And on Mozilla Central, we run everything.
To give you an idea, on Tri, we will have hundreds of pushes per day. On Autoland, the
same. And on Mozilla Central, we have only three or four. And it's restricted only to
certain people that have the necessary permissions since you can build Firefox nightly from there.
And it's going to be shipped to everyone. The scale here is similar to the bug case.
We have 100,000 unique test files. We have around 150 unique test configurations. So
combinations of operating systems, high-level Firefox configurations. So old style engine
versus new style engine, certain graphics engine versus another graphics engine, et
cetera, et cetera. We have debug builds versus optimized builds. We have ASAN, T-SAN, code
coverage, et cetera, et cetera. Of course, the matrix is huge. And you get to 150 configurations.
We have more than 300 pushes per day by developers. And the average push takes 1,500 hours if
you were to run it all at the same, all one after the other. It takes 300 machine years
per month. And we run around 1 million machines per, we use 100 million machines per month
to run these tests. If you were to run all of the tests, you would need to run 2.0, all
of the tests in all of the configurations, you would need to run around 2.3 billion test
files per day, which is, of course, unfeasible. And this is a view of our tree herder, which
is the user interface for Mozilla test results. You can see that it is almost unreadable.
Likely the green stuff is good. The orange stuff is probably not good. You can see that
we have lots of tests. And we spend a lot of money to run these tests. So what we wanted
to do, we wanted to reduce the machine time spent to run the tests. We wanted to reduce
the end-to-end time so that developers, when they push, they get a result, yes or no, your
patch is good or not, quickly. And we also wanted to reduce the cognitive overload for
developers. Looking at a page like this, what is it? It's impossible to understand. Also,
to give you an obvious example, if you have, if you're changing the Linux version of Firefox,
I don't know, you're touching GTK, you don't need to run Windows tests. At the time, we
were doing that. At the time, if you touched GTK code, we were running Android, Windows,
Mac. That was totally useless. And the traditional way of running tests on browsers doesn't really
work. You cannot run everything on all of the pushes. Otherwise, you will have a huge
bill from the cloud provider. So we couldn't use coverage because of some technical reasons.
We thought, what if we use machine learning? What if we extend bug bug to also learn patches
and tests? So the first part was to use machines to try to parse this information and try to
understand what exactly failed. It might seem like an easy task if you have one under tests
or ten tests, but when you have two billion tests, you have lots of intermittent filling
tests. These tests fail randomly. They are not always the same. Every week, we see 150
new intermittent tests coming in. It's impossible to, it's not easy to automatically say if
a failure is actually a failure or if it is an intermittent. Not even developers are able
to do that sometimes. Also, not all of the tests are run on all of the pushes. So if
I push my patch and a test doesn't run, but runs later on another patch, and it fails,
I don't know if it was my fault or somebody else's fault. And so we have sheriffs, people
that are only focused, whose main focus is watching the CI, and they are pretty experienced
at doing that. Probably better than most developers. But human errors still exist. Even if we have
their annotations, it's pretty hard to be sure about the results. You can see a meme
that some sheriffs created. Flaky tests are the infamous intermittent filling tests.
So the first step, the second step, after we implemented some heuristics to try to understand
the failures due to a given patch, was to analyze patches. We didn't have readily available
tools, at least not fast enough for the amount of data that we are talking about. We just
used Mercurial for authorship info. Who is the author of the push? Who is the reviewer?
When was it pushed? Et cetera, et cetera. And we created a couple of projects written
in Rust to parse patches efficiently and to analyze source code. The second one was actually
a research partnership with the Polytech clinical ditoreno. And the machine learning model itself,
it's not a multilabel model, as one might think, where each test is a label. It would
be too large with the number of tests that we have. The model is simplified. The input
is the tappel test and patch. And the label is just fail, not fail. So the features actually
come from both the test, the patch, and the link between the test and the patch. So,
for example, the pass failures, when the same files were touched, the distance from the
source files to the test files in the tree, how often source files were modified together
with test files. Of course, if they're modified together, probably they are somehow linked.
Maybe you need to fix the test. And so when you push your patch, you also fix the test.
This is a clear link. But even then, we have lots of test redundancies. So we use the frequent
item set mining to try to understand which tests are redundant and remove them from the
set of tests that are selected to run. And this was pretty successful as well. So now
we had architecture to train models on bugs, to train models on patches and tests. The
next step was to reuse what we built for patches to also try to predict defects. This is actually
still in experimental phase. It's kind of a research project. So if anybody is interested
in collaborating with us on this topic, we would be happy to do so. I will just show
you a few things that we have done in the space for now. So the goals are to reduce
the regressions by detecting the patches that reviewers should focus on more than others,
to reduce the time spent by reviewers on less risky patches, and to when we detect that
the patch is risky, trigger some risk control operations. For example, I don't know, running
tests more comprehensively in dispatches and things like this. Of course, the model is
just an evaluation of the risk. It's not actually going to tell us if there is a bug or not.
And it will never replace a real reviewer who can actually review the patch more precisely.
The first step was again build the dataset. It is not easy to know which patches cause
regressions. It's actually impossible at this time. There are some algorithms that are used
in research. The most famous one is SZZ. But we had some answers that it was not so good.
So we started here again introducing a change in the process that we have. We introduced
a new field, which is called Regressed By, so that developers, QA users, can specify
what caused a given regression. So when they file a bug, if they know what caused it, they
can specify it here. If they don't know what caused it, we have a few tools that we built
over time to automatically download the builds from RCI that we showed earlier. Automatically
download the builds from the past and run a bisection to try to find what the cause
is for the given bug. With this, we managed to build a pretty large dataset, 5,000 links
between bug introducing and bug fixing commits. Actually, commit sets. And then these amounts
to 24,000 commits. And then we were able, with this dataset, to evaluate the current
algorithms that are presented in the literature. And as we thought, they're not working well
at all. So this is one of the areas of improvement for research.
One of the improvements that we tried to apply to SZZ was to improve the blame algorithm.
If you're more familiar with Mercurial annotate algorithm, to try to, instead of looking at
lines splitting changes by words and tokens, so you can see past changes by token instead
of by line. This is a visualization from the Linux kernel. This is going to give you a
much more precise view of what changed in the past. For example, it will skip over tab
only changes, white space only changes, and things like that. If you add an if, your code
will be in tandem more. But you're not actually changing everything inside. You're changing
only the if. This actually improved the results, but it was not enough to get to an acceptable
level of accuracy. But it's nice, and we can actually use it in the IDE. We're not doing
it yet, but we will, to give more information to users, because developers use annotate
and git blame a lot. And this is a UI that is a work in progress
for analyzing the risk of a patch. This is a screenshot from our code review tool. So
we are showing the result of the algorithm with the confidence. So in this case, it was
a risky patch with 79% confidence. And we give a few explanations to the developers.
This is one of the most important things. Developers do not always trust developers
like any other user, do not always trust results from machine learning. And so you need to
give them an explanation. And this is another part of the output of our tool. This is again
on our code review tool. We are showing on the functions that are being changed by the
patch if the function is risky or not, and which bugs in the past were involved in this
problem. So developers can try to see if the patch is reintroducing a previously fixed
bug. And they can also know what kind of side effects there are when you make changes to
a given area of the code. Now, we did a lot of stuff for developers.
We trained models for bugs. We trained models for patches. We trained models for tests.
We trained models to predict the facts. Now I'm going to go to a slightly different topic,
even though it's connected. Privacy friendly translations. So we're working on introducing
translations in Firefox. The subtitle was actually translated automatically using Firefox
Translate, which you can use nowadays. The idea is that translation models improved a
lot in recent times. Current cloud-based services do not offer the privacy guarantees that we
like to offer in Firefox. They are closed source. They are not privacy preserving. So
we started a project. It was funded by the European Union to investigate client-side
private translation capabilities in Firefox itself. It is currently available as an add-on
that you can install in Firefox. We support many European languages, and we are working
on supporting even more. We are going to also work on supporting non-European languages
like Chinese, Korean, Japanese, et cetera. And in this case, we use machine learning
on the client side to perform the translation. So your data never leaves your Firefox. The
models are downloaded from our servers, but they run locally on your machine. So the contents
of the web page that you're looking at will never go to Google being or whatever. They
will be translated locally on your machine. We use a few open data sets. Luckily, we have
lots of them from past research. Not all of them have good quality, but many of them have.
But we are looking for more. So if you have suggestions for data sets that we can use,
please let us know. On the data sets, we perform some basic data cleaning, and we use machine
learning-based techniques to clean the data, to remove bad sentence pairs that we believe
are bad. Of course, the data sets that I showed before are open, but sometimes they are just
crawled from the web, so they contain all sorts of bad sentences. Also, HTML tags and
stuff like that, we need to clean them up. Otherwise, the translations will learn to
translate HTML tags. And we use some techniques to increase the size of the data set automatically,
like back translations, translating sentences from one language to the other, and back translating
it in order to increase the size of the data sets.
So we trained a large model on cloud machines, which is pretty large. You can see it's around
800 megabytes. So every language pair, you would need to download 800 megabytes, and
it is super slow. So we can only use that on cloud. So we use some techniques in order
to reduce the size of these models and to make them faster. We use knowledge distillation,
basically using the model, the large model that we trained as a trainer for a student
model, which is much smaller. So you can see that from 800 megabytes, we got 216. I think
now we're around 5, 6, something like that. So it's much smaller, and you can actually
download it on demand from our servers. And we use quantization for further compression
and perf improvements, so moving the data from the model from float 32 to int 8.
Then we compiled the machine translation engine to WebAssembly in order to be able to use
it inside Firefox. We introduced some SIMD extensions into WebAssembly and into Firefox
in order to be able to be even faster when translating, even though we translate a bit
at a time. So it's pretty fast. And the engines are downloaded and updated on demand.
Let me show you a demo.
So you can see the, my Firefox is in Italian, but you can see that it automatically detected
that the page is in French, and it is suggesting me to translate it to Italian. I will change
it to English. Oh, fuck.
So it is downloading the model. Now it's translating. So while it was translating, you already saw
the contents of the first part of the page was already translated, so it's super quick
in the end. And the translation seems to be pretty good. I don't speak French, but I think
it makes sense. You can also use it from the toolbar. So you can choose a language and
translate it to another. Let's do Italian to French. It works.
All right. So if you know any dataset that we can use,
in addition to the ones that we already use, or if you're interested in building a new
great feature in Firefox, or if you want to add support for your language or improving
support for your language, come and talk to us at our booth. We would be really happy
if you could help us. And before we come to an end, let me show you how far we've come.
The dogs have grown, and we have learned that it is possible to tame the complexity of a
large scale software. It is possible to use the past history of development to support
the future of development. And it is possible to use machine learning in a privacy friendly
way and in the open. What else could we do with the data and the
tools that we have at our disposal? I don't know. I'm looking forward to know. I'm looking
forward to see what other wild ideas you and us at Mozilla can come up with. Thank you.
Thank you very much, Madhka, for the amazing talk. Now we're open for questions. If anyone
would like to make a question, please raise your hand so you can take the microphone.
Questions, questions, questions? Hands up. There. Okay, okay. I'm sorry. I'm learning.
I'm new to this. I'm coming up. Hello. I have actually two questions. First question is
have you actually think about the idea to use this mechanism to automatically translate
interface of Mozilla products? Sorry? Testing? Yes. Yeah. So the question is have you think
about mechanism of automatically translating the interface of Mozilla Firefox products
or maybe documentation you already have, like MDN, because it's still a demand to translate
this stuff? I'm sorry. I'm not hearing well. Can you maybe come closer? From here? Okay.
Now it's better? Yes. Okay. So my question is have you tried to use this mechanism of
automatic translation to use this translation for existing interface you have in the products
and especially also documentation part? Because it's kind of vital part when you need to translate
new functionality or you have to translate something new in interface, you need the help
of translator. But if you already know how to translate new stuff, so that means you
already have a dataset, you can actually automatically translate new parts of interface without translator.
Yes. So it is definitely something that could be used to help translators do their job.
We could translate parts of the interface automatically and of course there will always
be some review from actual translator to make sure that the translation makes sense in the
context, especially because Firefox UI sometimes you have very short text and it needs to make
sense. But yes, it's definitely something that we have considered. And actually one
of the datasets that we use from the list, it's not possible to see from the slide, but
it's called Mozilla L10N and they are sentence pairs from our browser UI. People are actually
using it in research for automating translations. Does anyone have any other question? Please
raise your hands if you have any other questions to Marcum. Okay. If not, thank you very much
again, Marcum. Thank you.