Good afternoon. Are you ready? Martin, how many times did I tell you not to sedate the
audience when we give a presentation? I think this was a marketing ploy, wasn't it? At least
we get some customers. Let's try this again. Are you ready? Much better. Welcome to our
presentation on Linux in Oz. This is Oz? More like a talk than a presentation because
there's only one slide. This is us. If you like knowledge or madness, either is good.
Welcome. Just out of curiosity, how many people of you listen to podcasts? Very good. Pretty
much everybody. Wow. How many people have heard prior to this gig about Linux in Oz?
Your listeners are here. This is all planned. Ah, yes. Did you win the bet by any chance?
Because Martin now just bought officially the bet. How many people have listened to
one of our episodes prior to the presentation? This one gets the bottom up. After the presentation,
please collect your prize. Indeed. Well done, that man. On with the show. Thank you all
for coming. Today is really about getting an idea of what our podcast is like, which
is generally very free flowing and well prepared. Maybe before we go into the details, maybe
we should introduce ourselves more formally. Yes, I'm Chris. I'm Martin. Actually, it's
the other way around. This is Martin. My name is Chris. You want to say something about
you? Sure. Some of you may know that we've been doing some IT stuff for a bit. Chris
is retired now. He does it as a hobby. This is us. Martin has about 20 years of international
arms trade, drug trafficking and other professional activities on this. My name is Chris. I have
been using open source for the last 30 plus years. I also run a lot in Germany, the La
Frankfurt have been doing community events for ten years. About three years ago, but
more about that in a minute, we decided to start this podcast. Martin, what did you do
prior to the podcast? Prior to the podcast. Like yourself, I've been in IT since the year
dot. Messing around with PDP 11s and all that kind of stuff. If anybody knows where that
is. In short, we've been around for quite a while and been playing with open source
software, which you will hear all about today. Exactly. We should probably say where we actually
met the first time. We can do. Probably in a bar somewhere. We did. I was working at
a company called Redis. Redis, if you're watching this on the stream, the email response is
at Linux.inlaw.in case. This is where we met. Martin decided to join that NoSQL database
company. This is basically where we met about three years, four years ago. You're forgetting
COVID on you. Something like that. We were doing technical sales at the company. Now
on with the history of the podcast. It is November 2019. Yes. A rainy cold Prague. What
even was the event? The event was actually said kick off. Ah, yes, of course. Of course.
Or business review. I can't remember. Who knows? You know, some corporate nonsense.
But, yes, out of that was some craft beer places visited. And where we discussed all
things open source between us. Indeed. Martin was choking on hot check wings. And so was
I. And after a few beers, basically, we both discovered that, yes, we were heavily into
open source. And we always had this intention of doing a podcast. And then we said, why
not do it together? And actually the first episode that was published in 2020, in February
of 2020, actually is aptly named, or the second episode is aptly named Fostem. Mostly I talk
about 2020 Fostem. You went there at the time. I did, yes. I gave a presentation in the Rust
Dev Room on
a format that we both like. As in, discuss topics like operating systems, Rust, programming
languages, stuff like that. And in between that, we do various interviews of people that
are notable in the open source community. The format is loosely modelled on something
called Floss Weekly. I don't know if that rings a bell. Twit TV is the publisher. But
they do weekly shows with just interviews. And the idea that we had at the time when
we originally devised the podcast to share the episodes between knowledge, transfer for
one, or for better expression. But also, livening up the whole format with actually interview
guests. It took us some time to come up with the exact format. It was also loosely based
on, as the name says, some of you may have recognised Linux Outlaws. That was a podcast
a while ago that had a similar kind of format, right? Almost. Who of you knows Linux Outlaws?
Ah, okay. About 15 years ago, Fab and then Lin Shet, Fab Shetter and Lin Shet, the idea
of actually doing a weekly format, talking just about current events. Something that
we started with, too. Yeah, we did that, didn't we, for a while. But with the delay between
publishing and talking about current events, it wasn't that relevant. Because the podcast
came out three months later. Exactly. Go ahead, man.
Yeah, this brings us to where we started as well. Our podcast was first on Hacker Puppy
Radio, which you may be familiar with as well. They have a booth.
They do? Well, Ken has a booth called Free in Culture Podcast. And this is what we use
originally to bootstrap ourselves. That was actually, I spoke to Ken at Fostem in 2020,
and he said we're more than happy to bootstrap you in terms of host you to get initially
off the ground. And that's exactly what we did before we changed this, but more on this
in a minute. Yeah, so for anybody thinking of doing a podcast,
it's very easy to get started. We have an episode on this as well. We do, yes, we do.
So yeah, personally, I like the interviews. I don't know about yourself, but we have some
quite very good guests in the past that we've had, which you may know as well, like the
likes of a recent one we had, Ran Levy from... Malicious Life.
Yes. So we had various people supporting open source, like the FSFE.
Which is actually in the audience. In the audience, indeed. And we had various
people on programming languages, operating systems.
We yes. For those of you who are becoming interested, we do have a back catalog. The
website is linnesilnows.eu. For example, we had a kernel maintainer panel. We did the
same with BSD, of course. Program language panel, yes.
Yeah, program language panel and all the rest of it. So the idea is basically to get people
on the podcast, and not just one, ideally, but more than one, and talk about projects,
political issues, that sort of thing. Political issues. Is there a particular episode
you're thinking of from the Georgia...? Yes. We have the Electronic Frontier Foundation
on the podcast, but also, of course, the Free Software Foundation Europe.
Yeah, it's well worth a listen, that one. As is the one by Paul Ramsey. Do you remember
that one? Vaguely, remind me. I mean, we've been doing almost 80 episodes by now.
Yeah. So Paul Ramsey is a post GIS maintainer. I don't know if you... Does any of you
familiar with Postgres? Well, no, post GIS. But he's also very much a speaker on things
open source. And he kind of raises a lot of points around open source is free and available,
but you get just a few people maintaining it. So there should be more funding for open
source contributors in a way, but specifically in government, right? Because government uses
a lot of open source software. But they're not actually contributing, and the code should be
free as well. Things like that. So we had a lot of discussions about this. True. Yes.
I think it's fair to say that we keep a... Or we try to keep a well balanced middle ground
between technical stuff and also political stuff. Yeah, that's a good point, actually.
That's probably fair to say. But it's about raising that profile as well, right, for
open source and the people that make that software. This is part of what we want to do.
Absolutely. And this is basically why we came up with the podcast in the first place.
Yep. All those years ago. Well, all three of them.
So having said that, we do bi-weekly episodes, right? So it's quite a busy schedule.
And yeah, we also made between a topic and an interview. Now, we should probably mention
something called the dark side, Martin. The dark side. Do tell. Yes.
Martin and myself, when we set out doing the podcast, we had this idea of providing a little
bit of color to the podcast. So you've been sort of a bit of a dark color.
Exactly. So who knows something called the bastard operator from hell, B-U-F-H?
Okay. Martin, this is nodding okay. Fair enough. No, the B-U-F was, I think, about a
formula about what, 20 years ago? Maybe less, maybe more. That's where actually a system
administrator talks about his trials and tribulations. Let's put it this way.
And so we took this original idea and the dark side is loosely modeled on the bastard operator
from hell, but turned this into a much more comedy oriented format. Let's put it this way.
Yeah, for sure. It's a bit of dark humor. Let's put it that way.
And yeah, these are also the only parts that are scripted in the podcast.
Yes. Good point. Good point. Everything is normally very ad hoc.
It's free flow. Normally, we do these dark sides bits and pieces as part of a Halloween special,
for example. Halloween, Christmas, Easter.
Any other religious holiday you may want to talk about? Do you want to talk about
Duchess Vladessa, maybe? Some teaser?
Well, okay. So we have this, you're particularly talking about the Halloween one, right?
Yes.
Those of you who have heard this one, we have a yearly Halloween episode where various, we have
a friend of ours who participates and does a very good, let's say, female vampire impression.
If that's possible on the podcast.
Yeah, actually she's from Macedonia, right?
And there, essentially, she's our voice model. She's our voice actress.
And mostly, these Halloween episodes, of course, have a Halloween topic.
So essentially, the episode that I was referring to, and again, we normally do these kind of
round Halloween, that sort of thing, refers to the tribulations that a certain Transylvanian
Duchess encounters when her workforce decides to unionize. It's that sort of black humor,
and I won't give away too much. You have to listen to the episode. It's that sort of black humor
that drives the dark side, in addition to kind of, and the people basically who...
Slightly more serious subjects in other episodes.
And apart from the humor that is woven into the interviews, into the other sessions.
Definitely, definitely. On that subject, clearly, we make this podcast, well, partly for ourselves
because we have a bit of fun making it, but it's clearly aimed at listeners.
So we have many ways for people to provide feedback.
Yes.
Carry on.
The email address is, of course, feedback. But since we should probably talk about the hosting aspect, too.
Yes.
We publish normally on archives.org, so if you have an archives.org account,
you can also leave a comment and leave feedback there.
We do not do Twitter for obvious reasons.
Yes.
No, we haven't done Twitter any time...
No, no.
...from the making of the podcast because never mind the population of recent.
We started on HBR for a long time, right? And only recently, kind of, on other podcast media,
you'll be able to find us on most of those.
Yes. Of course, when we were still on Hacker Public Radio, we... You could leave comments on Hacker Public Radio, too.
Yes.
And, I mean, these comments are very important to us, really, aren't they? It's something that, yeah, the more feedback we get, the more they...
Exactly. I mean, yeah, the podcast is done for you listeners, not for us.
And certainly not for our sponsors, because we don't have any...
No. What we also do is actually we also invite people from other podcasts on the podcast.
For example, the Linux Lads, if Shane or anybody else, or Conan is here, but I don't see them.
Also, but we should also probably talk about the Grumpial Coders, right?
Grumpial Coders, yes. Another set of podcasters that have a... Well, not a similar format, but they have...
Yeah, they're more on the technical side, by the way.
Yes.
And they publish less frequently. But it's, again, it's some friend of ours that we occasionally have some banter with.
Exactly.
Yeah.
Yes. What else is there to talk about Linux, about Linux in-laws?
Well, you should listen to it. That's the main thing.
Yes.
Yeah.
So, why should you listen to Linux in-laws, right?
That's your cue.
Why don't you ask the question? You put the word Spotty Martin. Well, why would you listen to the Linux in-laws?
Well, I...
If you wouldn't be making it.
Personally, yeah. It's mainly because we do intermix the detect stuff with a bit of fun, right? That's the main thing.
And personally, I like the interview pieces generally very much because you get so many people from different parts of the world, from different projects,
and they all have clearly an open source link, but they all have different stories to tell about open source and why it's good, and their part in it, really.
Very true, yes.
How about you?
Well, I've been doing open source for the last 30 plus years, so...
This is why you run an Apple Mac.
Teets.
But as we all know, underneath is a well-hidden BSD system, right? So, no worries.
Do we not have an upcoming episode on Tuxedo computers?
We do. But I don't think they're listening, so it's not worth mentioning that as a sponsor. No worries.
That's a little teaser there, yeah.
No worries.
But no, because we touch on our... subjects that move people in terms of open source is more and more used across industries, countries, planets.
Whoever has a mobile phone running Android, but also running iOS, is essentially running open source software. Android is powered by Linux, as probably most of you know,
and beneath the iOS is something called BSD, both widely used open source operating systems.
Yes.
And I reckon with doing Linux in-laws, we are providing a platform for projects to voice themselves, to make themselves heard.
These are not just Linux subjects, right? We also, as mentioned, touch other parts of open source, whether it's software and hardware, occasionally.
And politics.
Politics, yes.
Society topics and all the rest of it, yes.
Yeah. Not to mention, yeah, the showering situation in Germany is a common topic.
Yeah, I mean, we normally reckon... we normally open with a little bit of humor.
I normally slag off the United Kingdom and Martin returns these jokes with dire descriptions of the situation in Germany.
That's probably fair to say.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So, yes.
So, yeah, if you want to... no, in short, Linux in-laws, you want to learn a little bit, you want to listen to people that have things to say about open source.
And you like a bit of fun, just come and listen to us, really.
Absolutely, yeah.
That is the... well, what's our slogan, by the way?
You come for the knowledge but stay for the madness.
This is something that marketing came up with before you fired them, right?
Marketing? What is marketing?
The department that you can fire them up.
Is that the people that make the t-shirts?
No.
So, who makes the t-shirts?
The people with graphic design capabilities, I suppose.
Fair enough, fair enough.
No, we should talk about the logo, actually, no?
We can talk about the logo, yes, yes.
Oh, how many stickers have you brought, actually?
Yes, you can find stickers, actually, at the Free Culture Podcast booth.
I didn't have any footer listeners here.
I do, only about four or five.
You'll find the rest, actually, at the booth.
This is a prototype.
Yes.
Very rare, very rare.
Like the t-shirts.
The first batch, yes.
So, the logo, Martin, why did we need a new logo?
Well, mainly because the previous logo was based on some pictures of us 20 years ago.
True, true, true.
It's not that representative anymore.
But, yeah, certain podcasts, let's say, publishers also didn't like the format, so...
So, we had to change this.
And after about 20,000 focus group sessions, quite a few...
This is without Martin.
Debates, exactly.
Quite a few debates.
Debates, various sessions.
We came up with a new logo, which I hope you will find on most podcasting platforms also.
By the way, yeah, although Ken is not the audience, I think we should probably talk about metrics.
Okay, go ahead.
Metrics in terms of basically how many people listen to us.
Well, metrics, but actually we had done some metrics in the room today, so we could...
Yeah, about what?
150, maybe 180 people in the room.
We host our episodes, our MP3s, now on arkaf.org.
And the download stats for an average fun episode,
just on that platform alone, clocked in between 2,500 downloads per episode.
But if you type Linux in-laws into your search engine of choice,
you come up with a syndication left, right and center.
Or even your podcast app of choice, right?
Yes.
So, it's probably fair to say that on average we are listened to by more than 8,000 people per episode,
give or take a few.
Yes.
Unfortunately, they don't all feedback, do they?
It's just a shame.
Well, we could...
Shall we interview someone in the room?
Where is that listener?
Where did he go?
You want to...
Okay, he doesn't.
Okay, fair enough.
He's too shy for that.
It's a shame.
We should get him framed.
Good chance.
We're not listening.
No.
By the way, when did you start to listen to a Linux in-laws, if I may ask?
I'm not sure.
I have a couple of them back on, but my answer is no.
We all know yours.
That's how you can find your own source app.
And then I'll be honest with you.
Okay, did you get that?
Something about feedback.
Sorry, okay, let's talk later on this, sorry.
Okay, no, we were just curious because...
Yeah, we get feedback at times, but the more we get, the better, obviously.
Exactly, because essentially we do the podcast for you in terms of, okay, this is our show,
but we live on feedback because if you think, and that goes for anybody listening to us,
if there's a subject that is of interest for you, feel free to give feedback so we can
get that project on the show, talk to these politicians, whatever.
And we're not kind of fixed on one particular topic, right?
If you take the Rand Levy example with Minish's Life, they're very much focused on security.
Very true, yes.
We'll do an episode on security, but we won't do a whole podcast on that.
We'll do anything around open source.
Exactly, needless to say, an open source angle would help.
Yes, that would help.
But at the end of the day, the Electronic Fronto Foundation is more like about civil rights.
And when we did the episode with the Jordan chapter, I think one of the focus points of
that interview was actually gun laws.
Yes.
For example, so the point that I'm making here is, yes, open source is important for us,
but so are the politics and the civil rights aspects behind this whole notion, behind this
whole revolution.
Well, this is the part about free, isn't it, really, that we have in free and open source
software that we also have talked about.
Absolutely.
And that's exactly the reason why we try to maintain the balance between technical and
non-technical subjects.
Ah, yes.
And also, if you do have trouble sleeping, there is an episode on licenses, if I'm not
mistaken.
Yes, on open source licensing.
So, yes.
But we didn't have guests on this, so.
So, yes, it has many uses there.
We should probably talk about the road ahead, right?
Oh.
I mean, we've been doing this for the last three years now.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Where do you want to take this, Martin?
Apart from the usual world domination, making lots of money, how is it yet to be determined?
No, the objective is already kind of met, right, we're spreading the word and supporting
the projects and the people that make open source, so we continue doing that, in my opinion.
True, true, true.
But maybe there's something more.
Is there?
Probably.
Do tell.
Well, some people have suggested, when we still have the focus groups, that more humor
might be in order, for example, as in more dark side stuff.
Okay, well, we'll have to get some feedback on that, won't we?
Indeed.
Okay.
Yes?
What happened?
And it doesn't say if our listeners have more ideas, the more the merrier.
Indeed.
Well, we have a, I mean, the whole year is planned out pretty much, but there's always
room for...
Of course, yes.
...
after this talk goes without saying.
Yes, this is exactly the point, right?
If you have things that you want to be vocal about
or talk about, open source related,
whether it's a project or your community efforts,
come talk to us and we'll put you on the podcast.
And with that, it's probably time for our interview guests.
Oh, interview guests, yes.
We do have an interview guest.
Right, welcome, welcome, interview guests.
Matthias, why don't you join us on the stage?
It's a little bit ahead of time,
but more than Maria anyway.
You get a bit of a feel for how we do the episode.
For those of you who do not know Matthias Kirchner,
why don't you introduce yourself?
Yes, my name is Matthias Kirchner.
I'm the president of the Free Software Foundation Europe.
That's my day job.
And yeah, beside that, I did some volunteer activities,
which is probably the topic of this interview.
Absolutely, so hands up,
who does not know what the Free Software Foundation Europe
does and is?
So everybody knows the FSFE.
You can skip that question.
Fair enough, that was just getting that, okay.
Of course, needless to say, there's also an episode
from something called Linus in Laws on the FSFE.
But yes, why don't you tell us a little bit about
how you came into the open source world.
Put you on the spot right now.
Oh, I first, the start was that I asked my father
to subscribe to more newspapers,
so I can inform myself from more sources
to see who is trying to accomplish world domination.
And my father said, oh, that's too expensive,
but I read something about this internet
and I will make sure that you get this,
which was at that time probably more expensive
in the long run with the modem there.
But yeah, I started with that
and then I had a second computer at home
and I tried to connect them
and I wanted to send emails to them
without connecting to the internet and it didn't work.
Also, both of those computers had an email program on them.
I complained at school.
Someone said, I have something for you,
brought some floppies, brought some CDs,
and then I installed my first GNU Linux distribution.
And a few months later, I had a mail server.
And from there on, then I read more about technology.
I organized the meetups to install parties
for in the local groups, went to events,
and then I read more and more about
that it's also about political, social beliefs,
and that's how I get interested in FSFE.
Yeah, so I understand the technical background,
but there's clearly more to it for yourself, right,
than just the tech side with open source.
I mean, at that time, I wasn't able to formulate it this way,
but in the end, for me,
Free Software is a way to distribute power in our society.
I think democracies depend on distributing power
and we also need a distribution of technological power
and Free Software is an important tool for that
to make sure that there is not one entity
has too much power in our society.
And I think that's the main part
which is driving me for the work there.
Very good, very good.
Did you want to take the next one?
And why did you decide to join eventually
the Free Software Foundation Europe?
So at that time, then, I mean, there was in this point,
I had this political interest,
I had this technical interest,
I thought there are so many people on the internet
when you have questions about technical issues,
you can ask and there are so many bright people
who will help you to figure it out,
but about the political stuff,
I was not able to figure that out myself,
so I studied politics and management then
and we had to do a seven months internship
and I asked some people, some DBN developers I knew,
where could I do that?
And one of the suggestions was the FSFE
and then I read about them and applied there
and after longer back and forth,
because they didn't have interns before
and didn't have an office at that time
and didn't have money to pay,
in the end, I ended up there in the one room apartment
of the president at that time on the sofa, he had a desk,
and from there, I then worked and attended
free software events, including my first Fostom
then in 2005.
Very nice, very nice.
So there's clearly, yeah, what's next after that?
Is there some other world domination plan for yourself?
I think that the one that is running is just the topic,
I don't know what you want to say already
about your next episode.
Tease it away.
I mean, tease it away.
Now is probably a good time to feature
an upcoming presentation today or reading rather.
Yeah, so I will do a reading of this new book,
which I wrote, it's called Ada and Sangaman,
A Tale of Software, Skateboards and Raspberry Ice Cream.
It's about encouraging people to tinker with computers,
it's about software freedom in a way that is hopefully
encouraging them to think on their own
how they want to use technology.
It will be at six o'clock now, I have to check the room
again in UB2147.
And there I will do a reading of the book in 30 minutes
and afterwards answer some questions about how to write
a book with under a free license, get that published
by O'Reilly for the German version and no starch press
for the English version plus other language versions.
Clearly you have an objective with the book,
it's not just, oh, let's write a book for a bit of fun,
but there is more to it than that if I'm not mistaken.
I mean, at the beginning, my main idea was how can I explain
this topic to my own children?
And I asked if others have some ideas about that
and if there are some existing books and they were either
for older children or they were about a bit complicated.
And then I started to tell some bad time stories myself,
always a bit improvised and then depending on the feedback,
I was then just changing the stories at that time
and then in the end, this came out of it.
Is this your personal kind of initiative
or is this something that the FSF is trying to promote
in terms of making awareness amongst younger people?
At the beginning, it was a personal project of mine
and I was also writing this on my own time.
Then at one point, I talked to someone and told him
about this plan and he said, well, if you will write a book
about free software, then I will buy 1000 copies
and give that to customers.
And then I talked with the FSFE and then I got the
confirmation that I can spend a few hundred euros
to get an editor on board so that I can get someone
with experience how to actually write a children's book.
And yeah, when we had this, then we could also hire
an illustrator to do the illustrations for the book,
and get an illustrator to understand Creative Commons
licensing, which is very unusual for this area.
And then we were also quite lucky to get two publishers
on board who also understand free licensing
and agreed to publish this as commercial publishers
under CC by share like.
Excellent, excellent.
So where can people find the book?
So the German one, it's-
Oh, and you brought some with you today.
So this is the commercial part or-
At the German version, you can already buy that everywhere.
The US version, the English version, you can at the moment
just get that from the US publisher because the worldwide
distribution just starts in May.
So the FSFE, we got some of the books and brought them
through customs, which was a pain.
And we have them at the booth.
And so we have a few amount of those here.
And yeah, else from now on already, you can order that
at every bookstore and pre-order will be shipped in May.
And tonight you're doing the first, let's say,
reading of the English version, right?
Yeah, that was one of my wishes that Fosten will be the place
where I do the first reading of the English book.
And yeah, I will do that there.
And for everyone else who would like to do that,
I mean, you can first try it out.
And one of my recommendations is it's a really great tool
to talk to children about our topics.
I did several readings with the German version at schools
with 30 people, 40 children, or even once in a cinema
with 150 children, talking with them about that,
answering their questions they have, or having some
discussions about what they want to invent, how computers work,
and so on.
And so we have all the slides and the text
and where to change slides and all kind of other information,
how you can do that on our Git repository.
It's all freely licensed.
You can make changes to it.
Let's see what's coming out.
You can make pre-ess equals.
Yeah, I think that's something we will also
discuss in the show, probably a tool for world domination.
And for those of you who cannot make it at 6 PM,
there will be a reading on something
called Linux in Laws in an upcoming episode,
more than likely in April.
So if you missed this reading tonight,
feel free to tune in or download that particular episode.
Anything else we should discuss with the president
while we have him on the stage, Martin?
I think we should have some minutes left.
Something else.
No, I think we have some minutes left.
So I think the subject has been beaten to death.
But anyway, I would like still to have your opinion on this.
Richardson Salomon, just to say this is on this,
just to wake up the audience once again.
I mean, it's history, fair enough.
But it's been a while.
But I think he has made a rebound in terms
of he's back on the board now, right, of the Free Software
Fund.
I know that the FSFE issues a statement
after the whole debacle.
But I reckon he's back on track now, at least in the US.
No?
I mean, any views on this that you would like to share?
Oh, that's very complicated.
OK.
And we still have, I think, 10 minutes left.
The abridged version.
Yeah.
Now I was cornered here on this topic.
Now I think that's a really complicated discussion.
And it's also a discussion which, at the moment,
I also prefer to have some personal conversations
with other people involved in this before this is going
public.
So I'm sorry, but this is a bit too difficult to discuss.
Very diplomatic answer.
Back to much more safer grounds.
Where do you see the Free Software Foundation Europe
going?
I mean, what I see is that the topics are going more
and more mainstream.
And so one of the big challenges there
is how can we make sure that this topic doesn't stay
at Fostem and at some Free Software conferences,
but that we are going to other conferences
and connect with other topics which are ongoing
and which are very much influenced by our topics
that we are usually discussing here.
So when we talk about there are discussions
in the sustainability area, which
there's a huge dependency on can you really make changes
to hardware or software.
And how is technology developed there?
There are questions about who should have control
over the computers.
I mean, we have net neutrality.
On the other hand, it's very important
that we also have device neutrality
so that every one of us has the right
to install or remove software on our devices
that we can change web browsers, that we can change app stores,
that we can change the services which
are connected to our devices.
And that's something which is, I mean,
at the time when the movement started, it was small.
And we had some desktop machines and some laptops.
And now we have the computers everywhere.
And now, I mean, there are so many people who
have questions about this topic.
So it's more and more important to translate this
to a more general audience, people
who don't have such knowledge about technology.
And that's something which the FSFE always was doing this.
But that's something where we have more and more demand
about that.
And it's now not anymore that you
want to talk with people about free software.
And most of them say, oh, I'm not interested.
It's now more the problem that there
are so many people who have questions about that.
And we just have a limited amount of resources.
So the important thing is, how can we enable more people,
more volunteers, to also work on these topics?
That's also why with this book, I mean,
I'm invited to do a lot of readings at schools.
But I will not be able to fulfill this, the demand there.
So we need to enable others to also do that and do this.
And that's also for all the other topics,
with device neutrality, with sustainability, with public money,
public code, one of the campaigns we are running,
where there are so many governments which
are interested and public administrations that
are interested.
Yes, I'm totally convinced, but how do I do that?
And so that's one of the big challenges there.
How do we enable that?
And I mean, during the last three years,
it was very difficult to motivate volunteers
to get in contact with new volunteers.
That's why something like Fostom now is very important there.
I mean, fully story, the public money and public code
was the first campaign where I came across the FSFE
all those years back.
At the moment, you're running a sustainability campaign
in the era of mobile devices, if I recall correctly.
That was, yeah, Upcycling Android,
where we help people to install other ROMs, other operating
systems on their mobile devices, and also explain people
that it's important that you can install or remove software
from devices and repair devices.
So that's one other area.
OK.
And would you go as far as associating these campaigns
with the right to repair that you almost
touched upon a minute ago?
Yeah, I mean, the right to repair
is definitely one part of this whole device neutrality area.
Any future campaigns that you want to tease now?
I mean, there are several things that will come up.
But one thing that, for me, is very important
at this time of the year.
So it's February.
And on the 14th of February, we are always
running the ILAF Free Software Day.
The idea at that time was I thought
that the flower industry is benefiting so much
from this day.
Why can't we have something where the free software
community is benefiting from this?
Indeed.
Free software is kind of what we need.
Yeah.
And I think in our community, we give each other
very open feedback, very direct feedback.
But sometimes we forget to say thank you
to all those amazing people here at the conference who
help others with their knowledge, who share their software
with others.
And so at the 14th of February, we always
encourage everyone out there to thank other free software
contributors out there.
Buy them a beverage.
Send them a letter or a postcard.
Or I mean, just in general, say thank you to them.
Because it's something which, in the end, I mean,
all of those people, they are doing such a great job,
such an important contribution to our society, which
we often forget about.
And so do this on the 14th of February.
Add it to your calendar.
And the next day, you can continue
to write feature requests, bug reports,
complain why this programming language is used,
and not the other, and why this approach is bad
and yours is better.
But yeah, don't forget to say thank you once a year,
at least.
Also, there are, at least in Germany,
there are a couple of events taking place.
For example, one of the Frankfurt user groups,
I think it's even the CCC, as in the GAS Computer Club,
has an event at the headquarters celebrating this free software
day.
So if you want to take part in this, check out.
Is it on the website?
So yeah, on the website, fsfv.org, in the news section,
you find an entry there about I Love Free Software Day.
And several local groups are also organizing events
where we are inviting free software contributors.
Make sure that there are some pizza, some cake,
and there are people who can thank the others.
We have, in Berlin also, at the C-BASE hacker space,
we have a DJ there.
We have an event in Crease.
We have an event in Frankfurt.
And there are others there.
And if you want to organize that on your,
something like that on your own, let us know.
So we can also list your I Love Free Software Day event.
It's an event where we hope that many of you here,
many of the people visiting Fosten,
will receive a thank you for your work.
And well, if you want to organize something there,
let us know.
We can also help you a bit when you register there
that we could cover the pizza for this event or so.
Then just write us an email and we
will see that we can also financially
support when you want to organize that.
Because we think that if every euro that
is invested in such a nice event and some nice cake there,
that this would benefit free software in the long run
a lot because it's so motivating to receive
some appreciation for your work.
Sounds like a bit like the dark side.
We have cookies, don't we?
Cake in this case.
So people, this has been almost a live session of something
called Linux In-laws.
This is the format that we normally do every month
as in bringing guests on stage, putting him or her
right on the spot, and then having a little bit of fun.
If you like this, the feed address is on the screen.
I think we have time for one more question
from the audience.
Is there any question that you would
like to get answered right now, preferably
from a free and open source software background?
If there isn't, thank you very much for listening,
I'm tempted to say.
There will be a session tonight.
As in, you can ask us anything.
You also find the address on the website.
It's just a little bit of fun.
And at that pub, we're going to start at about 8.30.
The place isn't too big, so just make sure
that you are there on time in order to avoid disappointment
if you can't get in.
So 8.30 at that address.
You also find this on Linux In-laws.
You just click on the Forstam tab.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.