I'm going to talk today about when I wrote the talk, I said open source collaboration,
but I think open collaboration more in general is maybe more appropriate.
I think we have as developers, it doesn't allow me to touch code anymore, but you have
an amazing potential to make the world a better place.
Today I'd like to talk about first of all, why open source is eating the world.
I want to start with a bit of my personal journey that hopefully makes you understand
sort of the background that I'm coming from.
I started about 15 years ago in open source and I had a lot more hair and I guess at the
cost of aging myself, how many people know something called Apache Cocoon?
Exactly.
I figured.
I started in open source really because it was fun, because it was, I gotta say, also
a way for me to accelerate my career.
The opportunity to collaborate on the left side, you got my best friend who still is
my best friend.
I made some of my best friendships in open source, but the day that I got my Apache email
address, I still remember it.
I was so proud about being in the, in between so many smart guys, effectively much smarter
than me because I've been pretty much mainly a release manager at that time.
I never really wrote super hard code.
That's where I started, really as a personal motivator.
Then I moved into, I had the luck to move to Holland.
Let's say in Italy, didn't really have such a lively technology ecosystem in 2006.
Then I had the luck of starting to get paid to do my open source work, whether it was
community open source, building SDKs, whether it is actually as part of my day job, being
able to be first a developer, then a product manager for the developer platform.
Not sure what I'm doing up there, but I guess clearly I was having a lot of fun in Munich
or thereabouts.
Then I moved to the US.
I never really grew up with the American dream.
I just say that, but both for work and for personal reasons, I moved to the United States
and I entered this magic world of foundations.
A foundation in a pretty conservative and regulated industry.
This was 2015 when I got called to run, what at the time was called the Symphony Software
Foundation and now it's Finos, the FinTech open source foundation.
I tried to take the Apache way, my open source upbringing and throw it at banks.
It didn't really stick.
I started saying, hey, if it doesn't happen on the list, it doesn't happen.
You guys should collaborate openly.
It didn't work.
I really had to switch gears and start talking to them about what was the value for them
to collaborate in the open.
Not undermining the principles and the transparency and the governance of open source, but I found
much more success in bringing all different constituents together, whether it is financial
institutions, whether it is technology vendors, whether it is individual contributors, of
course, that make still the largest part of our community.
I think very interesting regulators.
I think a theme that you're going to hear quite recurring during the presentation.
There is something there in having active public sector collaboration in industries,
in open source projects.
There's still a long way to go.
I wouldn't say that banks are first class citizens of the open source community, but
we were able to make some of the largest firms in the US and in Europe, and in the UK, I
guess, extended Europe, collaborate.
That's I think the beginning of something quite interesting because they have some pretty
powerful technology that they're now making available and trying to be good citizens to
maintain, not just dump and run.
And then it got personal.
Probably seen on my desktop the picture of my kid.
Leonardo, his special needs kid, pretty heavily fragile as a kid.
When I started seeing the... Yeah, he was born like a lion.
No, this disability.
I started seeing how open source, again, really this is close to my heart.
There are plenty of efforts out there that are trying to use either open data or open
source truly open collaboration approach to solve things that, for which there's no
commercial liability.
Big pharma is much more encouraged to work on cancer, vaccines, things that have a massive
applicability and therefore massive commercial potential rather than solving very rare genetic
diseases where you have 10 people in the world having that specific gene that is a mutation.
And so open treatment is under the Linux condition, open single nucleotide polymorphism.
I'm not really a biologist or doctor, but you see the power of bringing together data
from all around the world to make something out of where there's no really commercial
drive.
There's no drive for innovation.
And so all of this to say that I find open source itself to be the positive sum game
for which whether you are corporate, whether you are a government, whether you are an individual,
we can find ways to engage these people.
And I know that there's a lot of polarization today and I hope, nowadays, whether it is
individual versus big tech, whether it's Europe versus the US or China, but I do think without
being naive that open source actually can be a way for everyone to collaborate and deliver
not just technology innovation but social value.
So I want to, before we go into sort of what are the challenges, I think it's important
to talk and sort of understand how some of the most successful projects, at least in
my experience, came about.
I mean, I'm sure you're all pretty familiar with a guy called Linus Torbald, so I'm not
going to go into Linux as a pretty obvious example of a project that was individually
started or individually led at the beginning.
But more recently, again, more in the world of finance, one example that has been pretty
interesting to me of a project that started by an individual out of really coding, maybe
not certainly a garage, but during the pandemic in lockdown, it's a software called OpenBB.
It used to be called Gainstunk terminal.
If you're familiar with the GameStop frenzy two years ago where the community started
betting against Wall Street and created a pretty interesting basically growth of a stock
that really didn't GameStop, didn't really have a lot more value, but it was an example
of a movement that was really trying to democratize access to a very elitist and very wealthy
part of the industry.
And so one guy overnight built sort of a replacement Bloomberg terminal.
For those of you who are not familiar with Bloomberg terminals, what people use in Wall
Street is a very closed, very heavily proprietary terminal, literally a thing, a box that are
used by traders to research and trade.
And so someone went out there and built an actual terminal.
Turns out that normally when you pair open source with a cause, you really get a potential
amazing exponential growth, but of course timing has to be right.
This was done when at the very moment that the whole world of retail investors was betting
against Wall Street.
And of course it's not just about the code.
It was lucky DDA, which I happen to be a friend of, was able to put it on Acorn News.
It went viral on Acorn News, went number one.
And so it was off the races.
It started getting contributions, it's now gotten funding, and it rebranded from, again,
gainstump terminal to OpenBB.
So there's a lot of power when you are able to pair open source with an actual social
cause or an individual cause.
Now we're very familiar, I think, with corporate led open source projects.
We're getting more and more common.
There are two examples here.
As I said, I never really grew up with the American dream, but it has to be said that
some contributions from big tech like Kubernetes or PyTorch have certainly created opportunities
out there.
And of course this is not because of charity, let's be clear.
While us coming from the open source community have an aspect of conscience, these large
corporations largely do open source because they see a potential down the line, whether
it is commoditizing a competitor.
If you've never seen the Kubernetes documentary, they actually have a documentary.
Which one day I'll be so cool that I have a documentary about my project.
But Google said it out loud.
Incrementalism step by step wasn't going to get them to catch up with Amazon on the
cloud front.
And so the open source Kubernetes.
We now have about 21 trillion investment globally, about 1 trillion in Europe.
And Kubernetes is one of the most sought after skills out there.
And again, this doesn't mean that the motives originally were about the spirit of open source,
but certainly it has created opportunity.
Same for PyTorch.
Some of the main advancements out there, we can talk about TensorFlow, but really AI
has certainly benefited from the open sourcing and more recently the introduction of open
governance around some of these projects.
But of course, as I said, open governance, you must play by the rules.
And I know that we all have slightly different ideas what the rules should be, but certainly
a good starting point is to use an OSI approved license.
And ideally, be in any foundation where you can bring all the different parties together
and be a neutral environment.
And then we have plenty of examples of non-profit led open source, whether it is projects from
the Linux Foundation or more from a 501c3-type charity like, for example, Mojalup, the works
around financial inclusion.
We have seen, especially in the last few years, how open source not always super successfully.
Because, for example, I left Public Health was created in response to the COVID-19 pandemic
to have open source COVID tracking apps.
And it's been used in some governments.
But as a US resident, I still have my paper vaccine card like when I was in the 80s.
So it hasn't really been as ubiquitous as we wanted to be.
But certainly the attempt was correct, that we are all in a major global crisis and open
source can help.
A great example is OpenSSF.
Actually, while I tend to forget that OpenSSF was created two months before log for shell,
not after.
Although the Linux Foundation was pretty well positioned to help and corral a response,
at least from the US government.
We had several meetings at the White House, acting really as a sort of convening power
also for the large technology companies.
And I hope we can work together on a global standard here because we're all at risk based
on open source sustainability, really.
And then finally, as I said, non-profit, when you talk about financial inclusion or other
causes, you can attract also private funding, charity funding, the Mojo Lopez largely funded
also by the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation.
And so what is preventing us to make an even bigger impact?
I think there's a few reasons.
One I just hinted to, it's open source sustainability.
I think most of you have probably seen that comic about how often and in some cases how
little we know about how the modern infrastructure sometimes is relying on, again, the amazing
work of some random guy in the brass kit says that.
I know many of you can relate to sometimes how unthankful the internet can be or the
technology community can be when you are doing amazing work and maintaining a library that
then turns out large corporations, governments, and technology companies rely on every day.
And so why else, of course, log for shell, solar winds, and all the attacks that we've
seen in the last few years have raised the profile and created organizations like Open
SSS to really start addressing not only security but sustainability.
This remains a big problem.
Also because of lack or uneven funding across the world.
As I said, I had the luck finally in my career to start being paid to do open source.
And it's a beautiful thing.
I never had to really struggle to do what I love so much doing.
And a little caveat here.
I don't come from a rich family, but they were able to make me study.
And I think in Europe it's to an extent easier to have some of those basic rights.
But I never, never forget that it's a privilege to be able to work in open source.
I used to start growing up, I used to say, look, I wouldn't be here if I hadn't started
contributing to open source with that picture with long hair.
But it's because I had time to do it.
There are simply people and large slices of society that don't have time or don't have
the opportunity to be able to start contributing because they have to do three jobs to get
to the end of the month.
And so open source sustainability is a major issue.
And I think we need to continue addressing it.
And of course, a little touch on open washing.
It is very much still a thing, especially in less mature industries.
It's very easy and very cool to jump on the open bandwagon without truly understanding
or actually either maliciously, meaning trying to exploit the marketing value of open source,
or inadvertently not understanding that, yeah, you have to contribute back if you want to
ensure a live ecosystem.
And if you can do software as a corporate world, you can fund open source.
You can pay your developers to work in the open.
But I do think that the main issue is fragmentation, actually.
This is a report that Linux Foundation Research led together with other foundations like Eclipse,
Live Networking and Linux Foundation Europe.
It's about really trying to understand what are the main challenges that prevent us from
even further getting together and addressing some of the most pressing issues out there.
This is one that is near and dear to my heart, especially as we're here in Brussels.
And we recently started the Linux Foundation Europe in the understanding that there's a
lot of potential to help Europe, European technology, European values, start in Europe
but really go global through the Linux Foundation platform.
And of course, it is all over the world.
There's clearly a desire and a set of statements to use open source for advancing digital sovereignty,
creating the digital commons.
But it seems very much to me that there hasn't yet been a true set of actions that are very
concrete in driving towards that vision.
It's very much promoted in principle, but sometimes even well-intentioned regulations.
I think if you were here yesterday, there's been a lot of conversations around the Cyber
Resiliency Act and what the potential unintended consequences on open source can be and the
burden they might create on maintainers, on foundations, while again, in principle, the
goal was to try to address sustainability and try to address security and put some of
the burden on the commercial companies.
To me, it's fairly correct.
And so you always end up with great statements, but not so much of a aligned action.
And you have to say, OSPOs, the European Commission is an OSPO now, two days ago the Dutch government
announced the creation of an OSPO.
They are sort of really starting to spring out there and I think it's a construct that
is going to help.
But I think, again, for what I've learned from finance, you need a bottoms up and a
top down approach here.
So where do we go from here?
If we want to make an ever bigger impact.
Actually, I'm missing a slide.
Sorry guys.
Oh well.
I guess I lost it.
I think there is a couple of things that we need to look forward to.
From understanding that open source is not the battlefield.
We can compete on the commercial side of the house.
We can compete on what is truly differentiating.
But it's not the open source community where this battle should happen.
Digital sovereignty doesn't mean building borders around open source.
And indeed, that is also what's coming out the fragmentation report.
Transparent open source developments are the best antidote for techno-nationalism.
This is something that, again, despite we know there are tensions all over.
Open source should be a bridge.
It shouldn't be another way to divide us.
And there are plenty of areas where we can collaborate.
Whether it is open source infrastructure.
Whether it is open source security.
Whether it is intellectual property that remains a pretty regional sort of concern.
Whether it is even broader goals.
And that's where I'm going to go in the next slide.
And I want to say we are asked as foundations to work better together.
There are plenty of educational initiatives out there that we have helped the government.
We have the TUDA group at the Linux Foundation.
But there's OSPO++ who works a lot with the public sector.
There is the OSPO Zone and OSPO Alliance from the Eclipse Foundation.
If there's one objective that I have in my new tenure here in Linux Foundation Europe
is really to bring not only governments but really start from foundation.
This is something that we are being asked very much loudly by the ecosystem.
And I realize this is in the U.S. up there.
But we do have travel funding.
But we are starting to also organize conferences and moments where we're focused on really
educating the government into how they can help.
Not just in words, not just in sort of grants that stop at research level, but really in
active participation in open source projects.
And as I said, part of the issue here is fragmentation.
I know for a fact even within the Linux Foundation we create five or six projects every day, sorry
every day, every quarter.
There are thousands of projects created in GitHub every month.
If not probably thousands.
There's an underestimation.
And so it behooves us and that's again what comes out from the fragmentation report to
really do more to align projects.
And I think I want to applaud if you guys were here yesterday morning the open source
initiative announced their partnership with the Digital Public Goods Alliance, which is
very much aligned to the U.N. sustainable goals.
And at the Linux Foundation we're also trying to align our initiatives, our projects.
Again we have, I don't know what's the current count of projects, over a thousand projects
in the Linux Foundation.
And I have no idea how many can address climate, can address water prices, can address energy.
What I know is that Europe has, many of these projects are based in Europe.
OAS Climate has a large presence in Europe.
Agstack for agriculture and agtech and of course, elephant energy.
Those of you who know elephant energy know that the leader recently passed away, Shirley
Goodman.
She was a great activist and very much seen Europe as a springboard for global climate
action.
And so you can certainly expect from us a much stronger alignment towards sustainability.
In fact, again unfortunately the CFP closes today, so if you're quick you can probably
still sneak it in.
But we are adding another track to our open source summit, which is sustainability.
Again in the spirit of trying to at least have our house in Hordur and then hopefully
are collaborating more broadly on the 17 silver high value goals.
And then I think another way to go beyond standard, beyond this fragmentation is really,
and I'm sure again this is not a new comic strip.
I've taken part in standards, I've taken part in open source projects over time and hopefully
I don't offend anyone here, but I think open source is better.
I mean it's just more apt to incremental progress.
You can always fork later if you don't agree, but ultimately it allows to build on an existing
concrete piece of code rather than coming up with yet another top down 15th standard
whereby 14 do exist.
I think this is something that also impacts how we collaborate as individuals.
One hand, look, one of the things that came out of the fragmentation report is that fragmentation
is a double S word.
Sure we want consolidation, but on the other hand there is value in the distributed mode
of open source development whereby we want to allow multiple options to solve the same
problem, and then open source Darwinism is going to run its course.
I do also think that it beholds us as developers, I guess, I don't know if I can call myself
a developer anymore, to try harder, to try harder not to reinvent the wheel.
Again I keep aging myself, but I used to be the maiden guy before going into the foundation
world and I got so much crap from the ant guys.
Dude, what are you doing, this is not what you should be, it's very polarizing.
I'm like yeah sure, we know it's not perfect, but how about we try to consolidate and improve
rather than creating yet another framework or yet another library.
Again, sometimes there's perfectly valuable reasons to do so.
How do we bring it all together?
This is a very similar slide to the one that we've seen before on finance and the lesson
that I've learned is that it's important to start with why.
By why I mean not only the conscience aspect of open source, but we all I think if we're
here are familiar with, are driven by, but if we want I think to truly make an even bigger
impact and a more focused impact on whether it is those major social goals and sustainability
development goals, whether it is starting to change an industry, finance, healthcare
is one that of course is near and dear to my heart and due to many reasons it's still
very close, sometimes they hide behind the regulated nature to enact change, but the
reality is that as we've seen for banks this is actually possible.
Whether it is to make the government understand what they should be practically doing in an
open source project to advance a certain policy, there's so much at least in the EU talk about
open source and how open source can advance European small and medium businesses and innovation
and that really does need to be translated into action.
So I think independent organizations like foundations, or just the Linux Foundation,
any foundation out there and hopefully better collaborating with each other, is a way to
bring all these different actors together.
Still with the principles of open source, but I think if we lead with that we're going
to lose some people on the way, we're going to lose the people that really are there for
the money or for a cause or unfortunately not everyone has this natural driver to collaborate
and so you always need to try and sell it, I know it's a dirty word to an extent, but
sell the reasons and the value why people would want to participate in open source and
to me bringing everyone together under common governance is really the way forward.
And so, about to wrap, what can we do, can you do practically to help?
I think from our side there is much more work in being organized and collaborate and aligned
to common goals on the foundation's side.
But I think if anyone here is from the public sector and the EU or listening online, open
source can be the vehicle to drive policy goals.
I mean there's so much that we can bridge if we start with open governance and I think
we're not going to be there probably this year or even next year, but I see a moment
in which like I've seen with banks we can involve or why not?
The government should be able to start open source projects that contextually drive these
big policy goals whether it is DNA, DSA, the cyber resiliency act, the interoperability
act, there's so much out there that Europe in fact is leading.
I think about GDPR, I live in California and thanks to GDPR we have CCPA which is the most
similar sort of data privacy protection in another wise pretty wild landscape and at
the level of consumer protection that's really, you know, it's in the standard setting from
the EU and on the other hand it makes very complex for companies to implement it and
so open source can really deliver as a positive sum game an easier way to implement for the
regulated industries and a more effective way for the government to enact those policies.
Of course I will continue reiterating that digital sovereignty doesn't mean building
borders.
We don't want to fragment the open source community.
We're going to as Europeans not only lose existing technology is out there but potentially
lose sort of the innovation and the growth potential for the local small and medium businesses
and hopefully growing businesses.
I would like to see larger technology companies in Europe being born out of open source.
The companies invest in open source talent.
Again I have a lot of grievances in the United States but they do invest in talent and that
does allow maintainers to work in open source without having to struggle and that also has
a diversity angle here.
Just folks that cannot in many parts of the world don't have the time to just invest in
open source, to just do it in their own time.
And becoming open source leader I do think that like we've seen for the examples of Google
I was actually talking to a company here yesterday, a local company said we wouldn't even be in
the market if it was not for open source.
That's what got us on the global stage.
And I think if anyone here has the decision making power, if you're trying to sell your
CEO into doing open source, lead with why, lead with how they can commoditize a competitor,
they can become a de facto standard.
And then if you're not able as a company to contribute time or code, well contribute money
to open source through maintainer funding, you know, we have Patreon, GitHub sponsors,
the index foundation as a mentorship platform, there's so many ways to fund open source.
It doesn't have to be foundations, it doesn't have to be directly employing someone.
And then last but not least as an individual, I think you have an amazing potential to be
an activist through technology.
And being an activist I think some of the most successful activists out there are not
just about the quality of the code.
You got to market what you're doing and we're here to help.
I can't promise they will be able to market or promote every single open source project
out there.
Been working on this deck until 3 a.m. yesterday and got here 10 minutes late this morning.
But we're there to give visibility to a lot of these projects.
And culture remains still a major fragmentation problem in the industry.
The slide that unfortunately I wasn't able to present showed how there's still a lot
of prejudice.
And so whether it's national, whether it's racial, whether it's political, check it
out the door because it's just not going to, you know, that diverse perspective make better
projects.
And then as a guy with a big ego, this is more of a lesson for myself, put your ego
aside.
If there is, you know, I know as an engineer at heart I have very strong opinions of how
code should be written or how, you know, certain libraries should be done.
There's plenty of reasons why you want to start a new framework.
But there's the whole, there's a world of open source out there.
And we as foundations can do a much better job at showing what projects are healthy,
what projects are aligned with certain goals.
We have a lot to do there.
But if we want to really make that bigger impact, we will need commitment from you guys
to sort of put your ego on the side.
And with that, thank you so much.
I appreciate you being here so early and coping with me being a little late.
Thank you.
I know if there are questions.