So, it's been a while since I've been in FOSDAM and one of the things that I, well I usually
talk about technical topics but this is really me talking about sort of using open source
instead of producing it which is quite an unusual position for me to be in.
I work most often in things like the Linux kernel, I also work in open source politics
so I did a lot of kernel interaction with the Linux Foundation and one of those pieces
of interaction was actually being a founding member of Linux Plumbers Conference which
is the conference we'll actually be talking about for this presentation.
Plumbers was basically founded in 2008 as an in-person conference and it's always been
an in-person conference up to the pandemic years.
It's actually organized somewhat similarly to FOSDAM in that it has tracks and what are
called micro conferences.
The micro conferences are similar to dev rooms except they're really a bit more interactive
so they're really expected to do participant conversations and usually you get a cluster
of people at the front talking to each other.
The tracks themselves when we have them mostly tend to be presentations so very like this
but the micro conferences tend to be very discussion based so if you think about trying
to do that sort of hybrid and online you realize you need some sort of highly interactive video
system which is what we went through.
One of the good things we had for Plumbers is that the conference actually produces quite
a lot of money.
We have quite a lot of sponsorship so it's quite easy to pay people to do things in the
conference and one of the things we paid for in 2018 was to actually make the conference
live streaming for all of those who couldn't attend and also to try and put all of the
videos of every presentation and every discussion we had up on the website and obviously to
do that we needed to pay somebody to run AV in each of our rooms and Plumbers tends to
run us about somewhere between four and eight simultaneous tracks so we needed about 16
cameras to do this and about between four and eight people to stay in the room to also
do it.
And obviously this then included provision of cameras in the rooms and the way we set
up cameras at Plumbers is slightly different from what you have here because in your setup
the camera is mostly looking down at me because you think I should be the focus of attention
which is true because I'm giving the talk but when you're actually trying to record
an ongoing live discussion that mostly happens between people in the audience you also need
the people who are live streaming to be able to see it.
So one of the other fortuitous things is Plumbers is always set up with two cameras, one at
the back looking down on the speaker and then one at the front looking out at the audience
and the AV guys are actually responsible for switching between the front view and the back
view so that when we start to get conversations within the audience the camera can actually
catch them and you can watch it.
And this actually turned out to be really fortuitous as well.
Obviously when you try and record your conference the first thing you realize is that in a highly
interactive conference most people don't use the microphone and it's really annoying for
everybody on the streaming when you get a load of silence in the room.
So persuading people to use microphones is one of the key things that you have to do
when you start recording your conference and this is still nothing to do with trying to
get it live or hybrid, this is just recording the conference.
So you have to persuade all participants in the conversation to actually use a microphone
and however much money your conference makes you will only have a few microphones like
this one we have two microphones at the front, I have one lavalier microphone for a room
that could possibly seat over a thousand people.
Trying to run around with microphones when you're doing an interactive conversation is
really difficult as I assume the guys with the orange t-shirts will be able to tell you
over a beer after the event.
The solution we took was borrowed from another conference in Paris called Kernel Recipes
which are these things called catch boxes and effectively they're square plastic polystyrene
blobs that have a microphone inside that you can throw from one end of a conference room
to another and this gives you a way of actually getting the microphone between the participants
very fast and it's definitely fun to use and they do encourage participation.
So far we've had no injuries, I should actually qualify, we've actually had no serious injuries
so far with people throwing microphones at each other but I assume there's always a first
time.
And the idea was really to try and make the conference that we were running available
in real time to people who can't participate because you know it's a kernel development
conference we get people who want to come from all over the globe and we always have
corners of the globe especially when we run the conference in America that even if they
have the best will in the world and they can actually scrape up the money to come they're
often denied visas by the US authorities so it can be a real really difficult problem.
And for our first attempts at doing this the communication was really only outbound so
the remote participants could watch what was going on in the room but they couldn't really
participate.
And obviously this all changed in 2000 when we got to the pandemic years.
Like all other conferences plumbers moved to being fully online.
We didn't, we were actually in the year 2000 we already booked a venue up in Halifax Nova
Scotia, we had a huge amount of fun trying to get out of that venue contract when it
emerged that we couldn't actually hold the conference up there and then we all had to
scramble to try and actually do this fully online.
So this is where the story becomes quite interesting because there are ten people on plumbers committee
Mike Rappaport over here is one of them because of the origin we are primarily kernel developers
and because we're moving fully online effectively kernel developers are becoming responsible
for web programming because what we're really doing is setting up a distributed set of web
services and if you know kernel developers we mostly tend to theoretically look down
on web developers because obviously the kernel development is at the hard core of everything
so this is somewhat a story of how a bunch of kernel developers tried to do web and failed
a bit, screwed up quite a lot and eventually got it working by the seat of their pants.
We evaluated a load of options for actually going fully online as every conference did,
they scrambled to, we discussed it a lot with other conferences, people had different ideas,
we were actually under the umbrella of the Linux Foundation and they're a much more commercial
entity than we are, we're still volunteer run even pulling a lot of money, their idea
was just to pay somebody to do the solutions and frankly in the early days that looked
like a good idea to us, if you can just pay money to get rid of the problem why wouldn't
you and we have enough money, we've got almost a million dollars in the bank now for plumbers,
we could afford to spend a lot of that money to actually pay for somebody to sort out these
problems and the Linux Foundation tried to do it for several conferences and we looked
at their solution and went you know this is terrible, I mean why is it so difficult and
so bad trying to run a conference and so the only way we could actually foresee getting
this working is if we just abandoned all of the commercial solutions and did it ourselves
which is much more difficult than we imagined to actually do but the goal of this was that
we definitely needed in our online conference to have two way video interaction in real
time between the participants, that was the goal and there was no real conference system
that did that, if you've tried holding conferences over zoom you can just about do it but things
like BBB actually do an awful lot better than this and the other thing we discovered is
that when you're running a collection of web services it really is all about the integrations.
Open source gives you a lot of excellent pieces so we use big blue button, we use indico for
the conference scheduling, eventually we use matrix for the track, we didn't use it in
the first year but there's also a downside to that, whenever you try and integrate web
services you always write a set of glue around them that needs to be maintained and if there
are a load of disparate services that aren't used to talking to each other it does the
impedance matching between the services and as the years go by and remember this is a
conference so we put it on once a year, every year you upgrade to the new versions and suddenly
your glue doesn't work again so it always becomes a maintenance nightmare to get the
glue working. So if you ever came to the plumbers conference the web front end that you first
see if you go to meet.lpc.events is a piece of code that John Corbett wrote in Python
and Django called the Linux plumbers conference front end, LPCFE, oh and I should add that
these things here are clickable URLs so if you go to the presentation and you want to
know where it is you can just hover over it and it will tell you. Obviously green light
is actually the way you log people onto BBB so by replacing green light in big blue button
we've effectively taken on the job ourselves of doing integration, authentication, user
management and pretty much everything else, this is actually a major replacement of services
on big blue button and the reason we did this is because we needed an integration with our
conference timetable, we just wanted the conference timetable to display on the first screen with
a little button that said click here to go to this session, it's very like you have in
FOSDAM with the matrix chat, if you just click on the integration of the matrix chat it brings
up the live stream and you can see what's going on in the conference, we wanted it to
work pretty much as it does here and green light just wouldn't do that for us because
green light was designed to be a teaching front end for a single classroom, it wasn't
really thinking about multiple tracks, multiple track rooms and timetable integration. So
we also, by getting rid of all of the attendee credentials, we actually had to integrate
with some sort of authentication server that could be distributed, so being kernel developers
because we chose LDAT because it's the oldest one and it's the one everybody has the most
trouble with, so we should be able to use it right. The credentials were the email address
that you used to register with the conference which is easy and the password was just the
confirmation number because fortunately the Linux Foundation's CVAN system spits out these
long confirmation numbers and they're all guaranteed to be unique, so that's obviously
really easy. Problem, again, integration. The CVAN system will not speak to anything
outside CVAN, so if you register for the conference and you don't automatically show up in the
LDAP database, what has to happen is I have to go to the CVAN website and export a spreadsheet
of all of the users, figure out which are new ones and then feed the details into the
LDAP server, which, I mean, as an offline activity it sounds really simple. It becomes
really complicated when you keep getting people who don't register until the last minute of
the conference, turn up halfway through a session, want to register and then immediately
be able to see what the hell is going on and they have to wait for, I don't know how long
for somebody to actually put their credentials in the database and when you're running a
conference pretty much all of your attendees are running around, all of your organizers
are running around full time, nobody has time to tend the back end of the database and that
became a bottleneck for certain people. So my request of you is if you ever get into
this situation, register early, please, don't turn up at the last minute, it's much easier.
Then the next problem is that nobody is actually really used to interacting online. I mean,
you think it's easy, you've seen Zoom calls, you all just turn up and you've got, you know,
pieces of each other on it. If you try and do that with 800 people, Zoom doesn't really
do auto focus very well. You can't see who's talking and if you're just observing the conference
it just becomes a mass of faces and it's completely useless. So we obviously have standard issues
like good webcam, good microphone. The number of people probably among you sitting in this
room who think that the standard set of speakers on your Dell system when you just open the
laptop will do when you're chatting to each other, believe me it won't. The thing that
audiences hate the most in online conferences is static, background noise, indistinctness,
being unable to get the point across. If you don't have in the attendees who are going
to interact good AV equipment, this is the thing which actually makes the conference
experience go down the fastest. This is about the only thing we got right because we gave
us speaker gifts designed to be delivered to anywhere in the world a month before the
conference, a complete gift pack of headset lights so you could actually see the face
and a webcam you could put on the top of your camera, a 1080p webcam so we were sure that
we'd actually have a good view of the speakers. We made sure that they got to all of our nearly
100 speakers in the conference and most of them didn't use them which was a bit of a
problem. We also found as I've explained with Zoom that raised hands don't work and having
a load of people on video who you have no idea what's going on doesn't work either.
So the thing we pioneered for plumbers is called video muting which is where we try
and instruct the attendees to if you're just watching don't turn your camera on. So pretty
much it's a blank screen. The only people who turn their camera on are people who are
talking or people who are waiting to talk so it actually gives a good visual clue that
somebody wants to interject at this point and we found it was actually a reasonably
good way of facilitating interaction in an online conference and it certainly solves
the Zoom confusion where you just can't figure out who's talking to whom on your screen of
and for the online conference we did have about 900 attendees so you could imagine on
a Zoom screen everybody would probably get about 5 pixels. In 2020, Big Blue Button comes
with an internal chat system which means anybody logged into Big Blue Button can pop out a
chat tab at the side and they'll be able to chat with anybody who's logged into the conference.
So this is why if you were doing streaming of the conference you couldn't interact because
that is a completely enclosed chat system. But we realized that people wanted to have
conversations outside the discussion rooms as well, things like hallway tracks. So we
actually adopted a, it's a sort of open source project called Rocket Chat. Now the core of
the project is fully open sourced but Rocket Chat themselves runs a more open core model
where there are certain enterprise upsells and everything but this was just the one we
came across. And the good thing for us is it doesn't require any integration because
we'd already started to realize the more integrations you do, the more difficulty you have, the
more strings and balen wire stuff there is to go wrong at the crunch time when you put
the conference on. So no integration looked like a good thing until we tried to run the
conference. And then the problems were that chat was hard to read on the live stream because
we're streaming it out pretty much through YouTube. We actually, Guy Lunardi wrote a
streaming module for BVB and we just plugged it in as an additional attendee and what it
saw was what we streamed to YouTube. And the problem is that YouTube does dynamic compression
of most of the stuff while it's streaming and if you have a low bandwidth connection
it will quite happily Greek all of the chat that's going on and you just can't see what
is going on on the chat. Whereas, you know, if it's sort of having a bandwidth problem
with faces and you're just looking at lips moving, you can stand losing quite a few pixels
but if you're trying to follow chat it's just impossible. And obviously streamers didn't
have any credentials to the RocketChat anyway because we based it on our LDAP. If you're
not registered for the conference you have no chat credentials. So they couldn't join
the hallway track either which they didn't like. This was the problem. And the third
problem was we had to buy an enterprise license from RocketChat actually to get some of the
notifications that we used for integration to work. And the two chat systems were completely
and fully disconnected. So you couldn't use your RocketChat login to look at the BBB chat
and vice versa which also was a bit balkanizing and a bit annoying for people. And so you
can see that the thing I initially portrayed as a huge advantage because we didn't have
to worry about the integration was the thing that everybody found the biggest disadvantage
about the conference because it wasn't integrated. So you always get this pressure of, and you
know as conference organizers, the more integration you do the more chance there is that something
will go wrong. But if you don't do enough integration your audience don't like it. So
you have to get the amount of integration right. And for several conferences we actually
struggled to do this. Every registered attendee got a matrix ID and since we used email and
confirmation number to login we figured we just use email address matrix as well. But
there's a slight problem here. Emails contain an at sign. Matrix does not like additional
at signs in your ID so we had to replace the at sign with a full stop which I thought,
oh it could be easy for our attendees. They're all computer geeks. They'll get this. They'll
know email address for one server, email address but with at sign substitutes with dot for
another server. Complete disaster. You know they just couldn't figure out which ID correctly
to use for which. Eventually we got the BBB server to use either form of the address and
we actually got the matrix server to translate using a JavaScript widget. If they typed in
the email address it would just fill in the dot and everything would just work. We tried
it without doing that for a couple of days and got a bucket full of complaints. I should
also add that when we chose Rocket Chat in 2020 I wasn't very happy about the decision
because I was a fledgling matrix user and I was sure that matrix could handle the conference
and I thought it would actually be a good idea to do this. So I'd advocated even in
2020 that we should be using matrix and finally after all the difficulty with Rocket Chat
in 2021 I got my wish. So they told me we're using matrix and you're in charge which was
fun until the first day came along and the matrix server with 900 people on it just fell
over. And we had actually done scaling testing. I mean I'm not naive. I know things can go
wrong at scale that you know you don't see in your own lab. So we'd invited everybody
to come along for a town hall but only 100 people showed up and it turned out that most
of the scaling problems we had were somewhere between 100 and 900. So we hadn't hit any
of them in our little test. And I'd also tried to scale up the matrix server so our massive
16 CPU system that we were paying you know about $100 a month for when you ran top on
it was only using one CPU because I hadn't realized that matrix synapse which was the
server we chose was single threaded. I mean who in 2021 writes a single threaded web application
but the matrix people thread matrix by using the back end web server through a sequence
of proxies to actually do this but that is not the default configuration. And so on the
Monday of the conference I was left there in my own little basement sweating away going
how the hell do I scale this thing. But fortunately several people who attended FOSDEM which did
use matrix before we did also ran into this problem and they were able to send me email
saying yeah we've got this guy you can talk to he'll teach you how to do it. So fortunately
within about four hours of discovering the problem and realizing it didn't scale we had
a roughly scaling matrix server working and I managed to actually complete the scaling
by the end of the first day so for the second day matrix was actually fully functional fortunately
since it was my little baby. And I actually did a little blog post about how we got this
to work just so if anybody else ever runs into the problems there are online resources
to go to to get yourselves out of it. One of the good things about using matrix was
that even the free tier attendees the streaming tier attendees could now actually interact
by chat. So anybody with their own matrix ID could log on to any of our matrix rooms
because they're all public in the same way that all the FOSDEM rooms are public. Every
attendee still got their own separated matrix ID but that you only got logged onto the matrix
ID if you actually popped up the side chat panel. You could also use your own separated
matrix thing and use your own matrix ID as well if you wanted to. And it just depended
how you wanted to interact with the conference. Guilinardi was the one who actually modified
the BVB server to instead of opening its own chat tab we just stole the iframe concept
it uses for the blackboard and we did a riot embedded which is done by some URL to the
GitHub account is there. The integration, the riot embedded is not as good as running
the electron type application but trying to embed an electron application into a web form
is just a nightmare and doesn't work. So it's a very cut down version all it really does
is text pictures and reactions. It doesn't do any of these sort of complicated threading
or replies or anything but that's pretty much good enough for conference attendees. But
you can see the Primrose path we're treading down because this is yet another integration
into matrix, in a BVB in matrix that is not done by either upstream. But it was really
useful so the streamers could see the chat if it was grieved on their streaming screen
they could actually use a matrix client and still view the chat in real time without having
to worry about video compression and reduction. And so we thought after we'd done this successfully
for two years now, especially for one year with rocket chat, one year with matrix, it
wouldn't be too difficult to move over to hybrid which is probably really the point
of this talk. We already had all the remote infrastructure. By the way, to run this style
of remote infrastructure for a conference the size of plumbers so we're talking about
900 people and we assume that for the in person one we'd probably be about 400 in person,
500 online. It will cost you somewhere between three and five thousand dollars to actually
set up and run. It's not cheap to do the hosting of all of this stuff. Especially because we
had to host at scale. We needed one BVB server per each track room. We had about six track
rooms. We had a few spare servers left over for hack rooms and we had one for the hallway
track. But the way we looked at it is we already had all of the AV necessary for actually just
this is the naive thought which is where kernel developers go. You know, we've got AV in the
room, it's got two cameras and it's got a load of microphones. The room is just another
single person attending the BVB chat. It'll be easy to do it like that, the naive way
of thinking. But it really, really is not that simple trying to get a hybrid conference
running. The significant problem is that you have to integrate with in room AV and in room
AV, well, okay, so at ULB you control it. But we were doing it in hotels. Hotels have
their own local AV teams. If you touch a piece of their equipment they tend to go screaming
to management. In order to get the integration done you can't do it yourself as the conference
organizes. The AV people, the audio people have to do it. And it's surprising the number
of audio people who sort of sit behind those switcher boards at the back of conferences
who've never even seen a sort of online hybrid conference and have no idea how to set this
up. So just plonking this sort of video display down in front of them and saying, hey, now
you're in charge of audio and video and we just want the conference to work, wasn't actually
a winning strategy. So we discovered rapidly and unfortunately it was pretty much on the
day of the conference that we had to train the AV people and have to use all of this
stuff. And we were actually quite fortunate because we'd ordered the video based AV. We
actually had two sets of AV people. So the hotel usually supplies audio people to plug
in your projectors and your microphones into the hotel's audio. And then we had a separate
AV company whose job was to manage the cameras and sort of cut the whole thing together and
do the live streaming. So we actually had two AV teams effectively and we were assuming
that we could just co-opt the AV team who was doing the live streaming because live
streaming, running live streaming is not much different than running an online conference,
right? Wrong. So we held meetings beforehand with them and we talked to them about it.
We couldn't hold meetings with the hotel audio guys but we assumed it would just be a plug
for them, which it wasn't. And nobody really anticipated the issues that we actually had.
Specifically the AV setup of remote attendees is not obvious to somebody who's used to dealing
with throwing microphones around a room because there is one extra wire that's coming off
the internet over which a lot of attendee voices can come. And the first time they set
up their AV patch panels, this wire just wasn't plugged in. The second time it was bypassing
all of the audio routing which meant that the sound quality and the volume was chopping
at high strength because it wasn't being attenuated through the usual filters. I mean, this is
the 101, you know, how many screw ups can you have? We basically did them all on the
first day. So let's go through a list of the problems.
Oh, I even forgot to mention that between 2001 and 2002 we decided to upgrade the whole
of the infrastructure. We had specific things in BBB we wanted. Remember I told you we have
two cameras. We have one at the back facing the speaker, one at the front facing the audience.
The new version of BBB could actually handle multiple cameras with different views. So
we figured that wouldn't it be really great if, you know, you want to see the audience
so you just select the audience camera as a remote participant because you want to talk
to them. Or let's say you're a remote speaker, you want to see the audience but the rest
of the people just want to see you. We'll do this multiple camera selection. It was
going to be the cornerstone of our implementation of this. Problem was, nobody told the AV guys.
So the AV guys had come set up with a switcher for the two cameras which is how they ran
the streaming because obviously you can select one camera view or the other because the live
streaming pretty much has one camera view out on it. And by the time we all sat together
in the room there was no way of unplugging this set up and redoing it such that we could
plug in two video cameras because it all has to be done from the AV control deck and they
physically didn't have another input because they were expecting to use a camera switch.
So this is yet another screw up in planning. Third screw up was because we'd upgraded to
the newer BVB. They'd redone the, and this uses Node React as the frame backbone. They'd
redone the way it was working. Riot embedded no longer worked as a Popout panel. We discovered
this fortunately four days before the conference. So this was Guy Lenardi doing a very quick
back end retrofit trying to get the matrix chat that everybody was expecting to work
to work. And fortunately by the time we did the conference it was actually working but
this was yet another squeaky bum issue where we tried to do everything at the last minute.
The first day we had a lot of rooms where the room couldn't hear the remote attendees.
This is the wire problem from the remote. Or the remote attendees couldn't hear the
room because it's a two wire problem. It's not just sound from the remote coming into
the room, it's sound from the room going out to the remotes as well. So we had to have
the sound correctly plugged into BVB. The streaming guys thought they were just plugging
the sound into the streaming. So if you watched the live stream it had the correct sound but
if you were on the BVB thing it was completely silent because they hadn't plugged the sound
in. It's just yet another screw up that we didn't actually think to test out. So this
is how it looks in the sort of conference hall as we were going around it. So this is
the panel you can see. This is what BVB looks like pretty much in a classroom situation.
This is the presentation which you can actually minimize if you click this button but obviously
we thought that the AV people might be able to click the minimize button when the conversation
is going on and then click it back again. No, it didn't really work. They didn't really
want to do this. So we just kept everything up. This is the attendees panel which is all
scrolling which is nice but if you think about it that's not really what you want to see
in the conference. The chat panel if you click this will pop out and come here and this,
the rest of this will really shrink which is also not really what the attendees did.
So what we should have done is have the chat panel down here and get rid of the attendee
list or make it pop out only. So we put this on our to-do list for next time because it's
sort of nice to have but it wasn't essential to getting the conference working. This is
actually an excerpt from the RISC-V micro conference. So Atish Patra is actually asking
a remote question. You can see that he's asking it of a member of the audience so we've switched
to the audience camera view because ideally there would have been two cameras here, one
of the audience, one of the speaker and he could have switched between them but we screwed
up and didn't get that working in time. The tab also includes shared notes which goes
to a back end on ether pads so the remote audience can also see the shared notes and
they can also click on the pop up and these buttons here actually allow you to mute people
who are not supposed to be speaking when they are because in a remote conference you get
lots of people who forget to meet their microphone and then have a conversation with their wife
or their, you know, their significant other. This happens quite often. The way BBB is set
up is that anybody can meet anybody but we thought that might be a bad idea because it's
sort of, you know, cantankerous kernel developers, you never quite know who they'll mute. And
once you've muted somebody you can't unmute them, they can only unmute themselves because
this is a sort of, you know, you can't be unmuting people while they're going to the
bathroom or something, it wouldn't be good on a conference. And we figured this might
be a problem so we'd restricted this functionality to administrators only and then nobody could
figure out who the administrators were so it became a bit of a problem. The video overlays
work quite well so, I mean, this is pretty much a blow up of a 1080p thing and you can
see the Greeking happening in the room. It's very difficult to make out individual attendees
but the sort of remote participants were reasonably visible to most people. So BBB, and especially
you can actually see the way it works with the video muting idea, it's really all you
see are the people participating. Now one of the other things that we'd actually try
to do in the room is the back face, the camera at the back, the camera at the front facing
the back actually had a pan and zoom facility which the AV operators that assured us would
allow them to zoom in on whoever was speaking but in the event what we discovered is that
only two of the AV operators out of our six rooms knew how to use this. So we did get
panning and zooming in some of the rooms but not in all of them. Again, this goes back
to preparation and training. We will do better next time. Yep. And it actually took us quite
a while to get the audio routing right. You'd think that plugging two wires into an AV system
wouldn't be that difficult but in fact it really was. And we finally figured out that
what you had to say to the audio guy is here's a wire from what's effectively a microphone
on the computer. The video guy will give it to you. You just plug it into your fader panel
and remember you have it and you give him a wire for the AV stream that also has to
go into the BBB thing. And eventually we got that to work. But obviously we had other problems.
One of the other things that we'd really thought about was when we get into the room we'd actually
like to have the chat and all the remote attendees on one monitor and then we'd like to have
the presentations on another. So we thought we'll have a two projector set up which sounds
fine until you realize that we have rooms about as big as this and the two projectors
were right over there and right over there. So somebody sitting over there can't see what's
on that projector. Somebody sitting over there can't see what's on that projector. So the
only way we could make it work was to display the same image on both projectors which meant
that two projectors was a complete waste of money and we should have gone for a single
central one as well. So next year we will either try with one or three just to see if
we can actually get this right. Obviously as I said the two camera handling we thought
would be the centerpiece of the technology. The reason why we'd upgraded BBB and caused
all of the React JScript failures on the matrix back end was to get this facility that we
couldn't actually use. So that was not only sleepless nights for one person for a week
to try and get it all to work but complete screw up on the day when everything we thought
we'd bought with that upgrade didn't function. The other problem we had was because the AV
people are actually doing the live streaming and because of the way BBB works there is
no choice other than to actually run the master BBB session that is showing up on both projectors
on their AVmux console. And I had thought this might be a problem as well. So BBB is
very heavily matrix, it's very heavily React JavaScript based and certain browsers handle
it better than other browsers. So it's mostly, it works with Firefox quite well now but it
is mostly optimized for Chromium. So I'd actually already asked them God if we have to do this
what is the built in browser of this TMUX thing and they said oh it's Chrome and I thought
oh God it's going to work. But the problem was that the MUX platform might have used
Chromium as an internal thing but Chromium is open source. So the guys who built the
MUX platform had just basically taken WebKit, gutted some of the JavaScripts and hoped that
that would be okay. And what it really meant was the threading functions of JavaScript
didn't work very well. The result was that it kept dropping out of the conference and
obviously since this is running the AV conference when it drops out the in room chat and the
remote participants fully separate. And the problem is there's no indication that this
has happened from the console unless you happen to be watching very carefully because all
you see is that a microphone disappears from that little icon in the top left that says
hey you're the room and suddenly your microphone's gone. That's the only indication the AV people
had they dropped out. Trying to train them to notice this and reconnect was a bit of
a problem. So we do have automated reconnections on the back end but we will try and integrate
into BVV but when we raised it on the list they looked at us and said well how come you
have this problem because nobody else has this problem. If BVV kept on dropping people
out of the conversation as a matter of course people would have complained. This was a specific
interaction due to the cut down browser and the tmux interface that nobody had anticipated.
Again another screw up from not actually trying it beforehand. So as I said rejoin was manual
assuming the AV guy noticed. One of the good things we did have was in room shepherds who
were committee members so they could actually watch the on screen panel every time the icon
disappeared I could I or one of the other shepherds could run to the back of the room
and pat the AV guy on the shoulder and say you need to rejoin please do this. So we could
make it work with a lot of manual fussing behind the scenes but it wasn't easy. So one
of the other things that we realized is that you know hindsight is 20-20. I mean they might
want to run it from the AV console but they don't have to run the whole thing. What we
could have done is have a separate laptop that actually ran all of the AV connections
under the charge of I won't say somebody competent because it would have been one of me the
kernel developers or somebody but somebody who would pay more attention and then what
we could have done for the vmux guys was to actually give them a VNC session or something
like that into the panels they were projecting over the streaming and everything else and
that way we would have had much more control in the room and we'd have been running a full
fledged browser that wouldn't have had most of the connection problems that we had. But
obviously trying to sort that out on the day was pretty much impossible. Particularly unfortunately
is this AV mux platform is sort of Windows based and Windows does not do VNC very well
and trying to get it to work with RDSP which is the Windows native thing didn't work very
well and we just it was we were in Dublin we didn't have any equipment we had to organize
the parties and deal with online conferences we just couldn't get it to work. So we do
know that for the future we are going to try and do a shareable console. And I need to
leave time for questions I have 10 minutes left. We had a load of other problems as well
as you can see this so I'm in order to try and tell you all the difficulty about doing
this I'm talking up the problems. From the audience's point of view this conference was
actually very successful. We got plaudits from most of the attendees that the interaction
worked as they expected they could have their one on one conversations including between
remote and local people, remote and remote people. So everything appeared to just work
for them modulo you know the problems of not being able to hear the room and having to
rejoin and having to tell people the lost AV and they need to rejoin. They forgave us
for all of that so it was actually highly rated as an incredibly successful conference
but it was a bit like a swan with that you know serene sort of thing swimming over the
surface and a load of committee members frantically paddling underneath to try and get all of
this to stay up and running. Our other big screw up was that we had a committee of 10
people but because this was pandemic not all of the committee could turn up in Dublin and
by the time we got to Dublin we only had two local people who actually understood the system
and could deal with it. Surprisingly enough they're the two people who are actually standing
up on the platform now taking the blame for all of this. But believe me in a conference
with six tracks and AV guys who don't know what they're doing if you want a lot of exercise
please do it with two people but if you want to actually make it work seamlessly and vaguely
competently you need one person who understands the setup in each room. So next time we will
try and do it with a minimum number of people as we have same number of track rooms. Again
it's not rocket science it's perhaps something we should have seen ahead of time but we thought
it would be easy and it wasn't. So to leave a bit of time for questions if you have them.
Running conferences is actually hard so just remember that when you go home from here and
volunteering for a conference is actually an act of public self sacrifice that more
of you should consider because honestly you will find out that it is really hard. Running
online conferences is harder especially if you try and do it yourselves because there
is actually a lot more to do. It is actually more difficult to run an online conference
than it is to run an in-person conference paradoxically. And this is mainly to do with
the integration issues. Everything that doesn't integrate well is either your fault or you
are responsible for integrating it and integrating web stuff even in this magic day and age of
sort of you know web scripting and operators and everything else really doesn't work that
well. And hybrid is really only for masochists. Only do a hybrid conference if you want to
give yourself an untold amount of pain that you can then come and complain to an audience
like you about later. But if you really want to get it right the key is training your AV
people. Do not wait like we did to turn up on the day and say it will be easy. You need
a couple of training sessions a few months beforehand to try and get all of the kinks
sorted out. And having meetings and discussing it doesn't cut it. You need the AV people
to set it all up and preferably have a few people fly out to see the set up, work with
a few remote people so you actually check it out in all of its situations. And obviously
you need to do this in advance. You don't do it on the day of the conference which is
what we try to do. Oh well lesson learned. So with that I think I have about five minutes
for questions. This was actually all done in open source using HTML and CSS. That does
make me a web developer. Proud of it now finally. Obviously you can see that kernel developers
don't quite do web as well as web developers. So if any web developers would like to join
our program committee and become jointly responsible for next year's disaster please come forward.
The presentation is all online and I've also put it up on the link in Pentabath so you
should just be able to click on it. All of the links in the presentation that are highlighted
are clickable if you want to see the URLs. And with that I'll just say thank you and
Mike and I can now answer questions. Oops. You have Mike. Okay we'll share this mic.
Any questions? Please speak loudly into the microphone. Yes. Thank you. From what you
said about the AV set ups in the hotels were there any discussion to just ask hotels to
you know move their stuff and have your own stuff brought in because to me that seems
after your talk to have been an easier solution to just say you know your AV guys and your
AV is probably good but we have really specialized needs could we just bring our own equipment
in? Okay so the question is could we bring our own equipment in? And the answer is pretty
much every hotel no. Because remember they do the AV routing as a very specialized sort
of adaption for the conference rooms. They have a lot of really expensive speakers sometimes
in the ceiling sometimes at the back of the room and they don't want any non-experts touching
it. So what hotels usually have as a clause in their contract is a requirement that you
use their own sound guys and this clause is non-negotiable. We did try and negotiate with
a couple of hotels where we said because we had a few screw ups even in the live streaming
days where the hotel didn't do very well and we thought we could do better. But it's always
come back to us as an absolute no. It's actually very lucky for the ULB guys who are used to
having students handle their equipment and don't seem to have as many hang ups about
it as hotels. So there are people here who can be trained on this equipment who can use
it but pretty much when you're running a conference in a hotel or in a professional conference
hall that we've also been to so community convention center or something you actually
have to use their AV staff you don't get a choice. And that means that you always have
this extra component of people that you have to deal with and they're usually people who
don't really understand fully what your requirements are because it's very difficult to communicate
ahead of time. And these people are usually the people that you don't get to talk to until
you turn up at the conference. So when you have your intermediate AV guys like we had
and you have your meeting with them you always have to make sure that they have enough knowledge
and insight that they can do the knowledge transfer to the sound guys who are going to
be coming in on the day from the hotel. So yeah it's a huge problem and there's almost
nothing you can do to get out of it besides sort of having a very friendly university
who will let you play with their equipment because pretty much nobody in the professional
circuit will let you play with their equipment. I have one question from the chat. Was it
worth it to record the audience? So the question was was it worth it to record the audience?
And the answer to that is actually very much yes because remember in a micro conference
we're stimulating discussions between arbitrary groups of people. So these would be people
who are sitting in the audience physically versus people who are sort of remote. And
in order to have a correct two-way conversation you actually have to be able to see the person
on the other end. And so the whole point of the audience camera, at least when it worked
with the panning and zooming, was that if you were having a remote to local conversation
with the audience the remote people could actually see the local participant. And if
we only had a camera facing the speaker we'd either have to call every participant up to
stand on the stage which wastes time or we'd just have to not have them be able to see
the person they're talking to. And being able to see the person you're talking to is very
important for interactions. There are lots of visual cues that people get wrong. So I
think having an audience camera is actually one of the good benefits of, or at least one
of the benefits the plumbers did and one of the good insights we had to try and get an
interactive conference running. So I wouldn't go back and do no audience camera, no.
Just wanted to get back to what you said about the ULB being willing to allow us to use their
audio equipment. I just want to point out that this has a lot to do with the fact that
we've been doing this for 20 years and they know us. It wasn't always the case and if
you're not false them or you're not working with the ULB this probably isn't the case.
So could you repeat the, I got half the question, no. Yeah it wasn't the question really so
much as to point out that us being allowed to touch the audio equipment here by the ULB
has a lot to do with the fact that we've been doing this for 20 years and they know us.
Okay so the point being made is that ULB only allows the staff here to touch the equipment
because they've been doing it a long time and they've built up trust. The way we work
we tend to go to a different hotel every time we hold plumbers in a different location.
So pretty much even if we could get a trust to build up with a hotel chain we just, we
wouldn't be in the hotel often enough to do it. But the important point to emphasize is
that pretty much 95% of the time you will be forced to work with AV people who are supplied
to you by whoever owns the equipment. You won't get a choice of who does it. Okay. Is
that it? Okay. Well thank you very much indeed.