Hi, I'm Brian Bellendorf.
I'm the general manager for the Open Source Security Foundation, which is a project hosted
at the Linux Foundation, but has its own rather large membership and set of activities and
the like.
And I thought I'd take the time to talk to you this morning about some of the things
that we learned coming out of the Log4Shell incident, and in general what we're doing
at the OpenSSF to try to improve the state of security across all of open source software.
And I do apologize for using the term software supply chain.
I know folks are sometimes very sensitive to thinking of themselves as suppliers.
You're all developers.
You're all building components.
You're all handing things off to the next person, right?
And I just want to be sensitive to that and recognize a lot of us pursue this not just
to write code for our companies or for other people to use, but because we love it, because
it's like a form of literature.
And so I come to this very much from an expansive view of what software is.
But if you'll indulge me with the term software supply chain, you know, lots has been made
about the fact that today, 2023, open source software is incredibly pervasive, because
the further upstream you go in most software supply chains, even if the end result is proprietary
software, the further upstream, the much more likely it is that your dependencies, your
components are open source code, something like 78%, according to a study by Synopsys
last year, 78% of code in a typical product code base.
That could be a container image.
That could be software in a phone.
That could be or a car.
78% on average is preexisting open source code.
That last 22% is the part that, you know, the company put its name on and whatever.
But every and 97% of code bases somewhere contain open source software.
And 85% of code bases contain open source that is more than four years out of date.
The comparable for this and log for shell, by the way, were the number of companies who
claimed we're not vulnerable to the log for J problem, because we're still on version
1.x rather than 2.x.
Don't worry, which had been out of support, out of any updates for five years.
So this is kind of a disaster, but fixing this requires thinking about systematically
what does the software supply chain look like.
And this is highly simplified, and in a way, this is only what happens at one node of a
chain, right?
But within a given software lifecycle, you've got the developer writing, you know, code
from their head or in partnership with Copilot now, I guess, into an IDE that then goes into
a build system and pulls in dependencies and then creates packages and pushes them out
to a consumer of sorts, right?
Who could be another developer who then repeats that process and just uses that input as dependencies.
And there's at least eight, and there's probably a lot more, but at least eight kind of major
opportunities to take advantage of some default biases and assumptions and, frankly, just
things we forgot to close up in the course of this development process.
Everything from bypassing code review to compromising the source control system to modifying code
after it's come through source code and into build to compromising the build platform to
using a bad dependency to bypassing CI CD entirely, which we all know happens, to compromising
the package repo to using a bad package as a consumer.
So all each of those has had examples of compromise in the last few years that has caused major
breaches in and data loss out there.
And of course, we all, I don't know if any of you were on the front lines of fighting
this fire over the winter holiday of 2021 into 2022, but it ruined a lot of people's
holidays when log4shell hit.
And by the way, I want to refer to the vulnerability and the breach and the remediation as the
log4shell problem, not the log4j problem, because the log4j developers don't deserve
to have their brand of their project turned into exhibit A in what's broken about open
source.
They were actually, it's great software.
They're all professional developers.
Let's give them some credit.
There's a bunch of contributing factors we'll walk through, but it was really the log4shell
breach.
And what happened in the course of about six weeks is you went from a researcher for Alibaba
in China finding a vulnerability out of the ordinary course of due diligence work that
he was doing, reporting it appropriately through the Apache software foundation processes,
and that leading to the very first CVE, starting from November 24th all the way to January
4th and January 10th, so about six weeks, where you have governments like the UK government
warning people of this major systematic issue, right?
And three more CVEs being discovered of various degrees of intensity, each of them leading
to a subsequent patch, to a subsequent remediation by exhausted IT teams to, I mean, if you talk
to any of the log4j developers, I don't believe any of them are here, but they would talk
about things like getting these demand letters from corporate legal departments asking them
to fax back a signed attestation that they had fixed the holes in log4j and that company's
use.
That was a real relationship, that company was a free rider on top of their code.
So I'm not going to read through each of these steps, I apologize for this, but there was
this incredibly compressed timeline where people were intensely stressed, where really
the goodwill that we show as open source developers by putting our code out there and the fair
warning that we give people to use it at your own risk was substantially attacked, right?
It was substantially, all these misconceptions that companies have about underlying open
source code and the degree to which they take advantage of it kind of came to bear.
And so it raised a bunch of questions amongst folks who perhaps hadn't thought about this
before.
Is open source software's generally good reputation for security?
Is it well deserved?
Does this demonstrate deep and pervasive issues, technical issues, across how we consume and
develop open source code?
Do these issues extend to the sustainability model for open source itself?
Can we really depend upon so many, quote, volunteers, right?
I mean, think about it, we don't depend upon volunteers to build bridges and highways to
maintain our electrical grid, right?
How do we depend upon volunteers to maintain our critical infrastructure that everything
runs on, right?
And of course, it wasn't just like us as technologists asking these questions of each other, it was
like compliance and risk officers.
It was the cybersecurity insurance industry.
It was the European Union and the White House and UK's NCSC and other government agencies
kind of all challenging us, do we know what we're doing?
And one interesting report, and it is worth your time to read, it's about 49 pages, came
out about six months after the fact.
What happened was the US government convened a group of experts from across industry and
had them go and talk to the Log4j developers, talk to other open source experts, talk to
lots and lots of open source foundations, and try to ask what went on, what contributed
to this?
And it was modeled after, you know, when a plane crashes and the government will convene
for many of them, like a study group, to answer, well, why did this plane crash, other than,
of course, sudden loss of altitude.
You know, what were the underlying root causes to this plane crash?
And so this was modeled after the very same thing.
And it's a great report to read, I think, because it also comes up with some recommendations
for how potentially to prevent the next one.
And I'll walk through a couple of the conclusions, they said, you know, a focused review of the
Log4j code could have identified the unintended functionality that led to the problem.
Understand the bug, the original big bug was in a portion of code that had been contributed
to Log4j years and years earlier by a company that wanted to support LDAP lookups in real
time during the logging process, which seems like an extraordinarily bad idea to me, but,
okay, I'm not an enterprise IT.
So they had added this functionality and then kind of left.
They kind of didn't stick around to maintain it.
They didn't really do a due diligence into the security of its own code.
And the other Log4j developers just kind of kept it around because they didn't get many
bug reports on it.
It wasn't really a problem.
So it was kind of this forgotten portion of the code.
So part of it was if they had had security resources to look at every line of code that
they were shipping out, rather than just the core stuff, which they were pretty diligent
about, they might have discovered this bug.
It might also have been discovered if the developers themselves had developed, had adopted
certain secure coding practices consistent with how certain other organizations kind
of define how those processes should work.
If they'd had design reviews that focused on security and reducing kind of the surface
area, the attack surface, sorry, for problems.
If they'd used threat models to understand, hey, we really should try to make sure we're
better protected against people using through the user generated input.
When you're a logging engine, you're dealing with a ton of user generated input.
If you're parsing that for things like format strings, which is what they were doing in
this, that's potentially very dangerous.
That's something we've known kind of since some of the earliest CVEs out there.
And then finally, if they had had proper security audits.
And so in answering that and trying to generalize from it, and it's always dangerous to generalize
from a single example, but they found that the only way to reduce the likelihood of risk
to the entire ecosystem caused by these kind of vulnerabilities and other widely used open
source code was to ensure that as much code as possible is developed pursuant to standardized
secure coding practices.
Now that kind of sounds like, well, if only the pilots had had better training or if only
the planes had been maintained better, then we wouldn't have had these problems.
It seems a little bit like hindsight is 20-20.
But they did acknowledge that the volunteer based model of open source would need many
more resources than they have to be able to make this possible on average.
I mean, you've all heard the aphorism, which is called Linus's law, but it was coined by
Eric Raymond.
Linus has disavowed the law, actually, that says with enough eyeballs, all bugs are shallow.
But what was missing from that quote was eyeballs per line of code.
And I would argue that even in some of the most open source projects, we don't have enough
eyeballs per line of code.
And anything we do that divides that list, such as forks, for example, only takes us
further away from having enough eyeballs to review code.
There's lots that I can go into about it's not really just a supply chain security story.
It was kind of a supply chain story because of just how pervasive Log4J was.
It was a bug that affected everything from the iTunes store to people badging in with
security kind of like badges to all sorts of like embedded systems and the like.
Log4J was kind of everywhere.
And because it was everywhere, it was in a whole lot of places that people didn't have
the tools to even go and discover.
Often it was compiled into JAR files, so you couldn't even just, you know, do a directory
listing and grep through it to find Log4J.jar.
You actually had to interrogate the development process.
And without things like S-bombs, which appropriately the U.S. government has focused on kind of,
you know, saying this is an important thing to have, without a tool like that, a lot of
enterprises were left scrambling to figure out if they were vulnerable, which versions
they were running.
And then, as I mentioned, making ludicrous claims like we're not vulnerable because we're
way on an old version of Log4J, or asking completely disinterested third parties like
the Log4J developers themselves to attest that they're not vulnerable, right?
It was kind of crazy.
Moving on, part of this as well is trying to understand the motivations of developers
on an open source project, which, again, they took a look at, but I think they could have
pursued this even a little bit further.
When you work on an open source project, your primary motivation, well, okay, first off,
you probably all start as a user of the software.
Basically your first step into an open source project was not to write it from scratch.
Maybe it is, but in either case, you have some utility, something you want to use it
for.
So your first interest is get it running, and get it running correctly.
And so you're going to, like, be fixing bugs.
You're going to be adding features here and there, right?
But adding things that help make the software more secure, very rarely do they turn into
immediate benefit for you.
It's often a thing that's hard to convince your manager is worth doing, right, because
it doesn't necessarily affect what the manager sees in terms of, like, the feature set and
the code, or hey, it's now fit for purpose or whatever.
So there's a lot of sympathy that we can have for positions taken by, like, folks like Ben,
who wrote the cyber resilience act, who was up here yesterday kind of defending what was
written in the act, to say, well, maybe there are other forces that need to come into play
to help support those kinds of outcomes, right, to act as a forcing function for it if it
wouldn't otherwise be there.
But it's really hard to measure the return on that benefit independently.
And if you can't measure the ROI, it tends to get disincentive.
So as a way to illustrate this, particularly to Log4J, you know, I've had conversations
with the mirror Montezari, who some of you might know, who's with Ostiff, who's here.
We've kind of asked, hey, what would it have taken to do a proper third party code review
for security of the Log4J code base, right?
Just as an independent thing, looking at the number of lines of code in there.
And the estimate we came back was $50,000 to $100,000, depending on how deep you wanted
to get.
Let's say, and one of those would have found all four of those CVEs, possibly more, and
with a little bit more money, generously, let's say, another $50,000 to $100,000, you
could have funded the fixes for those bugs and coordinated a disclosure process such
that everybody got, or a lot of people would get updated, and then you publish the release.
And it wouldn't have been this mad scramble taking place over, between Christmas and New
Year's for a lot of folks.
So $200,000, which is beyond what I think any of the Log4J developers had in their back
pocket.
It's beyond what I think even, you know, the eight or ten of them together would have individually
been able to put together, or convince their employers to put in as a, as a, as a chunk
of cash.
But it was far less than the negative impact that that breach had on society, right?
I mean, it's hard, no one's actually sat and tried to calculate how much, and when they've
started they've come back with billions of dollars in lost productivity, in breaches,
in other things.
So, so like trying to play that back and do hindsight, you know, 20-20, that kind of thing,
could we have discovered this and fixed it?
You know, could we find the next one and spend $200,000 and fix that from being, from being
likely to happen?
I don't think I could give you the one that that's likely to be, but what if I could give
you a list of 200 projects, each of which probably had a greater than 1% chance, based
on their criticality, as you can measure from how often these codes, code bases are dependent
upon by other, other, other packages.
There's lots of data sources for that, and we at the OpenSSF have developed something
called the criticality index that'll find that.
What if we could find this list of 200 projects based on criticality, based on how well they
score by some objective measure of risk, and I'll get into this in a little bit.
Could I give you that list of 200 and could that likely, I mean more than 50% chance,
prevent the next log for J?
I would wager yes.
And that $40 million, again, is more than any open source foundation has to be able
to spend on this kind of work.
Even all the foundations together collectively probably couldn't spend that, and this is
the kind of thing you probably have to do each year in order to have that kind of impact.
But $40 million is, I don't mean to sound blasé about it, but frankly pocket change
for a lot of governments, especially if we got governments to work together on this,
or the insurance industry to work together, or say many of the sectors who use this software
without lifting a finger to contribute back.
If we pooled these kinds of funds, we could have an impact like that.
Some people just want to watch the world burn.
I had to throw in this obligatory slide, of course.
But I want to kind of push forward this theory of change then around, you know, because it's
not just about spending money on specific interventions like that.
I'll come back to that in a little bit, how we might rally those kinds of funds and focus
on that kind of work.
And what we're doing is the open SSF to have it.
But I want to also put forward, it's actually not just about a matter of spending money.
It's not just a matter of, you know, a mandate from a government to get an open source software
to be more secure, to get our processes and the supply chain to be more secure.
There's a culture change that has to happen as well.
People are often very resistant to change.
When your CI system is running and you're able to put out, you know, a new release and
turn the crank, and a few hours after issuing the, initiating, you know, accepting a pull
request, you've got a binary.
Like, you kind of don't want to mess it up.
You don't want to change it.
And especially the older we get, the more resistant we are to having to learn a new
system or change, especially if there seems to be no benefit.
But this is not unlike other times over the last 30 years that we've taken an insecure
paradigm and made it more secure.
And my general theory is something called carrots, defaults, and sticks.
And the best example I can come up with this is how we went from a completely unencrypted
web where browsers and servers talked clear text HTTP that could be sniffed by anybody
between browser and server and got to the point where today, I mean, somebody might
know the number, it was like 95% of web traffic is HTTPS.
It's actually probably 99% now based on what's happening recently with browsers.
But it didn't start with the browser maker saying, right, on April 1st, we're going to
cut off or send these warning signs about unencrypted access at the beginning of the
TLS era.
It started with incentives.
It started with carrots.
It started by having that little green key that would show up in the location bar on
a browser.
It might start by certain folks saying, well, this is something that should be used for
banking websites or for e-commerce websites or, you know, hosted email sites or that kind
of thing.
And that got about 15% of the web traffic getting encrypted out there.
But it started the flat line.
And then a bunch of people got together and realized, you know, we don't actually, it
doesn't have to be this hard to get a TLS certificate and install it in the right place.
We can automate this.
We can automate demonstrating that you have domain control over this domain name.
And if you do, then to give you a short-lived TLS certificate that can automatically be
installed in the right place in the web server.
And that service was called Let's Encrypt.
And it is now, I mean, for the last 10 years, it's been at the point where you can automatically,
when you install Apache, when you install a web server and install a, you know, the
TLS kind of version of that or a TLS profile, it will automatically set up a fetch tool
that's encrypt for a domain name you give it.
And it's like automated, automatable out of the box, right?
And that is what got us from 15% of the web being encrypted to about 75%.
And at that point, about five, six years ago is when the web browser maker said, right,
it's time for us to bring up the tail.
And that's where I talk about sticks.
And to finally get the laggards, the legacy sites, the folks who probably don't care about
it, even though who probably even haven't updated their web server in five years or
ten or whatever, to finally get off the duff and use Let's Encrypt or some other technique.
And they did that by making it progressively harder and harder for you to access a non-encrypted
website through Firefox, through Chrome, through, you know, MSIE, through other browsers.
And they kind of talked amongst themselves how to do that.
They tried not to piss people off, but you kind of have to piss some people off to do
that.
And as long as you just kind of progressively roll through, you can kind of bring people
along.
And there's some who will just, you know, forever be pissed off.
But that's like the tail end of an adoption curve, right, is this kind of concepts of
sticks.
And we think about the same thing when it comes to things like S-bombs or signing artifacts
in the supply chain or software at a station levels, which I'll get into a bit.
But when we think about how to get adoption of some of these security paradigms, it's
got to be through this three-step kind of process.
We can't just jump directly to sticks, which is kind of what the European Union Cyber Resiliency
Act attempts to do.
And I will say I think the CRA is a backlash to the Silicon Valley move fast and break
things kind of paradigm, this concept that open source software is some sort of reflection
of that or connected to that and that we're just as reckless.
But none of you all are Mark Zuckerberg, thankfully.
None of you all, I think, take that degree of recklessness as a badge of honor.
I think we're all just completely strapped for the amount of time that we'd really like
to spend on making the software as secure as possible.
And we need help.
We need defaults.
And we need, by the way, what's always worked in open source software as a duocracy, which
is people showing up and doing the work if that's what their primary interest is about,
right?
If somebody can sit on stage here and say, it's absolutely essential that this French
nuclear power plant only run open source software that has been certified against a whole bunch
of cybersecurity requirements, it's on them to do that work, not on the log4j developers
or others.
So this is where OpenSSF comes in.
We were started in 2020 kind of as a result of a small kind of gathering that had been
hosted on the West Coast, people working on software projects that had to do with enhancing
the software development processes in the open source community to be a bit more secure.
It was a mix of a bunch of different pieces of software, suggestions of protocols, building
on some of the SBOM work that had been actually championed first by the licensing community,
by the software licensing community, this is in particular a standard called SPDX for
SBOMs.
But they kind of realized that collectively what they were doing was building tools that
would help try to measure risk in open source and what does that mean?
It means measuring the likelihood that there will be a new undiscovered vulnerability in
this component and the impact that that would have downstream, right?
Measurement is essential.
If we can't measure whether we're improving the overall risk in that chain and the collective
risk in our use of that software, we're not going to know whether the interventions that
we're trying are actually meaningful.
So you've got to measure it.
You've got to then think about this sequence of carrots and defaults and sticks to eventually
get this stuff adopted if it's any good, right?
And then finally as part of this culture change, are there things that we should be learning
as open source developers, things that we should be thinking about as a professional
type of operation, like as a diligence of care, as something that as engineers and that
term used to have to go and take a certification exam to call yourself an engineer, right?
And that instilled a sense of professionalism in that industry that led to bridges that
didn't fall down when you hired an engineer to design it.
We need a little bit of the same professionalism in software development across the board,
not just open source.
And here are a set of resources that might help us from a security point of view be better
developers.
So collectively we want to put these pieces together.
And we've got all sorts of projects in working groups, projects organized by thematically
related working groups, a working group on best practices and documenting those and advocating
for those, a working group on identifying security threats, understanding, you know,
relatively speaking, what are the areas to really worry about in the areas that, you
know, might represent low threat.
How do we think about supply chain integrity?
Like that chart I showed, how do you get those pieces, those opportunities for bugs to be
inserted to just be locked down and hardened?
How do we think about, you know, the CVE system is not great, frankly.
It's nowhere near perfect.
It's not great for trying to automate and understand given this collection of software
I use, where might the vulnerabilities, where are the known vulnerabilities and how easy
is it to remediate them?
Are there known vulnerabilities that just don't matter because I'm not using them?
And so there's an entire working group focused on vulnerability disclosures and on the vulnerability
system that has a bunch of new ideas for this, but also developed content to try to help
developers simply be better at coordinating vulnerability disclosures and updates.
We've got another working group focused on once you've identified those critical projects,
well, securing and identifying critical projects.
And that's where we've defined the criticality score.
We've done some work with Harvard Business School to understand quantitatively how are
things being used by enterprises and where might the next log for JB lurking, so to speak.
And then one of the most important things we've got here is we've pulled together the
architects and the people responsible for product at many of the major security repositories,
NPM, PyPy, Maven Central, because if we're going to get anything improved throughout
the chain, you need to involve the last couple hops of each of the nodes in that chain, which
are the distribution points.
And there are things you can do there to encourage more secure alternatives and eventually have
the stick to say, well, no, we're not going to accept, you know, things like you might
need to enforce two-factor auth for the more popular packages, right, which has been controversial,
to say the least, but is one of those things where it's like somewhere in that adoption
curve we need to start nudging people into a more secure direction.
But all of these pieces work together.
And if you are an open source software maintainer, what I'm going to walk through now is a set
of specific things coming out of the OpenSSF that I'd love you to adopt.
I'm not going to be able to talk about all the features of each, just given time.
But we've come up the very best starting point you can start to consume.
The very first piece of thing that you can get from the OpenSSF are two concise guides,
one that we've developed for evaluating open source code.
When you're out there looking at packages and you're trying to figure out is this community
likely to have processes and is there likely to be an undiscovered vulnerability lurking
in this code that I'm about to use, right?
Is this a well-engineered, well-maintained active community that has adopted the right
practices and the like, or is this a one-off that was developed by one person in a hurry,
thrown up on a repo and not well-maintained?
I mean, we've got some ad hoc cues that we can use that most of us have, but how many
of you use GitHub stars as your basis for deciding whether something is probably secure
enough or not?
I'm going to guess probably too many of you.
So there's a bunch of subjective criteria that you can use.
The flip side of that is if you are a maintainer and you are pushing code out, here are the
signals you can send to your consumers of that software that show that you're taking
this stuff seriously, right?
And it's a bunch of best practices, adopting multi-factor auth, taking the courses on secure
software development, using a specific combination of tools in the CI pipeline, thinking about
how do you get to the point of doing rapid updates without throwing curve balls to your
users because you change APIs all the time?
What's the number one reason people don't update is that they assume, even in minor
point releases, something is going to break because somebody took an API and marked it
not only deprecated but removed it or changed a field that just sends things sideways or
changed behavior in a way that they thought was compatible but was not.
How do you get to the point where you can have more rapid updates and make it easier
for your end users to pick those up?
Now, some of these ideas were elaborated upon in a course that we built within openSSF and
have offered for free now through the Linux Foundation's training department called Secure
Software Development Fundamentals.
This has been translated to Japanese.
It's been translated to a bunch of other languages, Chinese, Arabic, and Hebrew.
And this is 14 to 18 hours worth of content that primarily talks about anti-patterns,
right?
What does it mean to not trust user contributed input?
What are some of the other common gotchas that have led to security vulnerabilities
and breaches that as a most software developers are self-taught.
Some people take courses, but even most university undergraduate level courses on computer science
don't really teach about vulnerabilities and about common mistakes as well as they could.
So this is something we think anybody who is writing code for a living or even for a
hobby and you're giving this to somebody else to run, you should probably take this course.
And the flip side of this is you might want to look and see whether the developers who
are working on a thing you really care about have taken this course.
You can get a badge that certifies you've taken the course, you've answered a basic
quiz, it's not honorous, and it's free, but we hope it's something that helps substantiate
that.
Somebody has a bit more knowledgeable about this than they otherwise would be.
Another part of this is something called the best practices badge.
This is a checklist that's fairly extensive of the things that open source projects can
do to show that they take steps, they have a security team, they distribute things over
HTTPS.
I mean, some of these things that seem pretty basic and each individual one is no guarantee
of its security whole free code, but collectively can represent that this is a project that
takes security more seriously.
And studies have shown that the projects that have better scores tend to have fewer CVEs
over the subsequent months and years.
Now there's an automated tool for those projects because the best practices badge is something
that requires the maintainers to fill out kind of a questionnaire, a checklist.
There's some automation to that, but it's really just used to check the answers that
the maintainers give.
There's a different approach, which is much more of a scanning kind of approach, called
the OpenSSF security scorecards that automatically goes and scans repositories.
It's done a first wave scan of a million different repos, and you can trigger it to
do an updated scan if you've made changes to your repo, but it takes dozens of different
heuristics.
Things like do you have binary artifacts you've checked into your GitHub repo?
That's probably not a great thing.
Storing binaries and repos, I don't know how many of you might disagree, but for reproducibility,
maybe, but use your package manager to get your binary packages, checking it into source
code control, opens the door to things that are not scrutinizable inside your source code
system.
Branch protection, CI tests, do you have the best practices badge?
Have you done code reviews before code is merged, or does everybody just have commit
proofs, right?
Do you have contributors from more than one organization?
Some of this adopts the chaos metrics, which looks at community health, but some of this
as well are things like do your automated tests, do they call fuzzing libraries?
You game a lot of these tests, right?
Again, none of this is proof that your code is defract free, but collectively what this
can do, along with these other kind of measures of risk, is develop a credit score for a project.
The scores in scorecard actually do correlate to lower CVEs.
There was a study done by Sonotype who looked at the projects that had been scored and discovered
that after receiving a score, there's a couple different categories within the security scorecards,
so they really were interested on which of those correlate most strongly to lower number
of CVEs.
That was an interesting outcome, and this is going to be used to refine the security
scorecards continuously over time to have them reflect the changing landscape of some
of the better run projects.
That's a big deal, and it's something that some projects have picked up as a leaderboard
tool.
The Cloud Native Compute Foundation ran a competition recently called the CLO Monitor,
on the sidelines for a month of their main KubeCon event, where they got the maintainers
of the different projects to commit to have a floor on the score.
I think it was six or seven out of ten for all of their projects, and have a competition
between them, and with rewards for the maintainers who got their projects highest on the scorecard.
Really cool to see.
All of that was about measurement.
This next set of things are about tools that help actually harden the software supply chain,
so to speak.
One that you've heard, no doubt, talked about before, so I won't dwell on it too much,
is something called SigStore.
SigStore is a software signing service.
It's a set of software that are clients into that service.
It's a protocol, because it's a certain way of signing it that's an alternative to GPG
signing of code.
It's a recognition that we haven't really signed artifacts to the supply chain, pervasively,
except for at the very end.
When you do an apt-get install, it checks the GPG signatures on each package.
That is helpful, even above and beyond the fact that you're sending stuff over TLS.
The rest of upstream, so often, people are just pulling off of NPM, pulling off of package
hosting, other packages just stored on bare websites, where even validating the hash of
that and fetching it over HTTPS doesn't prove the connection between the developers behind
that code and the binary you have.
There have been examples of people registering NPM packages that are named the same thing
as a GitHub repo, kind of a typo squatting kind of attack, as a way to try to cause you
to inadvertently pick up the wrong piece of code.
Obviously, even sites like GitHub can be hacked, could be compromised, and you don't want your
enterprise to be compromised if GitHub's compromised, frankly.
This is a tool to try to prevent that kind of thing.
It logs all of this to essentially a distributed ledger, a public database, using short-lived
keys, so you don't have to worry, like PGP requires you to, to have private keys that
you battle and keep private for a long time.
Just like Let's Encrypt, this is based on short-lived keys and an easy way to reprovision
those keys.
I won't go into much more depth on that.
There's a few other things I'll point you to, something called Salsa, which is for supply
chain level attestations, basically a way to distinguish between those things in your
chain that are built to a higher degree of rigor than other things that are not.
We've got another, something back on the best practices working group, which is a guide
to coordinated vulnerability disclosure.
The next time there's a team, say they're not associated with Apache, say they're not
associated with a major foundation who discover that they've got a pretty nasty bug and their
code is used pretty widely, well, who do they turn to to understand how to manage a coordinated
disclosure process, how to not get in trouble for keeping something a little bit quiet while
they come up with the right fix, and then how do you evaluate who potentially to notify
ahead of time so that you're upgrading enough of the internet before something becomes more
widely known.
By the way, even if that sounds controversial, like there's some people who say, including
the CRA, like if you know about a bug, you should tell everybody immediately.
Well, does anyone remember the hack that almost brought down the internet, the DNS cache poisoning
bug in Bind, that if that had become widely known before the root name servers had been
updated, would have set us back so far, we would have had to revert to Etsy host files
to be able to connect on the internet again and get started.
The need for coordinated vulnerability disclosure might be somewhat controversial, but has become
much more widely accepted today than ever before.
One thing we're going to do in the OpenSSF is pull this all together into a single dashboard
to understand that risk, understand how open source projects compare apples to apples, and
really as a tool to help the maintainers on those projects get better at what they do.
But also, frankly, if we can help enterprises understand where the risk lies in their use
of code, if they can start making more choices based more on the security of that code than
necessarily what is the most features or the most users, then we can start to, I think,
understand industry in a better direction, somewhere between the carrots and the defaults
kind of step of getting folks to adopt stuff.
I do also want to throw out one of the biggest efforts that we have under the OpenSSF is
this thing called the Alpha Omega project, which is independently funded and staffed,
and it's got two pieces to it.
The Alpha side is going and helping the largest open source foundations out there with the
most critical needs basically develop better security practices, develop security teams,
go and do some proactive third-party audits, but develop this muscle, this capability that
hopefully persists.
We'll go and we'll fund some of these projects for a couple years, and our hope is that at
some point the stakeholders in that community take on that funding themselves.
The companies who are depending upon that see the value of this kind of proactive investment
and continue it forward so we can move on to the next set of projects.
The Omega side of that is trying to set up scanning infrastructure for the most important
10,000 open source code bases to look for new kinds of vulnerabilities, to ask, in theory,
this Gindi LDAP bug in Log4J that led to this thing, is it novel?
If it's novel, can we systematically scan for other projects that might be vulnerable
to the same thing?
In some cases, could we even submit proactive pull requests to go and close those?
An example of another organization that has done this recently, I don't know if folks
saw this announcement by Trellix last week, where they went and discovered 60,000, 61,000
open source projects that used the Python tar file module in an insecure way.
This is actually an old CVE from 2007 that the CPython devs have refused to fix because
of a claim that the only way to fix it would be to break POSIX, so we can have that debate
some other time.
They went and found 61,000 projects that have a vulnerability because they used it unsafely.
They didn't sanitize inputs to it.
They went and proactively issued 61,000 pull requests on those projects to fix this code.
Doing this at scale is tremendously hard, but they did it.
So far, after a month and a half of having those pull requests up, do you want to guess
how many projects have actually accepted that pull request?
Really push the button to make their project more secure?
1,000.
We still have a culture problem here.
We still have an incentives problem, even when you've given them this gift.
It might not happen.
We're really towards the end of time.
I just want to say we've recognized that, as the point I made earlier, you've got to
show up.
If you're an organization that cares about increasing the security of code, you've got
to be prepared to invest time and ultimately money to make that happen.
You cannot demand that open source developers simply be better.
You've got to go and help them do that and spend that in.
One of the things we've done at the OpenSSF is, over the last year, we developed an overarching
plan to go and address 10 systematic weaknesses in open source and put together essentially
business plans for each of them that would call for some funding to pay for the core
of a project on the presumption that we could leverage volunteers around the periphery to
try and have some of this impact.
I won't go into detail of what that is too much.
We call it the security mobilization plan.
It includes things like $40 million to go and close security holes and some other things.
It includes setting up an emergency response team for development teams that are understaffed
who find a vulnerability to going and doing new scanning, to driving adoption of SigStore
and other standards.
It's pretty comprehensive.
It might seem like $150 million, which is the number we came up with after saying, what
could we do that would be lean, that would be low-hanging fruit but actually have a big
impact.
We came up with this two-year number of 150.
It might sound like a lot of money.
It's certainly more than the Linux Foundation has.
It's more than any of the other major open source foundations or even frankly Google
and Microsoft have to spend on this, arguably.
There's a larger number out there that I want to focus on, which is $700 million, which
is the fine that the US Federal Trade Commission levied on Equifax for the 2007 data breach
caused in part by their use of unpatched open source software, Apache Struts.
To the industry, making the case that we collectively could pool our funds to go do this should
be easy.
We've been out there trying to do it, have these conversations, doing it at a time when
the economic headwinds have not been in our favor, but still the kinds of conversations
we're having are very positive.
Things like seeing the Sovereign Tech Fund in Germany pop up and be able to fund not
just some improvements in open source code but security enhancements and the like has
been really positive to see.
It should be a model for other countries to go and do this, but frankly, insurance companies
as well as banks, as well as all these other industries that have benefited from open source
software and haven't put things really in.
Again, we're kind of out of time, so I won't go too much into depth.
I do want to emphasize tooling around the SBOM space is an important part of this as
well and being able to paint this overarching picture about how SBOMs, signed artifacts,
software level attestations, and all these other things could have a positive impact,
but we've got to show up and not just tell projects to adopt this, but weave it into
the development tools as defaults so we can bring industry along.
We've launched this with US government back in May.
We had a similar meeting in Japan in July.
We've had conversations in Singapore and with people in other countries, and hopefully we'll
see something here in Europe along the same lines.
But let me just wrap up by saying there are attacks on the integrity of open source software
that are increasingly disruptive and require us to work together to do things a little
bit different than we have before.
It's not that we were reckless or careless or didn't care about security, most of us
at least.
There's some open source projects that definitely have been problems, but there's simply more
that we can do and more that people who care about this and are starting to use open source
software in French nuclear power plants can do to help this space be better.
There's some specific steps, as I've talked about, and that's kind of why we're here at
the OpenSSF, and we're here to help, but we also need your help as developers.
It'd be very easy to see what we do as being the enterprises trying to make open source
boring and make it all about checklists, and I'll concede that, but we're also here to
try to say if we're going to shift the landscape, how do we work with the open source community
to do that?
Because we are part of the open source community, how we collectively take some action to make
it less likely that our next winter holidays will be ruined.
And with that, thank you.
I think I left about 22 seconds for questions.
Okay.
Five minutes.
Okay, so we've got about five minutes for questions.
So let me start by reading one question online.
There was a question whether OpenSSF allows for anonymous reporting, which could be without
disclosing the reporter, because that would be useful for companies fearing backlash or
high expectations regarding what they have to do.
So why bother reporting if they're just going to get into trouble?
Why not just keep it not release anything?
So making it possible to report anonymously would possibly improve that.
So the question is about anonymous reporting of bugs, and would that be helpful?
Well, I will submit, open source software has benefited tremendously by the fact that
you aren't badging in to GitHub with your national ID, right?
You are able to be pseudonymous.
And you can use Satoshi Nakamoto as a famous example of that, whatever, right?
But most of us, or many of us, have probably created login IDs that have nothing to do
with our real name, right?
And open source software is one of the last remaining places where you can actually productively
collaborate with people who aren't fully identifying who they are, right?
You're basing it on their quality of their contribution.
And that's a really essential thing to try to preserve.
And whether it's in reporting bugs or even collaborating on code, we should fight to
preserve the right to be pseudonymous, or even anonymous, if you want to call it that,
in the development of code and in the fixing, reporting of bugs and the fixing of bugs.
So I'm committed to trying to make sure we don't get to know your developer kinds of
rules like some countries have started to call for.
Thanks for the really interesting talk.
I have a question about the economics of your proposed solution.
It's not that you can pay developers out of the blue to do these tasks.
You have to pull them away from other work.
So you have to pay them actually more to let all the other work rest and focus on security.
So this requires a major shift.
Have you factored this into your proposal?
No, I haven't thought about having to pay not just for the work that we're doing, but
paying for work that wouldn't be done because we're paying people to do the work.
I think most of the time developers aren't able to work on open source code because they
have to work on proprietary code to pay the bills.
And so I think there's a lot of capacity out there for us if we do have funds to be able
to pay for the kind of work that needs to be done.
I also don't think we're talking about taking away from other software development work
that's about adding features or fixing bugs.
This is about bringing new types of organizations like the software auditor community to look
at to find new bugs.
So it's not a big deal.
And frankly, $150 million, even if that were all spent on software developers, would be
a drop in the bucket compared to the total amount that is spent on developer salaries
out there.
So that isn't where I'm at.
But it's a good question.
Thank you for that.
Do you have more questions from the public?
There was one question in the chat about how is the OpenSSL collaborating with OWASP?
Is that a collaboration there or not?
So there's a question in chat on how is the OpenSSL collaborating with OWASP.
So Andrew Van Der Stock, who's the executive director of OWASP, is on our board.
There's a lot that OWASP does in terms of education and certification and community
building that absolutely is essential.
And so we look for ways to work together and we'd like to avoid overlap with what they
do.
But yeah, that's about it.
We're very complimentary to their efforts and I think they think the same.
Okay.
Anybody else?
Hello.
We are in Europe here.
You have spoken about different conferences all over the world in Singapore.
But do you have something in Europe?
We've had lots of conversations in Europe.
There are many OSPOs starting in Europe who are interested in this.
And I do think OSPOs are an interesting lever point in being able to get standards adopted
around security, being able to present measures of risk to be thinking about all these kinds
of things.
So have had interesting conversations that way, have not had the kind of full-throated
engagement around this that we've seen with the United States and with some other countries.
So I would like to see more.
But frankly, even those other countries haven't yet put money into this.
They're kind of waiting for certain political cycles to make their way through.
But I know we've inspired some action.
Again, I do want to cite the sovereign tech fund out of Germany as not specifically a
security fund, but the right kind of thing for these countries to be doing.
So anyways, thank you for the question.
Anything else?
That's exactly how much time we've had.
So thank you again, Brian.
Thanks all.
Over and out.
Thank you.