Okay, then our next talk is by Fraser.
Over to you.
Okay, thank you.
So I'm going to talk about user namespaces and delegation of control of C groups in container
orchestration systems.
So yeah, container and container standards.
This is the container's dev room, I think hopefully most people should have some idea.
Talk about Kubernetes and OpenShift, user namespaces and C groups, and then a demo of
a system B-based workload on Kubernetes and more specifically OpenShift.
So a container is a process isolation and confinement abstraction.
Most commonly it uses operating system level virtualisation where the process is running
in the container using the same kernel as the host system.
Examples of this include FreeBSD jails and Solaris zones as well as Linux containers.
And the container image is not a container, the container image just defines the file
system contents for a container and some metadata suggesting what process should be run, what
user ID it should run underneath and so on.
On Linux containers use a combination of the following technologies, so namespaces, process
ID namespaces, mount namespaces, network namespaces, et cetera, to restrict what the process running
in the container can see.
The container may have restricted capabilities or a sec comp profile that limits which system
calls or operating system features it can use.
There may be SE Linux or App Armor confinement and it can use C groups for resource limits.
Not necessarily all of these are used at the same time, it depends on the implementation.
The Open Container Initiative defines standards around containers in the free software ecosystem
and its runtime specification in particular defines a low-level runtime interface for
containers that is not just for Linux containers but it defines the runtime semantics for Linux,
Solaris containers, Windows containers, virtual machines.
And so there are a bunch of implementations of the runtime spec including RunC, the reference
implementation, C run and CART containers which is a virtual machine-based container
runtime.
The OCI runtime spec has a JSON configuration, there's a link to an example.
It defines or lets you define the mounts, what process to be executed, its environment,
life cycle hooks, so extra code to run when the container is created, destroyed, started,
stopped.
The Linux specific capabilities that can be controlled via the OCI runtime spec include
the capabilities, that's the kernel feature capabilities, namespaces, the C group, the
system controls that should be set for that container, the seccomp profile and so on.
This is what an example runtime specification looks like, so it has a process structure
which includes a field for the user ID and the group ID.
It has this Linux structure which defines the Linux specific attributes for this container
and one of those attributes is the namespaces list which defines a list of the different
namespaces that should be used or should be newly created for that container.
Kubernetes is a container orchestration platform, has a declarative configuration system and
it integrates with many different cloud providers.
Anyone not know what Kubernetes is in the room?
The container is an isolated or confined process or process tree, a pod is one or more related
containers that together constitute an application of some sort, so it might be an HTTP server
and a database to encapsulate the entire web application.
A namespace in Kubernetes terminology is not a namespace in Linux kernel terminology,
this is just an object scope and authorization scope for a bunch of objects in the Kubernetes
data store, so if you have a particular team or project in your organisation you might
deploy all of the Kubernetes applications in a single namespace.
And a node is a machine in the cluster where pods are executed, there are different kinds
of nodes, there are control plane nodes, there are worker nodes where the actual business
applications run.
Kuberlet is the agent that executes pods on nodes, so there's a scheduling system, the
scheduler will, when a pod is created, decide what node that pod should run on and Kuberlet
is the agent on the node that takes the pod specification and turns it into a container
running on that node.
The Kubernetes terminology uses the term sandbox, that's an isolation or confinement mechanism
and there's one sandbox per pod, so there could be multiple containers running in the
sandbox.
And the container runtime interface defines how Kuberlet actually starts and stops the
containers or the sandboxes.
So cryo is one implementation of the container runtime interface, that's what's used in OpenShift,
there's also containerd, that's used in some other distributions of Kubernetes.
So visualising this, the whole box is one Kubernetes node, the Kuberlet has the gRPC
client to talk to a CRI runtime, the CRI runtime does something and containers appear.
So we could instantiate the container runtime interface implementation as cryo and then
we can see that cryo talks to an OCI runtime, it uses exec to use the OCI runtime and we
can go one step further and say that the OCI runtime implementation will be runc and this
is the setup that we use on OpenShift.
This is a pod spec in YAML format, so we have kind pod, the specification has a list of
containers, in this case there's one, the container has a name, defines the image to
use, the command to execute environment variables that should be set and so on.
OpenShift or OpenShift container platform is an enterprise ready Kubernetes container platform,
it's commercially supported by Red Hat, there's a community upstream distribution called OKD,
as I mentioned before, it uses cryo and runc and the latest stable release is 4.12, I think
that came out just a week ago or so.
And its default, the default way that it creates containers is it uses se Linux and namespaces
to confine the processes.
Each namespace gets assigned a unique user ID range and the processes for the pods in
that namespace have to run in those host UIDs.
You can circumvent this using the run as user security context constraint, but that is not
a good idea, you don't want your containers running as root on the container host because
if they escape the sandbox then your cluster got owned.
So this is the why of user namespaces, user namespaces, we're talking now Linux kernel,
user namespaces can be used to improve the workload isolation and the confinement of
the pods in your cluster.
They can also be used to run applications that require or assume that they're running
as specific user IDs or to phrase this a different way, you can drag your legacy applications
kicking and screaming into the cloud and get the benefits of all of the orchestration and
networking support that these platforms like Kubernetes and OpenShift can give you while
still running that workload securely.
In other words, trick it to believe it is running as root.
And there have been a bunch of CVS in Kubernetes and the broader container orchestration ecosystem
arising from sandbox escapes where user namespaces would have prevented the vulnerability or
severely limited or curtailed its impact.
So visualising a user namespace, we can have two separate containers with a user namespace
mapping of UID range 0 to 65535 inside the container's user namespace to a range of unprivileged
user IDs in the host's user ID namespace.
So the processes running in the container believe that they are running as, for example,
root UID0 or some other privileged user ID when in fact it's running as UID200,000 on
the host and unprivileged user ID.
Escape the sandbox and you're still an unprivileged user on the host.
So in Linux there's some references to some man pages about user namespaces and how to
use them.
The critical thing is the unshare system call which is how you create and use the user namespace.
In the OCI runtime specification there are some fields and again this is Linux specific
so it's inside the Linux specific part of that configuration that you can specify that
a user namespace should be created or used for that container and you can specify the
mappings of how do we map the container's user ID range to the host user ID range.
These namespaces were implemented, before they were implemented in Kubernetes upstream,
we did it in Cryo.
It first shipped in OpenShift 4.7 but it required a considerable amount of additional configuration
of the cluster to use it and since OpenShift 4.10 you've been able to use it out of the
box.
You do still have to opt in using annotations on a per pod basis.
It requires the NEU ID security context constraint or an equivalent privileged security context
constraint in order to admit the pod because the admission machinery does not yet understand
about user namespaces.
So the pod spec says I want to run as user ID zero and the admission machinery says no
way.
We need to circumvent that for the time being but the workload itself will run in the user
namespace.
And depending on the workload it may still require some additional cluster configuration.
So the annotations to opt in, you can say I o.OpenShift.builder is true, that activates
a particular Cryo what we call a workload, basically an alternative bunch of runtime
settings and then we use the user NS mode annotation to specify that we want an arbitrary
user namespace of size 6.536.
So that will allocate you a contiguous host UID range for that container and map it to
unprivileged host user IDs.
In the Kubernetes upstream it took a bit longer to get user namespace support and it's still
a work in progress but the initial support was delivered in Kubernetes 1.25 and that
version is what we've moved to in OpenShift 4.12 so you can now use the first class user
namespace support in OpenShift.
It is an alpha feature so it's not enabled by default, you have to turn it on with a
feature gate and at the moment it only supports ephemeral volume types so empty config maps,
it's no persistent volume support yet.
You opt in by putting host user's false in your pod spec and currently it gives you a
fixed mapping size of 6.536 that will be unique to that pod.
It is hoped that a later phase will deliver support for the additional volume types.
The reason we didn't have them is the complexity around ID mapped mounts and how to adapt the
volume mounts to understand how to map the user IDs between the host UID namespace and
the container's user namespace.
There's also very simple heuristics around the ID range assignment, as I mentioned it's
a fixed size of 6.536 that limits the number of pods that you could run in user namespaces
on a given node.
There are still some other mount point and file ownership issues, for example with the
C group FS.
That takes us to the C group's topic.
OpenShift creates a unique C group for each container and it also creates a C group namespace
so that the container in the CFS C group mount only sees its namespace.
Inside the container CFS C group points to CFS C group slash a whole bunch of stuff specific
to that container in the host's file system.
If you want to run a system D based workload, system D needs right access to the C group
FS.
But by default the C group FS will be mounted read only.
So the solution, we modify the container runtime to the C group to the container's process
UID.
So that is we chain it to the host UID corresponding to UID zero in the container's user namespace.
But first before we did this in an ad hoc basis we engaged with the open container initiative
to define the semantics for C group ownership in a container.
Those proposals were workshopped and accepted and after that we were able to implement those
semantics in run C.
So what are the semantics?
The container's C group will be choned to the host UID matching the process UID in the
container's user namespace if and only if the node is using C group speed two and the
container has its own C group namespace and the C group FS is mounted read right.
So only the C group directory itself and the files mentioned in Cyskernel C group delegate
are choned.
These are the ones that are safe to delegate to a subprocess.
And the container runtime, if that file Cyskernel C group delegate is defined then it will read
that file and only chone the files mentioned there.
So it can respond to the evolution of the kernel where new C group nodes may come and
go.
Some of them may be safe to delegate.
Some of them may not.
In OpenShift C group speed two is not yet the default when you deploy a cluster but it does
work and it is supported.
And to activate the C group choned semantics that I just explained we still require an
annotation in the pod spec.
So let's do a demo.
Here's a cluster I prepared earlier.
And we can see new project test, okay, OC create user test.
Maybe test already exists, okay.
We'll just use test.
So we can now, oh, I'll show you the pod I'm going to create.
Cat pod nginx host users false.
So this is a pod spec.
Let's get some syntax.
This is going to run nginx.
It's a system D based workload.
So it's a Fedora system that will come up and system D will run and it will start nginx.
We setting host users false so that it will run in the user name space.
I have already enabled the feature flag on this cluster.
There's that annotation for the C group choned.
And the name of the pod will be nginx.
So let's create that.
So OC as test create dash F. Okay.
Fingers crossed.
Okay.
So we'll say OC admin policy add role to user edit.
Let's try that again.
So the pod has been created.
And we'll just check its status to see which node it is running on.
And it hasn't yet started.
So we don't have a container ID for it yet.
But in the upper pane, I'll get a shell on that worker node.
Okay.
Pod is now running.
So we can run cry control, inspect, container ID.
And we'll just pull out the PID.
So this is our PID.
Now if we have a look at the user ID map for this process.
Okay, so here we see that we have a user name space with a user ID mapping of size 65536.
Which is mapping user ID zero in the container's user name space to user ID 131072 in the host
user name space.
And now we can look at the processes that are actually running there.
So we'll do p grep, double dash n s says show me everything with the same set of name spaces
as this process ID.
And then I'll just pipe that to PS.
Let's print the user, the PID and the command.
Sorting by PID.
Okay.
So we can see that this container is running, well, in it.
And then a bunch of system D processes.
And then eventually, nginx.
And these are running under 131072.
Yeah.
132071.
So these are running as various user IDs in the container's user name space.
And those are being mapped to the host user ID name space as these PIDs.
If we look at the logs, we can see that it looks like a regular system D system has come
up.
Indeed, it has.
And let's see.
I see.
Maybe we'll get a shell on the pod.
And, yeah, if we have a look at what is the container's view of the processes that are
running, it sees that system D is running as root or other system D related users inside
the container's user name space.
nginx is running as the nginx user in that container's user name space.
But as we saw, these are all mapped to unprivileged host user IDs in the host user name space.
So that concludes the demo.
Here's links to various resources.
I have a lot of blog posts and this and related topics.
So you can hit my blog and just look at the container's tag.
A recording of a demo or a similar demo.
Slightly earlier version.
And to KEP 127, which is where all of the discussion around how to do the upstream support
for user name spaces in Kubernetes.
All of that discussion happened there.
The OCI runtime spec is referenced there.
And that's it.
So I think there is time for some questions.
So please stay seated until 25 so we can ask questions.
Okay.
There is one in the back.
Do you want to read the one from the chat first?
There's a question in chat.
I don't see it anymore.
It says, why would I want to run system D in a container?
It's cool that it's possible with user name spaces, but I lack an idea for a use case.
So the use case is you have a complicated legacy workload that runs under system D or
makes assumptions about the environment it runs in, the user IDs that the different components
are running as.
You've got two choices.
One is to spend a whole lot of upfront engineering effort to break up that application and containerize
it and make it quote unquote a cloud native application which is expensive and typically
has a long lead time or you can just wrap that whole application up in a container and
run it securely, hopefully, in a container orchestration platform and get the benefit
of all of the scaling, networking, observability features that the orchestration platform gives
you without having to spend that effort to bust your application into 100 pieces.
So I would say that that is the use case.
I think it's a compelling one.
If you were building applications today, you certainly wouldn't do that, but there are
100 million legacy applications out there and people don't want to break them up and
change them.
Hi.
Thanks for the talk.
I'm actually doing this right now at my company, but basically the container is running as
privileged.
So that's why it can access a C group.
Doesn't use user namespaces, just runs as privileged.
So I was wondering if using this method you could set a memory max, memory high or other
values for some processes running in the container, I mean?
I'm sorry, I couldn't hear the question because it's rather echoey.
Sorry.
Yeah.
So can you set memory high, memory max, values, CPU affinities, like all these kinds of things
you would set in the C group usually?
Can you set them from this particular use case of C groups in a container?
Yes, absolutely, because the container still has its own C group namespace, so all of the
standard C group confinement and resource limit capabilities can be used.
Okay.
I guess I got confused by the list of values that were allowed to do a list in the previous
slide.
There was a restricted list of values.
Yeah, yeah, so those were just the particular files that need to be chined in order for
safe delegation of control of that branch of the C group hierarchy to another process.
So you can still set on the C group directory all of the limits and the container won't
be able to change those because those will not be chined to the container's process UID.
Okay, thank you.
So I have a question regarding the CSFSC group CSH own.
So you mentioned it's going to be changed to the UID of the process container.
Can you do that if you want to have several ports to run their own system D?
So, because it seems, is it in the sub-tree of the C group hierarchy that you do that
or at the top level?
Is your question around can you do it in a nested way?
No, not in a nested way.
You have three different ports which each port needs their own system.
Yes, yes, absolutely.
So if I created more pods in my demo, you would see that they would then be mapped to
different host UID ranges.
So the limit is only how many of the range allocations can you fit into the host UID
range.
So the limit will be a little under 65536 because the size of the host UID range on
Linux by default is 2 to the 32.
I think we have time for one more question.
Thank you all for your patience.
Thank you, Fraser.
I just wanted to know if v2, v2 by default in OpenShift is on the roadmap yet and whether
or not there's any sort of estimated time scale for that?
Yes, it is.
So there is a plan to eventually move to secret v2 as the default.
I don't know the exact time frame.
Thank you so much for your talk.
Thank you all for your patience.
I know this sounds weird, but your patience is on me.