Our next talk is by Peter.
He's going to talk about database in a container to debas on Kubernetes.
I hope I pronounced this correctly.
Yeah.
Okay.
Hello, everyone.
You hear me well?
Okay.
Cool.
So, let me ask first.
How many of you folks have been involved with open source in 90s?
Anyone remember those days?
So, well, I was.
And for me, in those times, right, you remember that open source was, well, quite different
than today, right?
You needed a lot of elbows greased, right?
I remember how you have to, you know, download the source packages, maybe patch them some
way to make sure it works if your particular compiler, right, and, you know, figure out
all the libraries, dependencies, all this kind of stuff to make it work, right?
And you could feel that certain pride for just installing some applications.
And since that, we had this never-ending move to simplicity.
Making it possible to run open source software more and more easily, right?
So, from that, download sources, patch and compile.
We had a wonderful invention of TarGZ binaries and install script.
Anybody remembers those?
No?
So, I'm do, right?
And then they go with like packages of dependencies.
And then those have been in repositories, right?
And in the end, they're coming to say, hey, you know what, now we don't really care about
the disk space anymore.
So we just, you know, jumble it all together as a, you know, docker or snap packages, right,
with no dependencies, right?
So we got a lot of that move to their simplicity.
And obviously, that is, you know, fantastic and convenient.
One of those ways, which is very popular, is docker.
And a question in our talk, as it relates to the database and what is my background,
is to what extent you can and should use database with those technologies?
And if you look at the docker, we use that actually quite a lot in particular in test
and dev environment, right?
What is wonderful about docker, if you want, several database versions, right, or wherever
you can, install them very easily on the same node, which don't conflict with each other,
right there in, you know, your classical Linux operating system, if you want to install,
you know, MySQL, 556.7 at the same time, because you maybe want to make sure your application
is working in the firm.
But good luck, right?
They all conflict on the shared files and so on and so forth.
Dockers enable that, right?
And that is absolutely fantastic.
And also, you can use solutions like a docker compose and bunch of hours if you want to,
you know, deploy your application and, you know, database, it depends on in a docker
containers, make it very easily, very nicely.
Now if you look at docker in production, though, it is also possible, though we actually see
less than that.
Some of cancels come from overhead, and I would say these are mostly unfounded those
days, but if you really, like Google, you can still find some articles saying like some
scary stories about docker and database being absolutely horrible, right?
But also you need to take care of, in this case, is a little bit of extra complexity,
which I know especially a lot of not-docker experts have been beaten by.
Like you have to have your database on a data volume for best results.
Otherwise, you can remove your data container, right, and boom, all your data is gone.
Now that is a very different experience compared to, let's say, uninstalling the RPM or depth
package on Linux, where you can uninstall the database package your data remains so you
can install a different one, right, in docker, unless you have the data stored in a separate
volume, you will trash your data, right, to give if you're moving their container.
So in production, that is somewhere you need a lot of monitoring and observability, okay.
Okay, hopefully that will settle.
So if you look at the introduction, we often need some observability, right, and monitoring,
which initially lacked support for docker, which I think got a lot better those days.
So what is the state of open source databases with docker?
If you think about that, what most open source databases out there have official docker images.
For those which don't, you will find a variety of unofficial docker images out there, right,
so you can pretty much run it everywhere.
It is very commonly deployed for test and dev.
You will, if you look at the docker stats, you will see like hundreds of millions of
downloads, like a docker pools for many, many of them.
Though I would say in production, it is limited, right.
I know some companies say, hey, we have deployed our production with docker with, let's say,
a custom orchestration system, but I would not say that is very common.
You know, at your corner, for our software, for database, we support, we essentially do
the same thing.
We provide their docker packages for everything.
So if you are just sticking to docker, to pure docker, what problems are not solved
very well in this environment?
The third thing, I think, the most important one is, you know, date two operations.
The databases are interesting, right, in a way, unlike the application where you often
can say, hey, you know what, let's just, you know, tear it down and redeploy it from scratch,
right, and that is the approach which is increasingly often taken, right, instead of just, you know,
modifying their application right well.
You cannot really do that with a database.
You know, database is something which has to retain the data, not lose any transactions
which have been committed and so on and so forth, and that means what majority of complexity
and majority of the life in database happens is what's called day two, right, after you
have the deployed, right.
And docker-wise simplifies your installation, does not do anything really to solve all that
needs to.
Upgrade database, you don't really have the ability, and so on and so forth, right.
Also we can see what a lot of database management problems for real production database have
to be done in context of a cluster because every real production database will require
high availability and that is cannot be done by the single instance, right, that has to
be some sort of distributed cluster and docker doesn't really help us in this regard.
So what does?
Well, as you may have guessed, that would be a Kubernetes, right, really there are,
there have been some other container orchestration system for years, but I think you can say
with confidence is what docker has won at this level and in this regard it has a, you
know, largest, largest market share.
So where do we see the state of Kubernetes and databases?
Well, the relationship has been kind of complicated through years, why?
Because Kubernetes initially was designed for a stateless application, right, and if
you're saying, well, something is designed for a stateless application, you can say,
using that for databases, are you freaking crazy?
The database are the opposite of stateless, right, the database where we're supposed to
have our states, right, and I think that is something which has been getting improvement,
right, and now the Kubernetes is actually quite capable to run databases as well.
But that wasn't always the case, right, I think this is interesting to look at this
tweet which is what, like almost like four years ago, right, at that time, which in this
case, KC Hightower, which is one of the very, well, you know, the expert and the third leader
in the Kubernetes space, was not very sure, right, about running databases on Kubernetes,
right, well, let's see what has changed and look at some stats.
Now over the last few years, in the Kubernetes space, we had this doc community, right, which
stands for data on Kubernetes community, very active, right, and really working to enable
running data intensive applications on Kubernetes.
And I think we've quite good results, right, these are actually like a little bit outdated,
like from the last year, pool results, right, but we could see what there is a fair amount
of companies running some significant number of data intensive applications on Kubernetes
already.
Here are some stats which are newer from a cloud native foundation this day, right, and
these are comparing 2021 to 2022, right, essentially just last year starts where we can see what
goes with databases was the second most common workload, well, second most fastest growing
kind of workload, which is the flow in Kubernetes, right, so we can see what the things are
changing, right, now you can see also some other stuff like messaging and big data, all
of those are also actually data intensive applications, right, so we can see Kubernetes
have moved in this field, right, now here is our interesting data point, right, if you
look at the database as a service, public database as a service, right, you would see
many independent database as a service solutions which have been released over the last, you
know, three, four years actually Kubernetes built, right, based on Kubernetes, right,
here are, you know, number of companies, right, which you may have held, which are running
their public database as a service on Kubernetes, so I hope by this point I have convinced you
what the database is on Kubernetes is, you know, quite possible and can be run quite
successful.
Now what is wonderful about Kubernetes specifically?
Well I mentioned that as a container orchestration system, right, but I also can think about
that as essentially an operating system, which is focused on the, you know, data center,
right, a set of data centers, environment rather than on a single node.
What I think is particularly great when it comes to the databases, it has a very robust
mechanics to deal with all kind of failures, node failures and some others, right, because
this is actually quite complicated problems, right, if you think about like a very large
systems you have to be thinking about failures happening all the time, so for maybe multiple
failures at the same time, right, and really doing that manually, right, as you would have
to do if you want to, let's say, roll out your highly available system on a, you know,
like a bare metal or a bunch of VMs, right, it is tough, right, it is tough to get that,
you know, last one, two, wherever, or maybe even kind of zero one percent of edge cases,
which is absolutely essential for running applications and scale.
Specifically for databases, these typically are being built with the operator framework,
right, the operator framework is something which as a name says allows you to put a lot
of logic in, right, and say, hey, do what a skilled database operator would do, because
being stateful, database needs like an extra care, right, how you are going to upgrade
the cluster, right, well, you know what, you don't shut all the database nodes down, right,
and then change between your version and spin up, well, no, you don't do it this way in
databases, you often need to follow some process, you know, upgrade them one after another,
maybe when to ensure your grade was successful, database was warmed up appropriately, right,
and all the nuance things which databases at scale need.
Now if you look at the databases on Kubernetes, we can see their pickup by vendors is slower,
right, if you think about, you know, the many of them would have operators that are not
quite existing, right, or quite limited, and I would say a lot of reason for that is what
in this age vendors often would want you to rather to go to the database as a service
solution, right, idea, hey, you know, if you are, how you would like you to develop cloud
native applications is go to our solution, right, if you are playing with, you know,
MariaDB, go to SkySQL, right, if you are, you know, MongoDB, go to MongoDB Atlas, right,
and so on and so forth, right, but in this case you often steal a lot of third party
solutions were developed, and then slowly but surely many vendors they start to pick
up, right, because hey, you know what, it's better to have a Kubernetes operator and people
doing something else entirely, right, so we have, for example, official operators for
MySQL or MariaDB or even MongoDB, they are, though, relatively limited at this point.
Now from our side, we've been in this operator game, I think, for a while, and for MySQL,
MongoDB has pretty robust solutions, right, which you can use.
What I would say is the problem with Kubernetes in this case.
Well, if you look in this case of the Kubernetes, it can be quite complicated, right, and the
running database is something you need to really be careful because often you don't get
a second chance, right, if you sort of lost your database, well, that can be already very
big and serious issue for your business, right, and setting up Kubernetes for a database,
for like a storage and backup, right, can be quite advanced skill at this point.
Now if you look at the databases, where we see their state of art simplicity, I would
say, is in a database as a service, right, and databases as a service as it available
in a proprietary cloud, I think, brings a lot of great usability, but of course also
at a great cost.
And in this case, I mean both as direct cost as well as a vendor lock-in, which happens.
In this case, if you look at the database of the servers as they exist right now, there
are a number of proprietary databases as a service offerings, like obviously any launch
cloud has them.
Then there are some database vendors, right, which have their own.
You think about MongoDB, SkySQL from RETB, Cochroach, Cloud, TimeScale, everybody also
has their own branded database cloud those days.
And there is also a bunch of other vendors, right, which has also their own proprietary
database management framework, like Avian Instaclassers gets you that.
Now why database as a service is important from my standpoint?
Because it really removes a lot of toil, right, managing high availability, like things of,
hey, you know, patching, like security updates, it's all can be done either automatically
or, you know, like a pretty much push data solution in the backups, makes things easy
to scale, right, hey, you know what I want to scale, right, instead of figuring out how
to do that.
But the problem with a database as a service, as it comes right now, it often would be what
I would call like a hotel California compatibility, right, like you can move into something as
Amazon Aurora, right, from your, you know, of cloud installation, but then it may be
very hard to move back.
In fact, a lot of work out there is done exactly to make that, that hard.
What also would see with a lot of the cloud vendors is those solutions, they are called
fully managed, right.
Well, and fully managed is kind of over a market in my opinion, right, because when
you talk to Amazon, for example, they say, oh, our solution is fully managed.
Okay, so who is responsible for database security?
Oh, that's shared responsibility.
Who's going to tune that?
Well, what if I could not share responsibility, right?
Everything is shared responsibility and that means, well, which you may not find from the
marketing pages, you still need people to understand databases on your stuff.
Those if the budgets have been reallocated to a fully managed database service providers,
you may not have those people or enough of your people on the team.
Now my concern, of course, with those commercial databases service solution is that it is a
vendor looking, as I mentioned right now, right, which may be, you know, painful for
some, right.
Maybe some of you have heard about 37 signals who recently wrote this article about why
they live in the cloud and saying, oh, my gosh, that is like so expensive, right.
And they mentioned specifically expense and a lot of, you know, fully managed database
solutions they have been doing.
But that is also something likely to come, become even more painful.
So anybody of you recognize this young, good-looking guy over here?
Anyone?
Well, this is Mr. Larry Ellison, right.
And what Mr. Larry Ellison was doing in 80s, he was really saving people from the nasty
big blue and a vendor looking which was happening right with the mainframe, right.
But we go, we understand what happened, you know, couple of decades after, later, after
people were sufficiently saved by the Oracle.
Now what do we say?
Well, Oracle doesn't have customers, Oracle has hostages, right.
So that is what we should expect with a database vendor looking as well, right, as you sufficiently
adopt all of those like wonderful extra features and you don't have a way back anymore, right.
You can expect their cost of escalating as if Oracle.
In my opinion though, there is a good way to use the cloud, I would say, as indicates
here where you can really use the cloud as a commodity and build the value through their
open source solutions as a Kubernetes and really look at this side, right.
Instead of really building relationship on the property or cloud vendors, you can see
how you can embrace their solutions which are coming from open source stacks like a
one in a cloud computing foundation.
You can see this as an example, right.
And there are a lot of icons here.
You probably cannot really read all of them but the point what I want to indicate here
is just how big is an open source ecosystem is and you probably find some projects for
almost any need which you would have in like a property cloud but they're open source.
In my experience what I would like to see and what you're working on as per corner in
the database space to really provide a fully open source solution which you can write on
variety of environments, right, like hey, you want it on a cloud, you want it in any
of the on-prem environment, well, you got it, right.
You should be able to do that with no changes.
If you are just looking for the basics, actually, well, I take it back.
If you are having a lot of Kubernetes experience in your company already, actually their Kubernetes
database operators are already pretty cool, right.
They really, you know, eliminate so much of toil, right.
And you can check this, you know, tutorial which shows you how you set up a cluster,
scale it, you know, wherever, back it up, right, really, you know, just a couple of
single comments compared to what that would do on Linux.
It's like on a bare Linux is a lot more complicated.
And for those who like more of, you know, graphical user interface similar to what Amazon
RDS or other cloud vendors provide, we are also working on that through our solution
PMM which is also 100% open source.
Well, like you can, you know, check it out.
So if, in the end, we would like to see, right, and hopefully we will see more similar solution
coming up from a industry where we have open source databases as a service experience.
Some people wonder in this case, like, what does that really mean?
Because databases as a service supposed to be like a fully managed.
And what I mean by that is this, right.
First part of a database as a service is your interface and experience.
Like, hey, I deploy the database in a couple of clicks, right, or like a single API call.
Well, and nothing prevents us having an open source software which has those features.
We can do it, right, and we should do it.
Now, of course, there is an other piece, right.
Typically, then things go beyond software ability to deal with that.
There are some people, you know, in Amazon, right, or, you know, SkySquad or Avian, right,
any of those providers, right.
And of course, that is something, well, you don't get if you get a software alone.
But that is something I believe you should have a choice where you are building those
troubleshooting skills in-house.
If that is the choice you take, right, or you should be able to pick from a variety of
vendors, right, which can provide that kind of need for you, right, to provide a full
database as a service experience comparable to the get-in and commercial cloud those days.
So with that, let me finish up with this, right, is what, if you look at the database
as a service, the databases, they have been really going from container to full database
experience in the open source side quite well.
We can see what the Docker support is very mature.
Kubernetes, I think, is getting there, right, if a lot of people using that already.
And the database's experience in the open source space is still work in progress, but
I would expect it's coming mature in both from Percona and other vendors in a few years.
And well, because of the open source, you can be part of solution in this case by, you
know, by contributing to the ecosystem.
So I think the database as a service has won, right, because of unparalleled convenience
and you know what, deep down, we're all suckers for that.
The software vendor lock-in sucks, right, I don't think anybody wants to build the company.
And as in many other areas, I believe the open source is coming for rescue as well.
With that, that's all ahead.
Okay, we have time for about one, maybe two questions.
Hi, thank you for your presentation.
Quick question about the more operational side of running a database in Docker or in
Kubernetes.
So the main part people are usually scared about is of course the stateful part of it.
So the storing the data somewhere should be for like file system snapshots or doing backups
and so on.
So that's in a way stored in a separate place afterwards.
For that second building block, what kind of services would you suggest in that case?
Yeah, so the question is about some operational aspects about running a database on Kubernetes
and specifically as it relates to the storage, right?
In our experience, a lot of that depends on what already exists.
I think one of the big improvements in Kubernetes recently was having a unified CSI, right,
internal storage interface, which allows now a lot more flexibility than before, right,
and it's ever-improving, right?
For example, snapshots, they're building in, right, or you can now like a scale the volume
in many cases, right?
So that is what we rely on.
Okay.
We're unfortunately out of time.
Thank you for the talk.
Thank you for being here.
Okay.
Well, and I will be outside so you guys have a few more questions.
Happy to answer.
Thank you.