Our next talk is by Akihiro.
He's going to talk about Bit4Bit reproducible builds with Docker files.
Hi, I'm Akihiro Sada from NTT Corporation at Zebra.
In this session, I talk about Bit4Bit reproducible build with Dockerfile.
Depending on the determinants of the timestamps and the object-produced versions, I have a
demo and you can reproduce my demo by yourselves using this repo,
www.tav.com.slash-reproducible.com.
Let's begin with water reproducible builds.
Which means producing exactly the same binary when you have the same source.
For containers, the source means Dockerfile and every source code files that are referred
from the Dockerfile.
And the binary means OCR images, including the tar layers and the metadata JSONs.
This reproducibility has to be accessible by anybody at any time, but not necessarily
on any machine.
Because typically your machine has to have a specific version of two chains.
And sometimes you have to use a specific version of the host operating system with a specific
file system and with a specific CPU.
So this limitation is very far from ideal, but this is sometimes in NTT Pro.
So why do we need reproducible builds?
It's because we want to verify the actual source code of the binary, not the claimed
source code.
The actual source code may differ from the claimed source code when the environment,
such as the developer's laptop or CD server, such as changes or dev action is compromised.
Or when the developer simply has malicious intent.
So we want to be sure we have actual source code and if the builds are reproducible, we
can be sure that we have actual source codes.
Otherwise we are not sure whether we have the actual source code or not.
Maybe we are using some compromised source code.
So reproducible build is really great, but it's not a policy.
Especially reproducibility has nothing to do with whether the source code is safe to
use.
The source code may still contain malicious codes.
So reproducible builds make sense only when you actually review the source code by yourself.
So it's really time taking job and very few people are motivated to bother doing that.
But this problem is beyond scope of my talk.
So maybe this task can be automated using some AI in the next couple of years.
But it's beyond scope at this stop.
I don't know.
And it was hard to make the builds reproducible, especially with Docker files.
So there were three major changes.
The most obvious one is timestamps.
Such as the timestamps of the files in OCI tar layers and other timestamps in OCI JSON.
Such as ORZ, OpenContinance, image, create it.
And we also have timestamps in the image histories.
It can be printable with Docker history commands.
So the timestamp problem is the most obvious one.
But the timestamp problem is relatively easy to solve.
So the biggest problem is not timestamps.
The biggest problem is non-deterministic of aftergates.
So when you run aftergates, the package version that is installable with aftergates changes
every time.
And of course, this is not specific to absolute.
So the same problem exists in DNF, APK, JIPA, Pacman, and almost all package managers.
Actually Nix, the package manager, has solved this issue with a version cleaning system
called Flix.
But Nix is very complex and still hard for most people to run.
And Gix is also similar, but Gix is still complex and very hard.
So most people still want to use aftergates or DNF or APK.
And the third problem shown here is characteristics of the file systems.
Such as hard links and X attributes.
So these special characteristics may differ across file systems.
So reproducible builds were really hard in the ecosystem of a Docker file.
But it's now supported in Buildkit version 0.11.
Buildkit is a modern image building framework made for Docker and Moby.
And it has been embedded in the Docker demo since Docker version 18.06.
But it's not specific to Docker and Moby.
So it can be also used as a sound-alarm demo called Buildkit D. And Buildkit D can be executed
inside Kubernetes or NetCity or Potomar or any other control engines that supports OCI
specs.
Buildkit version 8.1 was released the last month with Buildkit support for reproducing
timestamps.
Next to Tony Stigley who is a version of this work.
And this version 0.11 still needs really complex Docker files.
But the next version 0.12 is likely to require less complex Docker files.
And reproducing timestamps is supported using the special build org called Source Date
Epoch.
This build org conforms to the reproducible builds.org's source date epoch spec, which
is available under HTTPS
construction.
And the argument value is usually expected to be set to the
next epoch representation of the GIT commit to this using GIT log dash one dash dash pretty
equal passability.
So you get an integer number that corresponds to the sequence since 1970, generally first.
And this source date epoch is exposed to the run instruction of the Docker file as the
environment variable.
And in addition, it's also consumed by Buildkit itself for the timestamps in the OCI JSONs.
But that's for the timestamps in the OCI tie layers and Buildkit version 0.11.
This is planned to be improved in version 0.12.
So as I mentioned in the previous slide, there is a bunch of cables in version 0.11.
So especially the file timestamps currently has to be explicitly touched with using the
command command, XR command and the touch command like this very complex script.
And that already takes more than three lines.
And also you have to squash all the layers to eliminate over a first white glass that
are created on removing the files in the continuous because the timestamps of the whiteouts are
not reproducible in Buildkit version 0.11.
And also there's a restriction on the mount point trajectories.
So cache mount points can be only created under TMPFS such as Threshold.
And also hard links are not reproducible depending on the file system stamp filter.
So in this version we still have a bunch of cables.
But these cables are already being improved in my project list 3560.
It's not merged in the master branch yet.
But I hope that this project will be merged in the next version 0.12 in the next couple
of weeks or maybe in the next couple of months.
The next topic is reproducing package versions.
This is the most important topic of this talk.
The package versions are hard to reproduce because most distributions do not retain all
the packages.
For example Ubuntu does not retain all the packages as far as I can see.
Debian does.
But the package archives are not mirrored widely.
And basically we only have the central snapshot. Debian.org and only a few mirrors.
This is causing too much load on the central server, snapshot. Debian.org.
So basically this snapshot. Debian.org server can't be used in the CI environments because
it's really slow and it's really freaky.
And this slowness and the freckiest program will get even worse when more people begin
to make their builds reproducible.
This situation is very similar for Fedora and Linux as well.
And Reprogate is my solution for this program.
This is a decentralized and reproducible frontend for Aftergate, DNF, APK and Perkmar.
The package version can be locked with SHA256, SAMS5 and packages can be fetched from several
transports such as HTTP, OCL, OCL registries, IPFS, Local 5 systems and NFS.
By default, Reprogate attempts to fetch the packages from dev.debian.orz using the package
name.
So dev.debian.orz server is fast but it's ephemeral.
It doesn't retain all the packages.
So for all packages, Reprogate automatically horsebacks to devian.notset.fwar using the
SHA256 hash.
This is relatively slow but this server provides processing snapshots of all the packages.
You can also configure Reprogate to use OCL registries, IPFS and Local 5 system.
Reprogate currently supports the five distributions, Debian, Ubuntu, Fedora, Alpine and Linux.
Reprogate is expected to be used in containers but can be used with non-continent environments
as well.
The command user is like this.
So you run Reprogate hash generate to generate the hash file and run apt-get install hero
to install hero packages and Reprogate hash generate again and you will get SHA256, SAMS5
like this.
So this file contains hash of 12 slash main slash hero slash hero 2.10 and d6 photo to
dev.
And inside the containers you can run Reprogate install with this SHA256, SAMS5 and Reprogate
fetch this package from HTTP after get repo or maybe from OCL registry or maybe from IPFS
or maybe from NMS depending on the configuration.
And here is the demo.
So to reproduce this demo you have to run specific version of build kit version 0.11.0.
And in this directory I have SHA256, SAMS5 like this.
This is mostly for running GCC.
And Docker file is a complex machine generated and it has a bunch of work arounds like this
for source list stuffs.
And you can use this to test reproducibility.
It takes a few minutes but the result is like this so you will get the same hash 0a3bc
fub67c85 on any machine such as on detailed actions or local laptops.
So you can try this by yourself on your own machine.
And the future works includes simplifying the Docker files and cache management.
I'm also trying to improve interoperability with 26 stages x6 opt and x6 APK for cross
cooperation.
And also the reproducibility should be testable with open SSS, source of provenance.
And probably more contributions are welcome for these topics.
And here is the wrap up of my talk.
So reproducible builds help to adjust the origin of the binary.
And it challenges like non-deterministic time stamps and the project versions.
And the project version 0.11 adds preliminary support for source data APK.
And the project can be used for reproducing the project version with 5, 6 sums.
And I think the demo is still running so I can't show the results of the demo but that
should be like this result.
Any questions?
Would it be fair to say that this sacrifices security in favor of reproducibility because
you would have to keep that list of hashes maintained to make sure that the packages
downloaded are always like the most secure ones?
So your question was how to make it hash wise, right?
How do you make sure that the list of package hashes is always pointing to the most secure
versions of a package?
So you can use reproget hash
and make the hash file like this.
You can also create the hash file by yourself just with text editor or maybe just your own
NSR tool to maintain this hash file.
Okay, we're out of time.
Thank you for the talk.
Thanks everyone for attending.
Clapping