And our next talk is by Sean and he's going to talk about bottle rocket.
Thanks.
Thank you.
Yeah, so I'm going to talk about the Bile Rocket container optimized Linux distribution.
My name is Sean McGinnis.
I work, I'm an engineer on the Bile Rocket project and I work at AWS.
So I'll just go over what a container optimized Linux is.
I'm assuming most people in this track probably have an idea.
But go over the basics, talk a little bit about what Bile Rocket is, show a little bit so you get a feel for it.
And what I'd really like is to see others get involved.
So the statement, you know, kind of the mission statement I guess is that it's a free and open source Linux based operating system for hosting containers.
So what does that mean?
Before we get into, you know, the motivations behind that, it's interesting to look at general purpose Linux distributions.
And some of the challenges with using those when you are, when you have hundreds of nodes in a Kubernetes cluster,
you really have a lot of workloads that you're running, containerized workloads that you're running,
and you need to optimize how you're using the resources.
So with most general purpose distros, it's, you know, the configuration is immutable.
You can log into the machine, you can make changes, make adjustments, add, install extra services.
Out of the box, a lot of them come with a lot, you know, kind of a default baseline set of services that you might not necessarily need when you're just trying to run containers.
And that uses more system resources and then also creates more of a security risk of there's more attack service available.
And because of that, because you can log in, you can change things, you can tweak configuration settings,
those kinds of systems are easier to become pets where you really customize that node exactly how you want it,
and you're less likely to just blow that away and spin up a new one, especially when, okay, I've made some changes there.
I don't quite remember what I changed because I was troubleshooting something, there might be something important there.
So now I need to take care of this node and it becomes my pet.
So for container optimized Linux distributions, especially for Bio Rocket,
really try to optimize for just the services that you need running on your Linux machine to be able to run your containers.
That means less resource usage for things that aren't very important to you,
it means less attack area for someone to compromise that machine,
get all kinds of added benefits, faster boot time, smaller image sizes to transfer around.
So with Bio Rocket, we try to make things as small as possible, just what you need.
And try to make it more secure by default.
I don't say secure by default because that's impossible, try to make it more secure.
So really locking things down, making sure that if someone were to try to compromise your host,
they're going to have a hard time doing it.
And it's open source.
Bio Rocket is not a general purpose operating system, if you're looking to do other things besides container workloads,
Bio Rocket is probably not the right distro for you.
It is backed by AWS but it is not an AWS only solution.
Coming from AWS it is very well integrated with AWS but I hope that doesn't stay the primary case for long.
And it is not a container based OS.
So what I mean by that, and this is a lot of, comes up a lot in conversations where there's this confusion
where you talk about a container distro and different people kind of already have a preconception of what that term means.
So the really, the two kind of paradigms that come up are the distro, that's kind of the base image that you build on top of.
So you're docker fell from Bio Rocket versus your OS.
You're running and then on that you spin up containers.
And it really is, when we talk about Bio Rocket being a container optimized Linux, it's that second one.
Bio Rocket is not something that you would use to create a container image.
A little background of Bio Rocket, we, if you see the date in the bottom left there, we launched March 2020.
Which there are a few other things going on around that time.
So didn't quite make the big splash on the launch there that we had hoped for.
But it's great now to actually be back in person in front of people being able to talk about the work that we've done in the last two years, or three years.
And hopefully get the awareness out there a little more.
Bio Rocket, right now we build and distribute different variants.
The variants term for us is, it's the, how we try to optimize things for your specific scenario.
So if you're running Kubernetes 1.22, there is a variant specifically for Kubernetes 1.22.
And Amazon ECS and VMware.
The reason to have these different variants is back to that idea of no extra overhead.
So for these, for the metal variant, we try to limit the number of kernel drivers that are loaded.
The kernel drivers that you need between a metal deployment where you're running on an actual server hardware, versus where you're running in a virtual machine instance, are different.
You know, we would know if you're running in a virtual machine, there's a very small subset of the available drivers that you need to actually do that.
So anything extra is taken out of there.
Any specific agents that are needed to integrate well, like in VMware, we have those baked into that variant.
You pick the variant that you want for your scenario and that gives you a well integrated option.
Now Bio Rocket isn't, you know, we're far from the leaders in container optimized distributions.
CoreOS is one, you know, they really popularized the whole idea.
Flakar is very popular. I just wanted to acknowledge that and make sure that everyone's aware.
There are other options out there. None of the things here are meant to say one is better than the other.
They all approach things from slightly different angles, just because there's maybe a smaller list for one.
You know, if you're using that platform, then you're well integrated.
Maybe that is the best option for you. But Bio Rocket is trying to address all of these kind of similar problem spaces that the other distributions are doing.
We all come at it a little different way, just like how you have Ubuntu and Red Hat and many, many other general purpose distributions.
So to dive into Bio Rocket a little bit, this, there really isn't too much more than these blocks.
You know, we have the base Linux kernel. System.bedewe is used to manage things.
And we actually run two different container instances.
And the reason for this is, again, security. Everything on the left hand side, host containers, are things that are used to manage the node.
They're things that have a little more privilege, that might be able to access things that regular pods that are running on the container instance that's used, say, with Kubernetes,
that would be a little more locked down. And then if there is any security vulnerability, it helps isolate things.
It's an API driven configuration. So when you deploy an instance, you can give a configuration that actually, everything, even though it ends up being a file with settings,
everything goes through the API and that's what actually sets the values for how, what happens when this instance boots up and runs.
The host containers, so again, the things with a little more privilege.
Host container is really where, how you would access the machine.
So Bio Rocket, the actual Bio Rocket base itself, if you look at this actual Linux kernel running and all the systems on there, there's no shell.
There's no SSHD. It really is isolated. You need to physically connect some way to this instance.
So how do you actually do things? And that's where the control container comes in.
That provides an environment that you can connect to and has a few of the tools that you may need if you need to actually interact beyond the API configuration.
One step above that then is from that control container, you can launch the, an admin container.
And that actually does then give you the option to run SSHD. It lets you access more of the system settings.
But it's something that's not run by default and it's not something that we recommend you keep running.
Really, it's there, kind of a break glass if you need it. You need to get in the node. You need to be able to troubleshoot some things.
This is how you would do it by running an admin container.
And then there's also other privileged things that we call bootstrap containers.
Those are things that, they're container images that you can customize and spin up to be able to do special things.
We've seen some cases where, okay, maybe I have some specific file system requirements or I need to do some special thing.
Bootstrap container is one of those host containers that's a little more privileged that you can have it when the system just starts up, initializes.
That can, can set some, do some, some custom things for you.
So to see what this actually looks like, you know, I talk very vaguely about distributions, I'll just show you what it's like to interact with a Biorocket host.
So typically you would, you would, the only way you would interact with the host is through whatever container orchestration you're using.
You shouldn't care what's running, what nodes are actually part of your cluster.
You just have a Kubernetes cluster and you use it.
So you can use things like kubectl to get information about nodes.
You could describe the nodes if you'd like and if you do that, you can see here it's an OS image, Biorocket 1.12.
But most of the time you would just be running your, your services, your pods, your load bands, you know, demon sets, those types of things.
If you need to connect, then you actually need to connect to the console.
So if you're on a bare metal instance, this is actually plugging into the display port.
You know, if you're using a host, a hosting platform, this is whatever console interface that gives you.
And you're presented with this.
It's, this is the control container that, that lets you actually access the host.
So back to that diagram, within these host containers under that container instance, right now the shell that I have is actually this control container.
Because there's no shell on the base OS itself.
So this gives you a little information to help you get started.
There's the API client.
And I can, I can use that to, let's see, I want to get my Kubernetes settings.
But if I look at Kubernetes puts everything under configuration under Etsy Kubernetes by default.
There's nothing there.
There's, there's no shell.
I can't do, let's see, I can't access file.
Can't make changes here.
But there's nothing on here that shows you that this is a, is part of a Kubernetes cluster.
And that's because we're just inside that control container.
This isn't actually that the host OS, the host file system.
The trick that it have there is there is a hidden mount that has, that'll give you some access to the root file system.
But if you notice, I didn't point it out.
There's enable admin container.
It was one of the commands that that banner recommends or lets you know about.
And that's what actually gets you into this admin container that has more access.
So if I do enter admin container.
Maybe I should have reset things.
Normally you just enter admin container.
So that, that spins up that, that container instance because it's not running by default.
It's only when you need it.
So I started up an admin container.
Now I have a shell within the admin container.
So now I'm, now I'm from there.
And, and now that I'm in that container, I have a little more access.
I can see some more files, but it's still not going to give me full access yet.
So there's a tool called Sheltie.
Now that I have that, now there's, I have access to the actual underlying file system.
So now I can go in.
That's the Kubernetes. I want to take a look at the Kubelet config.
All that information is there.
So, yeah.
Aren't command line demos exciting?
So in addition to being able to access the system only through these controlled mechanisms.
So I try to, to limit anything else that, that could be running, that could be used.
There's a root only, a read only root file system.
So even if a container running in your Kubernetes cluster somehow was able to break out,
it's, we'd only have access to the read only file system.
It can't make any changes there.
We also use de-imverity as an extra layer of precaution.
So even if something happened that, that adds some checks and things are locked down.
So really it'd be very difficult to compromise a system.
And then we also use SeLinux.
So there's multiple layers of protections in place here to try to, to limit things.
There's PCI compliance.
Sorry, I don't know what happened to that slide.
And we are looking at FIPS compliance in the future to be able to show that the system really is secure.
So I mentioned it's a read only file system.
The way Bottle Rocket is distributed is it's, it's image-based.
There's no YUM, there's no DNF.
You can't go in there and install extra packages.
So it is, it is a static image.
So one nice thing about that is when you, if you want to upgrade a node to a new release of Bottle Rocket,
the way it works is it'll actually download that newer image and write it to the second partition of the, of the root disk.
And then upgrading really is just switching over and pointing at that new partition.
Because everything, all the settings that you have are persisted as part of what was set through the API server.
It can switch over to this new image, reboot when it comes up.
It reads all those settings again, uses the new image and post is running.
There's, there, we do provide a few tools.
There's a command line interface to be able to check for updates.
That's a pain, especially if you have hundreds of nodes.
But there's things like Bottle Rocket Update Operator, which will handle a lot of this for you.
So if you have a Kubernetes cluster, you can schedule when you want maintenance activities to happen.
That'll automatically go out and look for new versions being released.
And then it'll take care of interacting with Kubernetes to coordinate off nodes,
and then the workloads drained off into others, upgrade those nodes, and then allow things to move back.
So cleanly over, over a period of time, it'll get all of your nodes within the cluster upgraded to the new version.
Or, and this is my preference, just replace the nodes.
They're not customized.
You know you haven't left any special thing on the file system that you need to worry about.
Am I going to lose something if I get rid of this?
You just spin up new nodes, have them join, and then you can get rid of the old nodes and fresh system every time.
Either way works.
The configuration, like I mentioned, most of the time you're passing in a user data file,
and that's in the Tommel format.
But really, you know, we're an equal opportunity markup project.
So depending on how you're doing things, there's YAML.
If you use something like EKS cut all the things configured in YAML, so you can have settings there.
I showed the API client if you actually do want to go and make changes on the command line.
You can use that API client and set and give it a JSON string of the settings that you'd like, or the Tommel.
And they're on the CURL at the bottom in the repo.
There's a full listing of all the different settings that you can do with those configuration files.
Now, the ball rocket handles things slightly different than a lot of other distros.
So that can kind of be a stumbling block when you look at how, you know, if you want to adopt ball rocket
or you're trying it out and trying to see if it works.
So there's a few things to be aware of, I guess, when you do that.
One common thing that I've heard from users is, well, my company requires that I run this antivirus agent on all of my hosts.
If they have containerized that agent, great.
If they haven't, that's an issue.
Like I said, there's no DNF, there's no YAML.
You can't go in there and install software.
So really anything that you need to run on there, any kind of host agents that integrate with systems.
Can be run in privileged containers that can do a lot of things.
It just has to be containerized to be able to run on ball rocket.
And then, like I said, accessing it.
A lot of system admins are used to, okay, I've got all these nodes out there.
I know I just SSH in and that's how I access my system and do things.
So that can be a stumbling block too.
Things are done a little bit differently because things are so locked down.
Pros and cons.
So because things are locked down, you need to enable that admin container.
Then you can enable SSH if you need to.
But it's not going to be there by default.
And then the last thing I wanted to bring up, just because these are two AWS-initiated projects, both open source.
I'll be talking to someone about ball rocket and we'll go into some detail.
And it seems like we're both on the same page talking about the same thing.
And then somehow they say something and we're like, oh, wait, no, you're actually thinking about a different project.
So firecracker is another thing.
That's actually for a virtualized solution.
So that's ball rocket, firecracker, explosive things, but not the same thing.
So my main motivation for getting out and talking about things like this is love to see more people get involved.
Everything that we can right now is up on GitHub under the bottle rocket OS org.
Everything is Apache 2 and MIT licensed.
We try to publish a roadmap under that org.
So if you're curious what's happening, take a look there.
But we'd like to, the people working on the project would like to hear from folks about what they'd like to see.
If you have ideas and you want to bring pull requests, love that.
To actually work on ball rocket, we have the Linux kernel, obviously, C, but most of the bottle rocket pieces of putting all this together is in Rust.
So you will need Linux, you will need Rust, and you will need Docker to be able to perform, to do builds and things like that.
We have a ball rocket SDK image that we publish, so that has the specific Rust like the version, and there are some goal pieces, so it has the Go tool chain.
But you do need a base requirement on your machine to be able to actually run things.
And I say a decent amount of CPU memory storage.
I can't really give an exact number. You're compiling, you're building a distro.
So if you want to do that in a two core, eight gigabyte VM on your laptop, you're going to have to be patient.
That'll take some time.
So really, the more CPU, the more memory that you have, the better that whole situation is going to be.
But there is a building.md file in the repo.
If you are interested in that, take a look, and that will go through everything to get you set up to be able to actually check out the repo, make changes, and compile it.
Another area that I hope is going to help to get people involved, we're looking at what we're calling right now, auto tree builds.
So the variants that I spoke about, having these variants that are very optimized for different situations.
If you wanted to build your own, say you have your own container orchestration platform and you want to integrate Bala Rocket with it,
you would have, right now, you would have to fork the whole repo and do everything within Bala Rocket to get repo itself.
So we're looking at ways, how can we separate things out and make this easier?
So if you have a customized Bala Rocket image that you'd like to make for your company, for your home lab, how can you do that without having to pull everything in?
So if you are interested, you can subscribe to this, 2669 in the GitHub Bala Rocket issues.
And then even if you're not a developer, you don't have the resources to build your own, to be able to compile everything.
If you're not interested in that, that's fine.
We'd love people to just join our community meetings, let us know what you're looking for.
Let us know if there's anything missing from Bala Rocket. Be become part of Bala Rocket itself.
So that happens right now every other week and we manage it through Meetup just to have an easy way to communicate when those are.
There's a HackMD, you can throw your ideas in there and we can discuss them.
So, love to see anybody join there.
So that's meetup.com, Bala Rocket-community.
And with that, I'll open it up if there's any questions.
Oh, okay.
Hey, thanks for a great presentation.
Given that the file systems are immutable, where do logs go?
Does Bala Rocket itself log?
And I understood that the Kubelet is also running non-containerized.
So where do the Kubelet go, logs go, if you use Kubelet?
There are some very targeted areas where we mount a tempFS.
So things like how I was talking about all the settings through the API, you need to use those to spin up Kubelet or to run Kubelet.
It needs to know what settings and needs to read that from a configuration file.
So yeah, so if we have a read-only file system, how does it do that?
On boot, we mount these tempFS mounts in specific places where they're needed.
And then based on reading the configuration settings, that gets written out with a template.
So if changes somehow happen in there, your reboot comes back up and you're exactly how you have things originally.
There's a question in chat, is there a version of Bottle Rocket which is built through run on KVM lib world?
We, there, in the repo, let me see, where did I put that?
In the repo, there is...
Sorry, it must just be under building.
There are instructions. Bottle Rocket can be run on QMU.
So if you, that's a great development tool too, is if you want to make changes and spin things up and just have it running, see how it works.
You can run it as a virtual machine.
Thank you for your...