Our next talk is by Stefan.
He's the project leader for LexD, a container manager, former teammate of mine as well.
And he's going to talk about safe containers through system call interception.
Hello.
Is that working well?
Think so.
All right.
So you kind of did the intro.
I'm Stefan.
I work at Canonical.
I'm the project leader for LexD, LexC, LexCFS and a bunch of other stuff that we do.
Effectively, system container guy.
And yeah, we're going to be talking about system call interception today.
First, just a tiny bit of going back to the basics.
We kind of need to explain what we're trying to achieve.
So there are two main kind of containers out there.
We've got privileged containers and unprivileged containers.
The ones you want are the unprivileged kind.
Privileged is bad.
And just to clarify there, too, we don't mean privileged as in dash dash privileged in Docker.
That's extra, extra bad.
Docker by default is privileged.
And the definition of privileged is whether you're using a user namespace or not.
So in the case of LexD, which is a container manager that I'm working on these days, we
default to unprivileged containers.
That's great.
It means that root in the container is not root on the host.
If there's a container escape of any kind, you don't you get as much permission as nobody
uses on the system.
That's great.
Problem is not being real root also means you don't get to do stuff that real root can
do.
A lot of stuff have been enabled now inside the user namespace that you can do yourself.
You can create a lot of devices.
You can reconfigure a lot of stuff.
It's great.
But there are still things you can't do.
You can't change your process priority to something higher than what you would be allowed
to do as a normal user on the system.
Anyone can create a new user namespace, go in it and bump their process priority to whatever
they want and bypass all kind of settings on the system.
So there's a lot of things that are not quite possible.
In general, we want to eradicate privileged containers because having real root is very,
very bad.
And it's kind of a game of, like, whack-a-mole as far as trying to prevent nasty things from
happening.
We've got Appama, we've got SecComp, we've got a whole bunch of things that are all trying
to prevent you from doing bad things, but that's done by us thinking about what all
the bad things are and trying to block them.
And someone just needs to find another bad thing we didn't think of, and then there goes
the entire system.
So we don't want those.
We'd like to get rid of them completely.
But for that, we need to find ways to allow for unprivileged environments to do things
that are normally only allowed to be done by privileged environments in a way that's
still safe.
All right.
All I'm going to be talking about today relies on SecComp, which is the system code interception
mechanism in Linux.
It lets you do a bunch of nice policies.
You can just put policies for, like, this system code with those arguments, just deny
them or return this return code or return, yeah, this particular error number, for example.
But it also grew the ability with Linux 5.0 in 2019, it grew the ability to notify userspace
instead.
So you can put a policy in SecComp that says if this is code and the arguments are so and
so, instead of taking an action right now, go and notify the spider descriptor that something
happened.
And then the whole system can have a privileged daemon monitoring that notification mechanism
and take actions.
There is some complexity around security that I'm going to get into very shortly because
you can do very, very bad things with that.
But if you do it correctly, it lets you run a more privileged action on behalf of a less
privileged container after going through some kind of analysis or that kind of logic on
the host to make sure that this is actually fine.
Now for the nasty issues, time of check, time of use is a very, very common issue in security.
And this mechanism has definitely got some issues around that.
Userspace gets notified that a system code was made.
The system code can have pointers to a bunch of different arguments and structures.
And there's nothing preventing the caller from technically changing the value at those
pointers.
So you need to be a bit careful when you're processing those messages.
You effectively need to start by copying everything, evaluating it.
If everything looks good, then you can take actions.
But by taking actions, we mean you can run the thing on behalf of the user with the original
arguments, never putting them again because otherwise they could change.
Or you could just say, I don't want this reject.
What you shouldn't do is say, oh, based on those arguments, it seems fine.
And it continues.
Because there's absolutely nothing that prevents the caller process from just racing you and
immediately changing the arguments to something else before it goes back to the kernel and
then running with a value you would not have allowed.
So you need to be careful in your design so that this doesn't happen.
Otherwise you're literally allowing people to run stuff as full-root privilege inside
of continuous containers, which would be very bad.
So what do we actually do with this stuff?
So far we've implemented quite a few things.
And I'm going to go into more details about each of those.
The first thing we implemented actually, I don't know if you're on the right order.
One of the first things we implemented is make node.
Then we followed that, which is useful for save device node creation.
I'm going to go into more detail shortly.
SetXAdder we also added pretty early on.
We've got support for eBPF so we can allow some specific eBPF programs.
We've got support for set scheduler, which is used to change some of the process priorities.
We've got support for mount, which was a real pain in the ass to implement, but we've got
support for mount.
And we've got support for sysinfo, which was also reasonably fun to implement.
Now kind of going over those things directly, make nodes, what do we use that for?
Well, one of the things we wanted to enable is for running docker inside of LexD containers.
I said LexD containers are on privilege, they are nice and safe.
Docker by and large not safe.
But docker running inside of a privilege LexD container safe.
So we figured we'd try and make that work.
And we did manage to get it working.
The main driver at the time was Travis CI.
The Travis CI platform was using LexD containers on M64, IBM, Z series, as well as IBM power
at the time.
And they wanted the same behavior as they were getting on Intel.
And on Intel, they were using full VMs that you could do whatever you wanted.
So we wanted to make sure that docker worked properly in there.
And what we noticed is that docker layers, especially the directory whiteout files and
five whiteout files, rely on either I think it's C 00 device nodes, or they rely on specific
excellent attributes that just say that this is like a directory that was removed effectively
in D&L A using that as whiteout.
Both cases, those things were not allowed.
Device creation in a container is a big, big, big no-go usually.
Because if you can create, say, the device node for DevSDA, then there's nothing preventing
your previous container from rewriting your disk, which would be bad.
So that's usually not allowed.
But some specific device nodes are fine.
And the work we did there also allows for things like creating a new dev null device
or new dev zero device or those kind of devices which are inherently safe.
And making that possible means that you can now do things like running the bootstrap or
similar tools inside of an unprivileged container.
Those are the few devices that are needed to be created as part of an image creation
process are safe devices, and this allows it.
We generally consider this particular interception to be safe, as in you can pretty much turn
it on on any LexD container without having to think too much about who's in that container,
like do we actually trust the workloads and all that kind of stuff.
The other piece to that puzzle was SetX
other.
It does not allow all of SetX other.
It just allows very safe namespaces of extended attributes.
It will not let you do things like setting a security attribute, because that would let
you do some really, really bad things, for example.
And this is similarly considered to be safe on our side.
Then go to the pretty interesting one, mount.
So again, mount is a bit of a problem, because usually, well, for the whole, usually it relies
on having a block device.
You kind of need to have that allowed in the container, which is already a bit fishy in
many cases.
You've got to be careful that any block device you expose to the container you consider as
untrusted from that point on, and you never mount it as real roots somewhere else, or
they could try and attack you.
And by attack you, what I mean is the kernel has a superblock parser that will process
a new device as it gets mounted, and this is not guaranteed to be bug free.
So a user that can craft a very specific block device might be able to trick something like
X4, XFS, BarFS, or any of the other file systems into either crashing into your system or doing
arbitrary code execution in the kernel.
Both cases not very good.
But we still enable support for that.
If you have a container that you trust, that you don't want to give full access for everything,
but that you still trust, you can technically do this, and it will let you mount inside
of the container.
We added an extra layer on top of that, which lets us do a shift.
Because if you do the mount, the ownership information on that device is probably not
landing at your container.
So we allow stacking shiftFS, which is hopefully lying soon, but that we implemented for Ubuntu
on Ubuntu that we can stack on top and that fixes the permissions.
So we support that as well.
The really cool thing with this stuff is we also support redirecting to fuse instead,
which then becomes safe.
So what we can do is say, any attempt at mounting ext4 inside of the container, call the fuse2fs
binary instead.
And yeah, that's safe, that actually does work pretty well.
And I'll show that in just a tiny bit.
And then we worked on the BPF, not allowing all of the BPF programs, but specifically allowing
those that we need to do nested containers and doing device permission management through
that.
So we can review what the program is, if it matches what we expect, then we load it.
Otherwise, we just reject entirely.
And it's also considered to be safe.
Then for an unsafe one, a sched set scheduler is not super duper safe because it lets you
reconfigure scheduler options.
It was needed to be able to run Android inside of a Np
or a Lp, by enabling this thing, but there's definitely some ability to affect the entire
system.
And then we had sysinfo.
That was kind of led by Alpine deciding not to use ProkMEM info to figure out the memory
usage in the free command.
So you would run a container with a limit of, like, a gig of RAM and run free.
And you would see 128 gigs, because it will just show you the host value directly.
And that's because the ones you look, like CFS, which is another project we ran, that
overlays on top of proc to show the right values,
they don't work because they were not reading
the file system, they were going straight to the kernel
with a system call using CS info.
So we've implemented Interception for that
and we've fitted with the same values
as you would be getting from Lex CFS
and that gets us the right behavior.
And so just switching to the demo,
also just rechecking something here real quick.
Okay, just making sure that Christian was wrong
with the time, it's good.
I've got until three, you showed me at 10 minutes.
All right, so let's just move here to the terminal
and the first thing I'll do is play with make node.
So, and that should be, yep, looks all right.
Just launching a new container Ubuntu 22.04
and let's try make node,
just remember the other of the arguments,
I'm sure I'm getting those wrong again
because I always get them wrong.
Make node named and type, yeah.
Depending on the kernel, this might work.
Yeah, it actually does work now.
Let me figure out dev no, this one shouldn't work.
One is three.
C5 one.
Yeah, C1 three, for example, for dev no,
does not work out of the box.
But if we stop this,
then set demo make node security calls,
intercept make node true.
In this case, we do need to restart the container
because the entire second policy needs to change.
For smaller changes, we don't need to,
for that we do, and now that works properly.
So that's the make node piece.
Then we've got docker.
For that one, I did prepare ahead a tiny bit
because I did not feel like downloading docker
on the wifi here.
I mean, actually I did, but it took an hour,
so I'm happy I didn't do it during the talk.
So for docker, actually let me show you the config first.
So the container here has security nesting enabled,
which allows for running containers in containers,
and it has intercept of both make node and setXR
that are set up.
And in there, that part does use the network,
so I'm just hoping that's tiny enough.
There we go.
So that works properly.
And the issue before was that unpacking the layers
would just blow up.
All right, so that was docker.
Then to the more, to the fancier one,
which is mount.
All right, so for mount, launch the container here.
I'm gonna go and pass it a block device,
so I'm passing it dev loop 11 on my system
as dev sda inside of the container.
Yeah, your signs are still wrong.
I've got 15.
I mean, it's until three.
Okay.
So demo mount, makefs, ext4, and dev sda.
Is it capital F?
Yes, okay.
So just formatting, that you can always do.
There's nothing preventing you from creating a file system.
Normally, that works just fine.
What doesn't work is this.
You're not allowed to actually mount it
inside of a container.
But now we can make that work, actually.
So what we're gonna be doing here
is turning on mount interception.
And then we need to set an extra one,
which is the one allowing specific file systems.
So in this case, ext4.
And then restarting the container here.
Okay.
Exec back in there and try mounting again.
And that works.
And if we look at, oops, just nls,
and we look at the F, it's mounted.
Normally, it's fine.
Other than it actually did this at real root,
and I could have done very nasty things
by crafting that particular device ahead of time.
It works as expected.
Now, what we can do to make things
a bit more interesting here,
actually, let me get back in there.
Let's unmount it and then install fuse2fs.
That's a fuse implementation of ext2.3.4.
That's pretty readily available.
You can install that.
And then what we need to do is remove the config key
that allowed straight up mounting of ext4.
And we place it in another config key
that instead says ext4 is fuse2fs.
So we put that in there.
Go back in.
And then do it as the back to mnt.
And the funny thing is that you won't actually notice
any difference whatsoever.
It actually looks completely identical.
Unless you go look at proc mounts,
at which point you're gonna notice
that the file system here is not the ext4,
it's fuse.txt4.
And if you look at the process list,
you're gonna notice that there's an extra process
running in your container now.
So that's pretty sweet because it means
we can literally forward any file system to fuse.
Because it's done at the Cisco layer,
the container doesn't really need to be aware of it.
Like it is not doing anything to the mount commands.
You can just call the mount Cisco at any point
and it will just forward it to fuse
and do the right thing for you.
Which means no change to your workloads whatsoever.
It just works.
So that is pretty cool.
And the last thing I wanted to show in the demo
is if I launch a Alpine Edge container.
So that's gonna be the most info.
And I'm gonna set a memory limit of one gig.
So if I go in there now,
and I look at the free memory,
we can see I've got 16 gigs,
which is considerably more than one gig.
The enforcement is in place.
So that's where problems happen,
is that the enforcement is in place.
Now if you run something that will look
at the free memory output to figure out
how much memory it can claim, it's gonna claim
the wrong amount of memory and it will get killed
by the out of memory killer.
So that's a problem.
Which is why we did the work to fix that
through system co-interception.
So you can do security, Cisco, intercept, sys, info,
sure, and then bounce that container.
Okay.
And if I go in there and I look at free,
and we've got a gig.
So that actually works properly.
It also fixes a bunch of other things.
It doesn't just do the memory,
but also does CPU load, uptime,
and a bunch of other things.
Like the entire struct, sys, info,
is not properly handled.
It's just the easiest use case we have is free on Alpine,
because we know that this command has been changed
to use sys, info instead of the five system.
So it's a very easy one to just prove the concept works.
But that's, that particular piece of work
fixed a whole lot of other things.
I think it also improved Java was using
the wrong interface and the wrong amount
of memory sometimes, so that fixed that.
It fixed a bunch of other stuff.
That was pretty good to have.
All right.
Yeah.
So looking forward, where do we want to take this?
I mean, we've got most of what we wanted covered, really.
Like the big items that are really problematic
have been resolved.
Like Docker was a big one that we really wanted to solve,
and it's working fine.
Alpine behaving, that's really nice.
We're happy with it.
It's good.
The man interception allows for a lot of different stuff now.
It's possible to do things like image building instead
of on previous containers.
You can really do a lot.
And Android seems to be happy, too,
with the tiny bit of stuff we added for that.
The things we'd like to add now are kind of weird stuff, really.
The one I've got in mind, mostly for the sake of it,
but also because I'm sure we found a use case for it,
is to implement init module and finit module.
So the ability to do kernel module loading
from inside of an previous container, which
is as terrifying as it sounds.
But the idea there is that we would not actually
allow for the container to feed us the actual object file
that we would then store at the kernel.
What we would do is we would receive that object file.
We'd look at what the kernel module name is,
look against an allow list that we have of kernel modules that
are fine to dynamically load on the system.
And if it's in that list, then we'll
do the loading using the module from the host system
that we know is correct.
This might help quite a bit with things
like firewalls in containers that
might need to load custom IP tables or a NetFilter modules,
and potentially some other things like file systems
and other things.
So that would be an interesting one to implement.
And I'm sure we're going to have to explain to a lot of people
exactly how it is that we're doing it, because otherwise
they're going to be absolutely terrified.
More EBPF program handling, I think,
is also kind of in our plans.
As I said, we're currently on the intercept of the EBPF
program that's used for device management,
so for allowing device creation, device mapping,
that kind of stuff within containers.
That's because C group 2 removed the devices C group's file
interface and moved to EBPF instead.
So we implemented it that way.
We seem to have some interest for other programs,
like I think SystemD and some other pretty common pieces
of software, now generate a BPF hook
that they hook either globally or on two specific kind
interfaces.
And some of those should be safe.
That should be things that we can effectively pull,
validate that they match the expected pattern.
And if they do, then show that to the kernel, this is fine.
And that should actually make a lot more newer software
that make use of a lot of BPF stuff to just start working.
I don't think we're anywhere near getting something
like a BPF trace working safely inside a container.
That's absolutely terrifying, because it's
got access to all of the kernel constructs,
and that's not something we do.
But some subset of those interfaces
should definitely be fine.
Signed BPF will solve a lot of those problems, probably,
because then you can load unprivileged programs.
And the other thing that I've had in mind for a while,
it's mostly a cool thing, and not something
I've actually had a use case for yet.
Second comp has an interesting property
in that it runs extremely early.
It runs in the system called entry time in the kernel.
Before the system code is resolved,
that means we can intercept system calls that don't exist.
So we can intercept system code numbers that have not yet
been allocated, and that means we
get to actually implement new system calls purely
in user space that you can access
through the normal kernel system code API.
That's super interesting, because it
has to do very easy prototype and testing
of potential system calls.
If you want to try specific interfaces,
see how they look, the layout, what kind of arguments
you want, you can pretty quickly implement system
calls through that, and already show user space software
at it until you're happy with it, at which point you go back
and you do the actual kernel implementation of the system
code.
So that might be pretty interesting.
I don't think anyone has actually done that yet,
but that's a nice property of how second comp works,
that it works before any kind of resolution, any kind of validity
of the system call number.
All that second comp tells us is actually
a system call number, and all of the pointers to the arguments.
It doesn't care whether the thing exists or not,
so it means we get to actually intercept things
that don't exist.
And that's it.
So we can start getting a few questions.
Also on your way out, if you're interested,
we do have AlexD stickers on the table over there,
so feel free to help yourself.
There's a question over there.
I think he's worth the first.
Yeah, there's one here, one there.
When will we see the system call being intercepted by default
on AlexD or other distribution?
Sorry.
When will we see this info calls being default intercepted?
This is going to roll out?
Yeah, we've currently not decided to do any of that by default.
Please leave quietly while we are answering questions.
Yeah, so we've not decided to intercept anything by default
yet.
We consider it to be safe.
The main problem we have is it depends on the kernel version
that you're running, whether it's
going to be working or not.
And it's still recent enough, even though it's 5.1,
which has been around a while now,
it's still recent enough that a bunch of distros
would not work properly.
So we want to wait until we can truly
assume that all of the distros that are like all the long term
support releases are still supported before we can start
doing that kind of stuff by default.
Please keep it down while we are answering questions.
Thank you.
Hello.
Thanks for the great talk.
So I have two questions.
First of all, we have a question.
First of all, you said there is this time of check
versus time of use issue.
And so how do you solve it?
I'm trying to give a question, but I can't hear anything.
Hold on.
So first of all, how do you fix this time of check
versus time of use issue, where you call a syscall?
The syscall gets notified.
And you can, well, raise it with another thread
and change some arguments, right?
I didn't really get that.
But if Christian did, you can answer instead,
because you probably know it.
It's extremely noisy.
OK, I'm going to try this.
Stefan, how do you fix the time of check, time of use issue?
OK, so the time of check, time of use issue,
you fix it by never letting the kernel execute after the check.
So you never continue a system call after the check,
effectively.
If you want to intercept a system call,
you are now in charge of running it.
And so you copy the arguments as they are.
You do the check on your copy of them.
You never ever reuse the pointer that the user gave you.
And you go with your own copy of it.
And that's perfectly safe.
But if the argument is a pointer to a string,
you need to copy the string.
And when you're copying the string,
it may be changed under the hood.
So are you actually freezing the process
with something like the cgroup, the freezer cgroup,
for example?
So technically, the calling thread is frozen by the kernel.
But it doesn't prevent another parallel thread
to modify it, which is why we effectively
map the memory of the process.
We copy the entire thing that we care about.
The entire, like if there's pointer or pointers,
we just travel start.
We copy it.
Once we've copied that, that's what we check policy against.
And those are the arguments we're
going to be passing to the actual kernel.
And we just never look back at what came from the process,
which means if they try to erase us at that point,
it doesn't matter.
We create full copies.
We create full copies of everything.
We never continue the system call,
although that's an ability that I added a while back.
So you can even say, continue the system call
if I come to the conclusion that it's fine to do so.
But if you do that, then the kernel
needs to guarantee you that it's safe.
For example, continuing the make-not system call
after you inspected the arguments is safe
because the kernel will just allow the creation
of any device.
So I have another question.
Because you said about MKNOT that if you MKNOT
like this device, that nothing protects you against reading
or writing into this, right?
But there is this devices C group
where you can actually protect this device from being
written to or read from.
And this is what Docker does, for example.
So are you doing this in legacy?
I'm sorry, I only get about 20% of what you're saying.
Well, of times what we'll do is that I'm going to be outside
and we can just talk because you also have questions.
So just follow me and we'll talk.
It's going to be easier.
Thank you very much.