Okay. I think we're ready to start. Oh, excellent. This time it worked perfectly. Thank you
so much. Yeah. Chris is going to talk about C Group V2, seven years of C Group V2 in the
kernel, very exciting time, and the future of Linux resource control. Take it away.
Hello, everybody. Oh, yes, please go on. Thank you. That's it. I'm done. Good boy. Hello. I'm
Chris Down. I work as a kernel engineer at Meta. I work on the kernels memory management
subsystem, especially I'm a contributor to C Groups, which are one of the things which
underpins our modern love of containers. I'm also a maintainer of the system D project.
So there's two things on this slide, which you can hate me for. Most of the time I'm
thinking about how we can make Linux just a little bit more reliable, just a little bit
more usable at scale. We have a million plus machines. We can't just buy more RAM. It's
not really a thing we can do. So we need to extract the absolute maximum from every single
machine. Otherwise, there's a huge loss of capacity that could result. So that's the
kind of thing I want to talk to you about today. However, the last seven years we have
done this at Meta, how we've improved the reliability and capacity and extracted more
efficiency. At Meta and in industry, we are increasingly facing this kind of problem where
we can't effectively solve scaling problems just by throwing hardware at the problem.
We can't construct data centers fast enough. We can't source clean power fast enough. We
have hundreds of thousands of machines and we just can't afford to waste capacity because
any small loss in capacity on a single machine translates to a very large amount at scale.
Ultimately what we need to do is use resources more efficiently and we need to build the
kernel infrastructure in order to do that. Another challenge that we have is that many
huge site incidents for companies like us and companies of our size are caused by lacking
resource control. Not being able to control things like CPU, IO memory and the like is
one of the most pervasive causes of incidents and outages across our industry. And we need
to sustain an initiative industry-wide in order to fix this. So how does all of this
relate to this C-groups thing in the title? So C-groups are a kernel mechanism to balance
and control and isolate things like memory, CPU, IO, things that you share across a machine,
things that processes share. And I'm sure if you've operated containers before, which
I'm going to assume that you have, judging by the fact you're in this room, otherwise
you may be lost in looking for the AI room, you know, every single modern container runtime
uses this. Stalker uses it, CoreS uses it, Kubernetes uses it, SystemD uses it. The reason
they use it is because it's the most mature platform to do this work and it solves a lot
of the long-standing problems which we had with kind of classic resource control in the
form of U-limits and things like that. C-groups have existed for about 14 years now and they
have changed a lot in that time. Most notably, seven years ago in kernel 4.5 we released
C-group 2. I gave a whole talk around the time when that happened, why we were moving
to a totally new interface, why we weren't just iterating on the old interface. And if
you're interested in a really in-depth look at that, then here's a talk which you can
go and take a look at. But the most fundamental change really is that in C-group 2 what happens
is that you enable or disable resources in the context of a particular C-group. In C-group
1 what you have is a hierarchy for memory, a hierarchy for CPU and the two will never
meet. Those two things are completely independent. SystemD, when it creates things in C-group
2.0, it will name them the same. They get called something.slice or something.service
but they have no relation to each other across resources. But in C-group 2 you have just
a single C-group and you enable or disable resources in the context of that particular
C-group so you can enable, say, memory control and IO control together. That might seem like
an aesthetic kind of concern but it's really not. Without this major API change we simply
cannot use C-groups to do complex resource control. Take the following scenario. Memory
starts to run out on your machine. So when we start to run out of memory on pretty much
any modern operating system what do you do? Well you try and go and free some up. So we
start to reclaim some page caches. We start to reclaim maybe some anonymous pages if we
have swap. And this results in disk IO. And if we're particularly memory bound and it's
really hard to free pages and we're having to walk the pages over and over and over to
try and find stuff to free then it's going to cost a non-travel amount of CPU cycles
to do so. Looking through available memory to find pages which can be free can be extremely
expensive on memory bound workloads. On some highly loaded or memory bound systems it can
take a double digit amount of CPU from the machine just to do this walking. It's a highly
expensive process. And without having the single resource hierarchy we cannot take into account
these transfers between the different resources how one leads to another because they're all
completely independent. If you've been in the containers to everyone before you've probably
thinking I've seen this guy before and I think he's given this exact talk about three years
ago. I'm sure some of you think that already. Well the company name isn't the only thing
which has changed since 2020. Also some C-groups things have changed since 2020 and obviously
I don't want to rehash the same things over and over. I don't want to bore you. So this
talk will mostly be about the changes since the last time I was here in 2020. We're just
a little bit of context setting just a little bit. This talk is really about the process
of getting resource isolation working at scale. It's what it needs to happen in production
not just in a theoretical concern. The elephant in the room of course is COVID. The last three
years have seen pretty significant changes in behavior due to COVID especially for a
platform like Facebook which we own of course. This was by about 27% over what you would
usually expect and this came at a time where not only you're seeing increased demand but
you literally can't go out and buy memory. You can't go out and buy more CPUs. You can't
go out and buy more disks because there's a shortage because there's COVID. So what we
really needed was to make more efficient use of the existing resources on the machine.
We need to have an acceleration or existing efforts around resource control in order to
do that to make things more efficient. Now almost every single time that I give this
sounds like a personal point of concern. Every time I give this talk somebody on Hacker News
comments, why don't you just get some more memory? Now I don't know how trivial people
in this room think that is when you've got several million servers but it is slightly
difficult sometimes. For example there's a huge amount of cost involved there and not
just the money which is indeed substantial and I'm very glad it's not coming out of my
bank account but also in things like power draw, in things like thermals, in things like
hardware design trade-offs. Not to mention during COVID you just couldn't get these
kind of, you couldn't get a hard drive, you couldn't get some memory. You'd go down to
your local Best Buy and do it but that's about it. So not really an option. So here's a simple
little proposition for you, for anyone in the room who wants to be brave. How do you view
memory usage for a process in Linux? Oh come on. Free! My man said free. Oh lord.
This was a trap. So, alright. I appreciate it though. Big up about that. So yeah, so free and
the like really only measure like one type of memory. They do have caches and buffers in the
side but the thing is, okay so for free or for PS which were shut at the back, you know you do
see something like the resident set size and you see some other details and you might be thinking
hey you know that's fine like I don't really care about some of the other things. That's the bit
which my application is really using. For example, we don't necessarily think that our programs
rely on caches and buffers to operate in any sustainable way but the problem is the answer
for any sufficiently complex system is almost certainly that a lot of those caches and buffers
are not optional. They are basically essential. Let's take Chrome just as a facile example.
The Chrome Binary Code segment is over 130 megs. He's a chunky boy. He is. He's a big boy. We load
this code into memory. We do it gradually. We're not maniacs. We do it gradually but you know we
do it as part of the page cache. But if we want to execute some particular part of Chrome, you know
this cache isn't just nice to have the cache that has the code in it that runs this particular part
of Chrome. We literally cannot make any forward progress without that part of the cache and the
same goes for caches for the files you're loading especially for something like Chrome. You probably
do have a lot of caches so eventually those pages are going to have to make their way into the
working set. They're going to have to make their way into main memory. In another particularly
egregious case, we have a demon at Matter and this demon aggregates metrics across a machine.
It sends them to centralized storage. As part of this, what it does is it runs a whole bunch of
junky scripts and these junky scripts go and collect things across the machine. I mean we've
all got one. We've all got this kind of demon where you collect all kind of junky stuff and you
don't really know what it does but it sends some nice metrics and it looks nice. One of the things
we were able to demonstrate is while the team had this demon thought that it took about 100 to
150 megabytes to run using the things that we'll talk about in this talk, it actually was more
like two gigabytes. So the difference is quite substantial on some things. You could be quite
mis-underestimating what is taking memory on your machine. In Seagrory 2, we have this file called
memory.current that measures the current memory usage for the C group including everything
like caches, buffers, kernel objects, so on. So job done, right? Well no. The problem is here that
whenever somebody comes to these talks and I say something like don't use RSS to measure your
application, they go and say oh we've added a new thing called memory.current and it measures
everything. Great, I'm just going to put some metrics based on that. But it's quite important
to understand what that actually means to have everything here, right? The very fact that we
are not talking about just the resident set size anymore means the ramifications are fundamentally
different. We have caches, buffers, socket memory, TCP memory, kernel objects, all kind of stuff in
here and that's exactly how it should be because we need that to prevent abuse of these resources,
which are valid resources across the system. They are things we actually need to run.
So understanding why reasoning about memory.current might be more complicated than it seems comes
down to why as an industry we tended to gravitate towards measuring RSS in the first place. We
don't measure RSS because it measures anything useful. We measure it because it's really fucking
easy to measure. That's the reason we measure RSS. There's no other reason. It doesn't measure
anything very useful. It kind of tells you vaguely maybe what your application might be doing kind
of, but it doesn't tell you anything of any of the actually interesting parts of your application.
Only the bits you pretty much already knew. So memory.current suffers from pretty much exactly
the opposite problem, which is it tells you the truth and don't really know how to deal with it.
Don't really know how to deal with being told how much memory application is using. For example,
if you set an 8 gigabyte memory limit in CROOPy2, how big is memory.current going to be on a machine
which has no other thing running on it? It's probably going to be 8 gigabytes because we've
decided that we're going to fill it with all kind of nice stuff. There's no reason we should
evict that. There's no reason we should take away these nice K-mem caches. There's no reason we
should take away these slabs because we have free memory. So why not? Why not keep them around?
So if there was no pressure for this to shrink from any outside scope, then the slack is just
going to expand until it reaches your limit. So what should we do? How should we know what the real
needed amount of memory is at a given time? So let's take an example, Linux kernel build,
for example, which with no limits has a peak memory.current of just over 800 megabytes. In
CROOPy2, we have this tunable called memory.high. This tunable reclaims memory from the CROOP
until it goes back under some threshold. It just keeps on reclaiming and reclaiming and
reclaiming and throttling until you reach back under. So right now, things take about four minutes
with no limits. This is about how long it takes to build the kernel. And when I apply a throttling
like a reclaim threshold of 600 megabytes, actually, you know the job finishes roughly
about the same amount of time, maybe a second more, with about 25% less available memory at peak.
And the same even happens when we go down to 400 megabytes. Now we're using half the memory that
we originally used with only a few seconds more wall time. It's a pretty good trade-off.
However, if we just go just a little bit further, then things just never even complete. We have to
control see the build, right? And this is nine minutes in. It still ain't done. So we know that
the process needs somewhere between 300 and 400 megabytes of memory, but it's pretty error prone
to try and work out what the exact value is. So to get an accurate number for services at scale,
which are even more difficult than this because they dynamically shrink and expand depending on
load, we need a better automated way to do that. So determining the exact amount of memory required
by an application is a really, really difficult and error prone task, right? So SEMPY is this
kind of simple self-contained tool to continually poll what's called pressure-stall information,
or PSI. Pressure-stall information is essentially a new thing we've added in Cigar2 to determine
whether a particular resource is oversaturated. And we've never really had a metric like this
in the learnings kernel before. We've had many related metrics. For example, for memory, we have
things like page caches and buffer usage and so on. But we don't really know how to tell pressure
or over-subscription from an efficient use of the system. Those two are very difficult to tell apart,
even with using things like page scans or so on. It's pretty difficult. So in SEMPY, what we do is
we use these PSI pressure-stall metrics to measure the amount of time which threads in a particular
C group were stuck doing, in this case, memory work. So this pressure equals 0.16, then kind of
halfway down the slide, means that 0.16 percent of the time I could have been doing more productive
work, but I've been stuck doing memory work. This could be things like waiting for a kernel memory
log. It could be things like being throttled. It could be waiting for a reclaim to finish.
Even more than that, it could be memory-related IO, which can also dominate, to be honest. Things
like refolking file content into the page cache or swapping in. And pressure is essentially saying,
if I had a bit more memory, I would be able to run so much faster, 0.16 percent faster.
So using PSI and memory.high, what SEMPY does is adjust enough memory pressure on a C group to
evict cold memory pages that aren't essential for workload performance. It's an integral controller
which dynamically adapts these memory peaks and troughs. An example case being something like
a web server, which is somewhere where we have used it. When more requests come, we see that the
pressure is growing and we expand the memory.high limit. When fewer requests are coming, we see
that and we start to decrease the amount of working set which we give again. So it can be used to
answer the question, how much memory does my application actually use over time? And in this
case we find for the compulgial, the answer is about like 340 megabytes or so and that's fine.
You might be asking yourself, what are the benefits of this shrinking? Why does this even matter
to be honest? Surely when you are starting to run out of memory, Linux is going to do it anyway.
And you're not wrong. That's true. But the thing is, what we kind of need here is to get ahead
of memory shortages which could be bad and amortize the work ahead of time. When your machine is
already highly contended, it's already being driven into the ground and going towards the
umkiller, it's pretty hard to say, hey bro, could you just like give me some pages right now?
It's not exactly like what's on its mind. It's probably desperately trying to keep the atomic
pool going. So there's another thing as well which is, it's pretty good for determining
regressions which is what a lot of people use for RSS4. This is the way we found out that
that demon was using 2 gigabytes of memory instead of 150 megabytes of memory. So it's pretty good
for finding out, hey, how much does my application actually need to run? So the combination of these
things means that Senpai is an essential part of how we do workload stacking on matter. And it not
only gives us an accurate read on what the demand is right now but allows us to adjust
stacking expectations depending on what the workload is doing. This feeds into another one
of our efforts around efficiency which is improving memory offloading. So traditionally on most
operating systems you have only one real memory offloading location which is Yadisk. Even if you
don't have swap that's true because you do things like demand paging, right? You page things in
gradually and you also have to you know evict and get things in the file cache. So we're talking
also here about like a lot of granular intermediate areas that could be considered for some page
offloading for infrequently accessed pages but they're not really so frequently used.
Getting this data into main memory again though can be very different in terms of how difficult it
is depending on how far up the triangle you go, right? For example it's much easier to do it on
an SSD than a hard drive because hard drives don't, well they're slow and they also don't
tolerate random headseeking very well. But there are more granular gradual things that we can do
as well. For example one thing we can do is to start look at strategies outside of hardware.
One of the problems with the duality of either being in RAM or on the disk is that even your disk
even if it's quite fast, even if it's flash, it tends to be quite a few orders of magnitude slower
than your main memory is. So one area which we have been heavily invested in is looking at what
one might term warm pages. In Linux we have talked a lot about hot pages and cold pages if you look
in the memory management code but there is like this kind of part of the working set which yes
I do need it relatively frequently but I don't need it to make forward progress all the time. So
Zswap is one of these things we can use for that. It's essentially a feature of the Linux kernel
which compresses pages which looks like they will compress well and are not too hot into a separate
pool in main memory. We do have to page fold them back in into main memory again if we actually
want to use them of course but it's several orders of magnitude faster than trying to get it off the
disk. We still do have this swap for infrequently access pages that tends to be quite a bit cold
working set as well but you know this is kind of like this tiered hierarchy where we want to have
warm pages in Zswap, hot pages in main memory and kind of cold pages in swap. One problem we had
here was that even when we configured the kernel to swap as aggressively as possible it still wouldn't
do it. If you've actually looked at the swap code and I've had the unfortunate misery of working on
it, you'll learn that swap code was implemented a very long time ago by the people who knew what
swap did and how things worked but none of them are around to tell us what the hell anything means
anymore and it's very confusing. So I can't even describe to you how the old algorithm works because
it has about 500 heuristics and I don't know why any of them are there. So for this reason you know
we try to think how can we make this a little bit more efficient. We are using non-rotational
disks now. We have Zswap, we have flash disks, we have SSDs, we want to make an algorithm which
can handle this better. So from kernel 5.8 we have been working on a new algorithm which has already
landed. So first we have code to track all swap ins and cache misses across the system. So for every
cache page we're having to page fault and evict and page fault and evict and page fault and evict
over and over again. What we want to do is try and page out a heap page instead. If we're unlucky
and this heap page actually it turns out to be hot then you know no biggie like we we've made a
mistake but we'll try a different one next time. We do have some heuristics to try and work out which
one is hot and which one is not but they are kind of expensive so we don't use a lot of them. However
you know if if we are lucky and the heap page does stay swapped out then that's one more page
which we can use for file caches and we can use it for other processes and this means that we can
engage swap a lot more readily in most scenarios. Importantly though we are not adding ioload,
this doesn't increase ioload or decrease endurance of the disk. We are just more intentional about
in choosing how to apply the ioload, it doesn't double up. We only trade one type of paging for
another and our goal here is to reach an optimal state where the optimal state is doing the minimum
amount of iO in order to sustain workload performance. So ideally what we do is have this tiered model
of you know like I said main memory, Zswap and swap on disk. This is super simple idea compared
to the old model. The old algorithm has a lot of kind of weird heuristics as I mentioned, a lot of
penalties, a lot of kind of strange things. In general it was not really written for an era where
SSDs exist or where Zswap exists so it's understandable that it needed some some care and attention.
So what were the effects of this change in prod? Like what actually happened? So on web servers
we not only noticed like an increase in performance but we also noticed a decrease in heat memory by
about two gigabytes or so out of about 16 gigabytes total. The cache grew to fill this newly freed
space and it grew by about two gigabytes. From about two gigabytes of cache to four gigabytes of cache
we also observed a measurable increase in web server performance from this change which is deeply
encouraging and these are all indications that you know we are now starting to reclaim the right
things. Actually we are making better decisions because things are looking pretty positive here.
So not only that but you see a decrease in disk iO because we are actually doing things correctly.
We are making the correct decisions and it's not really that often that you get a benefit in
performance disk iO memory usage instead of having to trade off between them right. So it probably
indicates that this is the better solution for this kind of era. This also meant that on some
workloads we now had opportunities to stack where we did not have opportunities to stack before
like running say multiple kinds of ads jobs or multiple kinds of web servers on top of each other.
Many machines don't use up all of their resources but they use up just enough that it's pretty hard
to stack something else on top of it because you're using just enough that it's not actually enough
to sustainably run to workload side by side. So this is another thing where we've managed to kind
of push the needle just a little bit so that you can make quite a bit more use efficiency out of the
servers that exist. The combination of changes to the swap algorithm using Z swap and squeezing
workloads using senpai was a huge part of our operation during COVID. All of these things
acting together we termed TMO which stands for transparent memory offloading and you can see
some of the results we've had in production here. In some cases we were able to save up to 20%
of critical fleet-wide workloads memory with either neutral or even in some cases positive
effects on workload performance. So this opens up a lot of opportunities obviously in terms of
reliability, stacking and future growth. This whole topic has a huge amount of cover I really
could just do an entire talk on this. If you want to learn more I do recommend the post which is
linked at the bottom my colleagues Johannes and Dan wrote an article with a lot more depth on you
know how we achieve what we achieved and on things like CXL memory as well. So let's come back to
this this slide from earlier. We briefly touched on the fact that if bounded one resource can just
turn into another a particularly egregious case being memory turning into IO when it gets bounded.
For this reason it might seem counterintuitive but we always need controls on IO when we have
controls on memory otherwise memory pressure will always just directly translate to disk IO.
Probably the most attuned way to solve this is to try to limit disk bandwidth or disk IOPS.
However this doesn't really manifest usually very well in reality. If you think about any
modern storage device they tend to be quite complex they're queue devices you can throw a lot of
commands at them in parallel and when you do that you often find that hey you know magically it can
do more things. The same reason we have IO schedulers because we can optimize what we do inside the
disk. Also the mixture of IO really matters like reads versus writes sequential versus random even
on SSDs these things tend to matter and it's really hard to determine a single metric for loadedness
for a storage device because the cost of one IO operation or one block of data
is extremely variable depending on the wider context. So it's also really punitive to just
have a limit on you know how much can I write how many IOPS can I do because even if nobody
else is using the disk you're still slowed down to this level there's no opportunity to make the
most of the disk when nobody else is doing anything right. So it's not really good for this kind of
best effort bursty work on a machine which we would like to do. So the first way that we try to
avoid this problem is by using latency as a metric for workload health. So what we might try and do
is apply a maximal target latency for IO completions on the main workload and if we exceed that we
start dialing back other C groups with lucid latency requirements back to their own configured
thresholds. What this does is this prevents an application from thrashing on memory so much
that it just kills IO across the system. This actually works really well for systems where there's
only one workload but the problem comes when you have a multi workload stacked case like this.
Here we have two high priority workloads which are stacked on a single machine. One has an IO
dot latency of 10 milliseconds the other has 30 milliseconds but the problem here is as soon as
workload one gets into trouble everyone else is going to suffer and there's no way around that.
We're just going to penalize them and there's no way to say you know how bad is the situation
really and is it really them causing the problem. This is fine if you know the thing you're throttling
is just best effort but here we have two important workloads right so how can we solve this? So our
solution is this thing called IO dot cost which might look very similar at first but notice the
omission of the units. These are not units in milliseconds these are weights in a similar way
to how we do CPU scheduling. So how do we know what 40, 60 or 100 mean in this context? Well they
add up to 200 so the idea is if you are saturating your disk you know best effort will get 40 will
get I guess 20 percent of the work it'll workload one will get 50 and workload two will get 30.
So it balances out based on this kind of shares or weights like model. How do we know when we
reach this 100 percent of saturation though? So what IO dot cost does is build a linear model
of your disk over time it sees how the disk responds to these variable loads passively
and it works based on things like you know read or write IO whether it's random or sequential the
size of the IO. So it boils down this quite complex operation of you know how much can my disk actually
do into a linear model which it which it handles itself. It has a kind of a QOS model you can
implement but there's also a basic on-the-fly model using Q-depth so you can read more about in the
links at the bottom I won't waffle on too much but it is something which you can use to do kind of
effective IO control. In the old days I came to this room and talked about C-group B2 and the
historical response was basically that's nice Docker doesn't support it though so please leave.
I've had a nice chat with some Docker lads. No the Docker people are very nice and so are all the
other container people and what's happened is we have it almost everywhere almost everywhere C-group
B2 is a thing we have quite a diversity of container run times and police report is basically
supported everywhere. So even if nothing changes from your side moving to C-group B2 means that you
know you get significantly more reliable accounting for free. We spent quite a while working with
Docker and system defoaks and so on and so forth to get things working and we're also really thankful
to Fedora for making C-group B2 the default since Fedora 32 as well as making things more reliable
behind the scenes for users this also you know got some people's ass into gear when they had an
issue on their GitHub on their GitHub that says it doesn't work in Fedora so cheers Fedora people.
It was kind of a good signal that you know this is what we are actually doing this is what we as
an industry as a technology community are actually doing and that was quite helpful.
The KDE in Genome folks have also been busy using C-groups to give a better management of that
kind of desktop handling. David Edmondson and Henry Chain from KDE in particular gave this talk at
KDE Academy. The title of the talk was using C-groups to make everything amazing. Now I'm not
brazen enough to title my talk that but I'll just let it speak for itself for that one.
It basically goes over the use of C-groups and C-group B2 for resource control and for interactive
responsiveness on the desktop so this is definitely kind of a developing space obviously there's been
a lot of work on the server side here but if you're interested in that I definitely recommend
you know giving the talk a watch. It really goes into challenges they had and a unique feature
C-group B2 has to solve those. Finally Android is also using the metrics exported by the PSI
project in order to detect and prevent memory pressure events which affect the user experience
as you can imagine on Android interactive latency is extremely important. It would really suck if
you're about to click a button and then you click it and that requires allocating memory and the
whole phone freezes. I mean it does still happen sometimes but obviously this is something which
they're trying to work on and we've been working quite closely with them to integrate the PSI
project into the Android. Hopefully this talk gave you some ideas about things you'd like to try
out for yourself. We're still very actively improving kernel resource control. It might have
been seven years since we started but you know we still have plenty of things we want to do
and what we really need is your feedback. What we really need is more examples of
how the community is using C-group B2 and problems and issues you've encountered. Obviously everyone's
needs are quite different and I and others are quite eager to know what we could be doing to help
you, what we could be doing to make things better, what we could be doing to make things more intuitive
because there's definitely work to be done there and I'll be around after the talk if you want to
chat but feel free to drop me an email message me on master.com always happy to hear feedback or
suggestions. I've been Chris Down and this has been seven years of C-group B2, future of Linux
resource control. Thank you very much.