the next talk is by Scott. He's going to talk about quick starting, secure container storage
using squash of us overlay and de-embarity. Okay. My audible. Yes. Okay. Hi. Yeah, I'm
Scott Moser. I work for Cisco Systems. And over the past three years or so, we've been
working on a project internally that is that implements a lot of the image based workflows
that was in another that we were talking about in another room. And just kind of building
up that piece by piece. That is called project machine. And so that's what I primarily am
working on and stuff around that. So through that, we kind of came to some needs and desires
to change how we were running containers. And that's what we got here. The goal, the
goals pretty simple of this talk and our goal was really just to replace replace the tar
and gzip format in an OCI image with squash of s and discuss why there's benefits of that.
I'll show some comparisons of what what the registry data looks like what the registry
sees and compare it. What the runtime looks like and what what's different there. And
then I'll give a little demo. And the sales pitch part, we use there's two tools that
are that are ours. They're open source, but they're they're decent tools. So show them
here as stacker. And we signed with cosine, we published his odd and then we run with
LXC. Probably everybody's here is familiar with LXC. So in order to get squash FS file
system squash FS file system images in a registry, it looks a lot like it does in it with tar
gzip images. We put just files that go into registry. The metadata contains a list of
images. All right. Yeah. Let's see. The index is a list of images. Each of those images
has a list of layers. And then the difference really is just in the type of the media type
of the layer. So we get Yeah, and then and then first. And so we both have a sign check
some of the tar ball in both cases, or the image right that data is there so you can
know what it is. And then in addition on the squash FS one, we've put some we put the
DM Verity hash, the root hash in the metadata and we sign that that come into play later.
Oh, backward. There we go. So now run type at runtime that the the images really do look
this very similar. Both of them they we uncompressed with tar and gzip or we we we mount we either
copy the image out of the repository to a place on the on the disk. And then we can
either share that that same location for every container, or you can mount it. You can take
a copy of it for each container that you're going to launch. You know, that path makes
garbage collection a little bit easier. And then in tar world, if you want to compare
the the data that you're running, you want to compare the file system that is running
versus the thing that you downloaded. That's a real pain in the rear end, right? You got
to basically look at all the contents of all the files and look at their modification times
and compare that to the compressed tar ball, you know, extract it and just compare it to
file system trees. It's a real pain with with squash FS. The image is there. You it was read
only and you just shot summit and the shot some matches the shot some that you downloaded
and you know you're good. Right? So there's a lot of benefit out of that. The primary reason
that we kind of got here and we're looking into something else was really that once you've
extracted a tar file system out, there's kind of no way to put it back in, you know, you
can't ever really get back and and verify that you're running what you what you thought.
So and then in the runtime, other benefits of squash of S and Verity is we get in privilege
with privileged mounts. If we're running a container that is real root and can do a mount,
then we can use that deem verity data that we got in there so that the kernel can actually
then verify that the data is used as is as it as it reads it off the desk. And then but
is unprivileged when we're unprivileged running unprivileged containers. If you can't do
a mount, we do a mount with squash fuse and there you can't you can't use deem verity.
There's no to my knowledge way to use a block device or use the device mapper and get block
device get deem verity without being real root. So let's see. And then another benefit
is the file system doesn't implement right, right? So you're not going to be a tent. You're
not going to be attacked from the file system. Nobody's going to be replacing a binary there.
If they're going to get to it, they have to come in like from the other side and modify
the disk, the data, but that should be caught via check some more deem verity. So but that
comes at a little bit of cost because basically everybody and their brother can read a tar
ball right and at this point but not but squash F as is a little bit less readable, although
there's there's good tools, but they're not as widely as widely deployed. Oh, yeah, and
I just want to point out like so really the changes here it's it's not it's not evolution.
It's not revolutionary. It's evolutionary. It's a small change. There's changes being
discussed for like OCI image v2 or v2 repositories and different file formats that would really
kind of revolutionize thing and do much, much, much better than this. But this is a significant
improvement upon upon what's there right now. So I said there overlay overlay fs doesn't
have any right support or let's see I'm sorry squash fs doesn't have right support so you
end up having to use overlay overlay again was talked about in the image container or
in the image based workflow track all the time. I'm not sure how well people are aware
of here, but I think it's probably generally fairly common knowledge. It's a kernel file
system. It's very mature and you can basically stack stack file system data on top of each
other and get the same basic tree that the tar that extracting a series of layers for
OCI image gets you. I don't know really which came first if it was the overlay file system
in the kernel or in the whiteouts there or the whiteouts that are in a tar ball layer.
I don't know which came first, but they look very similar. So the ones we're using and
the ones that stack or stores in its stack or stores in the images are just the same
as the kernel writes them. So we just use the overlay there and then it's a it's simple
very use useful. Yeah. Yeah. And then I say overlay bugs are present in the kernel. It
has slightly different semantics than some other file systems, but largely over the past
10 years they have been really well squashed. So this it works real well. And then the last
thing is that if you're using an overlay, you can easily see the changes that that were
made to a file system because they're basically all on a single tree. You can look under you
can look at the overlay layer and see these are the files that were written. So DM Verity
is the device mapper verification. And it's just a feature in the kernel that basically
provides uses technology called a Merkel tree, which allows you to provide a hash of the
top and then each each blocks and cascading down are just our hashes that are built into
that. So basically you can mount the thing up immediately and start reading. And what
will happen is you you get bad reads if there's bad data or I learned today that you can also
you could trigger like a crash or something if data was not if there was an integrity
about violation there. So let's see. Yeah. So that's the invari very useful. But again,
that only works as real root. So let's go ahead and try to do a demo of this now. Yeah,
you anybody if you're if you think I'm just giving the sales pitch maybe I am I don't
say a lot of good things about software in general. But these two that I'm selling are
reasonable pieces of software and they may help you. So we're going to build with stacker.
We're going to sign things with cosine. We're going to publish to Zot. And we're going to
run Alex and we're going to run things with LXC. Let's see. See how this goes. This worked
at 3am last night. So you know, let's see. I just do that. All right. So this is a stacker
file. And then again, stackers are built tool. It's really very similar to Docker in where
it's capable of it runs completely unprivileged. It can run it can also run privilege but runs
completely unprivileged and allows you to build OCI images. You can build them either
in tar or in squash squash FF file system type. Let's see. It is it's a very mature project
and it's work and it works for it's working towards CNCF inclusion. So it it works and
it pretty much works out of the box. It's not single binary. It runs on most on distros
pretty close out of the box. So you don't need to have a huge stack to try it out. So
I'm going to go ahead and do stacker build. I'm going to I'm going to do this because
yeah, there's no way I was going to type that right. All right. So there we said build. I
want to build both this the layer types tar and squash FF and and then substitute. It
just provides some mechanism to substitute inside the the YAML file. I don't want to
go to Docker right now. I'd rather go to you know, a local a local's off that I'm running.
So there it didn't actually build that clearly. It didn't it didn't do all that apt and everything.
It was already built. So it reused its cache. And now we can go ahead and cosine or yeah,
we'll publish those images. So the oh yeah. So there, here's the two images that it built.
It built one called squa talk talk dash talk talk root dash squash FF and one just called
talk root and the one without that is a star and then up there is GZIP and then you can
see that this is a these are the same image manifest type. And so largely tools will still
be able to read the squash files as the squash data that we put up like scope a will still
copy it down. You can still move them around without a whole lot of extra work. Let's see.
So now go ahead and publish those
publish those two images. And that just uploaded them to a local's that's running here that
I've got running on on local host. And let's see now. That right? What did I mean? Cosine
come on. I didn't mean that. So go ahead and generate a cosine care a key pair and then
that is enforced currently in Etsy containers. That yeah, that's there basically I say anything
that come from local host there needs to be signed by by this key that we just did. So
we're going to need to go ahead and sign that stuff. Cosine is telling me that in that log
verbiage that nobody's really going to read is telling me that you should not just you
know refer to an image in a repository by its name you should give the hash because otherwise
it might not be what you think you're signing. So that's bad practice. Shame on me. All right.
See so now we've got now we've got stuff published into Zot. Our local Zot is running. And we
can see these images are in Zot. And Zot is just Zot is another thing that we run. It's
a it's a it runs a OCI registry. It's really it's really good software. You run it locally
very easily. It's one binary. You take it a little bit of config and then you can you
can run a you know a Docker registry. The biggest benefit that I see out of it is that I don't
I don't hit the Docker. Gosh bandwidth threshold right because out of our company out whatever
it is out of that lab that usually gets hit by like 7am in the morning. So if you don't
have something caching then you're out of luck. Let's see. So now we've got images in
our local Zot. We've got we've signed them. We built them signed them and published them
to a local repository. And now I can say now I can go ahead and try to run one. So this
is just this is the status quo. This is a create a user namespace container. And then
I can elixir elixir start my in. I meant now. Let you watch it boot. So there's just that's
just the tar one. It extracted that to the file system. It mounted up the file system
in a user namespace and it let me run. Come on now. Okay now we can do the same thing.
But instead of using the talk root of fast will use the talk root of fast squash of fast.
We'll name this image. So that then it copied the OCI it pulled down the OCI data out of
the Zot repository put on disk and then and then is ready for me to run it when I run
it. I hope. There. All right. So now I've got running on the system. Let's see. Here
I've got an overlay file system show it like is mounted underneath that
these squash fused binaries got mounted one one and then another and then another and then
an overlay over the top of those three. So this is running completely completely unprivileged.
I can mount those up and use them in place. Go ahead and see how much time in my mind.
Okay. Then I think I can show another one running as root but it's basically oh actually
yeah I will go ahead and try to start that just because if I can. The one that the thing
the show there is that. Oh no I should end and ask and take questions. Yeah because I
was saying I wasn't sure if you were. So yeah so thanks for listening. I just want to thank
God for letting me be here and you know spend another day on software and complaining about
software and think my team for letting and for helping me out my family for letting me
be gone and Cisco on you guys for coming. This is project machine and anybody got any
questions. Sorry. We have time for one question. All right. Cool. Very clear. Feel free to
reach out and thank you. Thank you.