We're starting now. Please. Please quiet down.
Hello folks. Today we are here to talk about Fedora
Corvus and how you can use that to do some fun stuff. The fun stuff being, you know,
hosting your own dedicated multiplayer server so that you and your friends can have some fun.
I'm joined here by Sumantro, Myself, Akash, Deep Dhar. We both work for Red Hat, but we
are Fedora Project contributors and part of Fedora Council as well. So we welcome you to this talk.
Right. So about the things that we would want to talk about, the first and the foremost thing
would of course be the OS, the thing that we run our containers on and why exactly should you give a
damn about it when there are like a plethora of Linux distributions out there with their own twists
and turns attached to them. The next thing is of course putting that operating system to use.
That of course is to have our own dedicated Minecraft server, understand how that process works
and how easy or difficult it can be to actually put that to use. We'll put that to use again for
the Valheim server too because guess what? The community is great and the folks have always
created containers and when it comes to containers, we always have something, some kind of platform
to make use of. And by all means, if you trust me enough, you can totally scan this QR code and
it will lead you to the documentation so you can totally go along with the talk because this will
be more hands-on. We'll be doing stuff over here and we'll be making you folks understand as to
what is happening behind the scenes and why exactly are we doing that. Or you can totally head
over to the schedules page on the container step room and find our links over there. So
documentation is over there as well. Speaking of the operating system that we're going to talk
about, what exactly is Fedora CoreOS? To begin with, it's a set of packages that's very minimal in
nature but it's very focused to the container-based workflows. So you won't get to see a lot of
bells and whistles out of the box. Sure, there's an option to add those by yourself whenever you
feel like. But then again, it's the networking, it's the container-based workflows like Moby,
Podman, which I installed over there as well as some tools like Firewall that you would need to
make sure that people actually connect to your containers and be able to do what they want to
do, which are pre-installed, which gives you just enough of a stuff to get started and a canvas to
actually add your own distributions, your own packages on the top of it and grow upon it as you
go on. And there's this thing called RPMOS tree, which is based on LibOS tree. The entire file
system is transactional in nature, which essentially means that if I were to add packages on the top
of the existing deployment, well, an existing set of installed packages, I can do so by ease
without actually worrying that, oh, what's going to happen if I add this bleeding edge package
when my deployment stopped failing to work? And if it does, you can always find your way back.
It's a good kind of a workflow. So if you understand Git, it's pretty much like that. So you can
always rebase your deployments, your own set collection of packages at any point in time,
and just fall back at any point in time you want to go back to. The next thing is the fact that
this is secure as well as scalable. So we, of course, would like to have this not only deployed in
bare-metal servers, but as well in a plethora of VMs having their own set of purposes. Now,
the way we do that is by the use of configuration. And it's kind of difficult that you need to
configure like tens of thousands of machines with hand. So guess what? You don't. You use
something called beauty in configuration, which is a human readable form of something called
ignition. And what it exactly does is you specify what kind of a change that you want to make on
that operating system. Some users that you want to add, some files that you want to make create,
some networking rules, firewall rules, services to start stuff like that. You can do so so that
when in the first boot you get the operating system exactly the way you want. So you don't really
have to install stuff and then configure it and then do that like a thousand times just because
scalability is a thing. The next thing that I want to talk about is the fact that this operating
system is available in not just x86 underscore 64, but in a lot of other places architecture such as
AR 64 and ST90X as well. And we plan on providing the support for other operating systems architectures
in the coming times. Speaking of the minimal set of packages, how minimal is it that we're talking?
Let's give that a number. So we have like three release sets, the one for stable, the testing,
as well as next they are determined by the number at the penultimate decimal place. So 3.0 is stable,
2.x is testing and 1.x is next. And you can totally see what those purposes are for and why
exactly would someone want to go for a next or stable or vice versa. So say for instance if there's
a contributor who wants to develop this thing they want to test all the bleeding is packages that
come to this platform, they know what they can choose. And for the ones who really want to set up a
server for their home people they don't really want to move around a lot of stuff. They can either go
for stable or they can reach out to our friends at CentOS because they have a CentOS team core as
too. So how exactly does this operating system become secure and scalable? I mean I do sure like
giving a business pitch because it's all buzzwords. So there are ways to make sure that the packages
that you have installed or to say layered on the top of your existing installation, the way it gets
automatically updated is very much in your control, which essentially means that it can go out in the
open, start downloading everything, every new and bleeding it stuff if you ask it to or just hold
back on it just because you want a stable operating system, you want to really curate the packages
that you end up having so you have a lesser variness to updates that you end up having. So it's
totally in your control and by all means there are ways to totally disable automated updates as and
when you see fit. And these updates for the packages that you have installed, these don't get
applied as soon as they get installed but rather you kind of make those applications of those
updates when you want them to happen. Usually it's a reboot because well the service actually
happens to go through all the packages and refresh them based on the updates that has happened in
the last boot but you can always do it either live or in the next time as well. So at any point in
time you feel like that a certain update has gone through which should not have, you can rest assured
because that has not yet applied and you can always fall back to the previous deployment. And oh,
I just happened to explain the last point. So that is rolling back whenever you feel like it. So
depending on how you want to use this, you can use it on a Raspberry Pi if you are having one on
your shelf gathering dust or you can have multiple VMs of yours on that desktop of yours that you
think is a overkill and you don't use it anything else other than gaming. And of course there are
choices to use it on the cloud too which we totally suggest because this is something that we want
to deploy on scale. So the kind of replicated deployment that you can have kind of depends on
the kind of purpose that you would want to use this for. Right. So that's basically about
operating system itself. Now we're going to make that thing, put that thing into use and understand
how we can do some fun stuff. You know, set ourselves up an environment on this laptop itself. I set
myself up a virtualization host and I'll configure it to the way I want it to. So if I want a user,
I'll add it there. If I want a server to run in a certain way, maybe allow for no more than 32
people, I do so too. And by all means here again, this is a thing that you can follow along. So
feel free to read the documentation by scanning the QR code and we'll move on to the next one.
Right. So the setup environment that we have in place is VMware workstation. We really wanted
to make sure that things are a lot more easier and off-limited scope for scope of this presentation.
But you can use Quemu, you can use VirtualBox, you can use anything that you want or if you want to
just nail it, you really want to make use of a bare metal too. And the specification that we
provided it for are listed over here. And for this case, just because we want a server that
actually runs, that actually is something that won't get a lot of packages, a lot of updates
down the line, we really want to make sure that this runs in the long term. We have approached
the stable stream for this one. Right. So I'm going to exit out of the screen for a bit and go
more into detail about the stuff that I talked about over here. Right. So speaking of the
demonstration, I have an entire directory of files that I need. Now these can either be firewall
rules, the system, the units that I want to enable on the first boot, the packages that I want to
install, the configuration for the swap that I want to put into place, stuff like that. So to get
started, like I mentioned, we required a butane configuration. Now what exactly would that be?
Let's find out. PuteCons and ifcauseMind.PU. Well, basically it's just a list of directives that
lets you do the stuff that you want to make happen. So if you want to create users with a set
password for them, add SSS authorized keys, stuff like that, you can have them over here. The same
goes for the stories, the symbolic links that you want to make happen from one folder to another
directory. And you can have files that you source from a remote location and place it to somewhere
else. Then finally we get to the system, the unit spot, where we can actually declare services. Now
these services can either be for installing packages, adding firewall rules, enabling containers,
stuff like that, and you can totally control them the way you want. And finally, there's this
cadence about what needs to be done first that you can use with the use of systemD directives,
like before, depends on, but you can also mention them over here. Right. So as you can see that we
have roughly three systemD units that we have mentioned over here. The first, of course, is to
install portman compose and firewallD. We have portman pre-installed, but not portman compose,
so we might as well end up getting one. And the next is to allow Minecraft server to firewall. So
before that, we, of course, would reboot because, like I mentioned, your updates only get applied
when you want them to be applied, which by this case, by default, is reboot. There's also an option
to apply them live, but then again, you'd want to use them for applications like, well, a text
editor or something of that kind, but definitely not for something that will end up becoming a
service on itself. And then finally starting the dedicated server, now that the stuff that we
needed for the firewallD service rules are everything in place. So just to avoid using more
time during the presentation, what we did was, well, we did that in the hindsight like previously,
and now what we have over here is the IP that we can connect to the container, the one that's
running firewallD, the one that runs that firewallD service as well as the Minecraft dedicated
server. To go forward in detail, I would show the status of the units that I mentioned off,
like those for allowing these, and depending on what kind of condition that you make happen,
you can either make them run once, like if the firewallD service has been enabled, so you don't
want to enable it again, so you can always put a flag of some kind telling that if a certain
condition satisfies, which it seems to have, it won't run again. So the next thing that I want to
show you is of course the server itself. So if I were to follow a certain unit, let's just say
start Minecraft server, but I'm going to save myself some effort and go like that. So we have
this container right here that's running on Pardman, and yeah, there's this internal IP address as
well that lets us connect to that. And finally, about the services that lets you install both
Pardman Compose as well as the firewallD. Well, head over here, where's the terminal? There it is.
And do, of course, mine. Just a moment. And allowing systemD system, allowing Minecraft server
to the firewall. So we have set up the condition with style stat. Once that thing is done, you
create a file called done, allow Minecraft server to firewall. So with the services like these,
we kind of make sure that the service runs exactly when we want it to, and not any time
more than that. So once it's done, it's done. And of course, the condition for setting up in
the first boot kind of falls in line for the one that helps us install these packages, especially
for the Pardman Compose and firewallD. So condition for the first boot is true, but you reboot after
this thing has completely done. And by that, we help applying these packages on the existing
deployment. Right. So we'll go over here, and we'll check the IP address again. This happens to be
this is NAT forwarded. So as much as any of you folks have Minecraft installed, I'm really sorry
that you folks won't be able to connect to this one for the security purposes. But I'm going to
connect to it and see what kind of world it gets me into. So we have the IP 192.168.234.129.
Let's see if it's reachable. Well, actually, it's kind of a firewallD thing if it's the service
runs. And if the rules have been applied, we would be able to. Hmm, strange. Just a moment, folks.
Oh, it seems to have run. Now to have a plan B and a plan C, I have heard stories of folks losing
their presentations. They have like three flash drives. So I also thought of deploying one in my
home. But we probably won't need that because guess what? We have a server that says that it's
running on this host. And it's running on, well, the forced-in setup that we have here. Well,
the other one, the plan C, of course, does not happen to be a plan C anymore because there's
something that I can't reach out to. So I'm going to connect over to this one. Right. So the worst
thing that can happen to a player when the entire Minecraft world has happened. But then again, if
I were to alter it and were to check the logs of the service, I should be able to see that I indeed
have connected and have reached. So, you know, folks can totally get creative with what they can do
with this. They can have their own servers hosted on their local place, maybe have an OCI cloud to
do some reverse proxing to have their friends connect to it as well. The possibilities are endless.
And when it gets deployed on scale, on cloud, it just goes to the next level. And it's not just
for gaming, but rather for if you want to do a local deployment for Plex or anything for that
matter which uses containers, it is possible. Now I'm going to hand it over to Sumanthro to be able
to talk about the Valheim setup. Say back to the presentation. What do you want to?
Hey guys, so exactly much like the Minecraft setup, we have the Valheim setup which is basically
setting up the environment variables, configuring the host, making it work. Technically, all the
documentation has been put out on that QR code. So, if I go over here. Yeah, so all the required
files has been put out here. So, like Akash explained, we have a buton configuration generated by
this ignition file. So, if you look at it over here, the buton configuration has the storage,
the directories, and all we need the files, any rules. And finally, the system unit services
that needs to run, specifically in much like the exact case of Minecraft. If I go back,
this is actually the ignition file. This is the back door of how CoreOS would basically look at
that configuration and parse it for its own purposes. So, this is perfectly mission-readable,
not supposed to be edited by hand. But if you guys wanted to change something, that's supposed
to be on the buton side of things. Coming back to the configuration, there's a root, there's
supposed to be ETC system DE, and then the ZRAM generator service. And this one is swap on ZRAM
service. By default, we have put a ZRAM zero as the default setting. It requires a bunch of RAM,
and we literally have put one of those services over there just to ensure things are going fine.
Going back to my systems, there are going to be a server through the firewall. That's exactly the
same. If I open it, that's a very basic thing. Going back, we have the start-velven dedicated
service, and this one is going to have the podman compose parts, and that's an execute script with
up and down. Coming back to the point, so one more thing, we actually hosted it on private
servers back in the home. The way that we kind of can get it up and running right now is reaching,
I should probably practice turning on microphones before speaking. For the interest of time, what
we'll do is we'll just not show the Valheim demo, unfortunately, apologies for that, but this is
totally reachable on the VM that we have set up over here, and the port that it goes on is
reachable. But the point being that these things are very possible, fun stuff, and kind of gives you
a reason why you would want to try a new workflow where the entire file system, the entire packaging
workflow is nothing but a get kind of a thing, so you can roll back and roll front depending on
what you want to do. And the best thing that you can do is try it out today if you have a VM to
spare or a device to do so. Right, so that's about it for the presentation. We'd really love to have
your questions and answer them too.
We have a bunch of time for questions.
Hello, thank you very much for your presentation. I had a question about the relationship between
Fedora Core, Fedora Core OS, and persistent storage. My understanding is that when you're
working in containers, you want everything to be ethereal and temporary, and don't worry about
that. But you mentioned, if you have some sort of media server, how would you address that sort of
persistent sort of data pool? Is that part of butane or how is that configured and managed?
Do you want to answer?
Right, so the way we have it is by setting up mounts. The way it works is anything that gets
affected by the installation, removal, updating of the packages, these are the ones that are very
transient in nature. So these can get affected. But if you have mounts that lead to some different
place, they most likely won't be. The home directory would most likely stay untouched. So as long as
it does not have anything to do with a certain package, if it's not a file that gets introduced
when you install a package or something of that kind, it for most likely won't be touched and it
would always stay the same.
Any more questions?
Ah, okay.
What is the relationship between Fidora IoT and Fidora IoT?
Has everyone got that? What's the difference between Fidora and what?
Fidora IoT.
So for the record, Fidora IoT was an official addition for a long time, which means Fidora would
push in updates regularly. CoreOS recently became an addition which is a release back, which now
brings into question the release criteria for IoT and the boards that we support. They were very
officially declared as supported. But in case of CoreOS, there's no such official support that was
given before. It was never made an addition. So that's one thing that you're missing out on.
Second thing that you're missing out on is IoT, on the other hand, is released every six months with
the release. Fidora in CoreOS in this case would have a stream cycle, which means the next would be,
if today we get a next stream, in 15 days that would become testing, and then in next 15 days it
would become the stable. And then that's how it's going to roll. Obviously, given the fact that the
next stream is tested by the CoreOS' own CI, which runs for almost all the basic tests which
is required for the thing to run, both are based out of OS tree, but again, every 15 days, CoreOS
updates to the next stream or moves through the next stream. In case of IoT, you get it every six months.
Thanks for the talk. I would love to see this kind of bootstrapping of CoreOS happening on system
D and spawn, for instance. Would that be feasible like having that butane declarative way of just
instantiate me something under system D and spawn? Is that something that can work already?
It technically can, but then again, we kind of have to understand if system D and spawn,
the environment inside of it will have system D or not. It's very much possible. One of the
use cases that I've seen using it is building packages or testing them for that matter. The very
fact that you don't really have to configure it when it's up, but rather decide how it's going to look
like from the get-go, and that deployment can be replicated anywhere. That really makes it a prime image
of some kind. It does not even have to be a container image. That thing can be based upon and using a
virtual machine or system D and spawn, as you mentioned, you can have that kind of blueprint, but
guess what? It's not a container. It's a full-blown operating system which is running like it would on a bare
metal node. Thank you.
This is the last question we can take.
I was wondering this ignition file is only applied on the first startup. Can we make some kind of
declarative configuration for Silverblue, or for not for Silverblue for KOS? Is this also supported?
So if I get your question correctly, you are wondering if a certain configuration can be run again if I want to
on the same deployment.
Right. It's totally possible. The thing that you end up getting after running these many steps after running the
butane configuration is deployment. What you can do is you can use that deployment and run a butane
configuration on the top of it so that it becomes your base deployment and anything that you add on the top of it is the
resulting deployment. The very thing that deployment states in this case is a state in which the operating system is in right now.
So if you just mangle the state to create a new one, that state becomes your existing state. That's about it.
One last thing, guys. We have a Fedora booth. Feel free to go there, grab swags and what not.
And thanks for attending.
Thanks.