Hello. Hello. Okay. So, welcome to the Contano's Dev Room at FOSDEM 2023. We're all very happy
to be back in person in completely filled room as usual for this track. And we've got
our first speaker who's going to be talking about drawing Kubernetes cluster the right
way. Take it away.
Okay. So, yeah, you see the title of the talk. And the nature of Kubernetes is a little bit
specific. I would say, and that's why this talk exists and I hope can be beneficial.
If we speak about the Kubernetes specific, the first thing we actually think about is
the high-entrance threshold. First of all, we have tremendous amount of objects or entities,
I would say, which interact with each other in some predictable or not always predictable
manner. So, the slide just lists few of them. And as you know, Google likes inventing new entities with specific names which are doing something non-standard from the point of view of pre-Google systems. So, we have a lot of
objects. You have pods, services which are not traditional service. You have a large amount
of controllers. You have labels, lectures. You have some objects which are really Kubernetes
specific and such as deployments. Then you have specific tools or components or concepts
to control all these orchestrated together set of containers. And due to this complexity,
you really need good and simple drawing to illustrate it. Well, from the cognitive load
theory, we divide cognitive load in several groups, actually in three groups. The one
is early on cognitive load related to the subject you are presenting and to other groups
are more related to the way you present the subject and decreasing cognitive load for
presentation. Actually, free some mind resources of the consumer of your drawing and makes it
much easier to understand. And that is really needed in case of Kubernetes. The specific
of Kubernetes cluster relies on two things. The first thing is, well, we can traditionally
think about the cluster of virtual machines as cluster of some machines connected in one
network. But actually, a traditional networking based approach in case of Kubernetes is not
so beneficial. First of all, the network in case of the Kubernetes cluster is more about
namespaces, network policies, granted or not granted access and so on. And actually, well,
virtual machines are still machines. They are somehow virtually connected with each other,
but that's not the problem of you as a cluster creator. It's actually the problem of Kubernetes
itself to manage this and no reasons to draw it on your diagram. Then you have to draw
objects, Kubernetes objects, you have to combine objects in groups and just connecting them
with some network lines is not helpful. And if speaking about grouping, the other problem
is that sometimes groups should be presented as objects and sometimes groups should be
presented as groups. It's really Kubernetes and it's really a Kubernetes way of thinking
about, well, things and you have to deal with it. We will see it a little bit later. So let's
try to look how people are drawing Kubernetes clusters. The first thing to think about is
using some black and white drawing a traditional way. Maybe an old school graph is example
would be the good starting point. Well, what's good with it? It's graph is recognizable and
people will say, ah, he uses graph is cool. But as you remember, your Kubernetes cluster
is not a graph. Yes, it's not actually good to use network diagram in traditional ways.
So using graphs is nothing good as well. Well, some author, by the way, on the bottom you
have the source of the slide of the drawing and regards to the author. Some are using
LibreOffice diagrams with blocks and lines. You see not too much lines here. It's good.
And it's really better than the previous one and really easier to understand. Then you
see that shades of gray are using to distinguish group of objects one from another. Actually,
it's a good approach. So grouping should be actively used in black and white drawing as
well. And you see if you just draw rectangles without using color, it will be dull a little
bit and it will be a little bit empty. You will look at it and think, is it a diagram
at all? Okay. If we are speaking that shades of gray are beneficial to distinguish groups
of objects one from another, then what about colors? Colors are also beneficial. Frankly,
speaking, this diagram comes from the official Kubernetes documentation from Google. What
good with it? It uses colors. What's bad with it? Never use black text on blue background
because blue and black has the lowest possible value of contrast. Other examples, just a
few of them. Just to notice that people are actively using colors. This one at least uses
white on black. It would be more readable. Well, actually, if you choose colors, the
good idea is to use color wheel, especially if you are more confident with containers
than with color combinations. So color wheel allows you to choose colors with good contrast
and which are complementary to the main color you choose. You can even follow the color
scheme of your website or of your slides or anything like this. It will give you the unique
and recognizable diagrams. So if you linked the color wheel available online on the slide
and I would say it's a good thing to use. So a little bit more about networking diagrams.
They're actually second drawing from the official Kubernetes documentation. What's good? It
has stacks. Stacks are also good in grouping. It has some UML like arrows which are actually
not inheritance. Just used for some aesthetic reasons, I think. And it's clearly drawn in
LibreOffice. So if Google is okay with drawing things in LibreOffice, why not? And it uses
some traditional networking icons, but just to put something except rectangles here. The
really good example from Red Hat, sorry, you see colors with grouping. You see few network
icons which are just objects to make the overall drawing more interesting and not overloading
your mind. A little bit more about networking diagrams. If you have lines and arrows, not
to show that everything is connected with everything, but to guide viewer how to scan
this diagram, then in this case networks are really good. Network is really good. Network
I mean lines, arrows. But if you add more icons, it will be a disaster. The diagram
becomes really difficult to read. Tiny icons, all tiny icons are looking similar and will
be lost. So you can see that the lines are not connected. So you can see that the lines
are not connected. Tiny icons are all looking similar and will be lost. Sequence drawing
as well. We were speaking that arrows are good in putting some order in which the reader
should scan it. Sequence numbers are okay as well. But once again, don't overdo it. Also,
it's popular to make some experiments with shape of objects. Non-rectangular blocks are
rather good. You can use them. Official Google documentation has a portion of diagrams with
something like this. If you are lucky, it will be a good sample of art. If you are not
lucky, it will be a good sample of art. If you are not lucky, it will be a good sample
of art. If you are not lucky, it will not. So guess whether you need it or not.
Code fragments. When you create flight, it's typical to put code fragments inside your
diagrams. Some UML files or something like this. YAML, I mean, of course. It works rather
well. Don't forget about colors. But probably not in web documentation or something like
this. One more point is to speak about the official Kubernetes icons. Well, blue haptagons
specify objects. Blue haptagons specify groups. They are very similar. Is it easy to scan?
No. It's not. It's a good example. Sorry. We have much worse examples. Which were officially
presented as an example to follow. It was slides on this one, exceptionally. This one was
present in slides on Google Drive. I have noticed it was removed from the readme file. But it's
still present over the Internet. It's difficult to close things when you have made them public
once again. So what to use? The first. A lot of angled shapes increase stress level. It's
known from psychology. So if you use official Kubernetes icons, use just a few of them,
not too much. And probably you would like to use grouping with rectangles with rounded
corners. Just, oh, sorry. Like this one. To reduce the overall level of stress caused
by these angular icons. And what else? Few is better than more in this case. Well, the
conclusions. The first thing to take care of is low consumption of icons. Which saves
your user from visual overload. More text, less icons. Like in Unix, you know, text is
okay. Then color. Color runs, well, not the world, but definitely runs your presentation.
Just use good color combinations. It's really a good idea to follow. Then round corners will
save your presentation as well. They are really important, especially if you use several
official icons to let people know that you are, well, the person who knows that these
icons exist. Then what about ideal drawing? Rectangles. Just few lines as a gaze
and course. Then maybe some numbers if you need to show sequence of actions. Maybe some
arrows if you need to show the sequence of actions. Then a good idea is to mix official
kubernetes icons with some other icons if you need more than two or three of them. It
sounds strange, but it really works. Then the last advice. Using several simple drawings
instead of one complicated drawing is a really good way to present your cluster. Actually,
it relates not only to kubernetes. Several simple drawings are almost always better than
one complicated drawing, but in case of kubernetes and this additional cognitive
flow it's really important. Then probably that's the last slide. Thank you.