We have Magnus here,
he's going to talk about like the current zone.
Magnus works for Microsoft,
and please welcome him.
Thanks a lot.
So we're probably shifting gears a bit from all this deeply technical,
intimidating talks and connect to the first talk of this track.
Basically, I found this really interesting idea of emulating
the Let's Encrypt moment for confidential computing,
because it is more or less what we're doing.
So I'm a software engineer at Microsoft Skinfolk team.
We do a lot of exciting stuff,
in terms of open source, Linux, EVPF, and containers and Kubernetes.
My team is also involved in exploring ways to integrate
existing confidential computing technology,
all that we heard in the talks before,
with existing ways to deploy containers.
So this talk is kind of, we're on a tight schedule,
so I have to really do cut a few and short and probably will be a bit hand wavy.
So sorry about that.
Please reach out if you want to get details about something.
So obviously, it's also not a comprehensive coverage of all the confidential containers realm.
It's quite wide and covers a lot of areas.
So I'm focusing on a few things that we are looking at at the moment.
And also maybe the point in the talks will not age very well,
because things are very much evolving and whatever is mentioned later could be,
in a few months, could be already like in another stage.
But the idea basically is to provide pointers for people who want to get involved in this,
because from my perspective, it's very exciting.
It's something that's a very practical problem you can solve.
And there's a lot of open questions that are really accessible,
I think also for people without a very deep technical background in confidential computing.
And eventually, we have to define cloud native to establish some terminology,
but we cannot go very deep here.
So essentially, it's a bit of a buzzword.
But you will find that it's more or less an ecosystem of practices, tools, interfaces,
APIs that more or less aim to ease the deployment and management of applications on cloud platforms.
And that can be infrastructure as a service.
It can be functions as a service.
But in most cases, containers are very prominent in this space.
And it's also what you're focusing on.
And Kubernetes in this space, among other competitors,
has been adopted as a go-to solution really for container orchestration and management.
And quickly, introduce Kubernetes in two lines.
So Kubernetes is a container orchestrator, management, API abstraction layer.
I would say that it's not trivial to host and operate.
So it's a very popular offering by cloud service providers
to offer some hosted solution for Kubernetes and provide the developers, engineers with some API layers.
And in Kubernetes, what we have is maybe a bit unique.
You have this notion of pods, which define a logical environment.
It's like they're isolated resource constraint.
They also share namespaces, C groups.
And they are composed of individual containers.
So a node has pods.
And in the pods, it can be very co-located containers if you want.
And this is an abstraction that is quite useful in confidential computing.
So in general, I think this is also for people who work with confidential computing quite common.
There's kind of this trade-off scale where you say, you have a small TCP surface.
This means you run in enclaves.
You have SDKs.
And your workloads have to be customized for this.
But this also means you don't have to care for a lot of stuff,
because the TCP surface is quite small.
On the other end, you have a bigger TCP surface.
It's like bare-metal VMs, Kubernetes clusters, for example.
And those have the convenience of running unmodified workloads, this kind of lift and shift idea.
And if you want, the Kubernetes pods could kind of fit in there somewhere on this scale.
Probably not exactly in the middle, but somewhere.
So because the idea is that we only have minimal adjustments to existing workloads that are already running in Kubernetes.
And as mentioned before, some workloads are simply locked out of cloud-native and public clouds due to compliance issues.
And so our approach is basically to ease the adoption of confidential computing by enabling confidentiality with minimal upfront investments.
Because really only big corporations are able to invest in self-hosting environments that provide confidentiality.
And as I said, it has been widely adopted by the industry, Kubernetes.
And Kubernetes provides some abstractions and technologies.
I think you could also even argue that the main value of Kubernetes is not really the tech, but the kind of API abstractions that are there.
That really makes you, if you move from one place to the other, you will be able to adopt quite easily,
because there's a lot of shared solutions these days.
And we can use those abstractions.
For example, we look at SEV and TDX.
They leverage VMs for confidentiality.
And we have already an established solution with Kata containers that run those pod units that we've seen before in virtual machines.
So this is something that we don't have to start from scratch, but we can kind of see, OK, there's something that's been working so far.
And maybe we can leverage this.
And so ideally, probably you don't see this, but ideally, the result is that you have a Kubernetes spec where you just add a property.
Something is confidential.
Confidential true.
So this is a kind of lift and shift idea that we have very low friction enabled customers to deploy confidential workloads.
And the problem starts when we look at the Kubernetes privileges.
Like they're formed in a permit usually.
So the squiggly lines here indicate that it's not clear cut, but it's more or less like some parts are owned maybe by the platform engineers, by the so-called orchestrators.
Some parts are taken over by cloud service providers.
But the idea is that the hierarchy is pretty clear.
So the closer you get to the app users, eventually to the service users, the less privileged you are.
And the platform engineers are really also an in-between the layer that exists like classical operators, but on Kubernetes API level.
And the confidentiality permit drops.
And it's a bit messy because now we basically have the system that's been built for years and everything's figured out nicely.
And now our privileged model doesn't fit anymore.
So from the confidentiality perspective, you want to lock out the cloud service provider.
And we also don't want the cluster administrators to mess with the workloads, possibly not even the developers.
So and it might be really only the app users who have access to confidential data compute.
And this is something we have to deal with.
And this is also basically the challenges I think in this model we have to overcome.
I think it's definitely not an exhaustive list, but it's like three topics I picked, which in recent months I followed the discussions.
But I also don't think they're insurmountable.
So it's definitely stuff that we can solve and it's partially nice engineering problems.
Starting with image management.
So the container images usually are managed by the infrastructure, by the cubelet, container D, by those layers.
And this makes a lot of sense because there's also a lot of shared resources.
So containers images are organized in layers.
So instead of pulling an image 10 times, it can be cached on the node.
It can be shared through replications of a single service, for example.
And in a trusted execution environment, we need verified or encrypted images for workloads.
And actually, there are already OCI facilities for those aspects.
But the problem is they're running on the wrong layer.
So they're not in the TE.
So if basically the infrastructure part is not part of the TE, then we kind of need to drill a hole or move stuff to a trusted execution environment.
And so there's basically some approaches.
So I think the pragmatic band aid to start with, which made a lot of sense, is just pull everything in encrypted memory in a confidential pod VM.
And this has, I think, practical merits in the first, because you can start with a solution.
But it's very clear that there's downsides to this because you need to provision potentially a big chunks of memory for this.
And also, each pod needs to pull individually their image layers.
And some of those workloads, they run PyTorch images, for example.
They're really like gigabytes big.
And it's not something that you want to pull individually all the time.
We can, of course, create encrypted scratch spaces to do this.
So we get rid of the over provisioning of the memory.
But the unshared images will still yield pretty bad startup time.
The good news is that there's approaches that we can use today.
Like we can stream encrypted image layers or otherwise chunked up logs.
So there's different ideas from the host to the confidential pod. And the technology to do this is also not something that we need to invent from scratch.
It's already there in recent versions of ContainerD.
It's called remote snapshotters that basically do this.
But it's not 100% there.
But it doesn't meet our requirements fully.
But I think it's pretty close.
So about the whole image topic, I think we can be pretty optimistic.
There's another problem that's about metadata.
Kubernetes, and that's maybe a bit counterintuitive to people who don't know this.
But Kubernetes will freely transform your specified workloads in multiple ways.
So it will inject mount points, environment variables.
It will change your image definitions.
And this is all by design.
So because the cluster operators that I mentioned before, they basically make sure that all the workloads are compliant.
That if some engineer deploys some Redis image, usually like Redis latest or something,
they would basically on the fly have some admission controller that just rewrites this stuff.
And from our perspective, this is not what we want from the confidentiality perspective.
We specify what we want to run, and we cannot have the orchestrator or the platform engineers rewriting our specs.
So we want to run exactly what we specified.
And also in terms of, for example, environment variable injection.
So Kubernetes does this for very good reasons.
For example, for service discovery, all kinds of information, the pod receives from the orchestrator.
But it's very problematic if you think of the pod image before.
You have a small batch thing that does some caching on Redis locally.
And if the control plane would just inject the Redis host environment variable and forward this to whatever Redis instance,
this would obviously top a confidentiality.
So this is something we need to deal with.
And this is a bit, I think from my perspective, a bit messier than the image part.
Because we basically have to, or at least I don't see another way than saying, OK, we have to review the delta between what the user eventually specified and what is eventually being provisioned on the container D site.
And I think we can then validate whether we're fine with the applied changes in the user specified policies.
But it's very hard, I think, in some cases, to write those policies.
They're very complex.
So the whole idea that we have a nice UX that says, like, just confidential true is not working anymore because the users have to write those policies.
And there's some dynamisms in Kubernetes that are very hard to model.
So we either have to find a way to kind of make this really convenient or we find some other way to tackle this.
And I think another idea I've recently read about is basically that we have a variation of this idea, as more or less, we kind of log the changes that have been performed and yeah,
toppled or approaches from this perspective that we see, OK, we don't model what could happen, but we more or less look at the log file of the changes that are there and see whether we are fine with those changes.
But that's, I think, the same idea, but it's only a variation.
Eventually, I think, and this is also something that is a bit more challenging.
We have to address the problem that the control plane, APIs and the host components, they interact with the Kubernetes parts.
And it's really like a crucial part of all the tooling of all the of how developers interact with Kubernetes, say, with, I know, XSAC into their containers for debugging stuff.
They will get locks and all this is currently going through the control plane.
And we basically our task is to cut out this kind of middleman from the user to the workload.
And there's a lot of aspects like observability.
This is a key concept of like cloud native workloads and it's obviously almost a contradiction like confidentiality and observability. It's very hard to reconcile, but it's something that I think is we have to address at some point.
So we kind of need to obscure the logs, traces, metrics from non trusted parties.
And those metrics are, for example, sometimes also used in by the orchestrator directly so they would use garbage collection metrics to perform out of scaling of pots.
So it's really a tricky question how to deal with this.
So we need to deprivialage basically the non trusted parties and prevent them from doing those or from retrieving those metrics, but also from executing commands and the scope of a confidential pot.
And I think there's, yeah, as we see images, I think the pragmatic bandaid is probably at the moment locking down those problematic parts.
It's like you cannot execute the moment, maybe retrieving logs is not that easy as it was before.
But obviously that's not something that's practical in the long run for for real workloads.
And there's two solutions to this problem I've stumbled upon recently.
It's more or less like say you split the container management APIs into the infrastructure and trusted parts and operate a kind of shadow trusted control plan that users and tools interact with.
And this is also part of a T.E.
And it would kind of mirror the Kubernetes API.
The downside I think it's from what I have seen is it's a large effort and also not sure whether it's maintainable in the long run because you basically have to evolve with the Kubernetes APIs all the time.
And I think the other alternative solution I've seen is more viable from my perspective.
It means we haven't kind of an encrypted transport between the privileged user and the container management tech on the confidential VM, for example.
And the downside to this approach is basically that it's also quite an invasive change because you need to extend many power touch many parts of the stack because you have this kind of confidential transport through all these layers.
It means you have to change components in Kubernetes and container D and even like the clients and tools that sit on top of Kubernetes.
So it's also not an easy thing to do.
Yeah, I think that's the three points I wanted to mention.
In summary, I think confidential computing and cloud native containers are a good match.
From my perspective, it could really boost the adoption of confidential computing.
There's definitely some hairy questions we need to figure out to make this work in practice.
But from what I'm seeing, like there's a very engaged community and yeah, it's very exciting.
So if you want to chime in, it's a confidential containers org on GitHub.
There's meetings.
There's slack.
And I think that's it.
We have some around 10 minutes for questions.
So please.
You mentioned the control plane issue and the fact that the API between the host control plane and the T is not practical in the lower end.
What do you mean by that?
No, no, knocking it out is not practical.
So if you basically say you're not able to use a full API in confidential context.
So if you basically right now, you can lock down the controversial parts of the API because it's very hard.
It's hard to untangle those things.
Some things are like, you know, when the APIs weren't conceived, you didn't think like X would be a problem, but create wouldn't be a problem.
So at the moment, I think we can do this on the container D level or on a data agent level where you can basically say, OK, there's a few things we just don't support.
But I think this is not sustainable in the long run.
So you're saying that you're not saying the architecture is not practical, you're saying that the fact that you're shutting the API off is not a long term solution.
Exactly. But I mean, it's if you want to basically start with something that is definitely like the image pulling on the on the confidential VM, this is I think makes sense if you want to start with this.
Yeah. We think about like we have to get the metadata problem and then having this trusted control plane also as a solution for the metadata problem.
But you're like a controller part of the API server that can give your descriptions and it will enforce them to the control.
I mean, that's obviously. Pardon.
Yeah. So the question is like whether basically the if you move parts of the of the control plane into the T whether you basically get around a lot of those problems.
And it's absolutely true because basically this self-made problems to a huge degree.
So if you just take the whole thing and put it in a T.E., then most of the things that were there or maybe even all of the things there aren't a problem anymore suddenly.
But this is like starting from the from the notion of existing users who basically use existing hosted Kubernetes offerings.
How do you basically migrate those users to confidential?
You would have to do those things. And so I'm not even arguing that this is like maybe the best solution in the long run.
But if you want to do this, then you have to kind of overcome those those issues.
We have like two more questions and I got to give so we can read it. OK.
OK, there's a question. Are there any new challenges related to attestation protocols in containers compared to already existing attestation mechanism in TDX, SAVS and P, etc.
From my perspective, I think this is not something that is necessarily conflicting with this confidential container.
So it's more or less we also have to basically follow the same attestation principles as like non containerized workloads.
Yeah, you're just moving it on a different layer. But I think there's no fundamental difference or problem that are specific to containers.
There's another question about the use of a proxy being considered.
I think it's a bit too broad for me to understand where a proxy would sit.
So you run a proxy in a confidential VM and all your control point APIs go through that.
Yeah, I mean, this is what I meant by like having this kind of transport.
But yeah, I think the proxy pretty much you need to then start also at the client to tweak things.
Maybe you have a distinct cube config for confidential parts.
I don't know. I didn't really look deep into this, but I think there's definitely changes you need to do also when you employ a proxy.
And one question or comment from my side is.
Well, there are a lot of challenges in order to have these done in the infrastructure side.
So you mentioned about like how we pull the parts of whether we can share those or not the image.
That's a problem that affects mostly the people providing the service.
But he might in my mind, like the biggest problem we have is like maintaining the ability and observability for the end users.
And that's something that we will have to think together on how so these.
I mean, the priorities, I think I agree. Sometimes I think are different for this way, because sometimes it's just things are just also KPI driven.
So you say like we have this solution and it starts like in three seconds and we do this, then it doesn't work.
So because then we request in some metric. But this I think a product question from my personal view.
I also don't think that the image pulling time, the startup time is a big issue.
But there's also like if many of those workloads are machine learning workloads, then it's like there's a pie torch image.
It's like I know 21 gigabyte or something. It's really crazy. And I understand that there's like a concern.
And it's not like a problem for for Kubernetes itself. Like we have to wait a lot with my.
But for functional service, it is. Yeah. This is one of the main things that people are looking for.
It's understandable.