We're going to start here. We have a presentation about constellation, how to manage Kubernetes,
we think Kubernetes. The presenters are Mojit and Malto. So big shout out to them.
Thank you. We'd like to pick up where Nick in his initial presentation of saying we need
to have a let's encrypt movement, we need to make confidential computing a commodity.
Where he started off and then Magnus I think had a great talk showing all those bits and
pieces that we need to have to bring together the use cases, the cloud native world, the
way we develop applications for the cloud and the advantages that the confidential computing
technology gives us, how to bring them together and where are those gaps.
Historically seen or for different kind of use cases, I would roughly split from a use
case perspective of if I want to develop an application, where can CC help me, how can
I play confidential computing. I can roughly split that in three tiers if you will. I think
one is definitely managing keys, having enclaves that hold your cryptographic certificates,
your keys that process the crypto operations for you. Very small TCB, very small kind of
application. Then the second one is where I package my entire application inside an
enclave inside a confidential container and I think that's what we've been doing lately
a lot. Then I think the third thing is what Magnus described, is how can we bring that
together making this orchestratable, making this manageable, deployable. I think there
are different ways of getting from the tier two or the way we are to here. One is I guess
what Magnus described with taking containers, making them confidential containers and then
having the problems with orchestration. An orthogonal approach that we like to present
now is more of the idea of having confidential clusters. Instead of isolating individual
containers, isolating the nodes, the downside probably is a little bit larger TCB and the
advantages being more closely to where we are right now with deploying and developing
cloud native applications. Talking about challenges, for level three definitely I think one of
the biggest ones is UI, UX. There's little hope that people will go ahead and drastically
adjust the way they deploy and develop applications for the cloud just because they want to use
this new type of technology. We need to get very close to where they are and bring those
worlds together. Then of course there are the challenges Magnus described with orchestration,
attesting, how can we attest all those different containers that are running in my cluster
and don't necessarily want to verify each individual instance of it. It could be a thousand
and more of the same. Once I have a cluster, all those day two operations of updating,
upgrading and doing that in a sensitive way where I can always verify what's currently
being running and what are the changes. A big part of what we're going to present today
is the right one here where a big benefit of the cloud is actually that I can give away
some of this orchestration work and I consume managed services that are operated by someone
or autonomously and I just consume them through an API or any other kind of interface. As
Nick has said, infrastructure is rolling out. We see all those confidential technologies
in the cloud, AMD, SCB. We have heard so many today, IBM, RISC-V. Most of them give us a
confidential VM which is as we've seen not necessarily the abstraction we want but still
we can already consume managed Kubernetes that runs on confidential VMs at least for
the worker nodes. I think Azure has it, GCP has it. This exists but it's not really solving
the problem. It gives us runtime encryption for the stuff that lives on that nodes but
all the edges, all the IO is not protected. The API server is not protected. We've seen
that in Michael's talk. The metadata problem, the problem of the trusted control plane,
the way if you want to consume persistent volumes, is that automatically encrypted or
do I need to adjust my application to encrypt before writing to storage? The idea of a confidential
cluster is that I have somebody or something that fills in those gaps so that I have instead
of those individual confidential VMs, I have one big context that I can verify through attestation
that I can establish a secret channel and then if I'm in that context, if I'm in that
cluster, I can just use Kubernetes as I used to and inside there, essentially everything
is trusted. It's a different type of approach. It just creates an envelope around my Kubernetes
and isolates that as a whole. As I said, I think UX and UI and the way we use this is
super important. It's not going to work that we need a lot of adjustments, a lot of additional
steps in the development workflows. This is just an example of consolation here but having
a simple way of creating such a confidential cluster and then using it is important and
all those things that I showed, all the challenges we need to solve below. We need to make this
more or less invisible. In terms of consolation, we try to make the node operating system as
verifiable as possible, strip it down as much as possible, harden it, then strip them together
for a cluster. We need to think about supply chain. We need to think about how we can automatically
encrypt all the stuff that goes over the network, that goes through the storage. Ideally, this
is all open source, so if I didn't mention it's open source and it's cloud agnostic so
it can run everywhere. Then for most of confidential computing stuff, I need some way of recovery
should things go south and everything is down and I need to get back into running mode.
The big problem with the confidential cluster concept is now I can create a cluster and
we will see in a bit of what that means but if I can create a cluster, I have everything
verified, now I have to maintain and run it on my own. This is, I guess, the biggest problem
with that concept. People want to consume managed stuff, want to have managed Kubernetes,
want to run their own, orchestrate their own Kubernetes. This is a big trade-off that people
are facing and we try to work on concepts of making that as easy as possible and Malte
is going to show you how.
Thanks for the introduction. The basic idea that we had was how can we manage Kubernetes
from inside Kubernetes itself and to kind of draft this idea, I will start by explaining
like what typically you can do today. On the left side, you really have the traditional
on-prem model which is you have the whole cluster in your own hand, the control plane,
the worker nodes, it runs on your own hardware which is great for security because you have
full control but it also means you are responsible for every single interaction like scaling
up the cluster, joining the nodes, performing upgrades both on the OS level and also Kubernetes
upgrades and then on the other side, you have something that is super popular. It is just
let the cloud provider deal with it and it means the cloud provider can scale your cluster
up and down just if you have a burst of traffic coming in, you get new nodes. It's all super
easy. You can set it up so that the cloud provider will automatically patch your operating
system. It will automatically upgrade your Kubernetes and this is great from a DevOps
perspective. It's super simple. It scales. It takes away work from the developer and
the operator of the cluster. What we thought is why don't we meet in the middle? That's
kind of like we have to run our own control plane in the confidential context but if we
do this, we lose all of these smart features from the cloud provider so we will just reinvent
them but inside the cluster. That means we can still do auto scaling. We can still join
the nodes by themselves without any human interaction. We can still roll out OS updates
and we can even roll out Kubernetes upgrades inside a running Kubernetes cluster. To explain
how this works, I will first go on to how Kubernetes nodes and consolations can actually
join the cluster without any outside interaction. What you have to understand here is these
are all confidential VMs and they make heavy use of the measured boot chain. I think we
already had some good introductions on this but I will still show you how this works in
an example. First, in the confidential VM, we have the firmware and the firmware is basically
just the first part that starts up. The main task here is to load up the first stage boot
loader and to measure it. We measure it on AMD, SEV in the approach we are currently
doing. It is measured into a virtual TPM. Then we load this boot loader and then we
will start executing it. The boot loader just has the task of, in our case, loading the
next stage and measuring it which is a unified kernel image. This is a very neat trick. It
is basically just one blob that contains the Linux kernel and init-ramfs and also the kernel
command line. The nice property here is we can measure all of these in one blob and don't
have to take care of the individual components which can be quite hard to do correctly. Inside
of this init-ramfs, we will use the kernel command line to extract the hash that we expect
for the root file system. For this, we use the mverity which I will not go into too much
detail about. It just allows us to have a read-only root file system and we know in
advance that it has not been tampered with. We can efficiently check every block while
it is read and before it is actually given to the user land. That is how we get to the
root file system. Inside of this root file system, we have a small application and the
task of this application is to join this node into the Kubernetes cluster. Next to the completely
unmodifiable OS, we have a state disk. The only task of the state disk is to have the
data for Kubernetes itself like container images and state at runtime that has to be
stored on disk. This is initialized to be completely clean. It is encrypted and that
is a component we need to operate. The next question is how do we make these things possible?
For this, we deploy some microservices inside of constellation. These are the node operator.
This is responsible for actually rolling out updates. It is the join service that tests
nodes that are joining the cluster and decides if they are allowed to join or not. We also
have a key service that is handling encryption keys and some more that are not really important
right now. How does a node actually join the cluster? I mentioned there is the boot stripper
that is started inside of the confidential virtual machine. It will autonomously search
for the existing Kubernetes control plan and it will perform remote attestation using a
tested TLS. It will basically use the attestation statement, for example from AMD, SCV, SMP.
The join service already knows what measurements to expect from a correct node that is running
the expected software. It can decide at this point if the booted node is running what you
want it to run and decide if it is allowed to join the cluster. Based on this, the join
service can then offer the node a join token which allows it to join the cluster and it
will also hand out a permanent encryption key for the state disk. Next, we will have
a quick look at how updates work. On a high level, we want the administrator to be in
control. We don't want to give up complete control over the update process, but we want
the actual execution to be completely automatic and seamless. We do this by basically just
telling the cluster what to do and the rest is done by a Kubernetes operator which is
a way to give in a desired state and let the cluster handle moving towards the state.
One important thing to think about here is we are running in the cloud environment and
we don't want you to depend on individual nodes. This is also what GKE and EKS and others
are doing. We're saying if you want to upgrade, we will give you a new node that has the desired
configuration and we will never try to do updates in place. How does the actual update
work? We basically give in custom resources that describe the desired state, so the Kubernetes
version and the OS image that we want to run on and some properties to actually verify
like the expected measurements for the new image and tashes for the individual Kubernetes
components. The operator reads this information and basically checks if the desired state
matches reality and if it detects a mismatch, it will first stop any auto scaling operations
that are happening in the cluster and then it will start replacing the nodes one by one.
For this we use the different APIs by the cloud providers. In this case, we will just
spawn a new node in the correct node group that has the desired configuration. We wait
for the node to autonomously join the cluster and we wait for it to become ready. Next,
we will coordinate and train the node, which just means we will safely move over your running
workloads from this node to other nodes in the cluster and only if we are sure that your
running workloads moved over, we will then remove the old node from the cluster. This
is basically how you can get from having outdated nodes to having updated nodes and this will
just go on until your whole cluster is up to date. You can also parallelize this. When
this is done, you can just restart the auto scaler and move on with your day.
All right, quick conclusion. In summary, the fundamental idea is we take this confidential
cluster concept, enveloping the entire Kubernetes cluster instead of protecting single containers
or parts. What we gain is we basically get all the orchestration for free. We need to
protect the edges, all the ION and so forth. The downside is we can't isolate inside that
cluster so it's one big envelope, of course. This works already. It's an open source tool.
You can check out Constellation on GitHub and then try it locally or on one of the big
clouds. From a Kubernetes perspective, it's just vanilla Kubernetes. Not surprising that
it's certified. To give out some more references, if you're
interested in this whole image part, there was the image-based Linux and TPM Devroom.
There's a lot of talks on these topics. Also very interesting. This is the last talk here,
but if you're interested in more confidential computing, sneaky little advertisement here
for the OC3 Open Confidential Computing Conference that's going to happen in March. It's virtual
free. You can just sign up and listen to the talks if you're interested. A bunch of the
folks that were here also have a talk there. If you have any questions, please feel free
to get in touch. That's it.
The question was about the attested TLS. When we join nodes, we establish a C connection
based on attested TLS. First of all, our implementation is open source. It's part of the Constellation
source on GitHub. I think it's nothing fancy. We use the AMD SCV or Intel TDX and so forth,
attestation statement to exchange a key as part of the data that's sent over. We bind
the TLS session to that attested key. I guess there are a couple of implementations for
attested TLS. They work more or less the same.
I'm really proud to be part of the most familiar with confidential computing. There is this
known flexibility in remote administration. It can be faked by a machine's host. I wonder
if it is possible to fight out from the remote attestation of the whole cluster any single
machine in the cluster may make a station and it goes unnoticed or not. All the others
are, for example, truthful.
Repeat the question. The question was there is a known vulnerability for attestation in
confidential computing. If given this confidential cluster, if from the whole cluster attestation,
I can refer to if one of the nodes is faking attestation. I have to say there were several
vulnerabilities in several of the CC technologies over time. I'm not aware of what vulnerability
you're referring to.
The question is, you don't know if it's a specific gem on a specific provider or someone
located in their garage. Is that what you mean?
The way the cluster attestation works is you give the first node, it has a known configuration,
and it will attest all other nodes based on this known attestation. If one node would
be able to perfectly fake that attestation, you would not know from a cluster attestation
perspective which node this would be.
But yeah, I guess that's what you can say.
It is super simple, but it is big TCB. Do you have any plans to reduce the TCB?
As I said, this is a trade-off. Yes, it's a much larger TCB than SGA, much larger TCB
even than confidential containers. We, of course, will try to make it as minimal as
possible. The biggest leverage is of course the node OS and everything we can do inside
there. We'll definitely try to improve there.
Yes? Very good question.
Sorry. Yeah, the question is part of the confidential VMs is the first component that's booted is
the firmware. Do we have control of the firmware? Ideally, we would have. But what's provided
by the cloud providers right now is Azure has something in preview that allows you to
do that. It's not generally available. And GCP does not allow you that. So the firmware
for at least GCP or Azure is completely controlled by them. On OpenStack with QMOKVM, you can
potentially fully control the firmware. Yes, next question.
Doesn't that create a huge trust problem? Does it have to trust the firmware to be secure?
Does this create a trust problem? That's the question. Yeah. I mean, this is a controversy.
I fully agree with you. This is not how we would like it. This is just the best we can
have.