And now we have Arjun Srepenice, and he is going to talk about how live-view will be
used to keep you warm.
So give it up!
Alright, thank you everybody.
Nice to see such a big turn up.
When he last organized this dev room, I think three years ago, it was a much smaller room.
It was really packed, now it's not packed but it's obvious because it's a bigger room.
But I'm very glad that everybody is here.
So my name is Arjan Skrepenis and I'm going to talk a bit about knitting today with you
and also a bit about LiveView.
So I'm going to give a little bit of background about my project, about what I'm doing, then
I'm going to talk about LiveView and how I use it and then I'm going to wrap up.
So let's start with some background.
I've been programming since I was a little kid.
Yesterday when we had a beer together I talked about what is your first OTP release that
you used.
I was actually R13 so that's a bit and you can guess my age a bit.
It's from 2009 so I've been using Erlang since 2009.
Before that I used PHP a lot but then I got introduced by somebody to Erlang and that
actually Mark Worell had a bit the same story as Jose Falimat when he created Elixir.
Mark wanted to create also Web Framework for Erlang.
Elixir was not yet born and so he created Zotonic, Web Framework and I'm still a contributor
to that and it's still alive although it's not as popular as Elixir or Phoenix for that
matter.
But then later I got used to programming in Elixir and I've been doing that since for
quite a bit.
So my background is I studied AI.
I have a Masters in that back when AI was not hot at all.
It was the middle of the winter of AI.
Nobody wanted to do anything with it but I thought hey why not.
But then it turned out I did not really do anything with AI for a long time so I just
became a regular web developer doing first PHP like I said and then Elixir.
But I'm still interested in AI in hardware and software and also in art actually because
after when I stopped or graduated from AI school I went to the art academy, the Rietveld
Academy in Amsterdam and I decided to proceed the career in art or at least try to do something
more creative outside of pure computer science.
So one of the, let's talk about that a bit because it gets me slowly to the knitting
stuff.
So I worked with Glazine van der Zonschl, she's a friend of mine and an artist slash
interaction designer and together we did quite a lot of projects that were related to this
kind of stuff.
So for instance we built an app where you could interact with a fake social network
from the Dutch Golden Age.
So you would walk around in a museum and then you would walk next to a Rembrandt painting
and then Rembrandt would send you a private message and wanted to become your friend.
And that way it actually told the story back in that Golden Age that was also already like
a social network.
It told the story of history basically through a current situation and it's still used by
children mostly for education.
Other similar kind of project is where in Ghent where we created the augmented reality
installation where there was actually a chat, a little chat going on here and there was
an archaeologist who was chatting to you about the objects that you would scan.
Another project that was really nice during Covid actually was Distance Disco and Duo
Disco which is like an app where you dance silently with your headphones on and you're
matched to somebody else and then you have to basically mimic how you dance and then
based on if you find somebody who dances like you then you're probably dancing to the same
song because everybody listens to another song.
I gave a talk, it's also written, that was written in Erlang actually, the back end for
that, like with processes for everything and matching people together.
That's another talk.
Another talk that I actually did three years ago here was with this printer.
It was also a project for Glazine where she created some kind of interactive cooking installation
from the future.
So you first would have to interact with this Google speaker over here and then the speaker
would ask you a few very personal questions like do you believe in God and do you value
your privacy and what would you do if, I don't know.
And based on those information there would be a little recipe printed out and you would
get instructions on to make something in that installation.
So it was only logical that when Glazine got some new projects that she thought of me and
she thought of hey, I have now this customer which is our customer.
It was some art collective of people who approach Glazine to make some kind of installation
for a conference.
People like conferences like this where there would be somewhere a back channel with information
on how the people in the conference are doing.
So for instance a graph of the mood or tweets or pictures, etc.
And she thought hey, why would we show that on the screen?
Why not show it in a knitting?
Which is logical, right?
And then she thought of me.
This doesn't work, sorry.
I have to do it like this.
Because actually 10 years ago I already hacked a knitting machine once together with two
very talented people who did actually most of the knitting.
I just did most of the software around it.
But this was also a long time ago.
You can I think still loop this project up.
So Glazine thought well, I want to make like a giant knitting for a conference where everything
that is happening in the conference gets knitted out and then we have this big carpet that
you can still look at after, like a big blanket of conference feedback.
So she asked me do you want to do this project?
And I was like yeah, why not?
Because it was for me, it's not like I do this kind of stuff full time.
It's more that I do it because I just like it and whenever Glazine has an idea I just
do it.
So we went on to eBay or Mark Platz actually and we bought this Pass Up electronic knitting
machine, which is a machine from I think 30 or 40 years ago.
Swiss made, so very well made.
Some people describe this machine as the Rolls Royce under the knitting machines.
So I thought hey, this is a nice machine to look at and to see if I can make it knit what
I want.
So I bought it and I put it in my home.
So now I have a room which is basically the knitting room because it's a large machine.
It's like I couldn't bring it unfortunately.
I would have.
And I thought well, it's like a printer, right?
It has pixels.
Every knitting is a printer, is a pixel and I just write a printer driver for it basically.
Well, it's not that easy as it turns out.
Unfortunately and over the last couple of months I've grown a lot of respect for the
whole knitting industry, the robotics things because there's actually a lot more to it
than just now we as a software developer, we're very lucky to be in such a stable environment
where we just write code and it does something or it doesn't something but there's nothing
in between.
It's not hardware.
It is kind of interesting to learn.
And also I found out there's actually YouTube videos of people operating this machine and
those people are usually like 60 year old women.
But they can do it.
So there's like a lot of instructions how to do it.
There's a lot of parameters to tweak.
A lot of weird tools that you have to use to get it right.
But eventually I got it somehow working.
It's basically the parameter space of like you have to have a certain knit, a certain
thickness of the yarn and you have to like the proper tension of the yarn because otherwise
you get loops.
It is unbelievable how much it's like it's basically like trying to learn to play the
violin or trying to yeah something like that and like playing trying to play the violin
without a proper instructor present or the instructor has died already because it's such
an old violin.
So I have a very small clip of me knitting if it's here.
Hello.
Oh, there we go.
It takes a while.
And there's no release, no sound.
Oh, it's very short.
But this is basically how it goes.
So the machine is there, there's yarn coming in from the top and the machine goes over
the needles.
There's a lot of needles here and then once this carriage goes over, it basically the
needles hook into it and make it like a yarn or the knitting and the knitting comes out
from the needle.
And how did I want to automate this?
I have to watch my time a bit.
I actually found online some Germans who actually used this machine before to hack it because
there's actually, ah, damn it, this doesn't work.
So what I wanted to replace was this, how you used to program it was you basically,
there was this big flow chart in this manual where you would need to press the buttons
in a certain combination and then set the dials, everything, and then upload the pattern.
And the way you upload the pattern is you basically take a piece of matrix paper like
with a grid and you make some of the cells you make black and that's basically your pattern.
So you draw pixel art on a paper and you feed the paper into the scanner because this is
a kind of a scanner.
And then this thing somehow says, okay, well, I've now remembered that pattern.
And then this machine communicates with the thing that goes, the carriage that goes back
and forth and that actually then knits that pattern.
I did not try to do that because it sounded very hard.
So instead I found this space from the Ekerspace Bemberg in which they used an Arduino because
this is the connector that you need to plug into the console.
So I basically replaced the whole console with an Arduino.
So on one side there's the Arduino communicating with the carriage and then out comes digital
signals, just a serial protocol that goes back into the computer and then the computer
can tell, knit this pattern, knit that pattern, etc.
If you have more questions about this, I can answer a lot.
I'm not going to do it right now.
Basically the new user interface that I'm working right now looks a bit like this.
So it's just basically a browser.
And also because I wanted to use LiveView for something.
So we're finally getting to that subject.
Yes.
So this knitting interface shows a bit, it shows, well, basically where the machine is
at in the knit process.
And it shows the current color that it is knitting.
And it shows whether you have to move it left or right because there is a motor, you can
enable the motor so that it knits automatically.
But you can also do it manually.
So it has a little counter, it has a start-stop button and it has several configuration things
like because it's a very big knitting machine.
So you have to specify, I have to knit it here, I can knit it there.
It's so wide.
And then you can upload a pattern.
So you can type in 1 to 0 here.
Literally you can type in 1 and 1 to 0 and it will then create a pattern and then there's
a state machine that will loop through that pattern to send the proper instructions to
the Arduino.
So I'm going to demo that a bit later because first I want to go a bit into the detail of
this live view.
It's not only live view.
It's basically just a Phoenix or just an Elixir project.
And it has several parts.
One of it, of course, is the user interface which is all the way over there.
And the other part is the actual knitting machine that's over here.
So it's connected with an Arduino like I showed.
And the Arduino is connected to the Elixir.
So this middle part is the interesting software part that I've built.
So there's a few components here and I've created some kind of color coding for that
in front of myself.
So basically green is an Erlang process or Elixir process.
And orange is like state.
It's just data.
And without color is something that is not very interesting.
So basically whenever I used a NURV3 library, I think it was already mentioned that NURV3
is really nice for doing IoT kind of things with Elixir.
So UART is the protocol.
It's basically a serial port.
So whenever you program an Arduino, you can tell it to send and receive serial commands.
And you can very easily listen to them with Elixir.
There's a monitor that basically looks for the serial port.
So I can hotplug basically the knitting machine into my computer and pull it out.
And then basically whenever it receives some serial packet, just a line, basically just
a text line, it sends this over, Phoenix pops up to the rest of the system.
And then there are several other components that listen to those serial commands.
One of them is the control, which is a gen server that basically has all this state.
Basically it has all this state, like where am I in the knitting, et cetera.
So that gen server holds the state of the knitting machine itself.
So that basically has the task of transforming this pattern plus the settings into a sequence
of commands that needs to be sent out to the knitting machine.
And also the state is also updated whenever new serial commands come in.
And then the control is also connected to the live view, which actually shows everything
that is being done.
So what I'm going to talk the rest of is mostly this part, because that's the title of the
talk.
It's about live view and how that works and what it is actually, how it works in my case.
Are there any questions?
Oh, I have 10 minutes left.
Really?
Okay.
I have 10 minutes left.
So let's go for a bit quicker now.
What is live view?
Well, from the docs it says, live view provides rich real-time experiences with user rendered
HTML and to understand or with server rendered HTML.
And to understand what that actually means, let's dive into a little bit of the web history.
When this whole Internet thing started, the first thing there was was just a browser with
HTML, right?
So you had a web server, you uploaded the HTML file to and you just view it.
That's basically it.
And when you want to go to another page, you just click a link and you view the other page.
That's basically what we now call a static website.
Very static.
So that worked pretty well for a while.
And then when at some point people thought, well, we can also not make the static, but
we can send something different back every time.
So that's when it became the HTML, dynamic HTML, PHP was born, other programming, I'm
getting feedback from the mic now.
It's a bit irritating.
Whatever.
So basically, the HTML became dynamic.
So there was a lot of logic on the server.
You would make a PHP file that rendered out HTML.
The HTML was different for each user even because there were sessions.
You have cookies where you store basically the state.
Like this user is logged in.
This user has this stuff in his cart.
Whatever.
So there's a lot of logic on the server that renders into HTML and then the HTML is just
sent over the wire and the browser displays it when done.
So that worked pretty okay.
But it was not really interactive because every time you had to do something in the
site, it would reload the page.
So then at some point people thought, hey, I can make little effects.
I can do hovers and animations.
So we make a JavaScript that was born basically, I think with IE version something free started
to become popular.
So there was a bit of JavaScript written to make things a bit more lively and a bit more
dynamic without having to reload the page every time.
Well, of course, you know what happened next.
So JavaScript became very big.
So a lot of the logic was actually moved to the client.
So the pages did not reload every time.
Basically just loaded the page one time and then JavaScript basically takes care of the
rest.
It was just parts of the HTML with other parts.
It even sends you to another URL without actually re-loading the page with push date kind of
things.
So there was a lot of logic on the client suddenly.
And it would fetch underwater, not over HTML, but it would just use what's called Ajax.
But currently we have REST and GraphQL, all kinds of protocols to get data into the client
and then do stuff with the data.
So there was a lot of logic suddenly on the client.
And this is still the case.
I think when you write JavaScript, there's a like, or when you, any web project is quite
heavy on the server side or on the client side.
Now with LiveView, the pendulum has swung in the other way a bit again.
Because the actually very interesting thing about LiveView is that we can do very interactive
things.
We don't have to reload the page every time to do something interactive.
We can stay on the same page, but we can still dynamically change parts of the page without
having to do very heavy, create all kinds of APIs and do complicated things.
So suddenly with LiveView, the logic is again mostly for 99%, I would say, back on the server.
So it's actually, it's like a bit again from back in the old days.
You just render something, you just put it to the browser and then the browser displays
it.
It's as simple as that.
You don't need to write a lot of JavaScript unless you really want to.
And that's actually one of the promises of LiveView, that you can make UIs very quickly
just staying in Elixir and just templating from Elixir.
So how does that actually work?
Is there a diagram on the next slide?
Yes.
So basically what happens is, I can show this one first.
So there's one LiveView process.
So basically in Erlang, processes are very lightweight.
Five minutes left, oh no.
Templates are rendered on the server and they are rendered every time you update the state.
But it does not send the whole template over to the client, it just sends the things that
are changed.
So basically it works a bit like this.
So the first time it renders, we get some HTML and then it actually connects over a
WebSocket and then it says, hey, I'm a LiveView process and I can now interact with you.
And then whenever some state changes, the browser is now connected to the corresponding
process in the server.
So when the state changes, it actually re-renders something and it actually just sends the things
that have changed, sends it to the browser.
And then the browser is intelligent enough that it can just patch small parts of the
DOM tree to just change that part and not change everything.
So that makes it very lightweight and very flexible.
And this is a bit, well, when you start with this, it is now integrated into Phoenix, the
Elixir Web Framework.
And I will give a little demo now, I think.
Yeah, so let's make the knitting live.
So it would look a bit like, when you write in the Elixir module, it looks a bit like this.
There's always something you have to write, it's mount.
When you mount something, you just return, okay, I'm mounted and I have some assigns
in my socket.
It's a bit like normal Phoenix templating.
You assign things to something and then you can render, use those assigns to render something.
So back below here, there's actually the render function and in this case, it just renders
an image tag, image class movie.
Wonder what that is.
And the source is some kind of, is an image URL with a variable in it, a frame, and the
frame is assigned here.
So it renders a single image.
And whenever a serial command comes in from a serial port, basically, I calculate a new
frame and then assign it to the socket again.
So this triggers another render here and it will probably change the frame number, so
it will change the image.
So this basically connects the serial port to a live view.
I think that's better.
So I actually have a demo of that because I actually, well, I did not bring my knitting
machine, I actually brought my knitting machine emulator, which is an Arduino with a potentiometer
attached.
And I can probably now, this will fill, but who cares, plug it in and then we go to this.
So if you look in the source, we see somewhere that here, this is the one, we see the movie.
It's now at frame number 15.
And then if we, is it running?
Should be running.
If we now turn the knob.
Yes.
Okay.
So now I can knit.
You see, I am knitting.
So I did not bring my whole machine, but I brought a virtual version of myself that is
now at home and I can control it through this little Arduino over here.
I thought of this last night to demo it like this.
It was not really prepared.
So I hope that gets you a bit of the idea how live view updates its state.
And in this case, it is very simple, but an actual live view, of course, is much more,
much bigger.
And actually that is the rest of my talk that I'm still need to do.
Let's continue very quickly.
How much?
Oh, time's up.
Okay.
Is it really up?
I think that you can take like one or two minutes.
Okay.
I will quickly skip through the next slides then.
So you can imagine that writing a single Elixir module with every logic in it, you get one
big assign with everything.
It's not really scalable.
So there are actually two things to make that scalable.
You make components.
So one of the components is function components, which are basically just rendering templates
inside functions.
And then the other ones are Phoenix live components.
And those are basically like sub live views in your live view that have their own state
and their own render function and their own mount function.
So in this case, in my UI, these are, I just created a few components, one component is
settings components, which contains a form.
Another component is a row component that just renders a single row.
So the row components are very simple.
It just renders basically a set of diffs.
And then you can call it like this.
So it's basically in the template syntax using function components, basically the same as
a normal tag, but you prepend it with a dot, which is because it's basically a function
call.
And the live components are stateful.
So live components have their own state, so they have a mount.
You can assign things to there.
It's basically what I already said.
It's a live view inside a live view.
So these signals directly communicate with the live components in this case.
Then there's some more things like slots you can create like different parts of your component
and make them into like separate things where you can put part of your DOM tree as well.
And I just wanted to say there's a lot out there, like there's a big community, and I
think live view is really getting a lot of traction.
And it's actually a shame.
I have not done anything really with live view in production actually.
I wanted to make a disclaimer there.
But I really like where it's going, and there's a lot of projects popping up with component
libraries and people making stuff on top of it.
There's the storybook project, which is also very nice, which allows you to make a library
of components and then have a live environment somewhere where you can document these components
and try them out and copy paste the code for you to use inside your live view.
So there's a lot of things, like JavaScript integration, which I'm not going to show.
There's live view native coming up.
It's also very nice technology where you don't render things to the browser, but you render
things into a native app so that it actually builds a native act.
What React Native is to React is, well, you get the drift.
So thank you for listening.
Thank you, Aryan.