Okay. Okay, now we have Linus de Meijer with shorter feedback loops with Livebook. Give
it up.
All right. Thank you. Can everybody hear me? Yeah. To my surprise, I am the first and
only Belgian here presenting. I can welcome you all here. Maybe the first question I
want to ask, which is the most important one, who is hungry right now? All right. Sorry,
I cannot help with that. But another question I would like to ask is who has heard of Livebook?
Who knows what it is, more or less? Yeah. Okay. It's a lot of people. Who has worked
with Livebook professionally or has just it on their computer? Okay. Less people, but
there are some. If you want to follow along and if you already installed Livebook, then
you can go to my GitHub repository. I have a little notebook prepared. And I try to switch
back and forth between this presentation and the Livebook. All right. The goals of today
would be to introduce you to Livebook to make sure you all understand what it is, how you
can get it, how you install it, the various options. And then I think the most interesting
part is how I used it in three different cases and what I learned from using it in a real
project. And underneath all this, I hope I can bring across the message that Livebook
really helps to start somewhere in the middle. So you don't spend time like folding an application.
And then just after a few days or hours, get to the most interesting part. So Livebook
enables you to start in the middle. That's my main message here. Whenever you start Livebook,
you're greeted with an introduction page. At the top, you see your folder structure.
There is a very nice learning section. And at the bottom there, you have your sessions.
So you will import a Livebook often, and then a session will appear, and you can hook into
that. So you can... That's actually what we are going to do here. I'm going to go to my
notebook that I just prepared here. And, yeah, I just wanted to point out if you are just
starting with Livebook, there is a very good learning section. So please go through these.
Also if you're learning Elixir, it's a very good way to familiarize yourself with Elixir.
And it also covers things like how you make pretty graphs or how you would use the Kino
library, which is the one that is used to actually interact with your Livebook.
It's all just markdown. So it uses those... Yeah, you can see here. It uses these code
fences with Elixir annotation. So it's very easy to check into your GitHub repository
and make sure you can review it if you want. And GitHub also recently added the feature
that it nicely formats your Livebooks. They have the extension LiveMD. So it integrates
nicely with your version control system. The basics. We have code cells which can be
executed. They contain your codes. And the first one is a little bit special in the sense
that it often contains your setup. So you can pull in all your dependencies. So you
can use the mix install function. And I'm going to use a few here. Not too many. But
I'll go over these once they become relevant. So right here we have our first code cell.
We can just execute it. Takes a while to just start up. But then we can go. It is being
evaluated. You can see the green dots. So it's being evaluated. And you have all those
nice features that you can expect from an IDE. So you can ask it to autocomplete. If
you control space one more time, you get all the documentation that is for that function.
So you get a lot of help editing your code here. The result is being printed down below
here. And you also have the ability to, like I did here actually, to put stuff. And that's
also being printed underneath your code cell. So that's very nice. And, yeah, maybe the
most or a very important feature at least, it's that you can interleave your code blocks
with just regular markdown. So it's a really nice way to do little coding and then explain
what you have done and then go on to do the code again. Yes. A few words about reproducibility.
It's very nice to have this notebook and to know what actually will happen if you execute
all those code cells. If you start from the beginning, it's very clear. You go from top
to bottom. But what if you're going to edit in the middle, make a change somewhere? Well,
Livebook has you covered. It analyzes all those bindings that are being made in those
code cells. And it makes sure that if you change something, the relevant code cells
underneath them are also going to be executed again. So that's actually the way you often
build up states. You have a code cell that creates a binding. And then in the next code
cell, you can reuse that or you can use that binding so you can build upon when you go
through all the code cells. I can do a little demonstration how branching sections work.
So the sections are actually shown very clearly here on the sides. I have a few of them. But
one has the little branch icon. So this is a branching section. And this is just to show
how the execution model actually works. So right here, I demonstrate that you can use
the bindings from before. So from the main flow of the notebook. And if I start an infinite
loop here, this is just going to stay printing in this little frame here. You will see that
if I execute a code cell below, it will be queued. But it will never run because the
other code is just blocking that one. But if we carry on to the next session, we can
see that all is well again. So this is still blocked. But this is the main threat of execution.
So we are not blocked here anymore. And just to show that we cannot access the bindings
from before, I just triggered this error because we cannot access this variable. Okay. This
is a pretty picture that I stole from Rosse Hallem. I'm not going to go into detail. But
I just want to point out that everything is based or is heavily using the airline distribution
mechanisms that we all know from the airline OTP ecosystem. So we have a central application
here. It's a live view application actually with a lot of JavaScript. And we can connect
to it through WebSockets. That's all being handled for us. And it does not run the code
actually on the live book application itself. But in normal mode, it will spawn a new node
and run your code on this new node. So this we call it a runtime. This runtime is not
aware of anything live book related. It is just a plain node that can execute code and
you get the results back. So that's what's going on underneath. There are a lot of ways
you can get live book on your computer. Recently, well, I used to like Escript installation.
But since it's tied to your Elixir installation, I now switch to using the desktop application,
which is getting very good at this point. You also can run it in the cloud. You can
have it as a Docker image. That's all being covered. The various ways to start. Not very
interesting. But I think what's more interesting is my story of how I used it to mitigate risks
early on some projects that I've been doing. Yes. I just want to sum up here the benefits
that I see. So it allows you to start in the middle. If you're using live book, you can
jump straight into your problem space. It increases transparency. And you can use it
because you can use that markdown in between to document your process. So all your thoughts,
you can put them in between all those code cells. And it's, I think, way better than
those obscure scripts we sometimes write. And you can also very easily share this document.
So that's actually something that we did. I got some tasks to do. A client was asking
something. We were doing something with machine learning and artificial intelligence. We were
not aware or we did not know whether we could do it. So I sat down, made a slide hook, and
then documented all the steps I did. And in the end, got a pretty graph out of it so I
could convince the clients that we could do it actually with Elixir.
Just a little bit of context. I work for a small company. We often switch in between
projects. The company is named Zenjoy. And we are often working as a team of two. So
documentation and collaboration is very important. And also the communication with the clients
is very, very important. So this first case, we were tasked to interpret
with or to call an undocumented legacy API. It was very low level. It was not as low level
as tools explained to us. So it was not like we had to do the pattern matching on the bit
level. But we had to use the GenTCP module straight from Erlang. But it was very nice
to have this live book environment where we could just throw the commands at this server
that we could somehow use and see what came back. So in this way, we were able to create
a notebook that documented all the commands we could see or how it reacted. And you see
some pattern matching going on here. You also see some magic variables. So this was given
to us. So we could not change this. But at least we could document it. And this became
a very long document to refer back to. So this is another demonstration I wanted to
do. It's not because you're in the browser that you're constrained by any way. You can
still use all the process magic and all the Gen servers you like. And this is just a demonstration
of how you would go around and spawn a TCP server. I'm using Thousand Island here. In
reality, I was using the other one, the older one. Cowboy and ranch. Yes, thank you. But
now for this demonstration, I got to use Thousand Island. And it's super nice. So you can just
define your handler. It's just going to echo back whatever we sent to it. And here I started
up the only caveat or the thing you have to be aware of is that you can start your children,
your processes and your supervisor tree under the keynote code cell. So whenever you reevaluate
here, you see that you can't see. But another process is started or a whole tree started.
So this is a nice interop with the livebook environment. And once we have those, we can
even... Yeah. Yeah, I guess that the gods are not with me today. But at least, yeah,
what I wanted to show is that you can actually draw a pretty picture of the supervision tree
right here. But still, I think the server got started. And so now I can net cut into
my local host on this given port. And I can see how some stuff is being echoed back to
me. So at least that works. All right. Back to the presentation. So it is a nice environment
to like stop out a server and set up a situation where you can then use your application to
interact with this stubbed version of your API. All right. I'm going to show... Or this
is just an example of how you would integrate your livebook with a regular mix project.
It's all just sitting next to each other. Oftentimes, I just make a folder where the
notebook lives and then your mix project, whatever it is, it can be a Phoenix application.
You can access it if you use the bot way of referencing your dependencies. A few words
about a typical lifecycle that I've observed. You often start to experiment in your livebook.
On good days, you add tests. And then you move all that code into the regular application
or in the regular mix project. And you reference it from there on in a way that I just described.
So you promote reusable code. And that's often a way that worked very well for me. The second
case that I want to discuss is how I set up or created concurrent ETL pipeline, which
is a fancy word for just loading CSV files and then maybe transforming them and dumping
them into Postgres. So I really got to learn a lot about how concurrent data processing
actually happens. I got to play around with Flow, which is a very nice library which builds
on top of Gen State. No, not Gen State, the other one. Gen Stage, that's the one. And
you can still use all the power of processes that is available in Erlang and Elixir. To
demonstrate, I've prepared or I want to show how you can use Ecto and then this Flow library
right within your live hook application. To start off, I create a repository just like
you would do in a Phoenix application. Don't worry if you do not recognize this. This is
kind of standard stuff. You have to specify the adapter. And then you can emulate whatever
mix Ecto creates with you. So you make sure that your storage is up. In my case, it was
already up. So that's what it reports. And then you can even make your migrations like
you would if you used Ecto together with a Phoenix application. In this case, I also
make sure there was an item in the database so we can query it later on. So I have to
make sure that this repository actually runs. And then I migrate, well, I do a rollback
to make sure nothing is being left over and then I migrate again. So we have the end situation
that I can query right here. So you can see that our fresh entry is just inserted with
this new timestamp. And then we can build upon this. This is another demonstration,
very short. This is a definition of a flow. Also, don't worry if you do not recognize
this. That's not the key here. I just want to show that you can use all those goodies
and you're not constrained in any way. Right here, we are just emitting a value every second.
And we're going to wait for three seconds and then insert an item in the database again.
So you get the logging. And if we query again, so you might recognize the nice Ecto query
syntax you see. I've wrapped it in a data table and you can now see the three new items
appearing. So what's very nice, here you see me playing around and actually visualizing
this ETL pipeline where every color actually is another class of objects or is being inserted
in another table. It went very quickly. But when making this presentation, I also saw
there is some room for improvement. So not all cylinders are firing together, but at
least it was fast enough for our purposes. Another case I want to share with you is that
we used a live hook to actually connect to a live running instance. So remember, as I
have shown in the beginning, it's all just Erlang distribution under the hood. So instead
of using the regular setup where you do an Elixir standalone setting, you can also do
an attached node configuration. The only thing you have to know is your node's name or your
short name and a cookie which you have to agree upon. And it's very good for doing one
of tasks. Maybe you don't have a UI for something yet and you want to do it in a live book,
then this is a nice way to actually have like a super admin interface. But be aware that
it's still a live environment. So if you do this, make sure to put a big disclaimer on
top of your notebook to remind you of the risks involved. All right. The last thing
that I want to share or show is how you would do tests in live hook. Like I said, on a good
day you write tests. And we have seen some examples in the previous presentations how
you would do a doc test where you attach some kind of formatted tests and its expected output.
Well, since a few versions, these tests are actually automatically run. So if you define
a module, in this case Christmas, you see that the doc tests are failing. I think I
can easily fix it by changing the expectation. And if you run it again, the doc tests are
green again. But you can also do just your regular testing. The only thing you have to
think about is that you have to disable your auto running. But then again, you can do your
testing and you have to make sure you call the run function on the XUnit module. So there
is no excuse not to test, actually. I want to end with reference to these two resources.
There is an initiative by DocYard Academy. It's an open source curriculum to learn elixir.
And they have used the notebooks or the livebooks to actually teach this to students. And the
other thing you might have heard about in the elixir news is the project Bumblebee,
which allows you to actually play around with these new neural networks like GPT-2 and stable
diffusion. And you can just do it locally. So it's a very nice way. It integrates very
nice into your live notebook. All right. That's it for me. Thank you very much.
Thank you very much. Is there any question? Could you maybe compare and contrast live
books with Jupyter notebooks? Yes, that's actually a reference. Sorry. So the question
was how this relates to the Jupyter notebooks, which we might also know. I think it's very
much inspired by it. So it's also a computational notebook. But I also see a lot of differences,
although I do not know Jupyter notebooks very well. But I think, for example, like the dependencies
in the first cell, I do not think there is such a system in the Jupyter notebooks. You
would have to use like Comda or Anaconda to set up your dependency. So it's a little bit
less integrated. But I cannot say more about differences. But you're very right. There
is a strong inspiration there. Yes. Thank you. Any other question?
Cool. Thanks for the talk. I wanted to ask actually whether there is an option as well
for a lifebook being available as an UI within the IDE. So kind of connected closer to the
development environment? No, not that I know of. No, no. It runs in
the browser and that's where it lives. So you can install it as a standalone application,
but it's still something that lives in the browser. But you're right in the sense that
it is not a full blown IDE. And that's also one of the nuances that I have noticed is
that if you have very large code cells, for example, you are missing some features. And
if you're used to VI bindings, for example, you will not find them there.
Cool. Thanks. Yes. Okay. Last question.
Does this work for multiple users collaborating on things?
Yes. And I should have shown this. It is one of the nicest features. Thank you for opening
that door. If you're using multiple sessions or, for example, multiple users in multiple
locations, you, for example, see the selections they made. You see a little cursor where they
are editing or you are editing. And you're actually editing the same notebook. So yes,
that's kind of a life coding environment. Yes. Yeah.
I don't know. No. It's building on top of these goodies we have. Yeah.
Okay. Thank you again.