Okay. Now we have Trolls Brozgad and he's going to speak to us of Biner pattern matching and
Elixir and Erlang, one of the cool features of Erlang and Elixir. So, do you speak binary
to me? Give it up for Trolls. Thank you. Don't worry, I'm not going to speak binary, but
yes, this is talk about speaking binary to other devices. And this is me and you can
find me around the web at TRARBR. Yes. I work as a software developer in Denmark and a company
called IndieLab and part of my job is to work on innovations in the Internet of Things realm.
So things like smart buildings, smart cities and smart factories. In practice, this involves
building gateways that link many different kinds of stupid things together and then when
we have a network of things, we can exchange information and we can embed the smartest
into the system. And by many different stupid things, things like remote terminal units,
which are used in the grid, electric grid and other utilities, PLCs, which are used heavily
in factories for automation, solar inverters, heat pumps, thermostats, all kinds of smart
home equipment and at the lowest level we have simple sensors and actuators. And the
thing that all these things have in common is that we had to speak binary to them. They
don't speak JSON, they don't know XML, they don't know protocol even. They had their own
custom binary dialects depending on the protocol that they are using. And later in this talk
I'll show an example of a simple binary dialect so that we all know what that is. When I'm
building an integration for a system like this, I always read for Alexa first. This
is because Alexa has a special authority system that makes it extremely good at this kind
of work. This is also the case for Erlang and LFE and Beam and Gleam and the other languages
on the Erlang virtual machine, but Alexa happens to be my happy space. Some of the Beam's
known strong points in this area are fault tolerance, state machines and concurrency.
And then there's bits and text. That's what I'll be talking about today. This is a beginner
level talk. I don't assume you know anything about Alexa or the previously mentioned systems.
But my hope is that if you should find yourself in a situation where you need to speak binary
to something, this talk will help you get started.
So binaries. Computers today work by manipulating electric signals. And a signal can be either
a logic high or a logic low. Such a signal is known as a bit. And a sequence of eight
bits is a byte. And this is also how computers communicate. No matter if it's ethernet or
Wi-Fi or whatever, it's about transferring a logic signal of high and low bits. And there
are different ways we can write down the sort of binary signals. The first notation that
I highlighted here isn't binary, where we just take every bit in the sequence and we
write it down as a zero or a one. And then it prefixes it with a zero or a B so that
it's easier to tell from other numbers. And in this case, the sequence of eight bits,
which is a byte, can also be turned into a decimal number. Because in a byte we can have
256 different combinations. So it's a number from zero to 255. And in decimal notation,
this sequence of bits is 75. There's also a hex notation where we use the characters
zero to nine and A to F. This means we can have described the concept of a byte with
just two characters. So this is very convenient when we are dealing with binary numbers. Just
a common example of where we write the bytes as decimals. We do that with IPv4 addresses.
Because an IPv4 address is just four bytes. But then for human consumption, we write it
as a binary number. Or sorry, a decimal number. And Mac addresses use a hex notation instead
of the binary notation. While all the operations in our computers are processing bits and bytes,
we rarely think about them when we are programming. We think in terms of integers, floats, strings,
lists, maps, and other structures. But binary data is just a flat stream of bits. There's
nothing inherent in it to tell one field from the other. Or any kind of structure. It's
all down to how we interpret those bits. This means that when we need to speak binary to
something from our programs, we need to write a translation layer that can take whatever
list of maps we have in our program and turn it into a binary sequence. I prefer calling
this translation layer a codec because it's short to write. And you can say that a codec
encodes our data structures in bytes for sending. And then we receive data, the codec decodes
that data into our higher level data structures. And sometimes we're lucky we can find a library
that will do that for us. But sometimes we need to do it ourselves. And that's where
bits and text comes in handy. So let's take a look at that. Let's say I need to send a
sequence of three bytes to some other system. They need to have values 10, 20, and 30. To
do that, I use distance X. So I use double-ankle brackets to start the binary sequence. And
then I write the bytes that I need in sequence and separate it by a comma. So that's pretty
simple. Yes. And when I need to receive that data, like if I'm receiving the same sequence
of bytes, I need to decode that into three variables, A, B, and C. Then I use distance
X, again, double brackets. Then I put the variables instead of the numbers that I want
to extract. So it's pretty simple. But of course, we're not really done yet. There's
very few domains where we only work with integers in the sequence of 0 to 255. We need larger
numbers. We need negative numbers. We need loads and strings. But many languages will
just give a byte stream. And then you need to sort of do a lot of strange computations
to turn that into lists and strings. But in Elixir and on the Beam, we have the distance
X and we can do more. Specifically, with distance X, we have the option or the ability to specify
modifiers. And the modifiers can specify the type, the size, unit, and indianness of the
sequence of bits we want to extract from the binary. So here you see that the type is integer.
It's unsigned, so it's positive numbers only. It has a size of eight units. And one unit
is said to be one bit long. And it's big indian, which I will talk about later. So these are
all equivalent, 10, 20, 30. They're encoded the same way as just different syntaxes. So
you can see if you don't specify any modifiers, these are the defaults that I used instead.
And in the second line, I omitted size of just row eight. That's something you can do
when you know it has a constant at compile time. If the size is variable, you will need
to use the full size modifier. And the modifiers can be combined in any order. So you can do
whatever you like. And when we decode it, we use exactly the same syntax. We can say
the same things like grab the first byte, tell it to compile it as an integer, and then
it will extract it like this. And instead of just going through all the different modifiers
and the combinations, I move on to showcasing some examples. But before we do that, I want
to mention where the bits and text came from. Bits and text comes from a place of pain.
These two guys, Claire, we're working at the computer science laboratory on implementing
networking protocols for Erlang. And it was painful. And so they sat down since they were
so close to the makers of the language, they could invent a new syntax for use in Erlang.
And this paper, which is published in 1998, describes the first version of the syntax
as it was implemented in an experimental version of Erlang. I think a few months later it was
released with a slightly different syntax, but with all the same concepts. And that paper
also explains what Indianness is. And it's actually just a fun word for byte order. Because
if you have a 16-bit integer that you need to send to some other system, that's two bytes,
right? And you have to figure out the one byte is A2 and the other byte is C1. And you
have to figure out which byte do you send first. Some systems will send the most significant
byte first. So that's A2. But other systems will send the least significant byte first.
That's C1. And so this obviously has consequences because you need to know the byte order that
the system you're talking to, what it expects. Otherwise, you just get confused. And yes,
the byte ordering is said to be big Indian when you start with the most significant byte
and it's said to be little Indian if you start with the least significant byte. And this
is kind of a thing. I've been working with this for years, but I didn't really know what
Indian means because it's a sort of weird name, right? But the paper by class and Tony
hinted me in the direction of finding that by pointing me to this Internet experiment
note from 1980, which is I think the first sort of place where Indian and byte order
was used together on holy wars of the plea for peace. And that sort of shows that this
is an important topic, sort of like VIM versus HEMEX, I guess. And it's actually just Indian
is just a pop culture reference to a book called Golovac Travels where a seagull travels
out into the world and meets the people of the Lilliput and Blya Fusco, I think, and
the armed conflict because the emperor of Lilliput has commanded that X must be broken
at the little end when you eat them for breakfast or whatever. So that's obviously absurd and
so they wait a war. So big Indian means we send the big end of the number first and the
little Indian means we send a little end of the number. So examples of bits and texts.
For the purpose of this talk, I have invented the T-box, which is very simple device. It
has a name and it can measure the temperature and it can tell you if there's an error in
the timestamp or the measurement. It has a binary dialect or protocol, which I also invented.
And this sort of mirrors what you will find in a real protocol description for some kind
of device. A client can connect to a T-box and can send requests to the T-box and the
T-box will respond with a reply. Every message that is sent includes a header, which is one
byte long and replies from the T-box will also contain a value. The header starts with
four bits of magic, which is a constant value that is always there and is used to sort of
make sure this is the beginning of a message. Then there's a direction bit, which tells
whether this message is a request or a reply. And there's the attribute free bits, which
are used to tell if this is a name or temperature message. Yes, there are extra, we only use
one bit in the attribute, but that's just because they expect to expand the protocol
someday. So this is an example of a sequence request
reply. First we send the request with the header with the magic bits first, then it's
a zero because the direction is a request. And then we're requesting one, which means
we're requesting the temperature. And then the reply has almost the same header at the
beginning is just one in place of the direction and then the bytes with the value after that.
If you're requesting the name of the T-box, then it will respond with 12 bytes and it's
always 12 bytes. If the name is shorter than 12 bytes, then the rest of the bytes are just
null bytes. And that looks like this. If the name of the box is first, then you have six
bytes of actual characters and then null bytes for the rest.
And the temperature is a little more complicated. It has three fields. There's the time, which
is a 32 bit integer. Counting the number of seconds since 1st of January 1970. Then there's
the temperature, which is a 16 bit float. And then there's a quality byte which tells you
whether there's an error in some of the measurements. It's the two last bits in the cube byte that
are used. The second to last bit tells you there's an error in the clock. And the last
bit tells you there's an error in the temperature measurement. And it's important to note that
the numbers are a little Indian. So this is what a temperature value looks like. First
it has a time stamp, which is a couple days ago. Then the temperature, which is 32 degrees
about that. And then both of the error bits are high, so you should not trust this sample.
So bit syntax. We want to send a request to the T-box to get the name. I used the double
anchor brackets again. It's all integers and it's all unsigned, so the only thing I have
to specify is the size. And here I specify the magic is four bits. Then I have my direction,
one bit. And the attribute, which is zero for getting the name. So this shows how we
can use the bits and text to easily encode things which are smaller than bytes. And the
reply that comes back looks like this. But when we receive the reply, I do it like this.
First I assert that the message I get back is what I expect. So in place of the header,
I assert that the values are what I expect. I assert that I get the magic bits first,
that I get the direction bit is high so that I know it's a reply. And that the attribute
is zero so that I know it's a name. And when this is all true, I know that the rest of
the message is 12 bytes long. And I want to assign that to the variable name. And here
you can see I used the bytes modifier. This changes the type. And it changes the size
or the unit property. So before with integers, I would specify, like in the header, you can
see it's the colon, colon four for the magic. That means four bits. But when I specify bytes,
that the type of name is bytes, then I also say that it's the 12 means 12 bytes long and
not 12 bits long. Yeah, so that's just interesting that the bytes is the type that has different
defaults than integers. When I get the T box temperature, I request it like this. Pretty
much the same as before, just with a one for the attribute. And for the reply, I again
assert on the header that I expect what I get back what I expect. Then I have the timestamp
which was the 32 bit integer, but little indian. So let's put that in there. And the temperature,
which is a float, 16 bits, also little indian. Then I discard six bits from the Q byte because
they were not used. And then I just pluck the second to last and the last bit out as
clock error and temperature error. Yeah. So that's the basics of bits and text. There's
so much more to cover with writing whole applications to libraries to do this kind of stuff. Like
what do we do when you don't receive the entire message at once? You have to frame messages
when you're streaming them or receiving them as a stream. There's generators. There's a
special, it looks like just a normal four generator, but it actually has some interlanks
and special optimizations for working with binaries when you need to generate a binary.
We could talk about performance tuning, but as I said, I've been working with this for
years and I've never had to really do any performance tuning. It's pretty performant
as is. That's also one of the points in the paper by Claire and Tony is that this is performant.
And yeah, there are many other tools for working with binaries that help us when we're looking
at this data and not understanding why it's not doing what we expect. WhyShark is definitely
one of them. I recommend checking that out. I also recommend if you want to explore more
depth that you check out ProtoHackers, which is a sort of admin of code challenge thing,
but about the networking protocols. And Andrea Lo Party from the Elixir core team has a live
stream on YouTube or has streams on YouTube where he sort of goes through the problems
one by one. So that's very good for learning that. And they also started writing a book
about this kind of stuff. So that's it. Thank you.
And for the thought, Charles, do you have any questions?
So I've done, I've implemented a few binary protocols like network protocols, like HTTP2
or other stuff like that. I'd love to know how you, if you have done any like streaming
of data and passing of messages coming from streaming data and generators also would be
interesting. Just know like how you approached it because I know I did something, but I don't
know how we did it. I think I've implemented a few protocols that use, for example, TCP
as the underlying transport and then that's like a stream. And then there are a few patterns
for how you want to handle that. I think Frank and the NERF team wrote a sort of framing
behavior which where you have a couple of callbacks that you need to implement in order
to handle a stream so that they give you bytes and then you return back messages when you
see a full message. It's actually a very good sort of guideline for how to do that. Another
approach is taken by Andrei Luapati in his library for the Redis, where it's like you
call off when you call the decoding function and it returns a result, the result will be
whatever messages was in that binary you gave it and then a continuation function which
you call next time with more bytes so that continues to return new messages. Any question?
If I would buy a T-box from you, do I still get support in about 16 years from now? No.
Maybe five minutes. I actually have a question for you if there are no other questions. Do
you have a library you suggest to see because I implemented a library to decode the QOAI
which is the quite okay image format which is a new image format just to get my ions
dirty with binary pattern matching in Elixir but it gets very unwieldy very fast. So I
saw like in JZone they have some macros that generate binary pattern matching. Do you have
any libraries you recommend to check out? I think the Redis library is pretty nice.
I also have a KNX library which is like a small home protocol which I don't know if
I would recommend but when I wrote it I thought it made sense. Okay, thank you. Any other
questions? Okay. The last one I guess. Maybe a word about exceptions when patterns don't
match. You didn't talk about that if I'm correct. That's true. I mean sometimes we say we should
just let it crash and this community that's not always the case. Sometimes the protocol
will say that if you're unable to decode a message you must ignore it and just continue
going. In that case what I usually do is I define functions where I match on the data
I received and then I always need to have a fallback clause in case it didn't match
anything and then just lock an error and continue. But I mean probably the proper thing to do
in Erlang is to just try to die. There's also you could when you receive a message you could
have a special process that is only for decoding so you start a task, decode message and get
the data structure back. But I think it depends on the use case how you want to handle bad
data. Okay. Thank you very much.