All right, cool.
So again, apologies for being this late.
I really don't take it out on the people that are organizing this room.
It's really my fault.
So I hope still you have a nice day and I'll try to keep it short so we stay on schedule.
So this is kind of an introductory talk for people that are new to Alexur and Erlang.
So Alexur is a language which now already exists for 10 years and it's built on top
of the Beam virtual machine, also called the Erlang VM.
So they hired some of the properties that the Beam runtime has as well.
And Beam runtime is actually created for telecom systems.
So it's meant to be 24-7 on and by doing that it has to be full tolerant so if something
goes wrong it can still heal and keep on running.
And because it has to be on all the time, it also means that any code changes should
be done on the fly while the system is running without interruptions, without bringing systems
down, bringing systems up.
But just keep things running on and changing the code under the hood.
It also needed to be concurrent because it needed to handle a lot of incoming telephone
calls at the same time.
And it also needs to be distributed because you have to connect telephone switches together
and make sure that everything runs smoothly.
So those are kind of the properties that Erlang also inherited, oh I'm sorry, Alexur inherited
from Erlang as well.
So when you look at other systems, multi-threaded, okay, programming can be hard.
So in theory it should all work like we have, you know, if you want to do something concurrently
we spawn a few threads and they do their work.
But in practice, because threads can actually interfere with each other's work, it actually
becomes a mess.
So hence the second picture.
The other property that Erlang has is full torrents.
So in Erlang you set up a supervision tree in which a supervisor is actually watching
monitoring a worker and if one of those processes dies, then the supervisor actually makes sure
that a new process is spawned in its place and the system as a whole keeps running even
though one of the parts actually fail.
That's also the mantra that's very often told in Erlang is let it crash.
Nice timing, okay.
Because people feel safe by, you know, if there's an exception, if your code always
goes for the happy path and something goes wrong, Erlang developers tend to not care
that much about it because the system, like the supervisor will restart that process again.
So very exceptional edge cases are sometimes not covered because they feel comfortable
having the system pick it up from there as well.
Before Erlang also existed for quite a while, so Alex also inherited some of the experience
of 20 years building telecom systems which also makes it, for example, WhatsApp had only
57 engineers working for them when they sold to Facebook, but only about 20 of them were
Erlang developers.
The rest were actually mobile developers supporting Androids, Windows, iOS, et cetera, and actually
could handle a lot of users while having a small team.
So then the question also comes a little bit why does Alex exist?
And when people innovate and build new things, there are approximately three ways they can
go around it.
So they completely build something very new which didn't exist before, or they try to
combine ideas from other fields, for example.
Or in some cases people just put a new label on it and say, well, this is new, this is
innovation.
So that hence the title of my talk, is Alex really something new or is it just a new label
on the existing Erlang foundation?
And some other languages, they try to incrementally do some innovations, but after a while the
original sources picked up those changes.
Like CoffeeScript is a very famous example in which the original language picked up those
changes and nowadays a lot less people actually use CoffeeScript.
So how are we doing on time?
So the question is then also why did Jose is kind of the creator of Alektra, why did
he write a new language?
And he was at a time when he wrote Alektra, he was working at Rails team, and one of the
things that he faced was trying to make Rails thread safe.
So making sure that several threads that were running in the Rails program weren't interfering
with each other.
And by doing that he was actually looking around how did other, like folks, how did
other programming languages, other frameworks, how did they solve that issue?
And that's when he actually stumbled upon Erlang and he liked it.
It was just the thing he needed to use.
But there were also some things that he was actually missing.
So for starters, the syntax stems from prologue.
So it's unfamiliar for a lot of people.
So that means that new people who come to Erlang have to have a high barrier to actually
get around because they feel unfamiliar with the syntax.
So he did that first.
And he also introduced other new syntax, for example, the pipe operator in which, like the
result of the previous expression, is piped into the next function as a first parameter.
So by doing that you can avoid having a very nested function calls by having something
that's more readable, more clear to other people.
He also introduced more extensibility to the language by introducing macros and protocols.
And one of my favorites is actually the bottom one.
I'm not sure if everybody can read it, but it's an upcase function which takes a string
and upcases every letter.
And it does that under the hood via a macro.
So the Unicode definition, like the library definitions of characters is downloaded and
actually been translated to functions under the hood.
So when you call this, you're actually using some data that is transformed into functions
for that language.
I'll skip over this part because we don't have that much time.
And you also actually see that those macros are used everywhere.
So even like defining module is a macro, defining a function, et cetera, everything is actually
implemented through macros.
The other thing that he also introduced is a build-to to make it easier for people who
are, for example, new to the language.
If you want to have a package manager, like before, didn't really have package management,
like in the sense that you could add packages to your project, but you had to download them
by yourself, put them somewhere, define it in your config, like, okay, this is the path
to my library that I'm using.
And with Hex and with Mix, just say I made it easier by having a list of dependencies
and go download it from a central place.
Documentation was also made more prominent.
For example, the doc tests which are inspired by Python.
So in this case, we have a function defined and above it is a document, a comment in which
there's an example.
And this example doesn't serve only for documentation, but in the same time, it's also a test.
So, you know, actually, you can, if you would change the implementation, you can directly
see the effect of it because the test is just above it as documentation fails.
So, and, yeah, the documentation is also accessible from REPL from other places.
And this was built before the LSP.
So nowadays you can just hover over a function in your editor and you will see the documentation.
But when Alexa was created, those functionalities weren't that common, like among other languages.
And that's something that's really nice to work with.
And the last thing that he kind of also introduced is a different culture.
Culture which is a little bit more open to newcomers.
So it's not like Erlang shed away from newcomers, but it also didn't, like, make it easier for
new people who are new to the language to get started with it, et cetera.
So that whole, you know, like, to come back to my question, like, is Alexa a kind of new
flavor on top of Erlang?
I think there are kind of projects stemming from Alexa which make it more interesting
and which are really new.
So, for example, Nx numerical, Alexa is an extension which makes machine learning easy.
And that's something that, you know, before Alexa nobody actually thought would be useful
to do with the beam, with the Erlang VM.
Because it wasn't meant for that.
It wasn't meant for number crunching.
But this library, this tooling actually makes it a lot easier to do.
And that's very promising.
Nx is actually a web framework which was inspired by Rails.
And now, so you worry around, it's now an inspiration for Rails and other frameworks
to work with.
And Nx is also kind of an interesting project which makes it possible to run on smaller
devices like Raspberry Pis or something like this.
So to answer the question, is Alexa really different from Erlang?
Is it really, you know, an innovation or is it really hashing?
I would say no.
I think Alexa really adds something to the whole ecosystem which, yeah, wasn't that easy
before that.
So with that being said, thanks for listening.
Thank you.
Unfortunately, we don't have any time for Q&A, but you can find it.
Yes.
So if you're looking for me online, I usually have the handle toxified.
So on Twitter, if it still works or mastered on you, you can also find me.
And I'll be around, I think, for today if you have any further questions.
Thanks again for listening.
And apologies for being this late.
Thank you again.
And with that, stand by for the audience.
I'm