Hello, everyone. Do you hear me well? So thanks. Pretty large audience. If I may ask a quick
show of hands, who among you have some experience, just any level of experience with machine
learning? Okay, cool. Awesome. So I'll be talking today about how to run testing on machine
learning systems. So there are different keywords, CICD, quality assurance. A few words about
us. So I'm one of the founders of GeeseGuard. We are building a collaborative and open source
software platform to precisely ensure the quality of AI models. And I'll be explaining
in this presentation a bit how it works. In terms of agenda, I prepared two sections on
the why. Why a project on testing machine learning systems is needed. Why I personally
decided to work on that problem. Some of the risks and why classical software testing methods
don't quite work on AI. And then I'll do some more concrete examples on two important quality
criteria that you might want to test for machine learning. One is robustness and the other
is fairness. And if we have the time, it's just 30 minutes, I hope that we can do a quick
demo of an example use case where we run the full CICD pipeline on a machine learning model.
So to kind of start off easy, I put together a series of memes to explain my personal story
of why I came to create a company and a project around this machine learning testing thing.
So about ten years ago, I started in machine learning, statistics, data science. And you
know, you had this, you start using the Scikit-learn API and you're like, yeah, it's super easy,
right? Anybody can be a data scientist, you just dot fit, dot predict, and that's it.
You're a data scientist. And probably if you're here today, you're like, yeah, have you tested
your model? Yeah, sure. Train test, split. Reality, if you've deployed in production,
it's quite different. So if you've deployed to production, often you'll have this painful
discovery where you have your product manager, business stakeholders to whom you said, look,
I worked really hard on the fine tuning and the grid search to get to 85% accuracy and
you push your first version to production and things don't quite work out. You don't
reproduce these good accuracy numbers. So, well, this was me. I hope it's not you. It
was one of these, my first experience deploying machine learning for production was on a fraud
detection system. Frauds are notoriously difficult as a use case for machine learning because
what you're trying to detect doesn't quite want to be detected. There are people behind
it who have a vested interest not to have your machine learning system detect them.
So often in terms of performance, that's at least what I ended up doing a lot of hot fixes
in production. It's bad. So kind of like five years ago, this was my stance on machine learning
in production. A very painful grueling experience where you just never know when you're going
to be a complaint, where you're going to be on call to solve something in production.
So that's when I decided to buff up and switch roles to join a software engineering team.
I was at DataEcoo back then, so I moved internally from data science to the product team. And
here are some of the things to summarize that as someone with a machine learning background
but no real software engineering experience that these were kind of like what I was told.
You must learn the ways of the CI CD. Otherwise your project will not come to production.
And for context, so I was specifically at that time in charge of creating like an open
source layer to federate all the NLP and computer vision APIs that vendors in the cloud provide.
And then to do the same for pre-trained NLP and time series models. So what was difficult
in this context is I was not even the one in charge of the models. And the models will
be retrained fine-tuned. So the guarantees into the properties of that systems as an
engineer, that's more difficult. There are some elements in the stack that you don't
have control of. So yeah, this is a bit of a repeat of a previous
meme and I really wanted to say one does not simply ship an ML product with our tests.
The challenge I had then is that from an engineering management standpoint, I was told, yeah, but
you know, it's easy. No engineers, they all write their test cases. So you do machine
learning, just write them all. Just write all the test cases.
So this was me being kind of square one. It's like, okay, so you're telling me I just need
to write unit tests? Okay. That will not really solve the issue. And that's kind of the beginning
of a quest that set me on to build something to solve that gap between, okay, I want to
test my models, I need to test my models, and how can I do that? Because clearly, and
I'll explain why, unit testing your model is really not enough.
So a different angle on the why. I'll try to take a step back and talk about quality
in general. I think in this track, we all agree that quality matters. And if you look
at AI, it's an industry that's an engineering practice that is far younger than software
engineering or civil engineering. And it's just riddled with incidents. I encourage you
if you don't know that resource already, it's an open source database. It's incidentdatabase.ai.
And it's a public collection of reports, mostly in the media, of AI models that have not worked
properly. And it's a really great work that has been going on for about two years and
a half. It's a global initiative. And just in this time, they collected more than 2,000
incidents. Since these are public reports, think of it as the tip of the iceberg, of
course. There are a lot of incidents internal to companies that are not necessarily spoken
out in the media. The incidentdatabase has a very interesting taxonomy of the different
types of incidents. It's very multifaceted. I took the liberty to simplify it in three
big categories of incidents. One is FX. The other is business, economic impacts. And the
third one is on security. And we are talking about really if they happen at a global company
scale, incidents that are very, very severe. In FX, you can have a sexist credit scoring
algorithm that exposes the company to lawsuits, to brand image damages, et cetera. And these
are notoriously hard to identify. Because, I mean, in a way, machine learning is precisely
about discrimination. So it's hard to tell a machine that is learning to discriminate,
not to discriminate against certain sensitive groups. I'll speak on some methods that can
be used precisely on this problem. Apple was working with, at the time, Goldman Sachs on
deploying this algorithm. And probably some tests and safeguards were unfortunately skipped.
So it was actually discovered on Twitter that, in a simple case, a male loan applicant would
get 10x their loan limit compared to it was his wife. That sparked a huge controversy.
That probably exposed Apple to some lawsuits. In another area that is not with sensitive
features such as gender, there was a huge catastrophe a year and a half ago that happened
to Zillow, a real estate company, where there was a small bias that was overestimating the
prices of homes. And they decided to put this algorithm live to buy and sell houses. In
turn out that this tiny bias, which was left unchecked, was exploited by the real estate
agents in the US. And literally, this created a loss of nearly a half a billion dollars.
And again, probably going back to testing, this could have been anticipated and avoided.
Now on a more cyber security spectrum, there's a lot of good research from cyber security
labs showing that you can hack, for example, a computer vision system in an autonomous
driving context. So here you put a special tape on the road and you can crash a tester.
We don't quite know if these types of vulnerabilities have been exploited in real life yet. But
as AI becomes super ubiquitous, and obviously there are some bad actors out there that might
want to hack the systems and introduces a new type of attack vectors. So that's also
something we need to care about. So both from practitioners of AI and from a regulatory
standpoint, testing just makes sense. Yann LeCun, chief AI scientist at Metar, was actually
taking a stance at the beginning of last year on Twitter saying that if you want trust in
the system, you need tests. And also making a slight criticism towards some of the explainability
methods. Because two years ago, if you've followed that realm, people were saying, oh,
you just need explainability and then your problems will go away. Well, that's just part
of the answer. Lastly, and this was covered in some of the talks this morning on the big
auditorium, there's a growing regulatory requirements to put some checks and balances
in place. And that also says that you need specifically in case your AI system is high
risk, you need to put quality measures in place. And the definition of high risk AI
systems is pretty large. Obviously, you have anything related to infrastructure like critical
infrastructure, defense, et cetera. But you also have all AI systems that are involved
in human resources and public service and financial services because these are considered
obviously critical components of society. Right. But now that we kind of agreed that
it's an important problem, these are some of the challenges because if you've encountered
some of this issue, you probably looked at some easy solutions, right? Taking some analogies
on what you might do to do this. And there are three points that make this problem of
testing machine learning a bit special, meaning it's still a big work in progress. Point one
is that it is really not enough to check the data quality to guarantee the quality of a
machine learning system. One of my co-founders doing his PhD proved it's a mountain. You
can run experiments that you can have really clean data in a bad model. Right. So you cannot
just say it's an upstream problem. It's technically like systems engineering. You have to take
the data, the machine learning model and the user into context to analyze its properties.
Moreover, the errors of a machine learning systems are often caused by pieces of data
that did not exist when the model was created. They were clean, but they did not exist. Second
point, it's pretty hard just to copy paste some of the testing methods from software
into AI. One is like, yes, you can do some unit tests on machine learning models, but
they won't prove much. Because the principle is that it's a transactional systems and things
are moving quite a lot. So that's a good baseline. If you have a machine learning system and
you have some unit tests, that's really like step one. It's better to have that than to
have nothing. But you have to embrace the fact that there has got to be a large number
of test cases. So you cannot just test on a free 500, even a thousand cases will not
be enough. The models themselves are probabilistic. So you have to take into account statistical
methods of tests. And lastly, and I think this is specific to, because there has been
some systems that were heavily dependent on data, but with AI, AI also came with a fact
that you increase the number of data inputs compared to traditional systems. So you very
quickly come into issues of combinatorial problem and it's factually impossible to generate
all the combinations. Very simple example of that. How can you test an NLP system? Lastly,
AI touching a lot of different points. If you want to have a complete test coverage,
you really need to take into account multiple criteria. So performance of a system, but
also robustness, robustness to errors. Fairness, privacy, security, reliability. And also,
and that's becoming an increasingly important topic with green AI, it's like what is the
carbon impact of this AI? Do you really need that many GPUs? Can you make your system a
bit more energy efficient? So today I'll focus on the, because I see we have 10 more minutes,
I'll focus on two aspects, the robustness and the ethics. So I'll start with robustness.
Who has read or heard about this paper? Quick show of hands. Okay. Ah, one. So who has heard
of behavioral testing? Because that's not machine learning specific. Yeah, cool. So
Ribero three years ago, along with other co-writers of this paper, did I think a fantastic job
to see how to adapt behavioral testing, which is a really good practice from software engineering,
to the context of machine learning and specifically wrote something for NLP models. The main problem
that this research paper aim to solve was test case generation. Because really NLP is
by a sense a problem, NLP, a natural language processing, so you have an input text, right?
It just wrote text, right? So you cannot, you need test this, really. But what you can
do is to generate test cases that rely on mapping the input and the input changes in
the text to expectations. I'll give three examples from very, very simple to a bit more
complex. One is like the principle of minimum functionality. For example, if you are building
a sentiment prediction machine learning system, you could just have a test that says if you
have extra ordinary in the sentence, you should always predict that the model will say it's
a positive message. Now you will probably tell me, yeah, but what about if the user
has written it's not extraordinary or absolutely not extraordinary? And that actually brings
me to the concept of test template. And the fact that probably for NLP, what you need
to do, and this is obviously language specific, is start to have templates where you change
the text by, for example, adding negations. And then, so you might want to test if your
system, if you're adding negation, if you have a certain direction, because normally,
if a machine learning model has understood, it should, if it's about sentiment, understand
that putting not an extraordinary or not good, you have then synonyms, will not affect the
system too much. Or actually, either your system, you want it to move to a certain direction,
or there are cases where you want actually the opposite behavior. You want robustness.
So that's called invariance. So for instance, you will want a system that is robust to typos,
to just changing a location name, just putting synonyms, et cetera, et cetera.
So we've created this diagram to explain it, and it's a really thriving field in the research.
There is a lot of research going on these days about testing machine learning systems,
and metamorphic testing is one of the leading methods to do that.
The principle is, if I take an analogy, is very similar to if you've worked in finance
or if you have some friends who work there, the principle of backtesting, an investment
strategy. You simulate different changes in the market conditions, and you see how your
strategy, your algorithm behaves, and what is the variance of that strategy.
This concept applies very well to machine learning. So you need two things. You need
one to define a perturbation. So what I was explaining earlier in NLP, perturbation might
be adding typos, adding negation. In another context, like let's say it's more in an industrial
case, it might be about doubling the values of some sensors or adding noise to an image.
And then, pretty simply, you define an expectation, a test expectation, in terms of the metamorphic
relation between the output of a machine learning model and the distribution of the output after
perturbation. And once you have that, and if you have enough data, then you can actually
have a, like you can do actual statistical tests, see there's a difference in distribution,
et cetera. So I won't have too much time to dive into
all the details of this, but we have wrote a technical guide on this topic, and you have
a link in QR code up there. Next, I'll talk a bit about a really tricky
topic, which is AI fairness. And I want to emphasize that it's, at least our recommendation
is not to come at the problem of AI ethics with a closed mind or a top-down definition
of this is an ethical system, or no, this is an unethical system. My co-founder did
his PhD on precisely on this topic and wrote a full paper on this, looking at the philosophical
and sociological implications of this. And the gist of it is that, yes, to a certain
extent you can adopt a top-down approach to AI fairness, saying, well, for instance, as
an organization, we want to test the fairness on explicitly free sensitive categories. You
can say, well, we want to check for gender balance, we want to check for race balance.
That means if the country where you deploy a machine learning allows to collect this
data, this is not always the case. But the challenge with these approaches is that, A,
you might not have the data to measure this, and B, you may miss out, because often when
this exercise of defining the quality criteria for fairness and for balance are done, you
only have a limited sample. So it's, and taking some sociological analogies, it's really important
to have this kind of top-down definition of AI ethics, meet the reality on the ground,
and confront the actual users and the makers of the systems to get them to define the definition
of ethics, rather than a big organization, if I put a bit of a caricature that says,
AI ethics, yeah, we wrote a charter about this, you follow, you read this, you sign,
and then, oops, you're ethical. Having said that, so there are some good top-down metrics
to adopt that are kind of a baseline, and I'll explain one of them, which is disparate
impact. Disparate impact is actually a metric from the human resources management industry
from at least 40 years ago, so it's not new, that says, so it's probabilities, but essentially
it's about setting a rule of 80%, where you measure the probability of, you define a positive
outcome with respect to a given protected population, and you say, well, I want to the
proportions of a probability of a positive outcome relative to a probability of a positive
outcome in the unprotected context to be above 80%. So, for instance, so if you want to apply
that to a, oops, to put more concrete, yeah, so if, say, you are building a model to predict
the churn of customers, and you want to check whether your model is biased or not for each
class, this formula allows you to really define this metric and write a concrete test case.
Right, so I just have three minutes, so I'll highlight what one of the features of our
project enables is putting human feedback, so really having an interface where users
and not only data scientists can change the parameters, so there's a link to metamorphic
testing and actually give human feedback to a point out where the biases may be, and the
benefit of this approach is that it allows for the community to precisely define what
they think are the risks. So, sadly, we won't have time to do a demo, but this phase, in
our project, we call that the inspection phase, and it's about before you test, and this is
super important, and again, one of the things where it's different from traditional software
testing, before you even test, you need to confront yourself with the data and the model,
so that's where actually we think explainability methods really shine, because they allow to
debug and to identify the zones of risks, and this is precisely what helps once you
have qualified feedback to know where you should put your effort in test.
So, in a nutshell, what I'm saying for testing machine learning systems is it's not a matter
of creating hundreds of tests, of automating everything, but rather to have a good idea
of from a fairness standpoint and for performance standpoint of what are the 10, 15, maybe max
20 tests that you want in your platform. If you want to get started actually on it, this
is up our GitHub, and yeah, if you have a machine learning system to test, we're interested
in your feedback.