Thank you for coming to my talk.
It's not a TED talk, but it's just my talk.
Continuous delivery to many coronavirus clusters.
My name is Carlos Sanchez, and I'm here to talk to you about our life experience, real
world.
I'm not here to solve you anything.
I'll try to tell you if I have time for some of the mistakes we made, she's not all beautiful
and wonderful.
I'm a principal scientist at Adobe Experience Manager Cloud Service.
I'll talk a little bit about the product.
On the open source side, I started the Jenkins Kubernetes plugin.
Anybody heard about Jenkins?
Yes, some people probably.
I'm a Kubernetes.
Anybody heard about Kubernetes?
Anybody using Kubernetes in production?
I'm a long time contributor to open source, multiple projects on Jenkins, Apache Foundation,
and all that.
A quick intro to what Adobe Experience Manager is, because every time I say Adobe, people
say Photoshop and PDF and Flash.
That's not any of those.
This is a content management system that you probably never heard of, but it's powering
80% of the 4100, and it's very enterprise-y, so I'm not expecting people in front of them
to know.
This is widely used because it's based in a lot of open source.
It's a distributed OSDI application that was started many years ago, and uses a lot of
components of open source from the Apache Foundation, and we contribute back to those
components like Felix, Apache Felix, Sling, and a few things about content management
there.
It has a huge market of extension developers, people that are writing their own Java code
and then runs on Adobe Experience Manager in AM.
When I'm doing Adobe, the goal was let's move this into a cloud service, and this is running
AM on Kubernetes.
We're running currently on Azure, and we have 35 clusters and growing very quickly.
Because this is a content management, we run it in multiple regions.
Right now, 11, so multiple ones in the US, Europe, Australia, Singapore, Japan, whatever,
because people want to have low latency between their users and the content.
Then, another interesting fight is that we have on the Kubernetes clusters, we don't
run them directly, we build stuff on top of them, and we have a different team at Adobe
that manages Kubernetes for us.
Some curiosity is that customers can run their own code, so we are running this for them,
and we take their code and run it inside our processes.
We have to limit clusters' permissions for security, and we have several security concerns,
because this is a very multi-tenant setup.
Each customer can have multiple environments, multiple copies, and they can self-service,
so they can deploy new environments whenever they want, they can update them and do a few
things, so it's not just us controlling what is running, it's also the customers.
Each customer can have three or more Kubernetes namespaces where these environments run, and
I like to call this a micromanolith, so we don't run a big service that expands like
thousands of instances, we run slightly different versions of the same service over a thousand,
ten thousand times.
Micromanolith defines it very well, and then we use namespace, Kubernetes namespaces, to
provide the scope of network isolation, quotas, permissions, and so on.
Now internally, we have multiple teams building services, so different services have different
requirements, people can use different languages, and we are more in a philosophy of you build
it, you run it, and we are basically doing each service as an API, or we follow the Kubernetes
operator patterns.
We also use, to split the monolith, we use a lot of init containers and sidecars, if
you know in Kubernetes, you can run multiple containers at the same time, so the main application
runs in one container, and then we have to apply division of concern, many sidecars that
do different things, and it's an easy way to split separate concerns without having
to rewrite your whole architecture to go to a fully network-based maker service oriented
architecture.
On the continuous delivery side, which is probably what you are interested in here,
we are running, we are moving from a generally released to, I mean we are pushing changes
daily multiple times, not only, not just the application, that the application is maybe
slower to move, but on the operational side, and all the services, and operators, all these
things, all of them together, any of them at any point in time, any day can receive
changes.
So we use Jenkins for CI CD in some places, we have Tekton, you heard about that in one
of the talks before, it's another open source project to do workflows on Kubernetes to
orchestrate some pipelines, and we also started using Argo CD for some new micro services.
We follow a GitOps process, so where most of the configuration is a storing Git, and
it's reconciling each commit, right?
And we use a pull versus push model to scale, and I'll go through this in a bit.
We have a combination of multiple things being deployed to the clusters, we have the AM
version that is deployed with a Helm chart, we have operation services that are operators
and services and all the other things that are not the application, these are deployed
using Kubernetes files but templatized, and we are also using customized Argo CD for some
new micro services.
On the Helm side, we use the Helm operator, so in each namespace we use the Helm operator
CRDs to do a more state-based installation of Helm.
So we create the CRD and the Helm operator is going to install the application based
on the parameters on the CRD.
A word of advice is don't mix application and infrastructural configuration on the same
package because if you cannot enforce the same Helm chart for all tenants, for example,
as I said mentioned before, customers can decide when to update things, right?
So we have some customers in older releases and some ones in newer releases, this is something
that we want to change, but in the meantime, if we want to update a specific version of
something in an old release, it's hard when this is already packaged on Helm.
So we built a solution for this.
So from the platform level, we can go and manipulate this Helm chart.
So we can have overrides and this is easy to do when you have the Helm operator.
So you can inject, whenever there's a request to install a new Helm chart, we change parameters.
So we change both Helm values, this is easy, instead of passing some values, we pass different
ones.
Or you can use customized patches and this is also support from the Helm operator, this
is also support for customized patches.
And customized patches are very interesting because they allow you to patch any Kubernetes
resource so even if there was no previous Helm value defined for it.
So if we want to change a sidecar container image version across the Helm fleet, we just
have to change the patch.
And this patch is going to be applied to all the clusters, all the namespaces, and all
the Helm charts that were installed are going to get reinstalled with the right version
that we want.
So we do this combination of both Helm chart and then operational values on the other hand.
Very important for us was the shift left mentality, right?
Detecting problems as soon as possible, not waiting for developers to push things to production
because the cost increases.
So we run checks as soon as we can on pull requests so it is still fresh in your memory
when you make a change and something is broken, you want to catch it as soon as possible.
And we do this by generating all these templates, we have some tests that generate these templates
and then apply tests, multiple tests on them.
The most basic check that you can run is the apply kubectl apply drive run.
This will tell you if the manifest is wrong in some very obvious way.
So if it's valid or it's not valid.
KubeConform is a tool that will allow you to validate the Kubernetes schemas.
So this is the successor of kubefall.
Anybody heard about kubefall or kubefirm?
Yeah?
So this is very useful for if you have custom CRDs or yeah, just to make sure typical problems,
you miss the JAML indentation and now it's not valid anymore and then you catch this
on a PR to just run this and it will tell you this property is missing or this property
is in the wrong place because everybody loves JAML, right?
Most tests is another tool for open policy agents.
Any people familiar with open policy agents?
Open policy?
OPA, yeah.
So OPA allows you to write policies where you can go and pretty much check anything in any
structure file.
In the case of Kubernetes, you could say, I don't know, don't run the pod as root, make
sure you don't mount secrets as environment variables or with files, make sure and force
that all the pods have some labels, any random thing that you can think of, you can do it.
And like don't pull from Docker Hub, pull from the internal registry, you can do that
with contest and OPA policies.
The only problem is that uses the regular language that if you haven't heard of is very
painful to work with, but it works great once you try to figure out.
We added another tool which is called Pluto.
Pluto is just a CLI that will tell you what API versions have been deprecated or removed.
So if you are thinking about upgrading Kubernetes, you run Pluto and it will tell you, you know,
this is deprecated, it's going to be removed in this version and so on.
So you can enforce that.
We built a tool that we call Git init, which is our own version of a GitHub spool.
So we have the Kubernetes definitions store in Git and we deploy these to blob stores
across regions.
So they are pulled in each cluster.
And Git init is a deployment that runs continuously on each namespace.
We have around 10,000 namespaces in our fleet.
So it basically pulls the blob, applies the changes and does this thing every so often.
And an example of why we do pull versus pull, because pushing to all the clusters, we have
a job that does this and it runs in parallel, like in 20 threads or something, and still
takes like five hours to run.
So we cannot push things when we want.
On Argo CD, we have a new CAS platform that allows you to do Argo CD based microservices.
Argo CD basically this would create a new Git repo, it would come with some templates
and that would get deployed with Argo CD to the cluster.
And this is for us, we're thinking about moving this way and each team will have their own
Git repo, because right now we have mostly centralized operators and everything.
And this is good for the, okay, you go on your own direction, you do whatever you want,
you build it, you run it.
On the other hand, this will be tricky because when we decide or figure out something is
problematic, we cannot just centrally say, you know, and this Git repo tell me who is
doing this and let's change it.
But we're moving towards that direction.
Let me skip this and talk a bit about progressive delivery.
So progressive delivery is a way, well, it's something that is a name for something that
you probably heard of, which is Canary rollouts and doing percentage based rollouts, feature
flags, blue ring.
So basically don't update everybody at the same time, because you can break everybody.
So we can do rollouts to different customer groups in separate waves and we can also do
rollouts to percentage of customers.
By default we have a time based rollout that goes from dev to stage to prod candidate after
a period of time.
And this is running on Jenkins and ensures that things have been running on dev and stage
before we merge them to prod.
I mean, this is very basic.
What we built was feature flags at the namespace level.
We have 10,000 namespaces and the in the Kubernetes definition templates.
So what we allow developers to do is for each namespace, they can decide I want to roll
out this change to this environment, dev, stage or prod, or I want to deploy this change
to a specific cluster or by template namespace type of namespace or a percentage.
And this is just using templates on Kubernetes objects.
So an example is in this case, a Kubernetes definition where you can have a template that
is says full version or bar version, or you can enable a site card container or disable
it.
And then at the bottom you can see the rules.
So by default we want full version to be 1.0.
But for the namespace, all the namespaces on the dev environment, we want that to be
1.1.
So this allows us to quickly roll out changes, but progressively.
We can also do it for percentile.
So in this case we could say, I want all the namespaces in dev and all the namespaces in
a stage to have this full version 1.1 and enable my rule true, but for prod I only want
5%.
I roll out the change to 5% of prod and then I can continue after that.
So this has proven really useful for developers to test things safely, increase development
speed, PRs are much faster, so it's all great.
And we are thinking about, well, we are thinking, we are working on getting our good rollouts,
but at the deployment level, article rollouts allows you to do blue, green and canary rollouts
where you can say progress the number of pods over a period of time.
So instead of changing, I don't know, 10 pods at the same time, it goes one by one.
And if you have a service mesh, you can go even more fine grained and say, I want 5%
of the traffic to go to the old version, to the new version, everything else to the old
version and keep progressing that and do automatic rollbacks.
So yeah, with the service mesh you can fine tune the traffic percentages, but with Kubernetes
services you can still do it, it's just that we are limited with the number of pods.
So to sum up, shift left on guard rails, so keeping people safe on what they are doing,
this increases development speed, it reduces the issues that you are going to have in production,
and you're never going to prevent having issues in production, what you can prevent is how
many customers are affected and how fast you can fix them, right?
So for us, what was very useful is the process delivery techniques like canaries, percent
of rollouts or automated rollbacks, and the automation to do these control and progressive
rollout pays off over time.
So I think we have one minute for questions.
Or you can find me afterwards.
Thank you.