Okay, hey everyone, I'm here today to talk about delivering a cross-plane based platform.
A few words about myself, my name is Max-Manian Blatt, I'm a Kubernetes and cross-plane developer
and consultant at Accenture in Germany.
I'm using or working with cross-plane for almost two years, or yeah, it's two years
now, and I'm the maintainer of several cross-plane related open source projects, including the
provider for AWS, the provider Staira, provider AgroCD, and I've contributed to many more,
including cross-plane itself.
Now since this is the CICD Devroom, I don't know if everyone is familiar with cross-plane,
so I just want to spend a minute or two explaining what it is.
So cross-plane essentially is an extension to the Kubernetes API and it allows you to
create cloud resources the way you would create resources in Kubernetes.
So the thing on the left is something most of you probably have seen once or twice, which
is a Kubernetes pod and it's a very common resource that you have in Kubernetes and it
basically just schedules and contain a way you can run an application.
And on the right you see a bucket as you would create it with cross-plane and it represents
an actual bucket on AWS S3.
And if you look at both of these objects, then you see that they are very, very similar
because they are both inside the Kubernetes cluster and you have both very common or the
same kind of structure.
You have your API version and your kind.
You have the metadata that comes with every cross-plane, with every Kubernetes object.
You have a declarative spec, so where you describe the state of the resources, the resource
that you want, and then you have the status information about the resource itself.
And that is one of the features that cross-plane does for you, so it connects external APIs,
any kind of external APIs with Kubernetes and lets you manage your whole cloud infrastructure
through one Kubernetes cluster.
And the second very powerful feature of cross-plane is that it allows you to create your custom
Kubernetes APIs by using something that is called compositions.
And then is the thing that you can see in the middle.
It's a very rough and simplified graph to show the way cross-plane works and it essentially
is always works that you have a user claim for a resource for your API that you have
to find using a so-called XID or a composite resource definition.
And that is then passed to a composition and then the composition spawns a number of managed
resources.
And those resources are something that you have seen in the slide before, which is a
bucket or any other kind of external resource, any other kind of external API.
Today I want to talk mostly about XID's and compositions, because that is what you do
most of the time when you are working with cross-plane.
Now developing a platform with cross-plane.
If you look at simple CI-CD pipeline, then you have usually build, test and then deploy.
And that is very easy and for most software projects that is also very easy to understand.
But because cross-plane is a bit different, you have different things that you do inside
these steps.
So what you do with cross-plane is you are first building and pushing a package and you
are not writing code, but you are just writing YAML objects which are then applied on the
cluster and then they are handled and treated like data by cross-plane.
And then when you are testing your cross-plane platform, then you are applying all your compositions
and your XID's to a test cluster and then you are claiming them and then you see if
they work.
And then if that is okay, then you are deploying them and you are just doing the same but on
a production cluster.
I don't want to talk about the deployment today, because that is very simple.
That is basically just like doing a Kubernetes deployment.
You are building an OCI image and then pushing that and then you are installing that on a
cluster using cross-plane and that is it.
There is not much to tell about, but I want to talk about the building and the testing.
Let's start with the building.
If you have worked with cross-plane before, then that is probably very familiar for you.
On the left you see an XID as you would write it and on the right you see a composition.
So an XID, I said it, basically just defines the API that your user has applied to and
it is very similar to custom resource definitions that you are writing in plain Kubernetes.
So you have your API schema in the spec of your XID and then in the composition, what
you do is you define the resource that should be created when the user claims this API.
That can be an arbitrary number of resources.
You don't have to create just one resource, but you can create dozens of them.
I have written compositions where you are creating 30 or more resources at once.
That is essentially how it is done.
You are specifying a base resource and then you can modify this resource by copying information
from the user claim into the resource that you want to create.
That is what you do the whole time.
You are working with cross-plane.
You are writing an XID and then you are writing a composition or multiple compositions and
then the user can claim it and then choose the composition that he wants.
That now looks easy at first, but when you are doing this on an enterprise level, then
you are very easily you end up with compositions that can be thousands of lines of code where
you are creating dozens of objects.
Because you are just dealing with pure YAML, then you really are starting to get at a limit
because you have a lot of things that are very repetitive inside compositions.
You have very similar structures.
Let's say if you are spawning a lot of similar objects on your cluster, but in different
compositions, then sometimes you have the same patches that you are reusing.
For example, if you just want to patch the name of a resource by what the user has given
to you, then you are repeating this patch over and over for every resource, for every
file you are writing.
Sometimes you then have compositions who only vary in details.
If you have different environments, for example, you are in different AWS accounts and you
only want resources to appear in specific accounts or you have different values like
the region or static resources that you want to connect like the account ID.
Then you have to write the same composition over and over, but just with different values.
Then you see that you are ending up with something that gets really, really complicated because
you are just doing a lot of copy and paste.
You need something to generate the YAML dynamically.
In these two years, I spent a lot of thoughts on how to simplify this process and I have
experimented with a bunch of stuff.
We have tried out Q, which is some form of JSON-like framework that allows you to build
structures and have them validated.
But it is very complex and not very easy for newcomers.
If you have new developers and teams, it is a bit hard to onboard them on it because the
error messages are not very helpful in many cases.
The tool that we ended up establishing was Helm.
I am not the biggest fan of Helm because it is a bit quirky to use.
Sometimes if you have error messages or if you have errors, it is sometimes hard to detect
where the error actually is because it just tells you there is something wrong with your
YAML but you do not know where it exactly happened.
The good thing with Helm is that it can do everything that we need.
You can replace common code blocks such as constants with things that you have written
out in your values, YAML.
You can use templates to parameterize patches to save lines of code.
You can even replace the API schemas of XRDS by something that you can generate.
That is a really, really cool thing.
I just checked the code in our repository and we have about 100 lines of code for Helm.
I am sorry, 10,000 lines of code for Helm and we are generating 200,000 lines of code
of compositions that are then applied on our API clusters.
If you are doing this, if you are generating code for cross plane with Helm or any other
kind of code generation tool, then I recommend you to check these generated YAML bits into
your Git because as it turned out, it is very hard to detect unintended changes that you
are doing in Helm with your bare eyes.
If you are changing one value or a template somewhere, then it might have some side effects
that you are not seeing so easily.
I really recommend you to check these generated YAML codes into your Git and do not treat
it as artifacts.
If you are in your CI, then what we are doing and that is really helpful is that you should
regenerate all your package and your generated YAML and see if any diff appears.
If that is the case, then you should just treat this as an error and abort and if there
is no diff, then it is okay and you can continue on and push your package to the OCI repository.
So much for the building.
Now let's look at the testing.
The first things that you are doing probably when you are starting working with cross-plane
is that you are writing your composition and then you are applying it on a cluster and
then you are claiming it and then you see if it works, if all the resources get ready
and if you can use them and then it's done.
That is all manual.
That is very easy to do because it requires no additional setup and you can just use the
cluster that you have.
But when you really want to do automatic testing or enterprise level testing, then that is
not enough and because you have manual steps, you have an outcome that is not reproducible
because you are doing the things all by yourself, then also you don't have to find what is actually
the expected outcome because sometimes even if a resource gets healthy, it doesn't mean
that the resource is configured the way you want it.
So we also tried and tested a few things and we started with Go testing but it turned out
to be much more complicated because you have to write a lot of boilerplate code stuff and
so we ended up using Kettle.
I don't know if some people know it.
It's basically a Kubernetes testing toolkit that allows you to define all your test cases
in YAML and then just let Kettle do all the work, all the application of the YAML on the
server and then you can define the resources that you expect afterwards and if you imagine
the graph that I showed you before where you have the composition and then you claim it
and then you have a number of managed resources that are then spawned and so you can have
the claim as an input and then you can justify the resources that you want to have created
as an output and then you can handle let Kettle handle all the rest for you.
And then it can do things in parallel and such and this is a really, really great thing.
So I recommend Kettle.
Just to show you an example how these tests look like, so you have your small bucket claim
if we are sticking to this simple bucket example then you have your bucket claim on the left
which is your test case and then on the right you are defining all the objects that you
want.
You have the bucket claim itself which has a resource status that should become ready
and then you have composite resource which is an internal resource that gets created
by cross-plane where it stores some reconciling information which should also become ready
and then you have your actual bucket managed resource which also has properties that you
are expecting it to have and it also has a status.
And so that is all you need to do testing with Kettle for cross-plane.
And one thing I want to highlight is because in cross-plane the names of the composite
resource are always generated by the kube API server so every time you are claiming
an API the name is different, it is always different and you cannot influence it.
And so what you can do with Kettle is you can let Kettle identify the objects that you
are expecting via the labels.
You don't have to pass the name but instead just tell YAML that you just want an object
with certain properties and labels set and then Kettle will look for one object, for
any object on the server and if there is one that satisfies this constraint then you are
good to go.
One other thing that we've experienced is very good is you should run your tests in
separate clusters for every pipeline that you are running.
So we are using virtual clusters or B clusters for that that are run inside a physical cluster.
Of course you can create your own physical cluster all the time but if you are spinning
up physical clusters at least on EKS it can take up to 30 minutes and that is not something
that you want for every test and it also costs a lot of money.
And so you are just spinning up virtual clusters which are kubernetes control planes that are
running as pods inside a cluster where you can then install cross plane, its providers,
apply the compositions and then run all the tests with Kettle and then once you are done
with the tests then you can just delete the cluster and everything is fine.
And also you don't have any intervention between two different pipelines because compositions
are cluster scoped and they are most likely overwriting each other.
Now I've been talking a lot about end-to-end tests and they are really good and I recommend
you to write end-to-end tests when you are building a cross plane platform.
But end-to-end tests also take a lot of time to run if you are considering that you have
an API where you are creating real physical cloud resources and then you always have to
wait for your resource to actually start and then after some time maybe it says that some
thing is misconfigured and then you have to look for an error and if you are really just
doing development that it really slows you down because you have always this 10, 15,
20 minute gaps between something happening.
And there are a lot of mistakes that you can make when you are writing compositions.
And so I just want to highlight a few things so you have these composite type rests that
reference the composition with the XID they have to match and they are only validated
at runtime.
Then you have the group names which have to match with the XID name.
You have an unstructured open API schema because XID is because Kubernetes does not support
recursive API schemas yet.
Maybe it will come in the future but as of now it's not supported.
The same goes for the resource base which can also have any kind of field.
Then you have the resource patches.
By default the behavior in cross plane is if you want to patch from a field to another
field and the path of your source does not exist then cross plane default behavior is
that it will just ignore the patch and it will not throw an error or anything and if
that is the case you might easily swallow any errors and then you are wondering why
things don't work but you just have a typo in your patch and it's really hard to find
these if you have 2000 signs of YAML code.
Then you have types that must match so if the user is inputting a string then you have
to make sure that the string is actually expected and not an integer on the actually bucket
API for example.
Then you have the indentation, the big thing that when you are writing YAML files that
is my big problem if I'm writing YAML files I always mess up the indentation and then
things get all messy.
We need something to detect these errors sooner because the sooner you detect an error the
easier it is to fix.
What we have done because there is nothing out there at least we couldn't find anything
we've developed a linter for cross plane compositions where we are loading actual XID and CRD schemas
and then comparing them with the compositions and then applying a set of rules like ensuring
that the composition actually supports a valid XID type that you don't have duplicate objects
which can sometimes happen especially if you are generating things with Helm.
And then the most important thing is that it actually validates the patches that you
are running against the CRD and the XID schemas and that is really really helpful that the
first time when we ran this against our production code it turned out to have I think 800 errors
that nobody noticed but somehow our platform still worked.
And the other cool thing about our linter is that it's pure CLI and you don't need a
Kubernetes cluster or a cross plane installation you can just run this locally without setting
anything else up and it really takes maybe one minute or two and then you have all your
own lintered and that is really really really great.
If you're wondering where to get it there will be a link on the last slide where you
can find the code.
Summing things up, this is our CI-CD pipeline that we have developed after a couple of years
of testing and failing.
So we use Helm to write and build our compositions to generate the YAML code dynamically.
We use our self-written linter to lint our compositions and we use Kettle to run all
the end-to-end tests and then we are just pushing things with Train or any other kind
of OCI tool that comes handy.
Here's a QR code for the linter, we are actually making this open source today.
So you are the first one to actually see the code except us.
Thank you.
Do we have time for questions?
Okay.
Any questions?
So my question is more about cross-plane then cross-plane lint.
This looks really good though.
How does cross-plane compare to things like cluster API and the CRDs that that introduces?
Where's the distinction between the two of them?
If you're familiar with cluster API?
So cross-plane makes use of CRDs under the hood.
So if you are applying your XID on the cluster then cross-plane will generate CRDs which
are then used as the API that the user can claim.
There are no more questions then?
Thank you.
We're going to make a five minutes break.