So, welcome to the first Haskell dev room at FOSDEM and thank you for coming.
We have a great line-up of speakers today on a diverse range of topics and a bunch of
the topics are really aimed at newcomers to Haskell or people who haven't been programming
Haskell for very long.
So please encourage people you know here at FOSDEM to come along.
I believe that there is a live stream, there is a matrix chat room where you can put questions
or discuss the topics and we're going to have a raffle at the end of the dev room.
We will hand out raffle tickets to people who are new to Haskell.
So the prizes, we have three copies of Graham Hartons programming in Haskell second edition
and we have the booby prize, jar of vegemite from my native country.
We have stickers up the front here, come and grab some stickers to adorn your laptops or
books or whatever you like.
How many do we have?
Stickers?
Yep.
A lot.
A lot of stickers.
So feel free to take a handful if you want.
The first talk will be in just a few minutes.
So I will introduce the speaker in a couple of minutes.
Thank you.
There we go...