Hekate is a Haskell from the trenches with an interest in resilient systems and documentation.
When not at work or in the Haskell community, they are a trombonist in various orchestras
and brass bands.
Hekate uses they and them pronouns and farcical amounts of caffeine to retain human form.
They are going to present to us a presentation entitled Web Application Architecture in
Haskell with Flora.pm.
Thank you Hekate.
Thank you very much.
Can everyone hear me?
Perfect.
So, welcome to this talk entitled Web Application Architecture in Haskell, When the Domain Drives
the Types and Types Drive the Program.
So this talk is intended for a missed audience of software engineers who are acquainted with
the practice of domain-driven design and Haskell programmers who are interested in crafting
better systems.
The goal is to create a bridge between the practitioners of domain-driven design and
the users of Haskell.
So my name is Théophile Chautry, aka Hekate, to the community.
I am a backend engineer at Scryve.
We are a three-ish company and we have an e-signature platform for contracts and various
documents as well as a digital identity hub where we aggregate various national identity
providers like Itzme in Belgium, for example, or BankID, France Connect for the French people
here.
I am also privileged to be a board member of the Haskell Foundation.
This is one of my numerous involvement in the community.
So Haskell, the pure functional programming language, so these are words and words don't
mean nothing until we can practically apply them.
These words bring us concrete features like native supers for recursion, for example,
without blowing your stack type system that doesn't hate you, high order functions that
almost every language has today and many other features.
There are two features especially that I want to talk about and it is going to be its ability
of the language to adequately represent business domains and the ability to track side effects
in a semantic way.
For example, the adequate representation of business domain, we can use algebraic data
types to allow us to model with more precision the real world and its nuances.
Encoding rules by construction at the type level is something that we can easily do.
In this example, for example, the members of the excess data type visitor and admin
are promoted to the type level for this user type, which means that, for example, there
can only be two values in the privileges parameter of this user type.
And also it means that I am going to get rejected if I pass a visitor user to this function
called view back office.
But I'm going to get rejected at the compilation.
This is something that is trivial to implement at the value level.
I could have a check on a member of the object, of a property of the object that would be
ease admin with a Boolean.
But I have to write the check manually and possibly for every function that needs to
have such a check.
If I encode this property, this immutable property at the type system, at the level
of the types, the compiler then is tasked with checking if I'm doing my job correctly.
Checking side effects semantically.
If we take the previous example, we can see that view back office has a result type of
IOHTML, which more or less means I am doing observable side effects and I return you a
value in HTML.
But that's, you know, it doesn't adequately represent the reality of the function.
And for example, here we have a way of tracking side effects that are being executed in a
more human readable form and we can declare them at the type level.
So here we have a function that's, so the signature is we get an int, which is an identifier,
and we return a function that returns text.
And this F, monad, this F return type has also a list of effects.
So what are these effects?
So, I declare that I'm going to perform database access and possibly mutation.
I am going to access a ready server for the caching and I'm also going to ship my logs
to an external platform or at least to perform the loading effects, whatever that means.
And then we can have more useful breakdown of which functions have which effects.
So get entity name is composed of first we get the entity from the cache if we have it
and then if we don't we can switch to the database to perform a perhaps more costly
access and then finally we log the effects.
So logging, DB, Redis, all of them are then unified in this list of effects at the type
level.
So when a type system is both strong and expressive, we get a lot closer to TLS refactoring.
And what does that mean?
Because many languages today claim to provide such a thing.
So TLS refactoring, you more or less get vibe checked by the compiler, which is pretty cool
because then the compiler keeps you in check regarding the changes in your program and
how they affect the program's behavior.
We also took up the terms with the fact that your worst enemy is now yourself.
You can't blame errors in production because undefined is not a function.
So there are limits of course to correct by construction and I think it's especially important
to be intellectually honest with that.
Haskell is not a prover.
You can prove lemmas and theorems with it.
So you have to write tests and tests come in many shapes and forms.
You write tests for your integrations, your properties and end-to-end tests.
Tests are not optional, unlike maybe.
So functional application architecture.
So this that I showed you gives us a tool to focus now on the topic of functional application
architecture and this time we arrive in the lens of domain-driven design.
There will be a brief overview of the terminology and the techniques that were created in the
discipline and how they apply to us.
So we have, without surprise, the concept of a bounded context.
It's a context.
There are workflow in there.
So what is it really?
It's an autonomous subsystem.
So it's responsible for one or multiple workflows and it has well-defined boundaries, which
is extremely important.
So we have to formalize, or at least be very explicit, how we talk to it, its inputs and
its outputs.
If we take the example of florida.pm, which is a community website, an alternative package
index for the Haskell community, the schema is fairly simple.
We have the web component that talks to the core component, which is tasked then to interface
with the database.
And we have a jobs worker for the jobs queue that also talks to the core components and
to the database.
But we know that it's not going to talk with the web components.
So this is the kind of setting boundaries because they are in a healthy relationship.
And we know that we will not talk to each other.
One more step forward, fearless refactoring.
Now something that the Java and C-sharp world gave us are the concepts of data transfer
objects, data access objects, and business objects.
Sometimes they are the same thing.
Sometimes you are lucky that the JSON payload you receive is the same object upon which
you will perform your business computations and which you will store in your database.
But sometimes they are not.
And really it is pure luck that sometimes these types align.
An example of how this bit me when I was young and hopeful, obviously, without much practice.
During meeting with other people, we were trying to define a JSON-based format for data
exchange between several systems.
And we had Elixir systems, PHP, Ruby, Python.
And these all give you several slight differences in how you can have data types encoded in
these languages.
And for example, if you are dealing with a Rubyist or PHP users, they will try and push
a heterogeneous list in the data format.
So you can have a string and natively in Haskell we don't do that.
So we would have to create some abstraction on top of it.
And I was realizing that I was constraining myself with the capacity of each language
to create this data format based on JSON.
But you don't have to do it.
You can have your fully external way to talk to your mates, your other systems, and have
different representation inside your core components.
For example, if we apply this to Flora, we can see that actually I have my business objects
living inside my bounded context.
When I need to store them, I serialize them to a data access object that will be compliant
with what my database expects.
So it means no fancy mutually recursive types, for example, or something like that.
And when I need to send that on the wire, I will serialize that to a format that is
easily representable by XML, JSON, and other various cursed binary representations that
we may find, especially in the banking system.
So in the end, if I was to summarize bounded context, I showed you a very simple diagram
earlier of Flora.
But how does it interface with each other?
So we have DTOs between each component, and especially between the clients and us, DAOs
for storage access, and inside each component we operate on our business objects.
It so happens that the business object can be extremely similar between the web and the
core components, but sometimes they are not.
And I think it's very liberating to know that you don't have to keep to a single representation
from A to Z all the way.
You really can have conversion layers between your components, between your interfaces,
and it's perfectly all right.
For example, very trivial, but reading configuration.
The 12-factor application model tells us to read configuration from the environment, from
the shell.
So what we have on the left is the config type, which models what I get from the environment
with a twist, because I can force some types.
It's not all text-based.
I can force my parsing of HTTP ports to be a word 16, for example, because I'm not so
interested in having port number of 1 million, unless not without overflow.
So I've got my external configuration that describes, for example, the first member is
DB config with a pool configuration.
So it's all the information I need for the pool, the database pool.
And then internal configuration, it's the pool itself.
And it's very useful because then I have this very explicit conversion, and it's perfectly
all right then to change something inside or outside my core components.
Because then I only have this bottleneck that I can easily change and one more step towards
TLS refactoring.
Separating commands and queries.
So this has practical effects in terms of operation infrastructure and also in terms
of ergonomics for the people who read our code.
In a practical way, if we know that we have a recurrent, fairly heavy processing query
that runs and can take significant lock or CPUs on our server, we have the option to
have these queries run on a read-only replica for our database.
And put this replica on another machine.
So PostgreSQL, for example, very specific example, but I can talk about that.
You can have read-only replicas which take read-only queries and will be very angry at
you if you ever try to mutate the state of this replica.
So you have your primary server which upon which you perform mutating commands and then
it will stream these changes to read-only replica and then the replica will provide
you with a read-only interface.
That is like not only enforced at the level of the types, for example, in your applications,
but fundamentally on the protocol itself.
You will get a runtime error if you try to mutate this state.
So you can't unsafe perform on an unsafe course your way behind that.
So something I learned at my current place of employment scribe is to have a physical
separation in the code between types, the commands and the queries.
So the dialect, the idiom that we have here is that we have these.query and.update modules
in which we put the read-only and mutating queries.
And then when we import them, we qualify them, for example, import qualified as query and
then there is a visual indicator.
So it's very bare-bones but it does work.
This is a query that is going to be read-only.
It's not going to increment a counter in a side table because you have performed something
that is seemingly read-only.
A good example, for example, it's LinkedIn.
When you view someone's page on LinkedIn, they have a notification.
So you would think that viewing something, it's fundamentally read-only, even the terms
reading, viewing, you know, you would think it's read-only.
But perhaps there is a counter that is increased with user tracking so that you can later report
who has viewed your page.
But if you can bring one step more into separating the queries and the commands, then it's much
easier to know which kind of operation you're performing at which place in the code.
So we could go further even and declare queries and commands as effects with their own connection
pulls.
For example, I don't only have the DB effects in my stack.
I'm declaring that I'm performing a read-only operation on the read-only replica of my PostgreSQL
database.
So one more step towards, you know, more...
So of course it can be a technical detail but also I think it's very important to be
able to say to the readers of your code what are you performing, which side effect does
it have, especially in the system that you have ownership of.
Now that's my...
An orchist tendency is coming up.
Let's keep our distance from the state.
The state is best contained.
So the cache of our application is actually a bounded context in its own.
It has its own lifecycle, data storage and API.
And by decoupling our application monolith from its state, we have worked a significant
portion of the path to having a setup where we can have multiple instances of our application
and serving data from the same database in cache.
So at this point, by ensuring that the database server keeps operations in sync, we've got
higher consistency of the application.
So that's the CAP theorem for the disability systems.
You've got CAP.
Is your application consistent?
Is it available or is it tolerant to partition?
And in some industries where you work in very sensitive... with very sensitive data, if you
have a production incident, you can't risk having inconsistent data or having an inconsistent
state where people can read someone else's private folder.
So it's better to shut things down for a bit.
We keep our count, we take a long, deep, long breath and then we restart the system.
But it's because availability has to take one for the team in order to keep consistent.
And partition, tolerance, sorry, to partition, can go out the window.
So for Flora, for example, very simple, we can have our clients that talk to our NGINX
gateway and then the multiple instances of Flora that still speak to the same database
server for mutating operations and the same replica for read-only commands.
I'm not selling you microservice architectures and scale to the moon type of stuff.
But I think it's a very decent way to start a monolith.
We all know that a good distributed system has to start as a monolith and then split
it further and further.
If you start with a microservice-based architecture, you might end up with a distributed monolith.
But the whole thing of a microservice-based application is to have independent contexts
that can still run.
So here we don't take the bet that every component is fully independent.
We acknowledge the boundaries that we have some boundaries between the web, the core,
and the job worker's components.
And then themselves, they have their own context.
So it's also about realism.
Do you want to scale to the moon and raise like hundreds of thousands of dollars from
venture capitalists?
Or do you want to create a nice community website that indexes packages for the Haskell
environment?
I'm going to make a short detour here, and it's directing our workflows with types.
So it's a technique that brings together type safety and ergonomics, which is one of my
favorite subjects, to create type-directed state machines.
Very fancy word.
Basically, it's really the way that your operations are composed together, and you will be driven
to compose these operations via their types.
It can be a bit scary sometimes to think of your business operations as a state machine,
but it gives us a terminology and a literature to take from and to think of how we organize
and compose our operations.
So for example, here we have a workflow state, which can have three values, arrival, processed,
and departure, and a workflow that has this state type parameter.
So we have a new workflow value that creates a workflow w1, and then the process workflow
function takes a workflow, but not any kind of workflow.
It has to be set to arrival.
It can only take newly arrived workflows and then sets them as processed.
Again, this could be in-codes trivially implemented at the value level with properties of the
workflow object, and we could very easily verify, check these properties in the value
level in the code.
But here I factorize all these checks, and I put them really at a place where the compiler
can guide my hand and tell me where I went wrong with that.
And finally, the send back workflow can only take processed workflows by the laws of the
use, and then sets the workflow as deported.
So if I compose the functions in the good order, so new workflow and then a pipeline
of functions, and then I pipe it into process workflow and send back workflow, everything
is good.
If I try to skip a step, I will get a compiler error that says you wanted me to take a processed
workflow.
But actually, I need, sorry, you wanted me to take an arrival workflow, but actually
I need the processed workflow.
And this code, you're not sending that code to production because you cannot compile this
code.
In terms of web application development, there are also some, for us, haskalers, we like
to put everything at the level of types and think of our code as being formally proven
or code by construction.
But sometimes we must not drink all the cool aid or all the clemate.
For example, database layers that promise type safe SQL.
If you ever find a database layer that promise type safety, either it's the kind of type
safety that is trivial to implement, and it's totally expected of the tool to have it, or
it has encoded the semantics of SQL at the type level, and we've either found the golden
goose or someone who has clearly underestimated the difficulties of SQL semantics.
Also SQLite for development and PostgreSQL for production, that's something that the Python
community has popularized in the 2010s.
So we can accomplish great things by lying to the universe, but we scarcely accomplish
anything by lying to ourselves.
And SQLite is its own system, and unless you somehow perfectly code in this common subset
of SQL supported by both implementations, you will be maintaining two sets of database
migrations and sometimes of code.
So PostgreSQL has very good features, SQLite has different but also good features, not
its type system, of course.
But if you get used to one locally and then discover the second one once you're deployed,
you're going to have a bad time and also the muscle memory, because the brain is a muscle,
that you will have accumulated with SQLite would be fairly useless with PostgreSQL.
So where to go from here?
Documentation.
You produce documentation.
We have many ways of producing documentation, and we hold also tremendous power in the types.
And coupled with introspection, it means that the algebraic data types, like the sum types
and the product types, so the enums and the records, they can serve as the backbone for
further even documentation.
The types themselves are not documentation, but they can be used to guide the reader.
And you remember how I told you to write the tests.
So the best tests are those that can describe real world behaviors.
And if you can even produce a summary web page that shows the behaviors and the high
level paths taken by your program according to some input, this is very particularly helpful
for less technical people, like product managers, who want to know the behavior of your program.
If you can present a nice interface of how the code is executed according to some high
level business operation, it's even better.
So I have a couple of sources for what I'm saying.
I'm not pulling that out of my ass.
The first one is Dominant Modeling Made Functional by Scott Vlachin.
It's an excellent book written in F-sharp for the functional and DDD practitioners.
It's excellent.
I encourage you to read it.
As well as Living Documentation by Cyril Marcher.
And that one is also excellent.
Really it puts documentation as its own living system for which you will have real clients,
because PMs and other engineers in your organization or consumers of documentation, and of course
hideous amounts of caffeine, as Fraser told earlier.
So that would be the end of my talk.
Do we have a couple of minutes for questions perhaps?
Yes, thank you, Akate.
And we do have about 10 minutes for questions.
Yes, young man there.
This is on.
This is more of a comment than a question.
So one little detail that I think that sort of you could have sold also, right, is the
fact that when you do this, when you do the data kind annotation on your workflow, instead
of checking that during runtime, we do the type annotation and that's actually more efficient,
right, because of type erasure that there's no runtime data or check that has to happen.
Yes, so what Bjorn says is that indeed there is a matter of efficiency, because the data
kinds when we encode the nature of parameters in our workflow, this all goes away at code
generation.
So if you are in a setup where you need some very minimal code that is being generated,
if you are in tight loop for example, this code is completely raised at the time of code
generation and indeed you spare some CPU cycles.
Any other question?
You can also call me up on my bullshit.
I won't be offended.
Yes?
Do I need my code?
I can repeat your question.
Oh yes, that's not quite quickly.
The libraries that offer type safe database access that are, I'm sure, hideously incomplete
also offer abstraction of a different database back ends, which is one of the problems you
were talking about, like why you're using Postgres to develop locally.
So my question is, are there really situations for a 4PM where those libraries didn't provide
a feature that you needed?
Yes, so the question is, those libraries that encode all of the semantics of SQL at the
type level, are there situations where they don't provide features that I would need for
a 4PM?
Yes.
So as I told earlier, I'm very preoccupied by ergonomics.
20 minutes of compilation time and 20 gigabytes of half the interface files on disk, I would
consider that a problem in terms of feedback loop for contributors.
My previous place of employment, we used the toolkit Squeal for type level-encoded SQL
queries because they were business critical.
So we wanted to invest in something very much type safe because of the critical aspect of
these queries.
It was hell.
It was horrendous.
It was not only to view and to review, but also because it took so much time to compile,
like unironically 20 minutes, and we had some problems with stack because the interface
files on disk were taking way too much space.
Type families in Haskell are best consumed responsibly.
I'm a servant user, so I can't shit too much on type families, but in some cases, very
specific cases, it's best to rely on the expertise of outside systems.
For example, my best friend, who's here actually in FOSDEM, is my database administrator at
work.
I keep him close.
Do you ever have experience to need to onboard like a newer developer to maintain or even
do new feature to the project?
If so, what's the experience, especially if they don't have any Haskell experience or
especially this kind of experience?
Yes, very good question.
Do we have any experience onboarding new developers on the project?
Actually this talk was supposed to be the continuation of the different onboarding sessions
rather than on Flora PM.
So sometimes if you find me on Discord or Matrix, I will share my screen and introduce
people to the code base.
I think that's one of the most important aspects of Flora as a project.
Not only it is a community tool that aims to satisfy the users, but also it's a vessel
for teaching.
So I have got many techniques that I explained in this talk implemented in Flora, and Flora
is the factor code base to teach these techniques.
I had very bad experience with community tools that have badly aged, and the code is only
known by the 10% of maintainers that stick around, even if the vast majority of contributors
of a project are the 90% of people who just make one pull request and then go away forever.
So it's very hard to retain institutional knowledge, and also it's very hard not to
aim to please the 10% of people who stick around and submit patches on the regular.
So yes, I would think that, and that's the goal of Flora, onboarding new contributors
easily is actually a feature, and if it can't be done anymore, it's a bug.
Any other question?
Nope.
With such a representation, is it possible to write a function that, say, generates a
diagram?
It technically is.
I have references for you.
So the question is, can we generate diagrams from such representations?
Because indeed we have the possible values that we have at a type level, and we can do
many things with our types, including inspecting them.
So yes, I believe there are several libraries on Hackage that aim to, for example, provenance.
It's a library that gives you the path that the data takes and the provenance of your
data throughout the code.
I would say it's one of the greatest things to be able to do, is to represent your code
and to extract facts and movements from your code in a higher level representation.
So yeah, I believe we can do it today.
I don't do it personally.
I think it's possible.
There's time for more questions.
Or you can like, duel me if you want to challenge my beliefs.
Okay.
That seems like it.
So thank you again, Ekate.
Thank you very much.