Okay, so our next talk is by Ivan Sakhka.
Ivan has commercial experience working in 3D graphics and runtime design with Rust,
Nix and Haskell, and he also does design algorithm competitions and children's coding
workshops.
He lives in Belgium, loves biking, hiking, climbing and vegan cooking.
His topic today is on the path of better interoperability with Rust.
Thank you, Ivan.
Thank you.
Hi, everyone.
So, this talk is about a thing I worked the past few months.
There is also a blog article on engineering.iog.io, I guess, which is basically the content of
the slides with links and references and everything.
And so, the IOG issue is there is really large Haskell code base to maintain and some parts
of the code base are C bits mainly for cryptographic library like Kryptonite.
And so, there is a way to more easily integrate Rust library because for cryptography, there
is cool Rust library implementation.
And that's not quite simple right now to interface Haskell and Rust.
And so, this talk is about how to make the experience easier.
And there is a repository.
Yeah, so, it's the links here, the subtitle where you can find the source and everything.
And so, when we try to integrate to runtime for example, Rust and Haskell in our case,
there is a lot of way to interoperate different programming languages.
And one of the solution which is often used is to use, I don't know, sockets or writing
on a file or pipe or something like that.
And to use a protocol, for example, protocol buffer from Google or anything you can use,
Amazon or HTTP API, all this kind of stuff.
But if you do such, you will rely on C skulls like EOs to make interoperability works.
And if the librarian which you rely, you want really little over to call it to rely on what
the librarian does, you prefer to use something which is called FFI, which is a library.
It's more close to system programming, which is foreign function interface, which is basically
jumping the memory of binary code generated by another languages and up it will work the
right way.
And to make it work, it requires special attention.
And the tools needed to underline that is we will take special attention to that right
now.
And if we look at what exists to FFI between Rust and other programming languages, because
there is such a common way to interoperate stuff, we can see that from C to Rust, there
is a thing called Rust
is a thing called C.
I will not name all of them, but there are all of them, which is Bongen, which is generating
bindings.
You already know that, but why we do binding generation?
Because FFI is really something dangerous where if your two foreign function interface
didn't match, you will not know.
Your compiler will not warn you about that.
It will warn you if a symbol is missing, but it will not check the types, the number of
your arguments, if you respect the same calling convention.
It will show you want this interface to be generated so you can ensure it matches something
very common, but it appears it does not exist between Rust and Askel.
So that's basically what this Tolkien project is about.
And so a bit of Rust code.
The way I choose to generate Bongen using a macro, which works like a function decorator,
so it's a function that does something really simple, just print hello name, string interpolation
in Rust.
Here, I import my library, and here I have my custom thing, which is I tell my binding
generation about what will be my Askel wanted function signature.
And so a macro will expand the code.
So it's got generation, macro actually, in most languages.
So here's a code expanded by the macro.
I have numonguel things because maybe you know mongling something that exists in C++2
is a function symbol change, a change in binary, and we want to preserve it.
We want binary to have the same symbol to be culled from the outside from an Askel program.
And all those things I want you to look at is I use external C here, precise C. That's
mean in Rust.
I want to use the C culling convention, C-heavy-i.
So high-be-i is a culling convention and memory type layouts, which is a bit of the same part
of the same definition.
The thing is when you define FFI in Haskell, we'll show you Askel code just after this
slide, you don't have the choice.
You use the C culling convention.
In Rust, you have a bit more choice, but you can't use, just not true what I wanted you
to say, you have the choice in Askel to, never mind.
I want just to point out that Rust, heavy-i, Rust culling convention, the cull convention
I use Rust function inside the binary between the same, is unstable, which is things that
exist in Askel 2, which is a way that Rust internal, the Rust core team, keep to be able
to break the mechanism inside Rust C without changing the module version of the compiler.
So for example, the culling convention changed several times in the stable version of the
language, which is Rust 1.0 something.
So if we build a thing on top of Rust, heavy-i, culling convention, keep memory layout, it
will not be stable, it will be an hack.
And so maintaining it will be really laborious because it's working with internal documentation
which is not made for people to use it as a public API.
And so, why Rust macro? I want also to point out that because there is a lot of way to
do binding generation and often it work as an external tooling.
And the issue with an external tooling, it's really easy to forget to integrate the external
tooling into your build suite.
And if you do that, your binding will be out of sync with your codes, so your program will
not work.
So we want binding generation to be part of the compilation.
Create is a Rust module.
And so I did it that way.
And I also want to point out that there is other programming in Rust space, like C-bindgents
are just try to integrate Rust code like search and replace.
So if you, for example, in the long range, have two identifiers in different namespace,
C-bindgents, that's a way to generate C-bindgents for Rust, will not be able to understand their
meaning.
So when they define the algorithm, it's part of the limitation of that library.
It's not part of the bindgen library we present here that understands Rust semantics because
it's implemented as a macro.
And so it expands Rust code and it also generates as a set effect R-scale code and R-scale modules
that just have the one-tied signature.
So same symbol, same signature, things that's synced together.
So if we relook the Rust code, there's another things I want to talk to you about here.
You see you have the C compatible coding conversion type.
The thing I want you to look at is I use trait, trait, rep C, trait, rep Rust, and that's
trait are Rust type classes.
That's a way to define contracts for data structure.
You mean a data structure should implement this and this method.
So I want every data structure that has this method would implement those internally, implemented
as virtual table, like in C++.
And why I use that?
I use that to be extensive programmable.
So I have nice error.
It's part of Rust type system.
Users can add types to this framework.
And for the types, which is part of the standard library that I implement myself, I take care
of the memory management.
And we talk about it a bit later.
And also the thing is in FFI, in Rust, you can use only what's called FFE safe types.
It means types that have a memory layout in SQL in convention.
And most of Rust type have undefined memory layout for SQL in convention.
So the thing is, for example, if I get Rust strings, I cast it safely to a C string.
So I could represent as C string works, which knows the way that Rust strings are actually
represented.
And so what about GC?
The thing is Rust have a destructor mechanism based on ownership lifetime, a lot of rusty
things, but the idea is more about destructor.
When you go out of a scope, the destructor of the value is called, which is dropped.
And so what I do here is I tell Rust type system does not call drop on Rust value because
it will live on the Haskell side.
So that's the other side of the bindings that need to free the value, which is similar to
what you can do with March, I don't know how to pronounce that library.
And the things is also I learned during this project, the real semantic of safe and then
unsafe for a code definition, because I finally understand that unsafe means you want to play
with any object on the Haskell heap, which is not the default case of what we actually
do when we pass basic data typesets.
It does not need the garbage collector to pause because it doesn't know if we could
get an inconsistent state by something that the foreign code will do.
And so if you use unsafe, you will have a warning that say a cautious, an unsafe code
will slow down your war program or you want to do that or not, anything.
And that's a library, a Rust library, but those are things I did.
And that's also what exists for all of the Rust tooling is a key tool that helps you
to set up a project because you have to tweak your Rust build file, you have to tweak your
Rscale build file.
Actually you have to do a set up that has built customization in Rscale unless you use
Nix, which I could understand a lot of people who want to.
And on Rust.ai I use build.rs if you do a dynamic library because dynamic library that
JC fetch needs a JC version in the name of the dynamic library.
So that's the things that I have to get as a build customization.
This scan of tweak, but overall this library is really small.
I'll put next slide just a few minutes later.
The world library, the world tooling I present here is less than 1000 lines of code.
So it's 1000 lines of code.
So that's really small and minimalist and key.
So actually I forget what I was about to say.
Actually all of that of this plumber is simple and I'm not sure myself I want to make it
more complex because it just works.
And the thing is it works but it is really simple data types.
The C data types that are representable in Rscale and Rust.
And there is a lot of things that are not representable in C. For example, Rust slice.
A slice is a pointer and a size and you have a guarantee that there is memory in it.
You can iterate on it.
You can represent it in C with a struct but it's not really a C type.
You will do a custom struct.
And those things are targeted by the Rust RFC which is an intramarable ABI which is
creating an ABI which is stable which have more Rust things than the C ABI but which
is flagged as stable which is not the case of the Rust internal ABI.
And the other thing is CABAL customization is a bit of a mess.
Doing this is a set up that has to find the library and anything to make it work because
of CABAL bugs.
So I will not have to have a standard way to integrate for example Rust and chain into
CABAL.
Here you have to run the total chain into different type.
And that's it.
I can throw a lot of questions or I can do a demo if I might talk in short hours and
what I was expecting.
So that's the day to ask questions.
Yeah.
Yeah I can do a quick demo.
Sorry.
It's not easy because it's not mirroring so I have to look at the screen YI.
I'm doing this thing.
What I can do.
Yeah.
Did you.
So from what I understand you can pass from from Rust to Haskell the subset of data that
is representable with the Rc.
So you can't really pass functions for example.
Or can you?
It will be unsafe on the Haskell side if you do that for example because you will need
to be.
I is an interesting example.
I didn't try passing a function pointer.
The thing is there is the thing is you if you want to pass complex data types you it's
always more meaningful to use serialization because it's it's it doesn't match the two
language model but function I didn't honestly think about it but I you mean a function pointers
that will cross if I buyer.
So that's the whole question right.
Yeah.
So if you have no concept of sharing pointers you copy the whole data and it's made to the
other node including function which are serialized and then read to present on the other node.
I guess it will not not really be an issue because because in fact there's there's no
really boundary at the end that's one binary so there's only things that I want my model
to have a better grasp around it is all GC Haskell GC will behave in this case but I
think there is no special issue for doing that but I think I should experiment on it
first to to to before saying it's it's completely okay to do that.
Yeah.
Thank you for the question.
I.
Did you see something.
Fuck.
So.
Sorry.
So if I go here for example I have a little rest things.
SRC.
Yeah.
Can show you the lead the rest which do a cryptographic primitive for example and you
what you manipulate is clearly rest types it's not C types and I have a warning and
I don't know why.
Yeah.
Because I don't start first and if I do I guess it will work I hope so.
I can check what's happened with after macro expansion.
Did it work.
Yeah.
Sorry.
demo effect.
Yeah.
Why.
Fuck.
Maybe the other one is locked.
I don't know why you do that maybe I'm no internet connection and that's a so issue
here.
Yeah.
I guess that's the issue.
So never mind I can show you the ask and things generated.
So no that's a cabal file generated by the client.
And so I have.
Looks like that.
I have my my.
What can I show you.
I can show you the bleed customization can see what it looks like.
Look like sit.
It's not really interesting but you do few things.
And what can I show you.
I have a little file that's unsure that's a client you use to generate the wall stuff
is compatible with a version of the library you use to do.
I want to change the world behavior in the future.
And now on the ask inside it looks something like that so I have a project I have a couple
project right.
It looks like that.
And the test scene just work like.
I have a test that couple.
It looks like that.
I can use it like it was normal ascal dependencies and my.
Ask code.
It's quite simple I guess.
Yeah.
Sorry fix me but don't look.
You have something like that.
It's always a bit you manipulate low level data structure but that's that's often what
you want to do when you you you broke something in the system programming language.
That's one reason to use rest over something else.
Otherwise.
I don't know I got the input that's the binding don't really need.
Don't really need.
More advanced data types for example ochamel have an interrupt ochamel interrupt things
with rust that helps to represent a duty bus rust and ochamel and I don't know if we really
need to have a duty conversion between languages for most of use case I don't know.
Yeah.
That's that's many.
I don't know if you have other question or just curious about something.
Or another.
Yeah.
Hey there's a question.
So you said I want one that rest will not drop the value and that's to scale to three
so how does that work?
Is that under by the GVIPE I have a GC or does it need to be done manually?
You mean I tell us to not drop a value?
No.
If we do rest doesn't drop the value who does is it the GVIPE or somewhere we need to add
that in a program?
Yeah.
The idea is because it's part of the marshmold things we have to free it explicitly as I
understand it.
If we do not value with leaf maybe somebody could tell me if I mistaken the spot.
It's really hard to debug what actually GC does.
So far I didn't experiment so mention that but yeah the real thing is really that if
you do not force Rust to not drop things it will because it's part of its type system
it will pull code to free memory to free of the memory allocator you used straight into
the code.
Rust statically decide where to put allocation and release of memory inside the bin and binary
computed statically at compile time so you have to tell the type system to not do it
for specific types if there is an internals for that.
But on the Haskell side I'm not sure I'm pretty sure that the GC will track it as a
garbage collected object I think because you have to do it explicitly.
That's one of the point I'm a bit unconfident so I want to check again this kind of scenario.
Do you have a question?
What do you do if there's an external Rust library that you don't have control over because
they might not want to add HS bindgen macros to their code base?
Is there a way of generating a shim or something?
In fact it's really easy in Rust to do re-export so you can always create a new create, re-export
a create as you say I depend on this create and re-export the thing I want to re-export
and I decorate or not element.
Yes it works.
Sorry?
Can you put those macros on the functions in the other library then?
In fact it's just wrapping function by function so you can do whatever you want.
And you can opt in or opt out some function of a library and some not which is to me is
the advantage of using macro and function decorator over code, work code parsing.
That's not free though is it?
That's not?
So if you're re-exporting functions but are you actually re-exporting the same function
or are you exporting a wrapper around the re-exporation?
Yeah but I, okay, I in Rust there is a clear idea of what symbol I want to expose and what
symbol I don't want to expose so I'm pretty confident that the compiler has the library
to inline or not things.
So for example most of the trait implementation I do which is casting are inline.
I explicitly say I want it to be inline and so yes it's a function that's called a function
but at the end it's just, it's, have no runtime cost.
So yeah.
Okay, we're out of time.
Thank you.
So thanks very much Yvonne.
Let's give him a round of applause.
Thank you very much.