So, I will speak about 2D animations in Haskell using low-slence and state.
I'm Julien Duos, and I am an assistant professor in computer science, and I use Haskell mostly
for teaching functional programming.
Haskell is not the most readily used language for implementing animations, but still it
has some interesting tools, such as library bindings like SDL2.
We also have some entity component system implementations, which is a classic technique
for developing games.
And we also have functional-reactive programming, which is a technique for implementing complex
user interfaces, for example.
And we can find some cool projects developed in Haskell, for example, defect process, which
is a game available on Steam that has been open-sourced recently.
And also the organic library, which can make quite impressive animations.
In this talk, I will show how to implement several animations on concrete examples using
functional programming and how to improve this code using some features of Haskell,
like data type, lazy evaluation, salence library, and state monad.
So first, let's look at a very simple example.
Let's say...
One note, can we get to a little louder?
Oh, okay.
A little hard to understand.
Okay.
So, as a first example, let's say we want to draw a solid disk on the screen with a
fixed radius.
To do that, we can use the GloST library, which is a classic library in Haskell, for
implementing animations and 2D graphics.
This library provides some functions for drawing primitives or for handling user events.
And the GloST library also provides some main loops that will run the main application.
So basically, all we have to do is to write some unlock function, which say how to render
the scene or how to render user inputs.
And then we pass these functions to the main loop, and that's all.
We can run the program.
So let's do that.
For this first example, we don't have any particular data.
We just want to draw a disk with a fixed radius.
So there is no letter to remember for describing the scene.
So we can write a type, which represents the model of our application.
But here, we don't need anything, so we can say it's a unit type, which means no letter.
Then we have to write a function that renders the scene.
So this function should take a model and return a picture.
Here we use a solid circle function, which is provided by GloST to draw a disk on the
screen.
And we say we want a disk with 50 pixels as the radius.
We also need a function to render user events.
That function should take an event and a model and return a new model.
This is a very classic way for modifying data in functional programming.
We can't mutate a variable because it's a side effect.
And pure functional programming, we can do that using pure functions.
So we just take the current model and return a new model, a copy of the model, which contains
the modifications.
For now, the scene is static, so we just return the same model.
And finally, to handle time, we just need a float.
The elapsed time is the previous update.
And the current model, and we return the new model with the modifications.
And once again, the scene is static, so for now, we return the same model.
Now we can write the main function.
We just have to set some parameters, for example, the initial value for the model and some parameters
for the window, the background color, and the format of the animation.
Then we can call the play function, which is main loop provided by the GloST library.
So we just pass to this function our parameters and our under function.
This is a very quick way to do in functional programming.
We have functions that we can pass to other functions and we can organize the code like
this.
So we get something like this.
I can run the program.
It's really impressive.
Nice.
And now let's add some animations.
So let's say we want to refresh the scene every second and change the radius using a
random number.
So to do that, we can use a pseudo random number generator.
We need to model our scene differently.
So we write a type, which is model here, which has two fields.
First is the current radius of the disk and the random number generator that we can use
to update the scene.
This is a record type in Haskell.
We have two fields, which has a name.
Each of them has a name.
And we can then use the function here.
So the name of the field is also a function that can access to this field using the model.
So here we get the radius of the model and we use that as the radius for drawing the
disk.
For the under time function, all we have to do is to generate a new radius.
So we take the generator inside the model and we call this function to generate a new
radius.
Since we cannot mutate the generator, we have to return a new generator for the next random
generation.
So this is why we get a new reduce here and a new generator here.
And that's it.
We can build and return the new model, which is the result of the function.
We need to update the main function.
We have to get a random number generator.
We can do that with this function, which gets the standard number generator from the system.
And we can also generate a first random number for the first radius of the animation.
And the model is built, is constructed here.
We get something like this, which is not so much impressive, but there is some animation.
Okay.
So this is a very classic way for generating random numbers.
But in Haskell, we can do differently.
Since Haskell has lazy evaluation, we can define an infinite list for all the radius
of the animation.
And Haskell will compute the numbers when it needs them.
So instead of the generator, we can use here a random list, an infinite list.
And that's all we need.
We will consume the elements in this list for having new reduces.
The unmet
have a function to get an infinite list.
So it just here, instead of the random R function, we just have to call the random RS function.
And this gives us an infinite list of random number.
And we don't have to under a random generator explicitly.
Okay.
So now let's look at a more complex example.
Let's say we want a ball that moves inside the window and bounces against the border
of the window.
And I can show and control the result.
Okay.
So we want a ball that moves inside the windows.
It can bounce against the border of the screen.
And if I hit the enter key, the scene is reinitialized with a random velocity and a random position
for the ball.
So how can we do that?
We need more complex types.
So we can first describe a ball, a ball as a position and velocity.
These fields are 2D vectors.
And now the model is just the current ball and the infinite list of the other ball.
We can generate randomly as we did before with the reduces.
These types are more complex than before because we have a model that has a ball and a ball
as two fields which are 3D vectors.
So these vectors have x-coordinate and y-coordinate.
So we have nested types which is a bit more complex to use.
We can under this type with the scale using standard record syntax.
There is no problem with that.
The syntax is just a little bit more complex.
So here we get the ball field of the model.
And here, for example, we return the same model as the argument.
But we change the ball field with these balls here, which has been computed before.
All the other fields of the model doesn't change.
We still copy them, in fact.
So this function updates the scene.
I have implemented it in two steps.
So first we move the ball and then we compute Bonsie's against the border of the window.
So let's look at the update Bonsie's function.
We have to compute the collision with the border of the windows.
So we take a ball as input and we return the ball after all the collisions have been computed.
To do that, we can use the record syntax as did before to change only the field that need
some modifications.
But in fact, it's sometimes simpler to fully reconstruct a ball.
So that's what I did here.
I have detected a collision with the left border and I have to return this ball so I
can set explicitly what is the new position vector and the new velocity vector.
In fact, there are only two fields which are different, the x-coordinate of the position
and the x-coordinate of the velocity.
So to avoid reconstructing the ball, we can use a library in a scale which is a lens and
which can simplify this code.
So the lens library enables us to access and modify nested types so we can go deeper inside
the type to just add a small modification.
To do that, we need to construct lenses.
Lenses are just functions that can access to a data type.
And when we have these functions, we can use all the functions and operators provided by
the lens library.
So let's do that.
We can build these functions, these access functions using this function, make lenses,
and that does everything for us.
So we just have to call make lenses for the ball and for the model.
And that's it.
We can use all the operators provided by the lens library.
This looks like this.
So here I return the model with two modifications.
The first modification, which is applying this function to the ball field and the second
modification here, where I apply the update functions, update bonuses function to the
ball field of the model.
And finally, the model with these two modifications is returned.
We have more than that.
For example, for the update bonuses function, instead of reconstructing the ball, we can
now just get it deeper inside the type to apply some changes.
For example, here I set this value to the x field of the position field of the ball
and finally the ball is returned.
And then I can change another modification here.
I apply the negate function to the x field of the velocity field of the ball.
So I can change several modifications and go deeply inside the type to make some modification,
setting a value or applying a function.
So this is quite interesting.
We can still improve this code.
As you can see, we take a ball and return a new ball.
So it's just updating a ball.
And to do that, we have computed here several steps, which corresponds to the collision
between all the borders of the windows.
In fact, we are modifying a ball, but we can't do that in pure functional programming.
So we have to use intermediate variables that store the modification after this collision
and this collision.
So the code is quite cumbersome.
And we can improve that using something in Haskell, which is called the state monad.
So the state monad is a very well-known monad in Haskell.
It's a very classic monad.
It's just a context where we simulate mutating a state.
So each action inside this monad is an access or modification of the current state.
And we can get the final state or another result.
We can do that also.
And that works well with the lens library because the lens library provides a stateful
version of its function and operators.
So let's do that.
We can change the under time function like this.
Instead of applying several modifications, we can just execute the state actions defined
here.
So this is a function.
This function takes a first parameter, which is the previous ball.
And when we have applied all the actions, the state action, we get a final state, which
is the final ball that we can use to update our model.
Let's see the update
this function.
So instead of taking a ball and returning a ball, now it's clear that we are in a state
monad.
And this is a state action where the current state is a ball.
And we can return a value.
But here we don't need that.
So the function return unit.
That means that every action inside this function is now an action, a state action.
So reading the state, modifying the state, and so on.
For example, here we can access the post field of the current state, which is a ball.
Here we can set this value to the x field of the position field of the ball or applying
a function on the x field of the velocity field of the ball, which is the current state.
Since the state monad is a monad, we can use all the features available for monads, such
as the new notation.
So we can change several actions like this.
And we can also use some functions provided for monads, such as the went function.
As a result, the code is a little bit more simple.
And it's clear that this is a state action that we have a current state, which is modified
according to the code.
And then we get the final state.
And this is checked by the compiler.
So to conclude, we have seen that functional programming and Haskell, using a functional
programming and Haskell, we can implement animations.
This is very natural in functional programming since we just have to pass some function to
other functions like a main loop.
And we can decompose and organize our code like this.
We use infinite list to generate random numbers.
So we don't have to use random number explicitly.
We just consume the elements of this list.
We also use the length library to access or modify nested types.
And we can go deeply inside these types.
And finally, we simulate a mutable state using the state monad.
So we can modify a variable and get the final result.
So all of this is still based on functional programming.
So we just manipulate pure functions and static typing.
And this is quite easy to read and less work-front.
Since we have no side effects, a function only depends on its argument and produces
the same result if the arguments are the same.
And all of this is checked by the compiler.
So this code, this state and the code shown here are available at this thing.
And you can find some information in the documentation of the libraries and see the things that sit
for me.
Thank you for your attention.
Thanks to the organizer.
Thank you, Julien.
If you have a question, put up your hand, I'll bring the mic.
Okay any questions?
Yes.
Do we know what the performance of gloss is like for complex applications?
Could you write a complex QI in gloss?
Do we know what the performance of gloss is for a complex display?
Okay, gloss is based on OpenGL, so it's not that slow, but I don't know for very complex
animations.
I believe some projects use SDL, and it seems they have no problem of performance, but I
have no experience more like that.
In the play function, it pretty much makes the whole program pure with no I.O.
What if you do want to do any I.O. in an application?
Okay, so the gloss library provides two interfaces, one which is purely functional, and another
where you can do I.O.
So there is a version where you can do that.
Okay any more questions?
Yes.
Maybe it's without a microphone, can you explain the operators used for the lenses?
There is many many operators.
Is the person signed?
Yeah, okay, so there is two versions of these operators, one which is purely functional,
so we just take the data structures that it can access and return the value, so this is
such operators.
So that means we apply the modification, so the ball 0 is returned after this modification,
so this is what this operator means.
Here it's for accessing another field, so it's an x field of the position field of the
table, and this operator says we set a value in that field, and this operator says we apply
a function on the field, and the stateful version is the same, but we have an equal
sign instead of the tilde.
It's like a get and a set.
Yes, we can get it like this, we can get the data.
Okay, any more questions?
Okay, let's thank Julia.
Thank you.
It's important for us to thank Juliahorn and her team, thank you so much, it was great
to be here.
And thank you, Julia.
Go learn better soon.