Okay, so here is a quick overview of the Haskell tooling. I am Julien Deus. I am an assistant
professor in computer science and I use Haskell since 2015, initially for teaching functional
programming. So since the beginning of the language Haskell has many tools have been
created for developing in Haskell and today most of the Haskell developers use a GHC compiler
for building Haskell projects we have an HCL such as Kerbal or Stack. Haskell is now quite
well integrated in the editor such as Visual Studio Code, VIM or Emacs, thanks to LSP implementations
such as HLS and all these tools can be installed using some tools like GHC app or Nix. In this talk
I will focus on Kerbal with VS Code and the Haskell plugin. First we have some online tools such as
Akage which is a package archive so you can go to the website and search for packages there is
for example some libraries for doing whatever you want. These libraries you can access their
documentation so you can see what to do with this library and how to use it and you also access to
their source code with nice colors and code navigation which is quite useful. We also have
Hoggle which is Haskell Google so it's a search engine and you can type the name of a function
and Hoggle will give you a link to the documentation of the function in Akage. If you don't know the
name of the function you can also type write the type of the function and Hoggle try to find a
function that matches that type so you can see its documentation on Akage and you see if it's
the function you are looking for. To work on a Haskell project you can use Kerbal which is a
tool for building and packaging projects. To use Kerbal we have to write a Kerbal file which is a
configuration file where you can specify some information about your project and also define
the target you want to build in your project. For example if you have a library or executables you
can write them. You can also add some dependencies for example libraries are available on Akage.
Then you can use the Kerbal tool once we have this file so you can run Kerbal build to build
our targets and when you do that Kerbal will get the dependencies from Akage and run the compiler
to build all your files. We also have the Kerbal run command to run specific targets and you can
also give command line arguments if your program requires that. We have a Reaper which is a read
eval print loop so this runs a compiler in an interpreter mode so you can write some Haskell
expressions and the compiler will evaluate these expressions and print the result so it's very
interesting for testing some code and you have also more specific commands. For example here
you can ask some information about the type of function or anything. Okay so to work on the
Haskell project we can use editors like Visual Studio Code with HLS and the Haskell. Haskell
plugin. It's a very easy tool so you have the file of your project you can open them edit them.
You also have code navigation and documentation so if I put the mouse pointer over a function
VS Code will show me the documentation of that function and if I control click on the function
VS Code goes to the definition of the function. We also have code completion so VS Code tries to
complete the code you are typing. We have an integration of the compiler so if there is
an error in your code VS Code will show you where is this error and it can give you the
message from the compiler. Even if your code is correct, VS Code can help you improve your code.
It can give some hints to refactor it. So for example here it says that my code is correct but
it would be better if I use the FMAP operator instead of the FMAP function. We also have HLS
which is let's say you are writing some code you don't know what to write at a specific
pace you can put this underscore character and the compiler will tell you what you'd expect at this
place. For example here it says that it waits for a function that take a string and return a hint.
We have an inline repo so you can type some Haskell expressions, Haskell expressions in your
code with a specific prefix and when you do that Haskell VS Code will print a button, will show a
button and if you click on this button it will evaluate your expressions and add the result of
these expressions in the comments below. So it can be very useful for adding some examples
as comments in your code for documenting the code. Speaking of documentation we have HADOC which is
a classic tool where we write documentation of our project inside as comment inside the code and
then we can run KBIR HADOC and this generates documentation as HTML5 which look like this.
As you can see it's a tool that is used for generating the documentation on IKG. And finally
we have some tools for testing our project. First of all Haskell has a quite powerful type system so
it already prevents us from writing many errors but we still need to test our code. We can do
that with a very classic unit test. So for example here we just write a Haskell expression with a
specific input and call a function on that input and we can write the value that we expect for this
input. So we can write many inputs to test and test many functions and when we run KBIR test
this will compile our testing program and run it and it checks that every expression is evaluated
and returns the expected value. If there is a problem in one of the tests, KBIR test will tell
us where the which function fails. We have more than that. We can use property-based testing
instead of giving a specific input we can write a property which is a function that takes
an argument and return a boolean and this boolean says if the property is satisfied or not.
And when we do that a quick check will generate random inputs. Here it says that it has generated
100 inputs and it tests the properties on each input. If one input makes the test fail,
a quick check will try to shrink the input to the smallest value such that it's simpler for us
to debug our program. Okay and to conclude Haskell has done nice tools for many years.
All these two, KABAL, repo, quick check are quite old and now very mature. Since more recently we
have very nice integrations in editors like VS Code or other editors. This is quite easy to install
at least on Linux. You just have to install JSTUP, VS Code and the Haskell. Haskell plugin and that's
it. You have a nice Haskell environment for the Rapinio project. This slide has an end-of-the-world
culture here. You can also see the tooling below which presents other alternatives. So if you
prefer to use VIM or MX there is a tool you can use to do that. And that's all from me. Thank you
for your attention. Thank you very much, Julia. There is time for questions.
Five minutes. Just shout it out and we can repeat the question.
Can you please repeat the question? So what is the difference between the KABAL repo and the JSTI
which is a repo from the compiler? In fact I think it's quite the same tool. KABAL will call
the JSTI, the repo from the compiler. But if your project has some specific dependencies or some
modules, the KABAL repo will take all of that into account so you can inspect that code and
it's quite more powerful. But it's the same tool at the end. Which tools do you recommend for
debugging Haskell? I don't use very much the Haskell debugger. There is a debugger.
Debugging in Haskell is quite different from other languages I think. So there is a debugger
where you can inspect memory or a runtime system using the JSTI compiler. It's not something that
I can do very well. So I won't recommend anything.
There's been your example which you showed that you can have comments evaluated as a record.
Because I know Rust has something quite similar and it makes sure that examples in your documentation
compile past tests. Can you do similar sorts of things? You had an example of a
REPL evaluated in comments in your code. Is that specific for the VS Code extension?
I think so. It's provided by Visual Studio Code with the SQL extension and it's automatic.
Yeah, Rust has this feature. The evaluator is doing a test. What is very confusing for beginners
sometimes if you come from another language like Rust or so, it's one way to build a project.
In Haskell you have like Kabbal and Stag and Dix and Stag and Nix together. Then you have Kabbal
V1, V2, NU. Is there some plan to clean this up someday to give a simple way to build Haskell
project? In fact, Kabbal and Stag don't do exactly the same. Stag is based on snapshots,
so it's more secure if you want to have the same build for a few projects. But both tools are
compatible, so Stag can use a Kabbal file. You can just write a Kabbal file, then add the version of
the snapshots you want to use for Stag. I agree with you, there are many tools.
I'm not familiar with Stag, but I thought that a Kabbal has something like a log file nowadays,
like a freeze is called. Is that similar to the Kabbal freeze?
I don't know. I thought it was Kabbal, so there is a freeze with Nix, but I don't use Kabbal
very much. Maybe, but I don't know. Okay, thanks.
Sorry. Okay, we're out of time, so please once again thank Julian.