Hello. Welcome to my talk about building a WebPI for the federal install. So my name
is Martin Koman and I work in the team that's building the Anaconda installer used by federal
and related distributions. First I would like to talk a bit about why we decided to actually
build a WebPI for our installer. And yeah, first like very shortly about like the federal
installer project. Yeah, the name of it is Anaconda which is very confusing for some
people doing Python in the scientific domain because there is a very similar project in
that it's like a Python thing but it's called the same as V but I think we are older. So
anyway right now we have a GTK3 UI for the installer. We have a text-based UI. It's also
possible to fully automate the installation. We have things like add-on support and yeah,
we are used as I mentioned by federal, CentOS and others. This talk is basically concerning
only the graphical user interface. We don't expect to have any changes for the text-based
interface and the kick-start based automation in the context of the WebUI. So why did we
actually choose to do something about the current graphical interface and why did we
choose to start working on a WebUI? So one of the points is that the current GTK interface
comes from the year 2013. Kind of looks like early GNOME 3 by coincidence maybe. It was
built at the same time basically. And over time we added new features. We fixed bugs.
We adapted to various federal changes for example. And the stuff kind of got bolted
on like not always it was possible to change the UI. So in some cases it's getting a bit
clunky already. Another issue is that some of the technology we build it on is getting
a bit old right now. GTK 3 is not that old at the moment but already you have GTK 4.
Eventually we would have to port it. One of the issues is for example that the federal
installation image. The federal project tries to have minimal dependencies of applications.
So like over time we want to have like the minimum amount of libraries. So we would have
to quite possibly migrate to keep the image sizes small. That's one of the reasons. We
also still run on top of X. There is even some hard dependency right now on keyboard
switching during the installation. So this is something we would have to address anyway.
The remote access to a graphical installation right now is not the best. It's based on VNC.
So it's unsecure. It's not very efficient. It requires you to have a graphical system
running on the host that you are installing. And you need a special application that might
not be available that users might need to install. So that's one of the issues. And
also I'm not saying it's not possible to test GTK 3 interfaces but basically it's not that
simple and we don't really have any unit test coverage. There are people from for example
the federal QA community that do test Anaconda but what they are using is basically a screenshot
or graphical bitmap based testing right now. So this is something that could be improved.
And also what we have seen in the past years is that there seems to be a clear trend towards
using Web UIs for system management. Some of you might still remember some of the system
config tools used on Fedora and CentOS and Trell that used to be available to configure
stuff like services, networking, firewalls. All of these over time effectively became
cockpit plugins for the cockpit web console. So this seems to be the trend overall for
system management as far as we can tell. So what we kind of found out, there are some
benefits of doing something about the current UI situation and doing something about it
with a web technology based UI. So while we are at it we can address some of the UX issues
we have right now because it's effectively a fresh start right now. It's easier to achieve
consistency because you are building the whole thing so you can make sure that it feels similar,
it's using the same concepts, the same workflows for everything hopefully. Also another thing
is that given the proliferation of Web UIs everywhere basically there seems to be much
bigger community of users, of developers of these technologies and there is overall more
documentation, there's even more resources for non-developer roles like UX designers
or usability testing projects. And this seems to be unfortunately quite lacking in many
native GUI libraries right now in comparison to the web technologies. And also like one
quite big point for it is that using a Web UI, just to be specific, we are going to use
the Web UI both locally and remotely. So we want to run it for the local graphical session
if any but also it makes it much, much easier to access the installation remotely. So for
any headless installations it should be much easier for the users using the installer to
connect securely and much more efficiently to the house that is being installed. Also
the house doesn't have to contain any graphical dependencies effectively because all the rendering
is happening on the client so the installation image could be much more and also the installation
time resource requirements could be much, much smaller. That could be an issue for stuff
like Raspberry Pis or some IOT SBCs which are perfectly fine for the tasks you will
be using them but if you try to do a graphical installation on them, bearing like possible
issues with drivers, it might need much more resources to just install to bring up the
graphical interface than it will be using for its lifetime of doing some useful work.
So let's talk a bit about the technical details of the tools that we are using to build the
UI for the Fedora installer right now. So this is the overall architecture. The install
is already modular in that it has a Python backend which has a D-Bus interface. Then
we are using Cockpit to provide a bridge between D-Bus and the web application which itself
is then written with ReactJS for the logic and pattern fly for the WebUI widgets. The
current Anaconda with the GTK3UI and even with the Kickstart support is actually using
the same Python backend and even the GTK3UI already is communicating with the backend
via D-Bus. So this makes it possible for us to right now work in parallel that we are
building the WebUI next to these other UIs right now. Just instead of directly calling
D-Bus you have pattern fly with JAX React talking via D-Bus calling D-Bus calls from
the backend. This is very similar to Cockpit plugins in general. Usually you have the networking
screen in Cockpit for example and what it does, it's talking to network manager via
this bridge. It's doing D-Bus calls from JVAS. It's basically the idea of Cockpit and we
are using this for our project. I've already mentioned this. It's not about another UI
that you can remotely access while keeping the current graphical interface next to this.
Eventually once we cover all the necessary functionality for the given project or product
it should replace the current graphical interface. But right now it's being developed next to
it and thanks to the modular backend text to the D-Bus interface it's not that hard
to do it. Also one more thing that we found very useful is the Cockpit test framework.
This is addressing the issue I've mentioned previously about no unit tests for the graphical
interface. This is something that has been developed for the Cockpit project itself which
directly maintains a lot of the screens you will see when you install Fedora or CentOS
or some such distribution and enable Cockpit. But there are also many community maintained
outside of the main community developing Cockpit, many other Cockpit plugins. So that is a very
comprehensive and I would say very nice test suite which makes it possible to essentially
write Python unit tests that then manipulate your Web UI or Cockpit plugin, in our case
the Anaconda Fedora installer interface. And it also supports pixel testing which we are
thinking this is nice but then we actually thought about the other issue that most web
applications have and that's dependencies. There are dependencies being pulled from NPM
for pattern fly for ReactJS and other libraries you might need to use and the problem with
this is that the release cadence is pretty fast. There are new versions of pattern fly
all the time and it would be very easy to get left behind basically to have very big
difference in using some old version and being much harder to upgrade later on. And pixel
tests make it much, much more easy to update this automatically or almost automatically
because you can effectively compare if you see any graphical changes from the old to
the new version. Same thing for any changes for the Web UI, you can easily see what the
new state looks like. If you see some changes that are expected, if you change some label
or add a button or if the layout is totally wrong. So, yeah, this is something I can recommend
for web applications. It seems to be very, not something we expected to be using but
it helps a lot. And it's, yeah, it's a part of the cockpit test tooling. So, okay, so
how far we got? This all started about a year ago in earnest. And right now we have very
simple but end-to-end install images that can be used to demonstrate the Web UI. And
actually you will end up with a functional, minimal but functional system. It's possible
to select an installation language. We already support geolocation like with the current
GTK3 interface. It's possible to select the disks. It's possible to dynamically add disks.
And this is kind of a demonstration of some dynamic behavior we wanted to have there.
That's it right now for storage. Storage, I'll talk a bit more about it later on. But
that's one of our main focus points because, like, that's like 90% of every install. We
have a review screen where you can see the settings. And where you can, where you are
so told that, yeah, you shouldn't really run it right now on any production system that
has any useful data because you select the disks and we will use them. Like, we will
wipe them and use them. So that's the minimal storage we have been able to come up with
for now until we have some more comprehensive screens where you can actually, like, keep
partitions and stuff like that. And the last one is just a progress screen where you can
see the installation happening, where you can see some errors if there are any, where
you can kind of guess how long it will take because that's not always easy to tell the
user correctly. So to have at least some pictures in the presentation. So this is in general
how it looks like. If you've seen the current Anaconda, this is quite a departure from it.
And he decided to have flexible design layout. And if you've seen some pattern file applications,
this should look pretty familiar. And that's one of the aims as well. Like, people who
are, who use cockpit or some other applications using this toolkit could be quite more familiar
than seeing some a bit outdated GTK3 interface in some unfamiliar theming. So as you can
see, it's pretty similar. This is the installation destination screen. We already have some built-in
help support. Like, you can help, you can click on some of the information links. You
will get a dock with help content. This is demonstrating just some simple disk selection.
You can plug in a USB drive already to add more disks. We expect this to grow in functionality
quite a lot for stuff like network attached storage and more complex disk layouts. And
this is the review screen. Right now it looks very similar, but again we expect this to
grow quite a bit because as we add more screens, this should directly proliferate here. And
we are looking into ways how to, for example, visualize more complex storage layouts because
that will be challenging, but it was one of the pain points we got from users so far.
Yeah, this is the progress. This is basically the last thing you will see. Then it will
just tell you, yeah, you are done. So that's it, like, four screens right now. But it's
already producing functional systems. One other outcome of this project so far is a
preview image. Sorry for the long links, but essentially the main information. If you go
to Fedra magazine and type in Anaconda, you will get a bunch of articles about the Web
UI because that's what we are writing about Anaconda right now. So there is a preview
image. The idea is that we will refresh it once every time we add something visible.
Right now it's about like a month old, but I would expect some new features landing in
the next few weeks. So this will be updated regularly. And that's the best you can use
right now to have a feel of how the Web UI looks like. It's a self-contained image that
effectively dumps F37 user space into the machine that you run it on. And please don't
run it on anything production resembling. So we found some challenges, like, working
on this. Yeah, we have a huge amount of functionality. The project is all the current UI has been
used for like nine years. So we are really trying to kind of check what is being used
and what not. So we don't go insane implementing it all. So that's ongoing. We try to identify
and avoid some of the UX problems we have right now. Also, and keeping things consistent.
Like, that's one nice thing about pattern fly. There are pretty nice UX guidelines that
you can apply on many, many things. And that helps to keep the UI consistent. Yeah. Another
issue is like how to run this locally. That's not that easy, actually, because, like, the
Web engines are pretty monolithic, pretty big. And they come with some mainly RAM requirements,
not to mention the image size requirements. And there are actually not that many usable
Web engines on federal. It's effectively GDK, WebKit, or Firefox. And each one of them has
some pluses, some minuses. So right now we are still comparing these two and deciding
which one to use. For remote running, that's kind of not our problem that much. That's
another issue with pattern fly. Like, if we see some corruption, some, like, layout issues,
it quite possibly would affect other pattern fly users. And you might not need to do something
about it unless, unlike if we used some very, very custom Web UI stuff. For the remote running,
another issue is how you actually authenticate the thing, how you encrypt in a useful manner.
So this is still ongoing how we solve that. It might not be pretty, but one way is to
show some certificate fingerprints to the user to show some generated passwords or stuff
like that. Another option is to use custom images. That might be perfect for some cases,
to bother some for others. So we will see right now. The Web UI image you can use right
now is, this is disabled right now, but if you use the inst.WebUI.remote option, you
can actually access the Web UI remotely. But you need to pass it because it's, like, totally
unsecured right now. These mechanisms are not yet in place. So, okay, this is really
in the planning stages and we don't have much time to talk about it. But the main focus
is definitely storage. This will be big. We plan to have something that you can manually
do, something that guides you. And, yeah, it should start landing in the next few preview
image releases, definitely. And, yeah, more screens, definitely. The priority is driven
by the next, the first image we could reply, basically. So right now there is, like, some
date and time work already running. We have some mockups for user and root password configuration.
We need to add the error reporting, definitely, and other stuff. Definitely add-ons. Already
the UI supports them. We need to keep it. And, yeah, I think this is actually, yeah.
So this is, uh-huh. So this is the, this is the last slide. And it's, I think we can start
with the questions just quickly. Like, storage is a big focus. This is a way you can provide
feedback to us about it. And let's start with the questions. Thanks.
Hey, Martin. I don't have a question per se. Oh, yeah. I really appreciate the stuff
that you folks are doing. I tried doing this myself by wrapping Kickstart with Vue chairs,
Flask. And I thought that it would be really feasible, really easy thing to do. But when
I started implementing it, I came to know the kind of intricacies that I was to take
care of. So I'm totally looking forward to what you folks end up doing. All the best.
Thanks.
Okay. Oh, Anakana has now just nice features as escaping to a terminal, for instance, to
bypass things Anakana can't do at the moment. Do you retain the two? Or plan to do?
So the current interface, as well as if you can access the machine locally, it should
still be possible to do anything in the terminal that you can do today. And you should be also
able to use the existing text interface. We won't be changing that.
Yes. But you can escape the web interface, get a terminal, or what is the way to do that?
This is not yet settled. We will include it. But the cockpit project has built-in terminal
emulators. I could imagine this to be included in the web UI. So we might be able to include
it in our web UI as well.
Would be nice if you did.
Thanks for the feedback.
Thank you for the talk. I think this is very interesting. I think it's a good idea. Certainly
convenient to set up headless machines this way. But at the same time, I was wondering,
I think it was Alex Larson who wrote this Broadway back-end for GTK. So basically you
could use GTK and it would output to what goes into a web browser. And it just comes
to my mind, why not use something like that instead? Because I think that if you, we want
to continue to invest in GTK and technical technologies using GTK because we need GTK
for Fedora, we don't really need web for sure. And so if we can end up using GTK and investing
more resources there, maybe this makes it just overall better for the whole health of
the ecosystem. And we get our web UI too.
Thank you.
I must say I don't have really very recent information about it. But we looked at it
a while ago basically at the Broadway technology. It definitely looked interesting, but it looked
more like a demo back then. It could have progressed since then. But I think there have
been some issues like with authentication or possibly performance. So yeah, that's a
good point, but I don't have like latest information right now for it.
I would check.
Okay.
Then you can have all your, you can have the GTK and you have your web, everyone wins with
one code base.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Well, just another question. Before Fedora was 37, we had a discussion about soft rate
installation using the BIOS boot machines and we found a good solution. But and I couldn't
ask currently a bit strange installing software rate on EFI systems because we don't use an
EFI system partition, but a rate partition. Do we have a chance to get that fixed too?
I'm not sure. Like I, like it's not that many people actually in the, in the installer team
and I have been very much concerned and concentrated on the, on the web UI right now for the couple,
last couple months. But definitely if you reach out to us, like we have a mailing list
or we have a metrics channel, I think right now already for Fedora. So please reach out
using some of these channels and we can look at it.
Yes. Oh, you do.
Is it, is it possible to provision the machine from the cockpit because you can already create
in cockpit virtual machines. So it would be nice to be integrated in one place in one
console. Is it possible or do you have such a plan?
I think it's a, I don't think we have like integration for it right now, but that's an
interesting idea. And like we have been thinking for stuff like satellite and some other provisioning
mechanisms that it would make sense to more closely integrate with the install with the
web UI because you could avoid the certificate and authentication issues if you could, for
example, inject something into the image. So that could, that would work like you could
have like create machine or provision bare metal or whatever. And it could like include
some like trust chain, I think there's whatever into the installation around and then you
could then directly connect to the, to the machine. Yeah. We have been thinking about
it, but we haven't yet implemented something like this, but it seems like obvious choice
for some mechanisms and we have integrating it like this with cockpit machines. That could
be a nice idea. So thanks for the suggestion.
Okay. Thanks.
We're at a time.
Okay.
Thank you, Mark.
Thanks a lot.
Okay. Thanks a lot.