Good morning. Wow. I was not expecting this much of an audience at 9am on Sunday at a
Fostem, so thank you all for coming. Yeah, I'm here to talk about how I was at Fostem
five years ago. I told you all a whole bunch of things, and I was utterly wrong so many
ways it's actually kind of amusing. But who am I? My name's Richard. I've been working
on OpenSUSE since it began. I've been a customer of SUSE's, I've been a contributor, a bit
of everything. QA engineer, I've been working there for 10 years now, or almost 10 years.
These days I am a ridiculous advocate of rolling releases. It's what everybody should be using.
I created the micro OS desktop. My day job is being one of the release engineers for
tumbleweed and micro OS. I also do a bit of consulting and photography. But, yeah, a long
time ago in a room actually just on the other side of this campus, I was here at Fostem
telling everybody that, yeah, containerised applications, so things like Flapback, Snap,
App images, the idea that graphical apps in some portable format are absolutely utterly
terrible and nobody should be ever using them ever, and they were going to eat all of our
users, and, yeah, it's just going to be horribly, horribly wrong. And I even started the presentation
with quippy comments, like, yeah, those who don't remember the past are condemned to repeat
it, and I even made really unflattering comparisons. Like, doing diagrams from Windows architecture
and pointing out, you know, Windows has all these wonderful runtimes where you can have
different environments and run your application on top, and, you know, it was absolutely terrible
in Windows. It's going to be absolutely terrible when we do the same thing in Linux. Giving
the examples of all of the security issues that you see in Windows in this kind of approach,
you know, things like security relevant DLLs lurking in some folder in your Windows machine,
you know, being an absolute nightmare to patch and an absolute nightmare to fix when it goes
wrong, you know, all these horrible update issues, you know, how do you end up getting
an update on your Windows or your Mac machine? Well, you download some EXE or some bundle
and then there's some updater in it, does whatever the heck it wants on its machine.
Licensing issues, especially with open source, you know, how do you mix and match all these
different licenses together in one cohesive thing? And, you know, it's just going to eat
up all of your disk space. And then I went back to this slide again and then started
talking about the various technologies at the time, 2017, were out there doing this
containerized runtime stuff and I would compare this lovely Windows diagram to this lovely
canonical diagram, which looks very, very similar because actually it is. The idea is
similar, the concept is similar, but as you'll see, just because the concept is similar doesn't
necessarily mean the whole idea is bad, execution does matter. And it wasn't just snap, I wasn't
just shifting on Ubuntu because I don't like Ubuntu. I was doing the same with Flatback.
And I was, yeah, basically pointing out that this whole containerized application idea
was repeating the same issue. We were going to be going down this road of security relevant
libraries lurking in all of these snaps in Flatback. Back then we didn't necessarily
have a good story about how are we going to update these things, how are we going to keep
them maintained, who was going to look after all of these base snaps and runtimes in Flatback
and the like. Who was going to look at all of the legal issues and review the possible
licensing issues of bundling these things together and who was going to buy everybody
bigger hard disks. And the kind of main conclusion that I left with, which despite the fact you'll
see I was wrong about a lot of what I said, I still actually hold true, is at the heart
of it, when distributing software, doesn't matter if you're doing it as a container or
as a full blown fat OS distributor or anything in between with any kind of fancy technology,
the responsibilities are the same. App image, Flatback, Snap might make it easier to be the
upstream than giving out your application to the users. That's great. But the responsibilities
are still the same that distributors have been doing in distributions for years. You
have to worry about maintainability, you have to worry about the security, you have to worry
about licensing and all this wonderful stuff. So they're going to have to borrow all of
the same stuff. So five years ago I gave this presentation. There was lots of people in
the audience from App Image, Snap and Flatback. Some of them said very nice things to me,
some of them said very un-nice things to me. Starting with App Image, they took a lot of
what I said surprisingly on board and really ran with it. I said all this stuff in February
2017 and by June 2017 I was saying stuff like this on stage. This was taken at the Open
SUSE conference, this was on the App Image website for, well, longer than I wish it was.
But the reason it was because in that short window, App Images thought they could address
most of my concerns by actually obviously running to the Open SUSE built service and
working with the Open SUSE built service guys and integrating App Image really quite nicely
with it at the time. So the idea being, you know, the App Image wasn't the problem, maybe
the way you build App Image is the problem. If you build them in a nice auditing built
system and have the whole thing tracked with dependencies in a built system and you build
it reproducibly and you do all the licensing reviews there, then OBS could be the solution
to all of the App Images problem. And, yeah, they worked really nicely with it and they
gave all these promises. They'd be encouraging people to be using OBS as the main App Image
building tool and we'd all move on happy in a nice unified way forward. And I even said
things to snapping a flat back, like you're falling behind App Image at this point, saying
App Image had a better build story. And they were working with other people and telling
people to be more like App Image. I still was badgering on, by the way, you can tell
all my old slides because they have this thing at the bottom. So you can see old me compared
to new me. I was still worrying a little bit about dependencies because, as you'll see,
App Image makes some really interesting assumptions. But I was, you know, June 2017 kind of hopeful
that, you know, we'd get to a point where everybody would be working together and we'd
have sort of maybe a new consistent run time and things could move forward. I was also
hopeful that we might have sandboxing finally because, you know, Snap kind of had some with
App Armor. Flatback has Bubble Wrap. You know, maybe App Armor would be the way forward.
How wrong I was. So now, five years later, where are we? And I don't want to go deep
down in technical issues too much because a lot of this isn't just technical. We're
an open source project. Any technical issue can be fixed, right? It is a lot about what
are people actually doing? What do they actually care about? Where are they actually taking
things? What are we actually doing? So let's judge people by their own standards. This
is a screenshot from the current App Image website. And it says, use this to make Linux
apps that run everywhere. But they don't run everywhere. And they say, as a user, it should
be as easy to install as it is on a Mac or Windows machine. But they're not. And they
say you don't have to learn all these distributions with all these different distros doing things
different ways. Technically, that's true. You just need to learn all these different
distributions and doing all the different things and you have to build your own to put
in your App Image. And I'm not just saying this to, you know, call shade on them. I have
users on micro OS who are trying to run App Images. And they can't because App Images
require Fuse 2. I'm a rolling release. I haven't shipped Fuse 2 for like a year. I've been
using Fuse 3. And you can't get an App Image to work with Fuse 2. It has to be Fuse 2.
The portable image format that isn't portable because it makes assumptions about stuff that's
on the base OS. And not just, you know, not just weird stuff like Fuse, but even down
and dirty in the kernel. If you're running Debian and you try to run an Electron app,
it's not going to work properly. Because the kernel in Debian isn't built the way that App
Image is expecting the kernel to be running. So this is great promise. And it's going to
work in some places. But only if you're lucky enough that your distro has the same assumptions
baked into it that App Image has. And this is a recurring issue. Even reading the App
Image documentation for building App Images, you know, it tells you as a developer, think
about all of the distros where you want your App Image to run on. So the whole promise
of not worrying about distros goes away. You have to worry about more of them than you
normally would. And put every single dependency which might not be fulfilled by that distro
in your App Image. So, yeah, avoid distros by building a huge one and putting it in a
big table. It's a lot of work. It's way too much work. I utterly respect anybody using
it because they're probably doing more work than I am doing of rolling release. Especially
when the recommendations for what you put in that giant App Image is the oldest, crustiest
stuff you can find. They don't recommend avoiding using anything new because anything new is
more likely to have compatibility issues with older distros. So literally find the oldest
distro that's still supported and use that as your base for building App Image. Which,
you know, also seems a bit of a problem to me because, you know, if you're always picking
the oldest, the oldest is always the first one to not get maintenance updates. So you're
just always going to be rebasing on some crusty old almost out of day LTS to do what you want
to do with App Image. It doesn't make any sense by their own standards. And they tell
everybody that it's installing just like on a Mac. You know, just download the binary,
put it on your desktop, right click it, make it executable and it will run. Which, you
know, 15 years ago that's true. That's how you run something on a Mac. I own a Mac now.
That's not how you run stuff on a Mac. There's not a single Mac application I've ever installed
that works that way. Even the Apple documentation makes it very, very clear that if you're downloading
something from the Internet and you double clicking it on a Mac, it's going to run an
installer. Which is a terrible thing anyway. But it needs to run an installer. When you're
downloading random stuff from the Internet, there needs to be checks for dependencies.
There needs to be some modification to what's on the host. So every random downloaded Mac
application has an installer just like Windows. Or it's done in an App Store where Apple are
controlling all that kind of things and helping that along. So, yes, I was wrong about App
Image. First thing, it was terrible. Because they did try and make an effort. But then
I was wrong again because it's actually even worse than I said five years ago. You know,
they failed to do everything that they set out to do. They don't do anything to address
the actual problems with software releasing. You know, dependency problems are just hand-waved
worse than anyone else could possibly do. Licensing issues, security, maintenance, good
luck. Just build a new distro and ship it again. This is worse than we do in distros
with all of the faults I will admit distros have on this. So please, do not use App Images.
And also they're not nice people. Because they kept publishing this for like four years
after I told them to take it down and I had to threaten to sue them. So, like, they're
just not nice. Now, Snap. Despite my reservations back in
2017, actually Snap was at the time the one I was most optimistic about. You know, at
the time, Canonical were actively collaborating with other distributions. They even invited
me to a Snap workshop. Trying to get Snap supported in as many Linux distributions as
possible. They had an approach of upstream first. They were promising that all of the
App Armor patches and all of the enablement they had to do was going to end up in the
kernel and going to end up being upstream. At the time in 2017, you could run your own
Snap store. You could have your own repository for downloading Snaps. And, unlike Flatpak,
where it's much more just graphical, they also had a story for non-graphical apps. It's
only five years ago, but back then, everybody wasn't necessarily using containers for server
stuff the way we are now. So, you know, it was interesting on all those levels. But it's
five years later. And all of the promises of Snap confinement working everywhere so
you can have your nice sandboxed Snap application hasn't come true. Snap does not support confinement
on most non-abundant distributions and even some abundant distributions. And, you know,
this was posted on their forums three years ago now. That was the case three years ago.
You know, users still waiting to get any kind of proper sandboxing in security with Snaps.
Still not there. And then this was posted this month. Still promising. It might happen.
But it's been five years. None of the app armor stuff is in the kernel yet. None of
the enablement we need is in the kernel yet. Distros can't easily or really at all, you
know, keep with an upstream kernel and get Snap running in the way Snap should be running.
So if you run a Snap on a non-abundant distribution, you're probably running it in an incredibly
secure way. Do you trust that random software deliverable with access to everything on your
machine? Probably not. At least that random software developer using Snap isn't using
their own Snap store because they can't anymore. You know, 2017 you could. Then they released
a new version of SnapD. So now the only version of the Snap store that works with SnapD is
kimono course. So, you know, it's an open source package format. But it's a closed source
delivery format. You're only going to get that software from kimono call. And if you
read up on it, there's lots of examples where kimono call have done the right thing and
handled snaps that were malicious and got them off quickly. But it's like, how do you
know you're just trusting kimono call that they're always doing the right thing because
you can't see. You can't see what they're putting on there. You can't see how they get
there. You can't do it yourself. If you trust kimono call, that's fine. But I'm much more
open source orientated myself. I'd rather, even if I am trusting somebody else, I'd rather
be able to have a look and see what's going on in there. Maybe run my own. Maybe compare
something alongside. And yes, for most developers or at least most small developers, this is
free so you can build your snap and publish it to the kimono call snap store with no effort.
But as soon as you start getting bigger, as soon as you start becoming a bit of an ISV
or doing stuff with IoT with lots of devices, then kimono call want you to have a brand
store. And this is in the documentation for snap craft where it comes to building. When
you actually have a look at the price list for having a snap store, the price list is
kind of dear. Do you really want to be spending at least 5000 euros just to be able to publish
your application on somebody else's server under your name? But I can understand if people
are buying into this, I can definitely understand why kimono call aren't in a rush to change
it. It's probably making them a good bit of money. On open suited, like I said, at the
time in 2017, they were working with us. Now, not going so well. Snap is the only bit of
software in all of my years doing anything, police manager at open SUSE where it's failed
more than one security order. It's the only bit of software I've had to project it multiple
times. And there was good collaboration going on to get those issues fixed. But since 2019,
it's kind of fizzled out. Haven't seen anything since. So when it comes to snap, you know,
I was wrong. I was really kind of keen on snap back in 2017. And these days, I can't
really say that much nice about it. The upstream first promises have all stalled. It doesn't
seem to be an effort to get it really moving again and on other distributions. So, you
know, it's not a portable format by any stretch of any imagination. There's no open source
delivery option, you know, even if the snap store may always be the best way of doing
it anyway. There's a case to be made for that, even if there was an open source way. And
it's not really a viable alternative for something like flatback until, you know, unless you
use Ubuntu, unless you trust canonical, unless you're willing to give them money to distribute
your stuff. And so, flatback. Now, need to kind of do a little bit of a detour on this.
Because when I was talking five years ago about all of this stuff, one of the things
that I was kind of trying to pitch in the side thing there was this idea that, you know,
well, everybody should be using rolling releases. I really, really believe that. And I still
believe that now. And I really think, you know, in this modern age, to get applications
in the hands of users, you know, a rolling base operating system is the absolute key.
You need to have it all built together, need to have everything integrated, built consistently,
tested consistently, and taking the fair share of the maintenance and security burden and
then shipping it all in a way that the users don't really care that everything's churning
around underneath. You know, it just works. And at SUSE, we've still been working on this.
We have an operating system called OpenSUSE MicroOS. Vanilla MicroOS is much more server-orientated.
It's immutable, like CoreOS and other similar immutable platforms. Can't be modified during
runtime at all. It's rolling, so changing snapshots. It's actually using the same code
base as tumbleweed, so every day almost. It's small, but small enough to do the job that
it's meant to do. And the assumption is, you know, that server is going to do just one
job in a data center, so, you know, a VM running one RPM or a VM running containers and then,
you know, as many containers on top, but, you know, the job is a container from the
operating system point of view. And this is working really quite well. In fact, SUSE also
has commercial products based on this. SLEE Micro is based directly on OpenSUSE MicroOS.
The new SUSE app you might have heard of where we're thinking of doing a whole new ecosystem
of enterprise distros. That's building off what we did with SLEE Micro and OpenSUSE MicroOS.
But me, you know, I'm still a desktop guy. So, you know, doing this with my day job,
I found myself asking, yeah, I found myself asking, okay, so I've got this nice small
OS and it can run just one thing. What if that just one thing with a desktop? And so
I started the MicroOS desktop project sort of alongside regular MicroOS. And, yeah, basically
it's a modern Chromebook-like, silver blue-like environment where you have a nice, minimal
base system. My recommendation would be running the GNOME one after the one that's most maintained
with a desktop environment on top. And the basic configuration tools are, yeah, in there,
but everything else is provided by somewhere else. In fact, everything else is provided
by Flatpak. So this is one of the reasons why I'm doing this presentation. I kind of
have to explain how in five years I went from Flatpak is the devil to Flatpak is the only
thing you should be running on your desktop. Because I talked to some of the people that
I was talking to back then and this is kind of their expression. Because five years ago,
when I was talking about this stuff, I was meanest about Flatpak than all the other ones.
I was even invited to Guardek and I gave the meanest talk I have ever given to anybody
right to the people who were actually developing the thing. And the guys from GNOME, they listened.
I wasn't right. I'm not right about everything. That's the recurring theme of this presentation.
But they challenged my opinions, but they accepted at least the ones that actually mattered.
And Flatpak has changed. Like I was talking about earlier, responsibility is the key issue
when you're talking about delivering software. No matter how you're distributing it, you
need to be thinking about dependencies and licenses and maintenance and security. And
one thing that Flatpak does very, very well is basically take all of that away from the
distribution and make it the package's problem. Not great if you're a package, but they do
it in a way that actually probably lowers the burden for everybody. So that's nice.
Automation and technology is great. But really, you know, dependencies become the issue of
the person making the Flatpak. Licenses become the issue there. Maintenance, security, et
cetera. So distros can stop worrying about it. And Flatpak does this very well with their
runtime concept where, you know, if you're building an application for GNOME, you have
a GNOME runtime. If you're building an application for KDE, you have a KDE runtime. Elementary
have their runtime as well. And then for everything else, there's the generic free desktop runtime,
which is a little bit heavier and clunkier, but gets the job done. And back in 2017, this
terrified me. Not because there was competing distributions, because I'm used to competing
distributions. The question was really, you know, are these mini distributions going to
be maintained anything like the one, you know, every other distro out there? Are these going
to handle CVEs well? Are they going to not have horrific licensing issues? Et cetera,
et cetera. Well, they've been doing this for five years now. These runtimes are very well
maintained. These are snapshots from their various Git trees. They're all updating very,
very quickly, keeping up with their respected upstreams of GTK and QT and what have you.
Building CVEs very, very well. I'll talk more about that later. So basically, they're handling
this just as well as any other distribution does. Maybe even better in some cases, because
they're narrower in scope. They've actually got less work to do themselves than a full-blown
distribution with tens of thousands of packages. So you've got your runtimes and you've got
your Flatpak application on top of that, but what about the Flatpak client? Especially
if you think about what I was just talking about with Snap earlier with all of the issues
with App Armor and custom patches and what have you. Well, as a distribution guy, getting
Flatpak in my distribution is really not that hard at all. You need to have the client on
that, but you're not having to worry about a huge chain of dependencies and a whole bunch
of plumbing to get it running. I don't need to have Fuse2 on my distro. All I need to
have is Bubble Wrap, OS 3, and a couple of XDG packages. And they themselves don't really
pull that much in as well. So it's small, it's simple, it's relatively easy, it's self-contained.
Doesn't cause me huge build chains when I have to rebuild the whole thing in Tumbleweed.
It's a really nice ecosystem to just plop on top of my distro and then all of the applications
come from Flatpak. From a licensing perspective, all the Flatpaks on FlatHub are checked. They
all have to have some kind of license that allows open redistribution or legal redistribution.
Or they do also support proprietary stuff. You can get a Spotify Flatpak. But obviously,
you can't have the source code for the Spotify binary in their get tree. So all of the proprietary
stuff has to be pulled through by discrete declared links. And the Flatpak, specifically
the FlatHub team, are checking that, verifying that things aren't changing there, not letting
nasty things happen and binary flip around. So at the very least, you may not know exactly
what horrible thing is in this sandbox, but it's sandboxed, it's not much of a threat
to your machine anyway. And you know it's the one that was sent at submission time,
you know it was the one that was reviewed, you know it isn't changing unexpectedly. So
basically it's as good or as better as any other distribution out there with their native
packages. When it comes to maintenance, basically the same story. Just like OpenSUSE, FlatHub
doesn't like FlatPaks to have distro specific packages or FlatPak specific packages. They
want as everything upstream as possible. They have an incredibly robust build, test, publish
workflow. They're not using OBS, I wish there was. They're not using OpenQA, I wish there
were. But what they're using is just as good, maybe in some ways it's better, they can actually
give everyone nice test channels for testing their application, which I really think I
want to copy sometime. But yeah, it's maintained, it's easy for maintainers to keep their app
maintained and that is all ticking over nicely. From a security point of view, well FlatPak
is the only one that works everywhere. It's the only one that those applications are sandboxed.
The portal concept where you know basically holes are pegged through the sandbox to give
you things like access to the file picker and other parts of the file system and the
like has proven to be secure enough and expandable enough. It's not perfect, nothing ever is.
But it's doing the job and it's doing the job well and these applications are working
very well. And FlatPak CVEs happen very, very rarely. And when they do happen, they're
not these terrifying, scary things because the thing is architected very, very well.
So the last CVE that I could find was in February 2022. It was a medium score, it was fixed
incredibly quickly. I think every distribution had no problem adding that because again,
like I mentioned earlier, given the client is very well structured, you don't have a
huge dependency chain, even the most ancient of OTSS distros can then just happily get
the patch in, get the thing running. So when I started the microS desktop, I adopted FlatPak
some FlatHub, actually November 2017, so if you put the timeline in there, I did change
my opinion quite a bit from the beginning of February 2017 to the end. But I was using
FlatPak as it was the one that I could work with. I couldn't use Snap, couldn't use App
Image. And I didn't trust it that much at the time. I was thinking, like you've seen
with other distributions of building my own FlatPak and using them rather than trusting
FlatHub or doing like Fedora does with they build their own and then they also give FlatUp
with some kind of filtering. But I didn't really want to mess with that at the beginning
of my project doing all of this, so I just opted for trusting FlatHub first and then
waiting for the problems to surface. And it's five years later and I'm still waiting. Like
we haven't had a single issue with the microS desktop where a FlatHub application really
got in the way and needed us to think, okay, you know, we can't trust these guys, we should
start doing all of them. It just hasn't happened. The few times an application hasn't worked
right, well, we send a patch. We work with them because that's how open source is meant
to work, right? So as a distribution guy, I've realized we don't need to be building
these giant humongous, huge code bases, even though that's still what we do with Tumbleweed.
I don't meet myself. I'm purely a microS person now. All of my servers are microS. My desktop
here is microS. I'm using a tiny 1,000 package fraction of my Tumbleweed code base. And everything
else is coming from containers, some of which are built from that much bigger code base.
All my graphical stuff is coming from Flour. And my life is good and I'm happy. And this
presentation is LibreOffice from Flour. So my final thoughts, which I realized I'm actually
finishing a little bit early, but that's good more time for Q&A. Flatpacks are ready for
prime time. The other ones aren't. Don't use app image. Only use Snap if you trust Canonical.
But we're here at Fostem. Flatpacks are the better way to go for people like you who are
here at Fostem. And my system automatically updated in the background. Yeah. Desktop Linux
distros do not need to package the whole world. If you're a distro builder, think about following
the model we are doing with microS desktop. Think about if not narrowing your scope because
you're building the packages and you don't want to tell maintainers to go away, then
at least just start drawing your focus more on just what you need to be doing. Start testing
that part more. Start telling your users that's the bit you can really, really trust and give
some secondary class to the old fashioned way of doing things. Yes. So you are telling
us that Flatpacks run everywhere. Is that also true for different architectures? That is
true at least for ARM, for Z, probably not. But do you really have that many desktops
in the mainframe? Yes, of course. Yeah. Well, then that's something I'm sure the Flathub
team wouldn't mind. I'm sure we could get that working on Flatpack. If there's a need
there, then... Also thinking about a risk drive, of course, and stuff like that. Yeah.
But then that kind of, you know, point actually nicely draws me to my sort of finishing point,
really. None of this stuff is ever going to be perfect. No technology ever is. That's
why we do this stuff in the open. That's why we do this stuff open source. So when things
aren't perfect and aren't the way they are, aren't covering an architecture that you want
or whatever, you know, isn't it better to go to a project that is already going in that
direction that is trying to be available to everybody that is open to me yelling at them
for months about how terrible they are and then work with them to get it all done rather
than sticking in your own tiny little sandbox, doing it all on your own and then being burdened
with it for decades. Like, if you're doing graphical applications, this is the way we
should be going. It's easier for package maintainers. It's easier for distros. It's easier for everyone
to keep up. It's easier for users, too. Nice little web store. They click on what they
want. They can have the beta version if they publish the beta version. It's a nice way
of getting stuff done. So, yeah. Please, if you're doing anything with graphical apps,
please get it on Flattobe. Please contribute to Flattback. Please put Flattback in your
distro. And is there any other questions? Yes, right at the back there.
You've addressed the outstanding question about CPU architecture, which is a great question.
How do you feel about the fact, and I realize I'm asking the Linux question of a Linux distro
container, but how do you feel about the fact that containers tie everyone in the world
to the Linux kernel interface as their interface, shutting out other open kernel options, like
the BSDs, from participating in that ecosystem? And that the overall drive towards containers
is further orphaning these already minimally represented but very, very strong options
in other kernels. They're strong, but I mean, I guess the recurring
point I get to with all of this kind of thing is, you know, niche players are great for
playing in niches. When you're talking about something that needs to have widespread adoption
and or widespread contribution, some degree of centralization does make sense. It doesn't
make sense for everybody to go make their own kernel. It doesn't make sense for everybody
to make their own distribution. I would say it doesn't make sense for everybody to go
packaging their own graphical applications 20 times over. So as hard as it is to say
to somebody who's clearly passionate about other kernels and BSDs and what have you,
I'm fine with containerization and these technologies dragging everybody to the Linux kernel because
that's where the contributions are. So, you know, and as long as the Linux kernel is open
to contributions and everybody can steer it in a good direction, I'm kind of okay with
that. Thank you for your talk. I was with the presentation
of 2017, so I think it's very nice that you changed the fuse. That year I also watched
the presentation about atomic from Fedora. So it was funny how those things interlapped.
I have a question about how you feel about the base system. You see currently there are
trends like Nix and like SteamOS, which use like an immutable image as a base. How do
you feel about that? So I think immutable distributions are the
way to go. Like I think if you're running Linux, it should be immutable. Immutability
does bring with it a bunch of extra questions. And, you know, and for us as geeks, I think
I can say that without insulting anybody in the room, you know, we are keen to tinker
with our machines and of course, immutability quite often can get in the way of that. If
you can't change your running system, how are you going to install that one little thing
that you want? I think there's a sweet spot. And I don't think some of the other distributions
get it. You know, image-based deployments, you know, you've got a frozen image, you can't
really modify that image, or you have to build a whole new one. That's too much work. I don't
like image-based immutable systems that much. Nix has an interesting way with everything
being declative, but it's a lot of hassle declaring everything. It kind of swings the
other way for me, so I don't necessarily like the Nix way. OSTree has an interesting take
on the whole thing, where both from a user's perspective and the fact it's immutable, it's
nice but then you end up with a million different layers of OSTree and it just gets technically
burdensome. Obviously, I work on microOS, I think we found that sweet spot. In our case,
we're using BTRFS snapshots to do all the magic underneath the hood where your running
system never gets touched, but you can still do traditional package management against
a new snapshot and that becomes your next boot target. So you're never affecting the
running system, but you can do whatever the heck you want with your next boot. And then
if that next boot goes horribly wrong, we just throw the whole snapshot away. So it's
super fast, super easy, avoids all of that. You can still tinker with it, but you're not
... Unfortunately, the downside of that is I do sometimes have to tell people don't tinker
too much. The more you do crazy stuff, the more likely you're going to throw that snapshot
away. But I think that sweet spot is better than super lockdown images or complete freedom
of having to declare everything in a config file.
Okay. Thank you for the presentation. I had never heard of Flatpak. On my Ubuntu, I'm
using Snap to install application. And on my Mac, I'm using Homebrew. What do you think
of Homebrew on Linux?
I don't see the point of Homebrew on Linux. Yeah. It's... Yeah. Why? Like I get it on
my Mac, I've installed a few things on my Mac that I desperately need there. But my
Mac, I use for photography. I don't do anything technical on it. So yeah. Don't see the point.
Okay. Thank you.
How likely is it for the files stored in the home directory, especially the user files,
to be accepted if I roll back a snapshot after a failed upgrade?
So yeah. That's a really like micro specific question. That's cool though. The way we do
it on micro OS is when we talk about the root file system, we're not talking about the root
partition because we're using BTRFS. So BTRFS, you have this concept of sub volumes. We have
a sub volume for literally everything where the data should be changing. So Home, Opt,
because that's third party, so it's not us. User local, because again, that's not us.
Anything that isn't the distro is in a sub volume, and then the distro's root file system
is just that last bit that's left. So that bit's read only. That's the bit that's managed
by the package manager. All the sub volumes are freely available and read write. That
does make ETC a little bit interesting, because that's like the one folder where it's both,
like distro's put stuff in there and that. In micro OS we handle that with overlay FS
right now, where yeah, we're basically taking copies of that, knowing what we put there,
knowing what the user put there, or at least trying to, and then merging everything together
so the thing works. Ideally what we would like is everybody to start using, like most
people already are, user for putting in distribution convicts at USR. It should be in user lib
or user ETC or whatever. Just like you see with system D, where distro's put their distro
config in user lib system D, and then users put their local config in ETC system D. That
way works very, very nicely, but meanwhile ETC's a bit of a mess, but a mess that we
can manage. Thank you for the presentation. Why isn't
flatback suitable for CLIs? Actually it is suitable for CLIs. There's actually a guide
now for how to do that. I think the, so yeah, there are examples of apps where they do that,
where the assumption is always probably going to be that it's graphical, but there's no
reason why a graphical application can't start an X term and run a CLI app. There's actually
examples in the flatback documentation of how to do that. Generally speaking, for apps
that might not fit that kind of model, I think a lot of that kind of CLI or more service-based
command-lining stuff, that's handled so well by OCI containers, Podman, Docker and the
like. Why mess with that? You've got all those containers already out there, you've got everyone
building command-line tooling and server tooling in containers. That does very, very well in
that context. It just sucks on the desktop to have flatback that just handles the desktop
issue. You don't necessarily have to have one thing to do everything. So I think flatback
draws that line quite nicely, where it naturally starts getting painful when you head down
that road. Any more questions? No? Well, hopefully I will see you in a couple of years when I'm
on the game. Thank you very much.