Hi.
Hi, everybody.
Yes.
So, talking about debug packages and distributing debug packages.
So, my name is Morten Lindreu.
I go by the nickname of Foxburn on the internet.
I have been a contributor to the Arch Linux distribution since 2016.
I've been doing sort of open source development since, I don't know, 2013.
I do sort of security teamwork, rep-use-builds.
My care is sort of about usable security, supply chain security, and all of that stuff.
And a lot of secure boots.
But today I'm going to sort of talk about what I've been spending over two years of
my life working on, which is debug packages in Arch Linux.
So in...
Let's scale this correctly.
So one of the sort of...
Especially when you sort of get some crashes at some point, you will see this fancy little
sack trace.
And if you use system D, you will at some point have the crash handlers getting you
about seg volts, which happens.
And then you can sort of just debug this with GDB.
And if you do look at the back trace, you just see nonsense.
There's nothing here that makes sense at all.
You can't figure out what happened.
You don't know what crashed.
And you have no idea.
So if you actually do this on an Arch Linux system today, what you'll actually see is
not that nonsense back trace.
You'll instead see...
No.
Let's cross Y.
And you'll instead get this, which has a lot more information.
You'll see what happened, what crashed it.
You'll get all the symbols.
And you did nothing.
You did not download any debug packages.
You didn't think about it.
It just happens behind the scenes.
And if we ask what actually happened, you see that there's some internal syscall that
crashed it.
So this is super nice.
This is a lot better than sort of what the D-Bring experience has been on Arch Linux previously.
And it took me, I don't know, three years, two and a half years, implementing a little
bit on and off.
So why do we care about debug packages?
So if we, for instance, have Pacman, which is a fairly simple and small binary, it's
like half a meg of size if you build it.
But if you strip away all the debug information, you can almost half the size, which is nice.
So if you don't need all of that information on your disk, it's nice to sort of have some
space savings.
And in more extreme cases, like in keypad, had some sole name inside of Python.
It's like half a gig.
And if you strip away the debug information, it's 33 megabytes.
It's sort of nice to have the opportunity to still sort of debug all of this.
And this can all be sort of very large.
So what people do instead is that GDB implements what we call detached debug symbols.
And that allows us to sort of separate out the debug symbols from the binaries and sort
of relink it together on the system.
And one of the sort of key elements for this is this fancy little build ID which gets stamped
into every binary on your system.
And we use that to sort of link, we define the build ID.
We can make some standard directory on your system.
We can split out the debug symbols from the binary, move it to that directory, add some
debug link to the binary, and everything just works.
It will be as if the binary was as the debug sections were still on the binaries.
And this is nice.
And this is sort of what Debian, Ubuntu, Fedora, all of them do to make those debug packages.
And that's nice.
But one of the things that you saw in the demonstration is that you also have the source
code of the binaries.
And that's more of a hack which some distributions have support for and some distribution doesn't
support.
And then Ubuntu does not have source listings, I believe, while Fedora, SUSE, and now Arch
as well has source listings.
And the way this sort of works is sort of you do a little bit of hacking.
So if we build Pacman just normally and we run gdb on it and we ask what the sources
were, you'll have your embedded project path in those binaries.
So what you can do then instead is to use debug edit.
Historically, this has been part of the RPM upstream.
So Pacman didn't want to have a dependency on RPM to support debug packages, which is
a bit weird.
But this was split out now in a separate project back in 2001.
No, yeah, 2021.
Which is now separate project which is quite nice and it makes more sort of accessible
for other package managers.
So instead of sort of using the current working directory to embed stuff, we can rewrite all
of those paths inside the binary to some standard path on the file system.
So in Arch we use source debug and we do them spacing so we can have sources from multiple
versions of Pacman.
And if you sort of do this dance, you'll have rewritten all of those source listings which
is part of the binary.
Which is super nice.
And then you can sort of get all the source code associated with binary.
So before debug edit was available as a sort of normal thing, Pacman also had support for
source listings.
But he didn't use debug edit.
He decided to use awk instead.
So it then tried to parse out all of the file paths, I don't know, from read-off, try to
figure out whatever was there and sort of try to get it out.
And this worked for like simple C programs.
But if you threw like Rust or Go at it, it had no clue what that was at all.
So it was a hack.
It worked.
It was in the source code for six years maybe.
So I ripped that out last year.
So this, yes.
So when these packages get built and you have the debug symbols and have all the source
listings, we can then sort of compile all this to some package and then distribute it
to our distributions.
So all our packages in Arch Linux goes to this repo.arch.org, which is the tier zero mirror.
That's where all the packages get distributed from to all our mirrors.
And on this there's two package pools.
There is from Corn Extra.
There's a package just fash debug pool.
And for community, there's a big community debug packages.
But these are done, it can be fetched and distributed to all mirrors.
But it's a huge amount of packages.
So what we do instead is that we are syncing over this to something called a debug info
instance we have, which allows us to fetch everything of HTTP instead.
So debug info is a very cool microservice which is capable of getting you the source code
and the symbols from binaries over HTTP.
So you don't have to think about which debug packages do you need, which ones you have
to download to get full back trace.
You can just point gdb at this instance and it will just fetch everything for us, which
is quite nice.
So it's written, maintained by ELF, utils maintainers.
Use a web server in C in the year 2020.
So it's running on like I think a few distributions like I think void Linux has one, Debian has
one, Debian and Ubuntu got one past six months.
And there's Fedora and SUSE also has several of these.
So it's super simple.
We can just use the debug info.
We can give it that this is on tar archives that you want to parse and give it a package
for and we just set the debug info URLs variable and then we can run gdb on the binaries and
it works.
That's all you have to do to sort of make gdb read those files instead of having to distribute
them.
So yes.
And then you can have this debug info find command line thing to fetch stuff for you or
you can use it as a library instead.
But yeah, so running a web server in C in 2020 is a little bit iffy.
So we sort of wrote this in sort of system hardener system def file so if something gets
exploited or something happening in that C code, you never know.
It still sort of only really contained to some fairly restrictive set of policies.
So you can't ask for privileges, you can't write anything to the system, but you can
sort of just read stuff, which is quite nice.
So the only really two paths it has access to in production system is just these two
package pools and some cache directory and that's everything it sees.
So that's fairly quite nice.
Been planning to upstream it and I think you've bumped to and Debian uses this as well but
I'm upstreamed it properly yet, sadly.
So you know, we have debug packages, we distribute it, people can use them, but we can also parse
metrics from people accessing this server.
So I spent a little bit of time.
I'm quite sure how this renders.
Yeah, okay, it does not like that at all.
No.
What?
I can't zoom out.
I hate this.
So what you sort of see here is just some basic statistics.
So what people have been doing on it, we enabled debug packages for all our packages fairly
recently this year.
So that's why I see the biggest corpus spike going straight up because we have more symbols
now.
We also see that we reached two terabytes of data being sent out to different users the
past month.
So that's the last 30 days with two terabytes out.
And I can see some statistics on how much data people are fetching, the errors, some
through-bout statistics.
And it's sort of quite nice.
And you sort of get this one free from hosting it.
Yes.
So all of this infrastructure that we put up in Arch, of course, is all open source.
There's no proprietary infrastructure.
There's no hidden files.
So all the stuff we use to distribute debug info is all in our infrastructure repository
under the rules of debug info.
That's sort of how we fetch all of the packages, how we do the service management stuff, and
all of those things.
Yes.
So probably have more time.
So one of the things I also did because, you know, debug packages is usually done on C
applications and stuff, but I don't actually know C. I do Python and Go instead.
So what I also spent a lot of time on doing is to sort of try to get better debug info
support in Go because that's cool.
So here, just to sort of give an example, here we're going to crash the tail scale SSH
client because that's a nice example, I think.
So this instructs the Go compiler to actually give us a core dump.
And then we can use the Delve debugger in Go.
And it actually, with a few patches, is able to read out all the debug symbols, all of
the source code, which is fetched from the debug info server as well, which is quite
nice as it will give us the more opportunities to sort of debug Go applications.
It also works on Rust.
It also works on Julia and whatever sort of programming languages you want, which is quite
nice.
So it's sort of an improvement for the entire ecosystem as well.
Yes.
That was it.
I probably have a lot of time for questions if anybody has any of anything.
There's a question there.
So I'm wondering what you actually store for the source.
Is it the build tree or are you trying to remove some things to save storage?
Because I mean, you have like a package, you have an upstream source, you have patches
on top of the upstream source, and then maybe even the build process might generate sources
itself.
So I don't quite know how, but this is just a binary which sort of generates the source
listing as part of the dwarf metadata, I think.
So this is all the, there's some generated optimized out sources, I think, and there's
some sort of things that points around to different sources.
But it will mostly just be sort of the patched up generated done sources, which gets embedded
there.
So it's the source listing is a nice bonus, but it's not necessarily some would normally
distributing with the binary.
That answers the question.
Yes.
Any more questions?
Thanks for using it.
Could you upstream the system, the surface files?
Yes, it's been on the to do list for a long time.
It's a little bit problematic though, because you need to figure out sort of how the path
paths and stuff needs to get into the service file with some configuration file, but it
can probably be done.
And I think that that people use it as well.
So yes, it should be, it should be fit upstream.
Yes.
Yeah.
So, and we normally hide the HTTP server behind the proxy.
It's written in C++, if that helps.
Yeah, no, yes, it's actually C++ is not C it's the other stuff that's mostly written
in C, I think.
Yeah.
So it's a C++ program that uses lib micro HSPD and SQLite to store our data.
So we have it behind the reverse proxy to sort of get the TLS configuration going and
outside, but we also just wanted the hardening there because it just, it's easy with CSPD
to just get the hardening there.
It's just no reason to sort of knock.
It's just quite nice, but I'll try to upstream it.
Thanks.
Yes.
Are those statistics on your dashboard pulled from, uh, the HTTP server he was describing
or those from like your engine X or whatever proxy you're using?
What sorry.
Are the statistics you had on your dashboard earlier, are those pulled from the backend
or are they from like a proxy in front?
So the debug info has a slash metrics, which is all promtail.
So it just exports a bunch of metrics and you just pull point promtail Prometheus on
it and it will just parse it.
So that dashboard is something we made internally, which I just spent two weeks making.
And that's also open source.
So you can just fetch the adjacent file for the dashboard on the Grafama and everything
there's all sort of open.
So you can go look at it, but it's all, it's just this sort of flash metrics, uh, endpoint
of debug info.
So the red hat people, uh, actually watches this for all the debugging for the servers,
uh, that has been employed and they can like look at the statistics and errors from all
of different servers and see how, uh, the traffic between all of those are, uh, so how
much is, how much is fedora distributing compared to arch and stuff, which is quite nice.
Uh, but that, that was not public.
I think.
It's cool.
Okay.
Can you tell us a bit about, um, the requirements in terms of storage?
Because I recently looked at another distribution and they didn't build all the packages because
of lack of storage.
Uh, so that's what I'm trying to figure out now because we, we enable debug symbols for
all the packages, but they're not currently distributing it to our mirrors.
So arch, the total mirror size for arch is like 60, 70, 80 gigabytes, I think, uh, of
data, but I assume like that would be several hundreds.
Uh, if we actually upload all the debug packages, but I think fedora in total is like three,
four terabytes or something.
Uh, so it's, it, it, I assume it will grow out inside, go inside three, four times and
stuff.
I know like the LLVM stuff takes like, is that two gigabytes package, I think with symbols
and people try to optimize it a little bit so you get a better, uh, this fast to upload.
So it's, it's, it's, uh, it's, it's yeah.
The one sort of main issue with debug edit and sort of debug influence stuff is that
you have a dwarf five has support for compressed sections, but debug edit does not understand
the compressed sections.
Uh, so you have to decompress the sections before you leave out the paths and there's
no good way to sort of recompress everything again.
So getting better support for sort of compressed, uh, dwarf info would sort of help, uh, fix
a few of those sort of space requirements, I think, uh, on the mirrors.
Can I ask another question?
Is there work on data application instead of compression?
Uh, because you have different version of packages as well.
Uh, so it's not that relevant for us because we, we, we don't keep those, uh, versions
and we don't really do Delta files, uh, on the packages.
So on the arch side of things, I don't think that's really relevant for us, but, uh, I
don't know.
It's probably could probably be done at some, some level, at least like, uh, the door, uh,
Debian that keeps multiple versions of the same package.
Yes.
Uh, small question for which architectures are you generating this, those debugging for
binaries?
Uh, so arch only really supports, uh, except the six, six to four.
We don't really have any other architectures.
So uh, but, but because we have, uh, the era, we have the 32 bit port and we have the ARM,
uh, people and I think they're just pulling our packages and probably building the begin
full for them, but arch itself is not really distributing anything else.
Some x eight to six, six to four currently.
So you mentioned different architectures.
Do you know if there's plan to upstream that book in for D and in general risk five, because
I know Felix Yan is working on this.
Yes.
I don't feel he's just working on it.
Uh, we want to, this is more an arch thing, but we don't have built.
We don't have traditional build farm server set up.
So it's a bit hard for us to sort of do, uh, multiple architectures because one package
maintainer has to build that package for each architecture.
So currently want to have support more architectures and better support like, uh, six, like the
V two, V three, V four versions of X that you see now supporting, uh, but you currently
haven't really solved that in a good way currently.
Okay.
Thanks.
Thank you.