I'm Wookie and I have come to talk to you about the year 2038 problem.
I would quite like to get feedback and not talk all the time, which means I have slightly
too much information to give you in the time available.
I will try and get this about right.
So just to make sure people understand what the problem is, time t on Unix is a 32-bit
signed int which started in 1970 and counts in seconds so it rolls over in January 2038,
at which point bad things will probably happen.
That is now less than 15 years away, which isn't very long when you consider the sorts
of systems that will still be running 32-bit code in that time.
There are a lot of other things which will also go wrong at various dates, but I'm not
talking about those today.
Now I don't claim to be a particular expert in this area, but I have been taking a look
at it for the last few months because Debian needs to do something and we should work out
what it is.
So I just kind of try and relatively quickly cover the problem and the issues as far as
we know them.
I was hoping to have done a few more tests before I got here so I could be a little bit
more explicit about things that definitely will or will not break, but we are where we
are and see what people think and also discover from you stuff that you know will break because
I'd like to make a list.
So obviously most people already use 64-bit computers which have 64-bit time to and this
problem doesn't arise for many centuries, but there are still areas where cheap really
matters and those people still use 32-bit, so cars, TVs, kind of embedded controllers
for buildings and heat pumps and plants and all that stuff and also cheap phones.
Talking to people in the business, 32-bit Android is still a thing and will remain a
thing for quite a long time.
The problem is that the stuff that people are still doing that with tends to get installed
and left for a long time.
So 15 years already isn't very long.
We're a bit late.
Quite a lot of the stuff that will break is already installed, well too late, but there
will probably be more so we should probably fix it.
Most of that stuff will be kind of embedded distros like OpenEmbedded and Android built
for the thing.
So the set of stuff using kind of Debian style binary distros that the supplies to is fairly
small but we should probably still fix it.
Some 32-bit architectures don't care because they already started with 64-bit time desensibly.
Big distros, I don't even care about 32-bit anymore.
If anyone wants to contradict me on that, that will be useful.
I'm pretty sure Red Hat's given up already.
I don't know about Fedora and how long they tend to...
Okay, excellent.
Obviously most of the other 32-bit architectures are varying degrees of obsolete but sort of
still in use now but probably definitely not by another 15 years time or at least stuff
that will still be installed.
But I think the one thing that does still exist and is still being used fairly heavily
is ARMv7 and Debian intends to carry on maintaining that for as long as people are using it.
So we kind of have to fix that.
And this problem is harder if you're a binary distro than if you're a source, rebuild everything
every time distro because how does the transition work?
So what has been done so far?
Ant, who unfortunately isn't here, he did quite a lot of work on this starting in 2017
with deeper fixing a load of kernel stuff at the bottom of the stack.
Turns out the Perl people fixed this 12 years ago, although in a slightly odd way of course
because it's Perl.
But the muzzle was fixed a couple of years ago, GLM2 was fixed last year, year before.
And I think quite a lot of stuff...
Because some of those embedded people especially have been building with new muzzle which forces
64-bit time to quite a lot of stuff has been fixed.
But I do not have a good handle on how much stuff still is not fixed and will just break
if you build it with...
It won't even build, never mind work or stuff which will build but it'll just explode your
file formats or eat its old data or whatever.
So again I would like feedback on that.
So quite a lot of people have done quite a lot of work.
Ant tried rebuilding Debian in 2020 but everything was too new and too much broke and he didn't
get very far.
So we've just done it again a couple of times last year and just rebuilding the base part,
that's what I've done and that seems to work.
And doing an ABI analysis, Steve Langisek did a load of work in Ubuntu on how many libraries
actually change which we'll get to in a moment.
So how does this work?
So Glibc 3.34, the way they've done it is to support the old 32-bit ABI and the new
64-bit ABI and each package, you know, you set a magic variable, are we doing 64-bit
or not?
So it's a per build thing.
Glibc doesn't just change.
So normally an ABI transition, you know, you get the new library, it's different, you build
against it, you get the new thing.
So you don't have to do anything.
But with Glibc we were given the choice, it's kind of unhelpful really.
So something somewhere has to set the magic variable otherwise you'll get the old thing.
They have some file format issues as well, the Yutomp and Co files and apparently that's
fixed.
QEMU allegedly is still broken but somebody has a plan.
So just to make this a bit more complicated, Glibc sets file offset bits to 64 if you set
time to 64.
So you have to have large file systems if you're having 64-bit time.
So that's two different ABI changes and that's been around a long time and people have been
fixing it for ages.
Again I don't know how much software doesn't work if you turn large file systems on, doesn't
build, gets it wrong.
My impression is that most stuff has been fixed and is actually using that already.
But again I'm not sure of the numbers.
The GNUlib, if you use GNUlib in your build system it will just turn on 64-bit support
if Glibc provides it.
So if you build with a modern Glibc you'll get 64-bit time to you unless you specifically
set this magic variable you've never heard of to stop it doing that.
So some people have been already bumped into 64-bit time when they weren't necessarily
expecting it.
And the last autocomp release was going, they decided that if you turned large file system
on, you should have 64-bit time to you, either opposite way around the Glibc.
Perfectively that meant anybody who'd ever put in large file system support any time
in the last 15 years suddenly got 64-bit time to you if they re-autocomped, which some of
us thought was a bit radical so we told them not to do that.
But the thinking there was it's time, we should change.
Please will people get a move on.
So it wasn't completely crazy but I think that would surprise too many people I think.
But we do need to work out how are we going to do this without surprise, so people transition
but like when they expected to not because something they hadn't noticed changed.
So the point here is if you use time t in any struct, especially in a public ABI for
your library particularly or any file, then if the size changes, the ABI changes and your
file format changes.
And that is the transition we have to deal with.
Now new ABIs is not uncommon, it happens all the time, libraries change, add new stuff,
we're not adding new stuff, that's okay, but change stuff.
But this is a big one because it affects a lot of packages, but not as big as some we've
done in the past.
File formats I think is harder to quantify and work out quite how big a problem that
is or still is and it's kind of up to each, mostly an application level thing, you know,
if your app stores files and it needs to be able to read its old files and its new files
without exploding.
File formats is a bit trickier, but again mostly that's been dealt with in the kernel,
I believe.
So the fundamental question, especially for Debian, but kind of more generally for everybody,
is are we just going to update the existing architecture with this new feature which changes
the ABI, which is what everybody's done so far.
You just rebuild it with the new 64 bit time and stuff changes, but we still call it ARM
Linux, new ABIHF or whatever in x86 world equivalent.
That's not too bad if you rebuild from scratch every time, it's quite a lot harder in the
binary distro world where we expect to upgrade things as we go along.
And it does change the ABI, so in a sense this is kind of wrong because that triplet
defines an ABI, but on the other hand we do this all the time.
LFS changes the ABI and nobody said we need a new triplet for that.
But from Debian's point of view, arguably a lot of people have said well this is too
big and scary and everything might break, so let's not do that, let's just start a new
architecture with a new triplet and then we'll know it's all done, everything will correspond
and we're much less likely to get random breakage from a bit of half and half time to 32 bit
and 64 bit time.
But on the other hand, other stuff will break just because you've changed the name of the
triplet and stuff, there's always some breakage in there.
The problem is that if we decide we need a new architecture and everybody else has done
it with the old triplet name, now the old triplet name means two different things, it
means the new ABI or the old ABI for in Debian ecosystem and that doesn't seem like a good
place to be either.
So I don't know, if we could all agree what we're doing amongst distro people who care,
that would be really helpful.
But as I said, glibc doesn't enforce 64 bit time t, so if just building against a new
glibc doesn't put you in 64 bit world, something somewhere has to set the magic variable and
the question is, does dpacket do that or glibc do that or gcc do that, I mean it seems to
me glibc should probably do it, but at the moment that's not a thing, we can work that
out.
As I said, a new triplet is kind of easier, we just start again, it gives the opportunity
to call it arm 32 for the rest of the time, which would be a much better name, but you
know, a very small bonus in comparison to how much work is involved.
So in a way this transition is just like any other large transition and we've done it before,
glibc5 to glibc6 was massive and that was like everything had to transition in one go,
Debian was smaller back then which made it a bit easier and it affected everybody, so
everybody had an incentive.
The problem here is that it only really is an armhf problem, but if we have a big transition
with lots of libraries, everybody has to wait whilst that piles up and then goes through
and all the other architectures, proper architectures will complain and go, well you people get
a move on, you've bunged up the whole world.
But we have done this before, back in 2007, apparently long doubles changed from 64 bits
to 128 bits on a whole load of relatively minor architectures nobody cares about, not
now, I mean they probably cared a bit more 13 years ago and the world didn't expect,
I didn't even notice, so it can't have been that bad.
So yeah, so I had a look at some numbers, how big is this problem, is it completely
intractable or not?
I think that's quite an important question.
So six and a half thousand packages out of our 35,000 have time to end them at all, so
that's how big it could possibly be, but an awful lot of that is not in public APIs or
file formats, again I have really no handle on how big the file format part of this is,
but the API part we're getting a reasonable idea, so in the bottom 150 packages that you
make to just bootstrap a system, 85 of those are libraries and 7 of those actually change
with time t, so that doesn't sound too bad.
Steve Langisek's done a very useful bit of work on Ubuntu, up to all 767 library packages,
209 didn't analyse for tedious reasons, weak mobile layer, but of the 558 that did, 17%
of them, i.e. 82, did change the ABI.
So that doesn't sound too crazy.
If we assume the same sort of fraction in the bit that's not yet analysed, there's
maybe 115 libraries or something like that which would need to transition together.
So that's a lot, but it's probably doable.
I've just done some fairly random experiments having built both standard armhf, armhf with
large file systems and armhf with time t and large file systems and just tried putting
binaries in between them, and nothing obviously blew up, it didn't just immediately fail,
so it's not that bad, but I didn't have a good set of things you should actually check,
what are the tests I should run having installed some of this on the old system to see whether
it broke.
So I think we need a list like that to kind of get a handle on how bad that part of the
problem is.
So here's a few things which have been mentioned as potential problems, NFS version 3, apparently
the time there, sometimes it's signed or sometimes it isn't depending on the client implementation,
so some of them won't break for another 150 years, some will.
That'll annoy some people.
I don't know how many NFS people haven't moved to V4 yet, probably some.
X3 is a problem, I don't know anything about that.
XFS was a problem, but I believe that's fixed in kernel 5.10 or something.
CPU was alleged to be a problem, but then somebody else told me that it has 11 octal
digits and therefore 33 bits, so we've got another 150 years before that breaks.
Does anybody know for a fact?
There's a lot of room that shouldn't know stuff like this.
Apparently INN will break, but you know, that's a thing, it could be fixed.
32 bit wine on 32 bit systems with 64 bit time to allegedly might break, but then that's
only on i386, I don't think we care about that, so I'm probably going to ignore that.
So yeah, what else?
Again, we shall come to some questions in a moment.
I'm sure there's quite a lot of other things, but I don't know what they are.
So yeah, it's question time.
I have done that reasonably quickly, excellent.
I would like feedback from people.
So this point about the, are we doing a new architecture or not?
Thinking so far in Debian has been kind of, this feels very big and intractable and we're
not sure how bad it is.
So it's a lot safer to do a new thing.
But having done some research, the research I've seen suggests that maybe it's not so
enormous we can't do this.
So I think an in place transition probably is doable.
There will probably be some breakage, but it'll only be an armchair, so it's like, we could
just annoy those people for a while.
It might eat your files a lot.
I think that's the thing that is really going to piss people off.
If you install a new thing and halfway through, it just corrupts files.
They could be important.
That's not good.
So that's the driver for going, let's just do a new triplet.
But I don't think anybody else wants to do a new triplet because most people have sort
of fixed this with a standard transition within the system and a rebuild.
So I'm not going to say what I think just yet, but I have been developing an opinion
having done this research.
Yeah, I would like to say I would love to get a list of things like, you know, is Dbus
going to break?
Does it have any times in it that's half your things are using new time and the other half
are using old time and Dbus has, well, things like that, you know, IPC mechanisms as opposed
to ABIs.
I think the ABI problem we understand is the rest of it.
I'm a bit worried about.
Yeah.
I'm not quite sure how to get, does anybody want to say anything?
Somebody wants to say something.
Have we got a roaming mic?
Excellent.
Steve, yeah, I see.
Hi, Wookiee.
Hi.
So of course, having discussed about this a bit in the past, this is most complicated
on arm hf, as you said.
It's probably not possible to necessarily change the ABI of i386 because there are a whole
load of old binaries that people will not be able to run anymore.
And the only reason you'd ever care about running i386 is for shitty old binaries.
It's less of an issue, therefore, arm hf, so that might be feasible.
Yeah.
So we need good test suites for all of these things and for good integration tests, as
you say, for either end of IPC and that kind of thing.
I have no idea on those.
I wish I did.
Okay.
I have the same concern about 32-bit wine, which is people care about that for running
shitty old Windows binaries.
Somehow, somehow...
I care about that.
I have some shitty old Windows binaries and that's what it's for.
I mean, somehow Win32 has become this lingua franca of I need an old program to run on
any machine and now, like, if we look at what Valve is doing with Proton, they've just decided,
fine, Win32 is the standard for it.
So I realize there's a difference between Win32 and the architecture that it runs on,
but Win32 specifically, as I understand it, 64-bit wine doesn't run 32-bit Windows binaries.
Correct.
So the thing is, wine already does API translation.
That's what it does, right?
So it seems to me that if the underlying system has 64-bit time calls, I'm not sure it necessarily
can't work with the old binaries.
Oh, that's something I haven't thought about.
I understand exactly how this works.
So I don't know whether, in fact, that is fixable or, as I say, whether anybody cares
enough about i386 world, just leave it alone.
I hadn't thought about the fact that that relies on the Windows time format, which isn't
faced with this problem.
Yeah.
So, yeah, I'm not sure whether it's actually a big deal, just means someone would have
to do some work in some old code that everyone's left alone for a very long time and nobody
can remember how it works.
I also wonder about ARMv5.
There's an awful lot of Raspberry Pi ones floating around the world right now.
Yes.
It's a good point, actually.
Are there any Pi people in the room?
What have the Pi people thought about this problem?
I haven't talked to the Pi people yet, and he's quite right that it's a significant constituency.
I'm not from Rhine, but I remember something about improving their abstraction so that
you can run 32-bit WINE applications on a 64-bit WINE.
So to move the 64-bit, 32-bit translation into WINE so that the native libraries are
all 64-bit, and I'm not sure if that would actually solve the year 2038 problem.
Fair enough.
So we're not sure.
Totally good.
So does anybody have things which they know will break, which have not been mentioned?
People.
There's a lot of software out there.
Because if we don't know of lots of things that will break, maybe this isn't as bad as
the...
Yes.
So you can use this magic autoconf variable that switches the transition to 64-bit time
to off, but you cannot be sure that somebody used, well, maybe an unreleased part of Knulip
into his autoconf code or whatever, and there are lots of exotic build systems out there
where somebody may just say we are using 64-bit time, and then you have some random piece
of software that is compiled in one way and some other random piece of software that is
compiled the other way.
So it's kind of already...
We are already in a mess, and we just need to find the best way to get out of it.
And the other thing that I wanted to say is that...
I mean, I'm...
Personally, I'm...
...who want to keep doing this.
I want to keep some ancient software running with binary compatibility, so...
Yeah, I think, as I said, the big boys just abandoned 32-bit world, so they decided it's
not their problem.
Yeah, I'm also not from wine, but for sure, regarding what I was saying before, yeah,
1.8 is basically going to start to support running on 64-bit, so the 32 binaries, so
that won't be a problem.
Another thing you mentioned, stuff like debus, as well, won't be a problem, because debus
is not a type for time.
It's basically passing numbers.
You define the kind of...
It's not passing time structs around to people.
Yeah, I mean, it's my passing time, but it's not the time type, so basically you define
the kind of...
Yeah, it was a problem.
I don't know how it works, but yeah.
Any sort of protocol like that which was being given structs by one application and taking
them out by another, if they have a different understanding of how big the time variable
is, it won't work.
Yeah, you know, that's exactly true, but I mean, in that case, there shouldn't be a
problem.
Why it might be a problem for stuff like using socket or FDS, that's indeed an issue, and
that's...
Right.
I mean, just to respond to Andrea, the...
I was going to say, no, my brain's failed.
No, that's right.
The fact that people, as you say, already there's a certain amount of randomness in
what's built out there, if we're not noticing a huge number of problems from it, then maybe
it's not too bad, right?
You know, it could be viewed as a good thing, as a good sign.
I don't know.
In any case, when you said that you have to do large scale rebuild and that source distro
is having easy, that's not entirely true because we will also have to schedule for our users
a large scale rebuild.
True.
Easier, I think.
Yeah.
There was someone up there.
There's at least an NTP which has some time of time T and...
Yeah, that's 26.
That runs out.
So actually that's first.
And that may be an even bigger disaster.
Yeah, I further understand that I have time T2.
I need to find that link for you.
Okay, yes, please.
Send me...
If anybody wants to send me examples of things that should be tested, that will be brilliant.
I think is probably the way to do it.
But the other thing that I failed to get onto is there's a list where we intend to discuss
this and produce a plan quite soon.
I think we should do something like this year, whatever the hell it is.
And we need a reasonable...
Some representatives from each...
It doesn't need to be very many people, but you know, the fairly small number of people
who actually care about this problem...
Which you're particularly worried about.
Yeah, I guess that's our time anyway.
So thank you very much.
Thank you very much.