Let me just quickly introduce myself.
My name is Mauro Morales.
I'm originally from Guatemala, but now living in Belgium.
Really like it here.
Just some random thing about me.
The first distro I used was Mephis.
I really liked it when I was going to university and never went away from Linux.
My current daily driver is OpenSUSE Tumbleweed.
I am a Ruby and Go developer, and there are some places you can reach out if you have
questions about the talk or anything afterwards.
I want to talk about how we build Kyros, but for that I need to tell you what Kyros is
first.
If you go to our website, you will see that we sell or advertise ourselves as the immutable
Linux meta-distribution for edge communities.
That sounds like a handful, so let me dive a little bit deeper into that.
What is edge computing?
There is a trend right now into moving the operational aspects from the data center outside.
What does that mean?
That you might have nodes in certain places.
Say you have a grocery store producing a lot of information about all the sales that are
happening, all the different products.
Instead of sending all the bulk of data up to the server and do some processing just
to send it back to all those nodes, what you do is that you do the heavy processing already
at the node.
The only thing that you send all the way to the server is the summary or the calculations
that you are producing in these nodes.
This is useful for doing some machine learning, some artificial intelligence stuff like this.
The thing is if you don't pass all the raw data, first of all you reduce a lot the latency
of the end result because you don't have to pass through the wire all this information.
Second is a lot more private because you are not putting all your eggs in one basket.
For some reason the main data center gets attacked.
They don't have access to all the raw information.
Instead the data is distributed across the different nodes and the only thing that they
might have access to is the resulting calculations for example.
Or even if a certain specific node gets attacked then that doesn't mean they can access the
rest of the network.
It's a very interesting concept that is being formulated right now and Kyros wants to be
a solution for those nodes that are being run there.
How does Kyros do that?
First of all Kyros is immutable and that means that the operating system is read only.
The user data of course can be written but if for some reason someone takes a hold of
the machine they cannot install any packages, they cannot change any configuration.
Even if they manage to do it as soon as the machine gets rebooted you still get the same
original image that you used to have.
If we go even a little bit deeper into that what does it mean that the OS is immutable
because there are for example some cases where the root partition is immutable but some other
areas are not.
Kyros in this case is an image, we distribute it as an image as a whole.
So that means that all the OS components including the kernel and the initRD they are all immutable.
You cannot change it.
initRD is not built at the moment of installation but it's already there when we ship it in
the image.
Let's see another interesting video of Kyros is that it's distribution agnostic or I guess
better said is we are friendly to every other distribution.
We don't want you to lose the distribution that you already like and love for some reason.
It could be that you already have a big know how that you have built onto your distribution
so you don't want to change to a different distribution.
It could be that you already have a licensing that you're paying for a central company and
you don't want to switch that because of costs or something else or it might just be that
your operational team has decided on working on certain golden images and we don't want
you to have to go away from any of these just because you want the goodies that Kyros can
offer you.
Right now Kyros can play well with OpenSUSE, Alpine, Fedora, Debian, Rocky Linux and Ubuntu
and we're trying to add more different distributions on top of that.
Another interesting thing that Kyros does is it tries to be really easy to configure
and maintain.
For that what we do is that we have YAML where you can define the way you want your
system to look.
In this case for example I am creating a user called Kyros with the password Kyros.
I want SSH keys, I want to go and grab from the user modeler his public SSH key and I
also want to put this particular SSH key in text that I want inside of the system.
I also want for example in this case K3S enabled.
As you can see it's very easy to use, it's very easy to keep version inside your Git
repositories so you don't have to break the current flow that you already have if you're
already doing DevOps.
Like I'm saying we want to make it really easy to configure and maintain.
We provide new web UI that was just introduced in version 1.5 for Kyros where you can take
that configuration that I was showing you, you go to a certain node so you look for the
IP of the node.
This is the node has just been booted, there's nothing else running in it, there's no installation
yet in it.
You just go to the IP of the node, you paste that configuration that you want, you say
install and the node gets installed the way you requested.
We want to make Kyros easy to configure and maintain but when you have a machine at the
edge that might sometimes mean that you don't have the person that is in charge of doing
the configuration there physically.
Sometimes you have someone who is maybe not technically that savvy to do the work or that
for some reason you don't have the trust of that.
It could be in this case the manager of the store let's say.
For that what we provide is that Kyros will present itself on installation with a QR code
and then all they need to do is send a picture of that QR code and then whoever is doing
the installation or the configuration can use a command line and then take the configuration
in YAML and also pass the image with the QR code and Kyros will be doing the configuration
itself.
What else?
So, Kyros also performs AV upgrades, what does this mean?
Like I was telling you Kyros is distributed as a full image so whenever we are doing an
upgrade we switch the image completely.
So whatever image you have on active mode that is being run on the system right now
we download the new image for the upgrade and then after we boot we do a transition
in which the new image becomes the active one.
That is helpful because if for some reason we cannot really start that new image there
is still your old version of the OS that can still run, right?
So it's a little bit more reliable we could say.
Of course things can go bad and even if you have your two versions of the OS you could
still screw things up and for that we also provide a recovery partition also in this
OS part which is immutable that you can access to so that you can do manually whatever fixes
you might need to do to one of those two partitions.
Another goodie that Kyros provides is it has TPM encryption so nowadays a lot of machines
or IoT devices comes with another chip generally which can do TPM encryption.
This is useful because you can imagine it's just like having a UB key or I don't know
there are other providers right now inside of your system and that way you can trust
that only this machine for example is the one that is going to be able to un-encrypt
the data of the user.
This is useful because like I was saying if you are at the edge of the network if for
some reason someone steals your hard drive and they put it into some other machine they
are not able to un-encrypt it because they don't have that chip on their machine.
There are multiple facets in which TPM encryption can work I'm not going to detail all of them.
I think if you're interested in that you should check there was a talk yesterday by
Leonard Pottering about TPM encryption was very interesting but it can get a lot more
complex we could say.
You could even say for example that not only you need the machine so the chip with your
data but you also need a Kubernetes approval in order to do that.
It will really depend on your model of security that you want to have of course.
If you put all of these things together we believe that Kairos makes it a great distribution
to be wrong at the edge.
What I wanted to tell you about is now how do we build that kind of distribution ourselves
and for that we use something that we call the Kairos factory and just to give you an
idea of how this works we start by having Linux container images that are provided by
the distributions.
We base our work on the amazing work that the distributions are doing of course.
We don't want to reinvent the wheel.
When we take that container image we pass it through the Kairos factory and as a result
what is at the end is what we call the Kairos images.
Right now we offer two different types.
One is the Kairos core which provides the immutability.
It has an agent which can be used for upgrades for installation and many other things.
It comes with the kernel and the initrd like I was mentioning and we also provide what
is called the Kairos standard which brings everything from the Kairos core but on top
we also add K3S Kubernetes flavor and also Hbpn uses it for peer to peer networking and
Bpn and other things.
The way you consume these ones is we have releases.
If you go to our GitHub page you can download for example an ISO and you can install this
in bare metal or we also have in our docs we have all the different distributions that
we support and links to the OCI images, the container images which you can use for upgrades.
Not only you can use those for upgrades but you can also use them for customization and
this is where I guess it gets most interesting to the people who are going to be using Kairos
at the edge because it's very simple to extend the image that we provide you.
If you're already using Docker which is probably the case if you're used to using Docker files
which is probably the case if you're using Kubernetes well you don't have to learn anything
new.
All you have to do is say the front part you use our image and then you do whatever you
want to do.
For example I'm installing the application figlet and then I just have to tag the version
of the OS that I want to distribute then you can have whatever release cadence of your
own that you might want to have.
Now you might tell me okay that sounds good but maybe I want something a lot more complex
maybe I want to do a release like the way you guys do Kairos standard no problem we
also provide we also have this thing called providers in which we allow you to do a lot
more complex things on the Kairos machine that you are building that's exactly how we
do the Kairos standard that's how we put K3S and HVPN in it and you can basically just
start from any of the ones that we have and build your own.
So that's pretty much the process that I was explaining let me talk a little bit about
the challenges of starting with the different distributions all over.
First of all it's not so easy with the packages because some distributions come with certain
packages some with others sometimes they are named differently sometimes they come in different
versions.
Another problem is that the base configuration is not the same in all the distributions.
So for example we recently had a bug related to QR codes not being easily displayed because
the configuration in Ubuntu was a little bit different.
Another thing that is quite different is the init system right now we only support system
D because it's basically the most mainstream one I would say on the mainstream distributions
and open RC.
That's problematic because we have to maintain two different flows of code right just for
these two systems but it is what it is and we also have issues with the C standard library
like for most distributions that we consume right now they come with the GLib C but there
are distributions like Alpine that comes with Mosul and that makes it a little bit challenging
for those distributions we cannot provide a kernel or init RD from that particular distribution
so if you check for example the image that we put out there for Alpine it will have open
source kernel or an Ubuntu kernel because we need to be able to build it somehow.
So let's dig a little bit deeper now that we know the challenges that we have how do
we try to address them well again starting from a Docker file we in that first from that
you see on the left we put the distribution image so let's say open source is tumbled
with latest and then after that we install certain packages that way we cannot base out
all the different distributions that we have out there so if there are some packages that
are not there in open source we install them or if it's in Ubuntu we install them so that
they are kind of balanced out so that we can do everything that we need to do and we also
do a little bit of system configuration mainly it is about ensuring that certain init processes
get started properly.
Then the result of that we put into container image one thing I want to mention is that
we are agnostic we use any OCI building engine if you're using Docker great if you want to
use spotman great whatever works for you right but yeah we start building that new image
then we install Kyros binaries this can be for example the agent the agent is used for
installation for upgrades and other things we then install Kyros packages this is different
from the distribution packages this is packages that are specific for Kyros they are mainly
for tooling and the really cool thing there is that they are completely agnostic
the OCI building engine so that means that we can be building fedora image and we can
be using packages from open source and Ubuntu at the same time to do this I personally find
that really cool and then after that we do certain system configuration this can be about
how we're going to for example mount the different systems in the disk and stuff like that the
result of it is going to be a container image an OCI image that you can download for like
I was saying because you might want to do certain configuration on top of it you can
use it also for doing upgrades or we pass it through something that we call the OS builder
which will convert that OCI image into an image that you can actually boot and you know
you burn it into a USB and you can put it into hardware or netbooted and of course all
of these changes are prone to issues to errors to breaking things to avoid having that kind
of situation we have a CI system that is ensuring that we can build every one of those distributions
if something fails there we go and fix it before it can be released and once every image
has been built we run a certain acceptance criteria tests like I don't know we're sure
that we can do an upgrade we're sure that we can do an installation of kyros etc etc
yeah and well putting it all together that's how you can have a really nice secure distribution
running at the edge of your network talking to your Kubernetes cluster so if you're interested
into testing it out please you can go to our website there's a lot of documentation there
you can download the different releases try it out you can try it out on your raspberry
pi it's quite fun to do you can talk to us via matrix github discussions and we have
even office hours so every Wednesday 5 30 p.m. European time you can chat to us if you
want and that's all I have for you today if you have any questions please let me know
or by the end if you have any interested in stickers please come and grab one or more