Okay.
All right.
Is Mike working?
Yeah.
All right.
Great.
Okay.
All right.
Welcome, everyone.
I'm going to talk about a program that I've started at Red Hat called Kernel Development
Learning Pipeline that I run with a small group of engineers have as a side project.
So first I'll talk about, you know, what it is, first of all, you know, why it's a good
idea, why we think it's a good idea and we're doing it.
A little bit about the program and some of the growth that we've had in the program over
the past year, two years approximately.
And then conclude with some resources about the program.
So first of all, what is KDLP?
So that stands for Kernel Development Learning Pipeline, a credit for that acronym to Julia
Dedem actually.
And we are building a comprehensive pipeline for Linux kernel talent and low level talent
more generally.
Because as it turns out, it's, you know, there's not a lot of younger people getting into the
kernel.
It's not an extremely popular area of study.
It's barely really taught in school.
So right now the main component is, you know, we have a course that we're teaching at UMass
Lowell and also on the Linux Foundation's platform.
We are trying to recruit interns from this course and from this program and through our
kind of our network.
We bring people in and then they serve as TAs and help develop the course and improve
the content.
And then ideally, you know, we bring them in and recruit them full time.
That's the goal.
So yeah, why is this a good idea?
So like I was saying, a lot of senior Linux kernel engineers are getting somewhat close
to retirement.
That's kind of definitely a much higher, I think, average age in kernel and in low level
engineering at least in the U.S. that I've noticed than in other areas of software engineering.
And it takes a very long time for people to learn the Linux kernel, especially today because
a lot of people don't even learn C in school and they're generally, you know, separated
from a lot of the low level kind of computer science concepts.
Things that people, you know, 20, 30, 40 years ago, so I'm told, were learned kind of as
a standard thing.
Today it's sort of a niche topic.
I mean, there are people getting into it, but you know, only kind of in niche communities
at certain schools, you know, if you're exposed to certain people or certain online communities.
So I mean, the kernel itself is barely taught.
I mean, people take maybe one class in operating systems and a lot of the tools, like some
of the more advanced get usage, for example, that's, it's difficult to learn that kind
of stuff.
Like how do people learn how to do email patches without trying and failing and just getting
roasted online?
It's kind of difficult.
So for a lot of companies, it's difficult to find talent.
I mean, I know, you know, at Red Hat, it can be somewhat difficult to find people who are,
you know, have some Linux kernel knowledge and, you know, are actually interested in
doing it.
You know, there's lots of people who are capable of doing it and just maybe don't like it that
much.
But of course, you know, the way that we're pitching this to Red Hat and, you know, the
way that it's a good idea for any company is that we think we can bring more value to
the company for a lower cost.
But for the community, what we are trying to bring is to train the next generation of
developers from all sorts of different backgrounds, as opposed to just people who, you know, like
happen to bump into somebody at a recruiting event, which is how I got into the kernel.
I just happened to run into somebody at an event that he wasn't even supposed to be at,
in fact.
So a little overview.
So there's kind of three main sections of the program.
So the first is this kernel development course that we've developed that is taught at UMass
Lowell.
So we've created this from scratch using, originally based on the Linux Device Driver's
3rd Edition book, but we've, you know, kind of gone further from that.
That's actually one of the latest books on Linux kernel engineering and it's published
in 2005.
But yeah, so we've been working on developing our own curriculum with a number of different
labs and some slide decks and kind of a whole set of things that people could do to learn
the kernel.
And then from there, we try to bring people into internships as we're able to do that,
or other kind of more second level or hands-on experiences where they can further develop
those skills.
And then ideally bring them in as full-time engineers at Red Hat, or I mean the beauty
of open source is if they get recruited somewhere else or if they go work somewhere else in
the open source community, that's still, that's a win for everyone in the community.
It's a win for all the companies working with the community, right, because everyone working
on the kernel is working on the kernel.
So a little more about the course.
The goal is to introduce students to Linux kernel development.
You know, obviously we can't teach them the entire kernel.
We can barely even introduce them to one subsystem.
But the goal is to teach them kind of what they need to learn, to teach themselves, and
to teach them what they need to know to work in one of these open source communities, specifically
the Linux kernel community, but those skills I think are pretty applicable to other kind
of more niche open source areas that can be somewhat intimidating for a lot of people
to get into.
We mostly just require C language skills.
I mean that's obviously the most important thing when you're working in the kernel.
That's a basic Linux experience, some programming experience in general, but not need a ton
of Linux kernel experience to get started.
But really the most critical thing is C. So we teach kind of an overview of just various
kernel features and subsystems, kind of describe a map of the kernel, what there is, how the
different pieces connect together, how you can interact with it.
We approach through device driver development, that's a good way to get people into, you
know, to work with a lot of the different APIs, because to write a device driver you
need to interact with a lot of different areas and you end up building something that's a
somewhat kind of complete piece that works on its own.
And then we introduce people to more advanced usage of Git.
I mean people may be familiar with GitHub, but believe it or not, a lot of people don't
know the difference between Git and GitHub.
So we help out with that and get them started with email patches and rebases and things
like that.
We also talk about BPF trace and other tracing, which are things that they, I don't think
BPF trace, BPF in general is taught in any school that I know of, at least not in undergrad
courses.
You know, NCSCOPE and other ways to explore large projects and repositories because, you
know, in a computer science program people generally don't get exposed to working on
like large ongoing projects.
You know, you work on some, you know, one and done thing and, you know, then you send
it in and no one else looks at it and you get your grade and you move on, right?
So we're introducing people to work on larger code bases, which is something that's somewhat
unusual for a university course.
So of course all these course materials and the assignments, completely open source.
We've linked it, it's all on our website.
And we're continuously improving it.
You know, the source for the website is also on GitHub.
You know, if anyone has any suggestions or changes, we're always open to them.
So we have undergraduate and graduate level university courses that run on UMass Lowell
that we've created over the past couple of years.
It became kind of a full fledged course in the fall semester of last year.
So it's relatively new.
And this semester we're also running it as a kind of dual program with the Linux Foundation's
mentorship platform.
So we have people applying on there to, I will also talk a little bit more about that
later.
But they essentially run through the course and kind of work with, at the same schedule
and at the same pace as the people at UMass Lowell, but they're from around the world
and they don't need to be enrolled as students.
They can come from anywhere.
All right.
And kind of the bottom line is we try to reimagine how to teach this kind of material from first
principles because it doesn't really make sense to teach it from a typical, like memorize
this and do the exam kind of perspective, right?
The goal is to get people to be able to explain things in their own words and to work on open
source projects and work in open source communities.
So we've replaced exams with presentations where they actually explain the work that
they've done in their own words to their peers.
So from there we recruit people as interns and try to bring them in.
So we find people in the course who are enthusiastic and capable.
So by the time we bring them in to the internship, they also have a lot of prerequisite knowledge
that they would need.
And so they're able to hit the ground running and do a lot more in their three to six month
period or longer than they otherwise would have because actually, so I had a, the manager
who hired me at Red Hat originally as a co-op, he said he didn't like to do summer internships
in the kernel because by the time three months are over, they've just gotten onboarded.
They've just started to understand how to work with the Linux kernel and then it's over
and then they got to go.
So he only really did co-ops.
But the goal with this is if we kind of vet people ahead of time and we give them the
skills that they need and give them kind of, you know, to get skills and they compile
the kernel and they have the background, they actually can get some value from an internship
and we're more likely to bring people into internships who actually want to work in the
kernel and then they're more likely to go off and work in the kernel in general or work
in open source communities.
So we pair them up with real engineers and they work on various initiatives within Red
Hat that are, you know, that are, need people to learn these kind of new and, but combinations
of old and new skills.
But the goal is to train these new people to work in those areas.
So we also bring them in to help with our program and we've had people come in, they
take the course and then they come in and they turn around and then they're TAs and
they work on improving the course.
Maybe they do a couple lectures here and there.
They do some grading and they kind of serve as TAs.
So another thing that we are doing is we have this kind of new kernel devs group within
Red Hat, which I thought I'll just briefly mention.
It's a little bit tangential, but you know, once people get into Red Hat and when people
are working in the kernel, especially in a remote job, which a lot of these positions
are, people get very separated, they get very siloed.
There's not a lot of socialization, so we run a group to, you know, just bring people
together for a meeting with very little agenda.
Occasionally we have a presentation here and there, but just to talk about things and share
concepts and tools and questions and, you know, it's a Red Hat specific thing so they
can ask about specific things related to their job and a place where, you know, there's,
manners are allowed, but it's not a specific structured meeting for a business purpose.
I think people who, you know, you might get that in an office somewhere when you're just
walking around and talking to people, but it's a little bit more difficult to get when
you're in a remote position.
So we also bring interns who we've recruited into that group, you know, and people from
elsewhere within Red Hat who are interested in the kernel and they can ask questions and
find resources and, you know, if they enjoy it, they can switch into the kernel.
There are actually a number of people who are interested and they just don't know where
to start.
There are just not a lot of good resources.
So now I'll talk about some of the growth of this program over the last couple of years.
So first of all, we've partnered with Red Hat's main educational initiative, Red Hat
Academy, which we found out about only through doing this program, but they work with universities
mainly on delivering and facilitating kind of systems management, you know, what do you
call system administration and site reliability engineering, kind of the more, you know, the
standard kind of Red Hat certifications that they do, but they don't have much software
engineering.
In fact, I don't think they had any software engineering component at all, so they were
happy to work with us and, you know, were happy to work with them and they made us these
nice posters, which we have down here if anyone's interested.
Or I guess they're called like leave behind sheets technically, but no.
We also ran a workshop last year for interns, co-ops in Ireland.
And that was just kind of every other week, kind of a casual thing.
You know, over time we had fewer and fewer people, to be honest, but the people who stayed
around really enjoyed it and I think hopefully some of them will end up working in the space
or, you know, open source generally.
Hopefully they, the feedback for them was generally fairly positive.
We've also been connecting to various educational programs in different countries.
A lot of this stuff's very preliminary, but we're hoping to kind of package what we've
done in our course in a way that can be replicated in other places, at other universities, in
other countries to bring people in from different places in the world.
And then we've also partnered with the Linux Foundation, specifically their mentorship
platform, which I will talk about next.
So like I was saying, the Linux Foundation.
So we have just put our course on the Linux Foundation's platform essentially as a mentorship,
but it's the same thing as the course.
We've been worked with Shua Khan.
She's been very helpful.
She runs this Linux Foundation's mentorship platform and, you know, great person to get
in touch with if you're interested in learning the kernel or have questions about this.
She's also a kernel maintainer if you're not familiar.
So we are running the same course, and this is kind of experimental.
We're running the same schedule with the same assignments with a group who are doing the
course for credit at UMass Lowell, and at the same time people who are just, they just
apply it online and they're just doing it.
They're people, you know, just on random continents.
Some of them are students.
Some of them are working.
Some of them are doing, you know, I have no idea.
Honestly, some of them are just probably, you know, having a good time.
But they're doing the same assignments and on the same schedule, and, you know, they
submit their assignments to a different mailing list than the UMass Lowell cohort, but they're
in a shared Discord server and they're interacting, and, you know, we're seeing how that goes.
And it's an extremely diverse group of mentees.
We have people from, I think, like five different continents, you know, people from various
places in Europe, a couple in America, South America, someone in Mexico, like three or
four from Africa, Nigeria, Kenya.
So very interesting group, a couple in India as well.
So a couple of statistics on what we've been able to do.
It's a fairly new program, but I am happy to show some results.
We were able to hire two people full-time from internships who originally did the, went
through the class.
This was during the year that was very difficult to hire people.
There was a hiring freeze, so I think two is still, it's a lot more than zero.
Two people who did co-ops or internships with us were recruited to Amazon at Microsoft,
but one of them liked Red Hat so much and liked working with Open Source so much better
than Amazon that he is pretty interested in coming back, leaving Amazon and coming back
to Red Hat, which is pretty cool.
But overall, we've had seven interns and co-ops who have been trained and have gone through
this particular program via this KDLP thing.
And last semester, we had our biggest class, well, until this semester.
We had 12 students, mostly graduate students, graduate and undergraduate courses are the
same, which I found out, same content.
And we have about a dozen, a couple more than a dozen students this semester.
And the course is actively going on right now.
It just started a couple weeks ago.
And I think about a dozen in the LFX mentorship as well.
And this is by far the most diverse group by gender and location, which is pretty interesting.
So now just briefly some program information.
So the team is, well, there's me.
Julie Denham is the program manager.
I think she's in the chat answering questions if anyone's interested back in Boston.
Charles Maraboule, he's a content lead for the course.
And Dennis Alexandrov, he is an intern who's been extended and also TA.
He's been working on the course since last summer.
Originally went through the course from McGill University.
And yeah, acknowledgments.
I just want to give a shout out to two Red Hatters in particular.
First Heidi Dempsey, the research and innovation director in North America.
She's been a long time supporter of this program from the beginning, from like, you know, before
I was even in an idea, you know, when we were talking about doing something in like February
of 2019.
So her support's been great.
And you know, recommend, you know, doing research and innovation with her if anyone's, you know,
interested in doing that.
And of course Mike McGrath, the vice president of REL, who is the executive sponsor for this
program within Red Hat.
Now a couple resources.
We have a mailing list, which is a link up there, which we pretty much just used for
giving a quarterly update newsletter, which we just started this quarter.
It's read only, so you're not going to get spammed with a ton of information.
If you subscribe to that mailing list, you get invited to a weekly office hour session.
That happens Tuesday at noon Eastern Standard Time, which just for asking questions about
the program or the kernel in general, or you can just send me or one of us an email.
And then on the right, we have our website.
We have a section of our website that talks about the information that's specifically
the structure and content of the course.
We have the page on the UMass Law Catalog that talks about the course description.
So in case anyone's interested in checking that out and the mentorship page on LFX.
Then down there on the bottom right, we do have a crowdfunding page on LFX.
If you want to support the program development and diverse engineers, it's a very, you know,
we'll be able to bring people on through that platform as TA's potentially give them, you
know, bring them on and continue them kind of beyond what we're able to do with just
Red Hat.
All right.
Any questions?
Hi.
I think there is an offer on demand problem.
If you consider every Linux kernel developers, it will be like 1000 JavaScript developers
and also people at the university, if you give them the choice between JavaScript and
Linux, they will have more opportunities going with the JavaScript.
They cannot do a mistake.
However, if they go with the kernel, like I don't know, in my country, for example,
there's a lot less jobs and you have less opportunities.
So what's your opinion on this?
Because people know the choice between like classic software development and kernel software
development.
So if I understand that correctly, you're saying there's fewer jobs in the kernel.
And so, you know, what would I say about just about what was like 1000 to one or something
you said?
Well, I mean, that's true.
But the competition for those jobs is much more intense.
It's much kind of broader, you know, skill area.
I mean, it's definitely, you know, I'm not condemning JavaScript developers.
JavaScript's fine.
It's necessary, you know, the web runs on it for all its problems.
But it's also true that, I mean, working in the kernel, you know, the Linux kernel, there
are fewer jobs, but there are a number of very solid jobs.
And it doesn't, learning Linux kernel skills is somewhat transferable to other areas of
development.
You don't have to work as a Linux kernel developer.
You don't have to, you know, go to Red Hat and work on rel and do back ports or whatever.
You can kind of just do it on your own.
You can do, you know, just some other low-level project and just having knowledge of the kernel
and how it works and the knowledge necessary to work on the kernel, I think, could benefit
people in many other areas and just is an overall boost to people skills that is somewhat
rare to find these days.
So even for a JavaScript developer, if they know how the kernel works and if they know,
you know, behind the scenes, you know, what's going on at a system level, I think that is,
can't be anything but a good thing.
Thanks for the talk.
I have a question about the audience.
So is it mainly targeting students at the college level and then partnering with university
or do you also consider a conversion program like existing software developers that want
to switch to more low-level kernel development?
Yeah, so the course at UMass Lowell is, you know, a course at UMass Lowell.
It's for people enrolled at UMass Lowell.
But the program on LFX, the whole idea of putting it on there is that we could accept
people from anywhere in the world doing anything, students, non-students, you know, U.S., non-U.S.,
whatever.
So any background, as long as they have some knowledge of C, good Internet access, decent
English and a computer, then we can take them.
The only limitation is our ability to grade the assignments and handle that many students
and like the resources that we have to work on the program.
Because this is, you know, for the three engineers and, you know, potentially a couple more people
who are interested and, you know, a couple of interns, right, it's, this is all a side
project for us.
Like, I'm mainly a real engineer.
That's my main job.
Like, this is just a side project.
So we don't have a ton of resources and, yeah, we're basically limited by how much time and
resources we have to run the program.
But we're, yeah, we encourage people to apply from all sorts of different backgrounds.
Okay.
Thank you.
So, back in the day when I used to participate in development of kernel, it required us to
basically build the entire main line.
Your slide showed something with Raspberry Pis.
Is it feasible to build the entire kernel using a Raspberry Pi?
So that originally comes from, we used to do a lot more stuff with Raspberry Pis before
the chip shortage.
It became more difficult to get them.
And then, you know, I think generally, like a lot of the introductory stuff we were doing
didn't require them as much.
So we moved somewhat away from them.
But yes, we did work with Raspberry Pis and we were compiling the kernel on the Raspberry
Pi.
So I was able to do it on the three.
It took a lot of weird tricks.
It took like a day, you know, because I think it was like single threaded.
And on the four, I could do it.
It was a little bit faster.
But if you didn't have cooling, the system would overheat unless you used fewer than
four cores.
But you can do it.
And in fact, you can install Fedora.
You can install CentOS.
And you can install Realm.
Yeah, I know that.
Yeah, all right.
That was my question.
Thank you.
Hey, you had said with the alternate, the non-university route for Doonit, you've got
people here working at the same time, possibly.
I was just wondering, since it's also got the same assignment schedule, what is the
time commitment like for someone trying to get into it that might have full-time work?
What is the time commitment like?
Because it depends how quickly you complete the assignments.
Okay.
So it's...
Well, the lectures are the sessions that we have, which are, you know, on Google Meet,
they're also recorded.
And then we post them.
There are about two of them per week, generally.
And they're each an hour and 15 minutes.
And it goes for, you know, like a standard 12-week semester.
In terms of the assignments, I mean, if you're, you know, I think at the beginning setting
up the environment to send email patches if you haven't done that before and compiling
the kernel.
And, you know, we have one assignment where you write a shell.
You know, that can be...
I mean, yeah, it depends how familiar you are with some of the concepts.
But I, you know, think of it as it's just like same commitment as, you know, maybe medium
to like junior to senior level undergraduate computer science course, approximately.
I mean, that's how we're designing it.
Sure.
Hiya.
Thanks for the talk.
Any of these courses, like I'm curious about backporting and forwardporting stuff.
So when you're doing this course work, are you working on a specific version of the kernel?
Like, yeah, this course is going to be on 6.2.
Because I find that a lot of problems that I run into is, okay, this driver was just
introduced, let's say, in October.
But I need it on 5.13.
So I need to backport it.
And that might be trivial, right?
Might just be copying some files.
But if the API has changed in some way, it can be really difficult to figure out how
it changed.
Because the documentation, to my knowledge, is not great there.
So is that something that you actually sort of discuss in these courses?
We haven't done backporting specifically.
We don't have any assignments that specifically ask for backports.
Because we design them in a way that each student is doing relatively unique work.
So it's kind of, and they're all posting it in a public mailing list.
So we need to figure out how we can kind of either generate assignments or figure out
assignments that are basically, by design, difficult to impossible to cheat in.
And so with backporting, we could figure something out.
We haven't really looked into it.
We talk about Git Cherry Pick and Rebase, and we talk about the background that you
would need to do that.
And I think we may have done a demonstration of it in the course.
But that's a good idea.
OK.
Do you anticipate that recent admission of Rust as a programming language, at least for
driver development in the Linux kernel, will cause renewed interest, especially among younger
talent?
And are you already anticipating for that in the program?
Potentially, yeah.
We've discussed it, and we've heard some people talking about it.
We had a few people who were in the course who were excited about Rust and Rust in the
kernel.
So we have seen some interest in the kernel.
Probably, yeah, it's probably increased interest from young people, I would say.
But personally, I need to learn Rust.
I don't know Rust.
But I'm ready to see it.
Thank you.
All right.
Here, help me to promote something specific.
Do you mind if anyone... Oh, sure.
Yeah, they're here, but people take us with business cards.
Thanks.
Thanks so much.
And then, yes, build it with some sort of a similar challenge.
Something like that, you know, to get a way of that.
But you have to do that challenge.
That was like the way you were asked, you know, if you were
on vice drivers and then you were on the car and you were on
the
patches and actually you were on the flight.
So they were teaching us this since, I think it's not going to be more.
But I think that's a good thing.
I'm sorry, let me get the mic wasn't you?
Oh, okay, yeah.
Yeah.
Thanks a lot.