Hello, folks. Welcome to my talk. I'm Akashdeep Dhair. Today I'm going to talk about Linux
distribution state of gaming. I'll talk a little bit about myself first. So, basically,
I'm someone who has been contributing to Fedora project for around a couple of years before
they taught, you know, the folks who actually help the Fedora distribution as a corporate
entity. They thought, well, I'm not going to leave anyway, so they might as well hire
me. So, the next thing that I find myself doing is actually working as a software engineer
for a team that manages infrastructure for Fedora as well as CentOS. It's called the
community platform engineering team. As well as, you know, just because Fedora is kind
of close to my heart, I mean, it's kind of CentOS at this point in time, but misappropriation.
I work for Fedora council as well as being the objective representative for the Fedora
website synapse team. Gaming has been a prime concern for me, especially having laptops
that don't quite run games. So, the thing that I used to do is have distributions that
can actually have a greater headroom assigned to that game instead of running some fancy
stuff in the background. So, that is what has been the entry point for Linux distributions
for me. So, over the course of last five years, I have written and demonstrated multiple talks,
multiple articles around how to be able to run video games on GNU Linux distributions,
how to be able to benchmark them, and what driver install is to while we're at it. Right.
So, I watched this movie called Zootopia, and there's this fox character that I can't
remember the name of. So, he tells that, you know, the best way of giving a talk is to
ask a question to themselves first, and then answering that question. So, I guess I'll
do that. So, we're going to ask ourselves three questions about the state of gaming
in Linux distributions. The first being, is it popular? The second being, is it convenient
to make happen? And the third being, is it performant? Like, why even consider gaming
on Linux distributions when there is some other consoles, there are other platforms
which are actually willing to do that. So, it certainly is popular. I mean, we can totally
thank our friends at WALB for the Steam Deck and for other people who run a lot of games
on their Android iPhones. I mean, Android is Linux, all right. But then again, is it
the way we kind of want it to be popular? So, there's small asterisks over there. We
have things for emulation. We have things operating systems dedicated for running video
games like distributions like Bartosail Linux, Laka, which runs RetroArch, and nothing else
on the bottom of it. Then there's this thing called RetroPie, which runs emulation stations.
So, if you must have gotten yourself a Raspberry Pi and looked for something in the internet,
some DIY tutorial, it's probably one of the first five things you will end up seeing.
And finally, consoles that actually use Linux on the top of them. Speaking of convenience,
that is convenient. Is it convenient to run Linux distributions for gaming? And you most
certainly will have different opinions regarding the kind of configurations that you want to
do. If you want to tailor-fit your stuff, get the frame rates that you want and the
quality that you need, there are more configurations too, like Bare-Bones Wine, RetroArch, so that
you can tailor-fit your stuff, or something like Android phones or Steam Deck, which can
do that for you. And finally, we have performance. Now, I have seen this over the course of years,
running video games on Linux, those things that are supposed to run on Windows, that
if the games run, well, if they do, they usually end up being 15 to 30 percent more performant.
You can totally find the references in the slide deck if the font's a bit too small,
but yeah, this thing is actually the case. But what exactly is the sacrifice here? Also,
I mean, I can pass through a GPU. If I have this big GPU, I can pass it through virtual
machines and have near-native performances, instead of doing, say, on a hardware that
is totally not okay for a certain game to run. But yeah, why exactly do I have those
asterisks out there? If it's performant, if it's convenient, if it's popular, then what's
with the terms and conditions supply kind of thing that I have over there? And well,
there are things that we're missing out. So one of the first things that we do is it is
popular. People are enthusiastic about it, but less people are enthusiastic about it.
And it's usually the people who would like to spend their hours configuring things, writing
config files, hacking stuff to be able to run some games on their desktop or their handheld
devices that run Linux distributions. And that's barely around 1.38%. And that's the
space about where I got that 1.38% from. It is something that has been going up since
the last couple of years. Here again, we have the friends at work to thank for, for this
team that we are getting increased usage. But a lot of these users are totally going
unaccounted for because telemetry is a big no-no for us. And we definitely advertise
telemetry as something that we should not do. And well, when there are things like Luthrys,
things like RetroPy, RetroArch, then Play on Linux, Wine, these tools are doing the
best that they can do. But guess what? We don't get to know how exactly are these being
used. And as a result, the publishers, they think that, well, Linux distributions, who
uses Linux distributions? Why should we port our games to Linux distributions? Better not.
We might as well create them for other platforms. Well, I won't name any, but with comparatively
higher market share, right, of our consoles. Because guess what? Consoles are supposed
to be for gaming, not for writing code. And then, you know, third-party developers, they
don't bother. They don't really care. They are like, ah, fine. They'll use their stuff
to emulate our games on their platform. They call Wine an emulator. We know the difference.
They probably don't. So I go, have my friends have a conversation with my friends that,
yeah, you play this game on Windows, here's how it can run on Linux. And they're like,
oh, my God. That's too many configuration files. That's too many hours of work. And
all my friends are on Windows. So sorry about that, brother. But I'm going to be at Windows
as well. And the other person, they try installing games. But guess what? It's a multiplayer
game. And it's like, oh, no. We don't recognize this platform. So you're cheating. That kind
of stuff. That totally puts people off. They don't want them to be here, even though they
totally are not. Talking about convenience. It's, well, it's convenient for some people.
The some, you know, I kind of count myself in the minority because I can totally go behind
the screen, do hours of stuff. But for what about others? You know, what about the folks
who just want to spend some time playing games on a weekend? You know? Someone who have a
busy life. So you don't expect them to actually sit behind their computer screens for like
five hours configuring stuff, right? You want them to actually be able to play games on
the get go. It does not quite happen that way for the most parts. Few games work as
it is. Some of them require minimal configuration, like some slides here, some slides there,
maybe some versions of DXVK. But others, they don't work at all. And, you know, you don't
get to know that they don't work unless you spend hours of it banging your head on the
wall, trying to make them work, and then you realize that they really don't. So, the convenience.
Like they follow through steps, but just because the Linux distributions are so fragmented,
we have a certain version of package manager in a certain distribution. There's a certain
way certain rootfs are installed. Stuff like that. So you can't quite expect a certain
steps to actually work on one distributions and to be replicated on something else. There
would be certain steps that would be required in between, and it only comes with experience.
But can we expect experience? Of course not. So people have difficulties with doing that,
and then people don't really want to spend time, and it's all valid because guess what?
People are there to play games, not to become contributors in an open source software, right?
Finally about performance. Right? So one of the things that happens with performance is
the fact that there are games that run comfortably, right? All fine, good frame rates, good graphics,
whatsoever. At the very same time, if you use that same distribution, you thought that,
this runs Final Fantasy. I might as well run Warframe with that. Bam. It won't happen.
It won't even load up, let alone have good frame rates in that. So there is some tailor
fitting required, but that tailor fitting works for one thing, but it does not work
for something else. So you don't have this one size fits all kind of a solution for gaming,
which is sad, but then again, it is what it is right now. And well, there are some publishers
who do not even support these environments. They are like, nope, not this, not that, nothing
at all. We won't let Linux users play our games because that's not how we do things.
And look, people are able to get frame rates. I was able to get a lot of frame rates, good
performance, but there have been times when it has been all inconsistent. The such thing
has happened with my friends as well, using a variety of Linux distributions. So it's
definitely not just for all Linux, but my friends who actually use PopOS because it
allows for having NVIDIA drivers installed from a get-go. So you don't really have to
pop open a terminal and do some crazy voodoo according to my non-technical friends to be
able to install drivers. It just works from the get-go, but guess what? Even they have
some inconsistent performances. And then there are ports that are for Linux, but just because
they are not a lot of takers, here again, telemetry. Just because people don't get to
know that there are actually people playing their games trying hard to actually make them
compatible. People pull them out, even if there was a version at some point in time.
Right. So if all I have are complaints, is it all bad? Is it something that does not
run at all? What is it like? You know, it's quite the opposite. It's not bad. The community
has been doing a great job. If I were to look back 10 years ago, people had to use wine
as it is, right? And it's a tool that gets things done, but then again, if you want things
to be done, things need to be abstracted for you to be able to understand it. And if someone
of a web developer is made to understand the things that go behind the scene, oh, my God.
Then it's totally not worth doing. So there are tools like Lutris, Play on Linux that
abstract the stuff that wine do. So it's a lot better right now than it has ever been
before. But then again, there are things that we can totally do to make things a lot more
better than they are right now. So there's a silver lining. It's a small market share.
People can be unsatisfied with big config files and stuff like that. But here are six
ways that I think, you know, it's all subjective. There can be other things that people can
think as well that I can add my list and make it 60 probably. But one of the things that
people need to understand is if it were really a technical challenge, right, say we have
a lot of people working hard to make these things work. Drivers, no matter how hard it
can be, for the property drivers, the property blocks, the kernel modules to be loaded up,
people are working hard. But people are not understanding how exactly is it affecting
or influencing the gamers, the folks who actually use Linux distributions to be able to play
these games. So there should be some way of open metrics, you know, some kind of telemetry
that is not shady. It does not look through your contacts and understand, oh, this person
reaches out to this at a certain point in time. Not that kind of metrics, but rather
what exactly is the tool, what exactly are the workflows that are used in order to make
these video games work. So these level metrics should be implemented for the developers to
understand that, yeah, their works are indeed worth it. And for the publishers, because,
oh, boy, they think that the market share is small. So in order for the rise in market
share, which has been for the most parts the ones that we get to see from Steam, we should
have more than that. So I don't know if there are metrics in Lutris, bottles or emulators
and I guess there's not apart from the ones that they themselves collect because guess
what, they really want to see if their stuff works or not and how exactly can they improve
their own software. But does it like add up to the entire Genio Linux gaming metrics and
make people understand that, yeah, folks using Lutris, folks using bottles, folks using Steam
Deck, folks using Android, they all combine together as being a market share for this
entire gaming. I don't think so at this point in time, but this is something that we should
definitely consider. The next thing, of course, is to account for feedback and promote participation.
So I have seen in the course of the last many years that if you make people feel like they
are being heard, no matter what kind of project it is, if it's just creating some websites
or deploying things on the infrastructure or be it about gaming, if people are heard,
if the features that they suggest, if the bugs that they tell is bothering them are
implemented, chances are that they will tell their friends that this is some kind of tool
that they make use of and they should make use of as well. And I like to think that reporting
for bugs is also a very valuable contribution. Being empathetic to the users, understanding
by putting themselves on their shoes, what kind of issues that they end up facing. And
finally, understanding the tools that people make use of. If there are a lot of dials,
if there are a lot of drop downs, if there are a lot of things that people have to do
before they are able to run their games, it's probably not the most convenient way of doing
so. So you can't quite expect a person coming back home after a long day to be able to tweak
those stuffs and make them work. So the usability of them, how do we make it more convenient,
should be something that we should look into in these distributions, you know, kind of
streamline the entire workflow in order to make sure that people know where exactly they
need to go to, to get a certain function, to get a certain settings applied. And that's
more about the convenience of, you know, so that people can focus solely on the video
games and not around the operating system that's built for the sake of running games.
Because trust me, if you have a PC, operating system, you know, video games are the one
thing out of thousand things that you will do. So it just makes it a lot easier to focus
on what they want. For convenience, we totally should be able to abstract complex things
when we need to. So customization is fine. It's one of the reasons why we are fragmented
and I'm kind of thankful for it so that I have a choice that I can customize the distribution
of my own kind to be able to make something to serve a certain purpose. But for the folks
who don't need, it's going to be overwhelming. They're going to be really scared of all those
options put out there in front of them and they'll be like, oh, my God, no, definitely
not. And they'll run back to the thing that they were playing games on. So it's definitely
not something that we would want to do. Being able to provide a balance between the two
of them and, you know, organically finding, oh, fine, this person is crawling down the
menu so probably is looking for something that's a lot more extensive than what we are
provided for. Some kind of organic way to find it and to be able to demonstrate how
they can do it is a way that would strike a good balance between the complicated looking
stuff and the people who really want to get their job done as quick as possible.
Finally, for distributions that actually prioritize these tools, these workflows, these applications,
these should be available, like, natively in their own repositories or there should
be a way to be able to install them and not, like, build from source or, like, dot-slashing
them out of the blue because who runs shell-script files anyway, right? You should definitely
read them. Drivers, codecs, kernel modules and things like that, if you don't have a
way to update them natively, trust me, it's really a bad choice to be able to use in that
distributions. Say, people are here to play games, not to build software from source.
So definitely we should consider having all of these things packaged natively. And finally,
to build standard workflows to be able to test and quantify that, yeah, what is good
performance, what is bad. Now, me, I can be really biased towards good performance, even
if I see 60 frames per second on a 165 hertz screen, I can tell that is good, but for someone
else, it's like, oh, no, it's just like one-third of that frame rate. How do you call it a good
performance? In that very case, we need to understand and tell that, yeah, this is the
criteria that was used to tell that, yeah, this video game actually runs and this video
game does not and could use some more work before it's able to be, well, executing the
way it should be. And when we have all of these things in place, probably the publishers
of AAA titles, popular ones like that, will be able to understand that, yeah, there is
some kind of standards used in this fragmented world of distributions to be able to understand
that, yeah, if we follow these rules to be able to create our games, it will have a compatibility
with at least 85%, 75%, I'm saying this on the top of my head, but at least majority
of distributions will not have a problem and you won't be actually told to use a certain
version just because, well, your friend uses it. So let's have a case study of Fedora work
station in the end. Say we have had distributions based on the top of Fedora Linux distribution.
Nobara work station, they have added meaningful additions on the top, so to be able to make
sure that people who really are willing to focus on video gaming, they don't have to
install much stuff on the top of it. And, you know, it's heavily popular with the folks
who develop bottles and looters because they get the latest and greatest stuff in the official
repository, so they don't really have to go out of their way to do so. And then the required
tooling to be able to run these games drivers and the ability to install them from RPM fusion
just in case they are proprietary in nature is totally possible. And the fact that the
GNOME desktop, well, what can I say? It's just one of the great ones. I'm a bit biased.
Say, you know, it totally keeps the workflows aligned and, well, unintrusive. And finally
talking about the consistent performance, well, let's just say that the configurations
should be done in a modular manner so as to make sure that if I do certain thing, I can
copy that stuff and give it to my friend. Here's, you know, you don't have to spend
many hours like I did, paste that stuff and this should be running. Or something a bit
more polished than that, but basically no more repeating of efforts. And, you know,
customizable enough to be actually minimize the footprint of the operating system, distribution
itself, to be able to dedicate more of that performance over to the actual video games.
And that's pretty much about it. I'm totally open to your questions.
Thank you for your talk. I got the impression that you're pushing for telemetry to be used
more. Would that be right? Well, let's just say I'm pushing for an open telemetry. So
you get to see what kind of information is being shared with the folks and what folks
are you sharing that with so you don't think that, oh, it's a shady number of information
and with a shady number of folks that it is shared with, right? So telemetry is important.
There are software that have telemetry like pre-built and they have it natively done,
but then again, it's just a limited set of telemetry people. Once we unify this and have
a place where we can say that, yeah, it's coming from them. So there's something that
we can improve upon in the distributions level so that we can understand that, yeah, a certain
application or an emulator is acting up and there's something to do that we can act on.
Any more questions?
Thank you very much. I think on the telemetry side, there is a fundamental metric that the
developers look at, which is sales. So I think the main thing is like there is a sort of
one to 2% audience on Linux that will buy games. I think that's pretty clear. I think
there are other advantages for developers having Linux users in early. We tend to report
bugs and if we do that in a helpful and non-annoying way, then we can be an asset, particularly
to the trend of people doing early access releases and wanting engaged users. So I think
that's the thing that you can think about supporting early access games, supporting
stuff on itch, I think is helpful. The other side is like if you just want to play games,
by far the easiest thing to do is ignore your distribution, install Steam, Proton handles
the config wrapping around wine really conveniently and the best game of the last five years was
released natively on Linux anyway. So play Slay the Spire. Thank you.
Thank you so much. One of the things that you mentioned that probably we could have
some kind of telemetry done in a central basis and the fact that early access can be something
that we can provide to people using Linux. It's one of the things that we can totally
use to actually increase our market share and make people feel like that it's worth
it if you give it a try and people might end up actually buying it. When it comes to Proton,
I mean, geez, they have done a marvelous job by abstracting what's not important or what's
totally really, really scary, might scare people away out of the room, leave their Steam decks
that they have purchased with their hard-earned money and to be able to play games while they're
on the go. So it's some kind of abstraction that, you know, keeps things convenient that
we are all looking for. And there should be a balance. So people should be like, oh, geez,
it's so abstracted that I can't do anything anymore, right? So that should definitely
not happen. All right, folks, I'm going to give way to our next talk. Please find me
over here if you have more questions. Thank you so much again.