Hello, everyone. Could you hear me well? How do you feel today? Sunday? Did you wake up
with energy? Or you are like... We have energy, right? Okay. That's good. I'm in a book from
Peru. I travel to Europe for the first time for this event. And it's the first time also
doing a talk in English. So if I have some mistake, I hope you can understand this. I
am a technology evangelist at Percona. I started six months ago. It's a really great company
focusing on databases. And if you want to follow me on Twitter or want to connect, I
will be really happy by Ling Ling. So I used to publish things about open source containers,
and I'm from Peru. I am a Google woman touch maker. I was nominated as a doctor. And I
am a container and database enthusiast. So this talk is about monitoring your database
with open source tools. We are going to focus on PMM. How many of you did you hear about
PMM before? Percona monitoring and management. Okay. So it's something new for this room.
And this is a perspective of a beginner view. So this is not something advanced. I will
see this monitoring tool as a beginner perspective because I am learning about databases in the
company where I am working, Percona. So we are going to evaluate why it's important the
value of monitoring databases. Also we will see PMM, Percona monitoring and management,
and how we can effectively see the dashboards and graphs that we can get to monitor and
manage our databases. All this time I was working in a database company, I asked myself,
and I realized the importance is to monitor databases because we can just have one database
running for us. We can have several of them. We can have it in cloud, in infra. So it's
very important and it's why we should ask why we should care about databases, why we
should care about monitoring these databases. And we can ask those questions like is my
database performing well? So as we start to work with databases, there are several queries
that we make. So these queries maybe is not executing in the time that we expected. It
could take more time and it's going to have a bottleneck in the time that we are executing.
So we should care about this and know that there are metrics that where we should detect
the problem for the performance of our databases. Another question that could ask ourselves
is our databases are available and accepting connections. We can have several databases
and many connections could be made, but if we don't put a limit in these connections,
it could just crash. But if we put a limit, also we should be aware when we are achieving
or we are reaching that limit to increase or maybe to stop the connection. But if this
is, we pass the limit, so this is going to be a problem in our databases, right? If this
is an e-commerce company, it can happen because the user is going to wait just two seconds
or maybe one second to go to the next page faster. But if we did this in three seconds,
five seconds, the user is going to go to another page and we lost as a business. Is my sister
Estable? We also monitor the infrastructure where our databases are running, not just
the databases, because it is running over an infrastructure. We are using CPUs, memory,
and we are not able to provision these resources on time. We will be in problem for our databases.
I'm having avoidable time. So if our software is not, if our hardware is not enough, so
our application could crash and we can have hardware failures or network outage. We should
be aware of these metrics to avoid these problems. So we have also can have human errors or these
crashes, these crashes. So there are metrics that we can see to identify this before. So
but we can just see what are the problems when we are having the problems. We can also
prevent these problems, asking these questions. I am minimizing performance issues that can
impact my business. I am able to identify these issues before they happen because there
is a way to prevent. As a previous example, if we are reaching the limit, we can see it
before we are reaching it. So we can prevent maybe provisioning more resources, maybe checking
the query that we already saw that is taking too much time executing. So there are ways
how we can prevent these problems. Nowadays, there are challenges that we have when we
think to monitor databases. For example, the data volume grow. We don't talk about gigabytes
now. We are talking about terabytes or maybe more because the data that the database has
is a lot. It is a challenge to monitor these days. The complexity of the model databases,
right now it is SQL databases, not SQL databases. The database has different models. It could
run in different cloud providers. It could have different models. So the complexity just
grows. Now it is different than before. The data loss, so it is one race that we should
try to monitor, to prevent it. Lack of visibility. If we don't have these things ready to check
it, if we have to do another thing, like maybe create scripts, Linux script or JavaScript
to check it and to get this metrics, we don't have that data on time. We don't have that
metrics on time. But if we have that visibility, it is going to be easy for us to detect these
problems to monitor our databases. Even better, if we have every single dashboard where we
can visualize it. We can monitor many things. But with this, we have different databases.
They can have MySQL. They can have other kind of databases. So it depends on the business,
what we want to monitor, what metrics we are going to get to monitor. But if we don't know
in all these things that we have for databases, we are going to get a lot of things that maybe
we don't need and create alerts for maybe things that we really don't need. We are not
focusing in that business exactly. We should try to focus to monitor, to monitor, we should
try to focus in the business. What's the metrics that are important for us, for our business?
Integration with other tools. So with the time we can do continuous integration, continuous
delivery things. So it increases also the complexity to monitor our databases because
this is not in a single place. This goes over a process that also devolves. Many things
are being automated. Now that we know why we should care about monitored databases,
we will talk about one of the solutions that will help us to monitor. This is Percona Monitoring
and Management, which is PMM. This is an open source tool and free tools, also based in
other open source tools like MySQL. This led us to monitor databases like MySQL, MariaDB,
PostgreSQL, MongoDB. But not just that. As I said before, this also led us to monitor
the infrastructure where our databases are running. It's important to know about that.
And it also helped us to performance our databases, to simplify the management of these databases
and we can exchange the security. Percona Monitoring and Management is built on top
of other open source tools like Grafana. I know many of you use Grafana, right? Who
use Grafana? Okay. A lot. And Victoria Metrics also to establish this data that metrics we
collect for a long time. We are using ClickHose too to create this reports in real time with
all these metrics that we collect in the time. We are using PostgreSQL to establish all the
metadata and all these metrics for databases, all the important data that we have in PMM.
And everything that we visualize is saved in this database set. And we use Docker to
install PMM. We can containerize the installation of PMM, the client and the server and using
in different platforms. We also use Kubernetes for Kubernetes operators for scaling our databases.
There are three levels of when we talk about PMM interface. This is the big one, which
is a dashboard that we all know. But we can go deeper and see the graphs. That is a graphical
representation of the metrics in long period of time. And we have the metrics also, which
is a countable number that represents some value, some important value of our infrastructure
of our database. Okay. As I tell before, what we want to monitor is going to depend on our
business. We are not going to monitor the same metrics as another business. It depends
a lot of that. And we also should be aware of the layers that we create that should be
focused on what we do as a business and create these alert and notifications that could be
notified when we need it. So it could be integrated with Slack, with many other tools that we have
in the hand to know when the problem is happening. Exactly. So important metrics. Some of that
that we can check it with PMM, high CPU, high memory usage, and this high disk EO part of
the infrastructure, the amount of user connections. We can know when the data grow and other kind
of metrics that we can have. Could somebody tell me what other kind of metrics we can
check it with PMM? With some monitoring tool? A part of the infrastructure or? Okay. We'll
check. If we see the long query response times, as I say, some queries could take some time.
PMM has a very good dashboard, which is this. It's come query analytics dashboard where we can see
for a specific we can see all the queries that are for our databases. In this case, I'm seeing all
the top queries that are running in our databases. But also we have an option to check it here if we
want to check for my SQL for Postgres or MongoDB. We will see the amount of queries per second,
for example, that we are running and how time is taking. So if we open this dashboard when we are
working in databases, the first thing that we are going to see is, okay, this query is taking too
much time. In this case, no. But if we have a query that is taking too much time or is running a lot
of queries per second, we can see the first one and we can start the troubleshooting from that point.
The high CPU utilization is part of the infrastructure. Also, it's important to know how
is this going. For example, this dashboard in PMM, in Percona monitoring and management,
we can see for a specific note, we can check a note because we can have different notes running
in our infrastructure. And in this case, for example, we have 25% of our disk that is using.
This may be not a good example because I checked it last 12 hours, but we can check our disk usage
during six months or more and then is when we can see and take decisions. Let's see if this is like
six months, we are using just 25% of our disk. It could be a problem because we have a lot of
infrastructure that we are not using and we are wasting money, right, because of this space that
we are not using in six months. We can reduce our CPU and save money. High memory usage is this
dashboard where we can see the amount of memory that I have for my databases and also can see
what is using for Kakache, what is being used, what is going to be ready to be free. This is good
because we can also see when we are reaching the limit of the memory and we can take actions to
provision another disk. We can say that this is very easy when we are working in cloud because
just we click in a button and say, hey, provision another disk or increment the memory, but if we
are working in an infra, maybe in a private cloud, this is hard because we have to prepare the
logistics to get another disk, another memory is going to take time and have this kind of
visualization helps. The amount of input output that we make in our disk, you also can check it
in this graph. We can see that this is your latency here. How is in this case is stable,
but we can have light peaks to see where we are detecting these problems. User connections, as I
say, it helps to monitor the number of active database connections and size it appropriately,
put limits in our connections for our databases. We have in this case MySQL connections. We can
see that for other databases, too, but in this case it is also stable. We are going to have spikes
when we can see that we are working with a lot of transactions on our databases and we can take
actions with that. In this case, the maximum of connections allowed is 151. We are in 150. If
this is going to be 151, this is going to alert us. You have to check this. So, data grow also. We
can see a dashboard where we can see where our data is a lot when we are inserting a lot of
data in our databases or we are just removing things. So, in this case, it is going to show
when my database start. It is not like too good to see it here, but if I have time, yes, I still
have in time. Still have in time? You are right. To show something, to show the dashboard. I have
time. Yeah. Okay. Okay. If you want to try it right now, we can check this PMM demo per con
graph. You can enter. Right now we are going to check the dashboard. But what we learned now,
it was why some aspects that let me think what we should keep away and monitoring our databases
and also how to explore PMM, which is an open source tool, is available there. You have to
double and start to check it and explore it and it is easy to visualize things. So, we are going
to check now PMM. You can also enter to this link. So, it is free to experiment. Let's see.
It is going to open. Yes. This is the dashboard that we have. We have several notes that we can
choose here. A lot of them. So, it depends on the database. We have notes of MongoDB, MySQL,
Postgres, and MySQL proxy also. We can check the details for a specific time. 12, 4. It is not
enough maybe for some things. But maybe six months, three months, we have a lot of things here. So,
we also can check things about the system operator. I don't have access right now to see that. But we
can also register alertings for this. In this case, we have three databases that are being
monitored for Postgres. One of that is the database for PMM itself. We have nine databases in Mongo
and 15 databases in MySQL. This is a good thing for PMM because you can see everything in one
single dashboard. We can go deeper for each note or for each database as you want. This is all.
Thank you so much. If you have some questions.
Thanks a lot for the interesting talk. Does anyone have questions?
Hi. Hello. Good morning. The query monitoring dashboard, do have some advices on how to
perform these queries, the bad queries, the slow queries? So, how to perform the bad queries,
the slow queries? How to rewrite them? Yes. If you go deeper into that query, you will open
another dashboard where you are going to be able to see suggestions. You are doing something bad
here and you can fix it with that. Thank you for the talk, first of all. One question regarding
the PMM query analytics. Is it possible to filter by connection and not by database? I want all
queries from one connection instead of... Is it possible? Yes. You can have just one connection.
Okay. Then we have to talk. Yes. Thank you.