Hi everyone, my name is Francisco Laniel and today I will present you Inspector Gadget
an EVP-F based tool to observe containers.
So first of all, what are containers?
Containers permits you to run applications isolated from each other.
So on the figure on the right you can see that there are actually three containers and
three applications A, B and C.
To isolate and run those applications we rely on a container engine like Cryo or ContainerD.
The container engine will ask to the operating kernel, to the host operating system to create
containers for us.
So contrary to virtual machine where you have a guest operating system and an host operating
system all containers here share the same host operating system.
So container engine will ask to the kernel to create two containers but sadly in the
Linux kernel there is no structure used to represent a container like you have the task
structure represent a task there is no such structure.
Instead the container relies on several features provided to you by the kernel.
To have security isolation you will rely on the name spaces.
For example with the moon name spaces each container will have its own set of file and
for example container A will not be able to access file of container B except explicitly.
To isolate this time resources you will use the C group.
So you will be able to dedicate a resource to one container.
For example with the memory C group you will be able to limit the memory footprint of a
container.
For example you will set the limit to 2 gigabyte and if your container allocate and try to
touch 3 gigabyte it will be out of memory.
So containers are really cool because they permit you to isolate different workloads.
Sadly using them pose several problems particularly when something is wrong and to debug them.
First it is harder to attach debugger to a running application.
You can still do it but it is not as simple as running gdb and running things locally.
Also you will need to take into account the communication between different containers.
Nowadays it is in the command to explode your application into several microservices.
For example if you have a website you will have maybe one container for the web server
and another container for the database engine.
So you will need to be sure that those two containers communicate otherwise your website
will just do nothing.
To do so we developed Inspector Gadget which is a Swiss Army knife based on EVPF.
It comes with actually two binary local gadget.
The first one to debug locally running container and CapCutter gadget which this time focus
on containers running in Kubernetes cluster.
So on the figure I will show you the different tools offered by Inspector Gadget and which
part of the kernel they permit to monitor.
The first type of gadget we have are the tracer.
The tracer will basically print events as they are going on the standard output.
So for example with trace exec you will be able to trace the call made to the syscall
exec.
With trace moon you will be able to monitor the call to the syscall moon which can be
pretty useful when you need to mount volume.
And for example with trace out of memory key you will trace when the out of memory killer
kills one application.
Then we will find the profile get the profile category.
So for example the profile category you will make it run for a given amount of time and
with profile block IO you will get information or getting the distribution of your input
output.
Then you will find the snapshot category which will give you some information on the system
as it is running at time t.
So for example with snapshot process you will be able to get all the processes which are
running in your containers or you can also get this information for your whole Kubernetes
cluster.
Then you will find the top category.
So the top category mimic the top command line interface tool as it will print ranking
on information which will be actualized each second.
So for example with top file you will get information regarding the file that are the
most accessed.
Then the last category is there is only one gadget in this category and it is trace loop.
Trace loop can be seen as a trace but for containers.
So you will be able to monitor all the syscall done by your container.
Okay so before going into the internal architecture of inspector gadget and what is eBPF I will
show you a small demonstration to compile local gadget trace exec.
So the tool to trace exec syscall made by container running locally and exec noob which
is an already existing eBPF tool.
Okay so we will first create a test container.
So the test container will execute sleep periodically.
And then we will now trace the new processes creation using exec snoop.
So exec snoop is an eBPF tool based and made by IOVIS or BCC people.
So as you can see there are two types of sleep.
There is one sleep point three second and one other sleep point five second.
Sadly in my container I only use point three seconds.
So the point five is done by the host.
And I'm not interested at all at processes running in my host.
To do so I will use local gadget to trace the same type same types of events.
But this time I will be able to get only the event inside the container.
And as you can see we will get the same information plus the name of the container whether event
occurs.
Okay so before going into the internal architecture of inspector gadget what is eBPF?
According to Brendan Gregg eBPF does to Linux what JavaScript does to HTML.
It permits you to run mini program which are safe into a virtual machine inside a kernel
which will be run only on some particular event.
For example disk IOV.
Sadly the eBPF program safety comes at a price.
You are kinder limited.
For example you cannot have an eBPF program which will have an infinite loop or not statically
bounded loop.
Also there is no function like malloc or cameloc so you cannot allocate dynamically memory
but you will see that there are some possibilities to cope with this limitation.
Okay inside the canary we will find two software components which are related to eBPF.
The first one is the verifier.
It will take as input your eBPF program and will ensure that it is safe.
If this is the case it will end your safe program to the just in time compiler.
The just in time compiler will basically translate your eBPF bytecode to the machine code and
it will install it to be run on some events.
When you want to develop an eBPF program you will write it in a syntax which is almost
that of the C you will then compile it using clang and the target eBPF to get an eBPF object
file.
So this eBPF object file will contain the eBPF bytecode.
You will then include this eBPF object file into another program running in the userland.
So to do so you can use your favorite language.
You can use C, you can use Golang.
There are plenty of possibilities.
So you will use this program and you will use also maps, eBPF maps.
eBPF maps are data structure related to eBPF.
It exists plenty of different type of map.
You will get one eBPF map to represent array, one eBPF map to represent key value store.
You have several possibilities.
So when you want to load your eBPF program into the kernel you will mainly use a library
related to eBPF like libBPF in C or cLUM eBPF in Golang.
So your eBPF program will be loaded into the kernel through the BPFC score.
It will be verified.
If it is okay it will be just in type compile and installed to monitor some event.
We will do the same with the map because for example we will be able to use the map to
either share information between several eBPF program or between kernel and userland as
our eBPF program are run into the kernel.
So now let's say that I have a process which called the x-axis call.
Then our eBPF program will be executed.
It will write some information into the eBPF map and thanks to the library I will be able
to read this information and print it for example to the standard put and then deal
with them in userland.
Okay regarding local gadgets the main component is the local gadget manager.
So the local gadget manager at each time maintains a container collection so it knows perfectly
what are the running container in the system at a given time.
Indeed we rely on run-fanotify to add container to this container collection where the container
are created and to remove them where they are deleted.
We are also able to start some inspector gadget tracer like the one to trace the exact system
call.
So when we decide to start tracer for example the one to trace exact syscall we will not
directly load the eBPF program.
We will create a particular eBPF map that we will use to store information regarding
our container of interest.
Indeed the eBPF program will be executed each time an event occur and we need to do a filtering
regarding this.
In the first demonstration I was only interested into events occurring inside containers and
not on the host.
To do so the eBPF map will contain the moon namespace ID of the container which interests
me.
So when I will run my eBPF program we will install the eBPF program and basically we
basically compare to the eBPF code of the exact snoop that I presented into the first
demonstration.
We took it and we modified it to add this filtering.
So basically with this code snippet we will get the moon namespace ID of the current
task and we will compare it if it is present into this map or not.
If it is not the case we just do not care about this container and we just do not care
about this task because it is not in our container.
If it is the case if the moon namespace ID is inside the container we will continue the
execution of our eBPF program because we care about it.
So now we will show you a more realistic world demonstration of local gadgets particularly
how to use it to verify second profile.
So okay we will create an nginx container with a ccomb profile installed.
So ccomb profile is a feature of the Linux kernel to allow or disallow the call of some
syscall.
So okay I will create it.
I wrote by hand the second profile that I gave to Docker.
So okay let's create it and now let's query the nginx server.
Yes some mistakes maybe I forgot to add one syscall into the second profile.
So I will stop the nginx container.
Now we will start local gadget and I will start local gadget on a container on one particular
container the nginx container.
Note that it is perfectly possible to start the local gadget with a given name with a
given container name even if this container name does not exist at the time because it
will be added automatically thanks to the container correction and rank for notify.
Okay I will now run an nginx container but without any second profile I will call it.
Now I will stop my container.
It will automatically stop local gadget.
Now I will just compare the two second profile the one that I wrote and the one generated
by local gadget.
Okay I forgot the same file syscalls so it can maybe explain some few bugs.
Okay let's run again the nginx container with this new second profile.
Okay now it's the moment of truth let's call it.
And yeah everything is okay so yeah basically local gadget really helped us to verify the
second profile that I wrote by N and more than that it can generate for you second profile.
Okay so I told you about local gadget and when I presented you first inspector gadget
I told you it comes with two binary local gadget that I already presented and cap cutter
gadget.
So cap cutter gadget is designed to monitor containers inside Kubernetes cluster.
So on the figure I represented a schematic of Kubernetes cluster so on the left we have
the developer laptop on the right we have the Kubernetes cluster so we have one node
for the K for the Kubernetes control plane and we have one worker node.
First of all we will need to deploy an inspector gadget pod on each node to be able to monitor
the events occurring on this node.
So we will create a diamond set Kubernetes will deploy then a inspector gadget pod on
each node of our cluster.
Then we will want to trace a specific event for example the execsys call so we will use
the cap cutter gadget trace exec command we will ask to the control plane to create a
trace CRD so trace CRD is a custom resource definition which is proper to inspector gadget
and that we use mainly to start and stop tracer.
So we will have also a trace CRD per node like we have one gadget pod per node.
So we will create the eBPF program on the associated map we will install it into the
kernel the eBPF program will be executed if there are some code to exec occurring on our
node those events will be written to a perf buffer a perf buffer is a specific type of
eBPF map I said leading that have the time to enter into the details so we will be able
to read this information from userland and the events are will be published to a stream
to a gRPC stream we will then use cap cutter exec to read the gRPC stream and so the information
will be printed on the developer laptop.
So I will show you a more realistic example about how to use cap cutter gadgets to verify
the container capabilities so just before jumping into the demonstration the capabilities
are another feature of the kernel to limit what your application can do.
So again time for the demonstration.
So this time I will deploy an nginx web server with some capabilities set so here is the
list of the capabilities so for example you can see that there is the sysadmin capabilities
which is not forcefully capabilities you want to but it seems nginx needed to run so you
did not have the choice okay so I deployed it and suddenly it seems that there are some
mistakes so okay let's get some more information okay operation not permitted okay if I have
an operation not permitted it may be because I forgot one capability into my deployment
okay so on the bottom I run the cap cutter gadget trace capabilities so as you can see
I just want to get capabilities which are used in the namespace demo because it is the
namespace where my nginx container is and so the big difference between local gadget
and cap cutter gadget is that cap cutter gadget will give us information regarding Kubernetes
so for each event we will get the node where the event occurred the namespace the pod and
the container it is really aware of the fact that it is running inside Kubernetes so okay
I deleted my deployment I will run it again okay we were in the world demonstration for
the beginning okay so during this time if someone has quick question or if there was
one point but wasn't clear I can take it quickly okay everything was clear until this moment
so perfect
okay let's delete our own I've used deployments now can take a bit of time because it is in
Kubernetes so yeah compared to when running locally need to take into a communication
with remote services so okay okay now I will deploy my nginx deployment again and so we
will get the information directly so as you can see we have the name of the capabilities
and when they are used and we have also in this column if it is allowed by the kernel
or if it is denied so all the above capabilities were allowed and the shown capabilities was
denied yeah I think I forgot it in my deployment file so I will just delete my deployment file
again yeah there is a lot of back and forth but sadly I do not think we have a lot of
choice
yeah again if there is quick question during the deleting and the redeployment of the whole
thing yeah I can take it and so I will update my deployment file to add the capabilities
that I missed okay let's deploy it again and just cross the finger that it is the last
time yeah let's wait for everything to be to be ready
also a bit of time so okay should do the trick and anyway I do not think we can wait faster
so okay everything seems to be ready now we will get the IP of our pod we will now kill
it and now it's the moment of truth and as we can see we get nginx default message so
everything was fine I just forgot to add one capability in my deployment file so it's now
time to conclude so as I show you during this presentation inspector gadget permits to monitor
containers both running locally with local gadget and both and running in kubernetes
cluster with cap cutter gadget it is of precious help to debug this application I really like
to use gdb but and any kind of debugger but in the case that I show you it would be not
so helpful particularly because if you run gdb for the second profile you will just get
an error number and it will not be so helpful and the same with the capability example we
will not be able to know why the syscall failed we will just know it failed with the neural
number but kinder hard to say it was because of the missing capability so as a future work
we plan to improve the scaling of inspector gadget because I has told you we use cap cutter
exact to read the gRPC stream and sadly doesn't scale very well we also plan to add a new gadget
and as inspector gadgets is an open source software if you have any idea of a gadget or
if you want to contribute one I will be really happy to see your contribution and to review
it so you can find us on our website inspector gadget dot io we are also on github so and there
are the inspector gadget organization and we also have a channel in the kubernetes slack
so inspector gadget so yeah if one day you use inspector gadget and there is something that you
do not understand please just feel free to come to the channel and ask we will be really we are
here to help you and it will be real pleasure to chat with you so I thank you all that for
your attention and if you have any question feel free to ask thank you thank you very interesting
talk I would like to know I've seen that you were deploying the agents as a demon set so you were
running it in all the nodes I was wondering if you can just tailor it to one single node because you
know that the current workload that you want to check or the current pod you want to check is there
second question would be I understand that this is really good for for debugging environments
would you do you think that this would be ready if you had an incident or something going on that
you want to investigate in a production environment okay just to be sure that I understood correctly
your question you were asking precision when I deploy the inspector gadget pod I deployed it in
each node in the kubernetes cluster and so you wanted to know if it is possible to not deploy it
on each node yes perfectly there is a and related to that when you're running the the comments from
your computer does it apply to all nodes at the same time or can you tailor also to just go
target it to one node or something you can you can target one node so you can basically you can
filter by several you have three possibilities to filter you can filter by node you can filter by
namespace and you can filter by pod name even container name and of course you can mix all of
this I was a bit quick regarding the demonstration on this but yeah you have yeah you can do a lot
of filtering so yeah so you can do you can deploy the inspector gadget pod on each node
and then filter by by node name but even though if you know that there is one specific problem
occurring on one particular node you can deploy the pod on only this specific node we had we have
an option to do so with capture gadget deploy to only say to specify which node you want to deploy
it thank you you're welcome thanks for the talk again I am just wondering if you can send the
metrics to grafana or something to do the filtering and the querying around is that possible
so just to be sure you asked if I can send the metrics to grafana yeah that raises that okay
so we plan to we we're actually developing it a lot and we are actually working on it a lot and
we plan to add an exporter to Prometheus all right but yeah it is still I would not say working
progress but thinking in progress all right yeah but nonetheless nonetheless we have a lot of
things to do with this but nonetheless if you are really interested into uh primitives I think
there is only if you go to the inspector gadget repository they will be you know on the right
there is uh used by and so there is a project which does the exporting to primitives but this
is not us we developed it and we plan to yeah there is a there is a lot of thing that we want
to support all right thanks
then I think we're done oh one more question
yeah I have a question regarding this demon said that it should be
installed on the kubernetes nodes is recommended to it like keep it there always or just install
when you need to debug it then remove it back I'm sorry can you please repeat it this demon set
on the kubernetes nodes is it recommended to keep it there for always like or just install for
the back and then remove back in in the diamond set if I can
this remote component
no so basically the question was about when I deploy the inspector gadget pod
if it is recommended to have it running it for a long time or just shortly no clearly you should
not have run it you should not have it running for a long time as we install evpf program we
need to have some privilege and we need for example the capsis admin and all this sort of stuff we
cannot use the user namespace which were which was added recently in kubernetes so no you just
deploy it you collect the mature you collect the you monitor the events you want to monitor and
then you just redeploy it so and deploying its specter gadget is as simple as deploying it is
one common line interface call and you are done so yeah just avoid it having it running for a long
time it's it is a tool to debug so it would be like if you run your application all the time with gdb
attached to be kinder so yeah no is there a measurable performance impact on of having the
agent deployed in your cluster since it's measuring all these things so you are asking about if when
we monitor event if we have a decrease in performance right so not so much and it would
be related to the whole evpf as evpf program are run into the kernel you do not have you know
context switch between userland and kernel learn so it is kinder as quick and you avoid having a
big decrease in performance okay thank you you're welcome then i think we're done thank you thank you