So, I'm going to give you a round of applause.
Welcome our next speakers and give them a round of applause.
APPLAUSE
. Can you hear me? I guess you can.
Hello, everyone, and welcome to the session about how we can use
open telemetry on Kubernetes to collect traces, metrics, and
how we can use open telemetry on Kubernetes to collect traces.
So, my name is Pavel. I'm a software engineer at Red Hat.
I'm a contributor and maintainer of open telemetry
operator and the EAGLE project.
My name is Ben and I'm also working on the open telemetry
operator and spent most of the time on open telemetry.
And so, as I mentioned on today's agenda, there is the open
telemetry operator. We will show how you can use it to
deploy the collector, how you can as well use it to instrument
your workloads on Kubernetes.
And after this brief introduction, we will walk you
through use cases, how you can use it to collect traces,
metrics, and logs. However, I will start with the history of
open source observability. I'm doing this because I believe
that if we understand the history, maybe we will better
understand where we as industry are going.
So, on this slide, you essentially see a timeline with
the open source project. And it's divided into the upper
and bottom parts. In the bottom, you see the open source
projects or platforms that you can deploy, and they provide
you with the storage and visualization capabilities for
the observability data. Most of them work with distributed
traces, however, some of them, like the Apache sky walking,
hyper trace, and signals, those are more like end-to-end
platforms that can show traces, metrics, and logs. I would like
to focus on the upper part that shows you the open source data
collection kind of frameworks. And what we see there,
especially with open sensors and open telemetry, is that it's
becoming more important that these frameworks kind of work
with all the signals. For me, the data collection, especially
for tracing started with Zipkin project. It gave us a stable
data model that we as developers could use to export traces
into Zipkin, but as well to many other kind of platforms that
adopted Zipkin project. As a developer, when we wanted to use
Zipkin clients, because the ecosystem hosted client
libraries as well, it was a bit problematic in polyglot
environments because those clients were using inconsistent
APIs. There was no standardization. And so this
problem then was partially solved with open tracing. The
scope of the project was a bit wider. There was a
specification, there was a document that defines which
data should be collected, and as well how the API in those
languages should look like. This enabled us to build
reusable instrumentation libraries. And then you later
open sensors project started with slightly different
approach. There was no specification, there was no API,
but there was SDK that everybody could use and a collector.
So with open tracing, the approach was that developers
would use the API and then at the build time provide the
SDK from a vendor. With open sensors, everybody would use
the SDK, and then the collector decides where the data should
be sent. Those two projects were kind of competing, and then
finally they merged into open telemetry in 2019. So the
hotel, it adopted all the pieces from open tracing and open
sensors, but kind of the biggest innovation in hotel is the
auto instrumentation libraries or the agents. Those agents
are production ready, most of them, because they were
donated by one of the observability vendors. So they
are production tested. So when we kind of summarize what
happened is that we started with some instrumentation
libraries, we started with a
project, and since we have some kind of standardization, we
could build reusable instrumentation libraries and kind
of create more sophisticated instrumentations for run times.
And now we are in an age that we have available in open source
agents or auto instrumentation libraries that we can just
grab, put into our platforms, and we will get telemetry data
from our platform. And I think, you know, so where are we
going? I think we are going into an era where we as developers
we won't have to care about how the telemetry is created for us.
It will be the instrumentation will become maybe the feature
of the platform where we deploy the application. So this is one
way to look at it. The other way might be that the
observability will shift left, and since we have this data, we
can do a lot of things. So we are going to look at the
observability and the
observability of the platform. And we will be utilizing it for
other use cases, probably like testing and security.
So with that, I would like to move to the open telemetry.
And it's obviously open source project hosted in the
community computing foundation, and its main goal is to provide
vendor on neutral telemetry data collection. It's the second
step. And it's a very large and there is several independent
components that we can use. There is a specification that
defines what data should be collected and how the API should
look like. And obviously then there is the implementation of
the API, the SDK and the standard data model called
OTLP, or open telemetry protocol. These four pieces are
meant to be used primarily by instrumentation authors or, you
know, the user-based
system. And the last two components, the auto
instrumentation, or agent, and collector are meant to be used
by end users to kind of roll out observability in their
organization. To facilitate open telemetry deployment on
Kubernetes, there is a helm chart and Kubernetes operator.
What I would like to stress is that open telemetry is only
available in the open telemetry
collection. It's not the platform that you can deploy.
It doesn't provide any storage or query APIs.
So now let's go to the main part, the Kubernetes operator.
The operator itself is a go-long application. It uses
kubebuilder and it has three primary use cases. It can
deploy the open telemetry collector as a deployment,
for instance, it can also install your own
workload. It can also install your own workload,
or instead of a stateful set, it can as well inject the
collector as a sitecard to your workload. The second use case is
that it can instrument your workloads running on Kubernetes
by using those instrumentation libraries or agents from open
telemetry. And last but not least, it integrates with
and split them across the collector instances
that you have deployed.
To enable this functionality, the operator
provides two CRDs, one for the collector that
is used to deploy the collector and integrate the primitives.
And the second one is the instrumentation CRD,
where you define how the applications should
be instrumented.
The operator itself then can be deployed
through manifest files, home chart, or OLM.
So what we see here is the Kubernetes cluster.
There are three workloads, pod1, pod2, and pod3.
The first workload is instrumented with the auto-SDK
directly.
So when we were building this application,
we pulled in the auto dependency,
and we compiled it against it, and used those APIs directly
in our business code and in the middleware that we are using.
The second pod is using the auto-instrumentation libraries
that were injected by the operator
through the admission webhook.
And the third pod is using Zipkin instrumentation and permit
use instrumentation libraries.
And it has the collector sidecar as well injected
by the operator.
So essentially, the operator there,
it reconciles three open telemetry CRs, two 4D collector,
and one instrumentation.
And then all these workloads, they
send data to the collector deployed probably as a daemon
set.
And then this collector then does some data normalization
and sends finally data into the platform of your choice, which
can be permit use for metrics and the algorithm for traces.
With that, I would like to move to the second part,
explaining the CRDs in more detail.
Yep.
I think the microphone should work.
Yeah, so with the CRDs for today,
we wanted to show both of them.
And we start with the collector one.
The collector CID is a bit loaded.
So therefore, we picked a few things here,
which I would say are the most used or important.
So as Pavel mentioned, there are different deployment modes,
different use cases for the open telemetry collector.
And in this specification, we can go to the mode
and just specify it there.
There's a handy thing, which is the sidecar.
We would see it afterwards.
But if we want to use it, we only
go to the part definition of our deployment
and inject the annotation we see on the top right.
And if we go to the part definition of our deployment,
if we go with the deployment mode or something like this
and we want to expose it for collecting matrix
locks and traces from a different system,
for example, we can use the ingress type.
We can set there a lot of more.
We configure there a lot of more, like also the annotations,
your ingress class.
But yeah, mainly the operator takes care of everything,
creating services.
Also is able to balance your load there.
And the last thing here is then the image section,
which is also important.
With the open telemetry operator,
it usually shapes the core distribution of open telemetry
by default. So in open telemetry,
the collector is split into two repositories when you go up
and look at that GitHub.
So in core, you will find OTLP, a logging exporter,
so some basic stuff.
And in contrib, you find basically everything.
So if you want to send your traces to some proprietary
vendor or to Jager, you probably need to look there.
OK, the next thing is then the configuration.
The configuration for the open telemetry collector
is here provided like it's usually
done for the collector itself.
So it's passed directly forward.
It's split into three parts here.
We see the receiving part there.
We specify our OTLP receiver.
Here it accepts GRPC on a specific port.
It could also be there that we specify a parameters
receiver, which is then scraping something.
Then the optional part is basically the processing part.
We might want to save some resources,
and we batch them our telemetry data.
And yeah, there are other useful things.
And on the exporter section here,
we use the logging exporter, which
is part of the core distribution.
But you can configure whatever you like.
You can also have multiple exporters for one resource.
There is one thing.
On the right side, we see the extensions.
It didn't fit on the slide, so it's there in this box.
This is then used if you have, for example, an exporter,
which needs some additional headers.
You want to set a barrier token or something else,
you can do it there.
And then finally, we go to the service section
where we have different pipelines for each signal.
And then we can then configure a processor and receiver
and exporter in the way we want it.
So then there is another CD, which
is used for the auto instrumentation.
And it looks slightly different.
So here we have also the exporter.
In the specification, we have the exporter.
And the exporter only exports OTLP,
so which means if we want to export it to some backend
of our choice, we usually instrument our application
directly then for what this traces to a collector instance
which is running next to it.
And we can use the power of these processors.
Then we can configure some other useful things,
like how the context is propagated and the sample rate.
And to use it, it's also quite easy.
So we have our deployment.
In this case, we can choose from this list
of supported languages.
We might use Java.
And we only set this annotation on the pod level.
And it will take care of adding the SDK and also
setting and configuring the environment variables.
If we use something like Rust, we
can also use the inject SDK path annotation
to configure then just the destination
because then the SDK should be there.
And if we have a setup where there is,
let's say, some proxy in front like Envoy,
we can then just skip the adding the auto instrumentation
there by only configuring the container names
we want to instrument.
And we will see this in a minute a bit more in detail.
So this is then basically what we would need to do.
So we create this instrumentation CRD.
We add this annotation.
On the left, we see the pod, there is our application.
And in this gray box, you see what automatically is added.
And this is then forwarded in this example to a collector.
And how does this work?
So the operator in the admission webhook,
he will add this init container.
On the top left, we see how the container looks before.
So there are no environment variables.
It's just a plain application.
And in the command section, there
is then the copy, which copies the Java agent
to our original container.
And on the right side, we see the final result.
We see the Java tool options where the container is loaded.
And then we see all these environment variables
to configure our SDK.
And finally, what we have seen also in the presentation
from Nicholas previously, we have here the Jaeger output.
So we can see the resource attributes
and all the beautiful stuff that comes with it.
So next, we have a look at metrics.
So there is the open telemetry SDK.
So if you want to go with open telemetry metrics,
but I assume a lot of people have already
some parameter stuff in place.
And the open telemetry operator also helps us with this.
So we can make we look first on the receiver part on the bottom.
We see there we configure the parameters receiver, which
has a scrape configuration.
And there we can, for example, add some static targets.
So we assume we add three different scrape endpoints.
Then afterwards, if the target allocator is enabled,
this will then take these scrape targets
and spread these targets across our replicas, which
are then responsible for getting the metrics.
And yeah, that's basically how it works.
There is also an option to enable parameter CRs.
So we can then forward to this one.
And the target allocator, which is an extra instance created
by the open telemetry operator, will then
get the targets from there.
So we see this here in this graphic.
Quite good.
On the left side, we see pod one,
which is using open telemetry.
And it's pushing the information telemetry data.
It gets directly to a collector.
And in this gray box, we see there
we have two instances running instrumented with permittoys.
And the collector one and collector two
are pulling the information from there.
So this is all managed then by the operator.
We have seen the replicas.
This is basically collector one and collector two.
And since we enable the target allocator,
we get the targets from there, so which is then
coming from the pod monitor.
And finally, we send the information somewhere.
So the last thing here, the last signal are then locks.
So for locks, there are different options.
So the first one would be to use the open telemetry SDK,
what we might don't want right now,
because we need to do some work.
But if we directly want to go ahead,
there is the file lock receiver.
We can configure it to get the information from disk.
And yeah, it's available in the Confrib repository.
And we have different parsers there,
which help us to move the locks into the OTLP format.
We will see in a minute how this looks like.
And there are other options if you
want to integrate with Fluent bit.
So there is a forwarder, so you can use it
as a kind of a gateway then.
And yeah, the only thing we need to do then
is we can configure it as a daemon set.
We need to pass our information there.
And the file lock receiver, for example,
can then get all the locks.
And how does this look like at the end?
So this is when we exported the locks to the logging output,
so it's done it out.
We see that we have the resource attributes, which
are added automatically.
And yeah, we see then the lock information.
And on the bottom, the trace ID and span ID,
which are not given if we read it just from disk.
But that's it.
Then we are almost at the end.
Thank you.
Thanks a lot for the interesting talk.
Does anyone have questions?
Any questions?
Raise your hand.
Question?
Yeah, there we go.
For the logging part, would you suggest
to replace any kind of cluster logging with fluent bit,
or that's sending it off to a low key or something
with an open telemetry log scraping?
Or is that complementary?
So I'm not sure if I fully got it.
So you want to?
Well, we already used like file being
to replace it for the logging part of the cluster.
And then we see that this is just
one of the ways to do it.
Yeah, in this case, it's just another way.
But the useful thing is if you have the open telemetry SDK,
it will automatically add then the trace ID to it.
And then you can correlate your signals.
Sorry.
So I'm super newbie to this.
So I fail to understand how the open telemetry is
trying to replace, for example, the log
parsers like the telegraph, for example,
which is able to generate promethyose metrics
by log scraping.
Also how Zipkin, which is the tracing thing,
fits in the metric collection of all this picture.
So I'm not trying to understand how you couple together
all these sources and how open telemetry either replaces
or either makes it easier to use all these technologies
together.
Thank you.
Yeah, so maybe on this slide, you
see that the third part is using the Zipkin and promethyose.
And the collector can receive data in Zipkin format.
It can scrape promethyose metrics,
then transform this data into OTLT or Zipkin as well,
and then send it to the other collector.
So the collector essentially can receive data
in multiple formats, transform them
to the format of your choice, and then use that format
to send it to other systems.
Hello, and thanks for the talk.
I'm just wondering what's your strategy of filtering health
check requests, for example?
Or the life probes requests that you get on the pod?
Health checks like to avoid generating traces
for health checks?
Sorry?
To avoid generating traces for health check endpoints?
Yeah.
That's a very good question.
So you could maybe configure the collector to drop the data.
But I think the best way would be
to tell the instrumentation to keep
instrumenting those endpoints.
To be honest, I'm not sure if this is implemented
in OTLT agents.
But I saw a lot of discussions around this problem.
So probably there will be some solution.
We have time for one last question, if there is any.
No?
OK.
Oh, no.
Then thanks a lot.
And I'll see you next time.