Thank you.
All right. Hey, everyone. My name is Owen. This is Kavi.
We're going to be talking about Loki today. This is a project
that's very near and dear to my heart. I've been working on for
a while. But I believe it's actually the second FOSDEM top
on the subject. First one right here by Tom, 2017 or 2018. So
I'm going to talk about how Loki works a little bit differently
than a lot of things that came before it. And what some of
those tradeoffs look like and why I think that's an advantage.
And then you can also learn some of the tips and tricks that
we've learned building cloud native distributed systems that
need to be up all the time. And maybe you can incorporate some
of that into your designs later. So we are both going to be
talking about how we can build a cloud-native distributed
system that can be built into the future. And it's going to
be a pretty good tool for that and to your designs later.
So we are both engineers at Grafana labs. We work primarily
on Loki, the open source project, but then also do a
bunch to make sure it runs as part of our SaaS. My move and
this is Kavi again. And you can find the project here. This is
So we both build and operate and run the software.
I use Loki every day to debug Loki.
And that's a kind of a labor of love,
but it comes because we get paged a lot.
Well, not a lot.
I actually shouldn't say that on the, you know.
But we do get paged, and so we are very empathetic
to that fact.
This was actually the last time I was here in Belgium.
This is in Ghent on top of the Gravnstein,
which is this castle.
This is not staged.
I actually did get paged here.
And so this is actually using Loki
to figure out what was wrong
with our hosted version of Loki itself.
But this is my first time here at FOSDEM,
and it's been a lot of fun so far.
So thanks for having me.
So this was actually coined by a friend and colleague,
Ed Welch.
Loki's a time series database, but for strings.
This is effectively how Loki works at the end of the day.
And so the first off, we'll jump into figuring out
what exactly a time series database is.
All right.
So yeah, what exactly is time series database, right?
So if you think from the normal database,
all you always see a key and value, right?
And in time series database, surprise, surprise,
you have timestamp.
So what you see is for every unique identifier,
you have array of records or tuple,
whatever you wanna call.
So on each record, we'll have a value
under timestamp attached to it, right?
So in this example, as you see,
so for this identifier, you have a value V0,
a timestamp T0, and value V1, a timestamp T1,
so on and so forth, right?
So this is the mental model we want you to,
like, yeah, I mean, keep in mind throughout the talk,
so that you understand some of the decisions
why we made the way we are.
So to see this in action, right?
So this is how it looks like in Prometheus,
and this is how it looks like in Loki.
So what is identified here is a unique combination
of this, what we call label set, right?
Here it's app equal to nginx, cluster equal to us central zero.
So this is like a unique identifier,
which has this list of records.
And as you can see, the only difference
between Prometheus and Loki here
is the type of the value, right?
So in the record, you see timestamp, comma, value,
and the value is floor 64 in Prometheus,
which is 34.5, you see here.
And in Loki, it's a string.
It's a log line, you ingest into Loki.
So that's what, when we say Loki is a time series
for strings, that's what we mean.
So yeah, it's a log line there.
And so we definitely take or steal
or however you want to put it, a lot from Prometheus itself.
And this is actually what this looks like
in terms of how we index and store data.
We're gonna talk a lot about indexing in this talk
or particularly the lack of indexing.
So Loki just basically takes in indexed metadata,
but doesn't index log contents at all,
which tends to be the vast majority of all this data.
So here we're looking at the set of Prometheus style
like label values and the timestamp,
all that is kind of controlled
and used for routing purposes of queries.
And then the log contents themselves,
which contrary to the size
of the underlying graphs on the screen,
or the lines, the log contents are much, much larger.
So that's the biggest piece here.
So this allows us to kind of figure out
and use our expertise for the systems that we run
and use these labels which tend to be topological
or so the source of your contents, right?
The application equals API, the cluster,
the environment, that sort of thing.
And then slice down to the time period that you care about
and we can use our own expertise as operators
to figure out where we should look.
And so as you can see here, right,
this maybe is a pretty broad section
corresponding to about a terabyte of data
over that period, but you can mix and match these things.
And so this goes to a fraction of that,
down to about 10 gigabytes by just looking at
the sets of applications that we actually care about
rather than all of the applications
and replicas deployed in that cluster.
So to give you a bit of a taste of what we mean
when we say Loki is performant
and Loki executes code faster.
So this is what we mean.
This is the metric we took from one of our
internal cluster.
So what you're basically seeing here is
this particular Loki cell at peak,
it's processing like 50 terabytes per day, right?
And what you see in the UI, it's a graph on a UI by the way,
where you're running some log queue, which is a query
language we use to get visibility of your logs
that you ingested into Loki.
We'll talk about log queue a bit later.
So yeah, this is specifically a metric query.
This is like basically you are trying to figure out
the metrics on the fly just from your logs
without any instrumentation, right?
So this particular query is processed like 10 terabytes
of data in 12 seconds, which is almost like
one terabytes per second throughput.
So that's what we mean when we say,
yeah, Loki is faster performant.
Yeah, so my favorite piece here is that these are
actually constructed from logs themselves.
They're not Prometheus metrics or anything.
We log query metadata for every query that comes into Loki
and we're kind of extracting the part of the log line
that talks about how fast it processes data
and then accumulating it over a bunch of subqueries
to get this final value and then graphing that over time.
So let's step back now and I like to think about
how Loki was designed kind of in response
to what came before it.
If we look really far back, we remember using
tail and grip on individual log files
and that's still in use a ton today.
But it doesn't work so well when you start to need
hundreds or thousands of machines
and maybe they're ephemeral, right?
So we had to kind of build new strategies for handling this
and a bunch of things have come up in the past
10, 15 years.
But sometimes it leads us into the next point
where we've accumulated all of this complexity
and sometimes we really miss that experience.
And I like this tweet because it's just incredibly
emblematic of that experience that sometimes
I just really wish I did have grep on top of
all of the log aggregation and on top of the underlying
complexity and scale that we've accumulated
over the past couple decades.
Yep, so broadly speaking, so that's one of the goal
of Loki, at least on the query side,
to take the same experience you have before
like with just grep and tail that you're confident with.
Can we bring the same experience in this modern
cloud native distributor systems era, right?
Where you have your logs like spitting out
from different machines, from different applications.
Yeah, similar setup, right?
So like I mentioned before, Loki has this language
called Locky and that's how you query your logs back
to get some visibility and this is heavily inspired
from Prometheus.
So people who are familiar with Prometheus may already
get a grasp here.
So this particular query what you see at the top
is basically saying like give all the logs
from this particular namespace, let's say,
Loki Dev 005 and then give me all the logs that matches
only the error in the log line, right?
So as you can see, the experience is like the pipe
equal to error.
So you can still combine multiple pipes here.
So that's the kind of like experience we're talking about,
right, so yeah.
So doesn't mean you have to, you can only like
grep for only specific pattern.
You can also grep for specific IDs.
Like use case can be like your order ID or trace ID
you want to find in the logs.
So you can also do some kind of regex match here.
Like I said, you can also like put multiple pipelines here,
right, you can do under or, doesn't matter.
So it's basically like first you choose which logs
to look for, like a routing, what Owen was saying
and then you can do all your piping to mix and match.
So that's the idea we're talking about.
So this query is a bit different.
As you have seen like compared to previous two examples
which we called as a lock query and this is a metric query.
So in the lock query, the output you see after,
when your query is executed, you will see,
you're gonna see like list of logs
that matches the particular pattern, right?
So here it's a metric.
So if you see what this query does,
it's similar to the last one
but we added two different things, right?
Here the rate and the sum by.
So what this means is without doing any instrumentation
like the logs are coming as it is,
so you can really find your error per second rate
of all your application aggregated by the container.
Which means, so doesn't matter like how many applications
running in this namespace, so you can aggregate
by container just from this metric query.
So yeah, that's the idea we are trying to,
like the experience we want to like with LockQL.
Yeah, this is probably my favorite part about Loki
of all the things, right?
The ability to extract information at query time
ultimately means that you can be reactive
instead of proactive.
You don't have to figure out a schema
and make sure that you're recording something
in a precise way before the bad thing happens, right?
Because a lot of the time it's the unknown unknowns
that get us.
And so this, the ability to extract this structure,
you know, and particularly to do it from logs,
really allows you to figure out when things go wrong
rather than having to re-instrument
before you can get that information.
So next up we're gonna talk a little bit less
about the experience querying it
and more about how it's constructed.
So this is the kind of design choices that we make.
So particularly individually being able to scale
different parts of the system,
particularly tuning your kind of a preference
for cost versus latency on the read path.
Loki runs, is intended to run across commodity hardware
and our only real dependency is object storage.
So we store everything cheaply
in a generally managed solution,
although you can run your own object storage
or use file system back ends if you prefer.
So this is how Loki ingestion path architecture
looks at the high level.
So when you send logs to Loki,
and this is what it goes through.
So the key takeaway here is like Owen said,
the only external dependency you see here
is the object store.
So everything else is a common of Loki.
So of course we have like different deployment models.
So usually all these components can be put together
in a single binary.
So if you're new to Loki,
you are starting just to play with it
at maybe like a small scale.
You just run it as a single binary, as a single process,
and you send all the logs to a single process.
And the only, you just put the bucket name and you're done.
So all your logs are getting ingested into Loki just fine.
So that's what we say like,
yeah, like less dependency in running Loki.
Yeah, in this case, it's an interesting part.
And so one of the things about not indexing
the log contents themselves means that it's really easy
to ingest data from a bunch of different sources.
So maybe you work at an organization
and one team writes in one language,
one team writes in another language.
They have no standardization over the formats
that they're using, the logs, the schemas of the logs,
if they're using structured logging.
So you can have one team in JSON,
one team who just pulls in Nginx logs
and then another team that uses something like log format.
And that's all okay, because Loki doesn't really care.
We just index the source of where this came from
along with the timing information.
So you can, each individual team in that sense,
can extract that information when they query it
and choose what and how that they actually do care about
in their logs.
Yes, speaking of Quarry Bart, right?
So this is high level architecture on the Quarry side.
So again, these are all like Loki components,
except like two dependency here.
One is object storage, of course.
The other one is like optional, which is like a cache.
So again, the same pattern apply here, right?
So you can combine all this Loki components
into a single binary,
and you can just run it as a single process.
And all you need to do is just point to the persistent
object store and then cache for the performance.
And that's it.
It's very good to go on the read path, right?
So yeah, again, if you want to run
in a highly available fashion,
let's say you hit some scale
and you wanna tweak some things.
So this is how, particularly, we run in our internal SAS.
So here, you have more control in a way.
Say you can tweak individual component,
you can scale individual component, and yeah, that's the idea.
So again, the key thing here
is the simple external dependencies.
So yeah, and it's really powerful to be able to develop
on a single binary running all these subcomponents
or things that eventually run in microservices
in a single process, and then being able to scale that out
depending on your tolerance for scale
and running HA or data replication, that sort of thing.
So because the index in Loki is very minimal,
it's just this routing information
or the data topology, really,
it allows this to be much, much smaller
than you would otherwise think.
So I actually pulled this from one of the clusters
that we run internally that is close to 40 terabytes
of logits a day and just shy of a,
so just 140 megabytes of index.
So it's much, much smaller.
And this gives us a lot of benefits
when we talk about some of the next stuff.
Yeah, so if I were you,
probably I'll be asking this question.
Okay, folks, you are talking a lot about tiny indexes,
how on earth do you make the query faster?
So also this thought comes from the idea,
like either you are from a academic background
or like a practitioner
who is building a distributed systems,
it's always been thought,
like if you wanna make something faster, you index it.
So here we are sharing our experience,
where if you want to index everything
to make everything faster, so at some point in scale,
your index is gonna be much larger than the actual data.
And in our experience, like handling huge index,
creates much more problems at scale.
So that's a whole idea here.
So let's understand like how Loki makes the query faster
with a tiny index.
And this is how.
So don't let the image scare you.
So let's understand piece by piece here.
So at the top, you see the query that comes in.
So for the sake of discussion,
let's say this query is asking for the data
for one hour period, time period.
So the query path architecture, what you saw before,
what the first thing it does is it takes this query,
the huge query, and it try to make it like a sub query
by time split.
So in this case, it splits this one hour query
into four 15 minutes query.
We call it a sub query, right?
And the trick is it doesn't stop here.
So Loki index is designed in such a way
so that it can look into the index and say,
hey, this many data, like this many bytes, it needs to touch.
So we can dynamically decide how many worker pool
you need to process that query.
So that's where this performance comes from.
So for example, like in this case,
let's say this 15 minute sub query is touching,
I don't know, like 10 gigabytes of data.
So and you can plan accordingly
like how many worker pools I can schedule this query into.
So let's think about this for a while.
So now the key takeaway here is you
get to have a control over your cost versus performance.
So you start with Loki and you hit some limit, right?
And at some scale, you're going to hit the limit.
And you can increase the performance just
by adding more query pool, like more query workers.
So yeah, that's like a key control
we want to have with the Loki.
So yeah, that's how we make query faster.
So the next thing we're going to talk about is retention.
We get asked this a lot, particularly wanting
to store things like application logs for some period of time.
You know, we use 30 days as kind of our standard,
but it could be whatever your use case is.
And then things like audit logs for much longer periods
of time.
This is pretty easily tunable in Loki.
But the important part here is we
were talking about the index size earlier.
Because we don't index, well, the log contents themselves,
retention is very, very easy and cost efficient to do,
because all of our data is stored in object storage.
And so if we extract that kind of earlier index sizing slide
out to what it would look like in a year,
this is roughly what we get.
And so again, we just use this index for routing information,
which means that all of the data is effectively live.
There's no like rehydrating or hot and cold storage tiers.
Everything is served out of object storage
generally all the time.
Now you can, there's some nuance there.
You can put like caches in a couple places
and that sort of thing.
But the idea that you can use object storage
as your primary back end is very powerful,
especially when you consider cost over long periods of time.
All right, so have you been saying
Loki has been built for the operators and for delves,
right?
And when it comes to operation, yeah,
if you've been run any database or any distributed systems
at scale, so you always want to keep
on top of the latest release of whatever the product you're
running to get the latest optimization, latest features,
so on and so forth.
And the other use case is like sometimes you
want to migrate your data from one persistent store
to another one.
In this case, maybe one GCS bucket to another one,
even across the cloud provider.
Sometimes you find like maybe S3 is better.
I can go with S3.
I can change from GCS to S3.
So with all these use cases, can we
do all these operations with zero downtime?
So can we do that?
So that's something like we can do in Loki.
We have been doing it many times.
So to give you a complete example here,
and this is one of my favorite part of Loki config,
like we call it as a period config.
So what you're seeing here is we have something
called schema version.
So whenever we change anything with the index
or any new feature comes in, and if it's
like we use different index format or something,
we change this version.
In this case, you see v11 to v12.
And so what you can do is let's say
you want to start using this new feature from Jan 2023.
All you need to do is go and put the version v12
from the start date, and you're done.
So Loki can understand this, and it
can work with both different schema version.
So this is how you can upgrade your schema and production
lively without downtime.
So this is one example.
The other one is the migration, like I talked before.
So you may want to move your data within the cloud provider
across the cloud provider.
For example, it's the same thing here.
So from 2023 of Jan, I need to store all my new data
into S3 instead of GCS.
So you go back, and you change this one config,
and you're done.
So Loki again understands this.
So when the query comes in, it checks
whether which data it's asking for,
like which time range it's asking for.
And it can go and fetch the data accordingly.
And again, without downtime.
So it also works really well with the retention.
Let's say if you have 30-day retention, and after 30 days,
you don't care.
So all your new data is stored to the new bucket.
So yeah, this is Fosdum, all about the community.
So we launched Loki at 2019 as open source,
and we have active community going on.
So these are some of the ways you can reach us.
We have public Slack, and we have a community forum.
And every month, we also have a Loki community call.
We alternate between US and EU time zone.
So yeah, come say hi.
Yeah, we are happy to.
And if any of the things which we talked about excites you,
come talk to us.
We'll be more than happy to have a new contributor to the project.
So yeah.
Yeah, we should have asked this probably in the beginning,
but is anyone out there using Prometheus?
Yeah, a couple.
All right, a lot.
Yeah, good.
What about any Loki users?
OK, not bad.
Thanks.
That makes me really happy.
Anyone run into hard configuration problems
with Loki?
Yeah?
Oh, no hands.
That's weird.
No, I'm just kidding.
Yeah, we got some work to do on.
Yeah, so things to take away from the talk.
Loki is meant to largely function
like a distributed graph that you can also kind of pull
metrics and analytics out of.
It's low footprint of storing things in object storage
and not relying on schemas.
And we really target easy operations with that,
as well as low cost.
And then please come join the community.
Come talk to us.
We're going to be hanging out for probably at least 10,
15 minutes.
If you have any questions, we'd love to hear from you.
Thank you.
All right, thank you.
Any questions?
Yeah, if you want to run up, we'll just share them right
down here.
Hey, great talk.
I was wondering with the amount of query sharding you're doing,
how are you kind of synchronizing the result in the end?
Or is it synchronized in the UI at the end?
Or do you need to sort things?
Because that might be very expensive.
All right, so I had a little difficulty hearing that.
But I think the question was, how do we synchronize sharding
in the query engine?
Is that it?
At the very end, when you show it in the UI?
Oh, when we show it in the UI, it
happens a layer down in Loki itself.
So we've already merged everything.
I think the real answer to that is probably a lot longer
than I can give in this question.
But talk to me.
It's one of my favorite things to talk about.
Thanks.
Great talk.
This was mentioned several times that the main power of Loki
is that it indexes only labels, basically.
And it doesn't index actual log messages.
But to make log messages searchable,
you want to have many labels in this case.
And many labels often lead to cardinality explosions,
how you deal with it.
Is there any good recommendation how many labels I
should have what are trade-offs here?
Yeah, so the way that I think about this
is you probably want to index where the log came from less
than what's in it.
So we definitely added the ability to kind of like,
especially in promtail configs, which is the agent that we
write, the ability to add extra things in there.
And people have been really clever about what they put in.
Unfortunately, that can also be somewhat of a foot gun at times.
So I'd say index the things that correspond
to your topology, where the logs come from.
So environment, application, cluster, that sort of thing.
And less things that have to do with the contents of them
themselves.
There's probably a somewhat longer answer there, too.
And then we've also been doing some recent work
to make some of this less of a user concern,
particularly about distribution of individual log stream
throughput.
So if you have one application which
is logging like 10 megabytes a second,
that could be really harmful on Loki in some ways.
And so people got clever around splitting that out
into different streams.
But in the future, we're going to be
doing a lot of that automatically and transparently
behind Loki's API.
Just to add one thing on top of what Owen said,
in logQL, which we didn't show here,
so if you have something in your log line itself
that you want to treat it as a label,
you can do it on the fly with the logQL query language
itself.
So we have some parser.
If it's a log form, if it's a JSON parser,
you can use it like labels, the things in your log line itself.
Hi.
Thank you for the great talk.
I have many questions, but I'll ask one.
Do you have any tips in terms of scaling query and caching
layers?
Like from my experience, usually they're very overutilized,
but when people start querying, you get all the crashes.
Do you have any code and ratios or anything?
Yeah, so this is one of the things
like how we expose configurations around query
parallelism and controls.
I wish I had a do over on this a few years back,
because there's a couple different configurations,
largely around, for every individual tenant,
how many subqueries you want to be allowed to be processed
per query at a time.
And then there's also things like concurrency
for each of your query or components, right?
How many go routines should you associate with
or should you devote to running queries independently?
But I got some work to do to make that easily digestible,
if that's fair.
So this year at work, I end up giving to Loki for 10 minutes
about 20 gigabytes of log from 500 machine.
It was just a one-time experiment
that I ran from time to time.
And we started using Loki.
We optimized it as intended.
So using index query was great.
At a certain point, my colleagues came to me and say,
we want the log string for each individual machine in a file.
And I started asking Loki for this,
and it took ages to extract this information.
Now, I hope you're going to tell me,
this is not the use case for Loki.
You did very well to use RCs log and just pushing things
in a file.
But if you have another answer, I'll be glad.
We didn't catch the question fully,
but my understanding is you're asking,
like, can the log field find the logs coming
from a single machine?
Is that right?
Am I getting it right?
Yeah, extract the log string for all these 450 machines
using RPC and put them in a file.
So you're talking about, I guess, some kind of federation,
maybe.
So why do you want to store it in the file in a single machine?
Because they wanted to run analysis
on a specific stream of log from a specific machine.
So they needed.
So technically, you can store log files in a file system.
So instead of using object storage,
technically you can use a file system.
That's completely possible.
But we encourage to use object storage
when it comes to scale, because that's how it works.
Yeah, is the question behind the question there
like changing where you actually store it
so that you can then run your own processing tools on top?
Yeah?
OK.
Yeah, that's actually a relatively common ask.
It's not something that we support at the moment.
We have our own format that we store in object storage
or whatnot.
We do have some tooling.
One's called chunk inspect, which
allows you to kind of iterate through all the chunks, which
could be from a particular stream or log file.
But it's not incredibly bad.
I always include it at the moment, if that makes sense.
Hello.
I have the use case that I store some telemetry data with my logs
sometimes, like a metric or sometimes which
I don't want to be indexed.
But I also don't want to encode in the actual log message
because it's already structured data.
Is it possible to have fields that are not indexed or data
that are not indexed?
It's funny that you asked that.
Yeah, so there's kind of a growing question
around non-index metadata like that.
That's not actually stored in the index itself,
but includes some degree of structure.
I know we see this as kind of a current need, particularly
for hotel formats.
So it's something that we're looking into right now,
actually.
Thank you.
So thanks a lot, everyone.