Hi, everybody. Thanks for being here for this talk. That's a lot of people. I'm Nicolas
Frankel. I've been a developer for a long time. And I would like to ask how many of
you are developers in this room? Quite a lot. Who are ops? Just as many. And who are DevOps,
whatever you mean by it. So this talk is intended for actually developers. Because I was or
I still think I'm a developer. So if you are a nobs people and for this for you is not
that super interesting. At least you can direct your developer colleagues to the talk so that
they can understand how they can ease your work. Well, perhaps you've never seen that.
But I'm old or experienced depending on how you see it. And when I was starting my career,
monitoring was like a bunch of people sitting in front of screens the whole day. And actually
I was lucky once in the south of France I was told, hey, this is the biggest monitoring
site of all France. And actually it really looked like this. And of course there were
people like watching it. And that was the easy way. Now I hope that you don't have that
anymore. That it has become a bit more modern. Actually there is a lot of talk now about
microservices, right? Who here is doing microservices? Yeah. Yeah. Because if you don't do microservices
you are not a real developer. But even if you don't do microservices, so you are not
a real developer and I encourage you not to be a real developer in that case, you probably
are doing some kind of distributed work. It's become increasingly difficult to just like
handle everything locally. And the problem becomes, yeah, if something bad happens, how
can you locate how it works? Or even if something works as expected, how you can understand
like the flow of your request across the network. I love Wikipedia. And here is the observability
definition by Wikipedia which is long and in that case not that interesting. So I have
a better one afterwards for tracing. So basically tracing helps you to understand the flow of
a business request across all your components. Fabian, where is Fabian? Fabian is here.
So he talked a lot about the metrics and the logging. So in this talk I will really focus
on tracing because my opinion is that, well, metrics is easy. We do metrics since ages.
Like we take the CPU, the memory, whatever. Now we are trying to get more like business
related metrics. But it's still the same concept. Logging also. Now we do aggregated logging.
And nothing by knowing. Tracing is I think the hardest part. So in the past there were
already some tracing pioneers. Perhaps you've used some of them. And, well, now we are at
the stage where we want to have something more standardized. So it starts with the trace
context from the WC and the ID is that you start a trace and then other components will
get the trace and will append their own trace to it. So it works very well in a web context.
And it defines like two important concepts that Fabian thanks already described. So now
I am done. So I have the same stupid stuff. So here you have oh, sorry. Yes. It reminds
me of the story. I did the same to my colleagues. They didn't care about the presentation. They
only remembered that. Okay. So here you have a trace. And here you have the different spans.
So here the X one is the parent one. And then the Y and the Z one will text this X span
as their parent span. So this is a single trace. This is a single request across your
service. Web stuff is good, but it's definitely not enough. And so for that we have the open
telemetry stuff. Open telemetry is just a big bag of miracles all set into a specific
project. So it's basically APIs, SDK, tools, whatever under the open telemetry level. It
implements the W3C trace context. If you have been doing some kind of tracing before, you
might know it because it's like the merging of open tracing and open census. Good thing
is the CNCF project. So basically there is some hope that it will last for a couple of
years. The architecture is pretty simple. Basically you've got sources. You've got the
open telemetry protocol. And as Tanveen mentioned, you dump everything into a collector. Collector
we should be as close as possible to your sources. And then some tools are able to read
like data from it and to display it into the way that we expect to see it. What happens
after the open telemetry collector is not a problem of open telemetry. Just they are
collectors that are compatible. And for example, you can use Jaeger or Zipkin in a way that
allows you to dump your data, your open telemetry data into Jaeger or Zipkin into the open telemetry
format. So you can reuse, and that is very important, you can reuse your infrastructure
if you're already using the stools. Just switching to open telemetry. And then you're like you
are using a standard and then you can switch your open telemetry back end with less issues.
Now comes the fun developer part. If you are a developer, you probably are lazy. I know.
I'm a developer. So the idea is open telemetry should make your life as a developer as easy
as possible to help your ops colleague like diagnose your problems. And the easiest part
if you do auto instrumentation. Auto instrumentation is only possible in cases where you have a
platform when you have a run time. Fabian mentioned Java. Java as a run time which is
the JVM. Python as a run time. Now if you have Rust, it's not as easy. So in that case,
you are stuck. My advice if you are using a run time and probably most of you are using
such run times, whether Java or whatever, use it. It's basically free. It's a low hanging
fruit and there is no coupling. So basically you don't need extra dependencies as developers
in your projects. So since it's called practical introduction, let's do some practice. So here
I have a bit better than a hello world. So I have tried to model like an e-commerce shop
with very simple stuff. It starts just asking for products. I will go through an API gateway
which will forward the product to the catalog and the catalog doesn't know about the prices
so it will ask the prices from a pricing service and it will ask the stocks from the stock
service. The entry point is the most important thing because it gives the parents praise.
Everything will be from that. So in general you have a reverse proxy or an API gateway
depending on your use case. I work on the Apache API project. It uses the Nginx reverse
proxy. On top you have an open REST because you want to have Lua to script and to autor
load the configuration. Then you have lots of out of the box plugins. Let's see how it
works. Now I have the code here. Is it the begin off? Good. So I might be very old because
for me it wouldn't. Here that's my architecture. I'm using Docker Compose because I'm super
lazy. I don't want to use Kubernetes. So I have Jaeger. I have all in one. I'm using
the all included so I don't need to think about having the telemetry collector and the
web to check the traces. I have only one single image. Then I have API 6. Then I have the
catalog which I showed you. Of course I have couple of environment, my variable to configure
everything. I wanted to focus on tracing so no metrics, no logs. I'm sending everything
to Jaeger and then I do the same for pricing and I do the same for the stock. Normally
at this point I already started because in general I have issues with the Java stuff.
So here I'm doing a simple curl to the product. I've got the data which is not that important.
And I can check on the web app how it works. So here I will go on the Jaeger UI. I see
all my services. I can find the traces. Here you can find the latest one. And here is the
thing. If I click on it, it might be a bit small, right? I cannot do much better. You
can already see everything that I've shown you. So I start with the product from the
API gateway. It forwards it to the product, to the catalog. Then I have the internal calls
and I will show you how it works. Then I have the get request made from inside the application
and then I have the stocks that responds here. Same here. And here we see something that
was not mentioned on the component diagram. From the catalog to the stock I go directly.
But from the catalog to the pricing I go back to the API gateway which is also a way to
do that for whatever reason. And so this is something that was not mentioned on the PDF
but you cannot cheat with open telemetry. It tells you exactly what happens and the
flow. And the rest is the same. So regarding the code itself, I told you that I don't want
anything to trouble the developer. So here I have nothing regarding open telemetry. If
I write hotel, you see nothing. If I write telemetry, you see nothing. I have no dependency.
The only thing that I have is in my Docker file and in my Docker file I get the latest
open telemetry agent. So you can have your developers completely oblivious and you just
provide them with this snippet and then when you run the Java application you just tell
them A, run with the Java agent. Low hanging fruit, zero trouble. Any Java developer here?
Not that many. Python? Okay. So it will be Python. Just the same here. Here it's a bit
different. I add dependencies but actually I do nothing on it. So here I have no dependency
on anything. Here I'm using a SQL database because again I'm lazy. I don't care that
much. But here I have no dependency, no API call to open telemetry. The only thing that
I have is in the Docker file again. I have this. Again, I'm using a runtime. It's super
easy. I let the runtime, like, intercept the calls and send everything to open telemetry.
And the last fun stuff is Rust. Any Rust developer? Please don't look at my code too much. I'm
not a Rust developer. So I hope it won't be too horrible. And Rust is actually, well,
not that standardized. So here I don't have any runtime. So I need to make the calls by
myself. The hardest part is to find which library to use depending on which framework
to use. So in this case I found one and perhaps there are better options. But I found this
open telemetry OLTP stuff. And here this is because I'm using Exum. I'm using this library.
And so far it works for me. I don't need to do a lot of stuff. I just, like, copy pasted
this stuff. Copy paste developer. And afterwards in my main function I just need to say this
and this. So I added two layers. So if you are, if you don't have any platform, any runtime,
you actually need your developers to care about open telemetry. Otherwise it's fine.
Now we already have pretty good, like, results. But we may want to do better. So we can also
ask the developers once they are more comfortable to do manual instrumentation even in the case
when there is a platform. Now I will docker compose down. And it takes a bit of time.
I will prepare this. And on the catalog side, now I can have some additional codes. So this
is a Spring Boot application. What I can do is add annotations. Like, I noticed there
were a couple of Java developers. So it's the same with Kotlin. It's still on the JVM.
So basically I'm adding annotations. And because Spring Boot can read the annotation at runtime,
it can add those codes. So I don't have to, like, call the API explicitly. I just add
some annotation and it should be done. On the Python side, I import this trace stuff.
And then I can, with the tracer, add some, again, explicit traces. So internal traces.
And from the first point of view, because I already, like, did it explicitly, it worked.
Now you can see that I am in deep trouble because it happened a lot of time. The Java
application doesn't start for a demo. And that's really, really fun. So I will try to
docker compose down the catalog. And docker compose. Hey, what happens? Dash? Are you
sure? No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no. Not with the new versions. Yes. That's fine. We
are all here to learn. Down? What? Stop. Thanks. The stress, the stress. Yeah. Honestly, if
there is any, like, person here able to tell me why this Java application sometimes has
issues starting because I've added one gig at the beginning. And it's stuck always here.
So I can tell you what you should see normally. If I'm lucky, I made a screenshot. And yes,
here. But it's the beginning. It's the Rust one. So here, this is what you can have in
Python. This is what I added explicitly. I have five minutes. Well, if the demo doesn't
work, it will be much better. Then I won't have any problems with the timing. Here, you
can see that this is the trace that, yeah, this is a trace that I did manually in Python.
And here we can see that I filled the ID with the value. And on the Java side, again, nope,
I think it will be here. This is not the manual stuff that I added. Yes, it is. You have the
fetch here. You have the fetch here. So this is the span that I added manually. I'm afraid
that at this point the demo just refused working. Yes, it's still stuck. I will stop there.
I won't humiliate myself further when it's done. It's done. Perhaps if you are interested,
you can follow me on Twitter. You can follow me on Mastodon. I don't know what's the ratio.
More importantly, if you are interested about the GitHub repo, to do that by yourself, perhaps
with better configuration of the compose with the right memory, it would work. And although
the talk was not about Apache API 6, well, have a look at Apache API 6. It's an API getaway,
the Apache way. Great. Are there some questions now?
I never got so many up louds with a felling demo. Please remain seated. Please remain
seated so we can have a Q&A. Who had a question? Thank you. Very good talk. I have two questions.
So one is about this. Let's start with the first one. Right. Yes, yes, yes. How much
overhead does this bring in Python and Java or Rust? How heavy is this instrumentation?
That's a very good question. And the overhead of each request depends on your own infrastructure.
But I always have an answer to that. Is it better to go fast and you don't know where
you are going or to go a bit slower and to know where you are going? I think that whatever
the costs, it's always easy to add additional resources and it doesn't cost you that much,
whereas a debug incident across a distributed system can cost you days or even like weeks
in engineering costs. And you are very, very expensive, right?
Okay. Thank you. And the second one, have you encountered any funny issues with multi-threading
or multi-processing? Something like when your server just now.
Can you come closer to your mother? Your server just now was not starting. So some
software when you have multi-threading or multi-processing, have you encountered any
issues when the instrumentation caused you trouble?
This is not production stuff. This is just better than the hello world. So I cannot tell
you about prediction issues. You should find people who have these issues. As I mentioned,
it's a developers-oriented talk. So it's more about pushing the developers to help
ops to their job. For production issues, I must admit I have no clue.
Hi. In the case of runtime, does it always work with also badly written application?
I mean, how bad can application be before it stops working?
I'm not sure I understood the question. So how often do you need to do it before it stops
working? No, no, no. I mean, let's say I use deprecated
libraries, bad clients, something that doesn't work as it's supposed to be for the instrumentation
perspective. I mean, I do request to the network using UDP client, something I've written myself,
some custom stuff that I'm imagining that the instrumentation sits between some layer
of the network, which is going to the internet, for example. And so how bad can I be before
it stops recognizing a request from junk? You cannot be banned.
Well, it's a moral issue first. But then on the platform side, the host to instrumentation,
they work with specific frameworks and tools. It's those frameworks and tools that know
how to check what happens and to send the data to open telemetry.
So if you don't play in this game, nothing will be sent.
On the manual instrumentation side, it's an explicit call. So it depends what you want
to send. Yeah, I was thinking of auto instrumentation.
So let's say I do DNS resolution by myself and then I just throw a request to an IP.
Let me show the Python stuff here. This is what I showed you in the screenshots.
This is what I write. And this is the attributes that I want to have.
So basically, if here you have something that is completely unrelated, it's up to you.
That's why it's easier to start with auto instrumentation.
And then once you get a general overview of what you have and your ops start saying, hey,
perhaps we want to have more details here, then you can come with manual instrumentation.
But start with the less expensive stuff. I didn't really answer the question.
I understand it. But that's the best I can do regarding it.
Sorry. Okay.
And for the talk, for the agent you're using the Docker file, how you can configure it,
for example, for the tracing for Jagger or other stuff.
Regarding the Docker file, sorry. Yeah.
How you can configure the agent to send the traces for Jagger or other...
The Docker file doesn't mention where you send it.
The Docker file just says, hey, I will use open telemetry.
And it's during configuration, it's like in the Docker compulse file where I'm using agreed
upon environment variables. Where I'm saying you should set it here or
here or you should use logging or tracing or metrics or whatever.
So that's very important to separate those concerns.
On one side in the Docker file you say, hey, I'm ready for open telemetry.
And when you actually deploy it to say, okay, a point telemetry will go there for the metrics
and there for the tracing and for logging, I will disable it or whatever.
Thank you for... Sorry, go ahead.
Sorry. And then you have a Docker image that can be, like, reusable.
Thank you for being good, first-line citizens to remain seated.
Next question. Thank you for your presentation.
So my question is, does open telemetry support error handling like Sentry?
If not, is there any plans to do that?
It's really useful to catch crashes and capture the context of the crash.
So that's it. Thank you.
If it happens, when you mean crashes of open telemetry itself or of the components that
are like under watch?
Yeah, of the application that's monitored.
Fabian showed you how you could log and, like, bind your traces and your logs.
So you could have both here.
My focus was just on tracing.
But you can reuse the same Docker GitHub repo and just, like, here.
Put the logs somewhere in, I don't know, Elasticsearch or whatever.
Because it's not a sponsored room.
And then you can check... And you introduce some errors.
And then you can check how the two are bound.
And you can, like, drill down to where it failed.
Okay. Thank you.