I think I will start, otherwise I won't have any.
I like to talk a lot, so I won't have enough time anyway.
So thanks for coming to my presentation.
Today I'm going to talk about the challenges of updating everything.
So my name is Wareking.
I'm also one of the CI, the room maintainer.
I'm working for SUSE on all things related to Kubernetes, Rancher.
So if there are anything you want to talk about, feel free to reach out after my presentation.
But today I'm not here to talk about what I'm doing at work.
I'm here to present a project that I started before joining SUSE.
By then when I used to work on a Jenkins project.
And that project is named UpdateSyli.
So UpdateSyli is a command line tool that we use to automate things.
So the design is to run it on your machine, on the CI environment, whatever it is.
And so you specify in the manifest what the update strategy would look like.
So initially I wanted to talk about first UpdateSyli and then all the challenges that
you have when you want to automate Docker images, when you want to automate infrastructure,
whatever.
But I won't have the time to do that here.
So for those people in Ghent, for the configuration management camp, I will have more time over
there.
And I'm just focusing on what UpdateSyli is, what the problem is and what I'm trying to
do.
So the challenge that I face is quite often when I maintain large amount of projects,
something that used to work do not work anymore.
Like you're using Hugo, for example, to generate a website.
And then at some point you cannot deploy the website anymore because even though the projects
release a new Hugo version, they fail to build the...
And publish the Docker images associated to that, or you would realize yesterday I was
investigating an issue where UpdateSyli would deploy and would roll back version of the
engine asynchronous controller and then it ended up that the people maintaining that
container just release, delete the release, forget to remove the Git tag and those situations.
So you would expect something to work, you won't automate.
And the thing is when you get in those situations, you try to understand why it didn't work.
It used to work for years and then suddenly it doesn't work anymore.
And then so you spend time trying to understand what's the latest version and what's the change
log, what's something failed, basically.
And so when you want to automate those updates so you don't have to pay attention to them,
I mean, it obviously has benefits, right?
I mean, by curiosity, who's using, for example, dependable or renovateable to automate things,
updates?
Yes, a few people.
It's only the start.
But once you start automating things, you know that obviously it gets easier to change
your project infrastructure documentation, no matter what, because you get confident
in the change that you want to do.
And in my case, most of my projects are always the DOM Git repositories.
And one of the challenges when you think about those Git repositories is everything is a
file and what you try to do is you try to automate them, but most of the time you have
no idea what you're trying to update, right?
So for example, dependable, we'll just look at a package of JSON.
So if you find a package of JSON, we'll list all dependencies and try to update them one
by one.
But on the other side, for those people using, for example, random JSON file, there is no
way to know in advance what should be updated in those files.
And then you have all those middle grounds, like, for example, for those people familiar
with Dockerfile, you have some instructions that you can automatically update, like the
from instruction, it's pretty straightforward to know what you need to update.
You don't know what you want to update.
That's a different story.
But the thing is, you know that you want to automate the base image.
On the other side, you can put pretty much every information in the run instruction,
the label, the end view instruction, and that's where things get difficult.
So when we started working on a data slide, we wanted to think, okay, we want to automate
everything, so we want to define where the information is coming from, what are the conditions
to automate the thing, and finally, what should be the state of your file on your Git repository.
So if I go back to my ego example, the idea is the source of information is the latest
ego release, that could be the GitHub, that could be the latest Docker image published,
that could be the GitHub release, for example.
But at some point, we have to decide what's the source of truth for that specific application.
And then you have, like, a bunch of conditions that you want to apply, like, does it make
sense to bump the version in production if you fail to bump the version in the dev environment.
So you want to be sure that you are using the same version everywhere, and only then
you will bump all the files related to that version.
And so when we come back about update.il, the idea is we specify a manifest, we have
to write a manifest, so that's a main different, for example, than for dependable, because
dependable, you just enable the button, it works, but it will only detect what it can
detect, but most of the time you have no idea what you should update.
With update.il, we went the other way.
We write a manifest, for example, this one is you have the source, the source of truth,
in this case it's a GitHub release, so can GitHub release, and then you have the specification
where you provide all the parameters for that specific project.
So in this case, I am monitoring the go ego, I go git repository.
This one gives me a version, let's say 100, that's the latest one.
And what I want to do is I want to be sure that all my files on name Netify.toml.
Are up to date, so I look at the key, and if I run this manifest on my machine, it will
just dump the file on my machine.
If I run this manifest on the CI environment, it will bump the file in the CI environment.
And so the next step is, okay, that's one thing to have it working in a machine, but
then you also want to be sure that your git repositories are up to date and don't pay
attention to them.
So you can just focus on what really makes sense in your case.
And so the next step is, okay, we want to specify where that file is located.
So we have a bunch of other resources, in this case it's a SCM of type GT, because I
want to update GT repositories, and then I specify that I want the pull request approach
where I create a temporary branch, and then someone can review my change.
And then when you think about all those building blocks, you can really have like more advanced
scenarios like this one is another project that we use, where we use it is when someone
really is in a new version of APNIO, we use GitHub action there that send a bunch of release
events automatically to other git repositories, and those git repositories will trigger update
CLI.
So update CLI will retrieve all the different information.
So for example, on the apnio slash docs, which is obviously the website, we retrieve the
latest version of APNIO, and then we check that all the download links are up to date.
We check that we have the version for that specific website.
So we maintain one documentation per major and minor version.
So we try to be sure that those files are to be up to date.
And if it's not the case, we open a PR, and then as part of the release process of APNIO,
someone needs to review the PR and double check that it still contains a file that you
want to have there.
Another example is the way we automate hand shots.
We define, OK, we are monitoring the APNIO UI, which is a front application, and we monitor
the backend, the APNIO.
And then if for some reason there is a new version, then it will automatically bump the
hand shot, bump the metadata, and so on.
And once again, we have a human validation where someone can just come look at the PR
and decide if we want to go one step further.
So really briefly here is when automated update is not so easy challenge, as I initially thought,
because we split the project in three different categories.
The first one is declarative.
So the idea is you know in advance what should be updated, and so you define in a manifest
how you want to update something, because it's not something that you can define in
advance.
The other discovery is a bit more like for those people familiar with dependable or renovate,
but you just run the command, and you ask it to automatically detect what could be updated.
There are scenarios where you can find that information.
For example, on the Maven project you have the PAM.exe, and you fetch all the dependencies
and update them.
That's pretty easy.
On other projects like Docker containers, it's kind of a mess over there, so it's super difficult
to know what should be the next version.
And then on the other side, you have all those situations where you specify a constraint,
a version constraint.
Like you don't want to use a version bigger than the 1.0, but at some point the project
upstream is like way further than you are in your project.
At some point you need to be aware that you will need to plan some work to catch up on
the upstream project.
And so that's another experiment, which is update-planetary.
I want to do a quick demo.
I don't have good internet connectivity here, so I hope it will work.
On the left side is one of the manifests.
Is it big enough?
Oops.
On the left side, we specify a few things like, okay, in this case we want to enable
the auto merge feature of GitHub.
We specify labels, so we automatically open a PR.
And if all the tests are passing, it will merge the PR automatically.
And so I don't have to pay attention, which reduces, obviously, the noise introduced by
those PR.
We need to specify which projects we want to go.
So in this case, that's the updated website.
And finally, we specify where the information is coming from.
So this one we monitor, goi, goi, yo.
As I said, we could have, like, instead of monitoring the GitHub release, at some point
I could have said, okay, I just want to monitor the Docker images.
But in that case, I just need to provide different piece of information.
Or you could say, for example, I want to monitor.
But here, writing from the ID is the easiest way.
Again, you can specify different ways of filtering versions.
Because what's something that we noticed, for example, is when I said the Docker ecosystem
is a mess, you can put whatever information you want in a tag.
So there is pretty much no way, I mean, most of the time there is no way to know what should
be the next version.
And depending on the registries, they don't return you the latest version because they
don't sort the tags in the same way.
So at some point, yeah, you need to enforce a specific behavior.
And then the target in this case is if there is a new version of Ugo, we want to be sure
that the workflow file has the correct version and that the Netlify is up to date.
So I don't care.
And so what it looks like on the other side is just a CLI, as I said.
So you can read it from my machine, Linux, Mac, wherever you want to run it.
And then voila, you get the latest version, change log, depending on the situation.
And based on that, you can just combine the project.
And so we have a lot of different workflows where we automate things.
The last thing, how many times do I have left?
Five minutes.
OK.
Where is that?
It's not this one.
So the thing that I was mentioning for the monitoring the different versions.
So this one is a different way to see the problem is you want to monitor the version
that you are using at some point.
And so you want to compare, OK, in this case, I have one, on one location, I say I want
to monitor a version from the Netlify.me.
So get me a version which is 0.110.
And on the other side, I want to compare with what's the latest Ugo version.
And so if it doesn't match, then I know that I need to work on that at some point.
And since I have a bit of a time, I can quickly show what the discovery looks like.
Fleet lab.
The auto discovery is a bit more difficult because you need to know in advance what you
want to do.
But where is that thing?
Oh, pop, pop, pop.
Yeah, this way.
As you can see, we don't have a lot of support at this time.
So it's mainly around containers because I'm working on containers most of the time.
But so it will parse the file.
So in this case, it identifies it's a run-shore project where we have fleets.
And then based on that, it will try to fetch all the different versions specified in the
fleet projects and will suggest other versions.
So that's it for my presentation.
And voila.
Is there any question?
One time, two times, yes, there is one over there.
Hi there.
Thanks for the presentation.
I was talking about the depender bot.
But you didn't mention about renovate.
I wonder how much it overlaps with renovate if it would be more customizable one.
So the question, I mentioned depender bots.
I didn't mention that much renovate bots.
So if you compare the depender bot and renovate bot, the renovate bot is way better than the
depender bot because depender bots, I didn't have the time to cover the domain.
There are a lot of things that I didn't have the time to cover.
But for example, one of the features that I really love in renovate bot is they allow
you to group PRs which reduce the noise.
Because for example, they depend on the bot, especially for those people maintaining JavaScript
projects, they can open 10, 20, 30 PRs and then you have to review all of them.
So there are different strategies to update.
Renovate bot is just way better in the way that it supports more modules.
On the other side, it's not really easy in the case of renovate bots to have workflows
where you really want to check.
In the fetching version, I check a bunch of things and then I update other targets basically.
So I would say renovate bots is better in the auto-discovery part where it can detect
things for you.
But on the other side, it's not really easy to have very complex update scenarios.
That's it.
Thank you.