Thank you.
Hey, everyone. Thank you for joining me. I'm Solomon Briss.
This is a mirror without reflection for Kotlin multi-platform.
Without further ado, let's go into the subject and define what
the
context of the program is, for example,
it's possible for a Java class to obtain the name of all of its
members.
This definition is extracted from the Java documentation, and it
explains that reflection basically allows a program to intro
expect upon itself and look at its own method and properties.
For example, in this code, I simply print every field and
method that a class is declaring as accessible.
And so this is possible thanks to these class objects that the
Java programming, the Java runtime gives me, and it allows me
to access all fields, methods, properties, and everything that
defines this class. Now, that's not the only thing Java
reflection can do. Java reflection can also provide
proxies. So, for example, here, I create a simple print-alent
proxy.
So here, I create a simple print-alent proxy.
So here, I create a proxy by saying, okay, here's a class.
Here's its class loader. Here's a class. It's not really a
class. It's an interface. So here's an interface.
And what I'm asking the runtime to do is to give me an object
that implements this interface and delegates every call to this
lambda. So basically, I'm creating an implementation of
an interface at runtime. And this is how you can use it.
As you can see, it's pretty simple. All you have to do is
call this create proxy method, and then you'll have an
interface, an implementation of the interface created at
runtime. So this talk is about to be a, is going to be about
a lot of definitions because we are going to have multiple
pieces of the puzzle. So the first piece of the puzzle was,
of course, reflection. Let's go into Kotlin Multiplatform.
And maybe let's not go into Kotlin Multiplatform because
you've just seen an entire presentation about what is
Kotlin Multiplatform and how it works. So I'm not going to go
into details about what is Kotlin Multiplatform and how it
works, but I'm simply going to say that Kotlin Multiplatform
is a way to compile Kotlin code for different targets,
namely JVM and Android on one side, JavaScript on another
side, and finally Kotlin Native on the last side.
Kotlin Native encompasses iOS and also other less
interesting targets. Let's face it, Kotlin Native exists
for the sole purpose of iOS. So while Kotlin JVM supports
reflection, Kotlin JS and Kotlin Native do not. What is
important to understand in this sentence is that reflection
is not a feature of Kotlin JVM, it's a feature of the JVM.
That Kotlin uses and builds upon with its own reflection
library, but basically it's a feature of the JVM, it's not
a feature of the Kotlin language. And as such, it is not
provided in Kotlin JS and in Kotlin Native. So Kotlin
Multiplatform being the center of Kotlin JVM, Kotlin JS,
and Kotlin Native, hence do not support reflection.
So we need to get together and find another way of doing
what we usually do with reflection. Maybe if we go back
to the definition of what reflection is, we can single
out this word. Reflection is a feature that allows an
executing Java program. So what this means is that reflection
is a runtime feature. And we all know that what we cannot
do at runtime, let's do at compile time. What can go wrong?
Right? So to do that at compile time, what reflection does
at runtime, we need to add several other pieces of our
puzzle. Kotlin Poets is a Kotlin and Java API for generating
Kotlin source files. So what you could do is generate
Kotlin source files by hand with templates and fill yourself
like the vibe of the PHP 2000 era where everything was done
with templating or you could use a type API that will build
the Kotlin file for you. So I strongly encourage you to not
generate your Kotlin source files by hand and use an API
such as Kotlin Poets. And here, for example, it's very simple.
I create a new function called hello. I declare that it takes
a name argument and I add the statement, print alone hello
name. So it generates basically this function. Okay. So that's
a very important piece of our puzzle, but that's by far not
the most complicated one. So the next piece of our puzzle is
KSP. And KSP stands for Kerbal Space Program. It's a very good
video game. And the goal of this video game is to build a
rocket and explore space. It's an exploration game. So it's
purposefully undocumented. So there's no manual for discovery
and that's the entire game. You need to build your rocket,
send your Kerbal to space and see what happened. So the game
is heavily based on trial and error. Not all Kerbal will
survive the journey. You will send them to space and not all
Kerbal will come back. But when you do build a rocket and a
space station in orbit, you feel a great sense of accomplishment.
And as it happens, KSP also stands for Kotlin Symbol
Processing API. The goal is to build a compiler processor,
a compiler code processor. And it is very, very likely
documented. Let's be honest. There is no manual for its
discovery. You will use trial and error and you will scream
at your screen yelling at your frustration. Using KSP is a
very good exercise in managing your frustration because of its
light documentation. But when you finally achieve a
functional Kotlin Symbol processor, you will, just like
in the KSP video game, feel a great sense of accomplishment.
So let's see all our pieces of the puzzle. We use KSP to
instrument codes at compile time. We use Kotlin Poets to
generate codes at compile time. And we use Kotlin Multi
Platform to compile everything for all targets that Kotlin
Multi Platform supports. So the idea here is not to allow a
code to introspect upon itself at runtime, but to generate
the information your code needs at compile time. It is a
lot more optimized, of course, because you don't have to
introspect all the code and all the information you need are
generated for you at compile time, but it is, of course, a
lot more complicated. So how do you create a mirror
generator? So a mirror is a class that contains reflection
information of another class. So how would you create a
mirror generator? Well, creating a Symbol processor in KSP is
not that complicated. What you need to do is create a Symbol
processor class that takes a code generator and a logger as
constructor input. And you will use those to, well, generate
code and log when things go right or wrong. And then you
can get, you can find all symbols that are annotated by a
specific annotation and then simply see what type of symbol
that is, and then you can continue to instrument the code
starting with this. So as you can see here, for example, look
at if the symbol annotated is a property or maybe it's just a
property setter because you can, in Coqe, annotate get and set
properties methods or maybe it's a function declaration or
maybe it's a class declaration and there are a lot of other
things available. What's interesting in KSP and what I'm
not showing here in code is that you could ask KSP to give
you all symbols that are of a simple, of a declaring
interface, for example, that are implementing an interface.
You don't have, just like APT, you don't have to use
annotations. Annotations are a very valid means of conveying
the information that the code will be instrumented. But you
could with KSP say, okay, give me all symbols, all classes
that implement this interface, for example, or give me all
codes to these methods or these kind of things. And then what
you need to do after you have instrumented the code is to
generate your file, the Kotlin source file that you will
generate. And the good news is that, sorry, the good news is
that Kotlin Poet does support KSP. So you don't have to write
a facade between the KSP code generator and the KSP code
generator. Kotlin Poet does support KSP, so it's, as you
can see, pretty easy to write your very own code generator
with KSP. And then what you need to do is to add your
simple processor to your Kotlin compilation tool chain with
Gradle. And as you can see, it's pretty simple. Just apply
the plugin. Now, the KSP plugins is versioned using its own
version number and the Kotlin version number. For example,
here it's version 109 of the Kotlin symbol processor of KSP
and it's version 1810 of the Kotlin language. And at the
moment, because the Kotlin compiler plugin API keeps
changing and is not stable and is not documented, KSP
depends on a very specific version of the Kotlin language.
So you need to upgrade KSP with the same Kotlin version
that you need to upgrade Kotlin. And that's kind of a
bummer because you need to wait when a new Kotlin language
version comes up, you need to wait for KSP to be compatible
with this new version, even for minor version. If you use
the wrong minor version, KSP will warn you that it is not
compatible with this minor version. And once again, that's
because the Kotlin compiler plugin API isn't stable and
that KSP is using internal function and features of the
Kotlin compiler plugin. Then, of course, you probably need
to add your own runtime because when you generate code, you
will probably need to provide with the generated code a
different time of your own. And then you need to declare
that your KSP code processor will run on this code. Now,
as you can see, it is declared differently than with regular
Kotlin dependencies because at the moment, KSP doesn't
interact with the Kotlin Gradle compiler, with the Kotlin
DSL. So you have to use this word KSP common main metadata
configuration in Gradle dependencies.
So what can you do with this technology? Well, for the last
two years, I've been developing an example because it was
needed for the company I worked at, and that was mocking.
So what we have here is a class that works with Kotlin
multi-platform tests, and that works with all targets of
Kotlin, and that generates mocks at compile time. Because
mocking in, for example, mockK or with mokito, mocking uses
the proxy reflection feature of the JVM, which does not
exist in Kotlin multi-platform. So, for example, here we
say we want a view that will be mocked. So view is an
interface, and it will be generated by the mok.mp
compiler plugin. We want a fake, and a fake is a data
class, and we want a data class that filled with fake
values, empty string, zeroed integers, and all those kind
of stuff. We want a controller that uses both a fake and
a mock. We want to define the behavior of our mock. For
example, here I say that in the interface view in my mock,
in my view mock, if I call view.render with any argument,
it will return true, and I want to be able to verify that
a mock has been called with a specific data in this
instance model. So all that, and all that DSL, is possible
thanks to KSP and Kotlin Poet, and the ability to generate
code at compile time. So what was previously unavailable to
Kotlin multi-platform, because reflection wasn't available,
is now available thanks to code generation. And by the
way, if you're interested in this in mocking for Kotlin
multi-platform, you can use mock.mp, which is a library that
we built with Deezer, and this testing library is used in
production, meaning in test production, at Deezer, almost
all the multi-platform tests at Deezer uses this mock.mp
library that we developed together. So there's a problem
with KSP. If we go back to the example I just gave you,
this method uses this inject mocks function. This class
uses inject mocks. And the fact is that inject mocks is
precisely the function that is generated for this class,
because this class, we can see here, because this class has
at mock annotated properties and at fake annotated properties,
then an inject mocks function will be generated by the
mok.mp compiler plugin slash symbol processor. And when you
load the project, the Deezer project, or any project that
uses this system, well, inject mocks is an error, because it
hasn't been generated yet. So IDEA will show you an error
saying, okay, this function just doesn't exist. I don't know
what you are talking about. So you need to either build the
project or you need to say to Gradle to generate and run KSP.
And at the moment, there is no way around that. And that's
because KSP has a very important limitation. It treats the
source code it is instrumenting as read-only. There is no way
with KSP to add properties or to modify a symbol that you are
instrumenting. So this, my test class, there's no way with KSP
that I can add a property or I can add an annotation and all
that. And since there is no reflection in Kotlin
multiplatform, there is no way to find a class that exists,
but there's no class then, class.withname. So that means
that you need in your code to use the code that is generated,
and that code doesn't exist unless you generate it. And
that's a small price to pay to use KSP. So why would you use
KSP as opposed to writing a full-fledged Kotlin compiler
plugin? First and foremost, because KSP provides a kind of
stable API, it is, the API changes, but it follows a
depreciation cycle, and the API of KSP is supposed to be
public, so they treat it with the respect of a public API.
And also because when you use KSP, you don't have to write a
compiler plugin. Writing a compiler plugin with Kotlin just
not only means that you will have to understand the inner
components of the Kotlin compiler, which are absolutely
not documented. KSP is a little bit documented. The Kotlin
compiler internals are just not documented, but it also means
that you will have to handle compiler integration and greater
integration. So you will have to add your own cradle plugin,
you will have to add your own compiler plugin, and it becomes
a very complicated endeavor. And finally, because for code
generating use cases, KSP remains a lot simpler than
writing a compiler plugin, which once again is done completely
in the dark. You won't have any support if you try to write
your own compiler plugin. So using KSP is still a very, very
important tool in the grand open source library of Kotlin
multi-platform project. A lot of Kotlin multi-platform libraries
use KSP now, and I encourage you to contribute to that grant
library. And that's it for me. Just want to say that I
represent here Coding Coders. We are certified for our Kotlin
training, so if you want Kotlin multi-platform training, be sure
to contact us. We have lots of libraries that are open source.
Ruma with the next talk is going to present to you. Another
one of them, and we like to do our open source work with
Kotlin multi-platform for every target it can compile to. So
whether you want to contribute to Kotlin multi-platform
libraries or learn how to use Kotlin multi-platform, be sure
to contact us. Thank you very much.
Thank you again. We have time for one question. If someone
has a question, raise your hand. Just shout it, and you have
to repeat the question.
Yeah, so you decided to write your own library. There was
any way of making Kotlin works with yours, or is that
impossible?
So the question is, rather than creating a whole new library
for marking a Kotlin multi-platform, is there a way to
port Mokito to Kotlin multi-platform? And the answer is
definitely no. Mokito uses a lot of reflection, not just for
proxy, but for object generation and for verification, and it
instruments the runtime heavily. And since there is no
runtime, there is no JVM runtime in Kotlin multi-platform,
there is no way to port Mokito to Kotlin multi-platform. Now
what we've tried to do with Mokay MP is to emulate the same
API that Mokito provides so that when you use Mokay MP,
you're at home, you're using an API that is really close, but
there's no way to port Mokito itself. Thank you very much,
and have a nice Fuzz