All right. Welcome, everyone. We're going to go. Yeah, it's four. So we did kind of
a dry run this morning and we realized that there's too much content. So we're going to
have to skip it. We're going to do the introduction. It's going to be very quick. So this is where
we work. It's called Mirai. Blah, blah, blah. Connect to the website. You're going to see
what we do. We do basically consultancy on a number of different clients on development,
architecture, digitalization, and so on and so forth. This is us. You can tell who's who.
These are our Twitter handles. And this is the Twitter handle of Mirai. If you like to
talk or if you don't like to talk, just be free to share on Twitter. What we're going
to talk about today. So this is the result of a number of lessons learned that we had
on a number of projects where we tried to solve a problem that we see coming up over
and over again. So it's just we just took stock of the situation. We saw what was around
all the mistakes that we made and we kind of condensed it into a presentation that we're
going to give to you. So this is by no means an idea of giving you best practices of any
sort because there's a lot of context that goes behind this kind of problems. But it's
just the way we are approaching the problem, the way we are analyzing the problem right
now and the way we are approaching it. And we're going to talk about this idea of digital
experience platform. You will see that like behind the name there is a thing that you
will know that is this idea that you start to have technical ecosystem that are more
and more complex and this technical ecosystems are done by a number of systems that need
to integrate together and they need to communicate together and they need to give back to the
user in some form or another on one channel or another a number of information, a number
of capabilities and interaction. So that said, what is the state of the art? What is the
thing that is the trendy thing right now? It's kind of synthesized but this idea of
the Mac kind of technologies, there's an organization behind it, you may know it about
it or not, but it's this idea that the new architectures have kind of four major characteristics.
They're based on microservices. We're not going to go into the debate of the microservice,
what micro means and why do we need microservices or not. They're API first, they're cloud native
and they're headless. We talked about headless. I think Alexander talked about headless on
material UI in the previous talk. I think that the two that you have to retain for this
talk are these ones. That you have systems where you don't necessarily care how the information
or how the capabilities are going to be exposed because it can be on a mobile app or it can
be on a web application or it can be on a kiosk that you have on a store or on something
else, you just don't care. The system is capable of giving you this kind of capabilities and
data regardless of the channel that you use and how do they do that precisely by having
an API first approach. You don't have the interface, you have the capabilities, you
can call any kind of HTTP REST service that is behind, the capabilities is there and then
you take care of the visualization or the user interface or the user experience somewhere
else. Am I going too fast? No? That's okay. All right.
There's a kind of a yes but kind of situation. Let's see that you start from a simple website.
This is what happens most of the time. You have a relatively complicated kind of interaction
website. You choose your framework. Here you have React. You may have a number of others.
We basically don't care but that's kind of one of the possible starting points. You say,
okay, I would like to manage this content. What you do, you add a content management
system. That is okay. You connect your content management system to your front end, off you
go, now you have a number of editors that can manage your content. All right. Sounds
good. Then you want to add some commerce because the company is doing good. They want to add
commerce capabilities. Very good. You have a commerce engine that is headless, API first.
You can add your commerce engine and then you start to connect it to your front end.
But you also have to connect it to your CMS because they need to share certain kind of
data. This is the situation that you have. Then you have a lot of products. You start
to need a digital asset management because you need assets for your mobile. You need
assets for your kiosk. You need assets for the web. You can't store them here because
they're not made for this job. They start to see a bit their constraints. You connect
the dam and you connect it with the commerce. You connect it with the CMS. Then you connect
it with your front end as well because it's the ultimate client. Okay. You kind of see
where I'm going with this. Search. You start to have a huge catalog. You need to add search.
You add Algolia or Elasticsearch. We don't care. It's the same kind of concept behind.
Then you connect Algolia and you need to connect it with your commerce layer. You need to connect
it with your CMS. You need to connect it with your front end. Off we go. Then you have a
Netlify because why not? Then at some point somebody says, you know what? I would like
to do some customer relationship management with the data that I have. Then you start
to add the CRM. That's where you end up with the situation.
Now if we remove all the capabilities that are provided by the system, which is a huge
step forward because before you had to do all kinds of plumbing behind. You need to
de-connect your user interface from the system behind. It was very tedious and very complicated.
Now we have all those pieces of software that are capable of doing this by themselves where
you're basically left with this. I was finding it funny. I don't know if you're still here.
I was saying in the previous talk, you go headless and you just remove the problem.
You would see that there's kind of a law of conservation of complexity. You just don't
remove the problem. You just shift it somewhere else. Someone or something still needs to
take care of this. Then of course because we're not stupid and we're good intelligent
developer, what we say is like, okay, this is not possible. We're going to create something
that is going to aggregate this all together. We basically create a layer. This complexity
is still here. You cannot have a tension between the fact of having these Lego blocks and
the modularity and the fact that someone or something still needs to orchestrate all this
kind of stuff. It can get very, very messy and very, very complicated very, very quickly.
This is the first problem, kind of big problem that we were trying to address. The second
kind of problem is that if you take kind of a random e-commerce kind of interface, what
you start to see more and more is that before it was just a matter of your CMS and your
commerce. You had the catalog and the basket. These were coming from the commerce system
and then your content was coming from the CMS. What you start to see right now is that
if you take all the blocks that compose, let's say, a fashion e-commerce, in the same blocks
you have pieces of data that come from different systems and you need to aggregate those and
you need to present them as if they were a unit because that's what the user cares about.
I need to have a catalog and the catalog is normally coming from the search because the
search is optimized so you don't ask it to the CMS and you don't ask it to the commerce
because you want to do all sorts of categorization and classification. But then you don't show
the ideas of the catalog. You show the product and the product comes from the image from
the dam, some content from the CMS and the SKUs from the commerce system.
So, again, you see where we're going with this, it can get very complicated very quickly.
And the problem for us as developers behind is that every time that you need to change
something here, you need to make sure that everything stays coherent and consistent behind
the scenes. And again, this can get very tedious very quickly.
So I hope what I said kind of made sense as an introduction for the context. You raise
your hand if that was not the case. Okay. Everything is clear? Sounds good. I was getting
scared. Okay. So we have the problem. Now what? And that's where I hand it over to Bhuva
that is going to show you what is the situation that we're applying right now.
So full disclaimer, it's an approach that I'm showing you. It's not simple, it's an
exploration. So be with us. It's such perfect. And just trying stuff and trying to see where
we can solve this problem. So first thing that I'm asking you, would you tell me which
framework I'm using? So basically I'm running on 4200 and 4201. And if you look at the two
websites, okay, we're in JavaScript. I have to make a joke about CSS. I'm really bad in
CSS. CSS is dark magic for me. So that's the reason why. Don't bother with the logo. It's
normal. It's okay. Just focus on the product here. Could you tell me on the right or left,
where you are? Who is build with next and the other one is build with next. No? No?
Okay. So let's see on how we... Here. So I will just open it. So if I do an inspect,
if I scroll a bit, so one of them is based on next. Okay? And the second one is based
on... because voila. Next. Okay? So you'll say why I'm asking that. So if I tell you
this two page, use the same base has code, okay? And I just compile it and then I get
a component that works for React, that works for Vue, and this is not a component. Okay?
So do you know a tool that can do that? Nobody? Okay. So I tried. Okay. So let's go. So for
this tool, I will be speaking about some tools that you are using to work with everything.
So the first one is NX. So if you don't know NX, it's kind of like a tool that you can
use to handle all your model repo. Okay? It's really a good tool because I don't want to
set up Webpack guys or Vue or anything else. So I use this kind of tool to handle all the
configuration. Just handling Webpack, handling Cypress, Storyblock, everything is handled
by this tooling. Okay? I just use that plugin and then give you a good basic when you work
with your team and really good standard. Okay? Second tool that we will be showcasing is
Metasis. Metasis will be the basic of how we build a component. Like I said, it's an
exploration. It doesn't solve everything, it's just a base. And we are trying to explore.
So if someone knows something about Metasis, did you hear about it? No? Okay. So give you
some context. Metasis is a kind of like a compiler, a component compiler, created by
the builder IOT team. So builder IOT, they build kind of like a CMS that completely,
I would say visual CMS, where basically they have a lot of history. They would like to
support all the framework that we have in JavaScript. So it's a lot of frameworks. So
they hire multiple people and then they're like, okay, guys, you're hiring too much people.
Okay. Maybe you should find a way to be able to handle all this complexity. So they begin
to create a compiler for components. So they use a common layer, like JS6, and then based
with this common layer, they compile it to natively to React, Vue, as well, or like all
bunch of stuff. Okay? Basically they take the approach of LLVM. So if you don't know
about it, they take the same approach, having a common layer where we can target and then
all the architecture can file for that. So we'll be using that. Frankly speaking, it's
not perfect. It's really at the beginning. What's really nice with that, they are really
pushing the boundary of that because all the SDK, so if you use builder IOT, basically
you are using it to disunder the hood. So they use that to build all the SDK for the
visual editor, like everything that you're using for React Vue is based on that. So it's
not perfect yet. It's improving every time. But it gives you really kind of like a good
code. I will not say it's perfect. A human will be better. Yeah, but at the end you win
time and energy because you write once and you believe you are. Okay, it's a dream since
like 20 years, I know, but voila. Every time, every 10 years we try to do it again and fail
maybe, but voila, someone tried. Okay? So basically if you take back what Maurizio
said, we are going on the headless. So our goal is really to reduce the friction. So
we have multiple frameworks. It's really difficult to go on client and say, hey, you use React,
you use Vue, you use Angular. Okay. And every time rebuilding the button, rebuilding the
same thing. So trying to find like a common layer and using it as this, we can really
focus on what I said most of the time, the presentation component. I don't mean like
for really big components with charts. It's not mean for that. And don't try to do it.
You'll be it hardly and you will hate it and you'll be like this is shit. Okay? It's really
for I would say common component that you will have that will be really simple, mostly
UI based, not too complex, but kind of complex for some stuff. So you can reuse. Basically
it's your, if you're on React, they call it the presentation component. So we shouldn't
say it anymore. Since then, it's bad, but voila, I use the term. Okay? So I will show
you how we did it and what we have built all the advantage issues that I got about it.
So ship. So I'm using upstone. Okay. And basically here on the left side, you can see I'm using
a, it's just a standard, uh, which application on the next. So you have the app folder, the
libs, and then all bunch of stuff that we have every time on every stuff. Okay. The
libs contain all the kind of library. What's cool with enix? So you don't need to publish
it. So you can really put it on the more repo. It under all the configuration. So when you
import it in a react, it's basically user test path under the hood and make the magic
on webpack. It just, it just works. Okay. It's kind of like dark magic, but it's not
too complicated under the hood. It just test path and bring you for import into a webpack
or vids. Okay. So basically we create a library, a core library, okay, using mitosis. Okay.
So if you open here, you can see I have a core library. This is the mitosis. Why I call
the core because it's the basic for everything, all the components we are using. Okay. Then
I create a sub folder called the UI. UIs will be like all my target that I'm pushing for
people. Okay. So I have the UI for react. Okay. And I have a guy for view. Okay. So let's
first focus on the car. So on the car I have like a miss mitosis config. So basically it's
a configuration layer where I basically set up how I want to target and how I want to
compile everything. So you can see it's a bit messy because like I said, it's not perfect
completely. You have some HKs. But behind it's just basically a config that you put
and you say, okay, let me scroll, what do you explore? You put where you put your file,
where you put overwrite, we'll put it after. And then the target is what we like to do.
It gives you also some HKH. Like for example, you can set up if you want to compile to TypeScript,
want to run feature already handling, like for example, how you want to handle a strict
act and have like kind of like plugin system basically to help you to hook into the system
like when decompile. Okay. It's really basic and it's not like a big compiler, just basic,
but it's already to fix some stuff that's not perfect. Okay. Like if I go a bit here,
like rec native, kweep, swalt, like as well, you can see here like, oh, shit, what this
guy is doing? Like basically it's replacing stuff under the hood and patching stuff. Yeah.
Sometimes you have to do it, but voila, it's just like to give you like extend where we
can go. Most of the time you don't need that. This is really like HKs for them, but you
have already code. Okay. So then you have the SRC. The SRC basically is just where we
put all the code. So I will focus mostly on the component. So the convention is really
straightforward. It's just you create a component basically with a dot light dot TS6 is a convention
that will be every time pick automatically by the compiler and then recompile it to view
or react. Okay. So basically here I'm just taking a simple component. This one it's more
tricky. I will open another one. I will say easier. Not this one because this one is all
low. Let's take this one. Okay. So here basically just under the hood is using like kind of
like a JS6, but a more JS6 contrain. So if you know solid JS, you have to play with it.
Not you. Basically solid. It's kind of like a react, which should have been if they write
it now and basically to use like really a constraints JS6 system to make it more performant.
And basically they kind of copy some stuff from solid. Like for example, if you want
to do a maps, you don't do a maps like in React. Like it's just JavaScript. Yeah. Okay.
We know it just JavaScript. Here you have to use the four component. Why? It's because
it makes easier for the compilation basically to be able to say, okay, if I am using in
view, I use a v4. If I'm in React, I use a map. If I'm in Angular, I use an ng4. Okay.
So this reason why they create this contrain to make the compilation easier. If not, I
have to play with the AST. So abstract syntax tree and just make the complexity increase.
So try to make it simpler. Okay. And then they come with some common ground. Like for
example, you store it just kind of like a hook. Basically this will be compiled to a
new state or some similar in view. Okay. So to give you some rules that you have to respect,
it's really strict. It's not easy at the beginning and that's make the complexity of using this
kind of tool. Because you have to really think like when I say if I'm working in Java before,
like an interface development way. Okay. What I mean by that, it's you have to think about
the common ground between all the component and all the frameworks. You cannot just say,
hey, I will write it like that. And basically this does not exist on the other component.
Okay. Or it's not compatible. Okay. You have some degree of flexibility, but it's not every
time the case. Okay. So you have to find really the common ground. But accept that. Okay.
It's kind of like a just a react. Okay. With some stuff. Okay. So basically you get this
component and it will be compiled and you can see it on the output folder here. It will
be compiled automatically on react. So if I take the here, why I have client and server
it because I'm already testing stuff. Whoa, five minutes. Okay. I have to go straight.
So client basically is where we put all the normal component. So where it's when you do
the C and so on and not speak about it. So component here, we have the future section.
So basically it's really, I think this one under the hood, it's looks like really something
that you should have written. Okay. The completion is a perfect, but it's going really well. The
good thing with that, it's like it gives you also an escape age under the hood. Let's get
it is the override system. So if some part of your application, you need to have like
components that's not completely right. It's complicated. You can override it and how you
do that. Basically it just follow the path here. And then you can say on the completion
level when you meet this import, replace the file by this one. Okay. And here, for example,
I do it for like headless UI. Okay. I say, okay, when someone needs the headless disclosure,
basically under the hood is switching to headless UI. And because it was working both in a
directed view, it works fine. Okay. When I have that, I could be completely automatically
on my library here, UI and next. And basically I just create a library, simple library where
the client and I do an export. Simple of that. This more I can take it and publish it in
PM it works. Okay. Then that's, I take it and then I use it in my application directly.
Thanks to Enix, I don't need to do like in PM blah, blah, blah. It's already handled
automatically. So to give you an example on next.js on the page here, I have like my application.
So basically I will introduce now the layer. So do you see here, we speak about the component,
but now we need a layer because everything is connected. So we need a layer to be able
to say, okay, I have a layer in common where I can connect everything and handle it. This
layer is called uniform. Okay. It's a tool that we use and we explore a lot of the teams.
So let me show you. So uniform is basically that. Okay. It's kind of like a visual editor
that you can get. It's, it's such a complete CMS, but it's way more powerful than that
where we can connect a lot of stuff. So here basically I'm connecting my next application
directly with my component. I will show you in two minute and I'm also able to connect
directly to data coming from multiple source if I want. So here, okay, to show you like
the example. So here I have my site map. I have my, what I call like, if I could mesh
it just an example. The effect you mesh basically it's connecting to, I hope it's not connecting
to my CMS. Okay. And you can see here on the content level, I'm clicking on this one. Basically
here we can see, provide me a component called loops that's allowed me to make reasonable
stuff and then it's okay. The first component is the template. Okay. And the template I
can say, okay, I want to connect it to something. The title, the title is connected to something.
Okay. This here, what you see, it's a note from my API from storyboard. Okay. How I get
that? I move uniform, come with a lot of stuff. First thing that you provide you is a component
layer. Okay. All the components that you saw basically are created here. So you can take
them, reuse them and use a building block like a CMS. Then with the component, you can
call what you call a composition. Composition is basically just aggregation of your component
or basically here are created pages. Okay. And then you have a third system called the
data type. Data type is basically your injector. Okay. Do you see all these mess? So they provide
your tool to be able to connect in one way in a standard way, every system that you want.
Here I will show you with my CMS. So basically here I'm configuring my CMS and I can go and
say, okay, I have multiple call and the call is really simple. Basically it's an HTTP request.
I can say what is the name. I can say where I want. I can create variable that can be
reused into the visual editor. And then here I can get that and connect everything. So
when you sort a lot, two minutes ago, what I'm using is basically a connection with that.
This gives you like the full extent completely when you have full power. But if you're lazy
and sometimes you come with an integration that already built, they have some integration.
One of them is you go here, have all these integration already available. You just plug,
unplay and they provide you into your system. You connect, you have access, you put your
credential and you're ready to go. Like for example here, I set up Shopify, blah, blah,
blah, and voila, I will remove stuff. But basically here if I wanted I can connect Shopify,
then basically it provides me information so I can just reuse and pick for example my
product magically, automatically. And then I get one endpoint where I can get the data.
One last thing that I would like to speak. Why this tool is also interesting is about
personalization and testing. So it's already built into the system. Because it's the orchestration
layer, you don't need to add like launch locally next to it because the handler did the personalization
for you, the handler already did the ABI testing for you. Voila. Do you have a question?
Before the question, we'll say thank you.