Okay, so welcome everybody.
My name is Alexander and today we'll talk about user interface library and the problem
of customization.
To give you some context, I'm a three years old React engineer and I'm working at MUI
during the day and during the night I was working for Open Food Facts, which is kind
of Wikipedia for food products.
At the end, don't hesitate to ask for stickers for both.
So for the few who don't know what is material UI, this is the homepage that you can get
what is a component we provide.
And we have the usual problem of user interface library, which is what the re-user want to
do with it.
So one aspect is making internal tools or small MVP, you work in NGO for example, this
is one project I'm working on.
I'm currently doing a lot of effort because you can see the colors are not the default
one, which is a lot better than most of the projects we're using.
But you also have a kind of a real website that do a bit more customization with the
library.
All the components are from MUI.
So you get a conflict about what is interesting for you because for me working out of the
box is super important.
I don't want to spend more than five minutes to set up a button.
If you're paying engineers, they can spend a bit of time on it.
Being big enough, finally, super important for me to get new contributors on the projects
for companies who don't spend time on onboarding.
Things about customization, I think the example before was clear enough.
So I would present you our perceived customization across my learning journey.
So I started into a consulting company and what you have to do most of the time is the
designer come ask to set up some specific colors.
And so you had a CSS specification selectors.
It has to be a bit more specific for some of them.
You have a class name.
You want to be again more specific.
You had another class name and it works by magic.
And one year later you will know that in CSS, the more classes you put, the more likely
you are to override the properties, which is called a CSS specificity for those who
are not aware.
For user interface library, this means only one thing, but all your style into one CSS
class name so that your user will be able to override them.
So here is one of the simplest components to override, one class with a meaningful name
and developers can override.
That's not all for customization.
Of course you need to respect to pass some attributes to your HTML, for example, to strictly
speaking disable your buttons.
And you can allow a bit more with React, for example, speeding custom props.
So that's all for me.
If you want to customize the style, it's CSS.
And if you want to modify the behavior, you will use props.
That's basically what you learn after a bit one year of development.
And for me it was the time to level up and to join a MUI.
So I was thinking, yes, I will walk onto those tiny components.
And the guys say, it will be slightly more complex, so you will walk onto the data grid.
Was a bit scared about at least being able to use it, but fairly simple at the beginning.
You define what is a role with a collection of objects, same for the columns.
You pass everything and the components magically do the stuff.
But of course such a component has a lot of features, and here is the problem of the complex
components being able at the same time for you to manage them internally, but also to
document them.
Because if you were just taking your component, put it into the website, it would be nice.
But of course they want to modify how the filtering is working or the seller wondered.
And they have very bad idea to test.
So here's one of the first issues I get.
So it's complex because you can open a filter panel.
Into this filter panel you can select on which column you will do the selection.
And they wanted to sort it by alphabetical order instead of the order of the columns.
It makes a lot of sense.
But the problem is how do you allow the developers to access this really specific rendering without
having to break everything?
If you're following what you learned during your first year, you say, okay, it's a behavior
modification, so I add properties.
And then you get a problem about all your documentation will look like in a bit one
year.
So you need to find a solution.
So there is three main solutions which we will talk about.
So the first one is a headless.
And basically it means you remove a problem.
You say I will not consider giving you the components.
I give you only the logics.
So you provide options here, for example, what are the columns, what are the data to
render.
And it returns you all the utilities function to quickly set up a filtering or rendering.
So you're not any more responsible of rendering the select.
So developers can do whatever they want in it.
So it's super customizable because you do not deal with the components.
It's clearly not out of the box because even the quick start examples are more than hundreds
of lines.
And beginner-friendly, yes and no, because you strictly give them like legal pieces.
Like they have a function.
They know what to do.
They can do whatever they want before, after, or with the results.
But you're also responsible to pass all the attributes to the HTML elements.
So you have to learn each of them.
If you don't know, you need to pass, for example, a label ID to be RER compliant.
There is no way to say you forget this specification in the component.
Another way to do is to provide the basic components.
The case here of React admin, which the name says it's an administration panel.
Basically this is how you define your administration panel.
You get a provider that wraps all your application.
And you define resources.
Which define how they will run the table.
Most of the time you don't want to get the default table because like always you want
to do some customization.
And so it's easy.
You define your own list.
So there is an example.
You can specify, okay, this colon ID will be text.
The category is text also.
Published at, it will be a date.
And so on.
And if you're not happy about the default way to render a date, you just remove the
date field and you create your custom components with smaller components they provide.
And you can go deeper and deeper as you want.
The idea in fact is that they provide the basic components as small as possible and
the way to wrap them all together, which is the providers.
And you get your application.
And if you know this image, you know that the result can also be this one.
This is a, so you know material UI so you will recognize the code.
It's a form control with an input and a select.
And just below it's a form control, a label and a text field.
It's a real code I wrote when I arrived.
And it was not working.
You can see the variant standard is not applied onto the text field.
And you probably already guessed why.
It's because the text field is already a form control with a label with an input and a null
product so without realizing I was putting a form control into another one, so it did
not work.
The problem is not that it's not working because it was my fault.
The problem is that I was not able to get any warning into the console to say, hey,
you're doing stupid stuff.
But that's because people can take all the components they want and wrap them in the
order they want and you cannot handle all the stupid ad cage that developers could be
able to do.
So you cannot prevent them from doing a mistake.
So here's a correction.
If you want an example, this is IKR page, fairly simple, but there is already six ways
of not to do.
And into documentation, developers do not already read the section how to do, so how
not to do, you are likely that they will never read it.
So customization is nice because you can already override your components.
It works out of the box.
If you stick with the default one, it's nice.
But it's not beginner friendly because you cannot prevent errors.
And there is another fact.
If you want to do customization, you need to understand how the providers are working
and it's super hard, one, to document and two, to explore.
You cannot say, oh, I can solve all the problems and I saw all the attributes that are available
and I guess how they work.
There is to use some provider and consumer.
So now the last one, which are the slots used at MIUI.
So if you remember, the first example I gave about a customizing button is to add an end
icon.
We can apply the same thing for custom components.
For example, I want to provide a custom filter panel, so I pass a props filter panel, but
we arrive at the same problems, an infinite list of props.
So we put some context.
So we defined the property slots and we will document in a specific place.
These are all the components you can override.
And that works, but this is a kind of basic filter panel with a lot of subcomponents,
a lot of logic and HKs that are already being solved and you want to take advantage of all
the issues we resolved.
So the idea is to provide also sub props.
So you say to my filter panel, which is kind of a box I can remove and replace by a custom
one.
I also want to put some inputs.
So for example, I want to provide the property colon is sorted by ascending order and the
default component might support it.
So of course, if you replace it with a custom one and do not support this props, it will
not work, which is a complex case.
But this is currently the solution to solve the initial issue sorting by ascending order.
So it's customizable because in the worst case, you remove the components and replace
it by your custom one.
It works out of a box because if you don't want customization, it's working and big enough
only because we have a single place for the interface between your code and our code,
which are the properties.
So you remove the components and you know props passed to these components is the only
responsibility we have to provide you.
You don't have to expect props coming from somewhere else or modification of the wrapper
because you see it has a new children.
So which one is the best?
I've already seen this question a lot of time on Twitter and of course the answer is there
is no best.
It depends on how many times you are able to spend on your project and how much custom
you want to be.
And there is a last solution, which is you can also not choose.
It's upcoming way to do it.
So for example, for a filter panel, you can use slots to override it.
So you have the way to say that your only props are your interface between the library
and your custom components.
You can use Atlas inside your custom components to say, okay, I know what I will get as a
props so I can provide you a hook that will transform them into helping functions.
And if there is a lot of elements inside, you can also provide the basic breaks to build
your filter panel consuming the, for example, your filter items, props that are provided
by the headless approach.
So there is a way to say, okay, you can do whatever you want with a filter panel.
If it's really common, you will just have to pass props.
It's more general.
If you want, for example, to modify the DOM, it's something like that when you have to
mix everything.
And if you want to do something completely different, you go to the trash and put your
own components.
And that's all for me.
Thank you very much.
We obviously have plenty of time for questions.
So who wants to ask the first one?
Hi.
First thank you very much for creating the data grid.
It has saved my job countless times.
My question was more related to oh, yeah, I don't want to.
Okay.
My question is related to another talk that we saw today called Pen Pot, which is an open
source version of Figma, basically.
And Mui has some design kits to use in different design tools.
Are you guys looking at Pen Pot?
Are you thinking about creating a design kit for it?
I would love to use it.
Thank you.
I have clearly no idea because it's a completely different team that is using it.
Okay.
Thank you.
Hello.
Thank you for the presentation.
Quick question regarding the design phase.
Did you consider about backward compatibility?
About what?
Backwards compatibility with previous versions of material UI.
Yes, but what is the relation with backwards compatibility?
So with its new major version that material UI has, usually there are quite a few breaking
changes.
So when you were talking about the considerations on the design phase about being beginner-friendly
and all this stuff, was backwards compatibility a thought at that stage?
I honestly don't understand how you want to provide a backward compatibility for such
a user library.
Sorry.
Can you repeat?
I don't understand what you're expecting to get solved by the library.
So you usually expect backwards compatibility so that every time that a major version is
upgraded, your code does not break a lot.
But that is not the case, unfortunately, usually.
As long as you do not go from one major to another one, it's working.
Okay.
I mean, we follow the same verse, so if you're into v4, you can upgrade as long as you want
and it will be working.
Okay, thanks.
Thank you.
While I walk up, I see a little bit of trash here and there.
So please, even if it's not yours, pick it up, put it in the bin.
Thank you.
So you showed us about slot props and slots.
You said that it was basically the best tradeoff between being beginner-friendly and customizable.
I was wondering what if you have really complex components, where the slot components also
have slots themselves?
Are you able to do this kind of cascade of slot props?
There is this problem sometimes.
It's problematic for documentation point of view because if you allow people to override
the sub-slot, they will not implement all the HKs, the interfacing with the props provided.
And after that, they want to just pass the props to the wrapper components and of course
it will break because they did not implement the internal ones.
And it's problematic, but you ought to say that the best way to mitigate is you do not
provide a slot for every component, just the stuff that can be considered as an independent.
For example, the filter panel is super easy because you have an entire piece of software.
You know it will get some filters in time.
It needs to update its value.
And that's all.
It's super clear.
It's the same.
You will not have a sub-component.
You want to customize except writing them by yourself.
So it's really rare when you have a sub-component into another one for slots.
Okay.
And for the rest, you are using props, I suppose?
Yes.
And I think for now, we do not do it because we don't need to reach this level of simplifying
customization, but I think providing the sub-components to do it is maybe the best way.
For example, we have a toolbar and the way to overriding is to provide a slot to define
what is the toolbar and we provide all the default buttons you could wish to put into
your toolbar.
Okay.
Thank you.