Hi, everyone. Hi, Fosdem. How are you doing? I hope that you're doing great. Yeah! Let's
go. So I'm really honored to present my talk about how I ported Doom to the browser with
Blazor Wasm. So it's a topic about another language, which is, we will see. So a quick
word about myself. So I'm Ehsin Benabas. I'm a dev rel at Wordline. I'm a teacher also.
And during my spare time, I love to play video games. So that's one of the things that made
me make this port. But before going further, let me explain what is a port. So game porting
consists of making a game run in another platform other than the original one. There are many
ports that are released nowadays. Some are good, some are bad, depending on how they
are developed. And it consists of adapting the source code of the original game into
the new platform. So adapting means that maybe we need to change some bits of the code.
Maybe sometimes it can be a whole rewrite, depending on the differences between the platforms
and how the game has been developed. And using a virtual machine or an emulator is not really
considered as porting. You really need to have access to the source code and adapt it
to the new target platform. So in the beginning, I wasn't really confident with making a port.
I considered it as a complex task, difficult. I didn't have a clear vision on what it is.
And what really gave me the first inspiration to consider porting games is modern vintage
gamer. Who knows about MVG? Yes. So he's a game developer, YouTuber, who makes great
videos. And just didn't expect it, but he made a video where he showed how to port Heart
of Darkness, one of the greatest games of retro gaming. And he showed how he ported
it to the original Xbox. So he made a video where he showed changing includes. So watching
this video really made me more confident in considering porting in one of my activities.
But that's not the only thing that gave me the idea of porting a game. The other thing
is I like to play with.NET framework. I really like this framework because it has many good
things. Some of them is that it's an open source, cross platform, general purpose framework.
So it runs on Linux, Windows, Mac, Android, iOS, a lot of platforms. And even other platforms
that I'll talk about now. And the main language of this framework is C sharp. So C sharp is
really, really good language that keeps evolving over the years. It has some features that
you can find in modern languages, null safety, extension functions, and this kind of stuff.
So it really keeps evolving great language. However, in the beginning of the framework,
the browser was not target. But in 2020, with the release of.NET 5,.NET introduced the
support the Blazor was framework. So it's a component based framework like Angular,
React and Jue with components. But the code of the component is in C sharp. And it runs
locally natively on the browser thanks to a WebAssembly stack, as you can see here.
So Blazor has WebAssembly implementation which allows the developer to access Razor components
and also access the.NET framework and also communicate with the DOM. So this is an example
of a Razor component. It's similar to what you see in Angular or Vue. The difference
is the code below is in C sharp. In addition to that, you can have also CSS, of course,
and you can even call JavaScript and it interoperates with C sharp. So when I saw this C sharp JS
which interoperates, I was like this. I was amazed. I was really happy to see this. And
I told myself it's time to make this port. So now I need to find a game to port. There
are many games with source code available. And the game that I chose, no spoiler here,
it's Doom. So I will tell you next why I chose Doom. But one of the reasons is that it's
one of the most successful first person shooters. And not footers, shooters, sorry.
And also technically speaking, it's well developed, in my opinion, because the logic of the game
is separate from the resources. So you have the famous WAD files of Doom. So it contains
the assets of the game. And you have really what updates the game state, the position
of the character, or the game logic in a separate project. So that allows to have Doom being
portable by design. And in terms of ports, Doom has a lot of them. In video game consoles,
of course. And even anything that has a screen and some processing, as you can see here.
And there are even more. So comes the reason why I chose Doom, because I found that there
is a.NET port already existing of Doom. Of Linux Doom, which is the source code released
by its software. And in GitHub, there is a repository which has developed a port of Doom
in.NET. However, this port uses libraries that communicate with hardware, like graphics,
audio input, which are not compatible with the browser. So that's why my work was to
take this port of Doom and make it work on the browser. So just to be clear, I used the
V1 of managed Doom, because currently they are developing a V2, which uses another library,
but just to be clear on my work. So to summarize, its software released the source code of Doom
for Linux. Since you developed managed Doom, which targets any platform that is targeted
by SFML, desktops mostly. And this is what I intervene to base my work on this port and
make it work on the browser. So before starting work, my porting, I made a strategy which
is this one. So this is an AI image, by the way. I taped Doom monster typing on keyboard
and I got this. So my porting strategy was to get something that works like proof of
concept that works quickly and to demonstrate quickly. So the first step is to take the
source code and compile it with the Blazor framework, as simple as it is. And as soon
as I see a compilation error, I delete the code and I add a to do. So another presentation
with to dos. That's fine. So after that, once the code compiles, I replace little by little
bits of code that are not implemented or the methods or functions that are not implemented
by giving priority to frame rendering. Because it's always nice to see something on the screen
rather than working blindly. And in terms of optimisation, I always left that to later,
unless it's really necessary. And in terms of reading documentation, so it's really well
documented how Doom is implemented, but I only read the parts which are really relevant
and important. Specifically how the Doom image is drawn on the screen when the frame data
is generated by the engine. And with this kind of porting strategy, like two or three
weeks of part time or set project work, I was able to achieve something, a port that
can be run, executed, even if it's not perfect yet, but we'll see in the demo later how it
works. Now let's enter into more details on how I ported more concretely this into the
browser. So first of all, before giving further explanations, let me show you how game is
developed most of the time. So it's a big, big picture of the game algorithm. First of
all, we have a while loop, which is an infinite loop, but it doesn't iterate as soon as possible.
It iterates only when the frame pacing is relevant. For example, if you have 30 FPS
game, this next iteration will wait a little bit if the first, the previous frame was computed
very quickly. So it allows to have frame pacing, which is correct and nice to the eye for the
user. So once the frame is ready, we get the user input compared to his previous frame,
really simple. And after that, we run a frame or we compute the next frame of the game.
So we run the update game state. It's just an example name of the method. It takes the
input of the user, the what file for the doom in this case, and then it advances the game
one frame. So it updates the player position, the monster position, the ammo, the status,
his life, all this kind of stuff. And it also generates to be rendered a frame and some
audio. And this is run. So for each frame, this algorithm is run and it updates the game
each frame. And once we get a frame and some audio, we play them and render them to the
user. So when you see this, you can start guessing which parts. So in the managed doom,
this all is done in C sharp. That's clear. And you can start to see which parts need
to be adapted for the browser, which are not available in C sharp, but need to go to the
JavaScript realm to be able to achieve it. But to show you what what I ported more precisely,
let me show this to the code in another way. So here, so we have the while loop and the
frame pacing step here. Next, the key, the user input is sent to the update game state
with the what file as argument. And then we generate some audio and the frame to be rendered.
And it loops. So this is what needs to be ported. What you see in red. So what you see
on the top is frame pacing. It's not really blazer relevant, but browser relevant. For
game for a frame pacing, there is a better way to base frame in JavaScript, base frames
in JavaScript. And to render, since it's not available in blazer, so this needs to be replaced.
Also the game states, which is also so everything in C sharp, if they can stay state, even though
it's a platform agnostic, it's not 100% the case. So there needs to be some bits that
needed to be adapted to the to the browser. But hopefully, 70% of the code approximately
was a cross platform and runs on the browser without any problem. So after some work, some
coding, some fun, some fails and learning, I achieved this result. So I replaced the
while loop with request animation frame. Anyone knows about request animation frame here?
Yes. So yeah, request animation frame is how you tell the browser, so I want to render
frames in an optimized manner for the browser. For example, when you switch a tab, don't
do anything to optimize energy. So you ask the browser, request a new frame. When you
see it's relevant to compute a new frame for my game, call me back. So it's a callback.
And for each frame, we call it back. After that, so once this has been changed, change
also the rendering. So for the audio, it's the audio context library. And for rendering,
it's the canvas, of course. So audio context is the audio API of the browser. But there
is one thing that I didn't mention yet that you see here is that in this state, since
I was, like I said earlier, Blazor is a component-based framework. It's like Angular view react. You
need to have some kind of main component, which is the entry point of your program or
of your component. So here it's missing. So that's why I added or I had to have a Blazor
component which only serves as the entry point to invoke the JavaScript, which then goes
back to C sharp. So this is C sharp. So when I say C sharp.net, I say them interchangeably.
So this is JavaScript. We go back to C sharp. We go back to JavaScript. So there is a lot
of context switching or language switching. And this is achieved thanks to this API. So
Blazor provides an API that allows to go back and forth from a language to the other. So
this is Blazor way of doing things before.NET 7. Starting.NET 7, there is even better
way to do this. I'll show it at the end of the presentation.
Okay. So now we have something that runs. So I will show you, quickly show you for the
audio parts, some code, and then I will continue the last or maybe just the entry point and
then continue the presentation. So this is the main component, as you can see here, which
in the code, so we have the canvas here. And here we have, we initialize the Doom object
or the game object. And then here we invoke the JavaScript method that calls request animation
frame. So we invoke the JavaScript method here. We here handle the frame pacing. Okay.
Here we handle the frame pacing. And then we call back.NET to run an iteration of the
game, the Doom engine, to run, compute the frame. And then we call request animation
frame to prepare for the next frame. Which calls back this method. So this is like an
infinite loop. And this method that you see here, which invokes.NET code, just invokes
the game object and the request set to render a new, to compute a new frame with the user
input. So this, I will just skip it. So this is how audio and video are rendered. So it's
communication between C sharp and JavaScript. And I continue. So what I learned from this.
In Blazor, avoid copying arrays, big arrays. In the beginning, in the dot manage Doom source
code, the final image is generated by copying, converting a one dimensional array into a
2D array. So this slowed down the game a lot. A lot, a lot. So I removed this part from
the manage Doom source code and I sent it to JavaScript. That's what you, what I was
shown in the previous slide about frame rendering. And I don't have to cover it. But yeah, avoid
copying big arrays in.NET. This is in.NET 5. Maybe in.NET 7 it has been improved. Avoid
extensive logging. And calling JavaScript from Blazor communication can be very fast
if you use the correct API. As I said, however, this, the API that I used is undocumented
and I confirm it because I found no documentation, just some source code or some obscure GitHub
repositories. But hopefully.NET 7 it's improved. In JavaScript, I learned that request animation
frame is the way to paste frames. And to play audio programmatically, you need to have some
user interaction before or the audio context API doesn't work. So here is the demo. Okay.
So I click to enable the audio, the user interaction. And let's see. Yes, of course. Yes. And here
we go. So just to show you that we have sound. So don't be afraid. It's just a game. And
just to show you that you also have secret passages. I don't know if you know this one.
You have 200 hours. But that's another topic. And it runs correct frames. It's 2012 MacBook
and it runs at 30 FPS. No problem. Okay. So that's two slides. The interrupt in.NET
7. So here is how interrupt works now. You don't need Blazor. It means you don't need
to create component if you want to interact between JavaScript and.NET anymore. And I'm
working currently on this part because it's really exciting to see this kind of work.
So to call JavaScript methods from.NET, you just need to export your JavaScript method
as you do in any JavaScript module. And you call here, you just import the method and
you have access to it. And in the opposite sense, you just export your.NET method and
then you import it in JavaScript using this kind of code. And that's it. So I'm working
on changing how the game is ported to this. And in terms of next step, then, it's to migrate
to JS interrupt, update to manage Doom v2. Maybe I will gain some more performance. After
that, I would like to have some game music and also to be able to play otherwise. Currently,
only the Doom one works. I don't know yet why. And as long term, I really also wish
maybe this can be integrated to the official manager Doom project. So as a conclusion,
Wasm makes existing code compatible with browser. It means that, I mean, Wasm is not just the
very fast JavaScript alternative. It also opens the way to make many, many languages,
many, many technologies run on the browser. So that's really what I like. What's really
exciting for me, at least about Wasm, and porting games is fun. Developing is fun. Do
you agree? Yes. Thank you very much. Thank you. So we have time for a couple of questions.
Who wants to ask the first question? Hi. First, thanks a lot. It was really, really
insightful. Thank you. I have a question about request animation frame. I think I saw, so
because request animation frame runs at 60 FPS, right? And then I saw you do something
with timestamps to try to do 30. Yes. Does it ever drop or become inaccurate? Or is that
the right way to achieve 30 FPS? Let me just go back to the, yeah, I guess it's maybe,
I'm not JavaScript specialist on this. Me neither. I'm curious. It's here, I guess.
Yes. It's here. For me, it worked. Yes. I didn't have eyes here. That's what I found
on the internet. I tried it. And everything in the demo doesn't drop. When it drops, it's
really when there is a lot of things happening, when there is a lot of audio, it's still not
optimized a lot, the audio part. But this frame pacing, for me, it works. So you compute
the duration between the last request frame and the new request frame. So for me, it's
okay. Excellent. Thank you very much. You're welcome. Next question. Yeah. The next speaker,
who is speaking after? Nobody? Nobody is speaking after. I mean, who is taking that seat who
are standing there? Okay. We'll call them. It's a follow up to the previous question.
Have you tried removing this check and see how fast you could run the game? Can you do
1,000 FPS? No, no, it's not 1,000. I actually tried to remove, but don't remember, but not
1,000 FPS. For sure. It's certain. It's not really, really fast. Also, like maybe 240,
50 FPS. It depends also on the machine. It depends on the hardware that you have. On
the processor hardware that I have, I don't have gaming computer. It was like maybe 40,
50 FPS. Okay. Thanks. But yeah, yeah, that's a good question because you see when we talk
about good ports, bad ports. For example, this, I mean, it's a quick to achieve port,
but it's not the most optimized one. So that's when you see game companies making ports.
And also, for example, when I said that the array copy on.NET is slow. So same time,
if you don't have time to optimize, you just leave it as it, and you get a crappy port
with slow frame rate. But I did the effort to at least make this part in JavaScript.
Welcome. So next question. He's going to ask more if you don't. So he's ready. Go for it.
Yeah. Another question is what is the size of the wasn't files or whatever that needs
to be downloaded to play this game? It's big. It's big. Let me show you. I don't know. It's
how to, like this. It's a big file. It's a big file. So let me inspect. When you go to
application here, you see the storage. You have like 21 megabytes. It's a big file. It's
not huge. It's not like Windows when you start on DevCorp. It has a little bit of overhead.
But it's not downloaded each time, you know. Maybe the first time. But yeah, that's a good
question. Yeah, that's a... So we can have one last question. And in the
meantime, all people are still thinking, please don't stay on the edge of the lines because
people are standing in the back. People arrive a couple of minutes later. So if you're at
the edge, if you're here and there is an empty seat, you need to shift just a bit. And you
can also optimize this by making a service worker. I did it, but it doesn't work anymore.
But you can also make... catch this as a service worker. So...
And now if you're here, if you're seeing me looking at you, please shift a little bit.
I don't do this for the pleasure of annoying you. It's because there are people who are
going to enter the room. We're going to have more and more people, hopefully, who are going
to ask written questions. So then please let them sit next to you.
Also there is a trash right there. So when you exit the room and if you see something,
even if it's not yours, please pick it up. There is another trash there.
Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you.