Hello, everybody. Thanks for being here. I'm so glad to be here for them. That's the first
time in three years we're in person. So, yeah, I'm so glad. So, I'm Julien. I work at Mozilla
for like ten years now. So, you can find me on Mastodon, you can find me on Twitter, you
can find me on Matrix, you can find me in Paris. And of course, Mozilla, you know that
so well. We are responsible for Firefox. It's high performance, open source, privacy conscious.
So I'm sure you already have it on desktop. You have it on your phone. So you link them
together and use your history and your password. You know that already. Mozilla is also famous
for the NGN, of course, for your audio development fantasies. And for the VPN and for Firefox
monitor. Lots of good stuff. But today I want to talk about the Firefox profiler. So you
can find this slide deck here and with the QR code as well. And let's dive in. So this
is the thing I want you to leave the room with today. First, I want you to know what
a profiler is. I want you to know how you capture and how you can share a profile, how
you can share a profile with your colleagues, but also how you can share a profile with
us Mozilla in case you have performance problems with Firefox. And finally, we will do a quick
tour of the UI so that you can have the first glance of how you can analyze a profile. So
first, the Firefox profiler, as is the UI, is just a web app. It's a React-based web
app with no privilege at all. It's used as a service worker so that it works offline.
And it's also an open source project. You can find it on GitHub. You can do contributions.
You can look at the source code. You can even adapt it for your needs. So, yeah, come and
do some React-based contributions with us. So first, what is a profiler? So, oh, yeah.
I was scared by this cat because it's so big here. So, yeah. How do you measure performance?
You can measure it on three different places. You can measure it locally on your computer.
You can measure on the CI with automated tests and benchmarks. And you can measure on your
user's computer. This is called real user monitor. But there are also different timings
characteristic, right? Locally, you get the results right away. New profile, you look
at it, you get the measure. On the CI, you can get the result after maybe one hour. And
with the real user monitor, of course, that takes a few days. And the profiler, this is
locally. So this has some advantages. Of course, you get the result right away. But this also
has some drawbacks that we'll dive into later. So basically, this is a tool. This is just
a tool in your toolbox. This helps you analyze performance issues in your application and
or in Firefox. But here it's more for your application, for your JavaScript or CSS stuff.
This gives you insight and clues. But this is really a detective work. When you have
a bug and when you have a performance bug, that's the same. It's just a detective work.
You have to look at the problem from different angles with different tools with console.log
sometimes. And always this tool can make things easier. But it's just a tool. And, yeah, that's
something I think the most important with performance is that if you try to guess, you
will guess wrong. Very, very commonly. Like, you know the web, right? You get some property
on some DOM element and suddenly you get a full reflow of the whole page and it takes
a few hundred milliseconds. And you can't see that really clearly with the code. So
with the JIT, with the JavaScript virtual machines, the JIT can optimize it for you,
can optimize a lot of good things. And for other things, they will just be very slow.
And it's very difficult to know in advance. So, yeah, do not guess. Try to measure, being
with the Firefox profiler, with the Chrome profiler or anything, even with performance
that measure or with timer in your code. But try to measure because not everything is always
‑‑ it can be confused on the web. All right. So now I'll try to do a live demo.
Let's hopefully that will work. So I will show you how to capture a performance profile.
Let's switch to that view. So this is a view of the profiler. But don't pay attention to
the UI right now. Just because I have a bug. A bug was reported lately. This is very slow
when we do a panning here. Like when I pan here, it's not so slow right now. Because
the resolution is slow. It's smaller here. But it's quite kind of slow here. So I want
to measure this. I want to profile this. So what I'm doing is first I'm going on the profiler
website. And there is this handy button here. Just click here. This has a profiler icon
on the top with a bunch of settings here. So you can use ‑‑ there is a setting
title for web developer here. Or you can profile the whole navigator if you prefer, the whole
browser. You can use nightly. You can also edit settings here. You can change the interval,
for example, if you want to reduce the overhead. Or you can change some features. I will maybe
talk about that later if I have enough time. But now I will just start the recording. And
I will run my scenario. Like that. And then I can capture. And I get a view into what
happened here. So we will dive into the UI a bit later. And I will zoom in also because
maybe it's a bit small for you. But I want to just to show you that you can also upload
the profile then. Of course, there can be personal information in anything you can show
from your browser. There can be things about you and how you visited, about the tab that
you have currently open. Maybe there are some tabs you don't want everybody to know. And
there can be tasks on your local computer. So you can disable some of these things. So,
for example, I will remove the, yes, the thread that I don't see here. I can upload here.
The Wi-Fi works surprisingly well today. And then you have this ND URL. You can take this
URL, give that to your coworkers, and this will open exactly the same view with the same
profile. And so this is very handy to discuss that with your colleagues. And some of you
can have different understanding of different parts of your code. And so you can have different
views like that. You can also share this URL with Gecko developers. If you have a problem
in Firefox, you can open a bug. Put this URL there. And that will help the Firefox developers
solve problems that you may find in the browser. And finally, because that's your data, you
can also delete it. There is a delete button here. You can delete the data that was uploaded.
Because otherwise it's public. You need to understand that it's very public. Of course
you need to know the URL. But otherwise it's public. There is no password, whatever. So
you can delete it when you don't need it anymore. So now I come back to the talk. We'll dive
into the UI a bit later. But first I want to explain how you actually get that. You
need to isolate the problem as much as possible. Like if you have a lot of tabs, lots of websites
in background that are running stuff, the problem you want to test can be isolated and
maybe there will be some different differences just because you have some websites in background.
Because you're building something in background of your computer. And that will skew the result.
So try to isolate the problem. Try to have a computer that is not too busy at that moment.
When you get the data, you try to ensure that the results you get are the ones you kind
of expected. You can look at the screenshots, see if this is the thing you actually wanted.
And you can keep recording. There is not one truth. There is several truths here. Depending
on if your system wasn't in the best shape at that moment, maybe you need to record again
so that you have something that you can work with. So now I want to go into the captured
data. So we have two types of data. The first type of data we do is sampling. So what we
are doing is every interval, every millisecond here, we look at what the current program
is executing. So we look at the stack. Here is an example of a program that starts with
main. This is the main function of a program that we call A, that we call B, that we call
C, C with returns, et cetera. So this is like a normal program calling normal functions.
And every millisecond, we look at where we are. So here we are in A. No, we are in main,
sorry. A, we don't see it here. Here we are in B. So we are in B, but we are also in A,
right? And we are also in main. And then at this point, we are also in B, in B, in A,
in main. Here we are just in main, for example. And here we are both in main, in A, in B,
and in C. And then so we take all this data and then we squish them together, which is
a technical term to mean that we aggregate the data. So we squish them. And so we show
this information as a form of a code tree like that. So that's basically the same. So
if I take, if I come back here, we can see basically main, we spend 100% there, right?
It's the same function in the world program. In A, we spend maybe 70% there. And in B,
we spend maybe 50%. And that's what we see in the code tree then. Here, the one at the
top, we spend like 98% in it. But we spend also 56 samples in, right in this function.
So the difference between this column and this column is that this column is this function
including everything it's called. And this column is this function only, excluding everything
it's called. Another view is the flame graph. The flame graph is the same data. It's just
more visual. The time we spend in one function is the width of a rectangle. The one at the
top are the one where we are at one point. So very visually, we can see where we spend
time. So here we can see we do a lot of convex rendering stuff. This is exactly the scenario
I was playing earlier, by the way. So we see that we're spending some time on the convex.
And we are maybe redrawing too much stuff at that point. So we can dive into that later
also if we have time. I don't know how much time we have. Okay. So yeah, sampling is a
view into the program that is currently executing. But we can miss things. Like you've seen here,
because we do only every millisecond, we can miss some of the codes. And maybe they're
important, right? So in this case, we see only ones because it was a bit longer. But
the small ones here, we don't see that. This can be missed. So that's why we can instrument
the code. So Firefox itself is instrumented for important things like the reflow, the
new styles, or the GC, or things like that. But you can also instrument your own code
with the performance timing API, performance.mark and performance.measure. You will see that
in the profile. So that's what we call markers in our little technical jambons. Some of the
profiler codes are events. And we get, like, another view on what's happening in the program
here. So for example, we see all DOM events here. This one is the mouse movement, because
that's exactly what I was doing, right? I was moving the mouse while I was panning.
So I get mouse movement that are pretty big, actually. 30 milliseconds for one event. That
means we spend maybe too much time there. We also see all the user timing, because the
code of the profiler is instrumented to add performance.measure any time we do some converse
drawing. But you can also see things that's happening inside Firefox. We can see, for
example, the restyles here, the reflow here. We can see some GC. We can see when it's awake,
or when it's idle. So we can see all stuff, more or less complicated. We want to make
this view a bit simpler for web developers. Currently, you have still everything. And
you need to probably ignore part of this and just focus on what's important for you, like
DOM events or restyles and graphic stuff. But it gives a quite... You get all the stuff
here. So you can dive into how Firefox works. You get the animation stuff. I don't have
animations here, but you can see CSS animation. You can see the target of this event. So yeah.
Those are pretty interesting. There are limits. As I said earlier, you're measuring on your
own computer, and this also has drawbacks. Your computer, as a developer, usually it's
very, very performant. You have the best CPU, and you have a sheet load of memory. And so
this means that the performance on your computer might be different than the performance on
your user's computer. And also just the act of profiling itself can skew the results.
Because by inserting markers, for example, we need to lock the memory in some place to
insert the data there, and we need to capture the stack sometimes. And this takes a lot
of time. And so that can skew the results. We try it to be constant override, but it
starts always the case. So there are limits. And you need to sometimes take a step back.
Sometimes what you're looking at, it's not an absolute truth, right? It can be... Yeah.
It's just a tool again. It's not absolute truth. You can take a step back. Maybe what
I'm seeing is not exactly the truth. Yeah. That's about it. So more and more about the
UI now. I will show you how we can navigate in this UI. So you can put that full screen.
It's not this one. Yeah. Full screen. And zooming a bit. Okay. Come back at the first
one. Okay. So what we have at the top... What we have at the top... I can't use the laser
because I have to use the laser that reloads everything on this computer. So I don't use
the laser. I use my finger. So at the top here, you have what we call the timeline.
It's a chronological view of what's happening. At the top, you can see the screenshots. You
can even hover them and get to see what's happening. So here I was on the first tab,
and then I go to the second tab, and here I'm scrolling them, scrolling it and panning
it. And yeah. That makes it possible visually to see what's happening and what was your
scenario. And then you have a bunch of tracks here that are interesting. The first one here
is the parent process. This is the process that is for the UI of Firefox. That's not
very interesting in your case. There is also the localhost here. This is localhost because
I was running my UI on the localhost so that I could get the name of the functions. They
are not minified because we don't support source maps yet. That will happen hopefully
this year. But currently, we're not supporting that. So if we want to see the functions I'm
profiling on the development version of our application, which also has some implications
because, of course, the development version does use the development version of React.
And development version of React is slower than the production version of React. So again,
taking a step back is always a good idea. Knowing that, we can dive into what's happening.
So I can dive into this part because that's where things are happening, right? There is
nothing elsewhere. So here you have what we call the category graph because the colors
might correspond to some categories. Like the blue is dumb stuff. Yellow is JavaScript
stuff. So here we can see that we don't do a lot of JavaScript. We mostly do a lot of
something else. So dumb, in this case, is Canvas stuff. I will switch to JavaScript
actually. Yeah. And then we see that we are doing the field stack stuff. So we see the
stack when we hover, right? So we see this is a full stack of React sheet stuff. And
then at the end, we just call field rect on the Canvas API. That's where we are here.
And so I can hover and have just a sense of what's happening. Also, I'm also setting field
style here, for example. And I can click there and just select whatever is below. So this
is basically a way to navigate into this profile. There is a red stuff here. The red stuff means
we spend more than 50 milliseconds on waiting on the browser to catch up. That's probably
the path where we want to zoom in, by the way. So we can do that. I can click there.
I can zoom in here. And I can look at what's below. So below is what you can see. So there
are a bunch of tabs. The first one is the code. We already explained you a bit of that.
Then there is a flame graph. I can show the flame graph by clicking. It's better. Right?
This is something I was showing up earlier. So I can also hover and see what was the stack
and have an idea of what's happening here. The stack chart is chronological way of looking
at your data. So here we can see, for example, I think we can see that we're rendering twice,
I think, for example. So we're doing twice the same thing. And I think we see that more
here. Like for one mouse move here, I have two render here. So that's how markers are
handy, all right? You can hear it. It's clear. It's clear that for one mouse move, we do
two render. And we shouldn't do that. So I guess I fixed my program here. I need to route
to... So then I need to look at the code. Of course, that doesn't solve everything. But
I have an idea where to look at my code. It means probably that I changed some state and
some React component and that does a new render. So we need to look at the code then and see
what's going on. Because this is just a tool. This doesn't solve everything. But that saves
a shitload of time to find the right data. So let's come back at the slides. Okay.
Some more advanced topics now. We also do... So the advanced topics are less exposed for
a reason because they're also less finished, less polished. You can enable this stuff from
the edit settings button that I was showing earlier. And one thing you can do is memory
allocations. So we have two types of instrumentation for that. And I think this is working only
in Firefox. One of them is you can see every allocation is happening in Firefox. Allocations
and deallocations and things that are written that are not deallocated but they should.
So you can see all these and where they were allocated to. And also another one is the
JavaScript allocation. And that works also in Redis, I think. So you can have a look
at the documentation here.
The one thing that could be interesting for you is we have an importer for Chrome and
Node also. So you can take the JSON of Chrome, put that in the profiler from the profiler
homepage, and then you can do all the things I was showing you earlier. You can share it.
You can zoom in maybe better than in the UI of Chrome and use some transform that I didn't
explain today. But advanced stuff you can do with the UI we do, that Chrome counts.
And that's a parenthesis. Chrome tools are also very good. And that provides a different
angle to your application. So because it's a different browser engine. So on Firefox
and on Chrome, maybe it makes sense that they don't work the same. So they won't show the
same thing. That's interesting to use both tools. And the one in other browsers too.
But you can import in Node tool and share with your colleagues. That's pretty interesting.
And you can also compare profiles. So there are some documentation in Node docs. So that
makes it possible to see the impact of a change. Like you think you fixed a problem, you can
compare the profile before and after and maybe check that you actually fixed your problem.
Because as I said earlier, you need to measure. Sometimes you think you fixed it and you didn't.
Or maybe you fixed one part of it. Like you fixed one state change. But there was another
one elsewhere. And so there is still an update happening. So my conclusion now. Again, the
most important thing is measure don't guess. I think you will remember this sentence. This
is just a tool in your toolbox. And yeah, sometimes you need to take a step back. You
can use a profiler to debug. I don't think it's much on that. But because you can instrument
your code, you can also use it to just debug your code. It's not just for performance.
You can just get a view of what your program looks like. What's happening in your program.
And finally, you can share profiles with your team. Especially when you're distributed,
like we are at Mozilla. You can share it, put it on metrics or ISC or whatever things
you're using. And go to a Zoom call and talk about that together. And thank you for being
here at that time of the Sunday. So you can find a Firefox profiler website here. Documentation
also here. We have a metrics channel. If you have questions, if you have a question about
a profile you want to ask or help to analyze it, come here. Ask us. We will gladly help
you. And this slide you can find them here with this QR code. So happy to answer questions
now. If you have questions. Thank you. So the microphone is here. There
is a question there. I am very curious how you ensure security of the profile information.
Because if I am on my usual admin account and I am debugging and all the network information
is there, it will have all the tokens and everything. All the API responses. Probably
half the API keys because I'm debugging stuff. And somebody nefarious with a strong Russian
accent could be waiting and just iterating over all the possible URLs all the time. And
how do you deal with that? So we, so the question, let me refer to the
question. What about the security? Because you can have API keys in the capture data.
Yeah. Right. For example. So yes, that happens. But you can, when you share a profile, you
can click the, uncheck the thing, include URLs and that will remove everything related
to URLs. So you won't have that anymore. We don't capture our headers and all that currently.
We just capture the URLs. So if you remove. Even in the network configuration?
Yeah. Okay. Okay. So it's not like the normal.
Thanks for the talk. Small question. I believe there is this kind of the same tool in the
performance tab of the Firefox developer edition DevTools. Is there any difference between
the two programs? Good question. I wanted to mention that I
forgot. There used to be a performance panel in DevTools. We removed it. Now it's been
replaced by this one. But we still have a performance panel in the DevTools. The same
thing except that when you open your DevTools, you have some overhead. So our recommendation
is that you use the popup like I've shown here. Okay. So general recommendation, use
the profile, the external profile. Okay. Yeah. You can have to profile your Firefox
on the way and you can profile remotely like that using the DevTools.
Small other question. Are there plans to add support for like flame graphs generated from
perf, for example, for native applications just to use it as a kind of a viewer for other
perf not related to the web? Yes. So we have an importer for Linux perf.
Actually, we have some documentation about that. There is also the fantastic tool by
Marcus, which is somewhere here. Called Simply. That is very well integrated with the profiler
to profile native applications to. So it's called Simply S-A-M-P-E-P-L-Y. You can compile
it on your computer. It's made in Rust. And this is just an amazing tool to profile your
native applications to. So you can try that. Hello. It is the way to profile a full stack
application. I mean the front end and the back end in the same time.
You can't do that in the same time currently. What you can do is you can profile with, of
course, the full stack. So it's probably not in back end maybe.
Not on Python. Or Python. So there is a tool called Function
Trace that I don't know well that is using the FIFR profiler to profile Python applications.
I don't know much about that. So I don't want to say too much things about that. So currently
we can't do what you're saying directly. So sorry.
Last question and then we'll close the room after, of course, all of us pick up all the
trash that would be left if any. Thank you for the talk. Is there any plans
to add support for importing P-prof files, which like some profilers output?
Can you repeat that again? Sorry. Are there any plans to add support for P-prof files,
which like for instance Go produces as an output of the profiler?
You mean to have output of, no, I think I didn't get the question. Sorry.
The output like the P-prof file format, which is used for profiling.
We're looking at P-profs with this viewer. Okay.
We don't have really a plan, but it's easy to, I mean easy. It's not very easy, but it's
possible to write converters for our format. The format is very well documented.
So we have converters for Linux P-prof, for Valgrants for Mac with DHAT, I think, for
Art Trace for Chrome. And currently that's all, but we also have a Next-Time Converter
for ETW from Windows and for I think Gper for GVM stuff.
So it's possible to do converters. We just need somebody to do it.
But if there is enough interest, maybe we can look into it or at least help somebody
do it. Thanks again.
And I don't know if you're going to be hanging around outside if you want to chat.
And there are lots of stickers. And there are stickers.
Thank you.