Thank you.
All right, so let's continue with one of our favorite topic which is dependency injection.
So we talked about it this morning.
As you can see, we have a lot of topics.
We have even more topics until what time do we finish?
6.30 p.m., right?
So 6 p.m., 6.30.
So we still have a lot of stuff coming in.
But for now, please welcome Arnaud who is going to talk about coin.
Thank you very much.
Let's talk about new Kotlin developer experience in coin.
Just about me, I'm Arnaud Jugiani, the lead maintainer of coin project and also Kotlin
GD.
Coin is a dependency injection framework and the idea is to help you structure your application
with ease and efficiency.
And this is the challenge of providing a DSL developer experience for you to make your
app very, very easy to build.
I tried to explain coin in just two minutes to explain how finally we improved behind
that.
As we have a dependency injection framework, we want a bunch of classes here, one A and
B with a dependency.
And we have a DSL keyword here that make the configuration space for us.
And this is a module keyword that introduce the way that we have definitions for the application.
Single keyword with a lambda function to create what we want to create the class that we have
here.
And the second one to declare the second button and then we are done.
We have declared our components inside the coin container.
The thing here is that it's working directly with your Kotlin code.
That means that here if you follow closely, we are using constructor directly.
And then it's not compiling.
Then that means that this class B is needed a dependency to class A. And then this is
where we need the last keyword that is get.
And then the challenge was that in three keywords, I can manage to write an application configuration.
The thing is that then coin can create everything by constructor for you and also run any kind
of Kotlin code directly behind the functions.
The other side of coin is that you can inject any field easily just by unlocking an extension
with the coin component interface.
That means that you can access to the by inject function that helps you retrieve a dependency
out of coin container.
Then you have both components.
Those one that are created directly by coin.
And when you can't have things created directly by coin, then you need to inject in fields.
This will perhaps remind you some of the Android activity things like you can't create activity
by yourself.
You can't create Android component by yourself.
You are called by a lifecycle.
Then you need to retrieve things from the outside of the container.
And then that's it.
You mostly have all the tools to have your dependency injection.
You need just to run and start your container.
But finally, the experience is interesting.
And the community raises many things like problem of verbosity.
Because sometimes in application, you tend to have, like, dozens of dependency.
I would say perhaps look at your code.
Perhaps you have kind of potato effect where you can have everything inside one component
and try to gather everything.
But yeah, not that great for us.
This is where the story starts for us and how we can improve this for the Kotlin developers.
And then from this really simplistic example here, what we have here is we would like to
avoid all the blubber to write manually the get things.
The idea and the need of get is that coin is made to be super efficient.
We don't use reflection.
We don't use any kind of meta data information over your code.
We just run the thing.
And then the configuration seems to be a bit manual over there.
But then you are manually writing the things for coin.
The new magic way finally to write this with coin is having a new keyword, single and single
off.
That is the same semantic keyword.
But we did a new function.
And then instead of asking you a lambda, we want to ask you a function directly.
This is why you have the double semi-colon character.
And then for us, you don't have to write things we get.
It's still readable, still very easy to use with the coin semantic, the sense, the meaning
of the DSL.
And then also it's consistent with changes in the meaning of, for example, if you change
the constructor of a class, your DSL can break because you didn't update it.
Then for us, it's a very great improvement to go over a DSL that is using lots of functions.
But finally, not a value to write those functions directly as a lambda, but directly with parenthesis
and this pointer kind of pointer function stuff.
The other side of coin, of course, is having dynamic behavior that are interesting, is
that you can pass data directly to a definition.
That means that in this class, we just want an ID.
And what we want to do is pass this ID dynamically to this component.
Coin offer you the way to do that directly when you inject a field by using the function
parameters of.
And then magically, your data is growing into the graph and then is injected in your definition
directly by this function.
This is very visual, interesting, but then this compact way of having the DSL also is
capable of dealing with your lambda expression.
Then you don't need lambda anymore.
It's quite interesting because finally, this was this feeling of having coin as a really
compact DSL and compact way to describe everything without to invade your implication.
Is now, it avoids an annoying side effect of the DSL and now you can just write directly
your class constructor like that.
There's of course some warnings.
If you have qualifiers, name parameters, like if you have two components that have the same
type but have not the same implementation, then you want to have the different name for
them.
Then here, we can't guess which one you want to use directly.
Function and classes that have different values, we don't know.
We don't know if you want to use the default values.
If you want coin to use this, then up to you to use again the lambda expression thing.
Also any kind of complex expression like builders, yeah, it's still cut in then for you.
You can just still use the lambda when those expressions are needed.
Else, go with this double semicolon character expression and then just use the class and
then you're done.
Mostly, keep the things up going in the easiest way to write for you.
It's opening a door for us like we are framework maker.
We try to understand what kind of DSL and options we want to offer you.
For example, when you're defining something in your DI, you can give it a name, a qualifier.
We can say that it's created on start.
For example, the container is starting, then you can create it on start and also you can
say that it's binding another type.
All of this is interesting, but it's not really easy to extend in terms of keywords and binding.
For example, you don't know if there is other keywords after the bind because we are already
using some lambda, then a function to express something.
Do we open a new lambda block after the lambda block?
It's a bit weird things.
With this new DSL, we can open a new way to write this function.
That means that we can directly open a lambda, there is theory for this option.
We have a name, we have created at start and we have bind.
This is the same world, but not implemented in the same DSL style.
Here this is functions directly out of the definition thing.
Clearly, you see it's a bit more readable for us.
It's clearly more maintainable and allowing us to add more features at time.
It's really interesting to provide a new way to write things and also feedback of the community
is super interesting for us.
One of the things also is that coin is really simple and keeps the things really simple
in terms of DSL that means that you declare anything in terms of module.
You can scale in the way you want by features, by layers, by everything, then up to you to
organize yourself.
Really, the idea is that the tool shouldn't impact your mind, it shouldn't impact your
way to build your application.
You should even forget that you are using coin.
This is really important for us to continue in this way.
In coin, the framework never had the need of gathering modules other by list or by let's
say something more common by your plus operator, but it was really simplistic.
The problem is that with scaling application development, scaling around all the development,
meaning really strong links between definition, between re-easibility of this component, this
layer and this stuff.
We finally introduced something that can be seen as really simple to add as a module is
that we add the includes function that help us really understand what kind of module we
want to reuse and then flatten everything that optimize your loading at start for you.
It may be visually, it may be really easy to use, but when finally at the beginning
for coin, you only have a list of modules to play with, it's kind of really hard to
reuse and really hard to figure out where finally you can build your configuration.
Then we are unlocking a really big door that means that you can begin to reuse parent modules
with chime modules, with chime modules and then you can begin to dive into really, really
complex big and complex configuration things.
Then for you, we are flattening all the graph, we are loading and optimizing all the stuff
for you.
Then all those Kotlin Multiplatform, all of these features are Kotlin Multiplatform ready
and to get those superpowers, sure, you can grab these directly in your Gradle file.
It's not 3.2 versions, time is flying, but 3.3 and if you are making a Kotlin Multiplatform
application, use the coin core module, Gradle module and if you are using Android, then
use the coin Android module version.
Coin has been made to make your development super easy and super simple and this is why
your coin configuration should stay really simple for you.
I let you meditate on this quote from Chet Haase.
The transition for us is we are trying to use another kind of expression in terms of
framework is that until now we were really people that pushing a lot for Kotlin DSL,
DSL stuff, etc.
The idea of perhaps introducing annotation is also to not reproduce what you can find
in other frameworks like Dagger and others, but truly point something, we want to bring
value.
The problem of also the DSL is that we clearly have some limits over that.
We can't understand really what you are writing, we can't trigger any static analysis of your
code directly.
That came to magic to the Kotlin compiler plugin.
I won't dive into details for that because I believe some people already talk about KSP
and everything about that, but let's say that Kotlin compiler is everything we could do
for you before we are compiling your code in Kotlin.
Then we could rewrite things, we could make code generation, of course, analysis, etc.,
etc.
What we will do with Google KSP is provide you a way to avoid the DSL and go really straightforward
with annotation and keep all the coin semantic, all the coin API for you.
We don't want to reinvent the wheel.
What we want to do here is that we want to generate what the DSL you would have to write
and then it's really, really, really a small piece of code that you would have to write.
Then if we can still avoid you to write things in your code, this is still a good experience
for us to let you understand how we can go.
In terms of definitions, what it means is that if you have a class, then you can just
add directly an annotation, you see that this is the same keyword we have, the add single
on it, and then you see that we are extending an interface.
The idea is that with just one annotation, we will understand that this class is having
a constructor and then we will also bind directly to type my repository.
The idea is that we allow you to have not to type anything in this.
We detect things for you, we detect the code and then we can say, okay, coin, just write
this definition for my repository type with the implementation of my repository.
We have another component.
We target add factory.
Factory is another keyword of coin is where you want, it's the opposite of a singleton.
A factory is something you want to create each time you want to ask a definition for
that.
If you want an instance of my presenter directly, you just type it add factory and then coin
will generate the DSL and then coin will manage to go to and get the definition for you.
You see finally you don't really care about the DSL and the complexity behind that.
Finally we can detect many, many things for you.
Finally for those who are making Android development, we have a add coin view model annotation dedicated
for coin that lets you understand that, let coin understand that we will create an instance
of view model.
Then we are reaching all the dependencies.
We understand that this is a view model and then we will bind everything for you.
You see that here we don't speak about DSL.
It's just that we tagged something here and the idea is that we can have automatic injection
and binding.
We can detect everything, all you need here by default.
We can deal with new label type.
That means that if you use the question mark in parameter construction, then we will understand
that this is something that can be new label and then for you it's completely transparent
and then it will be taken into account.
Also, as you have seen, we can tag a parameter in a function or in a constructor as injected
param.
That means it will be something that comes from the application that is sending a data,
a dynamic data directly to the definition.
Then the natural way to do that will be to tag a parameter as injected param.
You see that finally the experience for us is to try really to let you write the minimum
and the minimum things for you.
For example, with DaggerHit we still have lots to write, lots of things to specify.
For example, in the Spring framework, this is the kind of opposite because Spring is
scanning everything for you and making all the class pass analysis for you.
Then we are in between where finally we allow you to just tag your code with just a bunch
of annotation and then you're ready to go and you can manage any kind of tip of injection
with your constructor things.
The idea behind of the magic is that just you use annotation and you are ready to use
the standard coin API is that you can use by inject or by view model field injection
as tidy hair.
We don't break the experience of people that are already using coin.
Then we allow people that are using annotation directly to use those extensions as regular
extensions.
For the modules then, for definition we just tag annotation, we annotate classes but for
modules we can't directly tag something in the DSL.
How works KSP is that we are scanning from many classes or functions then it will be
kind of hard to tag around the DSL.
The proposal for now is to work directly with class module to let you have an organization
module for that.
How you do that, you declare a module and that's it.
You have a module, you have a hard module and the idea is that you put add component
scan and then we will scan any kind of component that has been tagged in your application by
package.
Then it's really specific in terms of scan.
That means that you can really filter by package, filter by layer, filter by features, how you
want to organize yourself and then you just have this annotation here.
Also, if you want, you can declare things directly inside a function.
Like we will understand that if you would tag something inside your module class it
will be a definition that we can bind for you directly.
You see it's still very, very natural to use and really super compact.
The idea is for us to let you go super fast for your dependency injection and keep everything
a side for you.
Of course, between two modules you can have the includes of other modules that will generate
the right things for you.
That means that it will use the includes function that has been introduced just above in the
new coin DSL side.
Then we just need to start coin.
That means that you have your module, you have a function where you want to start coin
and then the idea is we just run the module with a new instance of my module here.
The only thing we want to generate for you is that it's just a simple extension that
will generate the DSL and this is where we just want to make boundaries for us.
We don't want to reinvent the wheel.
We don't want to reinvent things to generate code over code.
We want to keep coin as it is, something that is super efficient to make dependency injection
but allow you to use the annotations.
This is why with such approach you can mix both.
You don't have to write a new project with annotation, you can already use coin annotations
inside your project and test with it.
The only thing you have to care is be sure to have the right import.
That means that we are generating all your coin content inside of.coin.ksp.generated
and then you can use both DSL module, class modules annotated and everything, everything.
Then up to you to express yourself and use the right tools that is great for you.
What is interesting for us is that we don't want to reproduce what we have seen and why
we have made coin is that we don't want to expose you to tools that can take dozens of
minutes to recompile your project.
The idea is that it should run for thousands of components really quick.
The other good thing about that is that behind the scene it is coin generated and this is
something you can clearly debug step by step if you want.
Up to you, that means that we don't want to replace DSL by annotations.
It's another way to express yourself.
KSP is a good technology for us to help you write less, less quads equals less bugs.
Then up to you to choose the right tools and the right solution to make your app structure.
To finish then about coin and some improvement of this here, what's next?
If you want to slow down about coin, we have many tutorials on many kinds of Kotlin application
from Kotlin, Kotlin Media Platform and Android application.
This is the roadmap for 2023 where we have end of track 3.2, 3.3 is the active track.
This is the current application that is still maintained.
Before the next release where we are in 3.4, where we want to focus on compose for the
JetBrains multi-platform side.
We want to bring better experience for Kotlin native and we have the verify API that is
a new verification API that lets you make a compile time verification.
Of course we are keen of Ktor and we want to push new things about Ktor.
Especially today at first then, this is my first session at first then, I'm really happy
to show all the people that are really sharing and contributing to coin and clearly want
to thank them.
Thank you all the community to work on coin.
I believe some of people can find themselves on this board.
If you want to chat with the coin community, then you can either find us on Twitter, on
Slack, the Kotlin on Slack and also you can go on the website that is in sartcoin.io to
find all the related sources that you want.
Also open source is great but you need a strong company behind that to help you and have support
on your project that is helping with coin technology and Kotlin technology.
This is why I founded Cozila last year to work with the people that are using such technologies.
Then you can find all the resources on Cozila.io and write on time.
Thank you.
Then we have time for questions.
No question there.
No, sorry.
We don't have time for questions.
We are so strict on timing.
The next talk will start in four minutes actually.