So this is more of an entertaining talk, let's say.
It's a lot less technical, probably a lot weirder, I would say.
And hopefully I'll go fast enough so that you can have all the crazy idea questions
at the end.
And even a little demo, I have some hardware with me if you didn't try VR, at least I
think today you should try this if you feel like it.
So that will be, like, say just there where it's fresh.
So I will...
So those are my slides, it's a JSON file, yes, why not.
I will start by saying that I gave a couple of workshops to kids, actually, on discovering
VR.
And that was pretty nice.
I thought initially I would give workshops and give, you know, a rollercoaster.
Some kids asked me about murdering clowns on top of a rollercoaster.
I did not prepare this, I admit.
But that was interesting, different inputs.
I think it's a really interesting way also to consider teaching computer science, programming,
because I was saying there my pine watch, like there is a computer everywhere, that's
just a computer.
That's why it might sound weird, it might be a little bit outside of people's comfort
zone but in the end you can program a computer, you can program that.
So I will introduce myself a bit first.
So my name is Fabien, I work mostly at the UPN Parliament as a web consultant, so I just
do VR and AR on the web, that's it.
And I do it as a prototypist.
So meaning all the tips you had or the suggestion you had at the beginning of the day on the
TypeScript, on quality code, I don't know any of that.
As I was saying before, you're chatting with somebody at the entrance, if my code runs
during the duration of the demo, I'm happy.
The next day, yeah, it's a bonus, but that's the length mostly.
And I gave a couple of talks here, at first, on connecting exotic hardware, like the watch
or IoT, everything of course using JavaScript.
And this one will be on how to do this on a plane in a VR headset.
So my motivation behind this is I have a bunch of notes, I have a wiki, that's the wiki,
and I have a, you can still hear me, the 2D visualization of it, but it feels flat, like
I don't want to have my notes in my molysceen or I don't want to have my notes behind the
thin screen, I want them everywhere so I can play with it, like I organize the space.
So for this, I already had a couple of versions, I used Mozilla Hubs, so a little show of hands,
how many of you tried VR at all?
Okay, I would say two-thirds, half two-thirds.
How many of you tried Mozilla Hubs?
Okay, five, six.
So it's a social VR experiment, it's a pretty good solution, to be honest, works quite well,
and you can do this, meaning you can be in a VR headset with your hands moving, you can
be on laptop, on a mobile phone, and you can see this shared virtual space, it's using
3GS for the 3D environment, and you can have PDF, you can have your webcam, you can take
screenshots, you can honestly do pretty much most of what one would want to do.
So I did quite a few hacks, so modification of it, it's obviously open source, that's
the interesting part, but it's not enough, so you can do a bunch of hacks, so I explained
a little bit how, for example, I turned on and off the lights in my office while I'm
in VR, director kits on how to record with traveling, a bunch of different things, to
the point that I did my little toolkit on how to customize, yeah, that's not going to
work here, so you will have the link on the page, so imagine a bunch of functions related
to Hubs to do all this, so I really think basically here the point is Hubs is a good
solution, it works quite well if you want to do just social VR.
The thing is, first of all, it doesn't work offline, and I started after the end of the
pandemic to start to fly again to go see family, and I thought that's one of the best use cases
for VR, like I don't like being on a plane, I don't know if you do, but I think if you're
the pilot it's fine, but otherwise as a passenger it sucks, and one of the beauty of those things
is you put the headset on and you're basically somewhere else, but I don't want to be in
VR on a plane and do a roller coaster or something, I just want to code, I want to be there and
be able to do something that I have agency over, I want to build stuff, I want to create
things, and I don't want to be like this, I want to feel like I'm somewhere else, then
I started to build on that, including, let's say, managing the history in my browser, so
I would take a snapshot of the different pages that I visited, be able to organize them, the
thing is, as you might be able to see, this doesn't look at all like Mozilla Hubs, so
Mozilla Hubs is amazing, but it's a huge stack actually, and it's a stack that depends on
AWS, which I obviously don't have on my plane, or the plane I'm playing with, so then I started
to rebuild it from scratch basically.
One warning also, when you saw it here, programming in VR, I had a discussion with somebody just
yesterday about it, it might be productive, I would say, at some point, but that's not
my point, I don't find that interesting, I have a really nice desk at home, it moves
and all, and I have my ergonomic keyboard, and I can move my 4K screen, I like it, but
I don't have that on the plane, so the point is, being able to move in space when I have
the space, and if I don't, to be able to use the space around me in a really compact manner,
so the point is, this whole argument is like, don't look at this presentation thinking,
is it to replace the way I work today?
That's not the point, it might be if you enter it, but it's more exploring what could be
interesting in terms of interfaces, so yeah, word per minute, if you're trying to sit next
to me with your laptop and we do a competition of how efficient you are, you're going to
win, I mean, I hope for you, but that's not the point.
And I was able actually on the plane to make friends, because the person next to me was
like, what is this guy doing with his keyboard on the tray, plus there was no USB-C on it,
so I need to plug the adapter, put it on top of the device, and then put, it was not wireless
back then, so now I'm pretty happy, I just received this little thing, so it's a Bluetooth
keyboard and it's, you can hear, mechanical one, that's way more efficient back then,
I didn't have this, so yeah, that was a good excuse to meet someone and chat about what
does it actually mean to program in VR.
The next step being actually tinkering with it, so I went from having the history of my
browsing behavior, let's say, to moving content and moving content by just pinching basically
a page, so that's a render of a page, that's not a web page itself.
What hopefully, I don't know if you can see all the way there, but basically with my right
hand I was, I'm able to move things around, and with my left hand I'm able to execute
code, so that's, let's say, the main trick, there was one thing you need to think about
that presentation, it's about moving things around freely or naturally, but also you will
see the, so I move things, the red sphere there, and then if I pinch on that piece of
code, the sphere there is blue, so it's not just moving things around, but it starts too
many text, which takes this code, and then code can change the environment you're inside
of.
And the one trick to do this, I will hide it away, but you can guess, how do I execute
code in JavaScript?
The one thing you're not supposed to use, evil, because it's evil, I think that's the
one use case when you can use it, when your string of text is actually code, and you're
not running a bank or something like this, like this is my code running on my headset,
I don't have anything that I won't accept to break, let's say, but even then it's executing
locally, so that's the one reason, in my opinion, to use it.
So the idea behind it is, oh, I can manipulate text, that text can be code, I can change
that text directly while I'm in the headset, either pinching it like single letters, or
with a keyboard to be more efficient, and then I can execute it, which is going to change
the whole environment I'm inside of.
So the trick for it was basically what I like to think of, the escape valve, which is to
say that, yeah, I could redesign an entire programming language, I could make it a programming
language for VR, but I can also rely on one I already know, and that already has an engine
in it, so namely JavaScript, so that's a little, let's say, trick, so I'll show a couple of
examples, but that was an excuse not just to manipulate text and this code, but then
to start to make my own programming language, so how many of us here have made their own
programming language?
Yeah, I see, I see, there are very few hands that are like this, most hands are like that,
I'm like that too, I don't think, honestly, I feel a little bit, maybe not ashamed, but
I'm not proud of it either, what I'm trying to convey is the endeavor, trying to do it
is super interesting, I don't think I've learned as much recently as trying to do this.
I also recommend, if you check the slides or the presentation after, don't learn my
programming language, I don't think it's a good one, it's a very interesting one for
me by building it, by seeing the limitations of my understanding of what a programming
language is, but so this, why do I recommend this course specifically?
It's because he's not going to, let's say, let's do an alternative to C, which for most
of us would be too far and not practical, he's basically saying, well, JavaScript is
a language, the browser will notice an environment you can already work with, you can transpile,
you can use Babel, and that's enough, let's say, to get the foundation of what a programming
language is.
So I really recommend this kind of course if you're considering making your own programming
language.
And also, I don't know how many of you are familiar with this book?
I don't think I can go back easy either.
So yeah, if you ever try to learn, I think, the foundation of programming and programming
languages, usually you often do it with Lisp, which works well because it's so compact that
you can keep it all in your mind, basically.
But again, most of us are not familiar with Lisp, and even if we are, then it's not what
we work with on a daily basis.
So, SAP, but the JavaScript version has been out for a couple of years now, so if you want
to learn the foundation of a programming language while being familiar with the language itself,
I really recommend it.
It's quite taking, but I think it's a good investment.
So then I'll show a couple of the features of the environment, but I won't show all of
them, go too deep in there.
But then what's interesting is you don't have just one line of code, but then you start
to have groups of lines of code or history, the stack of which you executed.
Of course, because you're in VR, code is not everything.
So for example, some of the code is about loading a 3D model.
So if you pinch it again, you execute that line of code, you get a 3D model out of it,
and then you can do it a couple of more times.
You get, I see that the contrast is not high there, but you get the history of what you
just executed, then you can save it and execute it again.
So you start to have the same, let's say, primitives you're used to.
And then you can do shortcuts, you can visualize the groupings.
So for the people who twisted their hand instead of raising it, this is also where I'm at in
the sense that I don't actually know if it's a fair thing to call this a programming language.
Is it just like a bunch of utils, a bunch of shortcuts?
I'm not sure.
Again, what I find interesting in that process of making a programming language is, yeah,
it's up to you.
It's up to what you find interesting, it's up to what you find efficient.
So yeah, I start, try to document it, stack back a bit, but all what it prompts me to
think of is really, really interesting, really valuable.
And also, if you don't go down that route, there is a subreddit for it.
There's a subreddit for pretty much anything, but yeah, for r slash programming languages,
where you can ask simple questions like this, like what is the most interesting aspect of
it?
So of course, I had to admit that so I display my issues from my repository in my environment
so that I can move them like as if I was on a wall.
I can display 3D models from, let's say, a library of 3D models.
This is where I can organize it, like tiles, and then start to make a 3D environment to
work out in of.
I can do honestly this part, the graphs.
I mostly did because a friend asked me during lunch, I was like, this is annoying.
Everybody find graphs sexy.
It is looking good, but I'm not sure what the point, so just, okay, I'll just make a
graph.
So those are actually the pages of the wiki where I'm taking the notes out of the display
there, and they're all manipulable.
Taking screenshots also in VR, I think that's a great way to document if you're doing a
process.
Of course, you can have the code out of it.
You can save it back to your wiki, for example.
But the movement, how things are going to be organized and how you want to, let's say,
organize the tiles to make the 3D world.
You want to tell a story to someone who might not have, no one to use a headset, then just
taking a screenshot, capturing it, and then sending it elsewhere.
It's a pretty efficient way to do it.
That was just this morning.
So there's the same thing of managing issues, displaying the issues from the repository
line.
I can, again, grab them, move them into places.
But using Swagger, if you're not familiar with Swagger, it's an API to manage all APIs.
So once you have access to when you load using Swagger, yeah, I can load from GitHub, whatever
is going to have a Swagger specification.
And that means making them as, for example, manipulable blocks.
It's federated, so it's social, but if you have your own server, then you can connect
to it, and we can be friends.
We can exchange code also, so I can move the code in my environment, and you can receive
it and execute it.
One port that is kind of funny is snapping, so those are blocks.
You cannot hear it, so you'll have to trust me, but when the blocks are close enough,
you hear them snap.
The points of those blocks of code, or blocks rather, are not just blocks, is you can attach
code on it.
So then you can manipulate them literally like Lego block.
Once again, the part of the interactions that become interesting, yes, you can have a keyboard,
and the keyboard works well, but if you just do the keyboard, yeah, you could just use
a bigger screen if you always not that interesting for it.
If you can have both programming with a keyboard, when naturally manipulating, or simply, let's
say, directly manipulating with your hand, I think that become, again, interesting.
So again, you need to imagine those are not just blocks or blocks of code.
It's called, let's say, for Swagger, so that you can get information from an API or execute
through that API.
So why also do I do all this with blocks?
Because I think that's a great way to learn.
So you can imagine this, the blocks for running code that is abstract, let's say, list things,
but you can use that for chemistry.
Let's say it's a C, and it's a C, or it's an H, H, and an O, and you bring them together,
and they snap when it makes a molecule.
I think the same kind of things apply to pretty much any field of study.
So physics, chemistry, sociology, like you have a set of atoms and a set of rules.
If you get them to have a certain organization specialized together, then you can learn this
field, hopefully, in a more embodied way.
Nope, I guess that's going to be it.
I have a Twitter archive, because it's not working properly, but not for recent things.
Well, okay.
So that's fine.
All this, I think it's pretty interesting.
The one thing I'm even more awkward with, rather than calling the thing I've done my
programming language, is this.
So that headset is an Oculus Quest, or a Meta Quest.
I don't have a Meta account.
I don't think it's, yeah, I don't think civilians' capitalism is a good business model, let's
say, as a society, but it works really well.
So that's pretty awkward.
I really don't think it's such a good thing.
I called it an adversarial dependency, because it helps me to build more, explore more, than
on something I don't want to rely on, because it's not aligned with my set of values.
So I still show all this, because, yeah, you won't see the photo, but there are a couple
of headsets, like the links, that should be there in a couple of weeks.
The point is, don't associate VR with just Meta or Facebook.
It is a convenient one, but there are alternatives coming out.
There is also a similar VR.
It's not the only way to do VR.
So adversarial dependency, in the sense that, yes, you can rely on it temporarily, as long
as you can have it just as a replaceable block.
And as long as you can swap it, whenever you get something that's more aligned with your
value, that is much better.
But that's it, yeah.
The whole point of this is building your own scaffolding, being a programming language,
using a tool chain, using VR, because I find that to be the most interesting interface.
But yeah, that would be my recommendation for you.
Just make your interface, make your scaffolding using VR or not.
And if you want to try the VR one, I'll be around with it.
Thank you.
I think we have time for a couple of questions.
Questions?
Do you have any questions?
I really like the VR experience in the play.
But have you thought about the incidents that may occur, like hitting my neighbors, punching
him?
No?
Thank you.
Yeah.
So I don't recommend punching anybody.
But you're not good.
So you define the interactions however you want.
So basically, if you put things, let's say, to the object, either a block of code or a
hat, whatever, a meter away from you, you're going to punch your neighbor.
But because now you have access to the code in there, you can just say, oh, I bring, let's
say, everything within 50 centimeters radius.
And yeah, you can just do it on the spot.
Again, it's using WebXR.
So it's VR and AR on the web, meaning there is no unity build.
There is nothing there.
Everything is done directly in the headset.
You can put your node, your server, your even your Python server, whatever you want to run.
So it means you can refresh the page.
And then you have your new content and your way to handle it.
So either you do it without even having to reload.
But you can fix it on the fly, let's say.