Thank you.
Hello, everyone. Hello, again.
So we are going to resume. If you are in the back, please come
in.
We have seats in the front. And please make sure to make
yourself comfortable for this next talk.
Where I have the pleasure to introduce Russell.
Russell is coming all the way from the USA to be with us
today. He works at touch labs, knows everything about Kotlin
and the real world.
And we will talk about the real world.
And today, we will tell us about from hello world to the real
world.
Yeah, thanks a lot. Yeah, I'm here from Boston where it's
actually like negative 24 degrees Celsius today.
So I'm all right with the rain.
And yeah, my name is Russell Wolf.
And I'm going to talk a little bit about the basic kind of
hello world example that you might start out with to the
sorts of things that you might need for a production
kind of app.
And I've been part of the work at touch lab, I've been doing
Kotlin multiplatform things since pretty much day one.
In a couple weeks it's going to be five years since I wrote my
first Kotlin multiplatform code.
And I'm going to talk about the other things I've been doing
for a long time.
And I'm going to talk about the first Kotlin multiplatform code.
Which is kind of cool. I don't know. It hopefully means I know
something about what I'm talking about. But you can let me know.
So let's get started.
So quick introduction to Kotlin multiplatform.
And I'm kind of breaking up my talk, breaking up the talk by
the way.
And I'm going to talk about the
Kotlin multiplatform code.
So Kotlin grew up initially as a JVM language.
But it also has back ends on JavaScript and native.
And all of these are actually kind of
a
very different kind of code that you can do.
And it also has a lot of code that
involves but the ability to share code between them.
So you have platform code that runs on a particular target.
And then you have common code that runs on all of them.
Or runs on combinations of them.
And it's a lot of different things.
And you can do it with a lot of different
things that make sense to share.
But you have the ability to drop into
platform code for things that you don't want to share.
And it lets you treat your shared code as basically just
another library.
So you can be writing what would otherwise be a native app and
share just a piece of it.
Just takenowing and telling the
NET
customer and talkinggal V
and
Ear Capitol inside of them.
requirement with cases in Clbusters.
Because KMM in the end is just like parts of KMP,
it's just kind of working on the same technology stack.
But in terms of what they're focused on for the developer experience,
KMM is kind of the piece that's coming first.
And yeah, as I mentioned before,
it's recently moved into beta,
it's planned to go stable this year.
So it's a really good time to get into it,
to start using it if you haven't yet.
And what beta means to
JetBrains can be a little bit different than you might be used to from other projects.
They're very slow about designated things as stable.
They want to be absolutely sure of every little detail.
But even by calling it beta,
they're very strongly committed to keeping things working.
They're just saying there might be some breaking changes in the future.
And to break down how Kotlin Multiplatform code works,
I like to use this Venn diagram and focus on the mobile use case.
So we're talking about Android and iOS.
So if you're an Android developer,
you're used to this diagram.
You have access to all the Kotlin APIs you're used to,
you have access to JVM and Android APIs.
And there's a subset of that,
just the kind of pure Kotlin stuff that in principle you can run on any platform.
Which then means you can take that over to the iOS side,
also add some iOS platform specific code.
So you have your shared bits and your platform bits.
And the KMP tool chain brings all of that together.
So that essentially each of these different colors on the diagram are just
a different source directory and the tool chain knows how to put the right parts together,
so that you get the right code for your platform.
And again, there's more to KMP than just KMM,
but the eight-way Venn diagram and everything is a lot more complicated to draw.
So what does it look like when you're writing your first Hello Worlds in Kotlin Multiplatform?
And one way to get that is to start with the Kotlin Multiplatform mobile plugin for Android Studio.
So you can do a lot of this stuff, I tend to use IntelliJ idea more than Android Studio
when I'm doing my KMP development.
But the new project template in Android Studio is a little bit easier to get started with.
They have these Kotlin Multiplatform application, or Kotlin Multiplatform library.
And what they give you is some code that looks kind of like this.
And don't worry about every little detail of it.
But this is kind of like the Hello World template that it generates for you.
So there is a platform interface in the common code.
So the common code is in the center here, the Android is on the left, the iOS is on the right.
So there's a platform interface that's implemented on each platform as Android platform and iOS platform.
There is a expect function.
So expect and actual are two keywords that Kotlin Multiplatform adds to the language that
essentially let you declare something in your common code but implement it in your platform
code.
Essentially kind of like a header.
I mean, actually they use the header keyword for it before how it was released in 2017,
2018-ish.
And so there's an expect function that you kind of get a default platform that has actual
implications on each platform.
And then there's a greeting class that just kind of brings it all together and prints
the name of the platform that you're on.
And this gives you a little playground to start messing around with Kotlin Multiplatform
code.
And I actually really like there's I like the way that they use expect actual in here.
It's very easy when you have this new tool starting out with Kotlin Multiplatform to kind
of overuse it.
I mean, you start making all these like expect classes and things like that.
I tend to find it's really nice to also use like to hold on to interfaces as well.
So when you define an interface platform rather than an expect class platform, you can substitute
other implementations a lot more easily.
And so this this is kind of like a rough sense of the code structure that you get from this
template.
So the the clue that I showed you is kind of this bottom three boxes.
So there's common code in the middle is the orange orange.
There's Android sources in that that you then compile to an Android library.
There's iOS sources that you then compile to a iOS framework file.
And then if you use one of the application templates, it'll look at you in that player
that consumes that.
There's multiple ways that you can configure configure the iOS app to consume it.
So you can, which essentially there's there's different dependency managers that you can
use in iOS.
The there's a default that's just kind of manually include the framework.
You kind of add a custom it at a custom build step in Xcode that will call into Kotlin and
do that.
There's also a plugin that's part of the Kotlin tool chain that uses CocoaPods.
So CocoaPods is kind of is the has historically been a commonly used dependency manager on
iOS.
It's these days starting to be replaced by Swift package manager.
The Kotlin tool chain doesn't have as good integration into SPM yet.
And then also just call out we at touch lab have a sample called camp kit that can also
be a nice kind of place to start out if you're if you're playing with stuff for the first
time.
It's a somewhat more complicated sample than that hello world.
It has a bit more kind of architecture to it and shows kind of some of our standard
architecture and library practices.
And also has a bunch of documentation kind of explaining why we make some of the choices
that we do.
So check that out also if you're interested.
So what are kind of some common themes around these sorts of starter projects?
And there's a lot more than just those two I should say also.
There's lots of people out there that have kind of put together interesting Kotlin multi
platform samples that you can use when you're first learning.
And something that comes up often in a lot of them is they tend to aim at maximizing
shared code.
Which like in an ideal world is really nice.
In the real world, oftentimes you're starting from two separate native apps and you want
to incrementally move towards more shared.
And you don't always get a good sense of what that looks like from any of the standard samples.
These also tend to be mono repos when you're looking at starter samples.
So what if I already have existing apps that live in different places but I want to start
sharing code between them, what does that look like?
A big piece of a lot of them is there will be some step in your build process in iOS
where Xcode has to manually call and have to exclusively call into Gradle to build your
Kotlin.
But if you're on a larger team, you might not want to have to do that every time.
Your iOS team might not even have a JDK set up if they're not used to using them.
So what do you do in that case?
And they also tend to be single module when you're looking at sample projects.
But what happens when things get bigger?
So that brings us to, yeah, what does it look like when you take all these sorts of things
and start scaling it up to real world projects?
I'm going to talk about some of the ways we tend to think about this at Touchlab as well
as some tools and things that we've put out into the community to help out with some of
these things.
And the first thing I want to talk about is team structure.
This is something we've been talking about a lot internally at Touchlab recently and
building out this sort of taxonomy of different ways that different teams approach the way
that they handle their shared code.
And a common kind of core piece of that is being thoughtful about the ways that the structure
of your team impacts the way that you want to organize your code.
Because lots of teams are very different.
The distinction I'll kind of highlight here, and it kind of works across a couple different
dimensions.
I tend to think of it as kind of small teams versus large teams.
But it's also sometimes teams that work kind of as one unit versus teams that work as multiple
units.
And a key piece of that is often is the group that is writing the shared code the same group
as the people who are consuming the shared code.
So when you're a smaller team or if you're one unit, you tend to have kind of fewer worries
about who's owning what parts of the code.
You're more kind of unified in what your developer setup looks like.
And you're more likely to be in a situation where you're kind of sharing a higher percentage
of things and just kind of wrapping a thin UI around it.
And you're more likely to be doing all of your feature development kind of at once for
both platforms.
On the other hand, when teams get larger, things get a little bit messier.
You're more likely to have IOS specialists who don't want to kind of deal with the Kotlin
directly.
And your Kotlin code, you're more likely to have a larger IOS app than just what the Kotlin
is.
So you might, like your Kotlin is just kind of one more thing in a sea of other native
libraries that your iOS app is using.
And you tend to want to minimize the impact of your Kotlin on the rest of the iOS code.
And what this means in practice is you want to kind of rather than linking your XO build
to your Kotlin directly, you want to kind of publish it as an external library.
And sort of so the diagram that I showed you that kind of diagram on the left earlier,
the way it can look like in a larger team is rather than directly consuming things,
your shared code is being published to some sort of repository.
And then your apps are pulling that artifact down.
And there's kind of more of a two-step process to making updates.
But it lets you kind of work in separate screens more easily.
And we put out a tool to help with this in the fall.
We touch lab.
It's called KMM bridge and it's a gradle plug-in that can essentially manage the publishing
of your iOS framework in a couple different ways.
So it gives you a gradle task to publish a new version when you've made changes.
It has options around how you implement that version and things like that.
Options for where you want to host that binary and the ability to plug in your own.
And then some helpers if you're using so package manager for making that local development
flow a little bit easier.
So sometimes you want to be able to toggle between using the binary that you pulled down
versus building it directly when you're trying to write new code or debug it.
So we have some helpers to make that flow a little bit easier.
There's a bunch of little things that are still kind of a work in progress on here.
If you're a team that's interested in using it, we'd love to talk to you and get some
feedback.
So feel free to find me and let me know if you want to learn more about that.
Another problem that comes up at scale is monetization.
So when you write Hello World, it tends to be one module.
But when you're writing bigger things, you might want to have more than one.
And Kotlin native, it turns out makes this a little bit complicated.
So when you have multiple Kotlin native modules and you export them to iOS, they're essentially
their own kind of separate worlds.
And so each of these modules has its own copy of any internal dependencies, its own copy
of the standard library, its own copy of any third module that you might have underneath
them that you're trying to share between them.
And they can't kind of talk between each other very easily.
And this can be okay if they're doing very distinct things.
So maybe one of them is making all those calls and one of them is running your database.
And they don't really need to interact with each other.
And then having them separate can be okay.
But often you end up wanting to kind of write this umbrella module on top of them so that
in your Kotlin layer, you can have them talk to each other more easily and then you have
sort of a shared module on top that you export as your iOS framework.
And that lets you more easily have that more typical kind of modular structure while working
with the Kotlin native limitations.
There's still some messiness to this because your umbrella framework will have you have
kind of namespace clashes where all of your declarations in here are essentially in one
giant global namespace.
And there's roadmap tickets that will improve this.
But right now it can be a little bit messy when you have a lot of code in there.
Another thing that comes up in real world projects is your binary size.
So hello world tends to be small, real apps tend to be larger.
And real apps have consequences when things are too large where things like the app store
will throttle your downloading or force you to do it on Wi-Fi rather than on mobile if
your app gets too big.
And this can be a significant impact to the amount of downloads that you get.
And it turns out one of the biggest contributors to this is the Objective-C interface that Kotlin
native uses to export your code to iOS.
And the kind of trick to use here is you want to limit the amount of public declarations
that you have in your Kotlin code.
And that will shrink that Objective-C interface because it only needs to be generated for
public declarations.
And that hidden from Objective-C annotation that Mark mentioned earlier can also be a
way to do that.
Or there's kind of different monitoring structures you can sometimes use.
So I'll mention quickly a couple other tools that Taut
that you get out of Kotlin native doesn't export to Swift very well.
So we have this tool called Crash Kaios that will essentially symbolicate your stack traces
better.
We have some updates to that in flight that will clean up different pieces of that story.
But I'm not going to go into detail there because I'm getting low on time.
And we also have an Xcode debugger that lets you debug your Kotlin code from Xcode, which
can be a nicer environment for your iOS developers when you're kind of introducing that.
That recently to be a CLI-based interface, which makes it much easier to update and install.
So if you've tried it out in the past, feel free to give it another look.
One of the things I want to talk about is kind of the shape of your API service.
So how will the app tend to be small?
But as your app gets bigger, you start to care more and more about what sort of the
how would you manage your API?
And Swift and Kotlin tend to want slightly different things with that.
So I just want to point out, like, don't be afraid to kind of need a bit of translation
layer between your shared code and your platform code.
And we have some tooling that we're working on to make some of that easier.
But it's not in the open yet.
So I'm not going to go into detail there.
I'll skip the example because I'm running out of time.
But kind of the overall lesson that I want to highlight is different teams have different
structures and want slightly different things.
Kotlin is all about adaptability.
And so if you're a team that wants to share a lot of code, you can do that.
If you're a team that wants to minimize the impact of the Kotlin on the rest of your domain
team, you can do that.
And you have the flexibility to kind of choose the way that you want to approach all of that.
So thanks.
I think I'm probably out of time for questions.
But I'm definitely happy to answer stuff in person.
Feel free to tap me on the shoulder.
Find me whatever later today.
If I'm staring at my laptop, it's not important because it's Saturday.
So I'd love to chat.
Thanks.