So, hi everyone, welcome back to the next talk.
Today we have on stage Anna Labellarte and Paolo Ratolo from Nextome talking about Kotlin
Multiplatform for Android and iOS library developers, I guess it was.
Now, yeah, gonna talk about it.
Thank you.
Yes, I'm Paolo and it's a very pleasure to be here with you.
We come from Italy, we come from a small company in the southern Italy and we decided to introduce
Kotlin Multiplatform in our code about a year ago.
We did this because for us it was easier to develop and also we wanted to share as much
code as possible.
We make libraries so we didn't have the part of UI to transpose in Multiplatform.
And this is our journey in the Multiplatform world.
Now, we've seen during this conference that with Kotlin Multiplatform mobile we can develop
a library that targets both Android and iOS by just writing a single code based in Kotlin.
Now, if you look at what happens when we distribute the jar inside an Android library, we can
say that the process is pretty straightforward.
Now, for an Android developer the language is the same, the ID that uses is the same
and most of the library that we can use are the same.
So we can't tell the difference between a library that was made with Kotlin Multiplatform
mobile and one made with the native tooling.
Now, things are not quite the same when we talk about the iOS part.
So if we distribute a framework, the process is not so straightforward.
And many of the problem arises because the code is converted for some Objective C and
then most of the time we'll be using side projects that has drift as the main language.
Now for a drift developer point of view, sometimes what can happen is that they can find the
API that we expose is just strange.
And this is just a base case scenario.
Other times the app made a crash and this is due to some differences that there are
between the two platforms that aren't automatically translated for us by the compiler.
So we will see during this talk what we can do to what happens when we distribute the
framework and what we can do to make libraries enjoyable also for the iOS part.
Now let's start with a simple example.
So in this case we talk about coroutines.
So inside our common code we can use coroutine.
So we can have a function like this, which is a suspend function because it performs
some operation with the network and some interaction with a persistent layer.
Now on Android we don't have many issues because if we have a coroutine scope we can launch
the coroutine.
But what happens on iOS when we don't have the coroutine library?
Now this function gets converted by two alternatives.
The first one which uses a completion handler, which is basically a callback that gets called
either when we have a result or when in this case the to-do variable would be populated,
or when we have an error.
So in this case I will have the error variable populated.
Now if we don't want to use the callback because it can become cumbersome when we have different
function one inside the other, we can use the second alternative which uses a sync and
a wait, but we have to target the list I use 13.
Now if we go back on Android we launch the coroutine inside the scope and this means
that if I don't need the job anymore what I can do is just cancel the scope and then
also the job gets cancelled.
By default I don't have this power on iOS.
So what we can do is try to use a library which is called coru.
Yes, we fix that problem with coru that is actually a library inspired by a blog post
of touchlab.
So thanks touchlab for this.
Does it work?
Basically you have to include of course in the common dependency of your code.
And using this library it basically introduces you to a new annotation that is to native
class.
So with that annotation you can specify a name for a class that will be generated just
in the iOS implementation of your code.
So if you have a look at the generated class we can see that it is basically a wrapper
of our original repository.
So you have two parameters that are passed.
We have wrapped this original repository and we have a scope provider.
We'll see what a scope provider is later.
And all the methods of that generated class are the same methods that you have in your
original repository.
But the result type list of to do is wrapped in another object.
So if we try to use this on iOS the code that gets generated is something like that.
We have two callbacks asked actually now.
But I can see for example other two problems with that code.
First of all we are exposing a coroutine scope for iOS developers.
And maybe iOS developers are not familiar with that concept of scope like culturally
in developers are.
And also we have that object that now is an SRA.
And it is not a list of to do anymore.
It is because we are wrapped the list of to do in another object that accepts generics.
And the objective C translation of the Kotlin code cannot do that for now so it gets simplified
to an SRA.
To solve this we go back in the common code and we use another function of that library.
This is a luncheon scope so we can define a scope in common code and tell the library
to run all our coroutines in that scope.
So the scope will not be provided by iOS developers anymore.
Also for the second problem is just a work around.
We can define a data class.
We can define a type or something to hide the fact that we are using a list of something.
So if we try to generate a new code for this, this is the final code that is much more readable
and usable.
And of course now we can dismiss the job if we are not interested in the result anymore.
What about flows?
We'll talk about coroutines.
These are an example of a simple flows that emits integers.
Of course, again, on Android it is simple.
You have a scope.
You can start collecting values.
Also if the code gets generated, it's something like that.
We still have a collect function to collect the values of the flow but we have to pass
this.
This is a flow collector so we have to implement the function emit.
Do something with that value that gets emitted and then when we are done, call the competition
handler so we can receive the next value.
Also notice that we don't have the type that we are collecting from the flow.
We just have any.
How we can improve this?
First of all, we tried to make that collector generic so we can use it in more part of our
code.
So we exposed another callback.
We actually casted the value as the one that we wanted.
We found that this is not good enough.
Also because the iOS developer has to do this in his code.
We are not doing it in common so every time he has to use our library, he has to define
this.
So we decided to fix it in common code.
Again, we used this.
That is a common flow.
There is a class found actually in the Kotlin Conf app.
This class wraps a flow and basically emits all the values of the flow and returns a crossable
object so you can dismiss the flow when you don't want to listen to it anymore.
So again, we return now a common flow using the extension function.
On iOS, again, now we have a much more readable code that we can also cancel if we want.
We mentioned before that sometimes the app may crash because of differences between the
two platforms.
One great example of this is our exception handling our handle in two languages.
Kotlin only works with unchecked exception while Swift only works with the checked one.
Now we will see what this means and what happens.
We are bringing back the function from the coroutine that we saw before.
In this case, because I'm calling item have to mark explicitly each throwing function,
I can wrap it inside a tri-catch so if something happens, I will receive the error inside the
callback.
If we bring back also the first alternative that we saw before with coroutine, what I
expect is to have the error in the function.
If I launch the application, it actually crashes.
This is because in Swift, I have to mark explicitly each throwing function.
The fix is actually quite easy because there is an annotation that we can use which is
called throws exception.
By doing this just in the common code, we don't have to make any changes inside the
Swift implementation so in this case, I will receive the error in the callback.
This works also with non-suspending functions.
If I have this function and mark it throws and exception, once I compile the code, the
generated function in Swift will be marked as throwing.
This time will be the compiler to force us to handle the exception.
Another API that is not quite Swift friendly is one of sealed classes.
On Kotlin, we can restrict the concept of inheritance by using sealed classes and sealed
interfaces.
When we use them inside our Android code, we can just make something like this because
we know for sure that those trees are data, error, and loading in this case are the only
cases that we have to handle.
On iOS, it gets converted by just using the concept of inheritance.
When I have to handle the in this case, the status, I have to define also the default
case which I know for sure that will never be called.
On Swift, we actually have a concept which is similar to the concept of sealed classes
which is the concept of enum.
What we want is to map the sealed classes with enum.
To do so, we can use a library which is called, it's quite dark, but MerkleKes-Wift.
In this case, using this library, it automatically detects any sealed classes and sealed interfaces.
The generates in this case would be UISTateKS.
It just takes the status as input and it is actually an enum that I can use.
For a Swift developer, this is much easier to use because I don't have to define a default
case anymore.
If you're writing code that is platform specific from Android, for example, you probably will
need a context to access some system functionalities.
What happens in the library ecosystem?
You may expose an API like this that gets the context from the user of the library.
Of course, you don't have to do this on iOS because you need a context on iOS.
You can improve that and you can unify those APIs.
We try to use Jetpack App startup for this because if you include App startup in your
app, in your library, basically you will be able to get a context that is injected by
the operative system and maybe save it.