Okay, so hi everyone. Good morning. This is so awesome. Welcome to the Kotlin Dev Room
at FOSDIMM 2023. Well, it's been two long years since we saw us in person. I still remember
when we had the first Kotlin Dev Room in 2020. And like not as many people as today. I'm
impressed. I think we had a bigger room and way less people, which was like, I don't know
how many people will actually show up. But yeah, today we are so many. And again, super
excited to get this kicked off. And as we get this kicked off, well, I want to give
like a little bit of stats. First, I'm so proud to share that this year we received so
many proposals for talks. We actually received more proposals than the Go Dev Room, than
the Rust Dev Room, and than the JavaScript Dev Room, which is opening tomorrow in the
same Dev Room. And by the way, if you're so much into Kotlin, make sure you don't miss
tomorrow's JavaScript Dev Room opening talk by Luis. Is Luis in the room today? He's finishing
his slides. But yeah, it will open the JavaScript Dev Room speaking out a ditched JavaScript
for Kotlin. So you definitely don't want to miss that. And so like a couple of other interesting
talks about Kotlin also in the Friends of the OpenJDK Dev Room tomorrow. So check the
agenda. There are a lot of interesting content. So back to the people to thank. Well, first,
I want to give a big shout out to the Dev Room managers. So thank you. It's me, Martin,
Sergey which is there, Olga and Marco. And we do this in our free time. Like we don't
get paid for that. And it's just like it's so awesome to get in touch with the community
and hear your stories, connect with you. And well, thanks for showing up and coming. I
want to say thank you to JabRains for supporting us. So every speaker today will get a t-shirt.
Plus we do have some stickers and stuff to give away. So stay tuned. But yeah, JabRains
is supporting us in organizing this Dev Room. And I want to say thank you to the speakers
which prepared content and just made the Dev Room possible. So thank you very much. And
now back to Martin. So we have a packed agenda for today with more than 15 talks. There is
no sorry, I do not get this good. Yeah, this is agenda. So it's available online. You can
go on the first-day website. You also have an Android app. I'm not sure about an iOS
app. I think some. There is? Okay. So you have apps. Make sure to check it out. We have
a lot of content today. And there is no lunch break at all. So you have to organize yourself
to just decide what you want to do or just bring some sandwiches or you can eat some
waffles too if you want. We have free waffles. That's it. If you want more Kotlin, as Nico
said, there is a talk tomorrow in the JavaScript. You have a lot of Kotlin content today and
tomorrow. If you want to discuss more and have some beers, we meet tonight at the Gist.
This is not here, but you can look it up on Google. And let's meet there. Just once the
Dev Room closes, we can meet or just meet directly there at 8 p.m. Am I doing this one? I think
you're doing this one or am I doing I think I'm doing this one.
I'm pretty fine with that. All right. So like the last years, we will have a live chat on
Slack. If you're not on Slack, give me a shout or we will have links on here. I think, Nico,
you prepared. Deep links. Ping is there. There's the first room. There is the deep link to
Slack room itself. If you're not signed up yet, for whatever reason, use this link. Ask
me if you need it again and you can't take a picture right now. And this is also a good
place to be because as Nico already said, we do have a couple of giveaways. Thanks to
JetBrains, we have I think free licenses to give away. How this works, I will let you
know on the Slack and on Twitter and on Mastodon. So keep an eye on there. Ask me how this works.
Essentially if you ping me there, if you tweet or post, if you tweet or post a picture or
post a picture, I will see you put on the hashtag, Fostum, Kotlin23 or Fostum23, something
like that. I will let you know. And you can win this one at the end of the day. I wanted
to say the year would be quite a long time. I think that's it from my end. If you have
any questions around this, approach me. I will be some there here or close to the coffee.
Okay. Fine. Yeah. Prepared as always. Thank you so much for coming. Yeah.
We will, yes, we will do. Good point. Yeah, here we go. Better? Excellent. All right.
So then enjoy the day. Have fun, network, speak to each other, code, whatever. Enjoy.