Okay, thank you for coming and thank you to the organizers as well for organizing this
for them and this JavaScript Dev Room. I'm Naviv Moreno. I'm a PhD student at the
Universidad Refon Carlos in Spain in Madrid and I'm going to present you how to visualize
the MPM dependency city ecosystem, original project in virtual reality. I would like to
say that this is not a technical talk, it's just a prototype that I designed. It's more
related to academia and I'm a PhD student so it's kind of showing new things and maybe
have your opinion on probably if this work is useful or not. So first of all, I'm talking
about a city. How many of you know something about Cold City, the Regiocam? Cold City?
No? One, two, three. Okay, so the city metaphor in visualization is just to take the characteristics
and layout of the city and then represent something with them. And the city layout just
means quarters and buildings. And in this case, Cold City is one of the most known tools
that uses this metaphor for visualizing Java software code. In this case, each building
is a source code of the project and the quarter is the level of the source code in the package
of the Java project. So in this case, we developed a new version of this city metaphor of Cold
City visualization using web technologies. It's related to the last talk that Fabian
gave us. We use WebXR and WebGL and everything related to web. In this case, it's A-frame.
How many of you know, say, A-frame? Probably more right. So we changed this metaphor a little
bit, changing the algorithm of the layout of the buildings. We used a spirit algorithm
instead of a trim up layout because we want to reorganize the buildings in a different
way because the layout is, the trim up layout is too fixed. And when you want to add a new
building there, there are many problems. So in this visualization, we have metrics that
we can represent in the buildings and in the quarters. The quarters represent a tree layout
because you have quarters, then you can have quarters at the top of the quarters and then
also. And the buildings have different metrics like the area of the building, the height of
the building, or the color of the building. We are using this metric to represent the
NPM, the
many URL dot com slash barrier for them. Barrier is the name of the tool that I developed in
my thesis. Just a minute. With your mobile phone, you won't have as many as the interesting
that you can have with your computer, but you can have an idea and you can visualize
the city. So this is what you can see in the demo. This is the dependency city of a project.
In this case, it's the user interface of Shorty Hat. That is a project for doing things. It's
under the grammar lab project. So in this case, in this city, each building represents
a dependency of the project. But we can see here is that, okay, there are buildings with
different colors and so on. But the first thing that we can see here is that the quarters
are kind of elevated. We can see here a quarter, what this big quarter, this quarter, this
quarter, this quarter, this quarter, and this quarter. This quarter means the dependency
level that your application has. And the first quarter, the big one, the first one is like
the bottom or the package.json of the NPA project where you define the first level of
dependencies. So we have the elevated city. We have to be clear of this. The second thing
that we can see in this city is where the buildings are. Where the buildings, the quarter
that the building is laying out means that this building or this package is in that level,
in that dependency level. For instance, this building is in the first level of dependency
that you probably define this package in your package.json if you're no project or whatever.
And these three buildings that are laying out in this level belong to the third level
of dependencies of your project. I'm explaining this because it's just a matter of understanding
how this resolution works. And some buildings go through a quarter, which means that the
building that goes through a quarter is the owner of the dependencies that are in that
building, in that quarter, sorry. In other words, this package is going through this
quarter, so the dependencies, this, this, and this are two dependencies of this quarter,
of this building, sorry. Okay? Again, for instance, this package is going through this quarter,
so this dependency, this dependency, are two dependencies of this building, of this package.
It has to be clear because it's kind of the core of this visualization. And if you are
in the demo, you probably noticed that there is kind of some buttons here that are the
metrics available in this visualization. These metrics that are here only change the characteristics
of the buildings. Okay? So we are going to focus on the third, first on this row, that
is the height. I don't know if you can see clear what it says here. Eight days. Okay.
Hey, this means the height of the buildings. And this now, the height of the building represent
the height of the package in number of days. Okay? We have this metric, this numeric metric
in height. The area of the buildings, we have three metrics. Now we selected this one that
is log slash H, which means the lines of code of the package divided by the 18 days. And
you are probably wondering why divided by the H number of days? Because if you divide,
if you multiply the height of the area of a building, of a box, you have the volume.
So if you compute these two metrics, multiplying them, you can have as a third metric, the
volume, as computed metric, in this case, the volume of the buildings will be the lines
of code in total. But we can change this metric into size, into size, in bytes, divided by
age. We can click on the metric, then the visualization is updated. Under third one
is the number of comments that the package has divided by the age. But probably this
is not as important because in this project, on this prototype, we are focused on the color
of the buildings. And now we realize why there are many metrics in the row of code. So by
default, what you see as a color building is the type of license that the package has.
In this case, we can see that there are many packages with a purple color, kind of a purple.
And then on the right, we have this legend that says which license is used. So with this
color and this city, we can have a quick overview of the packages that are used in the same
licenses or license, or if a package is used in a license that we don't want to have in
our projects or so. So that's probably one of the goals of this metric color. Then we
have two metrics that are times installed and times appear. These are not category metrics.
These are numeric metrics. These metrics follow a heat map color from blue to red. And this
is interesting because I think that you know pretty well the NPM ecosystem. When you are
defining when you're installing a package in NPM, if NPM found a dependency more than
once in the same version, NPM will install the dependency once. Right? We always know
that. All of us know that. But if NPM found the same dependency defined in two different
versions, then NPM will install the dependency twice in this case. So this metric represents
the color of the building, how many times the dependency of the package is installed.
In other words, how many times the dependency is defined in different versions. And this
one is how many times the dependency appears in the project. There are less versions. Because
we are using for instance GraphQL and we use GraphQL in many things. Where we define GraphQL,
I don't know a package that uses GraphQL but then we use another package that uses GraphQL
as well. So this represents how many times this package appears. How many times it stands
there. And these two metrics are completely related to the first line that is the attributes
line I call it. And it's used for changing the transparency or the wireframe of the build,
the working features of the buildings. Because now you notice that there are some buildings
that are kind of transparent buildings. Which means that these buildings are not installed.
These buildings are replicas and only the solid ones are the ones that are in this installed.
And if we go with our mouse or with our VR controller over a building, we can see that
if we hover a building with the mouse, we see here that this dependency is GraphQL and
then some other buildings are highlighted in white as well. But only one of them that
is this one is solid. So it means GraphQL is defined in many locations but only is installed
once that is there. But appears nine times. We have also metrics related to the community
of the package of the community behind the repository of the package. The first one is
last at days. Which means the days, the number of days since the last commit. So in a hit
map from blue to red, if the package is red, means that probably this package has no activity
in the last many days. We can see this package here. This is script 002. Two thousand years
since the last commit. So probably this is kind of a smell in this kind of visualization.
Also we have the number of commits in the last year of the package, of the repository
of the package, the number of unique committers in the last year of the repository of the
package, and of course the number of vulnerabilities that we can fund with the npm audit tool as
well. But this visualization has the goal of merge all the information that we can retrieve
from the package and then show it in this city. And the last one is the number of issues
radio that is just the number of issues open of the repository divided by the number of
issues closed in all the story of the package. So this is first overview of the tool. I invite
you to play with it. I was really quick. Of course, where are we? In the slides there
are plenty of QRs with links to the documentation, links to the step by step tutorial in order
to have this visualization with your own project. Because what you need is just to have a project
installed and then run a set of tools that I'm going to spread right now. But I said
that this is for virtual reality. So in academia some researchers validated the city metaphor
in virtual reality, agreeing that the notion of having a city in a table or something like
that helps the user or the participant or whatever to have better information that using
a computer or using a 2D screen. So that's the reason behind this research. So in this
case we are using a Metacrest 2 glasses. This is an experiment and then we have in the left
controller the user interface that we already saw in the demo. And then we can see that
when we click on the buttons you see that the city is updated instantly. I didn't tell
you but there is a second line, the user interface, because the demo, I forgot that, the demo
has four different projects to analyze in this city. Now we select the shortcut that
is the project that we are selecting in this project. But also we have the data from the
PM2 package. If you know PM2 you can click on it. We can click on the PM2 project and
then the city is automatically updated. We have also data from the portender user interface
and the desktop user interface because it's developed in the old. So we are going to focus
on the data just to finish. This QR will redirect you to this repository where I have all the
codes that I use for having the data because this is really, really easy to replicate because
what you saw here is just an HTML using A-frame, using Bavia, that is the tool that I developed,
and then adjacent with all the data. So now we are going to talk about how to produce
the JSON. But you can produce the JSON whatever you want. So it's not another of, you can
follow this tutorial or not. So the first step is to have your MPM package for application
installed, of course, because we are representing the MPM dependencies application. The second
step is to use MPM to have the dependencies list and the vulnerabilities list.
So, we are going to talk about how to use MPM. So, we are going to talk about how to
use MPM. So, we are going to talk about how to use MPM. So, we are going to talk about
how to use MPM. So, we are going to talk about how to use MPM. So, we are going to talk about