Okay, I guess I can start.
Yeah.
Right, so thank you very much for being here.
Thanks also to the folks organizing the dev room and the event.
My name is Joakim.
I work for Microsoft, and I'm here to talk to you about some stuff that we found while
building a UI project, a JavaScript UI project.
And maybe, yeah, maybe it's helpful for you too.
All right, so this is kind of a high level presentation, and I'm not here to tell you
how to do stuff.
Certainly certain things will be very basic or so.
Others you hopefully will also disagree, but the idea is to tell you about the patterns
that we found, which hopefully if you want to do something like this, you will already
be aware of these things.
So just to set up the context of what I'm talking about, and I should have started the
timer.
Yeah, you know, when we say, like, plug-in system, we're talking about applications like,
for example, ones you know probably metamos or VS code.
They have extensions or plug-ins, if you will.
I usually just say plug-ins, but it's essentially the same thing.
And the talk is not about the product that we do, but just to give you an idea of the
context, this is Kubernetes UI.
It's built with React, and there's a server and a back-end and a front-end, so it's very
traditional in that sense.
And you can run it as a web app or as a desktop app.
So yeah, and when I talk about plug-ins, still in the context thing, what this means is that,
of course, it's code that should be loaded dynamically.
It has an API from a library, of course, for you to change stuff.
And in our case, this is used basically for changing, you know, the UI, most of it.
But you can also change certain core things like adding routes, deleting routes, I don't
know, changing the token when you need to get a token, stuff like that, right?
But this is essentially the context of what I'm talking about when I say plug-ins and
functionality.
Okay, so let's start by looking at what the plug-in should look like.
This is usually we're talking about a bundled single JS file, right?
Let's not talk about, like, several JS files, you know, the drill, hopefully.
But so you have the plug-in code, maybe that's enough for us.
It's been enough for a while.
But likely you will need some information together with the code, right?
That's often called a manifest.
Certain plug-in system that I worked before, it was kind of programmatic, so the plug-in
itself declares here's my name, here's my, I don't know, dependencies for other plug-ins
or whatnot.
We recommend not doing that.
We recommend using a text file where you declare, like, a manifest file where you have all that
information about the plug-in.
Turns out that, you know, package JSON is pretty good for that already.
So the advantage of not having this in the file, hopefully they're obvious, but the thing
is that you don't have to load the code before you know if you should load the code, right?
So if you have metadata that you need to use to decide whether to use the code, for example,
you want to tell the user, okay, here's the name of the plug-in, do you want to enable
this plug-in so it's better that the code is not already running.
Loading and unloading plug-ins, so, you know, this is coming into what the plug-in should
be structured like, but of course you have to load the plug-ins dynamically, and usually
there is this pattern of an activate method.
This activate, of course, is about telling the plug-in developer more or less when the
code should be, you know, loaded.
So that's the sole purpose of this, right?
This is not so much for anything like, okay, if you don't put code inside the activate,
that means you're not one, don't trust that, right?
But it also can be used to tell the system that when you try to activate the plug-in,
then you can have like a return, for example, from that activate method, and the plug-in
can tell the system I could not activate, right?
We'll see a couple of examples.
Without deactivate, and our plug-ins for a while also didn't have the, like, well, you
can use them without deactivate, but that's because you should assume that the whole loading
is deactivate, right?
So both methods are fine.
Like I said, this is, in many cases, a matter of taste, but this is like a pattern.
So if you have an activate, of course, should you have deactivate, this is when you tell
the plug-in, okay, you're going away.
Maybe there's certain things that the plug-in needs to do before it goes away, like cleaning
up.
This is unlikely to be used by most plug-ins, but the thing is that, like, you shouldn't
rely on deactivate for just when the, like, you shouldn't trust that the plug-in will
only run the code inside the activate, you should also not trust the plug-in to deactivate
itself, right?
So this is mostly about telling the plug-in developers, here's a way that you know when
the code is going to be activated and deactivated.
Yeah, for unloading, of course, you should just reload the system without the plug-in,
mostly.
And that's pretty much the conclusion of the section, right?
Don't trust plug-ins code, I guess.
Now going into the structure, and hopefully this is a bit more interesting now, yeah,
so you have to decide how can people write plug-ins, right?
And since we are extending functionality and, you know, extending something that you already
know how it will work, maybe a plug-in class sounds good, like an object-oriented where
you extend stuff, sounds good.
But of course, right now we have a lot of functional code going on, so ultimately this
is a matter of taste, right?
We can argue, like, what's fastest, what's quicker to do, but in such applications it's
fine if you're not squeezing that extra 200 mil.
So yeah, so these plug-ins do exactly the same.
For example, in this case, the plug-ins would say, okay, we only work on Mondays, so if
the day is not a Monday, then you just tell the system I'm not activating, but these are
different flavors.
However, maybe an interesting plot twist would be that, of course, plug-ins have a life cycle,
right, they activate, they deactivate, so that's what React kind of gives you for a component.
So why not making a plug-in be a React component?
Right, you already have, you know, certain life cycle things like the, like, use effect,
for example.
Another advantage is that you could also use hooks inside it.
So we, for example, in our system have some hooks, and if you just use the, this method
is going to be a bit complicated to do, right?
But if you use this, then probably it's a good idea.
And if you, of course, this only works if you have a React-based system.
Other systems, I don't know, but yeah.
But then the other thing about the functionality is, okay, how about implementing actual stuff
to change the system, right?
And in here, I think there are mainly two options, so you can make it so that it's very
textual and declarative.
So let's say that you have a top bar, we do have a top bar, and you want actions.
Actions would be like a button or a string or something else that you want to put there.
Right, so if you make it declarative, like the left example there, of course the system
is responsible for interpreting whatever you put there, so as long as you don't implement
stuff, you won't give any power to that plug-in implementation.
On the other hand, this is kind of a bit limiting, right?
So because you always have to develop more and more functionality to support it.
If you want to be a bit more flexible, although not as, I guess, friendly to new developers,
you can just say, okay, just put a component here, and that's it, right?
And it can be a string or something else.
So that's the right side.
And of course, maybe people will do stuff that you're not expecting with that, but also
you basically support anything.
So it depends on the level of what you really want to give.
Now the functionality itself, like I won't bother you with the functionality that we have,
but of course you will usually say, okay, I want people to add, again, top bar actions
or I don't know, like a new route and all that, and it will be likely that you also
have to have a way to remove those, right?
So you can add an action.
Somebody will say, okay, now I need to remove it if it's not monitored or something, right?
So it's some sort of crude or crud or whatever you call it.
So let's look at what it could look like.
So in our case, now I talk about header actions and I actually put this screenshot here just
to illustrate, but this is a header action.
It's just a header with an action.
And yeah, so if we want to support something like this, should you have one function for
operation like register header action like we have here?
So you declare the button and you do it, or maybe, okay, if you add one button, maybe
you can add a list of buttons.
Just keeps getting appended there.
Sounds great.
And then you have a counterpart for the operation that's removing header actions.
And in this case, you can just call it deregister just to be the opposite or remove to be a
bit more direct.
However, how can you actually identify what you added there, right?
So if you declare the component or the function in this case on the left, then you have access
to it.
So you just call it again.
It's hopefully equal to the same thing internally.
And the system can understand, okay, this is something that we have here, so let me
remove that.
Right?
But let's say that we already have, we already have, we already have like default actions.
So how can the user refer to the default actions, right?
Will they import them?
That sounds like they cannot really refer to the actions by the function name because
it gets minimized and then things don't work.
So of course, one solution is to add IDs.
So it's probably a good idea that whenever you have a function where you're just passing
like a component or something else, probably you should identify it, right?
If you want to refer to it later.
But then you're very happy it works.
And somebody will go and say, hey, that's cool, but you keep appending the actions.
I want, sorry.
I want to actually have my actions prepended.
And then your world goes upside down, right?
So either you can add, of course, like, I don't know, like an index to the function
when you call it.
So now you have ID, index, and the actual action.
Or you can scrape all that and, for example, just use a list processor.
So instead of registering, okay, add function, remove function, and all that, you can say,
here's my list processor for header actions, right?
And it's going to be fed whatever is the default actions.
And you can add them, you can remove them, you can shuffle them, whatever.
So of course you have to identify them as well.
So the ID keeps going there.
But this is, I think, a more flexible way and less work to maintain.
Now developer experience.
So it's supposedly important that users can start plugins and develop plugins easily for
your system.
So just like other programs that you probably used before, there should be, like, this bootstrap
way of creating a plugin, right?
Either that, or of course you have a folder of examples that you say, okay, just use this
and modify it.
We do have something like a bootstrap script, like the headline plugin it's called, because
we're original.
And yeah, and that's interesting because you can just generate the base plugin, but also
you should take into account that you should require the developers to configure as less
stuff as possible, right?
So one way would be to say, okay, here's the package JSON that we generated, of course.
Here's the TS config that we generated.
Here's the webpack configuration that we have and all that.
However, of course, the next time that you need to upgrade the plugins, then you have
to upgrade all that stuff.
So probably a better idea is to try to add as least stuff as possible, right?
So if, for example, in the case of TS config, instead of just shipping the whole TS config
and then you have to figure out how to upgrade that if you need, we are already, as a module,
we are already inside the application at the development stage.
So we just point to it, right?
We ship the TS config that we want and we point to it.
So if the developer touches it, then it's fine.
We're never touching that again.
We're just touching the file that we ship, right?
So it's going to be updated automatically as long as you update the module.
So actually, we try to keep the dependencies as simple as possible in this case would be
just to have one, right?
Our headline plugin package in this case.
All right.
Next is about bundling.
So now you have your API with the processing, this processing and stuff.
Yeah.
And Webpack is very easy to use.
So you got your bundle, right?
And you got your bundle to be, you know, you got your single JavaScript file to be run,
ready to be run.
Because that's going to, if you just have like React, for example, that this plugin
will import, then you get React bundled there.
If you have your, in our case, headline plugin, then you're going to have that library, you
know, just bundled in.
And you should try to avoid that, right?
Because it's going to be running inside a system that already has this.
It should run with the same versions and it should not, you know, just even if it's for
size matters, not pack the same thing.
So Webpack has this thing called external modules.
And you can just say, okay, whenever you find this import, actually we mean this variable.
So when it finds the React router, it says don't care about the React router, just use
whatever you put there.
In our case, it's like plugin lib, React router, and it's going to use the same code.
So we were like, okay, this is great.
We can avoid shipping all the stuff.
We were going to keep our headline plugin package really lean.
It's going to be great.
So we even thought, okay, we're not even shipping our own library.
We're just shipping the typed declarations.
That's going to be fine.
So we spent many hours wiring, you know, TS config and Webpack and whatnot to make sure
that it was happy.
When users are developing, they can see that imports seem to work, even though they don't
exist inside the library.
And then somebody wanted to test the plugin.
And it's like, oh, okay, so now you cannot test the plugin because you don't have the
libraries around.
So maybe you have to use the program itself to test the plugin, but that's probably not
a great idea.
So we were like, okay, we have to ship the actual library.
Yeah.
And so, yeah, so it still works as an external module.
So we're not bundling it, but we're shipping it.
And it's fine because, I mean, yes, the headline plugin package is slightly larger, but that's
okay because it's just one time.
So take that into account.
Don't get too extreme with not shipping stuff.
Yeah.
And we're getting to the end.
So running the plugins, right?
So now you got your bundle.
It's not bundling React because we got it.
It's not bundling your library because you got it.
And you're going to run it.
However, you know, of course, at some point you will break API.
And if you do break API, it would be nice that you download a plugin that will be broken
because it's, you know, you'll break the system for your users.
So package.json has this already.
It's part of its known keywords, I guess, called engines.
So you can just put something there for your system.
And then, of course, when you run it, you should just check for that before running
it.
Now how to run the actual system.
So now you have everything in place.
And you can check for it before you load it.
But how do you actually load it?
Do you load it?
Of course, it's going to be loaded in the front.
And that's what we're talking about with JavaScript.
And this is highly special to each project, right?
So maybe you have something there where the users can just load the files directly.
And it just, you know, it just refreshes and loads.
In our case, we didn't want to do that.
We wanted it to be very transparent to the user.
So if the user, of course, downloads a plugin, next time they start the application, they
should see that things changed.
But also, in the case of our application, it works also if you deploy it as a web service
like that.
So in that case, we don't want really the users to keep using different plugins.
In this case, it's more like, okay, whoever deployed it is giving you, like, an experience,
user experience with the base code plus a bunch of plugins that the users shouldn't
really know about.
And for security reasons, of course, we don't want the users to keep loading plugins on
something that is now, you know, even though it runs locally, it's going to, you have it,
you know, just deployed for this user and other users.
So they would have different user experiences if they keep adding their own plugins.
Right?
So what we do in our case is that we have the backend or the server.
It's a server, but, you know, depending on if it's running locally or actually in the
server.
And then that's the thing that has to have access to the plugins themselves.
Right?
So it reads the plugins, and then it has an endpoint, and the frontend, when it loads,
before it loads everything, it says, okay, what are the plugins that you have?
It says, I got this 10 plugins.
It says, okay, give me the plugins now or give me this one plugin now, for example.
Then you get the actual bundle JS code from the backend, and then it loads it dynamically,
and then you get the shiny thing.
So this way, of course, if you're running it locally and you have the plugins in the
plugin folder that it expects, the backend has access, it actually keeps watching the
folder in our case.
It gets refreshed whenever you change stuff there.
And that's how we do it locally.
If you're running on the server, then, of course, we don't check if the plugins change
or not.
That's not supposed to happen, but you still get essentially the same experience.
But like I said, this is mostly, this is very tight-witched project.
And that's all I got.
So thank you.
Thank you very much.
We do have time for questions.
So raise your hand high, and we'll start with the first question.
Yeah.
Hey.
You said putting some dependencies in the plugin.
So having a module they import so they can use some things like hooks, do you have to
or do you do anything against a plugin modifying those things that would then mess with other
plugins, like changing the objects you passed in?
I can order them with so much.
Sorry.
If the plugins are depending on a module that you made, and the same ones being passed into
the different plugins, could they modify the things you're passing in to then mess with
the other plugins?
Yes.
But what was the actual question?
Sorry.
Go ahead.
Is there a way to mitigate against them kind of changing how the plugin system behaves
for the other plugins?
But you mean, for example, in the example of the actions, whatever goes there?
So you had a button.
Say you have a button class you're passing in, they can extend.
What if they changed the behavior of that button class to then other plugins have a
modified version when running?
Yeah, but that's actually something by design, right?
So you're supposed to, let's say that you changed the delete button, and now you still
have the delete button, but the delete button will no longer delete.
It will just say, actually it was on the example, but it will just say, not today, right?
Yeah.
So the delete button on the left just says, not today, right?
It actually replaces the delete button in this case, but that's fine, right?
That's fine because that's what the plugins are supposed to do, right?
So the plugins are supposed to do, and maybe you have even plugins that, okay, they expect
you already to have other things in there.
So if you have a combination of both plugins, they can see that you added stuff.
And yeah, so that's by design.
Of course, if you install plugins that will make your system not do anything, well, that's
also, you should be careful about what you install.
You talk about security in the front end, but isn't that something that Back Engine
handle more and just keep the JavaScript as light as possible instead?
About the security, what?
You talk about security in the front end.
Yeah.
So that users can't add their own plugins.
But isn't that something that the user would be responsible for anyway?
No, no.
Yeah.
I mean, I was rushing maybe I didn't explain that correctly.
No, the thing about the security is not so much about the security, it's about the user
experience.
So you suppose as a user to add your own plugins, of course.
But that's if you use, in our case, our application as a desktop application because then it's
you who's responsible for that application.
When you go and you use it because you access some service that gives you in the browser,
right?
It's the person that deployed that or the company or whatever that is supposed to give
you the plugins that you are supposed to see, right?
So you shouldn't change the way that the application works.
But that's, of course, our decision, right?
In other cases, like I guess Slack or something like that, you can add actually different
plugins for yourself.
And that's cool too.
But this is, like I said, this was a highly intimate decision for our own project.
So a couple of months back when we are checking for the plugins, so usually a few applications
run the plugins in an isolated environment, like they ship their micro run times and run
in them and then try to communicate.
So in your use case, are you running them in the parent application context?
Because in that case, we can't always trust what users are writing in their plugins, right?
So they can steal stuff from Windows, things like that.
Do you have any check to see all the plugins and do the legends before I load them to the
store or something like that?
Yeah.
Security would be a whole talk about it.
Which we don't have time for.
We're just running the plugins as is because as of now, you know, we don't have, for example,
you cannot just download plugins from NPM right now, right?
We're going to have that.
When we have that, we're going to have a different way to run them, hopefully.
I know that depending on the system, you're going to find that some do have a way to isolate
them.
There's a good blog article by Figma doing that.
And that's kind of cool.
They say what approaches they took and what conclusion they got to.
Other programs, they just say, okay, you're supposed to install stuff that you trust.
And they go through some, you know, just like when you install an NPM package, it can be
harmful, right?
But there are mechanisms to kind of mitigate that.
So I want to make it as secure as possible, but that's not, you know, it was not security
from the start before we actually have the system.
It's okay.
So do you have like any ways of handling code splitting and other stuff like that?
Like maybe a plugin wants to load some components later on?
Is there a way you can handle it using your method of doing that?
If the plugin wants to add components later?
If a plugin developer wants to use code splitting and loading stuff later on?
Is it fine?
I mean, if you have an activate method, I mean, if I understand your question, you have
the moment where the plugins are loaded, right?
So you can just say, okay, I'm not supposed to be running the buttons now.
So we're changing this functionality now.
I'm supposed to be changing the functionality whenever.
Of course, that's a responsibility for the plugins, right?
We just say, okay, we're loading you.
Now you should make sure that you do whatever you want, but it should be like, you can,
of course, this is just code you can change when it wants.
Thank you again.