Okay, so just a minute there.
Hello, everyone.
I guess we are starting because we have been told that we are strict on time, minutes to
minutes, so I cannot do anything, but I have to start talking now, and thanks a lot for
joining us today.
And let's start with a brief intro, probably, of our speakers.
All right.
Thank you.
Thank you all for being here.
I'm Marco.
And yeah, I'm Kotlin GDE based in Berlin.
I'm Italian, and today I'm here talking about Kotlin.
Same here.
I'm Sergei.
I'll be talking about Kotlin as well, and we were asked to get you the state of Kotlin,
whatever it means.
I worked for various companies in Kotlin for about seven years now, I guess, such a long
time, early years with the veterans in Kotlin now mainly in Android development and infra.
But let's start with important things.
We live in a modern time with modern technologies available, and so this presentation is powered
by generative AI.
It's really important to remember that the speakers today, both of us, are not anyhow
affiliated with any company that creates Kotlin or like sponsor it or anything like this.
It will be pure, our opinion based on our experience, our guesses.
I don't know.
We might be wrong, except for the places where when we are right.
That's it for today.
So yeah, and generative AI make a thing that probably the speaking these days will be an
easy job.
So last year, preparing for the FOSDAM talk, I've been writing my videos about 3am before
the deadline.
So Nikola was already saying why you're not sending me the videos, and I had to do.
And this year I thought, all right, I'm using the modern technologies and asked Chad GPT
to generate the slides for me.
Unfortunately we ended up in like 5 to 10 minutes saying, oh, I have no idea what is
Kotlin because I don't have data after 2021 probably.
So the rest of the presentation is really not powered by the generative AI.
I'm sorry for this.
So it's powered by us.
We had to figure out what is Kotlin and what is the current state.
So probably the first reasonable thing thinking about this is to get and try to understand
any of the developer surveys available.
And one of the most interesting ones in this domain is the JetBrains developer survey that
they run, I guess, every year from 2019 or 2020ish.
So here is the data available on the end of 2022, the survey.
And we can see definitely a domination of mobile development for Kotlin and presumably
it's Android mobile development.
I guess so.
And another leading stream is the web or back-end development, which is rising and 40% of all
Kotlin engineers are working with back-ends.
I must admit that at the end of 2022, the majority of the population is still in mobile.
The back-end is rising and back-end is trending up.
I was under impression like a year ago that, hey, Android is probably the only platform
for Kotlin.
However, I was like reasonably biased with this.
And the first time after COVID, when I arrived to one of the European conferences that had
a few topics there, I was impressed that the majority of topics were with back-ends.
But today let's try to avoid getting too deep into particular Kotlin platforms and focus
more on high-level language stuff, what is coming in the next years, or at least what
we can probably predict to come.
It's quite funny that it's possible to describe the whole 2022 and 2023 agenda in the Kotlin
world with just five letters.
And one is common in most of the words.
It's K2, the new Kotlin compiler that's coming, and the Kotlin multiplatform or KMP.
So I'm not very surprised.
And in the past year, we didn't see a lot of Kotlin language features.
And there are a few reasons for this.
And we'll definitely discuss them in the next slides and further in this talk.
But let's try to first understand what is K2 and what is what it's preparing for us
as developers and product owners or Plight engineers.
And then we'll get to KMP later in this presentation.
First of all, there are a few major problems in the whole Kotlin infrastructure.
And they are the stability and performance of the ID.
So Plight, even though probably IntelliJ is one of the greatest product on the market
for developers, it's not great for Kotlin.
I mean, it's fine.
But whenever your project is growing and growing and growing, and I know something about large
project in the industry, it's getting unusable.
The second thing is build speed.
Plight, whenever you try probably Java for its builds before, even if Java is slow, but
overall Kotlin is significantly slower.
And this is like a drawback, especially if you came from the legacy code base whenever
you had five or 10 years of previously Java code.
Yeah, I know, I know.
I tried to say we are not getting deeper into the platforms.
But it is what it is.
And the build setup overall is quite complicated.
So for example, Kotlin multi-platform.
How to run Kotlin multi-platforms from the common line.
If you can give me an answer, I will just take you out for dinner probably.
And currently the overall K2 is developing in the two major Kotlin roadmap milestones.
Like whenever you're interested, what is going on in Kotlin, you can get to the Kotlin roadmap.
Thanks a lot for publishing it to JetBrains.
It's like magic.
There are two key things.
Like getting K2 to better.
K2 is currently in alpha.
And it's the whole rewrite of the compiler front end.
Meaning that if you previously hacked something for the compiler plug-ins or compiler infrastructure,
for you an owner of the libraries like KSP or KPT, you basically have to redo everything
you did in the past three, five years.
And the second part is the IntelliJ based plug-in.
And the story there is like the compiler and the compiler front end especially is very
coupled with whatever Android Studio or IntelliJ ID or your ID of choice is doing with the
language.
Either it's a language server or the index you have locally, your compiler performance
really impacts the experience you have in the ID.
Let's get to the other things.
Like the unfortunate is the deprioritization of the API for compiler plug-ins.
It means that for all of the engineers outside of JetBrains, it will be still very hard to
create tools for a compiler for ID and evolve them over time.
So currently you don't have a stable and you don't have basically a documented API for
the compiler.
So for example, if you're creating a library that changes something, every major or any
even minor release of Kotlin, you need to upgrade it and evolve and maintain the compatibility
of the version for the compiler.
Please get back.
Yes, it's back.
So currently K2 is an alpha, but as far as we understand, the 1.9, Kotlin 1.9 is about
to get us K2 in beta.
For the current numbers, we have the improvement at around a rate of 2X for all the build that
at least JetBrains provided us in their benchmarks and publicly told us about these things.
With Kotlin itself being built in significantly faster.
But if you're impatient, there is the way to bring at least some of the improvements
for the build speed earlier in the pipe.
You can get to Kotlin 1.7 something and it has a probably 10 to 15% improvement in the
build speed.
And you can even experience this in the large scale code bases.
There are a few plans about the K2 going to beta and mainly what JetBrains and Kotlin
wants to achieve, it's the full functional compiler and it should work for the whole
ecosystem, not only the JVM.
It's probably usable for JVM even right now.
I tried it.
It's not a great experience, but you can experiment at least with it.
So there is a need for improvement in various plugins like Kotlin annotation processor,
serializable, KSP and others.
And it will take time.
As of yesterday, there is a well done support for Kotlin X serialization, all open, no arc
plugins and Lombok.
It's already in the source code of Kotlin compiler.
I'm not sure which version they are targeting.
So I was checking 1.9 daily build and it was fine there.
Probably there is something in 1.7.21, but I'm not quite sure.
So unfortunately KAPT is still not working.
So you cannot do any of the annotation processing yet.
And KSP, the simple process in the future of annotation processing for Kotlin also doesn't
work.
But let's get into some details of the annotation processor support.
Like luckily in Utrecht there are tickets for almost everything that works or that doesn't
work and what JetBrains is planning to work on.
So there is the ticket for frontend IR support for KAPT.
It's still in progress.
It should be done in 1.9 or at least it's a current version now.
I try to understand what doesn't work like right now.
And it got me to quite interesting things.
That KAPT currently doesn't support language version 2.0.
This used language version 1.9 or below.
It's just a source code that I saw yesterday.
And I tried to get deeper and saw that there is a Kotlin version introduced that has symbols
both 2 and 0.
I probably don't want to make any judgment here what the version would be, but there
is something suggested that we are going to have some major changes in the future.
Kotlin symbol processing is another thing that doesn't work currently, but it's expected
to get around 1.9.
There is some work going on in the domain in the Google repository for KSP, but still
nothing there done.
And the testing info doesn't work at all currently.
So one of the major libraries for the compile testing doesn't support K2.
I don't know when the support will come there.
There's a pull request getting this support at least partially, but who knows.
Probably will take another six to eight months.
And finally, the IDE support for K2.
So as far as I understand, the plan is to create the K2-based IDE plugin that will probably
start from a quite lightweight one that will support only a few things.
It should have the performance that started it to be everything worked fast and correct,
and likely stable.
The IDE plugin will have a lower number of features, will be lightweight, and will be
released likely after the better or stable of the compiler.
So it's not earlier than 1.9, probably even later.
So as stated currently, it should have all the quote highlighting.
It should have basic code completion, like nothing fancy, probably just the stuff you
use on a regular basis, but not for major refactorings or anything else.
In debugger, there should be breakpoints and some simple stuff, really simple stuff, as
it's declared.
And there should be a limited number of diagnostics.
The last but not the least thing, as you might notice, another big part is the Kotlin multiplatform
support.
This new lightweight plugin is aiming to have the full featured Kotlin multiplatform support
as well.
And yeah.
That's my third.
All right.
So now after some K2 magic, let's try to check what went through this year of Kotlin Multiplatform
and what will come in the future.
So let's start our journey from Kotlin 1.6.20.
And the first magic things, beautiful things that we saw was the hierarchical project structure
become in default.
And this thing was such a blast because you got finally don't need any more to do some
weird magic stuff like symbolic links and things to have to cover multiple architecture
like iOS version and Intel version and X64 version.
So you get automatically shared stuff and you can just use an intermediate target for
the thing, which was really a good thing to start with.
But wasn't the only thing in 6.20 because we got some improvements on Kotlin native
and we got all the improvement that as an engineer you can dream of.
So runtime, compile time and code size.
So it was an interesting update that brought many, many improvements on the developer experience,
which was really nice.
But the very big thing came later in 1.7.20, which was finally the new memory manager for
Kotlin native.
And with that version it's now enabled by default.
And basically it's again a huge win in terms of developer experience because a lot of change
changed and we got better stuff.
Just because the memory manager changed from reference counting garbage collection to tracing
garbage collection because in the past it was just made it quick and dirty.
Let's put it in the way to just get out.
But now that things are getting bigger and people are using it, they realize that some
stuff was not the best choice afterwards.
So what this means in reality is that there are no more restrictions on sharing objects
between threads.
There is more leak free primitives, which means no leaks on the internals but maybe
leaks on stuff that you wrote because we can introduce bad things but at least the tooling
is not sneaking leaks.
What does it mean at the end of the day for developers?
It means that no more freezing.
Finally we get all the beautiful sun because we don't need to freeze objects anymore.
We are really free to use everything.
And yeah, you just don't have to think anymore to freeze stuff and to understand that it's
not crashing, that there's no mutability and stuff.
So all magic now.
And this thing enables a bigger thing, which is finally Kotlin Music Platform mobile, the
mobile part, to reach the beta version, which is a huge milestone.
And this means that the technology is basically done and it is safe to use your project.
The fact that in beta means that there's still some work to do mostly on the toolchain, but
in general thinking you can use this safely.
Maybe there will be some cut corners on setting up the toolchain and stuff like that, but
don't worry, you can start using a learning, your project, and do it because it's fun.
So yeah, do it.
All right.
Now let's move to more close to today.
And with the release of Kotlin 1.8, we got a lot more interesting stuff in the field
of Objective-C and with interoperability, which is something that people always ask because
it could be better sometimes.
So with this release, we got some nice annotations, like Objective-C name, that let us specify
a more beautiful naming for some function that we want to expose to Swift so we can
just change the name without changing the Kotlin object itself.
Another one is hidden from Objective-C, which as the name suggests, we can hide some function
from Objective-C because maybe we want to have an application function that works better
or has a better representation for the Swift word, and we want to just hide the Kotlin
one so we can save precious binary size and have a specific function only for the iOS
part.
And finally, another interesting thing is the should refine in Swift annotation, which
basically is the compiler to mark a function or a property as Swift private.
So basically it's going to be exported on Objective-C with a double underscore.
And so with a double underscore, this function will be invisible because auto-seguestion
doesn't auto-seguest.
On iOS, sometimes stuff are invisible because auto-seguestion doesn't work properly in Xcode,
but that's another thing.
But in this way, it will be possible to hide some function and then rewrite it on Swift
to have a better, a better, um, idea-matics with way of doing things.
All right.
Another experimental thing that we got on Kotlin 1.8 is something that I was dreaming
of because every time I saw I see Android test and Android Android test, my ads explode
because I don't, every time I think that it's a typo or something, but it's not a typo.
But right now, this will change, and there will be a more descriptive things, like instead
of Android test, Android unit test, and instead of Android Android test, Android instrumented
test.
It's going to be more clear, and you've got to understand really what's this thing.
Connected to that, there will be more clarity also to where to put the manifest.
So not in the Android main, but you're going to have a specific folder for the bug and
the release version, so it's going to be more clear, and you've got to understand better.
This thing is still experimental.
Of course, it's going to be enabled by default sometimes in the future, but if you want to
use it, you have to opt in with a gradle option.
Another thing that was in Kotlin 1.8 was the stabilization of the Kotlin JS backend, and
so finally right now, all the three different technologies, so Kotlin for the JVM, Kotlin
native, are using the same backend, which means better handling, less bug, and everything
is works better.
Another interesting goodie that is not specific to a specific version is that since version
1.4 to 1.8, they were experimentally checking binary back to compatibility, which is always
a nice thing, and from now on, there are processes set up on JVM's side to keep binary compatibility
from every release, which is going to alleviate the pain of having stuff broken.
All right, another very interesting thing about Kotlin and the multi-platform world
is the fact that JetBrains is maintaining also a composed version for desktop and the
web, which is a fork from the Android one from Google, and the support is going on,
but it's really neat, it's really beautiful, because you can just use something nicer to
write desktop application and still not have to deal with Java, whatever stuff, so it's
really nice that we have some sort of things.
Of course, it takes time to keep it up with Google releases, because they have to catch
it up, but, for example, a couple of days ago, we got the 1.3.0 release, and, yeah,
so stuff is going forward also on this side.
Last year, we got also some interesting experimental stuff, which is composed for iOS.
Yes, it seems to have, seems happening.
It's still some very experimental and technical preview, so absolutely not ready for production,
but people in the community are playing with that.
For example, folks at Touchlab, they built the draw.con version of the draw.con app for
the iOS version of the draw.con app, which is something amazing, and, yeah, this is something,
as I said, not ready, but it's something to keep an eye on, because it's going to be wild
and interesting.
What is going to come this year?
There will be more improvements on the memory manager, even though it's still already stable,
and it's the default memory manager.
Folks at Jetman will keep increasing and fixing bug and increasing performance on that.
Of course, there will be more improvement on compilation time on Kotlinative, because
it's still sometimes not the fastest thing in the world, and so it has to be improved.
Another point, which is, like I was mentioning before, it's always asked from people, it's
better exporting to Objective-C, so it has better APIs to interact with from the iOS
part.
Also, another thing will be, after confirming that there are tools in place to have backward
binary compatibility for the Kotlin native version, they will describe and add more improvements,
and documentation for library developers to maintain binary compatibility as well.
All of that is going to...
These improvements are connected to having, finally, Kotlin-motive-platform mobile to stable,
which hopefully is going to happen this year, and in order to do that, there are a bunch
of things that need to be addressed.
Like I said before, it's mostly toolchain and infrastructure stuff, but the main thing
is working, and you can start already using it, because it's in beta, and stuff are kind
of working right now.
With that was it, the introduction of the journey into Kotlin from the past year and
for this year.
Thank you very much.
There will be a lot of content today, so feel free to catch it up with all of that, and
have fun.
Thank you very much.
We do have four minutes for questions, so if you have any, raise your hand, I will bring
you the microphone.
Is it okay if I ask three consecutive questions, two of which are related?
First of all, in terms of Kotlin JS and Kotlin native, those are not intended to be a performant
alternative for existing solutions.
Like Kotlin JS wasn't meant to be a challenge to TypeScript, what I heard somewhere, and
Kotlin native wasn't intended to rival things like Rust or Go, etc.
Is there a change in that ambition?
That's my first question.
My second question is, does JetBrains have any plans to use Compose to port their IDEs
to Compose from AWT?
Okay, for the first one, I'm not sure if I heard or read some changes or stuff.
There's just another thing in the ecosystem, probably it's not going to be a place.
I'm not sure what you catch or what not, so I'm going to start.
I haven't read stuff, or here's stuff that changed what you were saying.
Probably there's going to be other tooling to the...
It's another technology to support and not to replace.
So it's going to be another thing to cover in other use cases, not to completely replace.
I don't have more clear guidance or evidence or opinions about that.
The second one was about...
There was no easy, I didn't get it fully.
It's like eating your own doctor, or JetBrains, you should compose to fill their IDEs.
I'm not JetBrains, so I don't know, but probably yes if I have to bet it.
I know that they have their own runtime for UI and stuff like that, but probably yes,
they are going to use it, but I'm not JetBrains, so I don't know.