Let's move on everyone.
We have to keep the schedule and keep the pace for all our viewers online and the rest
of them.
For this next talk, we are welcoming Romain, who is going to talk about dependency on jurisdictions.
Please give Romain a warm welcome.
Thank you for having me.
I'm really glad to be here with you.
I'm Romain Brousel, and today I will guide you through our journey of improving the use
of CODAIN, a dependency injection library using KSP.
So you already seen that commercial art, so I'll make it quick.
I'm really happy to work with Solomon on advocating as well as providing services and trainings
on CODAIN, and I'm really grateful that JetBrains is rewarding us years after years.
So let's talk about the real subject here, open source.
So we are maintaining a set of CODAIN multi-partform independent tools that are compatible on every
target on which we can combine CODAIN.
And obviously today we're going to talk about dependency injection with CODAIN.
So let's team up and see what are our problems today and how we are trying to solve them
with KSP.
First, a little bit of context on why we are using dependency injection in our applications.
So let's assume that I have a view model that needs multiple instances of use cases.
So I will need to initialize every one of those use cases and their dependencies and
so on.
So to avoid managing those initializations, we often use the dependency injection pattern.
In dependency injection, the DI container has the responsibility to initialize every
instances we need to make our objects work, and so we can lazily retrieve them with a
simple function code.
So here we see that we used a generic function that is called instance, or we often see get
inject or whatever.
In some other libraries of frameworks, we often see a huge amount of annotations.
So it sounds like magic to a lot of people.
Another problem with the generic instance function is that I don't really know what
is behind it.
Is it a singleton, a factory, do I need to pass an argument?
I don't really know.
Another problem comes with the DI binding declaration.
As a maintainer, I know what's behind all that, but it can be confusing for newcomers.
And on top of that, there is no compilation checks.
So this means that if you forgot some bindings, you will probably know it when your application
crashes, or in worst cases, in your crash-lytics dashboard.
So did we just create a monster?
Not quite.
But there is still room for improvement.
So let's do what we do best and refactor everything to get a better API and improve the use of
code in.
So let's welcome KSP.
It stands for Kotlin Symbol Processor.
A Kotlin Symbol Processor is a meta-programming tool that allows us to generate code, generally
based on some existing code base.
Symbol processors are generally used with annotations that are used to mark our code
that needs a special treatment by the processor.
In short terms, it's a lightweight compiler plugin because it can just generate code and
not modify some.
A quick example here.
I have a foo interface that is annotated to be processed.
So a compiler plugin, sorry, a Kotlin Symbol Processor should be able to generate a concrete
class of this foo interface overriding the check function.
So back to our initial problem.
What do we need to improve the code in's API?
First, we need a readable and typed API to be able to avoid the use of this generic function
instance everywhere.
Because we cannot easily have compile checks, at least we want an easy way to check the
dependency container consistency with a few lines of unit tests.
Note that the API you'll see today are still work in progress, so they may change a little
before landing on the release.
The main idea is that you should be able to declare one or more interfaces that represent
the dependencies you need in your applications.
That's the one that you need to retrieve, at least.
After that, we need to annotate our interface so that the coding's Symbol Processor should
be able to generate some code to interact with a DI container to retrieve your dependencies
in a typed way.
Let's introduce the result annotation for that.
Once we have annotated our interface, the coding's Symbol Processor should be able to
detect and generate code for us.
In that case, you will see that we need a parameter to create a brewery service, so
it will know that we need to interact with a factory that needs a string as parameters
to get a brewery service instance.
As well as the controller functions needs to return a simple instance depending on the
context.
Here is what the coding's Symbol Processor will generate for us.
A concrete class implementing our app dependencies interface, and that needs a DI container as
input.
The DI container will be used to retrieve the proper instances, either a factory, because
it can detect that we need a parameter, or a simple instance for the controller.
Now, let's see how we can use it in our application code.
First, we need to declare our DI bindings so our implementation should be able to interact
with.
For that, we still use our current API of coding's DSL, or we'll improve it a little
bit, but we will keep it as well as it is.
Why?
Suppose we have history with solutions like daggers that have gone wild with annotations.
Even so, it's where coding was created in the first place to avoid that forest of annotations.
We didn't want to introduce tons of annotations again and go full circle.
Finally, we think our binding declaration API is good enough to explicit our dependencies.
Here are the dependencies we need to meet the app dependencies interface contract.
We need a factory that takes a string and returns a service, and a singleton that returns
an instance of a controller that itself needs an instance of a service.
Welcome to that later.
Now we can instantiate the generated class with our DI container and retrieve our dependencies
with a truly typed API.
As we don't want our user to know how we are generating our function, or class implementation,
we also introduced an extension function that helps us instantiate the app dependencies
for us.
Now that we are able to retrieve our dependencies with a truly typed API, let's see how we can
check their consistency.
For that, we introduced a DI resolver interface that only needs to respect the contract of
a check function.
Now we can combine the DI resolver interface with an at resolve annotation.
In an ideal world, the at resolve annotation should be able to add that DI resolver type
to our interface itself.
As we are using Kotlin symbol processor, we can just generate some code and not modify
existing one.
So now that we are fully packed with our annotation and our DI resolver interface, the Kotlin
symbol processor will be able to generate the overridden function check and create a
requirement for every one of the functions or accessor we have defined in our app dependency
interface.
Before with that code, you will have taken the risk to go in production without easily
knowing if you forgot some bindings.
No more.
Now we just add a test and as we saw before, we instantiate our app dependencies interface
with a concrete class and just call the check functions.
That way, if you missed a binding, your test suite will warn you instantly with a proper
message.
So here we saw that we missed a factory binding that returned a service and takes a string
argument as input.
One more thing.
Earlier, we saw that the Kotlin binding DSL was impacted with the use of those instance
functions.
So let's see how we can improve this user as well.
Let's take this example when I need a controller that needs itself a use case and that also
needs a service.
Here is the binding we will have defined to meet our architecture expectation.
So you probably have seen me coming with those instance functions.
In the explicit world, we will have written those functions with their targeted type so
we saw that we need a service and a use case.
So why not using a typed API and get this instance directly?
This is not that simple because in Kotlin's DSL, this is a typed DI builder so it doesn't
know anything about the app dependencies API.
Thus, the Kotlin's symbol processor will also generate a new function for us that is called
off with the name of the app dependencies contract we have.
Thus, it creates a new DI builder that is aware of the DI building API and the app dependencies,
allowing us to call straight functions to get our instances as long as they are part
of the app dependencies API, obviously.
So as a result of the type dependencies, I can now easily check the consistency of my
DI container or retrieve dependencies in my application.
So I feel the tension and excitement in the room, right?
No?
One question on everybody's mind.
Is this live?
So I can spoil it earlier.
It's still a work in progress and we still have some corner cases to crack, like how
to use tags, how to manage modules, how to declare and the end-all scopes and context
is a few more.
Here is a sneak peek of some ideas we have to solve those problems.
An easy one is the tag API when we can retrieve a dependencies by passing a tag parameters.
We could add an annotation with that tag and easily retrieve our dependencies without having
to pass or no the tag that is needed behind.
For the module management, we could just provide two ways to interact with dependencies, either
with a fully packed DI container or a DI module, or add some parameters to our annotations,
or either create a new annotations again.
We'll see.
Maybe not.
A more complicated use case is how to handle scopes.
With code-ins, we can define some bindings that are with some life cycle depending on
the scope or context and retrieve them with the on function.
To define the scope with KSP, we could define that a contract is scoped entirely and then
be able to retrieve our dependencies with the right context.
Maybe this rings a bell.
It sounds like context receivers, right?
Unfortunately, context receivers are not available in Kotlin Multi Platform yet, so we'll have
to find another way.
Also, we have plenty of ideas to make this work.
This is an open source project, so obviously, if you want to contribute, you're welcome.
That's it for me.
Thank you for hearing me.
If you have some questions, I think we have time for it.
Thank you very much again.
We do have quite a lot of time for questions now, so please raise your hand if you have
any.
Just shout it and you will have to repeat it.
Can I find a strategy from the idea support in all these and the previous projects, working
with libraries?
Is it a fact that the idea doesn't pick up?
Some of this is called a blocker with an option.
The question is, is there some support in the IDE?
How do you mitigate the luck?
As for the Mocking library, you will need to build your code the first time to be able
to have the right APIs.
Like the new function and the off dependencies function, for example.
For the dependency injection framework, you're not affected much like IDE limitations.
Nope.
All right, I think it's clear.
One question.
With this dependency injection framework, are all the dependencies compiled statically,
like the dependency injection part, or is that still dynamic runtime?
Is the dependencies injection resolved statically or at runtime?
Is this your question?
They are resolved at runtime.
As we saw, we provide tools to check that all your bindings are well defined with your
test suite.
But they are resolved at runtime.
There is no reflection like Solomon showed you earlier.
That's how Dagger works, for example.
So it's basically the best of both worlds between Spring and Dagger.
We hope so.
There was another unrest on that side of the room.
I think it's a bit of an obvious question.
How does it compare to the coin then?
The question is, how does it compete with coin?
I think we have taken different routes with coin.
I think Arno will present you this afternoon.
It provides an API using annotation, more that we are doing.
We prefer keeping the binding declaration as much explicit as possible.
After that, I think it's more some internal implementation that does not really compete,
I think.
There we go.
No problem.
Thank you.