Hello, everyone. Today I will talk to you about migrating your old project to, of course,
Python. No, just kidding. How many of you are using Python for work? Okay. We are in
the wrong room. We need to go downstairs. So I will talk to you about migration of your
Vue.js project from version 2 to version 3. And this is not working. Great. Okay. I am
Denly. I work as food stack developer with JavaScript and Python. Not go. Go. It's fake
news. And work as front-end developer also using, of course, Vue.js. And let's start
with a quick walkthrough of the Vue.js versions. They released version 2.6 in 2029, a lot of
time ago. Then in 2020, they released version 3, 3.1, 3.2, one year later. And then last
year in February, version 3 became the new default. So when you install, when you run
npm install Vue.js, you install the version 3 now. And then in July 2022, they released
version 2.7 in maintenance mode. So they want release. They should release a new version
of Vue 2. And it will reach the end of life in the end of this year. So 2023, it will
be the end of Vue.js 2. Then let's do a quick recap of options API. Options API are working
with Vue.js 2 as well as Vue.js 3. And you simply can define a data function. Inside
that you can return an object. And that object will be exposed in the template as well as
methods so you can define functions. And that functions will be exposed to the template
as well. Then again 2020, they officially announced the user history with composition
API, scripts set up, experimental at that moment, but now it's official. And I know
all of you are sad about this. No Internet Explorer support, but now it's dead, so who
is it? Then at that time I was like, oh, wow, nice. Let's drop Vue.js 2 and move everything
to Vue.js 3. Well, it wasn't so simple. So I started to check about the new script set
up in composition API. So you can define a set up function. And if you return a whole
constants and function you define in there, they will be automatically exposed to the
template. So not so clear, but nice, nicer than before. So you can compress constant
and function of a single piece of logic in the component and then return them. So if
you want to use this in Vue.js 2.6, you need to install Vue composition API and use it
like this in this example, importing from composition API, all ref computed and all
functions and you can use a kind of set up script like in Vue.js 3. But spoiler alert,
your test will break because, well, easy fix, you need to use Vue composition API also in
test files, in Vue.js or in the local Vue instance you are using in test. So, well,
easy fix for now. Then the best part about this is the composition API plus script set
up. So you can define a script set up in your single file component and defining constants
and functions. They will be automatically exposed to the template. So, well, is it clearer
than the set up script in my opinion? And everything is clearer and neat. So another
big news, 2022, they released Vue 2.7 with support for composition API and again partial,
but nice, script set up. So again, I was like, whoa, great, let's try Vue.js 2.7 before everything
else. And yeah, it was really nice. Now it's working with basically all components and
you can look at the documentation for this. So you can upgrade your Vue.js dependency
to 2.7 and it should be it. It should work. And you can change in your 2.7 projects your
script set up like this. So removing the script, changing to script step and changing it like
that. And if the component is not too complicated, well, everything should work as expected and
it will be ready for Vue.js 3. Yes. Now we can git commit push and deploy to production.
Well maybe not, because if you are using Vue router, then it will break. So you need to
use the new version of Vue router at least 3.6.5. And you need to import use route and
use router like this. And instead of using this dot route and router, you need to use
route and route like this. Pretty much the same for Vuex store. Well, not the same, but
you need to import your store from your definition and use the store like this. So store.state.property
name and not this.store anymore. Then everything is great. But another problem is test. Well,
test will return a lot of errors because of this Vue.js compatibility with jest.
Jest is not working with the version installed with the UCLI. That is 27 because they released
in September 2022. Support for that, but just for jest 29. So not a good news.
But we have a workaround for this. We can remove the usage of Vue.cliservice and use jest directly.
It's not so nice to do. We need to copy and paste the default jest.config file from the plugin
in use by Vue.cli plugin in our jest.config file. And then we need to update our package.json test
script using jest instead of Vue.cli service test unit. And everything should work kind of like
before. And then we need to remove cli plugin of jest and install everything the cli plugin was
installing automatically. But at version 29, like we can see over there, fix a couple of
deprecation warnings like this one. Just a minor change and that's it. We are ready to
work with Vue.js 2.7 and test working. Now it's time to move to Vue.js 3.
They released an entire whole website for explaining new features, breaking change,
recommendation and migration build. So tonight before going to bed, I suggest you to take a look
at this and maybe every night before going to bed because it's really interesting. And let's skip
breaking changes because there will be a lot, but it depends on the user usage. And let's have a look
at new recommendations. They're recommending to use new version, of course, of router, dev tools,
test utils, all of them with Vue.js 3 support. They have a new build tool chain. So they are
suggesting to use this instead of ucli. And this is great, but not the moment. And they are also
suggesting to use pina instead of ux. And ux is there to remain. But for now they are suggesting
a new default. So move to pina. And a new support. So instead of using Vetour, for example, for VS
Code, you need to use Volar. So easy migrations. Well, dev tools, just update your Dev Tool in
Chrome browser. The support, same as before, just remove or keep Vetour, but install Volar. And
that's it. Then you, of course, have a lot of mandatory migrations. For example, Vue router,
new version compatible with Vue.js 3, Vuex, test utils, and, of course, third-party libraries.
For example, Vue.T5, Quasar, Element UI. Before starting your task to upgrade the Vue.js from 2 to
3, you need to check all your dependencies and check if they release the version compatible with
Vue.js 3. They should, because, well, one year from now. But it depends on the library.
So you need to check that first. For now, you can avoid to migrate from ucli to Vet and from Jest
to Vetest, even if they are great tool. If you just want to move from Vue.js 2 to Vue.js 3,
for the moment, you can avoid to migrate them. But maybe in the future, you should migrate to
them because they are great tool and they are the new default. And now it's time to talk about the
migration build. So they released a new dependency, VueCompat, that is a build of Vue.js 3 with
configurable Vue 2 compatible behavior. And it runs in Vue.js 2 mode by default. And it will display
a lot of runtime warnings about changed and deprecated features used in your code.
It has known limitations, for example, dependencies that rely on Vue.js 2 internal APIs or
undocumented behavior, for example, Vue.js 5. The same for usage of private properties on V-nodes.
Vue.js 5.0, again, Vue.js 5.0, oh, no, Internet Explorer support dropped. Okay.
And server side rendering. So if you are using server side rendering in production,
well, you should complete the migration before releasing to production because, well,
it won't work anymore with VueCompat. And so let's start our workflow of migration. So at first,
we need to upgrade our Vue CLI using this command here or just CLI Vue upgrade. And if you are using
just custom Webpack setup, you need to upgrade your Vue loader to version 16. After upgrading,
you need to update and install your Vue.js instance and install Vue compatibility mode.
You can drop, for the moment, Vue template compiler. It's useful in test too, but for the
moment, we can remove it. And then we need to create an alias for Vue.js. So every time we import
from Vue stuff, we will import instead of Vue.js from Vue compatibility mode. And again, in our
configuration file, we need to enable, of course, compatibility mode via the Vue compiler options
using the version 2 for now. If you are using TypeScript, you need to upgrade your Vue typing
file using this. Again, this is explaining in their website that you will read tonight.
And now you can run your code using npm run serve, for example. And if you see compile time errors,
you should fix them. And when they are fixed, they should be, for example, configuration issues or
what? Small changes. You can switch your compatibility configuration to use Vue.js 3.
And you can run the app. It should work. You can open your DevTools, look at the console.
And you may see a bunch of errors, a lot of them. And now you need to focus on that errors. And you
need to fix them one by one. What I'm suggesting is that you need to focus on fix your own source
code errors and warnings mainly. Because you will have a lot of errors and warnings from Vuex,
router, and so on. But they are from Vuex and from Vue router, for example. And we will update them
in a moment. So, first of all, update your own code warnings. And then update a couple of things that
won't display warnings. For example, transition. If you are using transition, you need to do a
find and replace. And replace them with this. And then, okay, working. You need to update your
application entry in your main.js file. So, instead of using new Vue, you can use create app. Because
this is the Vue 3 way. And for the moment, we can pass to create app, router, store, and everything
else. But we will remove them in a moment. So, now it's time to upgrade Vuex to version 4. It is the
version compatible with Vue.js 3. And we need to upgrade our Vuex store definition using create
store. And moving from an object in state to a function. This is the main change, I think.
And then we can remove the parameter from create app and use the app.use store instead.
And in all components using the store, we need to change to this. So, again, like before,
instead of using this.store, we need to import the store in this way for Vue.js 3. And use it
in the store constant. Same for Vue router. So, we need to upgrade to Vue router version 4.
We need to upgrade our configuration, importing create router and create web history. Because
it's a new breaking change. And change them in this way. Then, again, we can change our main.js,
removing the router from create app parameter and using app.use router. And change everything in the
components. So, importing user router and or user out and using them in the components. And after
this, you should pick off individual warnings if any remaining. And fix them one by one. For example,
upgrading Vue 5, upgrading element UI, or other dependencies. Just solve them one by one in order
to isolate your problem in a single way. After this, you can remove the migration build and
switch everything to the official user history. Just when all warnings are fixed. And if you have
dependencies that rely on Vue.js 2, you may not be able to do so. So, please check
all of your dependencies before doing this last step. And that's it. Now, it's time to git
commit push and deploy to production. Well, maybe not. Maybe not. You should update your
Vue test setup, too. So, you need to remove Vue 2.js and move to Vue 3.js at version 29,
hopefully. And update also Vue test utils to version 2. Changing it in the Jest configuration.
And everything should work. Apart from a couple of breaking changes in Vue test utils, because
now props data, when you force a prop into component mounting, you will have to change
from props data to props. There won't be create local Vue anymore, because everything is a
isolated instance of Vue. You need to move mocks and stubs inside of global options. And findall
.at finally has been removed. So, now you can use findall like a proper array, finally.
And for all other problems in your test, you should go this website and look at
problems and warnings, for example, and solve them with their great documentation.
And that's it. Now, we can be happy with our Vue 3.js instance. So, as a quick recap,
if you want to stick to Vue 2.6, for example, you can use Vue composition API so you can test and
try with composition API in setup only. If you want to try the new composition API in script setup,
you can upgrade to Vue.js 2.7, waiting for dependency to date their compatibility with
Vue.js 3. But if you need to long-term support your code base, your projects, then now it's the
time to migrate from Vue.js 2 to Vue.js 3 properly. So, here's the link to the feedback
for Fosden, if you want to leave a feedback for this talk. And thank you very much for being here.
Thank you. So, if you have a first question, please raise your hand. Higher than this,
because I can't see it. Don't be shy.
While you think if there is a seat that is empty, we aim for this at the center.
Please don't stay at the sides of the ails. Defrag the rows, please. Questions? Hands up.
If you are our next speaker also, please come to the front now. We're waiting for you.
Hello. That was helpful. I haven't really got an app to upgrade. I did one app in Vue 2. Can you
hear me? Sorry? Can you hear me? Yeah, kind of. I did one app in Vue 2 two years ago, which I've
left. And now I'm trying to learn Vue 3. And that was really helpful. And I'll use your links,
because I'm mentally upgrading, if not upgrading the code yet. So, not really a question. But
one of the problems I've found is finding examples that are only Vue 3. And getting mixed up with
examples from Vue 2. Is there a good place to go? I mean, obviously, Vue.js.org is good. But
like Stack Overflow is full of mixed examples and mess. So, any help? Of course, the official Vue
JS 3 Vue JS website contains a lot of examples of composition API and options API. So, you can
switch, I think, in the homepage, your preference, if you prefer options API or composition API.
And all examples in there will be switched to use that kind of option or composition.
But other places, well, it depends. If you go, for example, to Vue.js website,
they have two versions of the website. So, the old version, it's all about Vue.js 2.
So, just options API examples. And instead, the new version contains examples about
options API, but a smaller section of the website contains also composition API examples.
I don't know why they are not upgrading all of their websites to composition API,
because I think it's great. But maybe it's just because now we are also, again, we are in a passage
between Vue.js 2 and Vue.js 3. So, they prefer to leave options API examples just to involve
everyone from Vue.js 2 to Vue.js 3. But I don't have an explanation of this.