Hello, everyone.
I am Egole Feuver, a PhD student at the University of Manchester.
In this talk, I will present the result of my research on compartment interface vulnerabilities,
a work that will appear in NDSS 23.
This is the result of a collaboration between Manchester, Bucharest, Rice, and Unicraft.io.
Before starting to talk about interface vulnerabilities, let me bring a little bit of necessary background.
And a very important notion in this work is compartmentalization.
Compartmentalization is about decomposing software into lesser privileged components, such that
components only have access to what they need to do their job.
Compartmentalization is not particularly something new, so let me illustrate it with a real-world
example, web servers.
Typically, web servers are composed of components that do, on the one hand, privileged things
like listening to port 80, and on the other hand, of other components that perform risky
operations like parsing network-provided data.
If we have these two components in the same process, then this process has to be root,
and that's problematic, because if an attacker manages to compromise the network-facing component,
for example, then it will immediately own the root process.
So what people do in practice is decomposing or compartmentalizing the server into two
entities in separate processes, the master, which is privileged and not exposed to risky
operations, and the worker, which is deprivileged and exposed to network data.
Both entities then communicate over shared memory.
Thus, if the worker gets compromised, it will not be able to perform privileged operations
and will remain contained.
Recently, we have seen really nice advances in the field of compartmentalization.
People have been taking more fine grain, more arbitrary, and more automatic approaches to
compartmentalization.
And what these work do is taking arbitrary applications, identifying a particular component
that may be untrusted or risky, or trusted and critical, and compartmentalizing it automatically
or semi-automatically.
The granularity of the component can be very variable, ranging from libraries to blocks
of code.
Notice that I'm talking about compartments here and not processes, as the isolation technology
too is very variable.
In short, the goal of these works is quite ambitious.
It's about compartmentalizing legacy software with a low engineering effort and a low performance
cost.
Unfortunately, as we're highlighting in this work, things are not as easy as they might
seem.
And privileged-separated software, cross-component interfaces are the attack surface.
And there, all sorts of things can go wrong security-wise.
Let me give you a few examples.
Let's say we have two compartments, one on the left, malicious, and the other one on
the right, trusted, protecting some secret.
The compartmentalization mechanism guarantees us that compartment one cannot access compartment
two's memory directly, so that doesn't work.
However, compartment one is still able to do legitimate API calls to compartment two
with, for example, an invalid pointer.
If compartment two doesn't validate the pointer, it will risk exploitation.
Another example is the usage of corrupted indexing information, for example, a size,
index, or bounce, as is done in this function.
Another one is the usage of a corrupted object, such as a tempered file pointer.
And there are many others which will go through partially in the next slide.
In this work, we unify all of these vulnerabilities under the concept of compartment interface
vulnerabilities, or SIVs.
SIVs encompass traditional confused deputies, IAGO attacks, which are SIVs specific for
the system called API, and their references under influence, and probably many others.
They are all attacks revolving around misuse of a legitimate interface.
SIVs are very common when compartmentalizing and modified applications, as we further highlight
in this talk.
They affect all compartmentalization framework because they are a fundamental part of the
problem of privilege separation.
To put it in more precise words, we define SIVs as the set of vulnerabilities that arise
due to lack of or improper control in data flow validation at compartment boundaries.
We observe three classes of SIVs, data leakages, data corruption, and temporal violations.
Within data leakages, we differentiate between address leakages, which can be leveraged to
de-randomize compartments and mount further attacks, and compartment confidential data
leakages, which result in information disclosure.
Both are due to data oversharing and sharing of uninitialized memory.
We have already illustrated a range of data corruption attacks in the previous slide,
but generally they are bound to happen in situations where interface crossing data is
used without appropriate sanitization.
They can affect control as well as non-control data.
Finally, temporal violations include vulnerabilities like expectation of API usage ordering, usage
of corrupted synchronization primitives, or shared memory time of check to time of use.
Temporal violations are usually caused by a wide range of behaviors, including missing
copies, double fetches, and generally lack of enforcement of API semantics.
This is a broad and succinct overview, but the paper provides a full taxonomy, including
an analysis of existing defenses.
So having observed and characterized the problem, we asked a few questions.
How many SIVs are there at legacy imported APIs?
Are all APIs similarly affected by SIVs?
For example, taking library API generally versus module APIs generally, do we observe
systematic differences?
How hard are these SIVs to address when compartmentalizing?
And finally, how bad are they?
If for some reason you don't fix one of them or just decide to not fix them at all, what
is the impact on the guarantees that compartmentalization can give to you?
We believe that it is really critical to understand these points to be able to provide countermeasures
that are adequate, systematic, and usable.
And so the approach that we take in this work to answer these questions is to design a tool,
and more particularly a fuzzer, specialized to detect SIVs at arbitrary interfaces, and
we call this tool Confuzz.
Then we apply Confuzz at scale to a range of applications and interfaces to gather a
dataset of real-world SIVs.
Finally, we study, systematize, patternize the resulting dataset to extract numerous
insights on the problem of SIVs in compartmentalization.
In the next slides, I will give a quick overview of Confuzz before focusing on the dataset
and insights.
So let me give you a high-level overview of the fuzzer first.
Taking unmodified applications, we instrument them to intercept cross-compartment calls.
These are freely defined, for example, a particular library boundary or an internal component
interface.
We based our prototype on dynamic binary instrumentation using Intel PIN, but also explored other
instrumentation approaches, for example, LLVM-based.
The interface between the trusted and untrusted components is automatically detected using
binary debug information.
Our fuzzing monitor then drives the exploration by ordering mutations of the dataflow to simulate
attacks from the malicious compartment to the trusted compartment.
The workload used to drive the program is application-specific, for example, benchmark
tools, test suites, custom workloads, etc.
You could even plug another fuzzer like OSS fuzz there.
Finally, the fuzzer automatically triages and stores crash reports.
That includes deduplicating, reproducing, minimizing, etc.
The paper provides much greater details on these technical matters, and I would be happy
to elaborate if you have questions.
Using Confuzz, we gathered a substantial dataset that we carefully dissected.
Here you can see the paper's big table that summarizes the dataset.
Let's have a closer look at it.
Overall, we applied Confuzz to 25 applications and 36 APIs for a total of 39 scenarios.
We considered a selection of library APIs, module APIs, and internal component APIs,
trying to focus on scenarios that make sense in popular software.
In fact, 16 of these scenarios have been previously considered by about 12 studies in the literature,
and the attacks that we find apply to them as well.
In total, we find 629 SIFs.
We classify these SIFs in five impact classes, read impact, write impact, execution, memory
allocator corruption, and null-pointing reference.
With this data, the first questions that we try to answer are how many SIFs are there
at legacy or unmodified arbitrary APIs, and are all APIs or codes similarly affected?
And looking into this, we quickly confirm that SIFs are absolutely widespread among
unmodified APIs or code.
Having said that, we also highlighted significant disparities of prevalence among scenarios,
and that's the really interesting part.
For example, we observed variations of SIF counts from 0 to 105 across APIs.
That's quite significant.
Take a look at this plot, which represents for each scenario, the number of vulnerable
API endpoints versus non-vulnerable.
It clearly shows that SIF prevalence among applications and APIs is very heterogeneous.
We have large and almost totally SIF-free APIs, and small and fully vulnerable APIs.
In fact, we show an entire absence of correlation between API size and SIF count in this dataset.
So while clearly, yes, SIFs are widespread, no, not all APIs are similarly affected.
This motivates us to look into the patterns and effects that influence these observations.
And doing so, we observe recurring API design patterns that result in SIFs.
This really comforts us in the idea that the presence of SIFs is influenced by structural
properties of the API, rather than API size or quantity of shared data.
In this talk, I will present one of these patterns, but there are more in the paper.
And the particular pattern I want to go through concerns modular APIs.
Indeed, we notice that modular or module APIs are the most SIF-vulnerable interfaces in
our study.
On average, we observe that module APIs feature more SIFs and worse SIFs than any other class
of APIs.
And looking at the structure of these interfaces, it makes sense.
Unlike library APIs, module APIs must be very generic and yield high performance.
As a consequence, we have patterns with the application exposing its core internals and
its core state to the module to achieve their generosity and performance.
But this results in a much larger attack surface exposed to the module.
Take the example of this data structure exposed to potential malicious modules by the Apache
HttpD core.
It is very complex with over 75 fields, 60% of which point us, referencing core data structures
like memory pools, connection state structures, or mutexes.
What we observe with this pattern is a somewhat counterintuitive thing.
Security is not always good for compartmentalization, and in many cases, it can even be counterproductive.
This is only one of the patterns that we highlight, and there are more in the paper.
Now having shown that SIFs are widespread but affecting applications unequally or APIs,
let's look at their concrete security impact.
And the first thing that we confirm is that they are quite impactful.
In fact, over 75% of scenarios present in our dataset show at least one right vulnerability.
And worse than that, about 70% of right and read and 50% of executed vulnerabilities
are arbitrary, which means that when the attacker controls a right or read primitive, then they
are likely to be able to read and write anywhere.
And while only a smaller proportion of these scenarios have execution impact, it is likely
that read and write primitives will be combinable to achieve execution capabilities.
In this talk, I will be concretely illustrating this impact with practical scenarios and real-world
SIFs taken from the dataset where we demonstrate key extraction from a protected OpenSSL.
Once again here, we show more details in the paper.
So here we assume a scenario with two compartments where the goal is to isolate OpenSSL.
For example, from a compromised web server engine exon.
Isolating OpenSSL or part of OpenSSL is a popular application of compartmentalization,
both in the literature and in the industry.
Thus here, the compartment interface and therefore the attack surface is the OpenSSL public API.
Unfortunately, we find several SIFs that enable for read, write and execution impact.
Take this option setting primitive, for example, which is part of the OpenSSL public API.
It dereferences an interface crossing pointer, sets it and returns it, clearly resulting
in an arbitrary read and write oracle.
Any attacker that can compromise the application's control flow will likely be able to extract
SSL keys easily.
Thus, clearly if the API is not carefully enough sanitized, the benefits will be pretty
low at most a form of weak hardening.
Now you could tell me that it's not a good idea to protect at the public API anyways
and that we should rather choose the OpenSSL internal key API that's much smaller.
So let's take a look at it.
This time we have engine ex and most of OpenSSL in the untrusted compartment.
While we have the small key handling part of OpenSSL together with the keys in the protected
compartment.
Unfortunately, here too we find several SIFs.
Take a look at this function of the internal key API, for example.
I only put the signature for simplicity's sake because the function is implemented in
per generated assembly.
You can manipulate the in pointer to point to the key that you cannot directly access
encrypt with a known key and then decrypt to get the secret.
Hence, here again, attackers that can manage to compromise the application are likely to
be able to easily extract the key.
Unfortunately here, fixing this SIFs requires to make the components stateful, which is
a fairly drastic design change.
Overall, through these two examples, I showed how existing OpenSSL isolation strategies
collapse when confronted to SIFs and how important they are security wise.
To conclude this talk, let's take a quick look at countermeasures.
How do we tackle SIFs?
Overall, we see two ways.
First, making progress on automatic and systematic countermeasures.
Our paper highlights the limitations as part of our SIF taxonomy.
Second, learning from our study of patterns, we also believe that software component APIs
should be designed to feature low compartmentalization complexity in the first place.
We provide a set of guidelines to achieve this.
The two approaches are complementary.
Even in the presence of countermeasures, well-designed APIs are wishable as the first point is known
to be fundamentally harder.
I will not have enough time to go over all the guidelines, but let me try to give you
the gist of them.
First, not every interface is a good boundary for privilege separation.
Maybe a particular API doesn't fit privilege separation, and that's fine.
In this case, it will be hard to harden anyways.
Second, we recommend that major attention should be dedicated to reducing the complexity
of interface crossing objects, avoiding, for example, sharing of resource handle, system
resource handles, complex tracks, synchronization primitives, etc.
If this is not possible, it should bring us back to the first point.
The interface is probably not the right point to compartmentalize, for example, because
components are too deeply entangled.
Third, compartmentalizable components should enforce API semantics to be safe, for example,
securing or concurrency support.
Under distrust scenarios, it is not acceptable anymore to assume that the caller will respect
them or face the consequences.
We are slowly coming towards the end of this talk, so let me summarize the key points that
I wanted to make.
Civs should be at the center of every compartmentalization approach, and you will likely not achieve
tangible security benefits without considering them.
API design patterns influence the presence of Civs and their severity.
Overall, it's not so much about the size of the API, it's about the complexity of
API crossing objects.
Addressing Civs is not just a matter of writing a few checks.
In fact, strong solutions often require refactoring the API.
Because compartmentalizing apps goes much further than just setting and enforcing bounds.
We want this work to be an appeal for more research towards addressing the problem of
Civs, systematically finding them, addressing them, or telling you what interface make good
compartmentalization boundaries.
If you are interested in this work, I invite you to check out our paper and the code and
data set of confuzz.
I will now be more than happy to take questions.
Thank you.
Okay.
Thank you, Hugo, for this very accessible talk on this important topic of securing interfaces.
One question maybe that I can start with is something that you brought up yourself as
well.
You say it's more about compartmentalization, but it also applies obviously to TEs.
Can you comment a bit on that?
Is that something you consider?
Confuzz, your physics could be extended to something like Gramine?
Actually, so maybe there are two different parts.
I think the conceptual part about compartment interface vulnerabilities, maybe we could
remove the compartment out of compartment interface vulnerabilities and just get interface
vulnerabilities.
I think it has also been described by other works previously, notably some of the work
that you did, Joe.
I think that applies to TEs really, really well.
I think it's just a generic problem about interfaces and that fully applies to TEs.
Regarding the fuzzer, from a very technical point of view, I think that it might need
some adaptation to be run on existing TE software, but it's absolutely feasible.
And yeah, I think that it could apply there as well.
We didn't really explore it because obviously at some point we needed to restrict the scope
of what we're doing, but I think it...
That makes sense.
So following up on that as well, I think you mentioned in your slides, one of the technologies
that you could use for compartmentalization is not only TEs, it's also something like
SHERRI, which uses capabilities, and I'm wondering, TEs are not great in these vulnerabilities
because you have these confused deputy attacks that you explained also where you have a pointer
that you essentially can dereference.
And with SHERRI, with capabilities, you have native mitigations for many of those capabilities,
I think were made with the idea of avoiding confused deputies.
So can you comment a bit on what the underlying technology can mean for the vulnerability
of compartmentalization essentially?
So I'm not sure if I can...
I don't think I can share my screen, but maybe I can.
No, no.
But you can put a link maybe in the...
Yeah.
... for people.
So actually in the paper, we did talk about this, so I'm just gonna...
I don't think I can share my screen, but maybe I can.
Oh, my God, I'm sorry.
I'm sorry, I just broke everything.
I just posted the link.
I don't know if I triggered something terrible, but...
I think I see the link.
I think you unmuted the tab or something.
So the paper goes in in case of that.
Can you summarize maybe in the minute that remains?
Absolutely, yes.
So SHERRI provides some features that, as you said, are really nice in addressing some
of the spatial part of the compartment interface spectrum, of the CF spectrum.
It does not solve everything.
It's not magic.
Many of the leakage issues remain.
Many of the temporal issues remain as well, because to some extent, they are a little
bit more high level than just spatial things on memory.
So they still apply.
For example, the issues with ordering of interface calls.
If you have an interface that has some ordering expectations, for example, calling function
one before function two, and you don't respect that, SHERRI is not necessarily going to help
you.
So this is going to remain.
So it does address part of it, but it's not everything.