Okay, hi. My name is Thomas. I'm an engineer at ARM. I'm also a contributor to the project
Verizon. This presentation is about Verizon and wants to give you an idea of what the
project is about and how it fits in the wider attestation slash confidential computing picture.
I hope that after listening to this, you'll be motivated to at least have a look at the
project and maybe become an early adopter or even a contributor in the future. Who knows?
So without further ado, let me go through what I've put together here, starting with
a bunch of trees via about the project. So we have a logo and the colorful ovals there
are supposed to represent grapes. In fact, Verizon is a term used in winemaking and is
the moment when grapes start frightening, at which point they can be of different colors.
In fact, the word means change of color. And this is sort of visual metaphor of the blurry
nature of trust, which can be yes, can be no green grape, red grape, or really anything
in between. Now there is some debate around the way the word is pronounced. The French
say Verizon or Verizon. The English say Verizon or Verasion. So you have a choice. You have
multiple choices. In fact, please do not spell it like the American technical company because
that would be really confusing. And it's also a acronym for verification of attestation.
And the project started within ARM in the architecture and technology group, which belong
together with my colleagues at the team as well. It's been adopted by the confidential
computing consortium in June 2022. It's currently in incubation stage, meaning it's in the early
phases of adoption. And we're looking at growing it across a few different metrics.
Most obvious being code and documentation maturity, but also we are also trying to grow
the community a bit. And being here is part of that effort. But yeah, the headline here
is that we've moved from being in our project to be under the Linux foundation umbrella.
Therefore we are completely open governance and of course open source. Before we dive
into the core of the presentation, though, let me give you a bunch of pointers, possibly
useful. The code base, GitHub, the chat, the Zulip chat, the mailing list hosted by the
Confidential Computing Consortium, and these confusing URL, which is one for our regular
weekly calls, which I'm not expecting you to memorize. In fact, you could just follow
the first link in the list, the GitHub org and the splash page should have all of these
other links. But, you know, generally feel free to join any of these channels, pop up
at our calls, ask questions, whatever. You will be always very much welcome.
So now we do a quick recap on remote attestation, starting with the problem. So you suppose
you have these two guys, a testor and a relying party that needs to engage in some sort of
distributed computation. Suppose also that initially they don't trust each other, they
are mutually distrusting. And then you can't make progress in the computation until a trust
relationship can be established between the two. And instances of this kind of situation
abound, for example, in Confidential Computing, the tester is typically the guy that executes
the workload, the Confidential workload, and the relying party needs to know that this
guy is trusted before he shares some input with it. Say, for example, you need to ship
an ML model or some privacy sensitive data or both. And there's obviously the dual problem
where the relying party is the consumer of the output of the computation. Say you are
an actuator of some sort that acts upon signals that are coming from the tester and you want
to trust the tester before making a mess. So you stuff in critical infrastructure especially.
So to break this impasse, the natural thing to do is for one party to convince the other
that they can be trust. And here's where attestation comes in the frame. So what is attestation?
It's a technique that uses specialized components, which is rooted in hardware called the root
of trust that the attestation can use to do basically two things. The sampling the current
state of its TCP, of its trusted computing base, and put together a report and be signed
this report with secret identity keys that are securely stashed inside the root of trust
in hardware. All of that in a trustworthy way. Now that is in such a way that no one
even co-located software or firmware can subvert these sequence of actions. And this signed
report is called attestation evidence or evidence. And the evidence, which is basically a very,
very strong authentication signal can be sent to the RP, which once it receives it, needs
to verify by checking that the signature of the report is correct and that the identity
of the signer is known and trusted. And also to check that the reported TCP state is acceptable
slash good for some local policy defined interpretation of what good means. And the process of verification
of evidence is the process that covers at least these two checks that we just discussed.
And in the remote attestation architecture, which is RFC 9334, freshly published, this
process of verification of evidence is taken care of by the verifier role, which basically
mediates between attesters and relying parties. Note that the lines in this picture are not
real channels between real devices. They are logical channels between architectural roles.
So they can be recomposed and put together in a very different way, depending on the
protocol. Logically, these are the relationships between the various architectural roles.
And in order to do to its function, the verifier needs to know a few things, a few very important
things. First, how to verify the identity of A of the attester. Typically, that is done
by knowing a public key associated with the secret signing key of the attester and knowing
that in a reliable way. And B, what is the expected state of the attester's DCB, of course.
And this can become pretty messy, depending on how complex the attester is. On one hand
of the spectrum, you have very simple attesters that can be described with a single measurement,
but it does not change or changes glacially. And on the other hand, there are composite
detectors that are made of more than one attester, each attester sporting its own DCB, each DCB
made of multiple separate independently moving parts, software components, configuration,
whatnot. With multiple different supply chain actors involved, things can become really
hairy. So if the complexity is very low, it makes sense to co-locate a simple verifier
with the line party. But if that's not the case, it might be a reasonable choice to design
a system where the verification function is effectively offloaded to a separate architectural
component. These options are not, aggregation, desegregation, they are not mutually exclusive.
For example, the case where the tester is composite and its evidence can be clearly
split along a platform slash workload access. So in that case, one might want to call an
external platform verifier. And if everything is okay, then move to a local verifier for
the verification of the workload. As I said, the things are logical, they can be reassembled
and put together in very, very different way. But in general, whatever the system architecture
you come up with, the verifier role needs a bunch of trusted links to the supply chain
that is involved in the verification. Because the supply chain endorses the attester, right?
And so it's critical that the link between the supply chain and the verifier is a trusted
one and that endorsements are genuine. And these are the green boxes in this picture.
But if I could also have an owner, I typically have an owner, that can provide the verification
policies for evidence to it, save for, to customize the process of appraisal or in special
situations to maybe provide out batching. And to complete the rats architectural picture
is the RP owner, or link RP owner that can feed the policy for how to act on the attestation
results coming from the verifier, right? To extract the right party to make decisions
based on the appraisal done by the verifier regarding the attester. So this finishes the
rat three cup. And the question now is, is where is the reason this picture? And as you
may have guessed, is the blue box at the center. But it's not just that it's also all the lines
that are attached to the blue box. That is all the verifier interfaces, which are quite
a few. So from the bottom left and then move. But why? So evidence, we built a bunch of
libraries for manipulating various evidence formats, both from point of view of the verifier,
so the coding and verification, but also from the attester point of view, which means encoding
and signing. This way, if one needs to put together an end to end flow, say for integration
testing or for the demo, it's quite easy to build this, you know, test emulator. You don't
need to deal with the real horror, which can be tricky, especially if you're dealing with
CI environments. The current list of supported evidence includes two EAT profiles, PSA for
Cortex-M, so IoT, Gizmo, and NCCA for the new ARM V9 confidential computing architecture.
We also have a TPM profile, and this came from an integration project we did with our
friends at Enact Trust, who have a product for monitoring device health that can use
Verizon as a back end. We have a bare bones implementation of DICE, TCG, but Open is okay,
I think. And then we have AWS Nitro, contributed by our friends at Veracruz. Veracruz is another
triplacy project that's, so a confidential computing project that uses Verizon as the
back end for their proxy CA. On the endorsement, ref value front, we have implementation for
Quorum, which is a format we co-designed with Intel and from HOFA in the DICE working group
in TCG, and has now been adopted in the ATF rats working group as a, you know, on the
standards track. It's basically a specialized format for describing the, how the attester
looks like to the verifier, which aggregates different sub formats for specifying a bunch
of orthogonal but cool existing dimensions of the platform, so software firmware, trust
anchors, other things. For policy, we have integrated open policy agent, which is an
existing successful general purpose policy engine. So we found something that existed
that was fit for purpose, so we didn't feel the need for invent this specific bit. And
for attestation results, there's an info model that's being standardized in the ATF
which allows to normalize the appraisal output so that the line party policies can be simplified
greatly because now they're fully decoupled from the specifics of the attester. But because
our force is just an info model, we had to create a serialization for it, which we based
on it, we call EER. EER is a good candidate for standardization because there's, you know,
there's nothing at this point in time. And so we're trying to push this through the
rats working group in the ATF as well. And it's the only output form of support for now.
As far as decision result policies, we do nothing because this is completely out of
scope. This is entirely on the underlying party. So yeah, now I wanted to give you the
map of what we just discussed with what exists in the Verizon campaign. And note that nearly
the entirety of what follows is Golang packages and also command line tools and services slash
demons in good old Unix patterns. And this was a conscious choice. We choose to go with
Golang because, you know, one of the main goals of the project is to provide a bunch
of component fleet to assemble system that provide verification as a service. Right.
So and Golang is a very good language in terms of library support, native library support,
system and also the in terms of business, you know, the learning curve is very, is very
non-steep, I would say. So it's trivial to learn and therefore, you know, we hope that
more people can be more contributors could be, could come by lowering the barrier here.
So let's start with a couple of layers zero packages. It is the entity decision token.
It's the main format for attestation messages, either evidence or attestation results that
have been put forward by the ATF. It's basically a framework that extends caught and jot by
adding a number of claims with attestation specific semantics and also a way to instantiate
the framework through so-called profiles and PSA and CCA being just two such examples.
The eat package is the reason the package is not tracking the most recent version of
the draft. We decided to wait for the draft to become out of sea before doing a final
alignment pass because it has all the claims that we need, you know, for independent packages
and so for the moment is as good as it is. But we will need to make it up to date, you
know, as soon as the document goes through the standardization process, final stages
of the standardization process. And it builds on COT, which in turn uses COSY sign and sign
one. So early on we realized that we needed a COSY implementation in Go and the only thing
could find at the point in time was COSY, which was originally developed by Mozilla
for their autograph service. But it supported only COSY sign. So we forked it and extended
to support sign one. But then Mozilla discontinued it. At the point in time we wanted to contribute
it back to the main line. They discontinued the project. So we took responsibility of
it alongside Microsoft. And together with Microsoft we did a fair amount of work, including
improving the ergonomics of the interfaces, you know, and also making implementation generally
more robust. And to that respect, we went through a couple of external security reviews
and addressed all their comments. So we're fairly confident in that this package has,
you know, production quality. And we shipped one zero zero just a couple of weeks ago. And
this is the first ever released bit of a reason. So we're particularly excited by that. It's
an interesting package among the lot also because it's used not just by Verizon, but
also by other quite big projects. Notary in CNCF and SIGStore open as a self. So it's
a nice, it's come out as a nice, useful building block that has relevance in the community.
Now moving on to the evidence, you know, these are the evidence base, the red, the orange
things. We have the two profiles for CNCA and PSA, the dice thingy and the sort of house
like shape is the command line interface called AVCLI, which is an attester emulator that
also talks of Verizon verification API client side. And so can be used to play with the
services quite easily on a command line. The yellow things are the attestation results
packages. So here is only one package, basically, it's Verizon here. And there's an associated
CLI arc that can be used to verify and pretty print results. So one can pipe EVCLI output
into arc to see what's what happened during appraisal. And the green thing is the bunch
of endorsement, rev file related packages, including the top level manifest format coding
core M and the dependent bits for for verification keys and software and so on. So, coding commit
coding quads and suite respectively. And also COCI, which is a common line interface for
assembling core M's from from a bunch of JSON templates. You assign them and then you can
submit them to the Verizon services using the provisioning API, which is linked into
cochlea. And finally, the blue box, including microservices, which I will talk about in
the next slide, and the client side interface of the Verizon API, which exists also in Rust
with C bindings. And I think a pure C implementation has been contributed as well. I don't know
if it's been merged fully or is still an open PR, but anyway. So yeah, well, let's have
a look, a quick look at the service architecture. Basically, there are two pipelines, one for
verification, the bottom one, and one for provision, they did the top one that converge
on to the core services service, VITIS, which connects to the data and the plugin stores.
It's called VITIS. VITIS is another wine making point. And it's basically Verizon's services
transfer computing base. It has a whole the security related computation in it. The interesting
thing is that the processing in both pipelines is in stages and with very precise hook points
where plugin code can be supplied by the user in order to customize certain aspects of the
processing. So basically, what you do is as a user that wants to add their own format,
either of evidence or for endorsements and ref values, you build your plugin code so
that you basically you adapt your formats to the standardized processing pipeline. Right.
So next steps. We have a few exciting new things in the pipeline. Adding new formats,
of course, opportunistically, though, depending on contributions, integrations, etc. We want
to improve documentation, not a very exciting bit, but a necessary step in making the project
useful and usable. And this is a big one. We want to work on the identity and access
management to support the, you know, the more the more generic multi-tenant service. And
this is the single missing bit that prevents the reason from being used in a production
context at this point in time. And finally, we want to allow a static plugin-less build
in order to reduce the potential attack surface on the surfaces. Yeah. This is what the next
months will bring us. So questions. Thank you very much, by the way, for listening.
Thank you.